<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02866682</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>14-001423</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02866682</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Prospective Study Comparing Brand and Generic Immunosuppression on Transplant Outcomes, Adherence, &amp; Immune Response in Kidney Transplant Recipients</brief_title>
  <official_title>Prospective Study Comparing Brand and Generic Immunosuppression on Transplant Outcomes, Adherence, &amp; Immune Response</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of California, Los Angeles</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Food and Drug Administration (FDA)</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of California, Los Angeles</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      As the patents for brand-name immunosuppressive medications expire, there is increasing
      interest in using generic immunosuppressive drugs. However, despite pharmacokinetic studies
      showing bioequivalence, questions remain regarding the clinical impact of use of generic
      immunosuppression.

      The most important immunosuppressive agent in the modern transplant era is arguably
      tacrolimus, a calcineurin-inhibitor with a narrow therapeutic index. This study seeks to
      answer the question regarding the clinical impact of generic tacrolimus use as measured
      primarily by acute rejection, loss of graft function, and patient death through a randomized
      trial of 2 phases: Brand tacrolimus only, and Generic A tacrolimus only. Given that kidney
      transplantations are the most commonly performed transplants with well-defined measures of
      rejection and graft failure, this organs will be studied in a six-center study designed to
      accrue the target number of transplant recipients within the one-year study period.

      The study has now been branched off into 2 phases. Phase 1: consists of randomization of
      patients onto brand and generic tacrolimus. This was completed once 40 brand patients were
      enrolled. Phase 2: consists of patients being enrolled only on generic tacrolimus (standard
      of care from subject's insurance). This will be completed once there is a total of 160
      generic participants. 200 participants total in the study.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      A prospective, randomized, open-label, multicenter, parallel, observational study to assess
      safety and efficacy of 200 kidney transplant recipients comparing brand tacrolimus to generic
      tacrolimus over a one year follow up period. All subjects will receive other
      immunosuppressive medications including induction therapy (thymoglobulin, basiliximab, or no
      induction) and maintenance including mycophenolate mofetil and corticosteroid therapy as
      directed by standard-of-care at each center. Their medication information will be recorded in
      their study files.

      The study population includes recipients of kidney allografts in the first 14 days after
      transplantation.

      The totals of 7 visits over 12 months period are planned as follows. The blood samples
      specified below are for the translational research study labs. Subjects will continue to
      receive routine labs as part of their standard of care from their treating physician. These
      safety labs are done as part of their stand of care from their treating physician.

      If the subject needs more study drug medication before his or her next study visit the
      subject will come in to the clinic to get a new supply.

      First (Baseline) Visit (up to 14 days after transplant but before you are discharged from the
      hospital):

        -  Review and sign this consent form

        -  Review of your medical history

        -  Review of your current medications

        -  Review of your physical exam including vital signs (blood pressure, temperature, pulse
           and respiration rate), height and weight

        -  Review of clinical labs

        -  You will receive your study drug if you are in Part 1 of the study.

      If you are a woman of child bearing potential, a pregnancy test will be completed prior to
      the start of the study. If you are pregnant, you cannot participate in this research study.
      You also cannot participate in this study if you are currently breastfeeding. You must use a
      medically acceptable method of birth control during the 1-year study period and for 6 weeks
      after the last dose of study medication.

      It is possible that after the study doctor reviews your medical history and test results, he
      or she may tell you that you do not qualify to be in the study. If you do not qualify for the
      study, the doctor will tell you the reason(s) why. If you cannot be in this research study,
      you will not lose any medical benefits, you can still participate in other studies, and you
      can still receive the standard treatment prescribed by your physician.

      After the Baseline Visit, you will have 6 additional study visits. These will be scheduled
      for 1, 2, 3, 6, 9, and 12 months after your transplant surgery. The following will occur at
      each visit:

      Month 1, 2, 3, 6, and 9 Visits:

        -  Review of your current medications

        -  Review of your physical exam including vital signs (blood pressure, temperature, pulse
           and respiration rate), height and weight

        -  Review of any changes in your health and any reactions to the study medication will be
           recorded

        -  Review of your routine standard of care lab results

        -  Return completed dosing diary and receive new dosing diary

        -  You will receive your study drug if you are in Part 1 of the study

      Month 12 Visit (End of Study Visit):

        -  Review of your current medications

        -  Review of any changes in your health and any reactions to the study medication will be
           recorded

        -  Review of your routine standard of care lab result

        -  Return your final completed dosing diary

        -  Return any study drug remaining in your possession to the study team if you are in Part
           1 of the study

      If you are Part 1 and require more study medication before your next study visit, you will
      come in to the clinic to get a new supply. If you are participating in Part 2, you will
      obtain more study drug from your local pharmacy.

      You will continue having your routine blood and urine collections to monitor your kidney
      function as part of your standard of care treatment at UCLA, UCSD, UCI, and UCD. The schedule
      for these routine blood and urine collections will depend on your condition and will be at
      your treating physician's discretion.

      Adherence will be measured with daily medication diaries and with the coefficient of
      variation of tacrolimus in subjects' blood.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 1, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to first occurrence of acute rejection, failure, death</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year post-transplant</time_frame>
    <description>The definition of graft failure includes re-transplant and/or death and in case of kidney transplant also includes return to dialysis. The definition of acute rejection in kidney transplant will be based on Banff 2007 classification, in heart transplant will be based on revised 2004 ISHLT grading and in liver transplant will be based on Banff schema for grading liver allograft rejection.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Graft Rejection at 1 year</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year post-transplant</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Graft Failure at 1 year</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year post-transplant</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of Infectious Episodes at 1 year</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year post-transplant</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of Malignancy at 1 year</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year post-transplant</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Death or loss-to-follow-up at 1 year</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year post-transplant</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in lymphocyte subpopulations and production of donor specific HLA antibodies</measure>
    <time_frame>post-transplant</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adherence with medication regimen</measure>
    <time_frame>post-transplant</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of Life with Medication Regimen</measure>
    <time_frame>post-transplant</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Satisfaction with Medication Regimen</measure>
    <time_frame>post-transplant</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">200</enrollment>
  <condition>Renal Transplant Rejection</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Brand Tacrolimus Only : Prograf</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Arm 1 will receive brand tacrolimus for the entire study</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Generic A Only</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Arm 2 will receive specific generic tacrolimus for the entire study</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Prograf</intervention_name>
    <description>Brand Drug for the duration of the study.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Brand Tacrolimus Only : Prograf</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Tacrolimus</intervention_name>
    <description>Generic</description>
    <arm_group_label>Generic A Only</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria

          1. Signed informed consent and or/assent

          2. Between the ages of 18 and 70 years, inclusive

          3. Current or future kidney transplant recipients, no more than 14 days after transplant
             and prior to hospital discharge. Inclusion of future kidney transplant recipients
             cannot exceed 30-days pre-transplant.

          4. Able to swallow tablets and capsules at the time of randomization

          5. Subjects must be receiving a primary or secondary kidney allograft from a deceased
             donor or from a non- HLA identical living donor

          6. Negative cross match test, and compatible (A, B, AB or O) blood type

          7. Subjects must have no known contraindications to tacrolimus

          8. Women of childbearing potential (WOCBP) must have a negative pregnancy test and be
             willing to use 2 methods of contraception during the study and for 6 weeks after
             stopping the study drug.

        WOCBP includes any female who has experienced menarche and who has not undergone successful
        surgical sterilization (hysterectomy, bilateral tubal ligation, or bilateral oophorectomy)
        or is not postmenopausal (defined as amenorrhea ≥ 12 consecutive months; or women on
        hormone replacement therapy with documented serum follicle stimulating hormone level &gt; 35
        mIU/cc). Women who are using oral, implanted, or injectable contraceptive hormones
        (intrauterine device), mechanical products or barrier methods (diaphragm, condoms,
        spermicides), are practicing abstinence, or have a sterile partner (e.g., vasectomy), will
        be considered of child bearing potential.

        In addition, WOCBP who are taking MMF must use methods of birth control as stipulated in
        the package insert, namely:

        Either intrauterine device, or partner with vasectomy, or one hormone (oral contraceptive
        pill, transdermal patch, vaginal ring, or progesterone injection or implant) and one
        barrier method (diaphragm or cervical cap with spermicide, contraceptive sponge, or male or
        female condom), or two barrier methods as described above.

        WOCBP must have a negative serum pregnancy test (minimum sensitivity 25 IU/L or equivalent
        units of human chorionic gonadotropin [HCG]) at the time of transplant.

        Exclusion Criteria

          1. Those who receive simultaneous combined organ transplants

          2. Subjects with clinically significant active infections (for example, those requiring
             hospitalization, or as judged by the Investigator) or malignancies

          3. Recipients who are concurrently receiving belatacept or anticipate to receive
             belatacept as part of their immunosuppressive regimen

          4. Subjects currently enrolled in another investigational device or drug study

          5. WOCBP who are unwilling or unable to use an acceptable method to avoid pregnancy for
             the entire study period and for 6 weeks after stopping the study drug

          6. Women who are breast-feeding or pregnant with a positive pregnancy test on enrollment
             or prior to study drug administration

          7. Prisoners or subjects who are compulsorily detained (involuntarily incarcerated) for
             treatment of either a psychiatric or physical (e.g., infectious disease) illness must
             not be enrolled into this study.

          8. Any psychiatric or medical condition that, in the investigator's opinion, may put the
             subject at significant risk, may confound the study results, or may interfere
             significantly with the subject's participation in the study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Suphamai Bunnapradist, M.D.,M.S.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of California, Los Angeles</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Janette Gadzhyan, M.B.A</last_name>
    <phone>310-794-8516</phone>
    <email>jgadzhyan@mednet.ucla.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UCLA Kidney Transplant Research</name>
      <address>
        <city>Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90024</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Janette Gadzhyan, M.B.A</last_name>
      <phone>310-794-8516</phone>
      <email>jgadzhyan@mednet.ucla.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Suphamai Bunnapradist, M.D., M.S.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Joanna Schaenman, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Phuong-Thu Pham, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Lum Erik, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Nakul Datta, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Basmah Abdalla, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Gabriel Danovitch, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Marcelo Sampaio, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 26, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 10, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 15, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 10, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 10, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">December 13, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of California, Los Angeles</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Suphamai Bunnapradist</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor of Medicine, Director of Research</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Tacrolimus</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

