<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02868216</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>UP4985.14</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02868216</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Management of Anger in Patients With Acute Myocardial Infarction (MAPAMI)</brief_title>
  <acronym>MAPAMI</acronym>
  <official_title>Management of Anger in Patients With ST Segment Elevation Acute Myocadial Infarction: A Randomized Clinical Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Instituto de Cardiologia do Rio Grande do Sul</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Instituto de Cardiologia do Rio Grande do Sul</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Stress, anger and depressed can operate as a trigger to an Acute Coronary Syndrome. It is
      often found in the literature that patients refer excessive anger, anxiety, sadness, pain or
      acute stress before the acute myocardial infarction (AMI). Moreover, a recent meta-analysis
      reported a strong association between the occurrence of AMI and many of these acute emotions.

      Anger is a common manifestation of psychological stress and could trigger off an atherogenic
      process through several mechanisms.

      Coronary atherosclerosis features narrowing of coronary arteries on account of endothelial
      thickening caused by the build up of atheromatous plaques. It is a process characterized by
      inflammatory and fibroproliferative response of the artery wall, caused by continuous
      aggression to its surface and whose thickening, evoked by the evolution of fat streaks
      atherosclerotic lesions, until fiber plaques is quite slow. Endothelial dysfunction also
      results in the loss of natural anti-thrombotic properties involved in the endothelium
      patency.

      According to a study performed by our group, anger management was significantly lower among
      patients with CAD when compared to those without CAD, and the occurrence of major
      cardiovascular events (MACE) was significantly higher in patients presented with lower anger
      control. Both associations were independent from traditional risk factors, occurrence of
      previous events or another anger aspects. Thus, this study was designed in order to evaluate
      the effect of the &quot;cognitive training to anger management &quot; on endothelium-dependent
      vasodilation of the arm artery in patients with acute myocardial infarction with ST segment
      elevation submitted to primary coronary intervention.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      ANGER EVALUATION:

      Anger will be assessed by the Spielberger State-Trait Anger Expression Inventory (STAXI).
      This instrument was developed to evaluate the expression of anger components and their role
      in a variety of medical conditions. These are statements to be assessed on a Likert scale of
      4 points. Individuals are asked about the intensity of his anger, and how often experience
      this emotion.

      The anger trait measures individual differences in willingness to experience anger. It is
      evaluated through 10 questions, with their scores between 10 and 40 points. It is divided in
      temperament and anger reaction. Anger expression provides a general index on the frequency
      with which anger is experienced, expressed, suppressed or controlled and is evaluated with
      three subscales: anger inside, when angry feelings are repressed or stored; anger-out, when
      the individual expresses anger toward other persons or objects in the environment; and anger
      management (control) which measures the frequency with which each individual tries to control
      the expression of raiva. Each of these subscales is assessed by eight questions, ranging from
      32 to 64 points. The total score for the expression of anger is evaluated by the results:
      Total + in total off - control +16.

      Randomization All patients were evaluated during hospitalization for AMI, but only those
      anger control score were less than 27 points were invited to participate. A randomization
      list was obtained by random.org site and were generated sequential envelopes, sealed and
      numbered which were opened in order day in assessment of endothelial function.

      Endothelial function Endothelial dysfunction is an early dysfunctional vascular responses
      observed in tissue prone to develop atherosclerosis and is also associated with vessel with
      atherosclerosis in later stages. The evaluation of endothelial function will be performed by
      researchers &quot;blinded&quot; as to treatment group. The endothelium-dependent vasodilation of the
      brachial artery will be evaluated by ultrasound with a linear transducer 3-12 MHz (EnVisor
      CHD, Philips, Bothell, WA, USA), being held automated measurements of vessel diameter to own
      the equipment used software. The evaluations will be conducted in the mornings after fasting
      for 12 hours under controlled temperature (22 ° C). After ten minutes of images of the
      brachial artery rest will be recorded with the linear transducer placed above the antecubital
      fossa continuously for one minute (basal). The sphygmomanometer is placed on the arm and
      inflated up to 50 mmHg limit above systolic blood pressure for five minutes, and the change
      in diameter of the brachial artery after 60 seconds of cuff deflation will be compared with
      the basal diameter. The images of the vessel diameter at end-diastole (identified by R wave
      of the ECG) will be digitized and recorded at intervals of 3 seconds throughout the
      procedure, and subsequently analyzed off-line using software itself equipamento41.

      ANGER TREATMENT:

      session 1 -Participants are asked what usually makes them angry. The &quot;triggers&quot; of anger are
      identified; the relationship between rabies and cardiovascular physiology is explained.
      According to Lipp and Malagris19 (p.115), &quot;anger changes the way the body works, changes
      breathing, pressure increases, etc. When a person feels anger, the physical reaction that
      occurs is automatic and unplanned, it is difficult control, but the identification of
      triggers before the emotion sets in, will help to prevent it. Identifying and understanding
      anger in three dimensions: cognitive, emotional, and behavioral Think before acting Behavior
      is the final step, which you do not need be damaging.

      Session 2 - Participants are reminded of &quot;elicitor rabies events&quot;. Investigate the situations
      that felt anger during the month and what they thought. To point out how the cognitions, that
      is, how one interprets the facts of life leads to different emotions. How anger behavior is
      directly linked to the interpretations people give to events; It is important to improve the
      way you evaluate events and the world around you. Closing: Deep Breathing Exercise Technical
      Time-Out: isolate yourself from the situation that generates anger to take control.

      The control group patients will not receive any anger managementtraining.

      STATISTICAL ANALYSIS

      The minimum sample size was calculated in 88 patients to detect a 1% difference in
      flow-mediated dilation between the two study groups, with an average standard deviation of
      1.67%, p &lt;0.05 and statistical power of 90 %. The data are presented as means and confidence
      intervals (95% CIs), unless otherwise specified. All analyzes will be based on the principle
      of intention to treat, and will be conducted by researchers who do and whether or not the
      cognitive training for control of anger. Repeated measures of analysis of variance will be
      performed to determine differences in flow-mediated dilation (primary endpoint) and all
      secondary outcomes between the two groups over time, using a conservative F test for the
      interaction between time and study group ( SPSS software, version 18).

      The Geisser correction for the F test is used to adjust the degrees of freedom for the
      roundness deviation (one of the conditions of the repeated measures analysis of variance
      [ANOVA]). logarithmic transformation of the data will be undertaken as appropriate. Fisher's
      post hoc analysis for unpaired and paired data will be performed and interpreted using the
      Bonferroni-Holm adjustment for multiple comparisons.

      The post correlation hoc analysis (by the Spearman rank-correlation method) will be performed
      to evaluate the relationship between the change in flow-mediated dilation of the baseline to
      3 months and the changes in the anger control scores assessed by STAXI from the beginning up
      to 3 months. Differences between categorical variables are calculated using the chi-square
      test. A value of P-tailed &lt;0.05 is considered to indicate statistical significance.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 15, 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">July 15, 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 1, 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>One group receives training for anger management, with guidance on infarction and physiology of anger and another group, does not receive.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>Blinding occurs only in relation to the evaluator of endothelial function</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference in Flow-mediated Dilation in the Brachial Artery in the Base and After the Treatment.</measure>
    <time_frame>three months after the first evaluation</time_frame>
    <description>Inter group difference in flow-mediated dilation in the brachial artery in the baseline and after the treatment (about Three months after the first).
Vasodilatation of the endothelium-dependent brachial artery was evaluated by ultrasound using a 3-12 MHz linear transducer. Three images of the basal diameter (BD) of the brachial artery at the end of the diastole were acquired, as well as the mean velocity of the baseline arterial flow, with the linear transducer positioned 5 cm above the antecubital fossa. Subsequently, the sphygmomanometer was placed in the arm and inflated 50 mmHg above baseline systolic blood pressure for five minutes. After that, 3 images of the arterial diameter were acquired up to 80 seconds of the deflation of the cuff (post-occlusion diameter- PD), as well as the average of the arterial flow velocity. Flow-dependent vasodilation responses were expressed as a percentage variation from the baseline brachial diameter (PD-BD/ BD x 100).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">90</enrollment>
  <condition>Myocardial Infarction</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>anger management training</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>treatment group- Two monthly sessions will address the events triggering anger, the physiology of anger and the influence on the cardiovascular system, the dimesions of anger: cognitive, emotional and behavioral.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Without management training</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>No anger management training</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>anger management training</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>anger management training</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        acute st elevation myocardial infarction

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  dementia, cognitive dysfunction,

          -  bypass surgery previous or during the study periods living from more 200 Km from
             hospital
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Marcia Moura Schmidt, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Instituto de Cardiologia do Rio Grande do Sul</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <verification_date>September 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 11, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 11, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 16, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <results_first_submitted>October 25, 2018</results_first_submitted>
  <results_first_submitted_qc>November 4, 2019</results_first_submitted_qc>
  <results_first_posted type="Actual">November 5, 2019</results_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 4, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 4, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 5, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Myocardial Infarction</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Infarction</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>

  <clinical_results>

    <participant_flow>
      <recruitment_details>dates of the recruitment: 09/15/2015 to 07/15/2017 patients with AMY in this period: 707</recruitment_details>
      <pre_assignment_details>Patients submitted to myocardial revascularization surgery, with acute or chronic infections, need for mechanical ventilation or other complications were excluded; those with delirium, cognitive or mental difficulties, aged ≥ 80 years; and also, unable to comply with follow-up visits or who refused to participate.</pre_assignment_details>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="P1">
          <title>Anger Management Training</title>
          <description>treatment group- Two monthly sessions will address the events triggering anger, the physiology of anger and the influence on the cardiovascular system, the dimesions of anger: cognitive, emotional and behavioral.
anger management training</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="P2">
          <title>Without Management Training</title>
          <description>No anger management training</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <period_list>
        <period>
          <title>Overall Study</title>
          <milestone_list>
            <milestone>
              <title>STARTED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="43"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="47"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>COMPLETED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="35"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="41"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>NOT COMPLETED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="8"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="6"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
          </milestone_list>
          <drop_withdraw_reason_list>
            <drop_withdraw_reason>
              <title>Death</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="1"/>
              </participants_list>
            </drop_withdraw_reason>
            <drop_withdraw_reason>
              <title>coronary artery bypass</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="1"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="0"/>
              </participants_list>
            </drop_withdraw_reason>
            <drop_withdraw_reason>
              <title>Withdrawal by Subject</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="7"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="5"/>
              </participants_list>
            </drop_withdraw_reason>
          </drop_withdraw_reason_list>
        </period>
      </period_list>
    </participant_flow>

    <baseline>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="B1">
          <title>Anger Management Training</title>
          <description>treatment group- Two monthly sessions will address the events triggering anger, the physiology of anger and the influence on the cardiovascular system, the dimesions of anger: cognitive, emotional and behavioral.
anger management training</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="B2">
          <title>Without Management Training</title>
          <description>No anger management training</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="B3">
          <title>Total</title>
          <description>Total of all reporting groups</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <analyzed_list>
        <analyzed>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <scope>Overall</scope>
          <count_list>
            <count group_id="B1" value="35"/>
            <count group_id="B2" value="41"/>
            <count group_id="B3" value="76"/>
          </count_list>
        </analyzed>
      </analyzed_list>
      <measure_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Age</title>
          <units>years</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>Standard Deviation</dispersion>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="56" spread="9"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="58" spread="10"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="57" spread="10"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Sex: Female, Male</title>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <param>Count of Participants</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <title>Female</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="8"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="9"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="17"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Male</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="27"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="32"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="59"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Race/Ethnicity, Customized</title>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <param>Count of Participants</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>Race</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <title>Caucasian</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="29"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="36"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="65"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Afro-descendant</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="6"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="5"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="11"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Region of Enrollment</title>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <param>Count of Participants</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>Brazil</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="35"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="41"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="76"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </measure_list>
    </baseline>

    <outcome_list>
      <outcome>
        <type>Primary</type>
        <title>Difference in Flow-mediated Dilation in the Brachial Artery in the Base and After the Treatment.</title>
        <description>Inter group difference in flow-mediated dilation in the brachial artery in the baseline and after the treatment (about Three months after the first).
Vasodilatation of the endothelium-dependent brachial artery was evaluated by ultrasound using a 3-12 MHz linear transducer. Three images of the basal diameter (BD) of the brachial artery at the end of the diastole were acquired, as well as the mean velocity of the baseline arterial flow, with the linear transducer positioned 5 cm above the antecubital fossa. Subsequently, the sphygmomanometer was placed in the arm and inflated 50 mmHg above baseline systolic blood pressure for five minutes. After that, 3 images of the arterial diameter were acquired up to 80 seconds of the deflation of the cuff (post-occlusion diameter- PD), as well as the average of the arterial flow velocity. Flow-dependent vasodilation responses were expressed as a percentage variation from the baseline brachial diameter (PD-BD/ BD x 100).</description>
        <time_frame>three months after the first evaluation</time_frame>
        <population>means and standard deviations after treatment</population>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Anger Management Training</title>
            <description>treatment group- Two monthly sessions will address the events triggering anger, the physiology of anger and the influence on the cardiovascular system, the dimesions of anger: cognitive, emotional and behavioral.
anger management training</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>Without Management Training</title>
            <description>No anger management training</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Difference in Flow-mediated Dilation in the Brachial Artery in the Base and After the Treatment.</title>
          <description>Inter group difference in flow-mediated dilation in the brachial artery in the baseline and after the treatment (about Three months after the first).
Vasodilatation of the endothelium-dependent brachial artery was evaluated by ultrasound using a 3-12 MHz linear transducer. Three images of the basal diameter (BD) of the brachial artery at the end of the diastole were acquired, as well as the mean velocity of the baseline arterial flow, with the linear transducer positioned 5 cm above the antecubital fossa. Subsequently, the sphygmomanometer was placed in the arm and inflated 50 mmHg above baseline systolic blood pressure for five minutes. After that, 3 images of the arterial diameter were acquired up to 80 seconds of the deflation of the cuff (post-occlusion diameter- PD), as well as the average of the arterial flow velocity. Flow-dependent vasodilation responses were expressed as a percentage variation from the baseline brachial diameter (PD-BD/ BD x 100).</description>
          <population>means and standard deviations after treatment</population>
          <units>percent change dilatation</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>Standard Deviation</dispersion>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="35"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="41"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="11.24" spread="5.10"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="7.70" spread="4.40"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <analysis_list>
          <analysis>
            <group_id_list>
              <group_id>O1</group_id>
              <group_id>O2</group_id>
            </group_id_list>
            <non_inferiority_type>Other</non_inferiority_type>
            <p_value>0.05</p_value>
            <method>ANOVA</method>
            <param_type>Mean Difference (Final Values)</param_type>
            <param_value>2.30</param_value>
            <dispersion_type>Standard Deviation</dispersion_type>
            <dispersion_value>0.84</dispersion_value>
            <ci_percent>95</ci_percent>
            <ci_n_sides>2-Sided</ci_n_sides>
            <ci_lower_limit>0.63</ci_lower_limit>
            <ci_upper_limit>3.98</ci_upper_limit>
          </analysis>
        </analysis_list>
      </outcome>
    </outcome_list>

    <reported_events>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="E1">
          <title>Intervention</title>
          <description>Major adverse cardiovascular events: totally of death, myocardial infarction, percutaneous coronary intervention in intervention group</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="E2">
          <title>Controls</title>
          <description>Major adverse cardiovascular events: totally of death, myocardial infarction, percutaneous coronary intervention in control group</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <serious_events>
        <category_list>
          <category>
            <title>Total</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, all-cause mortality</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="33"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="39"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, serious adverse events</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="5" subjects_at_risk="33"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="39"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Cardiac disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Major adverse Cardiovascular events</sub_title>
                <description>Mortality, myocardial infarction and percutaneous coronary intervention</description>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="5" subjects_at_risk="33"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="39"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
        </category_list>
      </serious_events>
      <other_events>
        <frequency_threshold>5</frequency_threshold>
        <default_vocab>PCI</default_vocab>
        <default_assessment>Systematic Assessment</default_assessment>
        <category_list>
          <category>
            <title>Total</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, other adverse events</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="33"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="39"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Cardiac disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Percutaneous coronary intervention</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="33"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="39"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
        </category_list>
      </other_events>
    </reported_events>

    <certain_agreements>
      <pi_employee>All Principal Investigators ARE employed by the organization sponsoring the study.</pi_employee>
      <restrictive_agreement>There is NOT an agreement between Principal Investigators and the Sponsor (or its agents) that restricts the PI's rights to discuss or publish trial results after the trial is completed. </restrictive_agreement>
    </certain_agreements>
    <point_of_contact>
      <name_or_title>Dra Marcia Moura Schmidt</name_or_title>
      <organization>Cardiologia (Institute of Cardiology of Rio Grande do Sul/University Foundation of Cardiology</organization>
      <phone>5551 32333600 ext 3765</phone>
      <email>mmoura22@terra.com.br</email>
    </point_of_contact>
  </clinical_results>
</clinical_study>

