<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02521844</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>D3-002</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02521844</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study to Evaluate the Safety and Tolerability of ETC-1922159 in Advanced Solid Tumours</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase 1A/B Study to Evaluate the Safety and Tolerability of ETC-1922159 in Advanced Solid Tumours</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>EDDC (Experimental Drug Development Centre), A*STAR Research Entities</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>PPD</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>EDDC (Experimental Drug Development Centre), A*STAR Research Entities</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a Phase 1A/B study consisting of four parts.

        1. Part A (completed) is a non-randomised, open-label, sequential evaluation of the safety,
           pharmacokinetics (PK), maximum tolerated dose (MTD), and recommended dose (RD) of
           ETC-1922159 in patients with advanced or metastatic, or unresectable solid malignancies,
           for whom no approved treatment option or standard of care is available. Dose escalation,
           with the goal of identifying the MTD and RD, is guided by an ordinal continual
           reassessment method (oCRM) model with a cohort size of one patient.

        2. Part A extension (completed) is a non-randomised, non-comparative, open-label evaluation
           of the safety and tolerability of ETC-1922159 together with the bone protective
           treatment (denosumab) in patients with advanced or metastatic, or unresectable solid
           malignancies, for whom no approved treatment option or standard of care is available.

        3. Part B dose escalation will be a non-randomised, open-label, sequential evaluation of
           the MTD, RD, safety, PK, and PD (pharmacodynamics) of ETC 1922159 in combination with
           pembrolizumab in patients with advanced or metastatic, or unresectable solid
           malignancies, for whom no approved treatment option or standard of care is available.

        4. Part B dose expansion will be a non-randomised, non-comparative, open-label study
           evaluation of the safety and tolerability of ETC-1922159 as a single agent until disease
           progression and then in combination with pembrolizumab at the RD identified in the Part
           B dose escalation segment, in patients with advanced or metastatic, or unresectable
           solid malignancies that are refractory, intolerant or not suitable for available
           treatment according to the treating physician.

      It is anticipated that the study will take approximately 78 months to complete (36 months for
      Part A and Part A Extension, approximately 6 months for Part B dose escalation and
      approximately 36 months for Part B dose expansion).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Sequential Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum Tolerated Dose (MTD) of ETC-1922159 when administered with pembrolizumab (Part B Dose Escalation)</measure>
    <time_frame>For 2 cycles (42 days)</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Recommended Dose (RD) of ETC-1922159 when administered with pembrolizumab (Part B Dose Escalation)</measure>
    <time_frame>For 2 cycles (42 days)</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with adverse events (AEs) (Part B Dose Expansion)</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of enrolment until end of treatment</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with adverse bone density imaging assessments via DEXA scan (Part B Dose Expansion)</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of enrolment until end of treatment</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with abnormal 12-lead electrocardiogram (ECG) readings (Part B Dose Expansion)</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of enrolment until end of treatment</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group performance status (Part B Dose Expansion)</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of enrolment until end of treatment</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with abnormal clinical laboratory test results (Part B Dose Expansion)</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of enrolment until end of treatment</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with abnormal vital sign measurements (Part B Dose Expansion)</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of enrolment until end of treatment</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Tolerability measured by monitoring of fatigue and gastrointestinal-related side effects and when applicable, immune-related side effects in patients (Part B Dose Expansion)</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of enrolment until end of treatment</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with adverse events (AEs) (Part B Dose Escalation)</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of enrolment until end of treatment</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with adverse bone density imaging assessments via DEXA scan (Part B Dose Escalation)</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of enrolment until end of treatment</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with abnormal 12-lead electrocardiogram (ECG) readings (Part B Dose Escalation)</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of enrolment until end of treatment</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group performance status (Part B Dose Escalation)</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of enrolment until end of treatment</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with abnormal clinical laboratory test results (Part B Dose Escalation)</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of enrolment until end of treatment</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with abnormal vital sign measurements (Part B Dose Escalation)</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of enrolment until end of treatment</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Tolerability measured by monitoring of fatigue and gastrointestinal-related side effects and when applicable, immune-related side effects in patients (Part B Dose Escalation)</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of enrolment until end of treatment</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical activity measured by RECIST (Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumours) version 1.1 and iRECIST (Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumours modified for immune-based therapeutics) (Part B Dose Expansion)</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of enrolment until end of treatment</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>ETC-1922159 Maximum plasma concentration (Cmax) (Part B)</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of enrolment until end of treatment</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>ETC-1922159 Area under the curve (AUC) (Part B)</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of enrolment until end of treatment</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Retrospective evaluation of plasma/serum concentration of pembrolizumab (Part B)</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of enrolment to Cycle 2 for Dose Escalation and Cycle 1 of combination therapy for Dose Expansion</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Retrospective evaluation of plasma/serum concentration of bone protective agents, if administered (Part B)</measure>
    <time_frame>Before and after the first administration only</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">83</enrollment>
  <condition>Solid Tumors</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Dose Escalation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>ETC-1922159 + pembrolizumab</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Dose Expansion</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>ETC-1922159 as single agent until disease progression, then in combination with pembrolizumab at the recommended dose (RD) identified in the dose escalation segment</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ETC-1922159</intervention_name>
    <description>Oral administration</description>
    <arm_group_label>Dose Escalation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Dose Expansion</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pembrolizumab</intervention_name>
    <description>IV administration</description>
    <arm_group_label>Dose Escalation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Dose Expansion</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria (Part B):

          -  18+ yrs (US), 21+ yrs (Singapore)

          -  Ability to give informed consent

          -  Histologically/cytologically confirmed advanced or metastatic tumors, that are
             unresectable solid malignancies, and that are are refractory, intolerant or not
             suitable to available treatment

          -  Objective and radiologically confirmed disease progression at screening

          -  Measurable disease by RECIST v1.1

          -  ECOG (Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group) 0-2

          -  Life expectancy ≥3 months

          -  Organ function:

               -  Absolute neutrophil count ≥1.0×10^9/L

               -  Platelets ≥100×10^9/L (w/o transfusions w/in 21 days)

               -  Hemoglobin ≥9 g/dL

               -  PT (prothrombin time) and PTT (partial thromboplastin time) w/in ≤1.5× ULN

               -  International normalised ration (INR) ≤1.5× ULN

               -  Total bilirubin ≤1.5× ULN

               -  Transaminases (AST and/or alanine aminotransferase) ≤2.5× ULN (&lt;5× ULN with liver
                  metastases)

               -  Creatinine clearance ≥60 mL/min

               -  Total calcium (corrected for serum albumin) within normal limits

               -  Magnesium ≥ lower limit of normal (LLN)

               -  Normal urinalysis

          -  Patients with osteopenia (T-score of -1 to -2.5 at L/R total hip, L/R femoral neck or
             lumbar spine [L1-L4]) eligible

          -  Capable of swallowing study medication or has caregiver responsible for administering
             study drug

          -  Negative serum pregnancy test

          -  Dose Expansion - Group 1 and Group 2a only (patients with MSS [microsatellite
             stable]-colorectal cancer [CRC]): Is refractory, intolerant or not suitable for
             treatment with fluoropyrimidine, oxaliplatin, or irinotecan.

          -  Dose Expansion - Group 1 patients: MSS-CRC with confirmed presence of at least one of
             the four different recurrent gene fusions involving RSPO2 or RSPO3 (Fusions A-D).

          -  Dose Expansion - Group 2a patients: Has MSS-CRC with confirmed absence of all four
             different recurrent gene fusions involving RSPO2 or RSPO3 (Fusions A-D).

          -  Dose Expansion - Groups 2b and 2c only (patients with MSS-ovarian and MSS-endometrial
             cancer): Has advanced or metastatic disease for which further conventional therapy,
             e.g. platinum-based chemotherapy, is not suitable. Has MSS tumour as determined by IHC
             (immunohistochemistry), PCR (polymerase chain reaction) or NGS (next generation
             sequencing).

          -  Dose Expansion: All patients must have sufficient archival tumour tissue available, or
             if no archival tumour tissue or tumour ribonucleic acid (RNA) sample is available, the
             patient must have tumour sites that allow conduction of biopsies.

          -  Dose Expansion: Pre-dose and post-dose tumour biopsies are mandatory unless tumour is
             inaccessible or deemed unsafe for procedure by principal investigator.

        Exclusion Criteria (Part B):

          -  Male patient with sexual partner(s) of childbearing potential unwilling to use
             contraception. Sexually active male patients must use a condom during intercourse
             during the study and for 12 weeks after the end of treatment. Condom must also be used
             by vasectomised males.

          -  Female of childbearing potential, unless birth control is used during study and for 12
             weeks after end of treatment.

          -  Pregnant or nursing (lactating) female.

          -  Dose Escalation: Current or anti-cancer therapy within 4 weeks pre-study or with Grade
             ≤1 side effects not resolved within 4 weeks pre-study.

          -  Dose Expansion: Has received previous treatment with pembrolizumab or other immune
             checkpoint inhibitors.

          -  Is receiving any concomitant anti-cancer therapy.

          -  Has used other investigational products within 4 weeks or 5 half-lives (whichever is
             longer) prior to first dose of study drug.

          -  Has evidence of other malignancy not in remission or history of other malignancy
             within last 3 yrs (exceptions: treated basal or skin squamous cell carcinoma or in
             situ cancer of cervix)

          -  Has central nervous system metastases, unless treated with surgery, whole brain
             radiation or stereotactic radiosurgery, and stable disease ≥8 weeks without steroid
             use for ≥4 weeks prior to first dose of study drug.

          -  Has received prior radiation therapy within 4 weeks, or limited field radiation within
             2 weeks, prior to study drug, or with unresolved Grade ≤1 side effects .

          -  Has history of radiation to spine/pelvis bone or chemoradiation to pelvic organs.

          -  Has had major surgical procedure within 4 weeks of starting study drug. Or patient has
             not fully recovered from all surgery-related complications to Grade ≤1.

          -  Has a history of interstitial lung disease, sarcoidosis, silicosis, idiopathic
             pulmonary fibrosis, or pulmonary hypersensitivity pneumonitis.

          -  Has received bisphosphonate therapy for osteoporosis or symptomatic hypercalcaemia, or
             denosumab for osteoporosis prior to starting study drug.

          -  Has osteoporosis (T-score of ≤ -2.5 at left or right total hip, left or right femoral
             neck, or lumbar spine [L1-L4] by DEXA scan).

          -  Has a history of symptomatic vertebral fragility fractures or fragility fracture of
             hip, pelvis, wrist, or other location (fragility fracture - any fracture without
             trauma or as a result of a fall from ≤standing height).

          -  Has moderate (25%-40% decrease vertebral height) or severe (&gt;40% decrease vertebral
             height) morphometric vertebral fractures.

          -  Has B-CTX serum level &gt;600 pg/mL in the morning after at least 10 hours of fasting at
             Screening.

          -  Has thyrotropin level less than lower limit of normal (LLN).

          -  Has 25-hydroxy vitamin D levels less than 50 mmol/L (20 ng/mL).

          -  Has bone metastases.

          -  Has a history of long QT or prolonged QTc (&gt;460 ms).

          -  Is receiving, or has received thiazolidinedione peroxisome proliferator-activated
             receptor gamma agonist (e.g. Actos® [pioglitazone] and Avandia® [rosiglitazone]) w/in
             4 wks prior to starting study drug.

          -  Has metabolic bone disease such as hyperparathyroidism, Paget's disease or
             osteomalacia.

          -  Has a known clinically significant bleeding disorder or coagulopathy.

          -  Is receiving or has received within 4 weeks prior to starting study drug, heparin,
             warfarin or similar anti-coagulants (except for patients on low molecular weight
             heparin for treatment or prophylaxis).

          -  Has severe or unstable medical conditions such as heart failure, ischemic heart
             disease, uncontrolled hypertension, uncontrolled diabetes mellitus, psychiatric
             condition, ongoing cardiac arrhythmia requiring medication (Grade ≥2, by National
             Cancer Institute [NCI] CTCAE v. 4.03).

          -  Has a known history of human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) or active bacterial, viral
             or fungal infections.

          -  Has a history of gastric bypass surgery.

          -  Has received prior treatment with an inhibitor of the Wnt-B-catenin pathway.

          -  Is unwilling or unable to comply with the protocol.

          -  Cannot start treatment with the bone protective treatment with denosumab and/or
             zoledronic acid.

          -  Dose Expansion: Patient is unable to provide tumour tissue (from archival tissue or a
             fresh biopsy or tumour RNA).

          -  Has received prophylactic administration of hematopoietic colony stimulating factors
             within 4 weeks prior to starting study drug.

          -  Is receiving active treatment with an oral or IV glucocorticoid for ≥4 weeks at a
             daily dose equivalent to ≥10 mg of oral prednisone within the 12 weeks prior to
             starting the study drug.

          -  Has recent or current active infectious disease requiring systemic antibiotics or
             antifungal or antiviral treatment within 2 weeks prior to the start of the study drug.
             Subjects receiving prophylactic antibiotics (e.g. for prevention of urinary tract
             infection or chronic obstructive pulmonary disease) are eligible.

          -  Has a serious non-healing wound.

          -  Has a history of vasculitis.

          -  Has an active autoimmune disease that has required systemic treatment in the past 2
             years. Replacement therapy is not considered a form of systemic treatment.

          -  Has received a live vaccine within 28 days prior to the start of the study drug.

        Other protocol-defined inclusion and exclusion criteria may apply.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Joel Leong, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>EDDC, Chief Development Officer</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Wenyan Li, MBBS, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>PPD, Associate Medical Director</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Colorado Hospital Anschutz Cancer Pavilion, 1665 Aurora Court</name>
      <address>
        <city>Aurora</city>
        <state>Colorado</state>
        <zip>80045</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center, 1515 Holcombe Blvd., Unit 455</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National University Hospital, 1E Kent Ridge Road, NUHS Tower Block, Level 7</name>
      <address>
        <city>Singapore</city>
        <zip>119228</zip>
        <country>Singapore</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Cancer Centre Singapore, 11 Hospital Drive</name>
      <address>
        <city>Singapore</city>
        <zip>169610</zip>
        <country>Singapore</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Singapore</country>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <removed_countries>
    <country>Spain</country>
  </removed_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.fda.gov/Safety/Recalls</url>
    <description>FDA Safety Alerts and Recalls</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>September 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 27, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 10, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 13, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 27, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 27, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 1, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>solid tumors</keyword>
  <keyword>responsive to Wnt signalling regulation</keyword>
  <keyword>RSPO fusions</keyword>
  <keyword>Porcupine</keyword>
  <keyword>PD-1</keyword>
  <keyword>MSS</keyword>
  <keyword>CRC</keyword>
  <keyword>endometrial cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>ovarian cancer</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pembrolizumab</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

