<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03711669</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PI17/00955</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03711669</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Biomarkers to Predict the Success of Immunosuppression Withdrawal in Autoimmune Hepatitis</brief_title>
  <official_title>Identification of Biomarkers That Help to Predict Success of Immunosuppression Withdrawal in Patients With Type 1 Autoimmune Hepatitis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Hospital Clinic of Barcelona</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Hospital Clinic of Barcelona</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Autoimmune hepatitis (AIH) is an inflammatory, chronic and recurrent liver disease of unknown
      etiology that can lead to cirrhosis or acute liver failure. It is a rare disease affecting 16
      cases every 100,000 persons in Europe, mainly in women in every age group. It is
      characteristic the presence of high levels of aminotransferases, hypergammaglobulinemia and
      high titres of autoantibodies, as well as interface hepatitis in the biopsy.

      Due to the autoimmune etiology of AIH, treatment is based on immunosuppressive strategies,
      mainly prednisone and azathioprine regimens which make possible to achieve remission in
      approximately 75% of cases with moderate or severe hepatocellular inflammation.

      Remission is defined as a normalization in aminotransferases, immunoglobulin G (IgG) and
      resolution histological inflammation (this last one comes after biochemical remission). It
      has also been observed that there is a restoration in number and function of Tregs after
      achieving remission.

      The rates of recurrence after withdrawing it varies from 30-87% depending on the studies and
      their follow-up. It is usual to maintain treatment indefinitely in clinical practice. This
      strategy implies maintaining treatment for long periods of time in patients that could be
      available to maintain sustained remission, exposing them to adverse effects. From all these,
      we think it is important to be able to identify patients who will be able to maintain
      biochemical and histological remission without immunosuppression (IS), which still is not
      known in this disease's management.

      Some observational and retrospective studies have identified some parameters that could imply
      a higher risk of recurrence after stopping treatment such as high levels of aminotransferases
      and IgG, less time of remission before withdrawal (specifically less than 2 years) or
      presence of interface hepatitis in a biopsy prior discontinuation of treatment. However, the
      accuracy of these parameters is low and as a result, management of this disease has not
      changed much over the past decades, still having patients under prolonged treatment
      unnecessarily.

      For the previously mentioned reasons, there is a need to identify new biomarkers that allow
      clinicians selecting patients with AIH in whom treatment could be stopped avoiding its costs
      and adverse effects. At the same time, it would help to understand the immunopathogenesis of
      AIH and identification of new therapeutic targets.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Study design: This is a prospective not controlled, not randomized, unicentric study to
      establish predictive biomarkers for a safe and effective treatment withdrawal in patients
      with type 1 AIH.

      Length of the study: Screening is expected to take a year. Treatment withdrawal will be done
      gradually over a period of 6 months and there will be a follow-up of 18 months.

      Sample size: The rate of recurrence has been around 36% in some studies. However, this rate
      is uncertain and it depends on the studied population and the afterwards follow-up. That is
      why investigators have calculated the sample size with the confidence interval of this rate
      and a 10% precision which was of 87 patients. Expecting 10% of losses, the final sample size
      is 96 patients.

      Patients: Investigators will select 96 patients diagnosed with type 1 AIH with biochemical
      remission of at least 3 years that are under immunosuppressive treatment followed in Hospital
      Clinic Barcelona. Patients with type 2 AIH are excluded because of their proved high risk of
      recurrence. Other inclusion and exclusion criteria are the following:

      Treatment withdrawal: IS will be tapered gradually over a period of 6 months. Azathioprine
      will be stopped during the first 3 months, reducing the dose 50% every month. Prednisone will
      be tapered 2.5mg monthly until total withdrawal. During withdrawal and the first year after
      stopping treatment patients will undergo laboratory tests on a monthly basis, afterwards,
      follow-up will be done every 3 months until the end of the project.

      Sustained remission: Patients that after stopping treatment maintain AST/ALT under 2 times
      the upper normal limit.

      Recurrence: Patients who do not fulfil previous criteria.

      Data collection:

        -  Demographic variables: age, sex, time from diagnosis to treatment withdrawal, laboratory
           information such as aminotransferases, gamma-glutamyl transferase (GGT), alkaline
           phosphatase (AP) and autoantibodies.

        -  Histological sample at the moment of inclusion in which the following analysis will be
           performed: usual staining techniques to evaluate the presence of portal inflammation,
           interface hepatitis and fibrosis. Expression of a group of genes involved in liver
           rejection (CXCL9, CXCL10, FoxP3, TK1, CD74, MMP9) will be evaluated with quantitative
           polymerase chain reaction (qPCR) in RNA of the tissue samples cryopreserved at -80ºC.
           Immunochemical staining to quantify the number of lymphocytes CD4+, CD8+ and Tregs.

        -  The following variables will be evaluated in blood samples collected at the inclusion
           and in every follow-up visit:

             -  Flux cytometry: Frequency and characteristics of Tregs (CD4+, CD25+, CD127- and
                FoxP3). The intracellular stain of CTLA-4 will be evaluated as well.

             -  Stimulation with interleukin 2 (IL2) to study Tregs response (measured by the
                expression of pSTAT5 after 20minutes of stimulation and the afterwards production
                of IL10).

             -  Autoantibodies titers: antinuclear autoantibodies (ANA), anti-smooth muscle
                antibody(ASMA), anti-liver kidney microsome type 1 (antiLKM), anti-soluble liver
                antigen (antiSLA) and immunoglobulins levels.

      Statistical analysis: Categorical variables will be compared with Chi or Fisher tests.
      Quantitative variables will be analyzed with non-parametric tests (Mann-Whitney for
      independent samples and Wilcoxon for paired samples). To quantify the expression of genes in
      blood and tissue sample the Ct of the gene will be normalized with the 3 &quot;housekeeping&quot; (18S,
      HPRT, GAPDH) to generate the delta Ct. Results will be expressed as a relative expression of
      the cDNA of the study and the calibrated sample. Differences of &lt;0.05 will be considered as
      statistically significant. Data analysis will be performed with Stata vs 15.1.

      Ambition: Investigator's hypothesis is that those patients affected with type 1 AIH able to
      maintain remission after treatment withdrawal will express distinctive serological and
      histological biomarkers, making possible the identification of patients that could benefit
      from stopping treatment in the future avoiding its costs and adverse effects. At the same
      time, it would help to understand the immunopathogenesis of AIH and the identification of new
      therapeutic targets. Therefore, changing the natural history of this disease where there has
      been little advance in this field in the past decades.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 10, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Remission rate after treatment withdrawal</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion (average 1.5 years)</time_frame>
    <description>Patients that after stopping treatment maintain aspartate aminotransferase (AST) and alanine aminotransferase (ALT) under 2 times the upper normal limit at the end of the study</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse outcomes after treatment withdrawal (descriptive)</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion (average 1.5 years)</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluation of complications that take place after treatment withdrawal: need of hospitalization if there is a flare or diagnosis of 'de novo' autoimmune diseases or worsening symptoms such as asthenia or arthralgias.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">96</enrollment>
  <condition>Autoimmune Hepatitis</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Immunosuppression withdrawal</intervention_name>
    <description>IS will be tapered gradually over a period of 6 months. Azathioprine will be stopped during the first 3 months, reducing the dose 50% every month. Prednisone will be tapered 2.5mg monthly until total withdrawal. During withdrawal and the first year after stopping treatment patients will undergo laboratory tests on a monthly basis, afterwards follow-up will be done every 3 months until the end of the project.</description>
  </intervention>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      -  Histological sample at inclusion. The following analysis will be performed: usual
           staining techniques to evaluate the presence of portal inflammation, interface hepatitis
           and fibrosis. Expression of group of genes involved in liver rejection (CXCL9, CXCL10,
           FoxP3, TK1, CD74, MMP9) will be evaluated with qPCR in RNA of the tissue samples
           cryopreserved at -80ºC. Immunochemical staining to quantity the number of lymphocytes
           CD4+, CD8+ and Tregs.

        -  Blood samples collected at the inclusion and in every follow-up visit:

             -  Frequency and characteristics of Tregs (CD4+, CD25+, CD127- and FoxP3).
                Intracellular stain of CTLA-4 will be evaluated as well

             -  Stimulation with IL2 to study Tregs response.

        -  Faecal sample at inclusion to evaluate microbiome.
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients diagnosed with type 1 AIH with biochemical remission of at least 3 years that are
        under immunosuppressive treatment followed in Hospital Clinic Barcelona. Patients with type
        2 AIH are excluded because of their proved high risk of recurrence.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Diagnosis of type 1 AIH.

          -  AST/ALT within normal limits the 3 years prior inclusion.

          -  normal levels of IgG.

          -  &gt; 18 years-old.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Presence of biochemical alterations during the 3 years prior diagnosis.

          -  Coexistence of another autoimmune disease that requires IS.

          -  Prednisone doses over 7.5mg/day.

          -  Biopsy prior starting withdrawal with a Knodell score over 3/16.

          -  Positivity for hepatitis B virus, hepatitis C virus or human immunodeficiency virus.

          -  Pregnancy.

          -  Glomerular filtrate &lt;35ml/min.

          -  Not being able to attend follow-up visits.

          -  Use of drugs or alcohol abuse.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Maria C Londoño, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Hospital Clinic of Barcelona</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Maria C Londoño, MD,PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+34 932275753</phone>
    <phone_ext>2845</phone_ext>
    <email>mlondono@clinic.cat</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Laura P Llovet, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+34 932275753</phone>
    <phone_ext>2344</phone_ext>
    <email>llovet@clinic.cat</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Clinic Barcelona</name>
      <address>
        <city>Barcelona</city>
        <zip>08036</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Maria C Londoño, MD, PhD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital del Mar</name>
      <address>
        <city>Barcelona</city>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Montserrat Garcia-Retortillo</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Spain</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 4, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 16, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 18, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 10, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 10, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 12, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Hospital Clinic of Barcelona</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Maria Londoño</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Senior Staff Specialist</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>autoimmune hepatitis</keyword>
  <keyword>disease flare</keyword>
  <keyword>treatment withdrawal</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis A</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis, Autoimmune</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>IPD are to be shared with researchers participating in the study.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

