<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03715244</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PODSPA</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03715244</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Rate of Postoperative Delirium and Postoperative Cognitive Dysfunction After Spinal Anesthesia</brief_title>
  <official_title>Rate of Postoperative Delirium and Postoperative Cognitive Dysfunction After Spinal Anesthesia With Short-acting Local Anesthetics Compared to General Anesthesia After a Shared Decision Making Process</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Charite University, Berlin, Germany</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Charite University, Berlin, Germany</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The aim of this investigation is to compare the standard of general anesthesia used in these
      patients with these short-acting local anesthetics (Chloroprocain (Ampres®) and Prilocain
      (Takipril®)) for spinal anesthesia as well as to report the patient centered outcome of
      postoperative delirium and neurocognitive disorder. In accordance to current evidence
      regarding the occurrence of postoperative delirium and postoperative cognitive deficit,
      patients are to be screened daily for delirium up to the fifth postoperative day if in
      hospital, or till the first postoperative day after ambulatory surgery and for neurocognitive
      disorder 1 year following the surgery. To detect delirium the Nu-DESC (Nursing Delirium
      Screening Scale) will be used as a validated scoring systems to ensure the highest
      sensitivity in delirium identification. CANTAB battery will be used for assessment of
      neurocognitive disorder. This is a neuropsychological testing (computer-based (I-Pad)
      [Cambridge Neuropsychological Test Automated Battery - CANTAB connect and parameters from the
      item list], as well as the subjective / by proxy Assessment of Cognitive Limitations. It is
      essential to perform the appropriate cognitive performance tests not only on operative
      patients but also on a non-surgical cohort, using currently established models of calculation
      in postoperative cognitive deficits and a control group generated from non-surgical patients.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      A conventional spinal anesthesia with long-acting drugs (such as bupivacaine) can lead to
      delays in postoperative recovery, mobilization, delays in discharge from recovery room and in
      ambulatory surgery. Short-acting local anesthetics (Chloroprocain (Ampres®) and Prilocain
      (Takipril®)) might be beneficial in short duration surgery under spinal anesthesia and could
      improve patients' acceptance for neuroaxial anesthesia as it might improve early recovery and
      early mobilization. Time to first oral nutritional intake/postoperative nausea and vomiting
      (PONV), time to discharge from post-anesthesia recovery unit and time to discharge home after
      ambulatory operation might be reduced and might reduce incidence of postoperative delirium
      and neurocognitive disorder after peripheral surgery.

      It is planned to retrospectively examine a group of surgical patients for the purpose of a
      comparative descriptive collective. This comparison collective is required for various
      questions, in particular influencing factors with regard to the postoperative outcomes
      delirium, neurocognitive disorder and mortality. Only the routine data is used and no
      additional surveys are performed on these patients. Inclusion criteria such as the study
      cohort and additionally the inclusion criterion: Spinal anesthesia with another local
      anesthetic
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 12, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 30, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 30, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of postoperative delirium</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to five postoperative days</time_frame>
    <description>Postoperative delirium rate, defined according to Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders (DSM-V) and/or as ≥ 2 cumulative points in the nursing Delirium Screening Scale (Nu-DESC) and/or a positive Confusion Assessment Method (CAM) and/or Confusion Assessment Method for the Intensive Care Unit (CAM-ICU) score and/or patient chart review that shows descriptions of delirium. The basis is the elevation of the sedation depth with the Richmond Agitation Sedation Scale (RASS).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Neurocognitive disorder</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Neurocognitive Disorder is evaluated according to DSM-V (postoperative cognitive deficit, activities of daily living, instrumental activities of daily living, subjective memory sensing).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of delirium</measure>
    <time_frame>Participants will be followed for the duration of hospital stay, an expected average of 7 days ]</time_frame>
    <description>Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders (DSM-V) Nursing Delirium Screening Scale (Nu-DESC) Intensive Care Delirium Screening Checklist (ICDSC) Delirium Detection Scale (DDS) Confusion Assessment Method for the Intensive Care Unit (CAM-ICU) Confusion Assessment Method (CAM) Chart Review</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Severity of delirium</measure>
    <time_frame>Participants will be followed for the duration of hospital stay, an expected average of 7 days ]</time_frame>
    <description>Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders (DSM-V) Nursing Delirium Screening Scale (Nu-DESC) Intensive Care Delirium Screening Checklist (ICDSC) Delirium Detection Scale (DDS) Confusion Assessment Method (CAM) Chart Review</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to mobilization</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to five postoperative days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to first oral nutritional intake</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to five postoperative days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time until leaving the recovery room</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to leaving the recovery room</time_frame>
    <description>Fulfillment of discharge criteria from the recovery room</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time until leaving hospital</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to five postoperative days</time_frame>
    <description>Fulfillment of discharge criteria from hospital after study procedure</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Organ complications according to Clavien</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to five postoperative days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Autonomy Preference Index (API)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to five postoperative days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Perceived involvement in care scales (PICS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to five postoperative days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Total treatment outcome in terms of quality of life of patients</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>EQ-5D</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Total treatment outcome in terms of functional autonomy of patients</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Activities of Daily Living (ADLs) or Instrumental Activities of Daily Living (IADLs)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Intraoperative Neuromonitoring</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to the end of surgical procedure</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cerobrospinal fluid parameter</measure>
    <time_frame>Until the end of surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Beta-Amyloid 1-40, beta-Amyloid 1-42, beta-Amyloid Ratio (42/40*10), phospho-TAU, Protein 14-3-3, PRPSc, TAU (Gesamt-Tau) from cerobrospinal fluid for measuring dementia</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Apolipoprotein E</measure>
    <time_frame>Until the end of surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Blood marker Apolipoprotein E for measuring dementia</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Multiplex Gene Expression Analysis (Whole Blood)</measure>
    <time_frame>Until first postoperative day</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Antibodies</measure>
    <time_frame>Until first postoperative day</time_frame>
    <description>Antibody from serum (anti-beta2-adrenergic receptor, anti-muscarinic acetylcholine receptor (M3 / M4), anti-serotonin receptor, anti-dopamine receptor)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pro and anti-inflammatory markers</measure>
    <time_frame>Until first postoperative day</time_frame>
    <description>IL-8 from whole blood and IL-6, IL-8 and TGF</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Immune cells</measure>
    <time_frame>Until first postoperative day</time_frame>
    <description>Immune cells from citrate blood</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Autophagy of platelets</measure>
    <time_frame>Until first postoperative day</time_frame>
    <description>Autophagy of platelets from citrate blood</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Intracellular pH</measure>
    <time_frame>Until first postoperative day</time_frame>
    <description>Intracellular pH from citrate blood</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cholinesterases</measure>
    <time_frame>Until the third postoperative day</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Anxiety</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Anxiety is measured by Generalized Anxiety Disorder 7 (GAD-7) and Patient Health Questionnaire 9 (PHQ-9)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Anxiety</measure>
    <time_frame>Participants will be followed for the duration of hospital stay, an expected average of 7 days ]</time_frame>
    <description>Anxiety is measured by he Amsterdam Preoperative Anxiety and Information Scale (APAIS) and Faces Anxiety Scale (FAS)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Obstructive Sleep Apnea (OSAS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Obstructive Sleep Apnea (OSAS) is measured by the STOP-Bang Questionnaire.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Fatigue</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Fatigue is monitored by Acute Fatigue Score</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Sleep behavior</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Sleep behaviour is measured by Insomnia Severity Index (ISI) and 2 items from the Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index (PSQI): &quot;How would you describe the overall quality of your sleep during the last 6 months&quot; (modified Item 6) and how often do you have sleep aids during the last four weeks taken; Which sleeping aid you have taken (Item 7); at baseline, 3 months, 1 year</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Sleep behavior</measure>
    <time_frame>Participants will be followed for the duration of hospital stay, an expected average of 7 days ]</time_frame>
    <description>Sleep behaviour is measured by intraclinical course (immediate perioperative: Richards Campbell Sleep Questionnaire)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Frailty</measure>
    <time_frame>Participants will be followed for the duration of hospital stay, an expected average of 7 days</time_frame>
    <description>Frailty is measured with a modified frailty score according to Fried´s frailty phenotype assessment</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Stress</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Stress is monitored by Perceived Stress Questionnaire 20 (PSQ20) and Disstressthermometer without areas</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Dose of concomitant medication</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 5 postoperative days</time_frame>
    <description>The types of medications used in the management of pain, agitation, and delirium on that day are documented.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of concomitant medication</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 5 postoperative days</time_frame>
    <description>The types of medications used in the management of pain, agitation, and delirium on that day are documented.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time of mechanical ventilation</measure>
    <time_frame>Participants will be followed for the duration of intensive care unit stay, an expected average of 1 day]</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Intensive care unit stay</measure>
    <time_frame>Participants will be followed for the duration of intensive care unit stay, an expected average of 1 day]</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of stationary recoveries</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 1 year</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Visits to doctors and outpatient treatments</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 1 year</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of additional operations</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 1 year</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mortality</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 1 year</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>3</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">530</enrollment>
  <condition>Delirium</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Study group 1</arm_group_label>
    <description>n=220 patients for routine data of spinal anesthesia with short-acting local anesthetics</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Study group 2</arm_group_label>
    <description>n= 220 patients for routine data of general anesthesia (current standard)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>No intervention: Control group postoperative cognitive deficit</arm_group_label>
    <description>n= 90 control subjects aged 18 years or older (without surgery) with a similar health status and age as the study group patients (similar distribution in the American Society of Anaesthesiologists physical status classification and relevant co-morbidities, e.g. diabetes, coronary artery disease, hypertension and hyperlipidemia). The patients are analyzed to correct for learning effects of the cognitive assessment testings in the study groups.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Spinal anesthesia with short-acting local anesthetics</intervention_name>
    <description>Spinal anesthesia in patients with duration of surgery &lt; 90 minutes</description>
    <arm_group_label>Study group 1</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>General anesthesia (current standard)</intervention_name>
    <description>General anesthesia in patients with duration of surgery &lt; 90 minutes</description>
    <arm_group_label>Study group 2</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Apolipoprotein-E-4, ncounter Neuroinflammation and micro RNA Panel from
      Multiplex-Genexpressionsanalyses
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Surgical patients at Campus Virchow - Klinikum and Campus Charité Mitte (Charité -
        Universitätsmedizin Berlin) with short, elective procedure (&lt;90 minutes), feasible in
        spinal anesthesia
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Study group 1 and 2

        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Surgical patients at Campus Virchow - Klinikum and Campus Charité Mitte (Charité -
             Universitätsmedizin Berlin)

          -  Short, elective procedure (&lt;90 minutes), feasible in spinal anesthesia

          -  American Society of Anesthesiologists (ASA-Score I to III)

          -  Age ≥ 18 years

          -  Informed consent process

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Non-consenting patients

          -  Lack of consent to participate in the study or to store, process and disseminate
             pseudonymised study data

          -  Allergy or contraindications to local anesthetics

          -  Contraindications to spinal anesthesia

          -  Coagulopathy or therapy with anticoagulants

          -  Higher grade aortic stenosis

          -  Anomaly of the spinal cord

          -  Pre-existing neurological deficit

          -  Pre-existing neurological disease that severely limits the performance of
             neurocognitive testing

          -  Hearing and / or visual disturbances (such as color blindness) or relevant language
             barrier severely limiting the performance of neurocognitive testing

          -  Spinal anesthesia with another local anesthetic

          -  Sole peripheral local anesthesia

          -  Participation in another prospective intervention study

          -  Emergency operation

          -  Pregnancy and breast feeding period

        POCD Control group:

        Inclusion criteria:

          -  Male and female patients ages 18-100 years, also controls from the POCD registry
             (EA1/104/16)

          -  Healthy volunteers (ASA I) / ASA II + III patients who are not scheduled for surgery
             next year

          -  Ability to consent to oral and written information

          -  Patient education and written consent

        Exclusion criteria:

          -  Operation in the last six months before inclusion in this study

          -  Lack of consent for the pseudonymised disease data to be stored and shared in this
             clinical trial

          -  Lack of readiness to participate in the follow-up examinations and contact to make an
             appointment

          -  Patients with a neuropsychiatric condition that limits the performance of
             neurocognitive testing

          -  Patients with hearing and / or vision disorders or relevant language barriers that
             limit the performance of neuro-cognitive testing

          -  Simultaneous participation in a prospective clinical intervention study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Claudia Spies, MD, Prof.</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Charite University, Berlin, Germany</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Claudia Spies, MD, Prof.</last_name>
    <phone>+49 30 450 55 10 01</phone>
    <email>claudia.spies@charite.de</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of Anesthesiology and Operative Intensive Care Medicine (CCM/CVK), Charité - Universitätsmedizin Berlin</name>
      <address>
        <city>Berlin</city>
        <zip>10117</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Claudia Spies, MD, Prof.</last_name>
      <phone>+49 30 450 55 10 01</phone>
      <email>claudia.spies@charite.de</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Claudia Spies, MD, Prof.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Valesca Kipping, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Sascha Tafelski, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jürgen Birnbaum, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Philipp Pickerodt, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Elisa Iwan, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Anika Müller, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Wiltrud Abels, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Antje Kirchstein</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Germany</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Aldecoa C, Bettelli G, Bilotta F, Sanders RD, Audisio R, Borozdina A, Cherubini A, Jones C, Kehlet H, MacLullich A, Radtke F, Riese F, Slooter AJ, Veyckemans F, Kramer S, Neuner B, Weiss B, Spies CD. European Society of Anaesthesiology evidence-based and consensus-based guideline on postoperative delirium. Eur J Anaesthesiol. 2017 Apr;34(4):192-214. doi: 10.1097/EJA.0000000000000594. Review. Erratum in: Eur J Anaesthesiol. 2018 Sep;35(9):718-719.</citation>
    <PMID>28187050</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 9, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 18, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 23, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 12, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 12, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 13, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Charite University, Berlin, Germany</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Claudia Spies</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Head of the Department of Anesthesiology and Operative Intensive Care Medicine (CCM/CVK), Charité - University Medicine Berlin</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Delirium</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cognitive Dysfunction</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Anesthetics</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Anesthetics, Local</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

