<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03718936</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>GCO 98-436</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03718936</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>ADNP Syndrome: The Seaver Autism Center for Research and Treatment is Characterizing ADNP-related Neurodevelopmental Disorders Using Genetic, Medical, and Neuropsychological Measures.</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Seaver Autism Center for Research and Treatment - Assessment Core</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Icahn School of Medicine at Mount Sinai</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>The Seaver Foundation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Autism Science Foundation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Research Foundation for Mental Hygiene, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Icahn School of Medicine at Mount Sinai</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      ADNP, also known as Activity Dependent Neuroprotective Protein, is a rare neurodevelopmental
      disorder caused by mutations encompassing the ADNP gene on chromosome 20. Clinically, ADNP
      syndrome is characterized by intellectual disability and global developmental delay. This
      study seeks to characterize ADNP-related neurodevelopmental disorders using a number of
      genetic, medical and neuropsychological measures.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Subjects with a variant in the ADNP gene will be asked to complete a battery of
      developmental, behavioral and medical assessments to better characterize gene-related
      neurodevelopmental deficits. This series of assessments takes place over the course of a
      three-day period. It includes the Autism Diagnostic Observation Schedule (ADOS), parent
      interviews regarding developmental history and behavior, a psychiatric evaluation, a
      neurology assessment, as well as a clinical genetic evaluation that includes a physical and
      vitals exam. Affected individuals, as well as biologically related siblings, will also
      undergo a series of sensory assessments, including a research EEG, visual evoked potential,
      and an eyetracking assessment. Family members present for the visit will also be asked to
      provide a blood and/or saliva sample for research genetics.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 14, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Cross-Sectional</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Autism Diagnostic Observation Schedule (ADOS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1</time_frame>
    <description>The ADOS is a structured, play-based assessment of communication, social interaction and behavior in individuals (children and adults) suspected of having a diagnosis of Autism Spectrum Disorder. The examiner will select 1 of 4 different ADOS modules, which differ based on chronological age and verbal fluency, to use for the individual being assessed. An Overall Total score &gt;= 16, if the individual meets for the &quot;few to no words&quot; algorithm, or 12, if the individual meets for the &quot;some words&quot; algorithm, suggests autism in the individual. An Overall Total score of 11 to 15, if the individual meets for the &quot;few to no words&quot; algorithm, or 8 to 11, if the individual meets for the &quot;some words&quot; algorithm, suggests the individual is on the autism spectrum. An Overall Total score equal to or lower than 10, if the individual meets for &quot;few to no words&quot; algorithm, or 7, if the individual meets for the &quot;some words&quot; algorithm, classifies the individual as &quot;non-spectrum&quot; or not on the spectrum.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Autism Diagnostic Interview - Revised (ADI-R)</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1</time_frame>
    <description>The ADI-R is a standardized, semi-structured clinical assessment used to diagnose Autism Spectrum Disorder (ASD) in children and adults. The ADI-R is a structured interview administered by an examiner to the primary caregiver of children and adults suspected of having ASD. The assessment contains 93 items, scored from 0 (behavior not present) to 279 (severe or frequent behavior). A higher assessment score indicates poorer outcomes.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Stanford-Binet Intelligence Scales</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1</time_frame>
    <description>The Stanford-Binet Intelligence Scales are a cognitive assessment measuring the five factors of fluid reasoning, knowledge, quantitative reasoning, visual-spatial processing and working memory. The number of correct responses for the subtests is converted to a Standard Age Score, based on the chronological age of the individual being assessed. The Area Scores and Test Composite on the Stanford-Binet test have an average score of 100 and a standard deviation of 16. The converted score of the individual being assessed indicates where he/she is relative to the norm. A score exceeding 145 is classified as &quot;Genius or near genius,&quot; and scores below 70 are classified as &quot;Borderline deficiency.&quot;</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Differential Ability Scales (DAS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1</time_frame>
    <description>The DAS is a battery of cognitive and achievement testing for children 2.5-18 years old that is divided into Early Years and School-Age versions. The 20 subtests of the DAS are broken up into 17 cognitive and 3 achievement subtests. The scores of the test are categorized into i) General Conceptual Ability (GCA) which is based on the ability of the individual being assessed to perform complex mental processing involving transformation of information ii) cluster scores that indicate verbal, spatial and nonverbal reasoning abilities and iii) subtest scores that represent specific abilities or processes. The tests yield t-scores and percentiles by age.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mullen Scales of Early Learning</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1</time_frame>
    <description>The Mullen Scales of Early Learning are a clinical assessment used to measure cognitive ability and motor development in children ages 0-68 months on the five scales of Gross Motor, Visual Reception, Fine Motor, Expressive Language, and Receptive Language. T-scores, percentile rankings, and age equivalents can be calculated for each of these five scales.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>ADNP</condition>
  <condition>Helsmoortel-Van Der Aa Syndrome</condition>
  <condition>Autism Spectrum Disorder</condition>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Whole blood and/or saliva samples from research participants who consent to giving biological
      specimens for research genetics may be retained with potential for extraction of DNA. Blood
      samples may be used to create Induced Pluripotent Stem Cells (iPSCs).
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Individuals for this cohort study will be selected from any population, provided that they
        have a variant in the ADNP gene and meet eligibility requirements.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Eligible participants must have a documented variant affecting the ADNP gene that the
             research team determines to be likely or definitely pathogenic.

          -  Eligible participants must be at least 2 years of age.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  none
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>2 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Silvia De Rubeis, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Icahn School of Medicine at Mount Sinai</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Paige Siper, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Icahn School of Medicine at Mount Sinai</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Alexander Kolevzon, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Icahn School of Medicine at Mount Sinai</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Lara Tang, B.A.</last_name>
    <phone>212-241-2993</phone>
    <email>lara.tang@mssm.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Tess Levy</last_name>
    <phone>212-241-5290</phone>
    <email>tess.levy@mssm.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The Seaver Autism Center for Research and Treatment</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10029</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Lara Lang, BA</last_name>
      <phone>212-241-2993</phone>
      <email>lara.tang@mssm.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Samantha Bright, BA</last_name>
      <phone>212-241-0961</phone>
      <email>samantha.bright@mssm.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 23, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 23, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 25, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 6, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 6, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 10, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>ADNP</keyword>
  <keyword>Intellectual Disability</keyword>
  <keyword>Autism Spectrum Disorder</keyword>
  <keyword>Global Developmental Delay</keyword>
  <keyword>Neurodevelopmental Deficits</keyword>
  <keyword>Developmental Disability</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Autistic Disorder</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Autism Spectrum Disorder</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

