<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03718156</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PT 71435</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03718156</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Prevention Program for Alzheimer's Related Delirium (PREPARED) Trial</brief_title>
  <acronym>PREPARED</acronym>
  <official_title>The Prevention Program for Alzheimer's Related Delirium (PREPARED) Cluster Randomized Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>McGill University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>McGill University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      By the year 2038, over a million Canadians are expected to have Alzheimer's disease, a type
      of dementia. Dementia increases the risk of nursing home placement among the elderly more
      than fivefold. Given the exceptionally vulnerable nature of this patient population, there is
      a pressing need to ensure that the clinical care they receive is evidence-based, tailored
      specifically for them, and meeting the high standards of quality that would be expected in
      any other health-care setting. Delirium is a sudden and severe change in brain function that
      can cause a person to appear confused or disoriented, have memory loss, and have difficulties
      maintaining focus. It is an urgent care issue facing elderly patients residing in nursing
      homes, or long-term care (LTC) facilities. Delirium is a significant cause of illness and
      mortality, affecting between 10%-89% of LTC patients, but little research has focused on
      delirium prevention in the LTC setting. This study will assess the effectiveness of a LTC
      multicomponent delirium prevention program (PREPARED Trial intervention). The PREPARED Trial
      intervention is an intervention provided to nursing staff working in LTC facilities that
      consists of four components: a decision tree, an instruction manual, a training package, and
      a toolkit. The feasibility and acceptability of the PREPARED Trial intervention has already
      been successfully demonstrated; however, a thorough and well-designed large scale study is
      needed in order to confirm its ability to reduce delirium among LTC residents. In this study,
      approximately 40-50 LTC facilities will be randomized to either receive the PREPARED Trial
      intervention or to receive usual care. At the end of the 4-year study period, the
      investigators will be able to demonstrate the degree to which the PREPARED Trial intervention
      reduces: 1) the number of new cases of delirium; 2) delirium severity; and 3) the duration of
      delirium episodes. This study will provide the blueprint of a program that can be
      transferable to LTC facilities across Canada.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Overall Goal: To reduce the incidence, severity, duration, and frequency of delirium episodes
      in cognitively impaired long-term care (LTC) residents at high risk for delirium.

      Background: Delirium is a significant cause of morbidity and mortality among older people
      admitted to both acute and LTC settings. Prevention, founded on a thorough understanding of
      associated risk factors, is the best approach for dealing with delirium. Several successful
      multicomponent interventions have been developed to reduce delirium incidence in the acute
      care setting (30%-73% reduction) by intervening on identified modifiable risk factors. Little
      work, however, has focused on using this approach to reduce delirium incidence in LTC. As
      such, co-investigators within the study team employed an integrated knowledge translation
      strategy to develop a LTC multicomponent delirium prevention program (PREPARED Trial
      intervention). The feasibility and acceptability of this program has been demonstrated using
      a participatory approach in two Quebec LTC facilities (LTCFs), and the program has received
      recognition by the scientific community. Given its large expected impact and high knowledge
      translation potential, a thorough and well-designed large-scale evaluation is urgently needed
      in order to demonstrate the effectiveness of the multicomponent delirium prevention program
      in preventing delirium among high-risk LTC residents.

      Primary Objective: To assess efficacy of the PREPARED Trial intervention in reducing delirium
      incidence, and delirium episode severity, duration, and frequency among cognitively impaired,
      high-risk LTC residents.

      Secondary Objectives: To compare the effect of the PREPARED Trial intervention to that of
      usual care on the incidence of falls among cognitively impaired LTC residents, to estimate
      the association between medication use and delirium incidence in LTCFs, to estimate if there
      is an effect modification by motor subtype of delirium or by dementia subtype, and to measure
      the prevalence of delirium in participating institutions.

      Tertiary Objectives: To compare the effect of the PREPARED Trial intervention on other health
      outcomes, including: changes in functional autonomy or social engagement, the number of
      transfers to acute care, consultations with healthcare providers, and mortality rates.

      Methods: This 4-year cluster randomized study will involve nursing staff and residents in
      40-50 public and semi-private LTC facilities in Quebec, Canada. Institutions within all 5 of
      the Montreal island Integrated University Health and Social Services networks (CIUSSS) and
      one private provincial network are currently participating. Approximately 900 LTC residents
      will be enrolled in the study and followed for 18 weeks only if they are at high risk of
      delirium and are delirium-free at baseline. The PREPARED Trial intervention is a program
      consisting of four components: a decision tree, an instruction manual, a training package and
      a toolkit. Primary study outcomes such as delirium incidence (measured by the Confusion
      Assessment Method), delirium severity (measured by the Delirium Index), and level of
      adherence to the PREPARED Trial protocol will be assessed weekly. Functional autonomy levels
      will be assessed at the beginning and end of follow-up, while information pertaining to
      modifiable delirium risk factors, medical consultations, and institutional transfers will be
      collected for the duration of the follow-up period. For primary analysis, hazard ratios will
      be modeled using Cox regression to compare the effect of the PREPARED Trial intervention to
      that of usual care on the time to first delirium episode. Clustering effects will be taken
      into account using frailty models, an extension of Cox regression for the addition of random
      effects.

      Expected Outcomes and Significance: This large-scale intervention study will contribute
      significantly to the development of evidence-based clinical guidelines for delirium
      prevention in this frail elderly population, as it will be the first to evaluate the efficacy
      of a multicomponent delirium prevention program translated into LTC clinical practice on a
      large scale. In addition to reducing delirium in this frail population, deliverables include
      validation of this prevention program, as well as the transferring of its components
      (including bilingual video training modules for LTC staff) to relevant knowledge users across
      Canada.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 23, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>The PREPARED Trial is a 4-year cluster randomized intervention study. A cluster design was adopted in order to prevent contamination across the intervention and control arms by nursing staff who may provide replacement hours of employment at different units/floors within their long-term care facilities (LTCFs). Participating LTCFs (clusters) will be assigned to either the PREPARED Trial intervention or the control (usual care) arm of the study using a covariate constrained randomization procedure. In addition, given the need to assess each resident weekly for a follow-up period of 18 weeks and logistical limitations (large geographical coverage, 40-50 LTCFs included, and limited work force), the investigators will employ a sequential approach whereby sets of clusters (LTCFs) will be randomized into the two study arms in consecutive 'waves' of follow-up lasting 18 weeks each. It is estimated that 4 waves of trial follow-up, comprised of 10-12 clusters each, will be completed.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
    <masking_description>Long-term care facilities (LTCFs) cannot be blinded, as trial arm allocation will be obvious (those in the intervention group will undergo delirium prevention protocol training before their respective follow-up periods, and those in the control group will not). Similarly, research assistants (RAs) tasked with conducting resident assessments cannot be blinded to group allocation, as they will be constantly exposed to the everyday workings of participating LTCFs. However, RAs will be blinded to resident cognitive scores. All researchers analyzing the data will be blinded to group allocation, as LTCF names will be anonymized and randomization statuses will be concealed prior to data analysis.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of delirium</measure>
    <time_frame>over the 18 week follow-up period</time_frame>
    <description>Confusion Assessment Method (CAM) scores</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Delirium severity</measure>
    <time_frame>over the 18 week follow-up period</time_frame>
    <description>Delirium Index scores (0-21)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Delirium episode duration</measure>
    <time_frame>over the 18 week follow-up period</time_frame>
    <description>the total number of days that a given resident experiences active episode(s) of delirium</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of delirium episodes</measure>
    <time_frame>over the 18 week follow-up period</time_frame>
    <description>count of delirium episodes</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Delirium motoric subtype</measure>
    <time_frame>over the 18 week follow-up period</time_frame>
    <description>Delirium Motor Subtype Scale scores</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of falls</measure>
    <time_frame>over the 18 week follow-up period</time_frame>
    <description>count of falls and fall-related injuries, as documented in medical charts</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to first fall</measure>
    <time_frame>over the 18 week follow-up period</time_frame>
    <description>days to first reported fall</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in functional autonomy</measure>
    <time_frame>over the study period (18 weeks)</time_frame>
    <description>Barthel Index (Shah version) scores</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in cognitive functioning</measure>
    <time_frame>over the study period (18 weeks)</time_frame>
    <description>Hierarchic Dementia Scale scores</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in level of social engagement</measure>
    <time_frame>over the study period (18 weeks)</time_frame>
    <description>Revised Index of Social Engagement in Long-Term Care Facilities scores</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">800</enrollment>
  <condition>Delirium</condition>
  <condition>Dementia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>PREPARED Trial Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participating nursing staff will be trained to apply the PREPARED Trial interventions, and will apply this knowledge to modify the therapeutic nursing plans of residents under their care who are enrolled in the study, accordingly.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Care as Usual</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participating nursing staff will only be provided with general information about delirium, but will not be trained or instructed to modify the therapeutic nursing plans that are in place for residents enrolled in the study. However, at the end of the follow-up period, nursing staff in the control arm will be provided with the PREPARED Trial intervention training program (including bedside coaching), which they can then use after the study has ended at their facility.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>PREPARED Trial Intervention</intervention_name>
    <description>Nursing staff members will be trained to adjust the therapeutic nursing plans (TNP) for residents enrolled in the study, as follows: 1) by providing optimal stimulation (surveying the use of eyeglasses and hearing aids, the room lighting and space organization; orienting the resident to time and space; and stimulating the resident using familiar objects, photos, and life histories); and 2) by assessing the presence of 4 modifiable delirium risk factors (antipsychotic use, sensory impairment, restraint use, and dehydration) and taking specific actions once a given risk factor is identified. For instance, if physical restraints are used, the TNP will require that they are to be removed during care when a caregiver is present (nail care, feeding, and wound care).</description>
    <arm_group_label>PREPARED Trial Intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  has dementia and/or cognitive impairment (as determined by discussions with the
             nursing staff and chart abstraction);

          -  a minimum length of stay in the LTC institution of at least two weeks prior to the
             start of the baseline assessments;

          -  at high risk of delirium, as indicated by a score of 3 or higher on a validated 5-item
             delirium risk screening tool;

          -  delirium-free at baseline, as assessed by the Confusion Assessment Method (CAM), the
             Delirium Index (DI) and a brief chart review over a screening period of two
             consecutive weeks.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  unable to communicate verbally in English or French (as determined by either the
             nursing staff or two consecutive 0-score administrations of the composite cognitive
             interview at screening);

          -  has a history of specific psychiatric conditions (bipolar disorder, depression with
             signs of psychosis, and psychotic disorders) or intellectual disability;

          -  is receiving comfort/end-of-life care.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>65 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Machelle Wilchesky, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>McGill University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Philippe Voyer, Inf. PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Laval University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Nathalie Champoux, MD, MSc</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Université de Montréal</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Antonio Ciampi, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>McGill University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ovidiu Lungu, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Université de Montréal</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jane McCusker, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>McGill University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Johanne Monette, MD, MSc</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Lady Davis Institute for Medical Research</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>T.T. Minh Vu, MD, FRCPC</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Centre hospitalier de l'Université de Montréal (CHUM)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Machelle Wilchesky, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>514-483-2121</phone>
    <phone_ext>2346</phone_ext>
    <email>Machelle.Wilchesky@mcgill.ca</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Stephanie Ballard, MSc</last_name>
    <phone>514-483-2121</phone>
    <phone_ext>2386</phone_ext>
    <email>stephanie.ballard@mail.mcgill.ca</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Association des établissements privés conventionnés</name>
      <address>
        <city>Montréal</city>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Machelle Wilchesky, PhD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Integrated University Health and Social Services Centre for East Montreal</name>
      <address>
        <city>Montréal</city>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Machelle Wilchesky, PhD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Integrated University Health and Social Services Centre for North Montreal</name>
      <address>
        <city>Montréal</city>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Machelle Wilchesky, PhD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Integrated University Health and Social Services Centre for South-Central Montreal</name>
      <address>
        <city>Montréal</city>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Machelle Wilchesky, PhD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Integrated University Health and Social Services Centre for West Montreal</name>
      <address>
        <city>Montréal</city>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Machelle Wilchesky, PhD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Integrated University Health and Social Services Centre for West-Central Montreal</name>
      <address>
        <city>Montréal</city>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Machelle Wilchesky, PhD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Elie M, Rousseau F, Cole M, Primeau F, McCusker J, Bellavance F. Prevalence and detection of delirium in elderly emergency department patients. CMAJ. 2000 Oct 17;163(8):977-81.</citation>
    <PMID>11068569</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fick DM, Agostini JV, Inouye SK. Delirium superimposed on dementia: a systematic review. J Am Geriatr Soc. 2002 Oct;50(10):1723-32. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>12366629</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lemiengre J, Nelis T, Joosten E, Braes T, Foreman M, Gastmans C, Milisen K. Detection of delirium by bedside nurses using the confusion assessment method. J Am Geriatr Soc. 2006 Apr;54(4):685-9.</citation>
    <PMID>16686883</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Voyer P, Richard S, Doucet L, Carmichael PH. Detecting delirium and subsyndromal delirium using different diagnostic criteria among demented long-term care residents. J Am Med Dir Assoc. 2009 Mar;10(3):181-8. doi: 10.1016/j.jamda.2008.09.006. Epub 2009 Jan 8.</citation>
    <PMID>19233058</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>McCusker J, Cole MG, Voyer P, Monette J, Champoux N, Ciampi A, Vu M, Belzile E. Prevalence and incidence of delirium in long-term care. Int J Geriatr Psychiatry. 2011 Nov;26(11):1152-61. doi: 10.1002/gps.2654. Epub 2011 Jan 27.</citation>
    <PMID>21274904</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cole MG. Persistent delirium in older hospital patients. Curr Opin Psychiatry. 2010 May;23(3):250-4. doi: 10.1097/YCO.0b013e32833861f6. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20224406</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cole MG, McCusker J. Treatment of delirium in older medical inpatients: a challenge for geriatric specialists. J Am Geriatr Soc. 2002 Dec;50(12):2101-3.</citation>
    <PMID>12473034</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Inouye SK, Bogardus ST Jr, Charpentier PA, Leo-Summers L, Acampora D, Holford TR, Cooney LM Jr. A multicomponent intervention to prevent delirium in hospitalized older patients. N Engl J Med. 1999 Mar 4;340(9):669-76.</citation>
    <PMID>10053175</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Reston JT, Schoelles KM. In-facility delirium prevention programs as a patient safety strategy: a systematic review. Ann Intern Med. 2013 Mar 5;158(5 Pt 2):375-80. doi: 10.7326/0003-4819-158-5-201303051-00003. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23460093</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Vidán MT, Sánchez E, Alonso M, Montero B, Ortiz J, Serra JA. An intervention integrated into daily clinical practice reduces the incidence of delirium during hospitalization in elderly patients. J Am Geriatr Soc. 2009 Nov;57(11):2029-36. doi: 10.1111/j.1532-5415.2009.02485.x. Epub 2009 Sep 15.</citation>
    <PMID>19754498</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hshieh TT, Yue J, Oh E, Puelle M, Dowal S, Travison T, Inouye SK. Effectiveness of multicomponent nonpharmacological delirium interventions: a meta-analysis. JAMA Intern Med. 2015 Apr;175(4):512-20. doi: 10.1001/jamainternmed.2014.7779. Erratum in: JAMA Intern Med. 2015 Apr;175(4):659.</citation>
    <PMID>25643002</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Martinez F, Tobar C, Hill N. Preventing delirium: should non-pharmacological, multicomponent interventions be used? A systematic review and meta-analysis of the literature. Age Ageing. 2015 Mar;44(2):196-204. doi: 10.1093/ageing/afu173. Epub 2014 Nov 25. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25424450</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gentric A, Le Deun P, Estivin S. [Prevention of delirium in an acute geriatric care unit]. Rev Med Interne. 2007 Sep;28(9):589-93. Epub 2007 May 15. French.</citation>
    <PMID>17512095</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pisani MA, Murphy TE, Van Ness PH, Araujo KL, Inouye SK. Characteristics associated with delirium in older patients in a medical intensive care unit. Arch Intern Med. 2007 Aug 13-27;167(15):1629-34.</citation>
    <PMID>17698685</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Voyer P, McCusker J, Cole MG, Monette J, Champoux N, Vu M, Ciampi A, Sanche S, Richard S, de Raad M. Feasibility and acceptability of a delirium prevention program for cognitively impaired long term care residents: a participatory approach. J Am Med Dir Assoc. 2014 Jan;15(1):77.e1-9. doi: 10.1016/j.jamda.2013.08.013. Epub 2013 Oct 2.</citation>
    <PMID>24094898</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rockwood K. Making delirium prevention acceptable in nursing homes. J Am Med Dir Assoc. 2014 Jan;15(1):6-7. doi: 10.1016/j.jamda.2013.09.002. Epub 2013 Oct 8.</citation>
    <PMID>24113630</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Inouye SK, van Dyck CH, Alessi CA, Balkin S, Siegal AP, Horwitz RI. Clarifying confusion: the confusion assessment method. A new method for detection of delirium. Ann Intern Med. 1990 Dec 15;113(12):941-8.</citation>
    <PMID>2240918</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wei LA, Fearing MA, Sternberg EJ, Inouye SK. The Confusion Assessment Method: a systematic review of current usage. J Am Geriatr Soc. 2008 May;56(5):823-30. doi: 10.1111/j.1532-5415.2008.01674.x. Epub 2008 Apr 1. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18384586</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>McCusker J, Cole MG, Dendukuri N, Belzile E. The delirium index, a measure of the severity of delirium: new findings on reliability, validity, and responsiveness. J Am Geriatr Soc. 2004 Oct;52(10):1744-9.</citation>
    <PMID>15450055</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Allison PD (1995) Survival analysis using SAS: A practical guide. Cary, NC: SAS Institute. Inc.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Klein J. ea (2003) Survival Analysis (2nd ed.). New York: Springer.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Therneau TM, Grambsch PM (2000) Modeling survival data: extending the Cox model: Springer Science &amp; Business Media.</citation>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 20, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 22, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 24, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 18, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 18, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 19, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>McGill University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Machelle Wilchesky</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>delirium</keyword>
  <keyword>dementia</keyword>
  <keyword>long-term care</keyword>
  <keyword>cluster randomized trial</keyword>
  <keyword>nursing</keyword>
  <keyword>geriatrics</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Dementia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Delirium</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

