<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03719066</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>8114</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03719066</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Extended Dose Intervals With Oral Cholera Vaccine in Cameroon</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effect of Extended Dose Intervals on the Immune Response to Oral Cholera Vaccine in Cameroon</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Johns Hopkins Bloomberg School of Public Health</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Bill and Melinda Gates Foundation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Meilleur Accès aux Soins de Santé (M.A. Santé)</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Johns Hopkins Bloomberg School of Public Health</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The primary aim of this project is to determine changes in the vibriocidal geometric mean
      titers (GMT) in subjects who receive the second dose of oral cholera vaccine (OCV) at
      different intervals: 2 weeks, 6 months, or 11 months following the first dose of vaccine.
      Secondary aims include a) vibriocidal antibody response rates in subjects who receive OCV at
      2 weeks, 6 months, or 11 months following the first dose of vaccine, b) age specific serum
      vibriocidal GMTs following the second dose among participants given the second dose of OCV at
      intervals of 2 weeks, 6 months, or 11 months following the first dose of vaccine, c) GMT and
      antibody response rates of Immunoglobulin A (IgA) and Immunoglobulin G (IgG)
      anti-lipopolysaccharide (LPS) as measured by ELISA following the second dose among
      participants given the second dose of OCV at intervals of 2 weeks, 6 months, or 11 months
      following the first dose of vaccine. The hypothesis is that the vibriocidal GMT following the
      second dose, when given after 6 or 12 months will not be inferior to the response when the
      second dose is given according to the standard interval of two weeks.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is an open label, randomized, phase 2 clinical trial of the immunogenicity of killed
      oral cholera vaccine (OCV) when the vaccine is administered to participants of three age
      cohorts (1-4 years, 5-14 years, and &gt;14 years) and in three dose interval groups (DIGs). The
      subjects in each age cohort will be randomized to a DIG of 2 weeks (DIG-1), 6 months (DIG-2)
      or 11 months (DIG-3). A total of 180 subjects from Douala, Cameroon will be enrolled and
      these are equally divided between the different groups (20 per age/dose interval group). The
      OCV to be used in the trial is Shanchol.

      Blood samples will be collected before the first dose and at intervals following the first
      dose depending on the dosing interval group assigned. The serum (or plasma) will be tested
      for antibodies to cholera.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 23, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 31, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Subjects will be randomized to receive two doses of Shanchol oral cholera vaccine with dose intervals of either 2 weeks, 6 months or 11 months.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Vibriocidal titer</measure>
    <time_frame>two weeks after the second dose</time_frame>
    <description>Geometric Mean titre of the vibriocidal titre</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>ELISA titres</measure>
    <time_frame>two weeks after the second dose</time_frame>
    <description>IgG and IgA geometric mean titres against V cholerae LPS</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">181</enrollment>
  <condition>Adverse Reaction to Cholera Vaccine</condition>
  <condition>Cholera Vaccination Reaction</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>DIG 1 (dose interval group)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>This group will receive two doses of killed whole cell oral cholera vaccine. The second dose being administered two weeks after the first dose.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>DIG 2 (dose interval group)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>This group will receive two doses of killed whole cell oral cholera vaccine. The second dose being administered 6 months after the first dose.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>DIG 3 (dose interval group)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>This group will receive two doses of killed whole cell oral cholera vaccine. The second dose being administered 11 months after the first dose.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>killed whole cell oral cholera vaccine</intervention_name>
    <description>two week interval</description>
    <arm_group_label>DIG 1 (dose interval group)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>DIG 2 (dose interval group)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>DIG 3 (dose interval group)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Shanchol</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Age ≥1 year, stratified into different age groups

          2. Living in the Soboum Health Area or adjoining area

          3. Good health condition, without clinically significant medical history (by participant
             or guardian, in case of minor)

          4. Not pregnant for female subjects.

          5. Available to participate for the study duration, including all planned follow-up
             visits for up to 18 months from screening.

          6. Signed informed consent -

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Presence of a significant medical or psychiatric condition (Examples include:
             Diagnosis and treatment of tuberculosis (TB) or HIV; renal insufficiency; hepatic
             disease; oral or parenteral medication known to affect the immune function , such as
             corticosteroids, other immunosuppressant drugs; or behavioural or memory issues)

          2. Ever having received oral cholera vaccine.

          3. Receipt of an investigational product (within 30 days before vaccination).

          4. History of diarrhoea in 7 days prior to first dose of vaccine (defined as ≥3 unformed
             loose stools in 24 hours).

          5. History of chronic diarrhea (lasting for more than 2 weeks in the past 6 months)

          6. Current use of laxatives, antacids, or other agents to lower stomach acidity?

          7. Planning to become pregnant in the next 2 years
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>1 Year</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>David Sack, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Johns Hopkins Bloomberg School of Public Health</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>M.A. Sante</name>
      <address>
        <city>Douala</city>
        <country>Cameroon</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Cameroon</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 23, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 23, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 25, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 6, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 6, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">December 7, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>cholera</keyword>
  <keyword>oral cholera vaccine</keyword>
  <keyword>vibriocidal titer</keyword>
  <keyword>ELISA antibodies</keyword>
  <keyword>Adverse event following immunization</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cholera</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>We will publish the results of this study in a peer reviewed publication and will make the data available on request after the paper has been published.</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Clinical Study Report (CSR)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>When the manuscript is published.</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>Researchers will need to submit a request to the investigators detailing their plans for analysis.</ipd_access_criteria>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

