<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03714893</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Sheba-17-4754-AC-CTIL</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03714893</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Analysis of Physical, Physiological and Behavioral Data Collected From Sensors That Track the Mental Condition of Psychiatric Patients</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Analysis of Physical Physiological and Behavioral Data Collected From Sensors That Track the Mental Condition of Psychiatric Patients Who Are at Risk for Relapse and Who do Not Abide With Their Medication Treatment</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Sheba Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Sheba Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      An observational study that uses a digital system to collect physiological, physical and
      behavioral data using worn sensors on psychiatric patients suffering from schizophrenia,
      bipolar and schizoaffective disorders. The system will enable to analyze the data using a
      personal digital algorithm in order to detect changes in mental condition and or changes in
      adherence to medication treatment, and assist in identification of illegal drug usage.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      An observational study that uses a digital system to collect physiological, physical and
      behavioral data using worn sensors on psychiatric patients suffering from schizophrenia,
      bipolar and schizoaffective disorders. It is a known fact that patients suffering from these
      disorders are more prone to changes in their mental health condition. Sometimes this change
      is due to change in medical treatment(whether it was the doctor's decision or low adherence
      to medication treatment).The mental health condition influences physiological, physical and
      behavioral aspects which could be detected through the personal digital algorithm and could
      prevent psychiatric deterioration. For example, in a case of a person in a manic episode
      investigators would expect to find changes in the personal digital algorithm in physiological
      aspects(increased heart rate, elevated Heart Rate Variability), physical aspects such as
      increased number of steps per day, and behavioral aspects(increased hours spent outside of
      home, excessive activity). An early detection can help in the prevention of psychiatric
      deterioration in this case and help minimize the suffering caused to the patient and
      caregivers and perhaps assist in minimizing the need for hospitalization.

      The data will be collected using wrist watches. The sensors will collect the physiological
      data(Heart Rate Variability), physical data(number of steps per day) and the behavioral
      data(quality of sleep). This data will then be collected and analyzed through big data
      analysis.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">October 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Retrospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Detecting changes in the mental health condition of psychiatric patients</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>The wrist watch using sensors will collect physiological data(Heart Rate Variability), physical data (Steps per day) and behavioral data(Quality of sleep).The algorithm that exists in the watch analyzes the amount of steps, the sleep quality- total sleep versus movement and restful sleep, and the distance travelled.The data collected from the wrist watch will then be transferred to an app located on the participant's smartphone which will enable the investigators to collect and analyze the data using big data analysis.After collecting the data above,the investigators will look for a correlation between changes in the personal digital algorithm and changes in the mental health condition of psychiatric patients</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Detection of illegal drug usage</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Illegal drug usage can contribute to changes in the personal digital algorithm due to changes in physiological(Heart rate Variability) and physical data(Quality of Sleep) collected from the sensors of the wrist watch and analyzed through big data analysis. Early detection can help in minimizing deterioration of the mental health condition</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Psychiatric Disorders Mood</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sensor wrist watch</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will wear a sensor wrist watch which will collect data</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Adults ,18-75, who are currently hosipatlized in the psychiatric unit at Sheba Medical
        Center.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Psychiatric patients diagnosed with schizophrenia, bipolar, or schizoaffective
             disorder according to the DSM 5

          -  PANSS and CGI scores are 4 and above

          -  Participants must have the ability to informed consent

          -  Own a smartphone android 2.3 or IOS 2010 and above

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Violent or suicidal participant

          -  Terminal illness

          -  Dialysis treatment

          -  Participants who have a legal guardian

          -  Participants who do not own a personal smartphone
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <verification_date>October 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 8, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 19, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 22, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 22, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 22, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 24, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Sheba Medical Center</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Dr. Asaf Caspi</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Mental Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Problem Behavior</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Mood Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

