<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03714711</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Pro00100351</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03714711</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Pain Profile and Pain Medication Use After THA and TKA</brief_title>
  <official_title>Patient Pain and Opioid Use Profile After Total Hip and Total Knee Arthroplasty</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Duke University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Duke University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The over-prescription and overuse of opioid medications in the United States has recently
      been recognized as an epidemic. A new law in North Carolina (STOP Act) is aimed to limit
      opioid prescriptions following any surgical procedure including total hip (THA) and total
      knee arthroplasty (TKA). However, there is limited evidence regarding patient's pain and
      actual opioid consumption following THA and TKA that can be used by practitioners as guidance
      adapting to the new law. The purpose of this study is to investigate patient's pain and pain
      medication use in the perioperative period (0-6 weeks) following THA and TKA to establish a
      pain profile and thereby investigating risk factor for increased postoperative pain and
      opioid pain medication requirements. This study aims to stratify a predication model of
      postoperative pain and opioid medication requirement after THA and TKA to identify patients
      with a high propensity for pain, improve preoperative patient education on postoperative pain
      expectations, thereby helping practitioners implement new postoperative prescriptions limits
      for THA and TKA patient.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Number of subjects: Patient undergoing THA and TKA will be enrolled in this prospective
      study. Patients older than 18 years of age, with cell phones capable of text messaging, and
      who agree to participate in this study will be included. Patients who have their primary
      residence in Missouri will be excluded from this study due to the lack of a state wide
      narcotic prescription database in Missouri. Up to 240 patients will be enrolled to reach a
      minimum of 200 participants (100 THA, 100 TKA patients) with complete data from pre to 1 year
      postoperatively.

      Preoperative questionnaires: Patient will be required to complete a preoperative pain
      catastrophizing score, abrief pain inventory, EQ-5D, a hip disability and osteoarthritis
      outcome score (HOOS JR.) or knee injury and osteoarthritis outcome score (KOOS JR.) and
      aAbaseline pain level on a visual analog scale (0-10) will be recorded.

      Preoperative pain medication assessment: Preoperative controlled substance use will be
      assessed using the patient's state residence Controlled Substance Reporting System. Patient
      socioeconomic status, prior history of pain medication use, and history of drug abuse will be
      recorded.

      Patient preoperative pain sensitivity testing: Patients will then undergo pain algometer
      testing (FPK algometer, Wagner Instruments, Greenwich CT) to establish an objective baseline
      pain tolerance. There is no risk to the patient with algometer testing. Pressure algometer
      testing will be performed in a standard fashion. The probe is applied at a 90 degree angle to
      the skin at a constant rate of 10kPa/s to minimize the impact of the examiner's reaction time
      on recorded pain thresholds. The participant is instructed by the measurer to say &quot;stop&quot; when
      the sensation of pressure became the very first sensation of pain. There will be three spots
      to test patients, one for familiarity of the testing and the other 2 for data collection.
      This is initially performed once on ipsilateral the tibialis anterior as a &quot;warm up.&quot; Then 3
      measurements are taken on the operative medial epicondyle (for TKA) or ipsilateral lateral
      iliac crest (for THA) and averaged for the official score. Lastly, 3 measurements are also
      taken on the contralateral olecranon to measure systemic pain sensitivity. If the
      contralateral elbow has had prior surgery or active bursitis, the ipsilateral elbow will be
      used. Of important note, the algometer has a max force lock out of 100N to prevent any harm
      to the patient. In addition, we will capture dominant handgrip strength measured by the
      average of 3 attempts on a standard dynamometer.

      In-hospital and postoperative pain and medication assessment: Patient's pain scores on an
      analog scale will be recorded daily from the patient's electronic medical record (lowest,
      highest, median) while admitted to the hospital. Patient will be contacted daily via text
      message to report pain scores and pain medication use. Text messaging via cell phones has
      become very common in the US and has been shown to be efficacious in obtaining longitudinal
      research data, specifically in assessing pain scores. Patient will be contacted daily via
      text messaging (Mosio, Seattle, WA).Mosio is a two-way mobile messaging platform that deploys
      automated text messages to study subjects. Subjects reply to the questions bv text message
      which are sent and received through mosio.

      The participants will be asked the following questions by text messaging daily:

        1. What was the average pain level (0-10) in the past 24 hours?

        2. What was the highest level of satisfaction (0-10) with the total joint in the past 24
           hours?

        3. How many pain medication pills were taken in the past 24 hours?

      The responses by the patient are replied to and typed as a standard text message. The answers
      will be captured by mosio and transferred in the secure database. The study team has instant
      access to the data server via secured log in authentication. Study replies can be downloaded
      as excel spreadsheets for further analysis.

      At the standard of care 6-week and 1-year postoperative visit, participants will complete a
      Visual Analog Scale (VAS), PROMIS pain scale, EQ-5D and HOOS JR or KOOS JR questionnaire.
      Once questionnaires are completed this will conclude study participation.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">October 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Patient Pain level</measure>
    <time_frame>1 - 6 weeks on average</time_frame>
    <description>Change in Patients' pain level on visual analog scale from 0-10; 0 no pain, 10 worst pain imaginable</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in opioid consumption</measure>
    <time_frame>daily for 6 weeks after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Change in patient use of opioid pain medication</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in satisfaction level</measure>
    <time_frame>daily for 6 weeks after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Change in patient satisfaction with total joint replacement, scale 0-10; 0 no satisfaction, 10, highest satisfaction possible</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>EQ5D</measure>
    <time_frame>Once before surgery, up to 10 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>Health related quality of life; scale of 0-100, 0 worst health imaginable, 100 best health imaginable</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>EQ5D</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks postoperative</time_frame>
    <description>Health related quality of life; scale of 0-100, 0 worst health imaginable, 100 best health imaginable</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>EQ5D</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year postoperative</time_frame>
    <description>Health related quality of life; scale of 0-100, 0 worst health imaginable, 100 best health imaginable</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>hip disability and osteoarthritis outcome score (HOOS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Once before surgery, up to 10 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>Total hip replacement clinic outcome measure; scale from 0-100; 0 total hip disability, 100 perfect hip health</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>hip disability and osteoarthritis outcome score</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks postoperative</time_frame>
    <description>Total hip replacement clinic outcome measure; scale from 0-100; 0 total hip disability, 100 perfect hip health</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>hip disability and osteoarthritis outcome score</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year postoperative</time_frame>
    <description>Total hip replacement clinic outcome measure; scale from 0-100; 0 total hip disability, 100 perfect hip health</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>knee disability and osteoarthritis outcome score</measure>
    <time_frame>Once before surgery, up to 10 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>Total knee replacement clinic outcome measure; scale from 0-100; 0 total knee disability, 100 perfect knee health</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>knee disability and osteoarthritis outcome score</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks postoperative</time_frame>
    <description>Total knee replacement clinic outcome measure; scale from 0-100; 0 total knee disability, 100 perfect knee health</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>knee disability and osteoarthritis outcome score</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year postoperative</time_frame>
    <description>Total knee replacement clinic outcome measure; scale from 0-100; 0 total knee disability, 100 perfect knee health</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pain threshold</measure>
    <time_frame>Preoperative clinic visit, up to 10 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>Pressure algometer testing</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">200</enrollment>
  <condition>Pain, Postoperative</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Total hip arthroplasty</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patient who are scheduled to undergo total hip replacement.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Total knee arthroplasty</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patient who are scheduled to undergo total knee replacement.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>total hip arthroplasty</intervention_name>
    <description>Total hip replacement</description>
    <arm_group_label>Total hip arthroplasty</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>total knee arthroplasty</intervention_name>
    <description>Total knee replacement</description>
    <arm_group_label>Total knee arthroplasty</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients undergoing primary total hip or knee arthroplasty
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients older than 18 years of age undergoing primary total hip or total knee
             replacement

          -  Able to give consent to participate in the study

          -  Patients have a cell phone capable of text messaging

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients from states in the US without a narcotic prescription database (Missouri)

          -  Patients with previous joint surgery
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Thorsten Seyler, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Duke University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Thorsten Seyler, MD</last_name>
    <phone>668-4373</phone>
    <email>thorsten.seyler@duke.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Jennifer Friend, AS</last_name>
    <phone>668-4373</phone>
    <email>jennifer.friend@duke.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 24, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 16, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 22, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 10, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 10, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 14, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>total hip replacement</keyword>
  <keyword>total knee replacement</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pain, Postoperative</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

