<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03716596</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CISPD-2</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03716596</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>SBRT and Anti-programmed Cell Death Protein 1(Anti-PD-1) in Late Stage or Recurrent Pancreatic Cancer Patients</brief_title>
  <acronym>CISPD-2</acronym>
  <official_title>Study on the Safety and Therapeutic Effect of Stereotactic Body Radiotherapy and Anti-PD-1 Antibody in Late Stage or Recurrent Pancreatic Cancer Patients Who Failed in Second-line Chemotherapy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Second Affiliated Hospital, School of Medicine, Zhejiang University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Second Affiliated Hospital, School of Medicine, Zhejiang University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      When gemcitabine based chemo and fluorouracil based chemo regimes are failed in late-stage or
      recurrent pancreatic cancer patients, there is no alternative options. Anti-PD-1 antibody has
      became a promising anti-cancer drug. While it showed limited efficacy in pancreatic cancer.
      Stereotactic Body Radiotherapy has been a new method to locally treat metastatic cancer. This
      study is aimed to evaluate the safety and efficacy of the combination of SBRT and anti-PD-1
      antibody in late-stage or recurrent pancreatic caner who failed in second-line chemotherapy.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Pancreatic cancer is a kind of cancer with poor prognosis. Nowadays, recommended treatment
      for late-stage or recurrent pancreatic cancer patients are fluorouracil based chemotherapy
      (such as FOLFIRINOX) and gemcitabine based chemotherapy. When these two chemo regimes are
      failed, however, there is no alternative options. With the improvement of immune therapy,
      anti-PD-1 antibody has became a promising anti-cancer drug. While it showed limited efficacy
      in pancreatic cancer. Stereotactic Body Radiotherapy (SBRT) has been a new method to locally
      treat metastatic cancer. And previous studies showed that SBRT may enhance the efficacy of
      immunotherapy. So this study is amed to evaluate the safety and efficacy of the combination
      of SBRT and anti-PD-1 antibody in late-stage or recurrent pancreatic caner who failed in
      second-line chemotherapy.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 22, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 22, 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 22, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>overall survival</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to approximately 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>The percentage of people still alive for a given period of time after diagnosis</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Disease control rate</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to approximately 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of patients whose cancer doesn't progress after treatment</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Objective response rate</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to approximately 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of patients whose cancer shrinks or disappears after treatment</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression-free survival</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to approximately 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>The percentage of people does not get worse for a period of time after diagnosis</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>EORTC quality of life questionnaire (QLQ)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to approximately 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Assessed by the European Organization for Research and Treatment of Cancer Quality of Life</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Common Toxicity Criteria for Adverse Effects</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to approximately 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>According to Common Toxicity Criteria for Adverse Effects version 4</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Related tumor markers</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to approximately 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Serum level of related tumor markers (like carbohydrate antigen19-9, carcinoembryonic antigen and so on)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">36</enrollment>
  <condition>Pancreatic Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>SBRT and PD-1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Stereotactic body radiotherapy, radiation dose is 40-50 Gy in total. Intravenous drug of anti-PD-1 antibody, 200mg, once a time, every three weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Radiation</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>SBRT</intervention_name>
    <description>SBRT radiation dose is 40-50 Gy in total.</description>
    <arm_group_label>SBRT and PD-1</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Stereotactic Body Radiotherapy</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>anti-PD-1 antibody</intervention_name>
    <description>Intravenous drug of anti-PD-1 antibody, 200mg, once a time, every three weeks.</description>
    <arm_group_label>SBRT and PD-1</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>keytruda</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  1.≥18 years.

          -  2.Histopathology or cytology confirmed pancreatic cancer.

          -  3.Patients failed in second-line chemotherapy: patients have failed in
             gemcitabine-based chemotherapy and also failed in fluorouracil-based chemotherapy
             (like FOLFIRINOX), failed in combination of chemotherapy and radiotherapy; patients
             may have failed in immune therapy (including anti-PD-1 antibody).

          -  4. Eastern cooperative oncology group physical fitness score was 0~2.

          -  5. The main organs are functional and meet the following criteria (Routine blood tests
             were in accordance with the following criteria):

               1. White blood cell (WBC) ≥3.5 x 10^6 /L, neutrophil &gt;1.5 x10^9/L,

               2. platelet (PLT) ≥50 x10^9/L,

               3. hemoglobin (HB) ≥80 g/L,

               4. total bilirubin (TB) ≤1.5 x ULN (upper limit of normal value). 5）Alanine
                  transaminase (ALT) and aspartate aminotransferase (AST) ≤ 2 x ULN (upper limit of
                  normal value) (if there is liver metastasis, ≤ 5 x ULN).

             6) Serum creatinine (Scr) ≤ 1.5 x ULN 7) Albumin (ALB) ≥ 3 g/dL.

          -  6. Patients will be informed consent, and understand and are willing to cooperate with
             the trial and sign related documents.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  1. In the first 4 weeks before the start of the study, they took part in other drug
             clinical trials.

          -  2. Before the start of the study, they were diagnosed as immune deficiency diseases or
             need systemic steroid therapy.

          -  3. In the first 4 weeks before the start of the study, they took anti-tumor immune
             therapy; or didn't recovery from the adverse effects caused by the anti-tumor immune
             therapy.

          -  4. In the first 2 weeks before the start of the study, they took chemotherapy, small
             molecule targeting therapy, and radiotherapy; or didn't recovery from the adverse
             effects caused by these therapies.

          -  5. Has had active tuberculosis before.

          -  6. Has a history of malignant tumor, except for basal and skin squamous cell
             carcinoma, cervical carcinoma in situ and papillary thyroid carcinoma.

          -  7. Has central nervous system metastasis or meningeal metastasis.

          -  8. Has serious and uncontrollable internal diseases such as severe diabetes, severe
             hypertension, serious infection, congestive heart failure, ventricular fibrillation,
             coronary heart disease with obvious symptoms or myocardial infarction in the past 6
             months.

          -  9. Has blood precancerous diseases, such as myelodysplastic syndrome.

          -  10. Has clinically relevant or preexisting interstitial lung diseases, such as
             noncommunicable pneumonia or pulmonary fibrosis, or evidence of interstitial lung
             diseases on baseline chest CT scans or chest x-rays.

          -  11. Past or physical examinations have found diseases of the central nervous system,
             with the exception of those that have been adequately treated (such as primary brain
             tumors, uncontrolled seizures or strokes with standard medication).

          -  12. Has preexisting neuropathy at &gt; level 1 (NCI CTCAE).

          -  13. Allotransplantation requires immunosuppression therapy or other major
             immunosuppression therapy.

          -  14. Has a severe open wound, ulcer, or fracture.

          -  15. Systemic treatment is required for autoimmune diseases that have been active for
             the past 2 years.Alternative therapies are not systemic treatments.

          -  16. Has a history of non-infectious pneumonia requiring steroid therapy or active
             pneumonia.Has interstitial lung disease.

          -  17. Patients with active infections require systemic treatment.

          -  18. Patients with active hepatitis b or c are not included in liver lesions SBRT.

          -  19. Has vaccinate within 30 days before treatment.Including intranasal influenza
             vaccines, except seasonal influenza vaccines

          -  20. Others: allergic history of similar drugs, pregnancy or lactation.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Tingbo Liang, MD PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>second affiliated hospital, Zhejiang University School of Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Yiwen Chen, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+8615088682641</phone>
    <email>cherry0705@zju.edu.cn</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Qi Zhang, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+8613858108798</phone>
    <email>zhangqi86@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The second affiliated hospital of Zhejiang University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hangzhou</city>
        <state>Zhejiang</state>
        <zip>310000</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Yiwen Chen, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+8615088682641</phone>
      <email>cherry0705@zju.edu.cn</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 21, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 21, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 23, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 4, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 4, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 6, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>pancreatic cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Second-line Chemotherapy resistant</keyword>
  <keyword>immune therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Stereotactic Body Radiotherapy</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pancreatic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Antibodies</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

