<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03714425</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2018P002392</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03714425</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Efficacy of the Quell Wearable Device for Fibromyalgia</brief_title>
  <official_title>Efficacy of the Quell Wearable Device for Fibromyalgia</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Brigham and Women's Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Brigham and Women's Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study is designed for patients with primary fibromyalgia (FM) pain. The overall aim of
      the study is to determine the effect of the high frequency Quell device to manage FM compared
      with a low frequency device. Investigators hypothesize that those assigned to using the high
      frequency Quell device will report reduced pain compared with those using the low frequency
      Quell device; with those using the high frequency device also showing more improvement in
      sleep, mood, and level of activity. Investigators also hypothesize that frequency of using
      the Quell (increased tolerability and adherence) will be correlated with greater reduction in
      pain.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The Quell is battery powered with rechargeable batteries and is strapped to participant's
      upper calf with a velcro band. It has been cleared by the FDA for safety. It is designed to
      improve fibromyalgia by the principles of transcutaneous electrical stimulation of nerves
      much like a traditional transcutaneous electrical nerve stimulator (TENS) unit. Investigators
      expect to enroll approximately 130 subjects in this study. Participants will be equally
      randomized to one of two experimental groups: High Frequency Quell group (N=65) or Low
      Frequency Quell group (N=65). This study hopes to find out whether low frequency or high
      frequency stimulation is most useful among persons with fibromyalgia.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 1, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 1, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>High frequency device vs. Low frequency device</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Patients' Global Impression of Change</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 6 weeks, 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>The questionnaire reflects a patient's belief about the efficacy of treatment. PGIC is a 7 point scale (1-7) depicting a patient's rating of overall improvement. Patients rate their change as &quot;very much improved,&quot; &quot;much improved,&quot; &quot;minimally improved,&quot; &quot;no change,&quot; &quot;minimally worse,&quot; &quot;much worse,&quot; or &quot;very much worse.&quot; Lower values represent a better outcome.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The Brief Pain Inventory</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 6 weeks, 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>The questionnaire assesses the severity of pain and its impact on functioning. Pain Severity Score is calculated by adding the scores for questions 2, 3, 4 and 5 and then dividing by 4. This gives a severity score out of 10 (0-10), where 0 means no pain and 10 is worst possible pain. Pain Interference Score is calculated by adding the scores for questions 8a, b, c, d, e, f and g and then dividing by 7. This gives an interference score out of 10 (0-10), where 0 means does not interfere and 10 means completely interferes. Lower values represent a better outcome.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Revised Fibromyalgia Impact Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 6 weeks, 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>The Revised Fibromyalgia Impact Questionnaire (FIQR) is an assessment and evaluation instrument developed to measure fibromyalgia (FM) patient status, progress and outcomes. The FIQR has 3 domains: function, overall impact and symptoms. FIQR has 21 individual questions and all questions are based on an 11-point numeric rating scale of 0 to 10, with 10 being 'worst'. The summed score for function (range 0 to 90) is divided by 3, the summed score for overall impact (range 0 to 20) is not changed, and the summed score for symptoms (range 0 to 100) is divided by 2. The total FIQR is the sum of the three domain scores. The total score of the FIQR ranges from 0 to 100. Lower values represent a better outcome.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pain Catastrophizing Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 6 weeks, 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>The Pain Catastrophizing Scale (PCS) instructions ask participants to reflect on past painful experiences, and to indicate the degree to which they experienced each of 13 thoughts or feelings when experiencing pain, on 5-point scales with the end points (0) not at all and (4) all the time. The total score is computed by summing responses to all 13 items (scale 0-4). PCS total scores range from 0 - 52. The higher the score, the more catastrophizing thoughts are present. Lower values represent a better outcome.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pain Disability Index</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 6 weeks, 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>This instrument is a simple and rapid instrument for measuring the impact that pain has on the ability of a person to participate in essential life activities. The total score is a sum of all 7 categories of life activity listed. A score of 0 means no disability at all, and a score of 10 signifies that all of the activities in which people would normally be involved have been totally disrupted or prevented by the pain. The total index ranges from 0 to 70. The higher the index the greater the person's disability due to pain. Lower values represent a better outcome.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 6 weeks, 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>The Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale (HADS) was developed to assess depression and anxiety in patients. Responses are rated on a scale from 0 to 3, with higher scores indicating higher severity. The ratings of the 14 items are summed to yield a total score (0 to 42), or for each subscale separately (0 to 21). 0 to 7 for normal or no anxiety/depression, 8 to 10 for mild, 11 to 14 for moderate, and 12 to 21 for severe anxiety/depression. Lower values represent a better outcome.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Satisfaction assessed by NRS (numerical rating scale)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 6 weeks, 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>This is a 16-item satisfaction questionnaire designed to investigate the perceived benefit of the device. 12 items are rated on a 0 to 10 scale (e.g., not at all helpful to very helpful) and 4 items are short answers. The questionnaire assesses different aspects of the device including helpfulness, bothersomeness, ease of use, how often participants use the device, and whether the users are willing to use the device in the future. The total score ranges from 0 to 120, where higher value means high satisfaction level about the device and study. Higher values represent a better outcome.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">130</enrollment>
  <condition>Fibromyalgia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>High frequency device</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects will use high frequency Quell devices.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Low frequency device</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Sham Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects will use low frequency Quell devices.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Quell</intervention_name>
    <description>Quell is a Transcutaneous Electrical Nerve Stimulator Device (TENS). The device will use nerve stimulation to treat chronic pain by sending signals to the brain that cause it to release natural opioids.</description>
    <arm_group_label>High frequency device</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Low frequency device</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. have chronic pain related to FM for &gt; 3 months' duration

          2. average 4 or greater on a pain intensity scale of 0 to 10

          3. are able to speak and understand English

          4. have a smartphone (Android or iPhone)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. diagnosis of cancer or any other malignant disease

          2. acute osteomyelitis or acute bone disease

          3. present or past DSM-V diagnosis of schizophrenia, delusional disorder, psychotic
             disorder, or dissociative disorder that would be judged to interfere with study
             participation

          4. pregnancy

          5. any clinically unstable systemic illness judged to interfere with treatment

          6. a pain condition requiring urgent surgery

          7. an active substance use disorder, such as cocaine or IV heroin use (positive on the
             Mini International Neuropsychiatric Interview; M.I.N.I. v.5.0), that would interfere
             with study participation

          8. have an implanted cardiac pacemaker, defibrillator, or other implanted device
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Robert N. Jamison, Ph.D</last_name>
    <phone>617-732-9046</phone>
    <email>rjamison@bwh.harvard.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Brigham and Women's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chestnut Hill</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02467</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Robert N Jamison, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>617-732-9046</phone>
      <email>rjamison@bwh.harvard.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Samantha Curran, BS</last_name>
      <phone>617-732-9858</phone>
      <email>scurran9@partners.org</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 17, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 18, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 22, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 8, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 8, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 10, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Brigham and Women's Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Robert N. Jamison, PhD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor of Anaesthesia, Harvard Medical School</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Fibromyalgia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myofascial Pain Syndromes</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

