<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03719196</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>RED_101</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03719196</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Reading Glass on Livelihoods and Quality of Life in Rural Bangladesh</brief_title>
  <official_title>Assessment of the Impact of Reading Glasses on Livelihoods and Quality of Life in the Context of Rural Bangladesh</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Brac</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>VisionSpring</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Brac</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The issue of uncorrected Presbyopia is an emerging health and livelihoods problem in
      Bangladesh. Presbyopia is easily corrected with an appropriate pair of reading glasses.
      Non-governmental organizations and government agencies have been working in many emerging
      markets, including Bangladesh, to increase eyeglass coverage among low-income adults by
      introducing basic vision screening and the dispensing of reading glasses at the community
      level. While vision screening is typically considered a health intervention, the primary
      motivation of these organizations and government agencies is to correct blurry vision with
      the intention of improving adults' income earning potential.

      VisionSpring and BRAC (previously know as Bangladesh Rural Advancement Committee. Now it is
      know as BRAC-no full form used) are two such NGOs who are partnering to implement a &quot;Reading
      Glasses for Improved Livelihoods&quot; program. VisionSpring is a social enterprise with a mission
      to increase access to affordable eye care and glasses in low-income settings. BRAC is an
      international development organization dedicated to alleviating poverty by empowering the
      poor.

      VisionSpring and BRAC have initiated a Randomized Control Trial to assess the economic and
      social impact that reading glasses may have on individuals that earn less than $4 a day. The
      study hypothesizes that post-intervention, the adoption of reading glasses will increase
      productivity related to paid work and non-paid household activity, and will enhance the
      vision-related quality of life of adults with Presbyopia.

      This experimental trial is designed to test the aforementioned hypotheses. In March 2017 a
      census survey was conducted in 59 villages of adults aged ≥35 and ≤65 years old in order to
      identify individuals with uncorrected presbyopia who would be eligible for enrollment in the
      study intervention. Following household visual acuity screenings, study participants were
      selected for enrollment. Randomization was conducted at the household level. Based on the
      inclusion criteria, a total of 1086 random households were surveyed at the baseline.
      Following completion of the baseline survey, in August 2017 the treatment group was given
      reading glasses free-of-cost. The endline survey will be conducted in May 2018, eight months
      from the baseline. Although some income-related outcomes may take more time to manifest, it
      is anticipated that the wearing of glasses precipitates changes in a relatively short time
      frame. The control group will receive reading glasses at the conclusion of the endline
      survey.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      BRAC (previously know as Bangladesh Rural Advancement Committee. Now it is know as BRAC-no
      full form used) has conducted a study on the Assessment of the Impact of Reading Glasses on
      Livelihoods and Quality of Life in the Context of Rural Bangladesh in 2017 with financial and
      technical assistance from VisionSpring. The goal is to assess the impact of reading glasses
      on economic return and social angles for people in rural areas in Bangladesh.

      BRAC and VisionSpring have developed an experimental trial to test the effects of reading
      glasses. The study will utilize both pre and post-intervention data to identify the causal
      effects. A randomized control trial is considered to be the most rigorous method of
      determining whether a causal relationship exists between an intervention and outcome. This is
      a Randomized Control Trial (RCT) conducted at the household level.

      First, investigators selected 59 villages in Bangladesh where the BRAC/VisionSpring
      distribution of reading glasses has not been present. A census survey was carried out in the
      59 villages to identify those suffering from Presbyopia who were eligible for glasses.

      Second, participants were recruited through a household Presbyopia screening of individuals
      over 35 years old and less than 65 years old. Participants with chronic eye diseases that
      require regular and intensive treatment were excluded from the study.

      A structured questionnaire was used at the census survey where demographic information,
      income, and occupation were asked. Randomization was taken place after the census survey, and
      a study sample was selected based on the inclusion criteria of the study which are: (1) Over
      35 years of age, (2) Presbyopia positive, (3) Have never used reading glass, (4) Selective
      occupation (tailor, barber, self-employed artisan etc), (5) Willing to provide contact
      information and give informed consent.

      The study proposal defines two rounds of data collection to be conducted; baseline data
      collection was completed in August 2017 and follow-up data will be conducted in March 2018. A
      quantitative questionnaire was distributed at the baseline survey in order to understand the
      livelihoods and quality of life before the intervention began. Skilled interviewers were
      recruited for this study, and a three-day intensive training was held to reinforce the goals
      of the study. The training module was developed in Bangla to guide the interviewers in the
      field. Questions related to socio-demographic characteristics, economic status of the
      household (e.g. monthly income), the productivity of the respondent and quality were
      collected during baseline, and the same questionnaire will be used in the baseline survey.

      A multi-stage simple random sampling technique has been used in this study. The sample size
      of the study is pre-determined through a power calculation, the inclusion criteria of being a
      Presbyopic patient. Power calculations are prescribed in randomized control trials to provide
      useful information on the likelihood of being able to reject the null hypothesis of zero
      effect. By using existing information on pre-intervention outcomes, investigators are able to
      calculate the Minimum Detectable Effect Size (MDES) for a given study. The Power calculations
      indicated that investigators would need a total sample size of 900 individuals to detect an
      effect size of 0.186 with power = 0.80. In essence, through this study design, investigators
      should be able to detect causal changes from 18.6% and up in the key variable of interest.
      Investigators selected 900 households (450 participate in the program, 450 individuals as
      control)to detect relatively small but meaningful effect size with sufficient accuracy.
      Assuming 15% attrition rate, the total sample would be 1036 households. At the baseline, a
      total of 1086 random households have been surveyed (T=555; C=531).

      As the study is randomized at the individual level, there is a possibility to have the
      spillover effect. To minimize the spillover effect, one participant was selected from each
      household. There is a risk that members of the control group may see the benefits experienced
      by others in their community and buy a pair of reading glasses during the study. In an
      attempt to mitigate this risk, members of the control group were promised free glasses at the
      end of the study.

      Investigators will use a difference-in-difference analysis to estimate the impact of the
      reading glasses study based on monthly income, unemployment rate, the productivity of both
      paid and unpaid work, the rate of mistakes or accidents that occur at work, and ability to
      read, and ability to do detailed oriented work.

      To measure the impact of reading glasses on income, investigators will rely on respondent's
      economic indicators (monthly income, unemployment condition due to near vision problem,
      expenditure on food and household goods, etc.).

      With respect to measuring productivity outcomes, investigators will rely on indicators to
      calculate outputs per time period for both paid and unpaid work (number of hours needed to
      complete a task by occupation, how many hours worked, output production per time period.).

      To measure the quality of life, investigators will look at respondents perceptions of their
      facility with caregiving, household work, ability to (for those who are literate), mobile
      phone use, personal hygiene, and dependence.

      Using this data, the investigators plan to estimate the impact of reading glasses on both
      livelihoods and quality of life.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 30, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 30, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 30, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Income (Bangladeshi Taka)</measure>
    <time_frame>7 to 8 months.</time_frame>
    <description>Each participant's income data will be captured before and after the intervention by structured questionnaire (e.g: how much taka you earned in last 30 days?). The data will then be calculated into per hour income before and after the intervention (8 months period) and will be compared between intervention and control group participants to see the difference.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Secondary outcome 1: Difficulties in performing daily wise task:</measure>
    <time_frame>7 to 8 months.</time_frame>
    <description>• Likert scale (scale of 5) will be used to capture data on participants' Difficulties in performing daily wise tasks. Each question related to visual function is rated on a five-pointed scale consisting of (1) None; (2) Mild difficulty; (3) Moderate difficulty; (4) Severe difficulty; (5) Extreme difficulty.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of vision: Likert scale</measure>
    <time_frame>7 to 8 months.</time_frame>
    <description>• Self-reported quality of vision as per responses of the respondents will be measured. Measurement will be based on a five point Likert scale as (1) Very Good; (2) Good; (3) Moderate; (4) Bad; (5) Very Bad.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Discomfort in functioning social activities</measure>
    <time_frame>7 to 8 months.</time_frame>
    <description>• Social functioning such as feel ashamed or discomfort due to eye problem in the society will be measured. Measurement will be based on a five point Likert scale consisting of (1) Never; (2) rarely; (3) Sometimes; (4) Often; (5) Very often.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">1086</enrollment>
  <condition>Presbyopia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Reading glass provided</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Randomization took place after conducting the census survey. Participants were selected based on the inclusion criteria.
555 random households were surveyed at the baseline. These households have been given reading glasses free of cost.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Non-reading glass</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>A total of 1086 households were surveyed at the baseline survey. Among them, 555 households have been provided reading glasses. The 531 remaining households were not given reading glasses during the baseline survey. The endline survey will be conducted in May 2018. Upon completing the endline survey, the non-reading glasses group will be provided reading glasses.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Reading glass</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants from the experimental group have received reading glasses free of cost. Investigators hypothesize that a simple pair of eyeglasses could improve the lives of these people by enabling continued participation in the workforce, restoring productivity levels in both paid and unpaid work, and enhancing the ability to perform everyday tasks. Investigators also hypothesize that reading glasses will improve quality of life.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Reading glass provided</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Over 35 years of age

          -  Presbyopia positive

          -  Has never used reading glass or any other eyeglasses

          -  Selective occupations associated with the need for clear vision at near distances
             (tailor, barber, self-employed artisan, housewife, etc)

          -  Willing to provide contact information and give informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Less than 35 years of age

          -  Presbyopia negative

          -  Serious medical/mental and or eye condition, and

          -  Meets criteria but does not wish to participate
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>35 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Narayan Chandra Das</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Brac</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Kamrun Naher</last_name>
    <phone>+8801761303087</phone>
    <phone_ext>3727</phone_ext>
    <email>kamrunnaherkemy@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Altamas Pasha</last_name>
    <phone>+8801716494887</phone>
    <phone_ext>3727</phone_ext>
    <email>altamas.p@brac.net</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>BRAC RED</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dhaka</city>
        <zip>1212</zip>
        <country>Bangladesh</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Bangladesh</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 19, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 24, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 25, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 24, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 24, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 25, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Brac</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Farzana Sehrin</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Senior Research Associate</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Presbyopia</keyword>
  <keyword>Quality of life</keyword>
  <keyword>Reading glass</keyword>
  <keyword>Productivity</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Presbyopia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

