<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03711526</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>LZJ001</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03711526</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Prognostic Value of Preoperative 6-Minute Walk Test for Laparoscopic Gastrointestinal Surgery</brief_title>
  <official_title>Prognostic Value of Preoperative 6-Minute Walk Test in Patients Undergoing Laparoscopic Gastrointestinal Surgery: a Prospective Cohort Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Peking Union Medical College Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Peking Union Medical College Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      6-minute walk test (6MWT) is widely used in cardiopulmonary surgery as a prognostic marker.
      This prospective cohort study aims to find whether 6MWT will be a good prognostic factor for
      patients who will undergo laparoscopic gastrointestinal surgery.The investigators will enroll
      patients awaiting elective laparoscopic gastrointestinal surgery in this study. After
      informed consent was obtained, the participants will be evaluated through 6MWT. Preoperative
      assessment and conditions during operation will be recorded. The investigators will analyze
      the correlation between preoperative 6MWT's result and outcomes after laparoscopic
      gastrointestinal surgery.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a prospective observational cohort study, which focus on the prognostic value of
      6-minute walk test (6MWT) in patients who will undergo laparoscopic gastrointestinal surgery.

      Enhanced recovery after surgery (ERAS) is an optimized program which help patients accelerate
      recovery and improve outcomes by integrating evidence-based protocols and guidelines. With
      the rapid development of ERAS, the preoperative clinical data of patients are paid more and
      more attention to evaluate the risk of perioperative complications and choose an appropriate
      time for surgery. A better perioperative evaluation method will lead to lower morbidity and
      mortality rates of postoperative complications and shorter time of hospital stay. So, it is
      important to find an appropriate evaluation method to predict the outcomes of patients
      undergoing surgery.

      6MWT is a low-cost, easy to operate and well-tolerated test to evaluate exercise tolerance to
      predict cardiopulmonary function. It has widely used in cardiopulmonary surgery as a
      prognostic marker. Even though massive studies showed that decreased perioperative 6-minute
      walk distance (6MWD) related to postoperative complication in patients underwent cardiac or
      pulmonary surgery, there are only small numbers of studies with small number sizes presenting
      correlation of decreased 6MWD and postoperative complication in abdominal surgery. Even some
      studies of upper abdomen got the opposite result. Furthermore, the critical value for 6MWD is
      still controversial. Based on these conditions, this study was designed to investigate if
      6MWT cloud be used as an accurate assessment with the prognostic value in patients who will
      undergo laparoscopic gastrointestinal surgery to improve the ERAS program.

      The investigators decide to enroll 200 patients awaiting elective laparoscopic
      gastrointestinal surgery in this study at Peking Union Medical College Hospital. After
      informed consent was obtained, the patients will be comprehensively evaluated from
      demographic characteristics, complications of systems and organs, laboratory tests results,
      6MWT, metabolic equivalents (METs), psychological states assessed by hospital anxiety and
      depression scale. Outcomes will be assessed according to the Clavien-Dindo Classification of
      Surgical Complications. Operative name, operation date, operative method, blood loss,
      situation of blood transfusion, operation time, duration of anesthesia, whether return to ICU
      or not (treatment time and tubulization time), drainage flow of within 24 hours after surgery
      will be recorded. Other outcome measures include the mortality rate within 30 days after
      surgery, second operation without plan, rehospitalized rate without plan, postoperative
      hospitalization time, patient satisfaction.

      Descriptive analysis, univariate analysis, multivariate analysis and establishment of
      complication prediction model will be used to analyze the correlation between preoperative
      6MWD and outcomes.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 31, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Postoperative complications</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days</time_frame>
    <description>Postoperative complications includes postoperative wound infections, delayed union or nonunion, intraperitoneal abscesses, intestinal obstruction, anastomotic fistula, postoperative hemorrhage which need blood transfusion, pulmonary complications, cardiovascular complications, cerebrovascular complications, thrombotic events, acute liver failure or deterioration of liver function, acute renal failure or deterioration of renal function, urinary infection, gastrointestinal hemorrhage, postoperative delirium, et al.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mortality rate</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days</time_frame>
    <description>Postoperative death due to any reason</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Second operation without plan</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>During the same hospital stay, unplanned reoperations were performed for a variety of reasons.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Rehospitalized</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days</time_frame>
    <description>Rehospitalized without plan due to any reason</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient satisfaction</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days</time_frame>
    <description>telephone visits by a blinded doctor with same standardized questions were conducted.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">200</enrollment>
  <condition>Outcomes</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Inpatient from 18 y/o to 75 y/o going to have elective laparoscopic gastrointestinal
        surgery in Peking Union Medical College Hospital from January 2019 to December 2019.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Inpatient in Peking Union Medical College Hospital from January 2019 to December 2019

          2. From 18 y/o to 75 y/o

          3. Consent got from patients

          4. Decide to take the elective laparoscopic gastrointestinal surgery in Peking Union
             Medical College Hospital

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Refuse to take part in the study (due to any reason)

          2. ASA grade ≥ IV

          3. Unable to cooperate with the study (mental disorder, disturbance of consciousness,
             dysnoesia)

          4. Have developed unstable angina or myocardial infarction in the recent 6 months

          5. HR&gt;120 beats/min or SBP&gt;180mm/Hg or DBP&gt;100mmHg at resting state

          6. During acute episode of asthma

          7. Diseases cause severe limitation of walking, including severe lumbar spondylosis, knee
             osteoarthritis, lower extremity varicose veins, et al.

          8. Other conditions make patients can't cooperate with 6MWT
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>YUGUANG HUANG, MD.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Peking Union Medical College Hospital, Chinese Academy of Medicine Sciences</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>ZIJIA LIU, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>+86-18501155710</phone>
    <email>liu-zj02@126.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>YUGUANG HUANG, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>+86-13601121351</phone>
    <email>garypumch@163.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Peking Union Medical College Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Beijing</city>
        <state>Beijing</state>
        <zip>100730</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>ZIJIA LIU, M.D.</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 10, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 16, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 18, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 13, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 13, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 16, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

