<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03711266</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HUM00149877</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03711266</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Implementing PTSD Treatment in FQHCs for Michigan Medicaid Enrollees</brief_title>
  <acronym>PE-PC Pilot</acronym>
  <official_title>Michigan Mental Health Integration Partnership (MIP) - Implementing PTSD Treatment in FQHCs for Michigan Medicaid Enrollees</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Michigan</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Michigan Department of Health and Human Services</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Michigan</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this project is to expand access to trauma-focused treatment among Medicaid
      Enrollees with PTSD, thereby improving the quality of mental health services delivered to
      this population. Specifically, the project goals are to evaluate the delivery and
      sustainability of a brief trauma-focused treatment, Prolonged Exposure for Primary Care
      (PE-PC), an evidence-based intervention for PTSD, when delivered via telehealth to patients
      enrolled at CHCs in Michigan.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This project directly addresses the Michigan Department of Health and Human Services (MDHHS)
      Mental Health and Wellness commission priority to provide &quot;better access to high quality,
      coordinated and consistent service and care between agencies, service providers and across
      geographical boundaries.&quot;

      The project goals are to evaluate the delivery and sustainability of a brief trauma-focused
      treatment, Prolonged Exposure for Primary Care (PE-PC), an evidence-based intervention for
      PTSD, when delivered via telehealth to patients enrolled at CHCs in Michigan. CHCs serve
      680,000 Michigan residents across 260 delivery sites. Ninety-two percent of CHC patients have
      incomes below 200 percent of the federal poverty level. Approximately 16 percent of CHC
      patients are uninsured, and more than 53 percent rely on Medicaid for their insurance. Thus,
      providing PTSD treatment to CHC patients will improve care to Medicaid enrollees and promote
      Mental Health and Wellness commission priorities of developing a trauma informed system that
      includes implementation of evidence-based trauma-informed care.

      To address the high burden of PTSD in Medicaid enrollees in Michigan CHCs, we plan to deliver
      PE-PC to patients in CHCs. This treatment consists of four 30-minute sessions of in-vivo and
      narrative exposure, with content drawn from the PE model. Recently published efficacy data
      from a randomized controlled trial showed that PE-PC significantly reduced PTSD and
      depression symptoms as compared to usual primary care treatment. These changes were
      maintained at 6-month follow-up.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 1, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 31, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 31, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in PTSD symptoms (as measured by the PCL-5)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 4-months</time_frame>
    <description>The PCL-516 is a 20-item self-report measure designed to assess PTSD symptoms as defined by the DSM-5. Each item of the PCL-5 is scored on a five point scale ranging from 0 (&quot;not at all&quot;) to 4 (&quot;extremely&quot;). The PCL-5 has strong internal consistency, test-retest reliability, and convergent and discriminant validity.17,18 Scores ≥ 33 indicate a probable diagnosis of PTSD.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in depressive symptoms (as measured by the PHQ-9)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 4-months</time_frame>
    <description>The PHQ-9 is a 9-item self-report measure that assesses the presence and severity of depressive symptoms. Patients are asked to rate the presence of symptoms over the past 2 weeks on a 4-point likert scale ranging from 0-3 (not at all, several days, more than half the days, nearly every day). Total scores ranging from 5-9 indicate mild depression, 10-14 indicate moderate depression, 15-19 indicate moderately severe depression, and 20-27 indicate severe depression.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Recovery goals (measured by the Recovery Assessment Scale; RAS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 4-months</time_frame>
    <description>Recovery orientation will be measured using the Recovery Assessment Scale - Short Form (RAS-SF). This 20-item scale is a shorter version of the RAS and has four factors: personal confidence and hope, willingness to ask for help, reliance on others, and no domination by symptoms. The RAS-SF shows evidence for both convergent and discriminant validity when compared to quality of life, social support, and symptomatic scales.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Posttraumatic cognitions (measured by the Post-Traumatic Cognitions Inventory; PTCI)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 4-months</time_frame>
    <description>The PTCI is a 33-item scale, which is rated on a Likert-type scale ranging from 1 (totally disagree) to 7 (totally agree). Total score is the sum of items 1-33. The inventory also yields three subscales - negative cognitions about the self, negative cognitions about the world, and self-blame. To allow for the different numbers of statements making up each subscale, the scores are calculated by taking the total for the subscale and dividing it by the number of statements involved - giving an average score per statement for each subscale.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>PTSD</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>PE-PC</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Eligible participants who present to participating CHCs and screen positive for PTSD will be offered PE-PC via telepsychiatry.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>PE-PC</intervention_name>
    <description>PE-PC treatment will follow the PE-PC manual and patient workbook. Treatment content for PE-PC is drawn from the PE model and condensed so as to deliver the most efficacious components of PE. PE-PC consists of four, 30-minute appointments scheduled approximately once a week over 4-6 weeks</description>
    <arm_group_label>PE-PC</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. receive care at a Michigan CHC

          2. have a PCL-5 score ≥33

          3. have had psychotropic medication stability for at least 4 weeks

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. substantially cognitively impaired (according to the Mini-Cog)

          2. unable to agree to study procedures for any reason (including incompetency)

          3. at high risk of suicide

          4. currently engaged in a trauma-focused behavioral treatment (such as Prolonged Exposure
             or Cognitive Processing Therapy)

          5. unable to speak English
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Rebecca Sripada, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Michigan</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Rebecca Sripada, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>734-222-7432</phone>
    <email>rekaufma@med.umich.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Heather Walters, MS</last_name>
    <phone>734-845-3650</phone>
    <email>heawalte@med.umich.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Baldwin Family Health Care-Cadillac Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cadillac</city>
        <state>Michigan</state>
        <zip>49349</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Heather Walters, MS</last_name>
      <phone>734-845-3650</phone>
      <email>heawalte@med.umich.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Rebecca Sripada, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>734-222-7432</phone>
      <email>rekaufma@med.umich.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hamilton Community Health Network-Flint Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Flint</city>
        <state>Michigan</state>
        <zip>48503</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Heather Walters, MS</last_name>
      <phone>734-845-3650</phone>
      <email>heawalte@med.umich.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Rebecca Sripada, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>734-222-7432</phone>
      <email>rekaufma@med.umich.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 12, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 17, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 18, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 4, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 4, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 5, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Michigan</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Rebecca Sripada</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

