<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03712306</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>678732</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03712306</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The (Cost)Effectiveness of Increasing Protein Intake on Physical Funtioning in Older Adults</brief_title>
  <official_title>The (Cost) Effectiveness of Increasing Daily Protein Intake to 1.2 Gram Per Kilo Body Weight on Physical Functioning in Community-dwelling Older Adults With a Habitual Daily Protein Intake &lt; 1.0 Gram Per Kilo Body Weight</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>VU University of Amsterdam</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Helsinki</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>VU University Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>VU University of Amsterdam</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      In this RCT with the duration of 6 months among 264 community-dwelling older adults (65+
      years) with habitual low protein intake, the investigators will examine the long term (cost)
      effectiveness of increasing daily protein intake to at least 1.2 gram/kg of adjusted body
      weight on physical functioning in older adults with low protein intake.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      In this RCT with the duration of 6 months the investigators will examine the long term (cost)
      effectiveness of increasing protein intake to at least 1.2 g/kg adjusted body weight/d on
      physical functioning in older adults with habitual low protein intake. Additionally, the
      investigators will examine the combined effect of increasing protein intake to at least 1.2
      g/kg adjusted body weight/d and consuming protein in close proximity with regular physical
      activity on physical functioning in older adults with habitual low protein intake.

      Three sub-studies will be conducted, of which the main objectives are to:

        1. Examine the effect of persuasive technology on adherence to consumption of protein rich
           food products in order to increase protein intake to at least 1.2 g/kg adjusted body
           weight/d, and to the combination of increasing protein intake to at least 1.2 g/kg
           adjusted body weight/d and consuming protein in close proximity with regular physical
           activity.

        2. Examine the effect of increasing protein intake to at least 1.2 g/kg adjusted body
           weight/d on faecal and oral microbiota composition in older adults with a habitual low
           protein intake.

        3. Examine the effects of increasing protein intake to at least 1.2 g/kg adjusted body
           weight/d on food-stimuli related central nervous system satiety and reward responses
           involved in the regulation of food intake, measured by functional magnetic resonance
           imaging in older adults with a habitual low protein intake.

           Study design: Randomized controlled trial with the duration of 6 months in two study
           sites: Amsterdam, the Netherlands and Helsinki, Finland. Stratification by gender and
           habitual protein intake (low protein (&gt;=0.9 g/kg BW/day - &lt;1.0 g/kg BW/day), very low
           protein (&lt;0.9 g/kg BW/day)).

           Study population: A total of 264 community-dwelling older adults aged ≥ 65 years with an
           habitual low protein intake (n=132 at each study site).

           Intervention: This RCT consists of three groups; two intervention groups and one control
           group. Intervention group 1 (N=44 at each study site) will receive personalized dietary
           advice aimed at increasing protein intake to at least 1.2 g/kg adjusted body weight/d
           without changing daily energy intake, by regular foods and by provided protein-enriched
           food products. Intervention group 2 (N=44 at each study site) receives personalized
           dietary advice similar to group 1 and also receives personalized advice to consume
           protein rich foods in close proximity of usual physical activity. All groups receive a
           standard brochure of the Netherlands or Finnish Nutrition Centre with general
           information about healthy eating habits. The control group (N=44 at each at each study
           site) receives no further intervention.

           Main study parameters/endpoints: The primary outcome of this study is change in walk
           time on the 400 meter walk test. Secondary outcomes are change in dietary intake
           (including macro- and micronutrients), malnutrition prevalence, physical performance,
           mobility limitations, muscle strength, body weight and body composition, frailty status,
           quality of life, and health care costs.

           Statistical analyses:

           The collected data at the two study sites will be pooled together.

           As a result of randomization at study baseline, we assume that groups are equal
           regarding demographical and socio-economic variables. If this is not the case, we will
           adjust for differences between groups at baseline. We will adjust for study site (the
           Netherlands, Finland) and baseline outcome values. We will present unadjusted and
           adjusted results.

           The main analyses will be based on intention-to-treat principles, but per-protocol
           analyses will also be conducted as a sensitivity analysis.

           Multiple Imputation (MI) using multivariate Imputation by Chained Equations (MICE) will
           be used to impute missing cost and effect data. For this, the missing values need to be
           missing at random.

           The (cost) effectiveness of two intervention groups will be examined against the control
           group on the primary outcome walk time on the 400 meter walk test. We will compare
           outcomes between the respective intervention groups and control group separately to
           determine whether the two interventions are effective (group 1 versus control group;
           group 2 versus control group).

           We will perform mixed model regression analyses adjusting for confounding variables at
           baseline and study site as cluster variable. We will not correct for multiple testing
           but look at the clinical relevance of the outcome.

           In addition, we will perform sensitivity analyses leaving out the participants who took
           part in the persuasive technology sub-study.

           **** Update June 2020 ****

           Deviation of the protocol

           Due to the worldwide spread of Covid-19, the original protocol of the PROMISS prevention
           trial has been changed for those participants who were still active in the study during
           the spread (March 16th - June 1st). In consultation with both Medical Ethical boards
           from Finland and the Netherlands, and PROMISS' ethical advisor, the following changes
           were applied:

           March 2020 * Starting from March 16 2020, the final follow-up measurement of 80
           participants (out of 276) was postponed until further notice.

           * Participants were informed that they would be invited for the final follow-up
           measurement when the country-specific governmental regulations allowed it.

           * Participants were requested to stick to their habitual diet (control group) or their
           intervention diet (both intervention groups).

           April 2020 * Final measurements were resumed (through interview by phone) except for the
           physical measurements.

           * Dietary intake was assessed in the week prior to the phone call measurement.

           * Self-reported body weight was added to the questionnaire.

           * The physical follow-up measurement was still postponed until further notice.

           May 2020

           * Data collection was continued by means of questionnaires during the phone call
           measurement in both Finland and the Netherlands.

           June 2020

             -  Starting from the beginning of June, the physical measurements at the clinic site
                were also resumed in both Finland and the Netherlands. Those with no health
                complaints potentially caused by the coronavirus were allowed to visit the clinic
                site.

             -  The data collection will finish by July 31, 2020.

           We will perform sensitivity analyses excluding those participants who were still active
           in the study during the spread and thus had their physical follow-up measurement +/- 8
           months after the baseline assessment (instead of 6 months).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 11, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 10, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 31, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Participants will be randomized intro one of the three study groups.
Stratification by gender and habitual protein intake (low protein (&gt;=0.9 g/kg aBW/day - &lt;1.0 g/kg aBW/day), very low protein (&lt;0.9 g/kg aBW/day)), since we expect a different intervention effect for participants with a very low baseline habitual protein intake (&lt; 0.9 g/kg aBW/d) compared to participants with a low baseline habitual protein intake (≥ 0.9 g/kg aBW/d), and because of potential differences in how women and men respond to the intervention.
In case couples participate, we will make sure they will be allocated to the same intervention group. This will ensure no interference between intervention groups. We will randomly select whether the randomization for the intervention group is based on the men or the women.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>6-month change in walk time on a 400 meter walk test</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Change in walk time on a 400 meter walk test</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Dietary intake assesed by three 24-hour recalls</measure>
    <time_frame>3 and 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>A 24-hour recall is a structured interview intended to capture detailed information about all foods and beverages consumed by the participant in the past 24 hours. Changes in dietary intake (based on data of the 24-hour recalls) enables to investigate compliance; i.e. higher protein intake indicates higher compliance.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Malnutrition incidence</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>BMI&lt;22 kg/m2 and unintentional weight loss &gt;5% over 6 months</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>6-months change in Physical performance assessed by the Short Physical Performance Battery (SPPB)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>SPPB consists of three tests: repeated chair stands test, 4 meter walk test, and tandem stand test. The total score ranges from 0-12. A higher score indicates better physical functioning.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>3, and 6-moths self-reported mobility limitations (questionnaire)</measure>
    <time_frame>3 and 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Mobility limitations will be assessed by means of a questionnaire; &quot;Because of your health, how much difficulty do you have walking 400 meter?&quot; and &quot;Because of your health, how much difficulty do you have climbing one flight of stairs?&quot; Participants responded using a five level Likert scale: 'No difficulty', 'a little difficulty', 'some difficulty', 'a lot of difficulty', and 'unable to do the activity'.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>6-month change in hand grip strength</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Hand grip strength measured by a hand held dynamometer</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>6-month change in leg strength</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Upper leg strength measured by a measurement chair</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>3, and 6-month change in body weight</measure>
    <time_frame>3 and 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Body weight (kg) will be measured to the nearest 0,1 kg using a calibrated scale.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Body height</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Body height (cm) will be measured to the nearest 0.1 cm using a stadiometer.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>3, and 6-month change in body mass index (BMI)</measure>
    <time_frame>3 and 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Based on measured weight (measured at baseline and after 6 months) and height (measured at baseline) BMI will be calculated as body weight (kg) divided by height (m) squared.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>6-month change in body composition</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Body composition (fat-free mass, skeletal muscle mass and fat mass) will be assessed from bioelectrical impedance using body resistance, reactance, impedance and phase angle. In the Dutch sample only, fat-free mass and fat mass will be directly measured by using densitometry (BODPOD).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Frailty assessed by the Fried Frailty Index</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Frailty will be determined using the 5 criteria of the Fried Frailty Index:
Self-reported unintentional weight loss: &gt;4 kg in past 6 months.
Self-reported exhaustion. Based on two self-reported questions from the Center for Epidemiologic Studies Depression scale on exhaustion in the past week at baseline and follow-up: &quot;I felt that everything I did was an effort&quot; and &quot;I could not get going&quot;. Scores ranges from 1 'not at all' to 4 'most of the time'. A score of 3 or 4 on either question indicates exhaustion.
Weakness: grip strength in the lowest 20% of the study population, adjusted for gender and BMI.
Slow walking speed: walk time on the 400 meter walk test in the slowest 20% of the study population, adjusted for gender and height.
Low physical activity: Kilocalories expended/wk based on accelerometer data in the lowest quintile of physical activity for each gender.
Outcome:
No components:robust
1 or 2 components:intermediate/prefrail 3 or more components:frail</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>3, and 6-moths self perceived quality of life</measure>
    <time_frame>3 and 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Quality of life measured using the EuroQol-5D instrument. The EuroQol 5D consists of five questions on a Likert scale (mobility, self-care, usual activities, pain/discomfort and anxiety/depression). Answer categories range from (1) 'no problems' to (5) 'unable to'. An additional thermometer for experienced health is scored on a Visual Analogue scale (VAS), ranging from 0-100. The exact point where the line crosses the VAS is the VAS score. The scores are converted to an index value, which facilitates the calculation of quality-adjusted life years (QALYs) that is used to calculate the cost-effectiveness of the study.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>3, and 6-moths health care costs assessed by questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>3 and 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>To measure health care costs the investigators will use a modified version of the Resource Utilization in Dementia Questionnaire WIMO. This questionnaire contains questions on hospital admissions, prescribed medicine use, care from health professionals, and use of other health care services in the past three months. These are the domains that the investigators might expect changes in due to the intervention.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Effectiveness of persuasive technology sub-study on protein intake</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Examine the effect of persuasive technology on adherence to increasing protein intake. A subsample of the Dutch participants will receive a food storage box that can measure which protein rich food products are taken out and a small-size screen (tablet) that provides reminders and nudges. The investigators will test if there are differences in adherence to the interventions between participants who took part in this sub-study and participants who did not.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Microbiota sub-study</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>The effect of increasing protein intake to at least 1.2 g/kg body weight/d on faecal and oral microbiota composition</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Effect of protein intake on satiety and reward responses measured by functional magnetic resonance imaging</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>To examine the effects of increasing protein intake on food-stimuli related central nervous system satiety and reward responses involved in the regulation of food intake, measured by functional magnetic resonance imaging.
BOLD fMRI will be used to measure neuronal activity in CNS satiety and reward circuits (including striatum, amygdala, orbitofrontal cortex, insula) in response to visual food stimuli (pictures of food items) and to the actual consumption of food (chocolate milk).</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">276</enrollment>
  <condition>Protein-Energy Malnutrition</condition>
  <condition>Physical Disability</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>No intervention. Participants will only receive a brochure on general healthy eating habits.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Dietary advice</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Personalized nutritional advice from a registered dietician or nutritionist aimed at increasing protein intake to at least 1.2 g/kg adjusted body weight/d, through intake of regular protein rich food products and provided protein-enriched food products.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Dietary advice and advice on timing</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Personalized nutritional advice from a registered dietician or nutritionist aimed at increasing protein intake to at least 1.2 g/kg adjusted body weight/d, through intake of regular protein rich food products and provided protein-enriched food products, as well as advice regarding the consumption of protein rich food products in close proximity of usual physical activity.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Dietary advice</intervention_name>
    <description>Dietary advice to increase protein intake to at least 1.2 g/kg adjusted body weight/d</description>
    <arm_group_label>Dietary advice</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Dietary advice and advice on timing</intervention_name>
    <description>Dietary advice to increase protein intake to at least 1.2 g/kg adjusted body weight/d plus advice on consuming protein in close proximity of usual physical activity</description>
    <arm_group_label>Dietary advice and advice on timing</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion criteria:

          -  Age ≥ 65 years;

          -  Community-dwelling;

          -  Lower protein intake defined as both a probability score above a certain cutoff on the
             protein screener (www.proteinscreener.nl) as well as based on actual protein intake
             assessed by 24-hour recalls. The protein screener was developed and validated using an
             extended FFQ among Dutch older adults. The cutoff will be chosen based on results of
             different studies in which the investigators compare the probability scores of the
             protein screener with protein intake as measured with food diaries and/or dietary
             recalls. The investigators will then choose the probability score that is most closely
             associated with a protein intake &lt; 1.0 g/kg adjusted body weight/day. This probably
             score reflects older adults with a higher probability on a protein intake &lt; 1.0 g/kg
             adjusted body weight/d than a general sample of older adults;

          -  Able to eat independently;

          -  Willing to eat our provided protein-enriched food products and change food habits;

          -  Able to speak, write and read the Dutch language;

          -  Able to walk 400 meter, with or without the help of a walking cane (self-reported).

        Exclusion criteria:

          -  Bedridden or wheelchair bound;

          -  Individuals who do not go outside;

          -  Individuals with bad hearing (who cannot hear without a hearing aid);

          -  Diagnosed with diabetes mellitus type I;

          -  Diagnosed with diabetes mellitus type 2 and starting with insulin;

          -  Diagnosed with severe kidney disease;

          -  Diagnosed with Parkinson's disease;

          -  Current treatment of cancer (with the exception of basal cell carcinoma);

          -  BMI &lt; 18.5 kg/m2 (self-reported, and assessed at study baseline);

          -  Overweight, defined as BMI &gt; 32.0 kg/m2 (self-reported, and assessed at study
             baseline);

          -  Vegan;

          -  Severe allergies to certain food products (such as peanuts, gluten);

          -  Alcohol abuse past 6 months (AUDIT-C ≥ 2);

          -  Diagnosed with an eating disorder (self-reported);

          -  Current participation to supervised behavioral or lifestyle intervention that
             intervenes with PROMISS intervention;

          -  Planning to move out of the study area in the next 6 months;

          -  Actively trying to lose or gain weight;

          -  Heart problems (heart attack, angioplasty, heart surgery, stroke or other serious
             heart disease)

          -  Not able to complete the 400 meter walk test (self-reported, and assessed at study
             baseline).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>65 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Marjolein Visser, Prof., PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>VU University of Amsterdam</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Helsinki</name>
      <address>
        <city>Helsinki</city>
        <country>Finland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Vrije Universiteit Amsterdam</name>
      <address>
        <city>Amsterdam</city>
        <state>Noord Holland</state>
        <zip>1081 HV</zip>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Finland</country>
    <country>Netherlands</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 2, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 16, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 19, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 19, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 19, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 22, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>VU University of Amsterdam</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Ilse Reinders</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Malnutrition</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Protein-Energy Malnutrition</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

