<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03717883</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>16-2984</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>5R35GM122576-02</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03717883</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>ADPKD Alterations in Hepatic Transporter Function</brief_title>
  <official_title>Endogenous Molecule Profiling in Subjects With Autosomal Dominant Polycystic Kidney Disease (ADPKD)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of General Medical Sciences (NIGMS)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a single center, comparative cohort study to investigate alterations in hepatic
      transporter function in subjects with autosomal dominant polycystic kidney disease (ADPKD)
      compared to healthy subjects and subjects with non-ADPKD renal disease. Eligible subjects
      will be 18-65 years of age and of any race/ethnicity and gender.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      ADPKD is a relatively common genetic disease affecting about 1 out of every 1000 people
      worldwide. Progression of ADPKD is characterized by the proliferation of fluid-filled kidney
      cysts. Development of these cysts is progressive and can lead to end-stage renal disease and
      ultimately, renal failure in many patients. The most common extra-renal complication of ADPKD
      is the formation of liver cysts, which can vary from minor to extensive. Hepatic cysts can
      develop from medium-sized bile ducts and complications (i.e., cyst rupture, infection,
      obstruction of bile ducts, and compromised portal venous flow) can arise from increasing
      cystic burden. Previous studies have shown that elevated levels of endogenous molecules such
      as bile acids in ADPKD may indicate altered transporter function. Other endogenous molecules
      such as coproporphyrin (CP) I and III may be used as probes to assess hepatic transporter
      function.

      The objective of this study is to investigate and quantify ADPKD-associated alterations in
      endogenous molecule profiles (e.g., bile acids, CP) relative to subjects with non-ADPKD renal
      disease and healthy individuals, and to investigate specific hepatic transporter
      polymorphisms that may be related to the alterations. This is important because subjects with
      ADPKD may be predisposed to adverse reactions associated with some medications that require
      hepatic transporters for excretion.

      Potential study participants will be pre-screened over the phone and then scheduled for a
      2-hour study visit. All urine samples within the 2-hour interval will be collected from all
      participants along with clinical, physical and questionnaire data. Fasting blood samples will
      be collected at time 0 and 120 min.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 17, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">January 29, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">January 29, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Other</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference in serum coproporphyrin I and III concentrations</measure>
    <time_frame>2 hours</time_frame>
    <description>nmol</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference in serum and urine bile acid profiles</measure>
    <time_frame>2 hours</time_frame>
    <description>nmol</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference in renal clearance of coproporphyrin I and III</measure>
    <time_frame>2 hours</time_frame>
    <description>mL/min</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">24</enrollment>
  <condition>ADPKD</condition>
  <condition>Autosomal Dominant Polycystic Kidney Disease</condition>
  <condition>Renal Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Healthy subjects</arm_group_label>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Subjects with ADPKD</arm_group_label>
  </arm_group>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Blood samples used for potential studies will not be labeled with personal identifiers and
      will be stored for up to 10 years.
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Healthy vs. ADPKD vs. non-ADPKD renal disease subjects
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria (all subjects):

          -  Provide signed and dated informed consent

          -  Willing to comply with all study procedures and be available for the duration of the
             study

          -  Male or female, aged 18 to 65

          -  Negative quantitative human chorionic gonadotropin (hCG) blood test (for women of
             child-bearing age only)

        For healthy subjects:

          -  Normal liver functions tests (LFTs) as defined by the University of North Carolina
             (UNC) hospital laboratory reference range [aspartate aminotransferase (AST)14-38 U/L,
             alanine aminotransferase (ALT) 15-48 U/L, alkaline phosphatase 38-126 U/L]

          -  Normal clinical laboratory results including kidney function (serum creatinine) and
             lipid panel as reviewed by the study physician

        For subjects with ADPKD:

          -  Man or woman between the ages of 18 and 65 with documented ADPKD

        For subjects with non-ADPKD renal disease:

          -  Man or woman between the ages of 18 and 65 with documented non-ADPKD renal disease as
             determined by the study physician

        Exclusion Criteria:

        All Participants:

          -  Donation of blood within the last 30 days

          -  Diagnosis of human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) and/or untreated hepatitis C virus
             (HCV)

          -  History of significant alcohol abuse and/or illicit drug use

          -  More than 1 glass of wine or 2 beers (or equivalent in % alcohol) per day during the
             48 hours prior to study and/or screening visit

          -  Inability to fast for 8 hours prior to study and screening sample collection

          -  Women who are pregnant, trying to become pregnant, or breastfeeding

          -  Current or recent (within 30 days) use of bile acid sequestrants, bile acid
             derivatives (i.e. ursodiol) or fibric acid derivatives

          -  History of diabetes or taking blood glucose lowering treatments

          -  Radiologic imaging consistent with cirrhosis and portal hypertension

          -  Evidence of decompensated liver disease defined as any of the following: serum albumin
             &lt;3.2 g/dL, total bilirubin &gt; 1.5 mg/dL, or prothrombin time (PT)/international
             normalized ratio (INR) &gt; 1.3 times normal at screening, or history or presence of
             ascites, encephalopathy, or bleeding from esophageal varices

          -  Estimated glomerular filtration rate (GFR)&lt; 15 mL/min per 1.73 m2, or on dialysis, at
             screening

          -  Subjects with a condition requiring systemic treatment with either corticosteroids (&gt;
             10 mg daily prednisone equivalent) or other immunosuppressive medications (including
             inhaled) within 14 days of study visit. Corticosteroids with minimal systemic
             absorption (for example topical) and adrenal replacement steroid doses ≤ 10 mg daily
             prednisone equivalent, are permitted in the absence of active autoimmune disease
             provided the dose has been stable for ≥4 weeks and is not expected to change during
             the course of the study.

          -  Primary, secondary or extra-hepatic malignancy

          -  BMI &gt; 35 kg/m2 at screening

          -  Inability or unwillingness to give informed consent or abide by the study protocol

          -  History or other evidence of illness, any gastrointestinal surgery (e.g., gall bladder
             removal), or any other conditions or drug therapies that would make the patient, in
             the opinion of the investigator, unsuitable for the study (such as poorly controlled
             psychiatric disease, coronary artery disease, gall bladder disease, active
             gastrointestinal conditions or taking drugs known to interfere with bile acid
             synthesis or metabolism or the metabolism/transport of other drugs)

        Healthy Subjects:

          -  Taking concomitant medications, both prescription and non-prescription (including
             herbal products and over-the-counter medications), other than oral contraceptives and
             multivitamins (women stabilized on hormonal methods of birth control will be allowed
             to participate)

          -  History or other evidence of liver, gall bladder, or intestinal disease in the opinion
             of the study investigators

          -  BMI &gt; 35 kg/m2 at screening.

        Subjects with non-ADPKD renal disease:

          -  ADPKD

          -  Proteinuria of ≥3 grams per day of protein into the urine; or on a single spot urine
             collection, the presence of ≥2 grams of protein per gram of urine creatinine (i.e.,
             excluding patients with nephrotic-range proteinuria)

          -  Diabetic nephropathy patients
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Vimal Derebail, MD, MPH</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Kim Brouwer, PharmD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of North Carolina</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chapel Hill</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27713</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Igarashi P, Somlo S. Genetics and pathogenesis of polycystic kidney disease. J Am Soc Nephrol. 2002 Sep;13(9):2384-98. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>12191984</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Boucher C, Sandford R. Autosomal dominant polycystic kidney disease (ADPKD, MIM 173900, PKD1 and PKD2 genes, protein products known as polycystin-1 and polycystin-2). Eur J Hum Genet. 2004 May;12(5):347-54. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>14872199</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cnossen WR, Drenth JP. Polycystic liver disease: an overview of pathogenesis, clinical manifestations and management. Orphanet J Rare Dis. 2014 May 1;9:69. doi: 10.1186/1750-1172-9-69. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24886261</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Salam M, Keeffe EB. Liver cysts associated with polycystic kidney disease: role of Tc-99m hepatobiliary imaging. Clin Nucl Med. 1989 Nov;14(11):803-7.</citation>
    <PMID>2598550</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hofmann AF. The continuing importance of bile acids in liver and intestinal disease. Arch Intern Med. 1999 Dec 13-27;159(22):2647-58. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>10597755</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zollner G, Fickert P, Silbert D, Fuchsbichler A, Marschall HU, Zatloukal K, Denk H, Trauner M. Adaptive changes in hepatobiliary transporter expression in primary biliary cirrhosis. J Hepatol. 2003 Jun;38(6):717-27.</citation>
    <PMID>12763363</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kullak-Ublick GA, Stieger B, Meier PJ. Enterohepatic bile salt transporters in normal physiology and liver disease. Gastroenterology. 2004 Jan;126(1):322-42. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>14699511</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Munoz-Garrido P, Marin JJ, Perugorria MJ, Urribarri AD, Erice O, Sáez E, Úriz M, Sarvide S, Portu A, Concepcion AR, Romero MR, Monte MJ, Santos-Laso Á, Hijona E, Jimenez-Agüero R, Marzioni M, Beuers U, Masyuk TV, LaRusso NF, Prieto J, Bujanda L, Drenth JP, Banales JM. Ursodeoxycholic acid inhibits hepatic cystogenesis in experimental models of polycystic liver disease. J Hepatol. 2015 Oct;63(4):952-61. doi: 10.1016/j.jhep.2015.05.023. Epub 2015 Jun 1.</citation>
    <PMID>26044126</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shen H, Dai J, Liu T, Cheng Y, Chen W, Freeden C, Zhang Y, Humphreys WG, Marathe P, Lai Y. Coproporphyrins I and III as Functional Markers of OATP1B Activity: In Vitro and In Vivo Evaluation in Preclinical Species. J Pharmacol Exp Ther. 2016 May;357(2):382-93. doi: 10.1124/jpet.116.232066. Epub 2016 Feb 23.</citation>
    <PMID>26907622</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gilibili RR, Chatterjee S, Bagul P, Mosure KW, Murali BV, Mariappan TT, Mandlekar S, Lai Y. Coproporphyrin-I: A Fluorescent, Endogenous Optimal Probe Substrate for ABCC2 (MRP2) Suitable for Vesicle-Based MRP2 Inhibition Assay. Drug Metab Dispos. 2017 Jun;45(6):604-611. doi: 10.1124/dmd.116.074740. Epub 2017 Mar 21.</citation>
    <PMID>28325716</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Devuyst O, Chapman AB, Gansevoort RT, Higashihara E, Perrone RD, Torres VE, Blais JD, Zhou W, Ouyang J, Czerwiec FS. Urine Osmolality, Response to Tolvaptan, and Outcome in Autosomal Dominant Polycystic Kidney Disease: Results from the TEMPO 3:4 Trial. J Am Soc Nephrol. 2017 May;28(5):1592-1602. doi: 10.1681/ASN.2016040448. Epub 2016 Dec 5.</citation>
    <PMID>27920153</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Watkins PB, Lewis JH, Kaplowitz N, Alpers DH, Blais JD, Smotzer DM, Krasa H, Ouyang J, Torres VE, Czerwiec FS, Zimmer CA. Clinical Pattern of Tolvaptan-Associated Liver Injury in Subjects with Autosomal Dominant Polycystic Kidney Disease: Analysis of Clinical Trials Database. Drug Saf. 2015 Nov;38(11):1103-13. doi: 10.1007/s40264-015-0327-3.</citation>
    <PMID>26188764</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lai Y, Mandlekar S, Shen H, Holenarsipur VK, Langish R, Rajanna P, Murugesan S, Gaud N, Selvam S, Date O, Cheng Y, Shipkova P, Dai J, Humphreys WG, Marathe P. Coproporphyrins in Plasma and Urine Can Be Appropriate Clinical Biomarkers to Recapitulate Drug-Drug Interactions Mediated by Organic Anion Transporting Polypeptide Inhibition. J Pharmacol Exp Ther. 2016 Sep;358(3):397-404. doi: 10.1124/jpet.116.234914. Epub 2016 Jun 17.</citation>
    <PMID>27317801</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Brock WJ, Beaudoin JJ, Slizgi JR, Su M, Jia W, Roth SE, Brouwer KLR. Bile Acids as Potential Biomarkers to Assess Liver Impairment in Polycystic Kidney Disease. Int J Toxicol. 2018 Mar/Apr;37(2):144-154. doi: 10.1177/1091581818760746.</citation>
    <PMID>29587557</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ferslew BC, Xie G, Johnston CK, Su M, Stewart PW, Jia W, Brouwer KL, Barritt AS 4th. Altered Bile Acid Metabolome in Patients with Nonalcoholic Steatohepatitis. Dig Dis Sci. 2015 Nov;60(11):3318-28. doi: 10.1007/s10620-015-3776-8. Epub 2015 Jul 3.</citation>
    <PMID>26138654</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gurka MJ, Coffey CS, Gurka KK. Internal pilots for observational studies. Biom J. 2010 Oct;52(5):590-603. doi: 10.1002/bimj.201000050.</citation>
    <PMID>20857422</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jennison C, Turnbull BW. Adaptive sample size modification in clinical trials: start small then ask for more? Stat Med. 2015 Dec 20;34(29):3793-810. doi: 10.1002/sim.6575. Epub 2015 Jul 14.</citation>
    <PMID>26172385</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Coffey CS, Muller KE. Properties of internal pilots with the univariate approach to repeated measures. Stat Med. 2003 Aug 15;22(15):2469-85.</citation>
    <PMID>12872303</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Denne JS. Sample size recalculation using conditional power. Stat Med. 2001 Sep 15-30;20(17-18):2645-60.</citation>
    <PMID>11523074</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 22, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 22, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 24, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 23, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 23, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 25, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>hepatic transporters</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Kidney Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Polycystic Kidney Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Polycystic Kidney, Autosomal Dominant</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

