<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03717376</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NI18039J</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03717376</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Movement Disorders and Early Maladaptive Schemas</brief_title>
  <acronym>SCHEMAF</acronym>
  <official_title>Specificity of Early Maladaptive Schemas in Functional Movement Disorders</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Assistance Publique - Hôpitaux de Paris</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Assistance Publique - Hôpitaux de Paris</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Functional neurological disorders (FND) are neurological symptoms that cannot be explained by
      a lesion or related to an identified dysfunction of the central nervous system. FND are
      under-diagnosed, although common and highly disabling. Childhood trauma events are found in
      30% to 80% of FND patients, and are more common in people with functional neurological
      disorder than in healthy controls and patient controls. Overall, risks factors, perpetuating
      factors and maintaining factors have been described in FND, although none of the studies have
      analysed the prevalence of Early Maladaptive Schemas (EMS) in these patients. EMS, as
      measured with the Young Schema Questionnaire (YSQ), are proposed to underlie a variety of
      mental health problems, in particular Personality Disorders. We hypothesize that some of
      these early maladaptive schemas may participate in the psychopathology and severity of FND.

      The main outcome of this study is to assess the prevalence of early maladaptive schemas in
      patients presenting with Functional Movement Disorders in comparison to patients presenting
      with Parkinson's Disease or Organic Dystonia. The secondary outcomes are to further analyse
      the underlying relation of these early maladaptive schemas and (i) the severity of the motor
      symptoms, (ii) anxiety and/or depression, (iii) the occurrence of childhood trauma events in
      our participants.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Functional neurological disorders (FND) are neurological symptoms that cannot be explained by
      a lesion or related to an identified dysfunction of the central nervous system. FND are
      under-diagnosed, although common and highly disabling. Functional Movement Disorders are a
      sub-category of FND, affecting the voluntary motor command. Childhood trauma events are found
      in 30% to 80% of FND patients, and are more common in people with functional neurological
      disorder than in healthy controls and patient controls. Overall, risks factors, perpetuating
      factors and maintaining factors have been described in FND, and some team research as Brown
      R. and al. have attempted to include it in psychopathological models such as the Integrative
      Conceptual Model in 2004. Nonetheless, none of the studies have analysed the prevalence of
      Early Maladaptive Schemas (EMS) in these patients. EMS, as measured with the Young Schema
      Questionnaire (YSQ), are proposed to underlie a variety of mental health problems, in
      particular Personality Disorders. Jeffrey Young has developed this concept in the 90's,
      through the so called &quot;Schema Therapy&quot;. EMS are proposed as the core and main target for
      treatment of personality disorders and long-standing characterological problems. The current
      definition of an EMS is &quot;a broad, pervasive theme or pattern, comprised of memories,
      emotions, cognitions, and bodily sensations, regarding oneself and one's relationships with
      others, developed during childhood or adolescence, elaborated throughout one's lifetime and
      dysfunctional to a significant degree&quot;. It has been studied in various conditions such as
      obesity, personality disorders, post-traumatic stress disorder, or obsessive-compulsive
      disorder, finding some EMS specificity in patients presenting with these conditions. In our
      study, we hypothesize that some of these early maladaptive schemas may participate in the
      psychopathology and severity of FND.

      The main outcome of this study is to assess the prevalence of early maladaptive schemas in
      patients presenting with Functional Movement Disorders in comparison to patients presenting
      with Parkinson's Disease or Organic Dystonia. The secondary outcomes are to further analyse
      the underlying relation of these early maladaptive schemas and (i) the severity of the motor
      symptoms, (ii) anxiety and/or depression, (iii) the occurrence of childhood trauma events in
      our participants.

      In order to reach these objectives, we aim to include 77 patients from which 30 patients with
      Functional Movement Disorder, 28 patients with Parkinson's disease, 19 patients with organic
      dystonia.

      All eligible participants who have accepted to participate in the study will fill the YSQ-S3
      (Short Form, French Version, validated and reliable instrument in clinical and research
      settings).The YSQ-S3 is a self-questionnaire which uses a Likert-type ranking, whereby 1
      means &quot;completely untrue of me&quot; and 6 means &quot;describes me perfectly&quot;. Similarly, questions
      range from life experiences to present feelings about certain situations. It consists of 90
      self-report items, measuring all of the 18 EMS, aiming to describe one's functioning schemas
      over the past year.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 12, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 12, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 12, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Assessment of the prevalence of early maladaptive schemas in patients with Functional Movement Disorders versus patients with Parkinson's Disease or Dystonic Disorders</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion, an average of 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Score ≥16 in each schema on the Young Schema Questionnaire-S3 (YSQ-S3) is considered as pathological</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Correlation between the YSQ-S3 scores and the severity of motor symptoms (score from the Unified Parkinson's Disease Rating Scale (UPDRS) part 3)</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion, an average of 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Clinical Severity score on UPDRS part 3 ranges from 0 (none) to 108 (severe)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Correlation between the YSQ-S3 scores and anxiety/depression symptoms (screened with the Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale (HADS) together with the Mini International Neuropsychiatric Interview (MINI))</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion, an average of 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Presence of anxiety if HADS-Anxiety ≥10; Presence of depression if HADS-Depression ≥10</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Correlation between the YSQ-S3 scores and self-reported childhood traumatic events (assessed with the Composite International Diagnosis Interview (CIDI) questionnaire)</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion, an average of 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Assessment of the different types of childhood trauma events</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">77</enrollment>
  <condition>Functional Movement Disorder</condition>
  <condition>Parkinson Disease</condition>
  <condition>Dystonic Disorders</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Self-questionnaire YSQ-S3 (Young Schema Questionnaire)</intervention_name>
    <description>All participants will fill the YSQ-S3 at home and send it back to the main investigator.</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients followed-up at Pitié-Salpêtrière hospital with functional movement disorder,
        parkinson's disease or distonic disorders.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Age ≥ 18 years-old

          2. Being diagnosed with Parkinson's Disease (United Kingdom Parkinson's Disease Society
             Brain Bank (UKPDSBB) criteria) or with Functional Movement Disorder (Gupta &amp; Lang
             criteria) or with Dystonia (criteria from Obeso et al. Mov Dis 2013)

          3. Being previously included in the research protocol untitled &quot; Retentissement des
             mouvements anormaux &quot;

          4. Patient informed and having given their non-opposition

          5. Written and oral comprehension of French

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Pregnancy

          2. Guardianship or Tutelage measure

          3. Psychosis

          4. Other neurological disorder (i.e.: brain tumor, ...)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Richard LEVY, MD. PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Assistance Publique Hoptiaux de Paris</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Richard LEVY, MD. PhD</last_name>
    <phone>33 (0)1 42 16 17 55</phone>
    <email>richard.levy@aphp.fr</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Guilhem CARLE, MD, MSc</last_name>
    <phone>33 (0)1 42 16 17 62</phone>
    <email>guilhem.carle@icm-institute.org</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>APHP - Pitié-Salpêtrière hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Paris</city>
        <zip>75013</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Richard LEVY, MD. PhD</last_name>
      <email>richard.levy@aphp.fr</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Guilhem CARLE, MD, MSc</last_name>
      <email>guilhem.carle@icm-institute.org</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 15, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 22, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 24, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 12, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 12, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 13, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Functional Movement Disorder</keyword>
  <keyword>Functional Neurological Disorder</keyword>
  <keyword>Early Maladaptive Scheme</keyword>
  <keyword>Parkinson</keyword>
  <keyword>Dystonia</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Parkinson Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Movement Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dystonic Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dystonia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Conversion Disorder</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

