<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03716037</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>18-010-ME</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03716037</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Improving Physical and Psychosocial Well-being of African American Older Adults</brief_title>
  <official_title>Improving Physical and Psychosocial Well-being of African American Older Adults Living in Rural Areas Through a Community-Based Exercise Program</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Alabama, Tuscaloosa</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Alabama, Tuscaloosa</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The proposed research effort will:

      The purpose of this study is as follows:

        1. Test the feasibility and acceptability of an eight-week community-based exercise program
           among AA older adults living in rural areas.

        2. Determine whether participation in physical exercise through a community-based exercise
           program in comparison with an attentional control group: a) improves physical well-being
           b) improves psychosocial well-being
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Among the aging population, African Americans (AA) experience depression and other chronic
      diseases such as diabetes, hypertension, and cardiovascular disease at a higher rate compared
      to non-minorities; moreover, those living in rural areas are less likely to seek treatment
      due to various factors including lack of accessibility, affordability, and acceptability of
      health care services. Fortunately, non-pharmacologic and cost-effective interventions such as
      physical activity can yield physical, psychosocial, and cognitive benefits for older adults.
      The purpose of the proposed research effort is to test the feasibility of, and effect of a
      community-based physical exercise program among community-dwelling older adults living in
      rural areas on the physical and psychosocial well-being. The research effort will be a
      randomized controlled trial. Fifty African American older adults will be recruited from
      community centers. A total of 50 participants will be recruited. These adults will be
      randomly assigned to either the intervention or control group, with each group containing 25
      participants. The intervention will occur over a period of eight week. The exercise program
      will be offered three times a week, with each session lasting one hour. Study measures will
      be collected prior to the start of the exercise program, after the fourth session, after the
      last session, and at one-month follow-up. The primary outcome measures for the feasibility
      study will include enrollment rate, randomization rate, retention rate, and data completion
      rate. Additionally, the investigators will examine whether there is improvement I both
      physical and psychosocial measures. All statistical analyses will be conducted using
      Statistical Package for the Social Sciences (SPSS) version 22.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">May 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 1, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 1, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Feasibility of the community based exercise program as measured by enrollment rate</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>enrollment rate which is the number of participants who sign the informed consent form divided by the number who are approached should be ≥ 60%</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>physical activity as measured by Fitbit trackers</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Fitbit will track the daily steps</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>psychosocial Well-being as measured by the Patient Reported Outcomes Measurement Information Systems (PROMIS) Global Health Measure-10</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Primary psychosocial variables of interest, that is depression and anxiety will be measured using the PROMIS Global Health Measure-10, a 10-item questionnaire that examines physical, mental, and social health. The questions focus on the previous seven days. This tool is scored on a 5-point Likert scale. Internal consistency of the subscales ranges from Cronbach's alpha = 0.8-0.92. Scores range from 10-50. Higher values indicate higher functioning for all scales- physical, mental or social scales.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Satisfaction Outcome as measured by the Client satisfaction Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Satisfaction with the intervention program will be assessed with the 8-item Client Satisfaction Questionnaire (CSQ-8; Attkisson, 2012), with established reliability, internal consistency, and validity across racial/ethnic groups. Summary scores range from 8-32 with higher scores indicating greater satisfaction. Study-specific satisfaction items will be assessed also using a 4-pt Likert scale . Higher scores mean increased participant satisfaction.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Physical Function as measured by the senior fitness test</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>all seven components of the senior fitness test will be examined. This is a validated tool for physical function in older adults.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>physical activity as measured by Fitbit trackers</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Fitbit will track number of minutes active every day.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Feasibility of the community based exercise program as measured by randomization rate</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>randomization rate which is the number of participants randomized divided by the number of participants consented and screened which should be ≥ 60%</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Feasibility of the community based exercise program as measured by retention rate</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>retention rate which is the number of participants completing T2 divided by the number who were randomized should be ≥ 80%.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Physical Activity</condition>
  <condition>Psychosocial Stressors</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Physical Activity</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Physical Activity for Life (PAL) is an 8-week exercise program, meeting three times per week for one hour sessions.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Contact Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>those in the attentional contact control group will receive a phone call from research personnel three times per week asking them about their physical exercise routines.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Physical Activity for Life (PAL)</intervention_name>
    <description>The eight-week exercise program (The PAL Study) will incorporate balance, strength, endurance, and flexibility training. The duration of each exercise session, which will be offered three times a week, will be one hour. The supervised exercise session will include 30 minutes of moderate-intensity aerobic exercise, 15 minutes of resistance training, and 15 minutes of stretching and balance training</description>
    <arm_group_label>Physical Activity</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. At least 65 years of age

          2. Identifying as AA

          3. community dwelling and living in a rural community.

          4. Sedentary life style (engaging in less than two hours of structured physical exercises
             whether independently or in a group setting every week)

          5. Identify as having altered psychosocial health by scoring at least a 10 on the Patient
             Health Questionnaire (PHQ-9), which is indicative of moderate depressive symptoms
             (Kroenke, Spitzer, &amp; Williams, 2001).

        Exclusion Criteria:

        1. cognitive impairment as defined by the St. Louis University Mental Status Exam
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>65 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>100 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mercy N Mumba, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Alabama at Birmingham</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Mercy N Mumba, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>682-521-0423</phone>
    <email>mnmumba@ua.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Rebecca S Allen, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+1 205 348 9891</phone>
    <email>rsallen@ua.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 11, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 19, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 23, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 24, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 24, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 26, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Alabama, Tuscaloosa</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Mercy N. Mumba</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>physical activity</keyword>
  <keyword>exercise</keyword>
  <keyword>depression</keyword>
  <keyword>anxiety</keyword>
  <keyword>stress</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

