<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03714906</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>1317655</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03714906</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Stellate Ganglion Block in Head and Neck Cancer Surgery</brief_title>
  <official_title>Utility of Pre-Operative Stellate Ganglion Blockade for Pain Control in Unilateral Head and Neck Cancer Surgery</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Augusta University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Augusta University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to evaluate and reduce pain and improve quality of life in
      patients being treated for head and neck cancer with unilateral surgery. In this study,
      patients will be randomly assigned to receive either pre-operative stellate ganglion block or
      no pre-operative treatment. Blocks will be placed by a trained anesthesiologist using
      ultrasound guidance in the preoperative holding area prior to surgery. All patients will
      receive the same post-operative pain medication regimen with appropriate pain treatment as
      needed. Patients will be asked to fill out surveys prior to surgery, while in the hospital
      after surgery, and at each follow-up appointment for up to 24 months.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Sympathetic blockade of the stellate ganglion is used for upper limb, temporomandibular
      joint, and facial pain, and may be placed pre-operatively to decrease post-operative pain in
      upper limb orthopedic surgery. Use of this block for head and neck cancer pain has been
      studied with mixed results in a case series in the distant past prior to the advent of image
      guidance or newer long-lasting anesthetic drugs. One recent case report for intractable head
      and neck cancer pain demonstrated encouraging results with relief provided after diagnostic
      stellate ganglion blockade followed by chemical neurolysis.

      Patients who choose to participate in the study will be randomly assigned to receive either
      stellate ganglion block placement in the pre-operative holding area on the day of surgery or
      no pre-operative intervention. Participating patients will be asked to fill out separate
      questionnaires to evaluate pain and quality of life preoperatively and post-operatively.

      Upon enrollment in the study, patients will be assigned an identification number and will
      undergo simple randomization to either the control or treatment group using a randomly
      computer-generated sequence. If patients have not had an evaluation of vocal cord mobility on
      prior workup, this will be assessed by flexible fiberoptic laryngoscopy prior to proceeding
      with block placement.

      Patients assigned to receive a block will have it placed on the respective surgical side in
      the pre-operative holding area on the day of surgery. A trained anesthesiologist will perform
      the placement using an injection of 0.25% bupivacaine under ultrasound guidance. While in the
      hospital after surgery, patients will be given a regimen of scheduled acetaminophen 650
      milligrams every 6 hours. Planned treatment of pain will include the option of requesting
      oxycodone on an as-needed basis every four hours and IV morphine for breakthrough pain.
      Surveys will be administered and collected on a daily basis while patients are in the
      hospital. If patients are already utilizing other non-opioid pain medications like muscle
      relaxers (Flexeril, baclofen, etc.), or neuropathic pain medications (Neurontin), they will
      be allowed to continue these medications while inpatient provided there are no changes in
      dosing. Home non-steroidal anti-inflammatory analgesic medications will be withheld while
      patients are in the hospital due to the potential risk of post-operative bleeding and kidney
      injury related to use of these medications in the perioperative setting. These medications
      may be resumed once you are discharged from the hospital.

      Patients will be discharged home on a seven-day course of acetaminophen with as-needed
      oxycodone. Outcomes surveys will then be collected at each subsequent post-operative follow
      up. Follow up visits will occur one week after discharge, four weeks after discharge, and
      then every three months until completion of the two year study period.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Enrolling by invitation</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 22, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 1, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 1, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Brief Pain Inventory</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Validated pain survey in head and neck cancer patients</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Inpatient morphine equivalents</measure>
    <time_frame>1-7 days or longer depending on length of stay</time_frame>
    <description>Requirement of short-term post-operative narcotic therapy</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Defense &amp; Veterans Pain Rating Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Non-validated pain survey in head and neck cancer patients</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>University of Washington Quality of Life Scale Version 4 (UW-QOL 4)</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Validated quality of life outcomes scale in head and neck cancer patients</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>EuroQol 5D-5L</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Non-validated quality of life survey in head and neck cancer patients</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">56</enrollment>
  <condition>Head and Neck Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Pain, Postoperative</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients randomized to the Treatment arm will be assigned to receive a stellate ganglion block. While in the hospital after surgery, patients will be given a regimen of scheduled acetaminophen 650 milligrams every 6 hours. Planned treatment of post-operative pain will include the option of requesting oxycodone on an as-needed basis every four hours and IV morphine for breakthrough pain.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients assigned to the Control arm will receive no pre-operative intervention. While in the hospital after surgery, these patients will be given a regimen of scheduled acetaminophen 650 milligrams every 6 hours. Planned treatment of post-operative pain will include the option of requesting oxycodone on an as-needed basis every four hours and IV morphine for breakthrough pain.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Stellate ganglion block</intervention_name>
    <description>Stellate ganglion block will consist of an injection of 0.25% bupivacaine placed under ultrasound guidance by a trained anesthesiologist in the pre-operative holding area prior to surgery.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  English-speaking patients who are greater than eighteen years of age with a known
             diagnosis of head and neck cancer and are planned to undergo surgery with unilateral
             neck dissection will be eligible for this study

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with a history of preoperative narcotic use for conditions unrelated to their
             head and neck cancer will be excluded.

          -  Patients younger than eighteen years of age, patients with a history of vocal cord
             paralysis on the non-surgical side, patients with a history of severe difficulty
             swallowing, and pregnant patients will be excluded from this study.

          -  Patients with a history of abnormal heart rhythm will be considered to have a relative
             contraindication and will require clearance by the consultant anesthesiologist prior
             to participation in the study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>James K Byrd, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Augusta University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Augusta University Department of Otolaryngology-Head and Neck Surgery</name>
      <address>
        <city>Augusta</city>
        <state>Georgia</state>
        <zip>30912</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gunduz OH, Kenis-Coskun O. Ganglion blocks as a treatment of pain: current perspectives. J Pain Res. 2017 Dec 14;10:2815-2826. doi: 10.2147/JPR.S134775. eCollection 2017. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>29276402</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wang QX, Wang XY, Fu NA, Liu JY, Yao SL. Stellate ganglion block inhibits formalin-induced nociceptive responses: mechanism of action. Eur J Anaesthesiol. 2005 Dec;22(12):913-8.</citation>
    <PMID>16318661</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>McDonnell JG, Finnerty O, Laffey JG. Stellate ganglion blockade for analgesia following upper limb surgery. Anaesthesia. 2011 Jul;66(7):611-4. doi: 10.1111/j.1365-2044.2011.06626.x. Epub 2011 May 31.</citation>
    <PMID>21627622</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jones GP, Tripathi SS. Successful use of stellate ganglion block and a new centrally acting analgesic with dual mode of action in a resistant temporomandibular joint pain. BMJ Case Rep. 2014 May 20;2014. pii: bcr2013203308. doi: 10.1136/bcr-2013-203308.</citation>
    <PMID>24849638</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Salvaggio I, Adducci E, Dell'Aquila L, Rinaldi S, Marini M, Zappia L, Mascaro A. Facial pain: a possible therapy with stellate ganglion block. Pain Med. 2008 Oct;9(7):958-62. doi: 10.1111/j.1526-4637.2008.00515.x.</citation>
    <PMID>18950449</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kumar N, Thapa D, Gombar S, Ahuja V, Gupta R. Analgesic efficacy of pre-operative stellate ganglion block on postoperative pain relief: a randomised controlled trial. Anaesthesia. 2014 Sep;69(9):954-660. doi: 10.1111/anae.12774. Epub 2014 Jul 7.</citation>
    <PMID>25040168</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ghai A, Kaushik T, Kumar R, Wadhera S. Chemical ablation of stellate ganglion for head and neck cancer pain. Acta Anaesthesiol Belg. 2016;67(1):6-8.</citation>
    <PMID>27363209</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 19, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 19, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 22, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 8, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 8, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 10, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>head and neck cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>pain</keyword>
  <keyword>analgesia</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Head and Neck Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pain, Postoperative</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

