<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03710642</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ADC-042-PRAZ</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>5U19AG010483</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03710642</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Prazosin for Agitation in Alzheimer's Disease</brief_title>
  <official_title>Prazosin for Disruptive Agitation in Alzheimer's Disease (AD) (PEACE-AD)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Alzheimer's Disease Cooperative Study (ADCS)</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute on Aging (NIA)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>VA Puget Sound Health Care System</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Alzheimer's Disease Cooperative Study (ADCS)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The study evaluates the effects of Prazosin on agitation in adults with Alzheimer's disease.

      Two thirds of the participants will participate in the medication portion, while one third
      will participate in the placebo portion
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Prazosin for Disruptive Agitation in Alzheimer's Disease (PEACE-AD) is a Phase IIb
      multicenter, randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled trial of 12-weeks treatment with
      the brain active alpha-1 adrenoreceptor (AR) antagonist prazosin for disruptive agitation
      defined as having at least one of any of the following target behaviors with ≥ moderately
      severe rating at least 5 times per week for a minimum of 4 weeks: a) irritability, b)
      physically and/or verbally aggressive behavior, c) physically resistive to necessary care, d)
      and/or pressured motor activity (e.g., pressured pacing) in approximately 186 Alzheimer's
      disease (AD) residents in long-term care (LTC) settings. LTC is defined as assisted living or
      skilled nursing facility. A previous single site pilot study addressing disruptive agitation
      in 22 predominantly LTC-residing AD participants demonstrated efficacy of prazosin on all
      three primary outcome measures.1 The current multicenter study is funded by the National
      Institute on Aging (NIA), and coordinated through the NIA-funded Alzheimer's Disease
      Cooperative Study (ADCS).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 23, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>ADAS-Clinical Global Impression of Change in Agitation (CGIC)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The ADCS-CGIC-A is the primary outcome measure. It will be anchored to disruptive agitation, the target behaviors in this study. It measures whether the effects of active treatment are substantial enough to be detected by a skilled and experienced clinician on the basis of a direct examination of the participant and an interview of the participant's primary caregiver and other LTC facility staff. The participant is rated on a 7-point Likert scale. Scores can range from 1 (improvement) to 7 (worsening).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Neuropsychiatric Inventory-Nursing Home version (NPI-NH)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">186</enrollment>
  <condition>Alzheimer's Disease</condition>
  <condition>Disruptive Behavior</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (Prazosin)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Eligible participants will be randomized using a 2:1 schedule to prazosin or placebo and stratified by site and gender, and will follow a fixed titration scheme for the first 15 days, followed by a flexible does titration from days 15-29, then a maintenance phase stable dose from days 29 to the end of the 12 weeks study period.
Prazosin Fixed titration dose schedule for Days 1 to 14 1 mg QHS for Days 1 to 3
1 mg QAM and 1 mg QHS for days 4 to 7
mg QAM and 2 mg QHS for days 8 to 10
mg QAM and 2 mg QHS for days 11 to 14
Prazosin Flexible titration dose schedule for Days 15 to 29. 3 mg QAM and 3 mg QHS on day 15, 4 mg QAM and 4 mg QHS on day 22, 4 mg QAH and 6 mg QHS on day 29,
Dose increases will be allowed only during the fixed and flexible dosing periods.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo oral capsule</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Placebo medication will be administered in a titration schedule mimicking the active comparator treatment.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Prazosin</intervention_name>
    <description>Oral prazosin HCl capsules (or placebo) will be administered twice daily, with individualized doses up to a maximum of 4 mg QAM mid-morning and 6 mg at bedtime (QHS), or matching placebo capsules</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (Prazosin)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Prazosin HCl</other_name>
    <other_name>Minipress</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo oral capsule</intervention_name>
    <description>Placebo capsule matched to appearance of active drug.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo oral capsule</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Placebo</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Males and females with probable or possible AD by NINCDS-ADRDA criteria utilizing
             medical history; medical records review; physical, neurological, and psychiatric exam;
             and screening laboratory tests, who are residing in a LTC facility. Brain imaging is
             not a requirement.

          2. At Baseline (BL), participants must have disruptive agitation (documented on the
             Behavioral Inclusion Criteria Checklist and detailed on the ADCS-CGIC-A BL Worksheet)
             defined as having at least one of the following target behaviors with &gt; moderately
             severe rating at least 5 times per week for a minimum duration of 4 weeks: a)
             irritability, b) physically and/or verbally aggressive behavior, c) physically
             resistive to necessary care, and/or d) pressured motor activity (e.g., pressured
             pacing). These behaviors must be problematic in that they cause participant and
             caregiver distress and/or interfere with essential care or disrupt the LTC
             environment. Target behaviors may be any combination of the listed domains, as long as
             there are 5 or more instances per week of at least moderate severity.

          3. Psychotropic medication, if used, should be stable for at least 2 weeks prior to
             randomization.

          4. If taking cholinesterase inhibitor and/or memantine, must be on stable dose(s) for 3
             months prior to randomization.

          5. Must be able to swallow capsules whole.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. History of schizophrenia, schizoaffective disorder, or bipolar disorder according to
             the criteria of the most current version of the Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of
             Mental Disorders (DSM).

          2. Other neurodegenerative diseases, including Parkinson's disease and Huntington's
             disease, or cerebral tumor.

          3. Dementia other than probable or possible AD per NINCDS-ADRDA criteria, such as human
             immunodeficiency virus (HIV) dementia, Creutzfeldt-Jakob disease, frontotemporal
             dementia, multiple cerebral infarctions, or normal pressure hydrocephalus.

          4. Current treatment for seizure disorder.

          5. Abnormal laboratory values with clinical significance in the opinion of the site
             Principal Investigator.

          6. Current unstable medical illness including delirium, worsening congestive heart
             failure, unstable angina, recent myocardial infarction (within the past 3 months),
             acute infectious disease, severe renal or hepatic failure, severe respiratory disease,
             metastatic cancer, or other conditions that, in the Site Principal Investigator's
             opinion, could interfere with the analyses of safety and efficacy in this study.

          7. Bedbound; participants may be ambulatory or use a wheelchair.

          8. Absence of any comprehensible language.

          9. Participation in another clinical trial for an investigational agent and took at least
             one dose of study drug (unless unblinded to placebo) within 12 weeks prior to
             screening. (The end of a previous investigational trial is defined as the date of the
             last dose of an investigational agent).

         10. Preexisting recurrent hypotension (systolic blood pressure [BP] &lt;110).

         11. Preexisting orthostatic hypotension (&gt;20 mmHg drop in systolic BP following 2 minutes
             of standing posture [or sitting if unable to stand], accompanied by dizziness,
             lightheadedness, or syncope).

         12. A 2-week washout is required prior to BL for the following exclusionary medications:
             prazosin or other alpha-1 blocker, sildenafil, vardenafil, tadalafil, avanafil, and
             trazodone.

         13. Women of childbearing potential (must be at least 2 years post-menopausal or
             surgically sterile for inclusion).

         14. The participant may not be an immediate family member of personnel directly affiliated
             with this study, the study site or study funding agency. Immediate family member is
             defined as a spouse, parent, child, or sibling, any of whom may be related by blood,
             adoption, or marriage.

         15. Participants whom the Site Principal Investigator deems to be otherwise unsuitable for
             participation.

             -
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Southern California</name>
      <address>
        <city>Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90033</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of California, San Diego (UCSD)</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Diego</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>92093</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Stanford University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Stanford</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94305</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Kentucky</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lexington</city>
        <state>Kentucky</state>
        <zip>40506</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Roper St. Francis</name>
      <address>
        <city>Charleston</city>
        <state>South Carolina</state>
        <zip>29401</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Texas, Southwestern MC at Dallas</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dallas</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>75390</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Washington</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seattle</city>
        <state>Washington</state>
        <zip>98108</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Peskind ER, Wingerson D, Murray S, Pascualy M, Dobie DJ, Le Corre P, Le Verge R, Veith RC, Raskind MA. Effects of Alzheimer's disease and normal aging on cerebrospinal fluid norepinephrine responses to yohimbine and clonidine. Arch Gen Psychiatry. 1995 Sep;52(9):774-82.</citation>
    <PMID>7654129</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Torroba Alvarez L, Hermida Donate JM, Ezpeleta Baquedano C, Muñoz Zato E. [Methemoglobinemia secondary to the treatment of opportunistic infections in patients with AIDS]. Rev Clin Esp. 1988 Mar;182(5):289-90. Spanish.</citation>
    <PMID>3399726</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Elrod R, Peskind ER, DiGiacomo L, Brodkin KI, Veith RC, Raskind MA. Effects of Alzheimer's disease severity on cerebrospinal fluid norepinephrine concentration. Am J Psychiatry. 1997 Jan;154(1):25-30.</citation>
    <PMID>8988954</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Raskind MA, Peskind ER, Holmes C, Goldstein DS. Patterns of cerebrospinal fluid catechols support increased central noradrenergic responsiveness in aging and Alzheimer's disease. Biol Psychiatry. 1999 Sep 15;46(6):756-65.</citation>
    <PMID>10494443</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Raskind MA, Peskind ER, Hoff DJ, Hart KL, Holmes HA, Warren D, Shofer J, O'Connell J, Taylor F, Gross C, Rohde K, McFall ME. A parallel group placebo controlled study of prazosin for trauma nightmares and sleep disturbance in combat veterans with post-traumatic stress disorder. Biol Psychiatry. 2007 Apr 15;61(8):928-34. Epub 2006 Oct 25.</citation>
    <PMID>17069768</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Raskind MA, Peterson K, Williams T, Hoff DJ, Hart K, Holmes H, Homas D, Hill J, Daniels C, Calohan J, Millard SP, Rohde K, O'Connell J, Pritzl D, Feiszli K, Petrie EC, Gross C, Mayer CL, Freed MC, Engel C, Peskind ER. A trial of prazosin for combat trauma PTSD with nightmares in active-duty soldiers returned from Iraq and Afghanistan. Am J Psychiatry. 2013 Sep;170(9):1003-10. doi: 10.1176/appi.ajp.2013.12081133.</citation>
    <PMID>23846759</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 9, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 16, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 18, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 18, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 18, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 20, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Dementia</keyword>
  <keyword>Agitation</keyword>
  <keyword>PEACE-AD</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Alzheimer Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Psychomotor Agitation</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Problem Behavior</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Prazosin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

