<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03718598</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>9671</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03718598</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Carpal Tunnel Syndrome in Pregnant Women</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effectiveness of Home Exercise in Pregnant Women With Carpal Tunnel Syndrome</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Bezmialem Vakif University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Bezmialem Vakif University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of our study is to evaluate the effectiveness of the home exercise program in
      patients who develop Carpal tunnel syndrome (CTS).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Materials and Method: Thirty-three patients with CTS (mild to moderate) were included to
      randomized, single-blind, controlled clinical trial. Based on EMG results and clinical
      examination, patient group was divided two part as mild and moderate CTS (group 1) and normal
      (group 2). The Sick Boston Carpal Tunnel Syndrome Questionnaire form was filled in
      face-to-face method.

      Cases in this study: Patients who had pain and numbness problems at the hands of the
      Bezmiâlem Vakif University Polyclinic for Women and Obstetrics were then directed to the
      Bezmiâlem Vakif University Physical Therapy Rehabilitation Policlinic. After the examination
      and clinical testing of each patient (Tinel test, Phalen's test, Reverse Phalen's and
      Durkan's Carpal Compression test), the patients were directed to Bezmiâlem Vakif University
      Neurology Policlinic. Based on electromyography (EMG) results and clinical examination, the
      group was classified as mild and moderate CTS (group 1) and normal (group 2). A disease
      exercise form was distributed for all patients to do exercises.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 1, 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">January 1, 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">January 1, 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational [Patient Registry]</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Control</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <target_duration>3 Years</target_duration>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Sick Boston Carpal Tunnel Syndrome Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>Patients were evaluated before treatment and 1 month after the birth.</time_frame>
    <description>It is a test consisting of two parts evaluating symptom severity (BSSS) and functional capacity (BFCS). BSSS consists of 11 questions for symptoms. In each question there are five different answers with scores between 1 and 5. The average score is obtained by dividing the total score by the number of questions. High score indicates severe symptom. BFCS consists of 8 questions for functional capacity. Again, there are five different answers in each question, ranging from 1 to 5. The average score is obtained by dividing the total score by the number of questions. The high score indicates that the functional capacity decreases. The questionnaire has been validated and tested for Turkish society (15). The questionnaire has been validated and tested for Turkish society (16).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">33</enrollment>
  <condition>Carpal Tunnel Syndrome</condition>
  <condition>Exercise</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Carpal tunnel syndrome</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients with mild and moderate carpal tunnel syndrome</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>normal</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients without mild and moderate carpal tunnel syndrome</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Tendon and Nerve Gliding Exercises</intervention_name>
    <description>Tendon and Nerve Gliding Exercises: The tendon slip exercises used in this study were performed in five different positions, namely flexion, flat, hook, punch, table top and flat punch positions. Nerve-gliding exercises were performed by moving the fingers and wrists in six different positions, focusing on the median nerve consisting of all the disease grip, finger lengthening, wrist extension, thumb extension, forearm supination and gentle gentle gait. Instructions were given to make 10 sets of exercises in 3 sets, written and verbal, in order to have e exercises for all patient's tendons and nerves shifting exercises. Brochures were also provided explaining the exercises.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Carpal tunnel syndrome</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>normal</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Non-Probability Sample: Any of a variety of other sampling processes, such as convenience
        sampling or invitation to volunteer
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Provocation tests during the examination and physical examination to match the median
             nerve distribution those who have symptoms of numbness, tingling, weakness and pain in
             the hands that have lasted at least 1 month.

          -  Patients with confirmed mild-moderate idiopathic CTS on EMG.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Previously undergone carpal tunnel surgery

          -  Gestational diabetes mellitus,

          -  Eclampsia, preeclampsia

          -  Thyroid disorders

          -  Arthropathies

          -  Hand or wrist trauma

          -  Bilateral fractures

          -  Severe cts

          -  Atrial fibrillation

          -  Cervical radiculopathy

          -  Peripheral neuropathy

          -  Thoracic outlet syndrome

          -  Diabetes mellitus

          -  Hypothyroidism

          -  Hyperthyroidism

          -  Rheumatologic disease
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>40 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <verification_date>October 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 23, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 23, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 24, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 26, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 26, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 29, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Carpal tunnel syndrome</keyword>
  <keyword>home exercise</keyword>
  <keyword>pregnant women</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Carpal Tunnel Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Syndrome</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Statistical Analysis Plan (SAP)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Informed Consent Form (ICF)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Clinical Study Report (CSR)</ipd_info_type>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

