<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03507790</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>COG0201</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03507790</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study to Evaluate the Safety and Efficacy of CT1812 in Subjects With Mild to Moderate Alzheimer's Disease.</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized, Double-Blind, Placebo-Controlled, Parallel-Group, Phase 2 Study to Evaluate the Safety and Efficacy of CT1812 in Subjects With Mild to Moderate Alzheimer's Disease.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Cognition Therapeutics</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Cognition Therapeutics</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a multi-center, randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled, parallel group 36 week
      multicenter Phase 2 study of two doses of CT1812 in adults with mild to moderate Alzheimer's
      Disease (AD).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a multi-center, randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled, parallel group 36 week
      multicenter Phase 2 study of two doses of CT1812 in adults with mild to moderate Alzheimer's
      Disease (AD).

      This Phase 2 study is designed to evaluate the safety of two doses of CT1812 administered
      once daily for 6 months in adults aged 50 to 85 who have been diagnosed with mild to moderate
      Alzheimer's disease (the targeted clinical indication for CT1812). Randomized participants
      will receive 100 mg of CT1812, 300 mg of CT1812, or placebo once daily for 182 days.
      Exploratory endpoints that evaluate the effect of CT1812 on biomarkers are also included.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 2, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 31, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>This is a multi-center Phase 2, randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled, parallel-group study.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of study participants with treatment related adverse events and serious adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>210 Days</time_frame>
    <description>Adverse events will be collected starting at Day 1 through Day 210 to evaluate safety.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">120</enrollment>
  <condition>Mild to Moderate Alzheimer's Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Active Treatment- CT1812 100 mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>CT1812 at a dose of 100 n=40 group</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Active Treatment- CT1812 300 mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>CT1812 at a dose of 300mg, n=40 group</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo Comparator - Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Placebo, n=40 group</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>CT1812</intervention_name>
    <description>Active Study Drug</description>
    <arm_group_label>Active Treatment- CT1812 100 mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Active Treatment- CT1812 300 mg</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Study Drug</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Non-active study drug</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo Comparator - Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Matching Placebo</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        1. Men, and women of non-childbearing potential, 50-85 years of age inclusively, with a
             diagnosis of mild to moderate Alzheimer's disease according to the 2011 NIA-AA
             criteria and at least a 6 month decline in cognitive function documented in the
             medical record.

             i) Non-childbearing potential for women is defined as postmenopausal (last natural
             menses greater than 24 months) or undergone a documented bilateral tubal ligation or
             hysterectomy. If last natural menses less than 24 months, a serum FSH value confirming
             post-menopausal status can be employed.

             ii) Male participants who are sexually active with a woman of child-bearing potential
             must agree to use condoms during the trial and for 3 months after last dose unless the
             woman is using an acceptable means of birth control. Acceptable forms of birth control
             include abstinence, birth control pills, or any double combination of: intrauterine
             device (IUD), male or female condom, diaphragm, sponge, and cervical cap.

          2. Diagnostic confirmation by amyloid PET with florbetaben or another approved amyloid
             PET ligand. Previous amyloid imaging study with a positive result will be accepted. If
             none is available, then amyloid PET will be conducted during screening. Diagnostic
             confirmation by a CSF sample collected at the screening visit lumbar puncture in place
             of amyloid PET will also be acceptable

          3. Neuroimaging (MRI) obtained during screening consistent with the clinical diagnosis of
             Alzheimer's disease and without findings of significant exclusionary abnormalities
             (see exclusion criteria, number 4). An historical MRI, up to 1 year prior to
             screening, may be used as long as there is no history of intervening neurologic
             disease or clinical events (such as a stroke, head trauma etc.) and the subject is
             without clinical symptoms or signs suggestive of such intervening events.).

          4. MMSE 18-26 inclusive.

          5. No active depression and a GDS ≤6 (see exclusion criteria number 6).

          6. Modified Hachinski ≤ 4.

          7. Formal education of eight or more years.

          8. Subjects must have a caregiver/ study partner who in the opinion of the site principal
             investigator, has contact with the study subject for a sufficient number of hours per
             week to provide informative responses on the protocol assessments, oversee the
             administration of study drug, and is willing and able to participate in all clinic
             visits and some study assessments. The caregiver/ study partner must provide written
             informed consent to participate in the study.

          9. Subjects living at home or in the community (assisted living acceptable).

         10. Ability to swallow CT1812 capsules.

         11. Stable pharmacological treatment of any other chronic conditions for at least 30 days
             prior to screening.

         12. Subjects must be capable of providing written informed consent to the study procedures
             and for use of protected health information [Health Insurance Portability and
             Accountability Act (HIPAA), if applicable]. Written informed consent also shall be
             obtained from the responsible caregiver. All consent processes must be undertaken in
             the presence of a witness and prior to any study procedures.

         13. Must consent to apolipoprotein E (ApoE) genotyping for data analysis stratification.

         14. Subjects shall be generally healthy with mobility (ambulatory or ambulatory-aided,
             i.e., walker or cane), vision and hearing (hearing aid permissible) sufficient for
             compliance with testing procedures.

         15. Must be able to complete all screening evaluations.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

        Participants will be excluded from the study if any of the following conditions apply:

          1. Hospitalization (except for planned procedures) or change of chronic concomitant
             medication within one month prior to screening.

          2. Subjects living in a continuous care nursing facility.

          3. Contraindication to the MRI examination for any reason.

          4. Screening MRI (or historical MRI, if applicable) of the brain indicative of
             significant abnormality, including, but not limited to, prior hemorrhage or infarct &gt;1
             cm3, &gt;3 lacunar infarcts, cerebral contusion, encephalomalacia, aneurysm, vascular
             malformation, subdural hematoma, hydrocephalus, space-occupying lesion (e.g. abscess
             or brain tumor such as meningioma). If a small incidental meningioma is observed, the
             medical monitor may be contacted to discuss eligibility..

          5. Clinical or laboratory findings consistent with:

               1. Other primary degenerative dementia, (dementia with Lewy bodies, fronto-temporal
                  dementia, Huntington's disease, Creutzfeldt-Jakob Disease, Down syndrome, etc.).

               2. Other neurodegenerative condition (Parkinson's disease, amyotrophic lateral
                  sclerosis, etc.).

               3. Seizure disorder.

               4. Other infectious, metabolic or systemic diseases affecting the central nervous
                  system (syphilis, present hypothyroidism, present vitamin B12 or folate
                  deficiency, other laboratory values etc.).

          6. A current DSM-V diagnosis of active major depression, schizophrenia or bipolar
             disorder. Subjects with depressive symptoms successfully managed by a stable dose of
             an antidepressant are allowed entry.

          7. Clinically significant, advanced or unstable disease that may interfere with outcome
             evaluations, such as:

               1. Chronic liver disease, liver function test abnormalities or other signs of
                  hepatic insufficiency (ALT, AST, alkaline phosphatase &gt; 1.5 ULN, lactate
                  dehydrogenase (LDH) &gt; 1.5 x ULN).

               2. Respiratory insufficiency.

               3. Renal insufficiency eGFR &lt; 50 mL/min based on the CKD‐EPI formula,
                  https://www.mdcalc.com/ckd-epi-equations-glomerular-filtration-rate-gfr

               4. Heart disease (myocardial infarction, unstable angina, heart failure,
                  cardiomyopathy within six months before screening).

               5. Bradycardia (&lt;50/min.) or tachycardia (&gt;100/min.).

               6. Poorly managed hypertension (systolic &gt;160 mm Hg and/or diastolic &gt;95 mm Hg) or
                  hypotension (systolic &lt;90 mm Hg and/or diastolic &lt;60 mm Hg).

               7. Uncontrolled diabetes defined by HbA1c &gt;7.5.

          8. History of cancer within 3 years of screening with the exception of fully excised
             non-melanoma skin cancers or non-metastatic prostate cancer that has been stable for
             at least 6 months.

          9. Seropositive for human immunodeficiency virus (HIV).

         10. History of acute/chronic hepatitis B or C and/or carriers of hepatitis B (seropositive
             for hepatitis B surface antigen [HbsAg] or anti-hepatitis C [HCV] antibody).

         11. Clinically significant abnormalities in screening laboratory tests, including:

             a. Hematocrit less than 35% for males and less than 32% for females, absolute
             neutrophil cell count of 1500/uL (with the exception of a documented history of a
             chronic benign neutropenia), or platelet cell count of &lt; 120,000/uL; INR &gt;1.4 or other
             coagulopathy, confirmed by repeat assessment of: i. Hematocrit ii. Neutrophil count
             iii. Platelet count

         12. Disability that may prevent the subject from completing all study requirements (e.g.
             blindness, deafness, severe language difficulty, etc.).

         13. Within 4 weeks of screening visit or during the course of the study, concurrent
             treatment with antipsychotic agents, antiepileptics, centrally active
             anti-hypertensive drugs (e.g., clonidine, l-methyl dopa, guanidine, guanfacine, etc.),
             sedatives, opioids, mood stabilizers (e.g., valproate, lithium); or benzodiazepines,
             with the following exception:

             a. Low dose lorazepam may be used for sedation prior to MRI scan for those subjects
             requiring sedation. At the discretion of the investigator, 0.5 to 1 mg may be given
             orally prior to scan with a single repeat dose given if the first dose is ineffective.
             No more than a total of 2 mg lorazepam may be used for the MRI scan.

         14. Any disorder that could interfere with the absorption, distribution, metabolism or
             excretion of drugs (e.g. small bowel disease, Crohn's disease, celiac disease, or
             liver disease).

         15. Nootropic drugs except stable AD meds (acetylcholinesterase inhibitors and memantine.

         16. Suspected or known drug or alcohol abuse, i.e. more than approximately 60 g alcohol
             (approximately 1 liter of beer or 0.5 liter of wine) per day indicated by elevated MCV
             significantly above normal value at screening.

         17. Suspected or known allergy to any components of the study treatments.

         18. Enrollment in another investigational study or intake of investigational drug within
             the previous 30 days or five half lives of the investigational drug, whichever is
             longer.

         19. Intake of drugs or substances potentially involved in clinically significant induction
             or inhibition of CYP3A4 or P-gp mediated drug interactions with CT1812, within 4 weeks
             or five half-lives of the interacting drug prior to administration of CT1812 and
             throughout the course of the study. Grapefruit juice should be avoided in the two
             weeks prior to dosing and throughout the course of the study. See Appendix A for a
             complete list of prohibited substances.

         20. Exposure to immunomodulators, anti Aβ vaccines, passive immunotherapies for AD (e.g.
             monoclonal antibodies) within the past 180 days and/or exposure to BACE inhibitors
             within the past 30 days.

         21. Anticipated use of nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs) on more than 14 days
             during the period from Baseline to Day 182.

         22. Contraindication to undergoing an LP including, but not limited to: inability to
             tolerate an appropriately flexed position for the time necessary to perform an LP;
             international normalized ratio (INR) &gt; 1.4 or other coagulopathy; platelet count of &lt;
             120,000/μL; infection at the desired lumbar puncture site; taking anti-coagulant
             medication within 90 days of screening (Note: low dose aspirin is permitted);
             degenerative arthritis of the lumbar spine; suspected non-communicating hydrocephalus
             or intracranial mass; prior history of spinal mass or trauma.

         23. Any condition, which in the opinion of the investigator or the sponsor makes the
             subject unsuitable for inclusion.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>50 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>85 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Alyssa Galley</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Cognition Therapuetics</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Imaging Endpoints</name>
      <address>
        <city>Scottsdale</city>
        <state>Arizona</state>
        <zip>85258</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>JEM Research Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Atlantis</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33462</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Allied Biomedical Research Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Miami</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33155</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Compass Research LLC- Bioclinica Research</name>
      <address>
        <city>The Villages</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>32162</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Alzheimer's Memory Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Charlotte</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>28270</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Austin Health</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ivanhoe</city>
        <state>Victoria</state>
        <zip>3079</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>St Vincent's Hospital Sydney</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ivanhoe</city>
        <state>Victoria</state>
        <zip>3079</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Alfred Health</name>
      <address>
        <city>Melbourne</city>
        <state>Victoria</state>
        <zip>3004</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Melbourne Health</name>
      <address>
        <city>Parkville</city>
        <state>Victoria</state>
        <zip>3050</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Australian Alzheimer's Research Foundation</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nedlands</city>
        <state>Western Australia</state>
        <zip>6009</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Australia</country>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>April 10, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 16, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 25, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 13, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 13, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 16, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Alzheimer's Disease</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Alzheimer Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

