<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04488224</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Nano-X IG</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04488224</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Nano-X Image Guidance: CBCT With Gravity-induced Motion</brief_title>
  <acronym>Nano-X IG</acronym>
  <official_title>Nano-X Image Guidance: CBCT With Gravity-induced Motion</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Sydney</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>South Eastern Sydney Local Health District</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Sydney</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      A pilot stage, device feasibility trial, to investigate the feasibility of acquiring cone
      beam computed tomography (CBCT) images for image guidance for radiation therapy by
      maintaining a fixed imaging system and rotating the participant about the horizontal axis
      using the Nano-X patient rotation system. It is a single-arm, controlled, single-blinded,
      non-treatment, non-invasive, single-institution trial.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Primary objective:

      To investigate the feasibility of volumetric image guidance for the Nano-X patient rotation
      system (PRS).

      Secondary objectives:

        1. To develop image reconstruction methods that allow target and normal tissue
           visualisation at all treatment angles to a clinical cone beam computed tomography (CBCT)
           standard.

        2. To determine the reproducibility and variability in Nano-X CBCT compared to clinical
           CBCT.

        3. To measure the magnitude of gravity-induced anatomical deformation and translation.

        4. To develop treatment plan adaptation methods to compensate for gravity-induced target
           motion based on Nano-X CBCT image reconstruction at varying treatment angles.

        5. To quantify the participant experience of horizontal rotation using the Nano-X PRS for
           volumetric image guidance CBCT acquisition.

      The investigators will perform a pilot stage, device feasibility trial, to investigate the
      feasibility of acquiring CBCT images for image guidance by maintaining a fixed imaging system
      and rotating the participant about the horizontal axis using the Nano-X PRS. It is a
      single-arm, controlled, single-blinded, non-treatment, non-invasive, single-institution
      trial.

      Eligible participants will be asked to attend the Nelune Comprehensive Cancer Centre (NCCC)
      at the Prince of Wales Hospital on two separate occasions to obtain Nano-X CBCT scans. For
      each scan the participant will be rotated 360° about the horizontal axis which will take
      approximately 72 seconds to complete.

      Participants will be asked to complete validated psychometric questionnaires before and after
      each Nano-X CBCT. The questionnaire responses will be used to quantify their experiences of
      anxiety and motion sickness, and report previous experiences of claustrophobia, in order to
      identify determinants of tolerance level.

      The projection data sets from the Nano-X CBCT scans, along with conventional CBCTs obtained
      for the participants' standard radiotherapy treatment, will be used to investigate the
      image-related objectives. The two Nano-X CBCT data sets from each participant will be used to
      compare Nano-X CBCT variability and reproducibility to clinical CBCT acquisition.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">August 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Early Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>All participants will undergo CBCT imaging during rotation on the Nano-X patient rotation system. For each participant, quality of CBCT images acquired during the rotation session will be compared with quality of CBCT images collected during their standard radiation therapy treatment.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Device Feasibility</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>The Postdoctoral Research Associate will collect and de-identify CBCT images acquired during Nano-X rotation session and during participants' routine treatment. The software used to display the scans will incorporate a random number generator to determine the labeling of images as 'A' or 'B'. Observers assessing image quality for study outcomes will be masked to the source of either image.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Cone Beam Computed Tomography (CBCT) images acquired with horizontal patient rotation that are deemed to be of comparable image quality to clinical CBCT or deemed acceptable for radiotherapy image guidance as scored by a panel of experts.</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Observers will view the image sets in 3 orthogonal views and grade the image quality considering geometrical accuracy, anatomical visualisation, sharpness of the image, soft tissue contrast, image noise and uniformity and overall clinical usability.
The imaging method will be deemed technically feasible if &gt;70% of CBCT images acquired with horizontal patient rotation are deemed of clinical quality.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in STAI (anxiety) and FMS (motion sickness) questionnaire scores before and after rotation as assessed by the Wilcoxon signed rank test.</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Wilcoxon signed rank test used to determine statistically significant differences in anxiety and motion sickness assessed using psychometrically validated surveys completed prior to and post horizontal rotation CBCT scan.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Patients receiving CBCT Image Guidance during treatment</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>On two separate occasions, CBCT images will be acquired while participants are rotated 360° about the horizontal axis on the Nano-X Patient Rotation System. The rotation will take approximately 72 seconds to complete. Psychometrically validated questionnaires will be completed by the participant before and after each Nano-X CBCT session.
Participants in this arm undergo conventional CBCT for image guidance during standard of care (SOC) radiotherapy treatment. These participants do not require an additional conventional CBCT as the SOC conventional CBCT images are used to benchmark the experimental Nano-X CBCT scans for evaluation of the primary outcome measure.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Patients not receiving CBCT Image Guidance during treatment</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>On two separate occasions, CBCT images will be acquired while participants are rotated 360° about the horizontal axis on the Nano-X Patient Rotation System. The rotation will take approximately 72 seconds to complete. Psychometrically validated questionnaires will be completed by the participant before and after each Nano-X CBCT session.
Participants in this arm do not undergo conventional CBCT for image guidance during standard of care (SOC) radiotherapy treatment. As such these participants will receive an additional conventional CBCT scan on standard equipment which used to benchmark the experimental NAno-X CBCT scans for evaluation of the primary outcome measure.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Nano-X Patient Rotation System</intervention_name>
    <description>The Nano-X prototype is a horizontal patient rotation system that immobilises participants while being rotated on the horizontal axis.
This device will be used to rotate patients horizontally while cone-beam Computed Tomography (CBCT) projections are acquired.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Patients not receiving CBCT Image Guidance during treatment</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Patients receiving CBCT Image Guidance during treatment</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Radiation</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Conventional CBCT scan</intervention_name>
    <description>A conventional cone-beam Computed Tomography (CBCT) scan is acquired on standard radiotherapy machinery.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Patients not receiving CBCT Image Guidance during treatment</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Psychometrically validated questionnaires</intervention_name>
    <description>The Claustrophobia Questionnaire (CLQ), Short Form State/Trait Anxiety inventory (STAI) and Fast Motion Sickness (FMS) questionnaires administered. CLQ only once before the first session, STAI and FMS both before and after each Nano-X CBCT session.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Patients not receiving CBCT Image Guidance during treatment</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Patients receiving CBCT Image Guidance during treatment</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Cancer patients that are receiving radiation therapy that are able to be imaged with
             the Nano-X PRS with one of the following tumour sites:

               1. in the head/neck region

               2. in the chest/abdomen/pelvic region with fast CBCT used for standard of care image
                  guidance and is aged 60 years or older

               3. in the chest/abdomen/pelvic region not receiving CBCT for standard of care image
                  guidance and is aged 70 years or older

               4. diagnosis of lung cancer with stage II-IV

          2. ≥18 years of age

          3. ECOG Performance Status 0-2

          4. Must be able to communicate fluently in English to:

             i. Receive instructions from operators of the PRS for safety entering and leaving the
             Patient Rotation System and required conduct during the during the rotation session,
             and ii. Communicate their level of comfort or distress to operators of the equipment.

          5. Signed, written informed consent or approved alternative, non-contact method for
             informed consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Pregnant women

          2. Patients for whom attaining informed consent would not be possible, including mentally
             impairment

          3. Patients with severe vertigo or recent a diagnosis of Benign Paroxysmal Positioning
             Vertigo.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Paul J Keall, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>ACRF Image X Institute, University of Sydney</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Michael Jackson, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Prince of Wales Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Simon Downes, MASc</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Prince of Wales Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Emily Debrot, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>ACRF Image X Institute, University of Sydney</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Natalie Plant, MHSc</last_name>
    <phone>+61 4 3483 4033</phone>
    <email>natalie.plant@sydney.edu.au</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 16, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 23, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 27, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 23, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 23, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 27, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Radiation Therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Image Guidance</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>De-identified study data may be provided to an external (non-university) research data repository, archive or register with the intention that it be made publicly available for other scientific research. Study data that are provided to an external research data repository will be stored at and managed by the external repository. Data will only be shared with repositories whose function has been reviewed and approved by an accredited Research Integrity/Ethics Committee/board, under a materials transfer agreement with the university.</ipd_description>
    <ipd_time_frame>This data will become available upon completion of the study.</ipd_time_frame>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

