<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04482244</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>19-886</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04482244</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>RCT of CBD for Anxiety in Advanced Breast Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>Randomized, Double-blind Phase II Study of a Single Dose of Cannabidiol (CBD) for Acute Anticipatory Anxiety in Advanced Breast Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Dana-Farber Cancer Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Hans and Mavis Lopater Foundation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Dana-Farber Cancer Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This research study is investigating use of a single dose of cannabidiol (CBD) to help manage
      anticipatory anxiety in participants with advanced breast cancer poised to undergo computed
      tomography (CT) scan to assess tumor burden.

      The name of the study drug(s) are:

      - Cannabidiol (CBD)
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled trial of a single dose of CBD for
      acute anticipatory anxiety in patients with advanced breast cancer undergoing computed
      tomography (CT) scan to assess tumor burden.

      The research study investigates use of CBD to manage anxiety prior to an oncologic imaging
      scan. CBD is a component of the cannabis sativa (marijuana) plant and of hemp. Studies of CBD
      have led to its approval by the Food and Drug Administration for certain childhood seizure
      disorders. Researchers have also been studying the use of CBD to manage anxiety and pain.

      This study is designed to find out if the drug can help reduce anxiety and can safely be
      given to participants with advanced breast cancer who are scheduled for a CT scan.

        -  After screening procedures confirm participation in the research study, participants
           will be &quot;randomized&quot; into one of two study groups: one group will receive CBD, the other
           group will receive a placebo of flavored corn syrup.

        -  Randomization means that participants are put into a group by chance. Neither the
           participant nor the research team will choose participant group assignment.

             -  Participants will have a 66% chance of receiving a single dose of CBD.

             -  Participants will have a 33% chance of receiving a single dose of placebo.

        -  On the day of scheduled CT scans, participants will complete questionnaires before and
           after receiving a single dose of CBD or placebo then undergo computed tomography (CT)
           scan. Participants will be contacted by phone approximately a week later and interviewed
           about study drug consumption and the CT scan experience.

      This study is supported by funding from the Hans and Mavis Lopater Foundation.

      Approximately 50 people are anticipated to take part in this study.

      This research study is a Phase II clinical trial. Phase II clinical trials test the safety
      and effectiveness of an investigational drug to learn whether the drug works in treating a
      specific disease. &quot;Investigational&quot; means that the drug is being studied. The FDA (the U.S.
      Food and Drug Administration) has not approved CBD to manage anxiety but it has been approved
      for use in children with some seizure disorders.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">September 18, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 18, 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 18, 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Anxiety Score-Visual Analog Mood Scale (VAMs) anxiety subscale,</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day of the drug administration pre-dose (T2) and 3 +/- 1 hour after drug administration (T3) up to 1 day</time_frame>
    <description>The change in anxiety score will be calculated for each patient and a Wilcoxon rank sum test will be used to assess whether the change score is different among patients randomized to CBD as compared to placebo.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants With Treatment-Related Adverse Events (PRO-CTCAE™) 5.</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day of the drug administration pre-dose (T2) and 3 +/- 1 hour after drug administration (T3) up to 1 weeks post ingestion</time_frame>
    <description>Measured using the Patient-Reported Outcomes version of the Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (PRO-CTCAE™) and a qualitative assessment, patient-reported side effects and acceptability of taking oral CBD (versus placebo) for managing anticipatory anxiety.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mood Changes</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline through 3 +/- 1 hour after drug administration (T3) up to 1 day</time_frame>
    <description>Measured by VAMS subscales-The Visual Analog Mood Scale (VAMS) a validated in-the-moment measure of eight specific mood states: Afraid, Confused, Sad, Angry, Energetic, Tired, Happy, and Tense. Subjects are asked to mark their mood along this continuum. The measure is scored using a metric ruler</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Nausea Rate</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline through 3 +/- 1 hour after drug administration (T3) up to 1 week</time_frame>
    <description>Measured by the European Organisation for Research and Treatment of Cancer core quality of life questionnaire-nausea subscale.
The EORTC-QLQc30 is a widely used and validated measure of symptom burden.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pain Rate</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline through 3 +/- 1 hour after drug administration (T3) up to 1 day</time_frame>
    <description>Pain levels (as measured by the PEG) 3 +/- 1 hour after study agent administration in patients with advanced cancer.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pain intensity scale (PINS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline , 1 day of the drug administration pre-dose</time_frame>
    <description>pain intensity scale is scored from 0 to 10 (with 10 representing &quot;worst possible&quot; pain).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Advanced Breast Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Anxiety</condition>
  <condition>CBD</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cannabidiol</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>After screening procedures confirm participation in the research study, participants will be randomized one of two groups:
Participants in the experimental arm will complete questionnaires and then receive a single dose of CBD prior to diagnostic CT scan.
Cannabidiol: Oral, per protocol dosage, single dose
Additional questionnaires 2 hours post scan and follow up via phone call 1 week regarding experience</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>After the screening procedures confirm participation in the research study, participants will be randomized one of two groups:
Participants in the placebo arm will complete questionnaire and then receive a single dose of placebo prior to diagnostic CT scan.
Placebo: Oral, per protocol dosage, single dose
Additional questionnaires 2 hours post scan and follow up via phone call 1 week regarding experience</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cannabidiol</intervention_name>
    <description>Liquid taken orally</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cannabidiol</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Epidiolex</other_name>
    <other_name>CBD</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Liquid taken orally</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Diagnosis of Stage IV or metastatic breast cancer

          -  Age ≥21 years.

          -  ECOG performance status ≤2 (Karnofsky ≥60%).

          -  Participants must have adequate organ and marrow function at baseline as defined
             below:

               -  total bilirubin &gt;2 times institutional upper limit of normal (ULN)

               -  AST(SGOT)/ALT(SGPT) ≤3 × institutional ULN

               -  creatinine within normal institutional limits OR

               -  creatinine clearance ≥60 mL/min/1.73 m2 for participants with creatinine levels
                  above institutional normal.

          -  Baseline anxiety as measured by GAD-7 &gt;5

          -  At least mild anxiety typically experienced prior to oncologic scans (as measured by a
             prescreen survey item)

          -  Computed tomography with contrast to assess tumor burden scheduled for day of study

          -  No cannabinoid use (inclusive of cannabis, tetrahydrocannabinol or cannabidiol) within
             24 hours of study drug administration.

          -  No benzodiazepine consumption within 12 hours of study drug administration (e.g.,
             nighttime benzodiazepine use permissible)

          -  No driving for 12 hours following study drug administration.

          -  English proficiency

          -  The effects of cannabidiol (Epidiolex) on the developing human fetus are unknown. For
             this reason and because cannabis is known to be teratogenic, women of child-bearing
             potential must test as nonpregnant prior to entering the study. The study team will
             encourage women of child-bearing age and men to use adequate contraception (hormonal
             or barrier method of birth control; abstinence) prior to study entry and for the
             duration of study participation. Should a woman become pregnant or suspect she is
             pregnant while she or her partner is participating in this study, she should inform
             her treating physician immediately. Men treated or enrolled on this protocol must also
             agree to use adequate contraception prior to the study, for the duration of study
             participation, and for 1 month after cannabidiol (Epidiolex) consumption.

          -  Ability to understand and the willingness to sign a written informed consent document.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  History of allergic reactions attributed to compounds of similar chemical or biologic
             composition to cannabidiol (Epidiolex) or placebo (which contains sesame, corn and
             gluten)

          -  History of current clobazam or valproic acid use

          -  &quot;Severe Risk&quot; AUDIT-C score

          -  Current uncontrolled illness, for instance sepsis, symptomatic congestive heart
             failure, unstable angina pectoris, cardiac arrhythmia

          -  Current use of antiretroviral therapy

          -  Participants with psychiatric illness or social situations that would limit compliance
             with study requirements

          -  Current hepatocellular carcinoma, liver metastases, or documented history of difficult
             to control diabetes
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>21 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ilana Braun, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Dana-Farber Cancer Institute</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Ilana Braun, MD</last_name>
    <phone>(617) 643-0576</phone>
    <email>ibraun@partners.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Dana Farber Cancer Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02115</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ilana M Braun, MD</last_name>
      <phone>617-643-0576</phone>
      <email>Ibraun@partners.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ilana M Braun, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 20, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 21, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 22, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 21, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 21, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 22, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Dana-Farber Cancer Institute</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Ilana Braun, MD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Advanced Breast Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Anxiety</keyword>
  <keyword>CBD</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Anxiety Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Epidiolex</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>The Dana-Farber / Harvard Cancer Center encourages and supports the responsible and ethical sharing of data from clinical trials. De-identified participant data from the final research dataset used in the published manuscript may only be shared under the terms of a Data Use Agreement. Requests may be directed to: [contact information for Sponsor Investigator or designee]. The protocol and statistical analysis plan will be made available on Clinicaltrials.gov only as required by federal regulation or as a condition of awards and agreements supporting the research.</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Statistical Analysis Plan (SAP)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Informed Consent Form (ICF)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>Data can be shared no earlier than 1 year following the date of publication</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>Contact the Belfer Office for Dana-Farber Innovations (BODFI) at innovation@dfci.harvard.edu</ipd_access_criteria>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

