<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04485026</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>WFBCCC 62420</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>P30CA012197</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04485026</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Local Consolidative Radiotherapy for Oligoprogressive in Non-small Cell Lung Carcinoma</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized Phase II Study of Local Consolidative Radiotherapy Versus Standard of Care Second Line Systemic Therapy in Patients With Oligoprogressive NSCLC on Immune Checkpoint Inhibitors</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Wake Forest University Health Sciences</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Wake Forest University Health Sciences</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a randomized phase II study designed to evaluate the effect of local consolidative
      radiation therapy (LCT) to all sites of oligoprogressive disease in patients with metastatic
      non-small cell lung carcinoma who have progressed through first line systemic therapy
      containing an immune checkpoint inhibitor (ICI).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Primary Objective: To compare overall survival (OS) from the time of the time of
      randomization between the treatment and control groups.

      Secondary Objective(s)

        -  To compare the extra-CNS PFS2 (EC-PFS2), defined as the time to extracranial disease
           progression on second line systemic therapy or death from the first day of local
           consolidative radiation therapy (treatment group) or from the start of second line
           therapy (control group).

        -  To evaluate time to initiation of second line systemic therapy or palliative care after
           completion of local consolidative therapy in the treatment group

        -  To compare the toxicities in the treatment and control groups;

        -  To compare overall progression free survival from the time of the first day of local
           consolidative radiation therapy for the treatment group and from the start of second
           line therapy for the control group

        -  To compare the pattern of next progression on second line therapy in the treatment group
           vs the control group.

        -  To evaluate local progression in lesions treated with local consolidative radiation
           therapy.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">September 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2025</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall Survival</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>In each arm overall survival will be defined as the time from randomization to death from any cause. . Patients who are alive at the last follow up at the end of the study will be censored at the date of the last follow up appointment. A comparison of overall survival between the two groups will be made first using bivariate Kaplan-Meier method and then a multivariable Cox proportional hazards model. Participants who do not die during the course of observation will be right censored. Key covariates to be included in multivariable modeling include age, ECOG status, number of progressive treated sites (1 vs 2-4), and PD-L1 status (&gt;=50%; 1%-49%; &lt; 1%).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to Progression Between Both Arms</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Investigators will compare progression after second line of therapy between both arms first using the bivariate Kaplan-Meier method and then a multivariable Cox proportional hazards model age, ECOG status, number of progressive treated sites (1 vs 2-4), and PD-L1 status (&gt;=50%; 1%-49%; &lt; 1%). RECIST version 1.1 criteria will be used to assess for progression.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to Second Line of Systemic Therapy or Palliative Care (Local Consolidative Radiation Therapy Arm Only)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2 years after the completion of intervention</time_frame>
    <description>The time to the second line systemic therapy or palliative care will be defined as the time from the completion of local consolidation therapy to the first day of cycle 1 of a systemic therapy the patient has not yet received OR the date of hospice enrollment, whichever is sooner. Patients experiencing neither of these events will be censored at last follow up visit. Estimated median time to second line therapy (or palliative care) and corresponding 95% confidence interval as well as estimated proportion (and corresponding 95% confidence interval) of the treatment group who have started second-line therapy (or palliative care) by key time points including 6 months, 1 year, and 2 years after the end of local consolidative therapy.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidences of Toxicities</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Toxicities will be evaluated per Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE) version 5.0. Toxicities between the two arms by comparing the proportions with grade 2 or higher, and grade 3 or higher, toxicities of any type at 3, 6, 12, 24 and 36 months following randomization using a chi-square test on the relevant 2x2 contingency table.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression Free Survival</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Progression free survival will be assessed by a modified RECIST version 1.1 criteria. If any individual target lesion meets RECIST v1.1 criteria - specifically an increase in the longest diameter (shortest diameter for lymph node lesions) of at least 20% and 5 mm absolute increase, the patient will be considered to have progression of disease. The criteria for determining pseudoprogression versus true progression and for mild progression while systemic therapy is held for the delivery of local consolidative radiation therapy in the treatment arm will be used for this outcome measure as well. Repeat oligoprogression will also be counted as progressive disease.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to Next Progression Following Local Consolidative Radiation Therapy or Second Line Systemic Therapy</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 3 years</time_frame>
    <description>The pattern of next progression following local consolidation therapy (in treatment group) or second line systemic therapy (in control group) into one of three possible mutually exclusive and exhaustive categories: No progression, repeat oligoprogression or polyprogression, and will compare these patterns between the two groups using a chi-square analysis on the resulting 2x3 contingency table.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of Local of Lesions Treated with Local Consolidative Radiation Therapy That Progress</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Investigators will estimate proportion of lesions treated with local consolidative radiation therapy that experienced local progression (yes/no by study end) and construct a 95% confidence interval around this estimate.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">70</enrollment>
  <condition>Non Small Cell Lung Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Oligoprogressive</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Local Consolidative Radiation Therapy Arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Definitive external beam radiation therapy will be delivered to all sites of progressive disease for all patients. The technique used to deliver radiation therapy will be determined by the treating radiation oncologist.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Standard of Care - Control Arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Second line systemic therapy is at the discretion of the treating medical oncologist.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Radiation</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Local consolidative radiation therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>All local consolidative radiation therapy should be delivered using hypofractionated local consolidative radiation therapy (&gt;2 Gy per fraction). Exceptions may be approved on a case by case basis by the trial principal investigator. Three-dimensional conformal radiotherapy (3D-CRT), intensity modulated radiation therapy (IMRT), volumetric modulated arc therapy (VMAT), stereotactic body radiotherapy (SBRT), stereotactic radiosurgery (SRS), and proton beam therapy (PBT) are all acceptable.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Local Consolidative Radiation Therapy Arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Radiation</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Standard of care radiation therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>Standard of care palliative radiotherapy to symptomatic lesions is permissible. The dose to symptomatic lesions should not exceed 30 Gy in 10 fractions. Brain metastases will be treated with standard of care CNS therapy throughout the study. This may include (but is not limited to) stereotactic radiosurgery, neurosurgical intervention, whole brain radiotherapy</description>
    <arm_group_label>Standard of Care - Control Arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Histologically confirmed diagnosis of non-small cell lung cancer.

          -  Have completed at least 4 cycles of a first line systemic therapy regimen for
             metastatic disease that includes a PD-1 axis targeted agent prior to progression.
             (Patients may be on maintenance/consolidation anti PD-1 axis therapy or have completed
             maintenance anti PD-1 axis therapy within the last 3 months at the time of
             progression).

          -  Initial response of stable disease (SD), partial response (PR) or complete response
             (CR) in at least one lesion prior to progression as defined by RECIST v1.1 criteria.

          -  Oligoprogressive disease in 4 or fewer lesions (Progression of the primary tumor
             and/or regional lymph nodes will be counted as one lesion)

          -  CNS lesions will not count towards the 4 or fewer progressive lesions if they are all
             able to be treated with stereotactic radiosurgery.

          -  Progression by RECIST v1.1 criteria or by PET/CT criteria will be considered
             progressive disease. Both are not required to determine progressive disease.

        Progression for study entry will be defined as by a modified RECIST v1.1 criteria,
        including: Development of a new lesion; increase in the longest diameter (shortest diameter
        for lymph node lesions) of any individual lesion by 20% above nadir and a minimal increase
        of 5 mm.

          -  In cases of PET/CT, the criteria for progression of PET/CT are: Any individual FDG
             avid lesion with an uptake greater than twice that of the surrounding tissue on the
             attenuation corrected image. Any individual FDG avid lesion with greater than 30%
             increase in 18F-FDG SUV peak, with greater than 0.8 SUV units increase in tumor SUV
             from the nadir or the pre-enrollment PET/CT in pattern typical of tumor and not of
             infection/treatment effect per the treating investigator. Visible increase in the
             extent of 18F-FDG uptake of any lesion by 20% in the longest diameter and an absolute
             increase of at least 5mm that is not consistent with treatment effect and/or infection
             per the treating investigator. No more than the following number of progressing
             lesions in any one organ (including any lesions previously treated with radiation
             therapy). Less than or equal to four (4) lung lesions (including primary and
             mediastinal lymph nodes as one lesion). Less than or equal to three (3) liver lesions.
             Less than or equal to three (3) cumulative vertebral lesions

          -  At least one non-progressing lesion, which may not have undergone prior definitive
             local therapy.

          -  All progressive lesions must be amenable to definitive radiation therapy as determined
             by the treating radiation oncologist.

          -  Age of 18 years or greater.

          -  ECOG Performance Status of 0-2.

          -  Negative serum or urine pregnancy test within 2 weeks of the date of enrollment

          -  for women of child-bearing potential.

          -  Ability to understand and the willingness to sign an IRB-approved informed consent
             document (either directly or via a legally authorized representative).

          -  If EGFR and/or ALK status is unknown, the patient is eligible.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Inability to safely treat all progressive lesions with definitive radiation therapy as
             determined by the treating radiation oncologist

          -  Patients may not be receiving any other investigational anti-cancer agents.

          -  Progressive disease in the CNS only.

          -  Known targetable EGFR mutation or EML4-ALK fusion.

          -  Progressive cutaneous metastases.

          -  Progressive disease involving the esophagus, stomach, or intestines.

          -  Malignant pleural or pericardial effusion at the time of oligoprogression.

          -  Thoracentesis/thoracoscopic biopsy for a stable or asymptomatic pleural effusion is
             not required unless the effusion is hypermetabolic on PET/CT or if there are active
             pleural based metastatic lesions at the time of oligoprogression.

          -  Effusions that are too small for thoracentesis/pericardiocentesis are considered
             resolved for the purposes of trial eligibility.

          -  Pregnant women are excluded from this study because radiation therapy has known
             potential for teratogenic or abortifacient effects.

          -  Uncontrolled intercurrent illness including, but not limited to ongoing or active
             infection requiring intravenous antibiotics, symptomatic congestive heart failure,
             unstable angina pectoris, unstable cardiac arrhythmia, or psychiatric illness/social
             situations that would limit compliance with study requirements as determined by the
             treating physician.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Michael Farris, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Wake Forest University Health Sciences</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Study Nurse</last_name>
    <phone>336-713-7748</phone>
    <email>saverill@wakehealth.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Alabama Birmingham Comprehensive Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Birmingham</city>
        <state>Alabama</state>
        <zip>35233</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Wake Forest Baptist Comprehensive Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Winston-Salem</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27157</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Study Nurse</last_name>
      <email>saverill@wakehealth.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Michael Farris, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 20, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 20, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 24, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 20, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 20, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 24, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Non-Small-Cell Lung</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

