<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04482179</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>831532</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>R01DC016800-01A1</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04482179</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Transcranial Magnetic Stimulation and Constraint Induced Language Therapy for Alzheimer Disease</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase II, Randomized, Blinded Study of Transcranial Magnetic Stimulation and Constraint Induced Language Therapy for the Treatment of Chronic Aphasia - Alzheimer Disease Sub-study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Pennsylvania</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institutes of Health (NIH)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute on Deafness and Other Communication Disorders (NIDCD)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Pennsylvania</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Impaired verbal communication is a cardinal symptom of Alzheimer Disease (AD) and the source
      of enormous distress and disability. Effective therapies for this deficit are lacking. In
      light of the emerging literature demonstrating that Transcranial Magnetic Stimulation (TMS)
      improves general cognition in subjects with Alzheimer Disease (AD), the investigators propose
      to study the effectiveness of TMS as a therapy for impaired verbal communication. The
      hypothesis to be tested is that TMS combined with Constraint Induced Language Therapy (CILT)
      improves verbal communication more than sham TMS and CILT. A second aim is to use
      state-of-the-art neuroimaging to understand the mechanisms underlying any beneficial effect
      of the treatment.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      TMS is a technique by which a brief electrical current is induced in brain tissue causing a
      brief suppression of the excitability of the underlying tissue; the technique, which was
      introduced in the 1980s and has been extensively used around the world, has been shown to
      transiently improve or disrupt specific cognitive operations. To achieve this end, a coil is
      positioned against the subject's head. The delivery of a single pulse begins with the
      discharge of current from a capacitor into a circular or figure-of-eight coil; this
      electrical current generates a brief magnetic field of up to 2.2 Tesla. As the pulse of
      electricity has a rise time of 0.2 ms. and a duration of 1 ms., the magnetic field changes in
      intensity quite rapidly. Because the magnetic field passes freely through the scalp, skull,
      and meninges, the flux in the magnetic field induces a small electric field in the brain that
      transiently alters neural activity.

      TMS may be delivered in a variety of ways. The investigators propose to use 10 Hz TMS; that
      is, TMS pulses will be delivered at a frequency of 10/second, for a total of 1200 pulses.
      Using the figure-of-eight coil to be employed here, TMS is thought to affect activity in
      approximately 1 cubic cm. of cortex. Many investigators have employed TMS for AD with a
      frequency of 10 Hz and most have delivered 1200 pulses per session.

      The baseline phase will consist of 3 sessions, each lasting 1-2 hours depending on the
      stamina of the subject. The point of the baseline testing is to characterize the subject's
      language function. To that end, a number of standard language and neuropsychological tasks
      will be administered. These include the Western Aphasia Battery, Pyramids and Palm Trees
      test, Figural Fluency Test, word and non-word repetition tasks, spontaneous narrative
      production, CILT stimulus naming, and the Repeatable Battery for the Assessment of
      Neuropsychological Status. Additionally, during the baseline, subjects will undergo MRI of
      the brain or, if they have a contraindication to MRI, a CAT scan of the head. No contrast
      will be used.

      In the treatment phase, there will be 10 TMS sessions over 2 consecutive weeks in which 30
      two-second stimulation trains of 10 Hz TMS will be delivered every 30 seconds to the left
      inferior pars triangularis and to the left posterior superior left temporal gyrus at 100%
      motor threshold. There will be a total of 600 pulses to each site in each session for a total
      of 1200 pulses per session. Each TMS treatment session will be immediately followed by a
      60-90 minute session of CILT.

      There will be two 3-month post-treatment visits and two 6-month post-treatment visits in
      which the full battery of language and cognitive assessments will be repeated. Subjects who
      are able to undergo MRI scanning will have anatomic and fMRI scans at the first 6-month
      post-treatment visit.

      The investigators will pair TMS with CILT which has been shown to have positive outcomes in
      post-stroke aphasia. CILT invokes use-dependent learning in communicative interactions by
      requiring spoken output and restricting use of alternative forms of communication, such as
      gestures. The investigators will use a dual card-matching task modeled after Maher et al. As
      in the original CILT design, the participant interacts verbally with a conversational partner
      (here, the speech language pathologist), in turn requesting a card of given description and
      complying with the partner's request. In this way, the treatment targets both production and
      comprehension. Moreover, as verbal targets increase in linguistic complexity across the
      protocol (&quot;a ball&quot;, &quot;throw a ball&quot;; &quot;Do you have a ball&quot;?), a variety of lexical and phrasal
      structures are targeted. Studies of CILT have reported gains on multiple language behaviors,
      supporting its broad engagement of the language network.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 19, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Participants will be randomized to either TMS or sham TMS in a 2:1 allocation ratio.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>The individual administering TMS will keep the master file of subject assignments, but all other individuals in contact with the subject or their data will be unaware of group assignment. Participants will not be informed of their assignment to active or sham status.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in WAB-AQ</measure>
    <time_frame>6-months post-treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Overall change in Western Aphasia Battery - Aphasia Quotient (WAB-AQ) between the first baseline visit and the 6-month follow-up visit</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in PNT</measure>
    <time_frame>6-months post-treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Change in naming accuracy on the Philadelphia Naming Test (PNT) between the first baseline visit and the 6-month follow-up visit.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Alzheimer Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Active TMS</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>There will be 10 TMS sessions over 2 consecutive weeks in which 30 two-second stimulation trains of 10 Hz TMS will be delivered every 30 seconds to the left inferior pars triangularis and to the left posterior superior left temporal gyrus. Each TMS treatment session will be immediately followed by a 60-90 minute session of Constrained Induced Language Therapy (CILT).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sham TMS</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Sham Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>There will be 10 TMS sessions over 2 consecutive weeks in which 30 two-second stimulation trains of 10 Hz sham TMS will be delivered every 30 seconds to the left inferior pars triangularis and to the left posterior superior left temporal gyrus. Sham TMS will be administered with a sham TMS coil that looks and sounds like the active coil but does not generate a magnetic field. Each TMS treatment session will be immediately followed by a 60-90 minute session of Constrained Induced Language Therapy (CILT).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Active TMS</intervention_name>
    <description>Active TMS will be delivered at 100% motor threshold</description>
    <arm_group_label>Active TMS</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>CILT</intervention_name>
    <description>60-90 minutes of CILT will be administered during each treatment session</description>
    <arm_group_label>Active TMS</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Sham TMS</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Constraint Induced Language Therapy</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sham TMS</intervention_name>
    <description>Sham TMS will be administered</description>
    <arm_group_label>Sham TMS</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  A diagnosis of mild-moderate AD as defined by the National Institute of Aging -
             Alzheimer's Disease and Related Disorders Association criteria

          -  Mild-moderate cognitive impairment, indicated by Mini-Mental Status Exam (MMSE) scores
             between 23 and 15 inclusive

          -  Must be right handed as defined by the Edinburgh Handedness Inventory

          -  Must be a native English speaker

          -  Must be able to understand the nature of the study, and give informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  History of stroke

          -  History of seizure

          -  History of any other significant neurologic disease (e.g., ALS)

          -  Significant depression as defined by the Geriatric Depression Scale.

          -  Any significant medical disorder that, in the view of the investigators, could
             threaten the subject's ability to complete the study (e.g., cancer, significant
             cardiac disease)

          -  Any contraindications to TMS, including uncontrolled seizures, previous brain surgery,
             and history of tinnitus
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>60 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>85 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>H. Branch Coslett, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Pennsylvania</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Daniela Sacchetti, MS</last_name>
    <phone>215-573-8485</phone>
    <email>danielas@pennmedicine.upenn.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Samuel Cason, MA</last_name>
    <phone>215-573-4336</phone>
    <email>sacason@pennmedicine.upenn.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Pennsylvania</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19104</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Research Coordinator</last_name>
      <phone>215-573-4336</phone>
      <email>braintms@pennmedicine.upenn.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Daniela Sacchetti, MS</last_name>
      <phone>215-573-8485</phone>
      <email>danielas@pennmedicine.upenn.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>H Branch Coslett, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Roy H Hamilton, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hamilton RH, Chrysikou EG, Coslett B. Mechanisms of aphasia recovery after stroke and the role of noninvasive brain stimulation. Brain Lang. 2011 Jul;118(1-2):40-50. doi: 10.1016/j.bandl.2011.02.005. Epub 2011 Apr 2. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21459427</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Medina J, Norise C, Faseyitan O, Coslett HB, Turkeltaub PE, Hamilton RH. Finding the Right Words: Transcranial Magnetic Stimulation Improves Discourse Productivity in Non-fluent Aphasia After Stroke. Aphasiology. 2012 Sep 1;26(9):1153-1168. Epub 2012 Aug 29.</citation>
    <PMID>23280015</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Seniów J, Waldowski K, Leśniak M, Iwański S, Czepiel W, Członkowska A. Transcranial magnetic stimulation combined with speech and language training in early aphasia rehabilitation: a randomized double-blind controlled pilot study. Top Stroke Rehabil. 2013 May-Jun;20(3):250-61. doi: 10.1310/tsr2003-250.</citation>
    <PMID>23841973</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Silvanto J, Muggleton N, Walsh V. State-dependency in brain stimulation studies of perception and cognition. Trends Cogn Sci. 2008 Dec;12(12):447-54. doi: 10.1016/j.tics.2008.09.004. Epub 2008 Oct 24.</citation>
    <PMID>18951833</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ayache SS, Farhat WH, Zouari HG, Hosseini H, Mylius V, Lefaucheur JP. Stroke rehabilitation using noninvasive cortical stimulation: motor deficit. Expert Rev Neurother. 2012 Aug;12(8):949-72. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23002939</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kakuda W, Abo M, Shimizu M, Sasanuma J, Okamoto T, Yokoi A, Taguchi K, Mitani S, Harashima H, Urushidani N, Urashima M; NEURO Investigators. A multi-center study on low-frequency rTMS combined with intensive occupational therapy for upper limb hemiparesis in post-stroke patients. J Neuroeng Rehabil. 2012 Jan 20;9(1):4. doi: 10.1186/1743-0003-9-4.</citation>
    <PMID>22264239</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Koganemaru S, Mima T, Thabit MN, Ikkaku T, Shimada K, Kanematsu M, Takahashi K, Fawi G, Takahashi R, Fukuyama H, Domen K. Recovery of upper-limb function due to enhanced use-dependent plasticity in chronic stroke patients. Brain. 2010 Nov;133(11):3373-84. doi: 10.1093/brain/awq193. Epub 2010 Aug 5.</citation>
    <PMID>20688810</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shewan CM, Kertesz A. Reliability and validity characteristics of the Western Aphasia Battery (WAB). J Speech Hear Disord. 1980 Aug;45(3):308-24.</citation>
    <PMID>7412225</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mirman D, Chen Q, Zhang Y, Wang Z, Faseyitan OK, Coslett HB, Schwartz MF. Neural organization of spoken language revealed by lesion-symptom mapping. Nat Commun. 2015 Apr 16;6:6762. doi: 10.1038/ncomms7762.</citation>
    <PMID>25879574</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Howard, D., &amp; Patterson, K. E. (1992). The Pyramids and Palm Trees Test: A Test of Semantic Access from Words and Pictures. Thames Valley Test Company</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nicholas LE, Brookshire RH. A system for quantifying the informativeness and efficiency of the connected speech of adults with aphasia. J Speech Hear Res. 1993 Apr;36(2):338-50.</citation>
    <PMID>8487525</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Foygel, D., &amp; Dell, G. S. (2000). Models of impaired lexical access in speech production. Journal of Memory and Language, 43(2), 182-216.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pulvermüller F, Neininger B, Elbert T, Mohr B, Rockstroh B, Koebbel P, Taub E. Constraint-induced therapy of chronic aphasia after stroke. Stroke. 2001 Jul;32(7):1621-6.</citation>
    <PMID>11441210</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Medaglia JD, Huang W, Segarra S, Olm C, Gee J, Grossman M, Ribeiro A, McMillan CT, Bassett DS. Brain network efficiency is influenced by the pathologic source of corticobasal syndrome. Neurology. 2017 Sep 26;89(13):1373-1381. doi: 10.1212/WNL.0000000000004324. Epub 2017 Aug 4.</citation>
    <PMID>28779011</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ahmed MA, Darwish ES, Khedr EM, El Serogy YM, Ali AM. Effects of low versus high frequencies of repetitive transcranial magnetic stimulation on cognitive function and cortical excitability in Alzheimer's dementia. J Neurol. 2012 Jan;259(1):83-92. doi: 10.1007/s00415-011-6128-4. Epub 2011 Jun 14.</citation>
    <PMID>21671144</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bentwich J, Dobronevsky E, Aichenbaum S, Shorer R, Peretz R, Khaigrekht M, Marton RG, Rabey JM. Beneficial effect of repetitive transcranial magnetic stimulation combined with cognitive training for the treatment of Alzheimer's disease: a proof of concept study. J Neural Transm (Vienna). 2011 Mar;118(3):463-71. doi: 10.1007/s00702-010-0578-1. Epub 2011 Jan 19.</citation>
    <PMID>21246222</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Brem, A. K., Schilberg, L., Freitas, C., Atkinson, N., Seligson, E., &amp; Pascual-Leone, A. (2013). Effects of cognitive training and rTMS in Alzheimer's disease. Alzheimer's &amp; Dementia: The Journal of the Alzheimer's Association, 9(4), P664.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Buckner RL, Sepulcre J, Talukdar T, Krienen FM, Liu H, Hedden T, Andrews-Hanna JR, Sperling RA, Johnson KA. Cortical hubs revealed by intrinsic functional connectivity: mapping, assessment of stability, and relation to Alzheimer's disease. J Neurosci. 2009 Feb 11;29(6):1860-73. doi: 10.1523/JNEUROSCI.5062-08.2009.</citation>
    <PMID>19211893</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cheng CPW, Wong CSM, Lee KK, Chan APK, Yeung JWF, Chan WC. Effects of repetitive transcranial magnetic stimulation on improvement of cognition in elderly patients with cognitive impairment: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Int J Geriatr Psychiatry. 2018 Jan;33(1):e1-e13. doi: 10.1002/gps.4726. Epub 2017 May 11. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>28493371</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cotelli M, Calabria M, Manenti R, Rosini S, Zanetti O, Cappa SF, Miniussi C. Improved language performance in Alzheimer disease following brain stimulation. J Neurol Neurosurg Psychiatry. 2011 Jul;82(7):794-7. doi: 10.1136/jnnp.2009.197848. Epub 2010 Jun 23.</citation>
    <PMID>20574108</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cotelli M, Manenti R, Cappa SF, Geroldi C, Zanetti O, Rossini PM, Miniussi C. Effect of transcranial magnetic stimulation on action naming in patients with Alzheimer disease. Arch Neurol. 2006 Nov;63(11):1602-4.</citation>
    <PMID>17101829</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Deters KD, Nho K, Risacher SL, Kim S, Ramanan VK, Crane PK, Apostolova LG, Saykin AJ; Alzheimer's Disease Neuroimaging Initiative. Genome-wide association study of language performance in Alzheimer's disease. Brain Lang. 2017 Sep;172:22-29. doi: 10.1016/j.bandl.2017.04.008. Epub 2017 May 31.</citation>
    <PMID>28577822</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Drumond Marra HL, Myczkowski ML, Maia Memória C, Arnaut D, Leite Ribeiro P, Sardinha Mansur CG, Lancelote Alberto R, Boura Bellini B, Alves Fernandes da Silva A, Tortella G, Ciampi de Andrade D, Teixeira MJ, Forlenza OV, Marcolin MA. Transcranial Magnetic Stimulation to Address Mild Cognitive Impairment in the Elderly: A Randomized Controlled Study. Behav Neurol. 2015;2015:287843. doi: 10.1155/2015/287843. Epub 2015 Jun 16.</citation>
    <PMID>26160997</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Engels MM, Stam CJ, van der Flier WM, Scheltens P, de Waal H, van Straaten EC. Declining functional connectivity and changing hub locations in Alzheimer's disease: an EEG study. BMC Neurol. 2015 Aug 20;15:145. doi: 10.1186/s12883-015-0400-7.</citation>
    <PMID>26289045</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Faroqi‐Shah, Y., &amp; Virion, C. R. (2009). Constraint‐induced language therapy for agrammatism: Role of grammaticality constraints. Aphasiology, 23(7-8), 977-988.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Folstein MF, Folstein SE, McHugh PR. &quot;Mini-mental state&quot;. A practical method for grading the cognitive state of patients for the clinician. J Psychiatr Res. 1975 Nov;12(3):189-98.</citation>
    <PMID>1202204</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fornito A, Zalesky A, Breakspear M. The connectomics of brain disorders. Nat Rev Neurosci. 2015 Mar;16(3):159-72. doi: 10.1038/nrn3901. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25697159</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Haffen E, Chopard G, Pretalli JB, Magnin E, Nicolier M, Monnin J, Galmiche J, Rumbach L, Pazart L, Sechter D, Vandel P. A case report of daily left prefrontal repetitive transcranial magnetic stimulation (rTMS) as an adjunctive treatment for Alzheimer disease. Brain Stimul. 2012 Jul;5(3):264-266. doi: 10.1016/j.brs.2011.03.003. Epub 2011 Mar 30.</citation>
    <PMID>22037125</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hameister, I., Nickels, L., Abel, S., &amp; Croot, K. (2017). &quot;Do you have mowing the lawn?&quot;-improvements in word retrieval and grammar following constraint-induced language therapy in primary progressive aphasia. Aphasiology, 31(3), 308-331.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hodges JR, Salmon DP, Butters N. Semantic memory impairment in Alzheimer's disease: failure of access or degraded knowledge? Neuropsychologia. 1992 Apr;30(4):301-14.</citation>
    <PMID>1603295</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Koch G, Bonnì S, Pellicciari MC, Casula EP, Mancini M, Esposito R, Ponzo V, Picazio S, Di Lorenzo F, Serra L, Motta C, Maiella M, Marra C, Cercignani M, Martorana A, Caltagirone C, Bozzali M. Transcranial magnetic stimulation of the precuneus enhances memory and neural activity in prodromal Alzheimer's disease. Neuroimage. 2018 Apr 1;169:302-311. doi: 10.1016/j.neuroimage.2017.12.048. Epub 2017 Dec 19.</citation>
    <PMID>29277405</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lee J, Choi BH, Oh E, Sohn EH, Lee AY. Treatment of Alzheimer's Disease with Repetitive Transcranial Magnetic Stimulation Combined with Cognitive Training: A Prospective, Randomized, Double-Blind, Placebo-Controlled Study. J Clin Neurol. 2016 Jan;12(1):57-64. doi: 10.3988/jcn.2016.12.1.57. Epub 2015 Sep 11.</citation>
    <PMID>26365021</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Martin A, Fedio P. Word production and comprehension in Alzheimer's disease: the breakdown of semantic knowledge. Brain Lang. 1983 May;19(1):124-41.</citation>
    <PMID>6860932</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Medaglia JD, Lynall ME, Bassett DS. Cognitive network neuroscience. J Cogn Neurosci. 2015 Aug;27(8):1471-91. doi: 10.1162/jocn_a_00810. Epub 2015 Mar 24. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25803596</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mohs RC, Rosen WG, Davis KL. The Alzheimer's disease assessment scale: an instrument for assessing treatment efficacy. Psychopharmacol Bull. 1983;19(3):448-50.</citation>
    <PMID>6635122</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Norise C, Hamilton RH. Non-invasive Brain Stimulation in the Treatment of Post-stroke and Neurodegenerative Aphasia: Parallels, Differences, and Lessons Learned. Front Hum Neurosci. 2017 Jan 23;10:675. doi: 10.3389/fnhum.2016.00675. eCollection 2016. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>28167904</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rabey JM, Dobronevsky E. Repetitive transcranial magnetic stimulation (rTMS) combined with cognitive training is a safe and effective modality for the treatment of Alzheimer's disease: clinical experience. J Neural Transm (Vienna). 2016 Dec;123(12):1449-1455. doi: 10.1007/s00702-016-1606-6. Epub 2016 Sep 8.</citation>
    <PMID>27631152</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rabey JM, Dobronevsky E, Aichenbaum S, Gonen O, Marton RG, Khaigrekht M. Repetitive transcranial magnetic stimulation combined with cognitive training is a safe and effective modality for the treatment of Alzheimer's disease: a randomized, double-blind study. J Neural Transm (Vienna). 2013 May;120(5):813-9. doi: 10.1007/s00702-012-0902-z. Epub 2012 Oct 18.</citation>
    <PMID>23076723</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rossi S, Hallett M, Rossini PM, Pascual-Leone A; Safety of TMS Consensus Group. Safety, ethical considerations, and application guidelines for the use of transcranial magnetic stimulation in clinical practice and research. Clin Neurophysiol. 2009 Dec;120(12):2008-2039. doi: 10.1016/j.clinph.2009.08.016. Epub 2009 Oct 14. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19833552</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rubinov M, Sporns O. Complex network measures of brain connectivity: uses and interpretations. Neuroimage. 2010 Sep;52(3):1059-69. doi: 10.1016/j.neuroimage.2009.10.003. Epub 2009 Oct 9.</citation>
    <PMID>19819337</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Saur D, Lange R, Baumgaertner A, Schraknepper V, Willmes K, Rijntjes M, Weiller C. Dynamics of language reorganization after stroke. Brain. 2006 Jun;129(Pt 6):1371-84. Epub 2006 Apr 25.</citation>
    <PMID>16638796</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Stam CJ. Modern network science of neurological disorders. Nat Rev Neurosci. 2014 Oct;15(10):683-95. doi: 10.1038/nrn3801. Epub 2014 Sep 4. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25186238</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Szatloczki G, Hoffmann I, Vincze V, Kalman J, Pakaski M. Speaking in Alzheimer's Disease, is That an Early Sign? Importance of Changes in Language Abilities in Alzheimer's Disease. Front Aging Neurosci. 2015 Oct 20;7:195. doi: 10.3389/fnagi.2015.00195. eCollection 2015. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26539107</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Vacas SM, Stella F, Loureiro JC, Simões do Couto F, Oliveira-Maia AJ, Forlenza OV. Noninvasive brain stimulation for behavioural and psychological symptoms of dementia: A systematic review and meta-analysis. Int J Geriatr Psychiatry. 2019 Sep;34(9):1336-1345. doi: 10.1002/gps.5003. Epub 2018 Oct 17.</citation>
    <PMID>30246461</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>van den Heuvel MP, Hulshoff Pol HE. Exploring the brain network: a review on resting-state fMRI functional connectivity. Eur Neuropsychopharmacol. 2010 Aug;20(8):519-34. doi: 10.1016/j.euroneuro.2010.03.008. Epub 2010 May 14. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20471808</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>van den Heuvel MP, Sporns O. Network hubs in the human brain. Trends Cogn Sci. 2013 Dec;17(12):683-96. doi: 10.1016/j.tics.2013.09.012. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24231140</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wu Y, Xu W, Liu X, Xu Q, Tang L, Wu S. Adjunctive treatment with high frequency repetitive transcranial magnetic stimulation for the behavioral and psychological symptoms of patients with Alzheimer's disease: a randomized, double-blind, sham-controlled study. Shanghai Arch Psychiatry. 2015 Oct;27(5):280-8. doi: 10.11919/j.issn.1002-0829.215107.</citation>
    <PMID>26977125</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 17, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 17, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 22, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 17, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 17, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 22, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Pennsylvania</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>H. Branch Coslett</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Alzheimer Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

