<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04481217</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>38RC20.055</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2020-A00452-37</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04481217</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Cognitive Factors Mediating the Relationship Between Childhood Trauma and Auditory Hallucinations in Schizophrenia</brief_title>
  <acronym>HADITRYOS</acronym>
  <official_title>The Mediating Role of Dissociative Symptoms and Early Maladaptive Schemas in the Relationship Between Childhood Trauma and Auditory Hallucinations in Schizophrenia</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University Hospital, Grenoble</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University Hospital, Grenoble</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      BACKGROUND A first generation of research has demonstrated strong associations between trauma
      suffered in childhood (physical, psychological and sexual violence) and having schizophrenia,
      and more specifically to experience &quot;hearing voices&quot; (acoustic-verbal hallucinations, AVH).

      A second generation of research is currently examining the cognitive and affective processes
      likely to play a mediating role in this association. These mediators appear to include early
      maladaptive personality patterns and dissociative experiences. Although these factors have
      most often been explored separately, recent research indicates that they could be associated,
      and thus contribute to AVH. More specifically, another study has shown that the association
      between childhood trauma and predisposition to AVH is not direct but depends on cognitive
      factors including the impact of violence suffered during childhood on early maladaptive
      schemas (for example, interpersonal functioning centred on &quot;subjugation&quot;, &quot;abandonment&quot;,
      &quot;vulnerability&quot;) and dissociation. However, this study was carried out on a non-clinical
      sample of subjects with a predisposition to AVH

      OBJECTIVES Here, aim is at testing a structural model of AVH, childhood trauma, early
      maladaptive schemas and dissociative symptoms in large sample patients diagnosed with
      schizophrenia and AVH (n=350).

      Secondary objectives are (i) to carry out exploratory analyzes which will allow investigators
      to test in the model the role of all the early patterns described by Jeffrey Young instead of
      targeting only the schemes that are part of the model tested in previous study as the one by
      Bortolon and colleagues, (ii) compare the quality of the adjustment of the confirmatory model
      to the quality of the adjustment of the exploratory model.

      METHODS

      A cross-sectional, multicenter design (3 centres) will be performed. Patients included will
      be diagnosed with schizophrenia or schizoaffective disorder, and experience AVH at the time
      of the inclusion (n= 350). All will be inpatients. The study consists of one single visit in
      which the subjects will receive all the self-reported questionnaires to be completed:

        1. General information sheet (socio-demographic and clinical data)

        2. Questionnaire on traumatic childhood experiences: Childhood trauma questionnaire

        3. Questionnaire on early maladaptive schemas: The Young schema questionnaire short form

        4. Questionnaire about dissociative experiences: Dissociative experiences scale

        5. Questionnaire on hallucinations: Launay - Slade hallucination scale and Cardiff
           Anomalous Perceptions Scale.

      All questionnaires have been validated in French.

      ANALYSES Structural equation model performed additional analysis using Partial Least Squares
      Structural Equation Modelling (PLS-SEM).

      The primary endpoint corresponds to significant associations (significance threshold &lt;0.05)
      between the variables as in the model described by Bortolon and colleagues. The quality of
      the model (both measurement and structural model) will be assessed using a fit quality
      measure.

      The secondary endpoints are significant associations between the different variables (p
      &lt;0.05) and the model quality assessed with a quality measure of the fit.

      HYPOTHESES It's hypothesized that the association between childhood trauma and predisposition
      to AVH is not direct, but depends on the impact of violence suffered during childhood on
      early maladaptive schemas (for example, interpersonal functioning centred on &quot;subjugation&quot;,
      &quot;abandonment&quot;, &quot;vulnerability&quot;) and dissociative symptoms in patients with schizophrenia.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">July 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Auditory hallucinations measured by the Launay-Slade Hallucination Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline</time_frame>
    <description>The auditory hallucinations measured by the Launay-Slade Hallucination Scale, which is a self-report scale developed to measure predisposition to hallucinations.
Three items were designed to measure verbal hallucinations, which are measured using a 5-point Likert scale, from 0 to 4 (0 = &quot;definitely does not apply to me,&quot; 1 = &quot;possibly does not apply to me,&quot; 2 = &quot;unsure,&quot; 3 = &quot;possibly applies to me,&quot; and 4 = &quot;definitely applies to me&quot;).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Defensive dissociation assessed by the Dissociative experiences scale (DES)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Defensive dissociation assessed by the Dissociative experiences scale (DES). The DES is a 28-item developed to measure dissociative experiences. Respondents are asked to rate how often they experienced each of the 28 described situation compared to other people. The scale was composed of 11 boxes that the participants had to tick (from &quot;much less than others&quot; to &quot;much more than others&quot;).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Early maladaptive schema &quot;Abandonment&quot;, which is measured by the young schema questionnaire short form (SQ-SF)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline</time_frame>
    <description>The early maladaptive schema &quot;Abandonment&quot;, which is measured by the young schema questionnaire short form (SQ-SF). The SQ-SF is a 75-item, self-report inventory designed to measure 15 EMS proposed by Young. Each item is rated on a 6-point scale (from 1 = &quot;completely untrue of me&quot; to 6 = &quot;describes me perfectly&quot;). Higher scores indicate a greater presence of a maladaptive schema for the respondent.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The early maladaptive schema &quot;Self-sacrifice&quot;, which is measured by the young schema questionnaire short form (SQ-SF)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline</time_frame>
    <description>The early maladaptive schema &quot;Self-sacrifice&quot;, which is measured by the young schema questionnaire short form (SQ-SF). The SQ-SF is a 75-item, self-report inventory designed to measure 15 EMS proposed by Young. Each item is rated on a 6-point scale (from 1 = &quot;completely untrue of me&quot; to 6 = &quot;describes me perfectly&quot;). Higher scores indicate a greater presence of a maladaptive schema for the respondent.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The early maladaptive schema &quot;Vulnerability&quot;, which is measured by the young schema questionnaire short form (SQ-SF)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline</time_frame>
    <description>The early maladaptive schema &quot;Vulnerability&quot;, which is measured by the young schema questionnaire short form (SQ-SF). The SQ-SF is a 75-item, self-report inventory designed to measure 15 EMS proposed by Young. Each item is rated on a 6-point scale (from 1 = &quot;completely untrue of me&quot; to 6 = &quot;describes me perfectly&quot;). Higher scores indicate a greater presence of a maladaptive schema for the respondent.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The early maladaptive schema &quot;Subjugation&quot;, which is measured by the young schema questionnaire short form (SQ-SF)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline</time_frame>
    <description>The early maladaptive schema &quot;Subjugation&quot;, which is measured by the young schema questionnaire short form (SQ-SF). The SQ-SF is a 75-item, self-report inventory designed to measure 15 EMS proposed by Young. Each item is rated on a 6-point scale (from 1 = &quot;completely untrue of me&quot; to 6 = &quot;describes me perfectly&quot;). Higher scores indicate a greater presence of a maladaptive schema for the respondent.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">350</enrollment>
  <condition>Schizophrenia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Schizophrenia</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Self-questionnaires battery</intervention_name>
    <description>Childhood trauma questionnaire (Bernstein, Ahluvalia, Pogge, &amp; Handelsman, 1997; Bernstein et al., 2003)
The Young schema questionnaire short form (SQ-SF ; Cottraux &amp; Black, 2006; Young, 1998).
Dissociative experiences scale (Laroi et al., 2013).
Launay-Slade hallucination scale (Bentall &amp; Slade, 1985; Launay &amp; Slade, 1981)
Cardiff Anomalous Perceptions Scale (Bell et al., 2006)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Schizophrenia</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Socio-demographic screening</intervention_name>
    <description>age; gender; education; highest diploma; job; marital status; living place</description>
    <arm_group_label>Schizophrenia</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion criteria:

          -  Schizophrenia or schizo-affective disorder

          -  Auditory hallucinations

          -  Fluent in French

          -  Gave informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Agitation or suicide risk

          -  Involuntary Hospitalization

          -  Neurologic condition

          -  No informed consent
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>60 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Clément DONDE</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>CHU Grenoble Alpes</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Clément DONDE</last_name>
    <phone>+33 (0)4 76 76 39 86</phone>
    <email>cdondecoquelet@chu-grenoble.fr</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Grenoble University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>La Tronche</city>
        <zip>38700</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Clément DONDÉ, MD PhD</last_name>
      <email>cdondecoquelet@chu-grenoble.fr</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Daalman K, Diederen KM, Derks EM, van Lutterveld R, Kahn RS, Sommer IE. Childhood trauma and auditory verbal hallucinations. Psychol Med. 2012 Dec;42(12):2475-84. doi: 10.1017/S0033291712000761. Epub 2012 Apr 16.</citation>
    <PMID>22716897</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Varese F, Smeets F, Drukker M, Lieverse R, Lataster T, Viechtbauer W, Read J, van Os J, Bentall RP. Childhood adversities increase the risk of psychosis: a meta-analysis of patient-control, prospective- and cross-sectional cohort studies. Schizophr Bull. 2012 Jun;38(4):661-71. doi: 10.1093/schbul/sbs050. Epub 2012 Mar 29. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22461484</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Williams J, Bucci S, Berry K, Varese F. Psychological mediators of the association between childhood adversities and psychosis: A systematic review. Clin Psychol Rev. 2018 Nov;65:175-196. doi: 10.1016/j.cpr.2018.05.009. Epub 2018 Jun 2.</citation>
    <PMID>30243100</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bortolon C, Seillé J, Raffard S. Exploration of trauma, dissociation, maladaptive schemas and auditory hallucinations in a French sample. Cogn Neuropsychiatry. 2017 Nov;22(6):468-485. doi: 10.1080/13546805.2017.1387524. Epub 2017 Oct 12.</citation>
    <PMID>29023198</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Evans GJ, Reid G, Preston P, Palmier-Claus J, Sellwood W. Trauma and psychosis: The mediating role of self-concept clarity and dissociation. Psychiatry Res. 2015 Aug 30;228(3):626-32. doi: 10.1016/j.psychres.2015.04.053. Epub 2015 Jun 11.</citation>
    <PMID>26099655</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bell V. A community of one: social cognition and auditory verbal hallucinations. PLoS Biol. 2013 Dec;11(12):e1001723. doi: 10.1371/journal.pbio.1001723. Epub 2013 Dec 3. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24311984</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bentall RP, Slade PD. Reality testing and auditory hallucinations: a signal detection analysis. Br J Clin Psychol. 1985 Sep;24 ( Pt 3):159-69.</citation>
    <PMID>4052663</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Larøi F, Marczewski P, Van der Linden M. Further evidence of the multi-dimensionality of hallucinatory predisposition: factor structure of a modified version of the Launay-Slade Hallucinations Scale in a normal sample. Eur Psychiatry. 2004 Feb;19(1):15-20.</citation>
    <PMID>14969776</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cottraux J, &amp; Blackburn IM. Psychothérapies cognitives des troubles de la personnalité. NPG Neurologie-Psychiatrie-Gériatrie. 2007; 7(37), 41.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Larøi F, Billieux J, Defeldre A-C, Ceschi, G, Van der Linden M. Factorial structure and psychometric properties of the French adaptation of the Dissociative Experiences Scale (DES) in non-clinical participants. Revue Européenne de Psychologie Appliquée/European Review of Applied Psychology. 2013; 63(4): 203-208.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Launay G, Slade P. The measurement of hallucinatory predisposition in male and female prisoners. Personality and Individual Differences. 1981; 2(3): 221-234.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mauchand P, Lachenal-Chevallet K, Cottraux J. [Empirical validation of the Young Schema Questionnaire-Short Form (YSQ-S2) in borderline personality disorder and control subjects]. Encephale. 2011 Apr;37(2):138-43. doi: 10.1016/j.encep.2010.04.014. Epub 2010 Jul 3. French.</citation>
    <PMID>21482232</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Briere J, Scott C. Assessment of trauma symptoms in eating-disordered populations. Eat Disord. 2007 Jul-Sep;15(4):347-58. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>17710571</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Darves-Bornoz JM, Degiovanni A, Gaillard P. Validation of a French version of the Dissociative Experiences Scale in a rape-victim population. Can J Psychiatry. 1999 Apr;44(3):271-5.</citation>
    <PMID>10225129</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Garrison JR, Moseley P, Alderson-Day B, Smailes D, Fernyhough C, Simons JS. Testing continuum models of psychosis: No reduction in source monitoring ability in healthy individuals prone to auditory hallucinations. Cortex. 2017 Jun;91:197-207. doi: 10.1016/j.cortex.2016.11.011. Epub 2016 Nov 22.</citation>
    <PMID>27964941</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Johns LC, Kompus K, Connell M, Humpston C, Lincoln TM, Longden E, Preti A, Alderson-Day B, Badcock JC, Cella M, Fernyhough C, McCarthy-Jones S, Peters E, Raballo A, Scott J, Siddi S, Sommer IE, Larøi F. Auditory verbal hallucinations in persons with and without a need for care. Schizophr Bull. 2014 Jul;40 Suppl 4:S255-64. doi: 10.1093/schbul/sbu005. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24936085</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Perona-Garcelán S, Carrascoso-López F, García-Montes JM, Ductor-Recuerda MJ, López Jiménez AM, Vallina-Fernández O, Pérez-Álvarez M, Gómez-Gómez MT. Dissociative experiences as mediators between childhood trauma and auditory hallucinations. J Trauma Stress. 2012 Jun;25(3):323-9. doi: 10.1002/jts.21693. Epub 2012 May 15.</citation>
    <PMID>22589015</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Perona-Garcelan S, Garcia-Montes JM, Cuevas-Yust C, Perez-Alvarez M, Ductor-Recuerda MJ, Salas-Azcona R, Gomez-Gomez MT. A preliminary exploration of trauma, dissociation, and positive psychotic symptoms in a Spanish sample. J Trauma Dissociation. 2010;11(3):284-92. doi: 10.1080/15299731003786462.</citation>
    <PMID>20603763</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pilton M, Varese F, Berry K, Bucci S. The relationship between dissociation and voices: A systematic literature review and meta-analysis. Clin Psychol Rev. 2015 Aug;40:138-55. doi: 10.1016/j.cpr.2015.06.004. Epub 2015 Jun 16. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26117061</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wright DB, Loftus EF. Measuring dissociation: comparison of alternative forms of the dissociative experiences scale. Am J Psychol. 1999 Winter;112(4):497-519.</citation>
    <PMID>10696264</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wright MO, Crawford E, Del Castillo D. Childhood emotional maltreatment and later psychological distress among college students: the mediating role of maladaptive schemas. Child Abuse Negl. 2009 Jan;33(1):59-68. doi: 10.1016/j.chiabu.2008.12.007. Epub 2009 Jan 23.</citation>
    <PMID>19167067</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Young JE. Cognitive therapy for personality disorders : A schema-focused approach. Professional Resource Press/Professional Resource Exchange. 1999.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Young JE, Brown G. Young schema questionnaire short form. New York: Cognitive Therapy Centre. 1998.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Young JE, Klosko, JS, Weishaar, ME. Schema therapy : A practitioner's guide. 2005.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hair Jr JF, Hult GTM, Ringle C, Sarstedt M. A primer on partial least squares structural equation modeling (PLS-SEM). Sage publications. 2016.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>First MB, Spitzer RL, Gibbon M, Williams JB, et al. Structured clinical interview for DSM-IV axis I disorders. New York: New York State Psychiatric Institute. 1995.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>American Psychiatric Association. Diagnostic and statistical manual of mental disorders (DSM-5®). American Psychiatric Pub. 2013.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bernstein DP, Ahluvalia T, Pogge D, Handelsman L. Validity of the Childhood Trauma Questionnaire in an adolescent psychiatric population. J Am Acad Child Adolesc Psychiatry. 1997 Mar;36(3):340-8.</citation>
    <PMID>9055514</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bernstein DP, Stein JA, Newcomb MD, Walker E, Pogge D, Ahluvalia T, Stokes J, Handelsman L, Medrano M, Desmond D, Zule W. Development and validation of a brief screening version of the Childhood Trauma Questionnaire. Child Abuse Negl. 2003 Feb;27(2):169-90.</citation>
    <PMID>12615092</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 22, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 21, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 22, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 21, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 21, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 22, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>schizophrenia</keyword>
  <keyword>auditory verbal hallucinations</keyword>
  <keyword>early maladaptative schemas</keyword>
  <keyword>dissociative symptoms</keyword>
  <keyword>childhood traumas</keyword>
  <keyword>mediation modeling</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hallucinations</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Schizophrenia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

