<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04480619</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>145314</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04480619</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study of AIP-301 Ga-68 Positron Emission Tomography Study for Imaging of Patients With Solid Tumors: The SHIVA Study</brief_title>
  <acronym>Shiva</acronym>
  <official_title>A Phase I/II AIP-301 Ga-68 Positron Emission Tomography Study for Imaging of Patients With Solid Tumors: The SHIVA Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Advanced Imaging Projects, LLC</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>All India Institute of Medical Sciences, New Delhi</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Post Graduate Institute of Medical Education and Research</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Witwatersrand, South Africa</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Lausanne Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Positron Pharma</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Università degli studi di Trieste</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>US Department of Veterans Affairs</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Advanced Imaging Projects, LLC</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a prospective, Phase I/II, multi-center, observational open-label study in a total of
      200 subjects with solid tumor cancers. Eligible participants will undergo baseline
      assessments at enrollment. Study participants will receive an administration of AIP-301 Ga-68
      and undergo PET/CT imaging.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a prospective, Phase I/II multi-center, observational, open-label study in a total of
      210 subjects with metastatic solid tumors, 10 normal controls, 40 with breast cancer, 40 lung
      cancer, 40 gastric and gastroesophageal cancer, 80 other cancer types. All patients with
      confirmed diagnoses will undergo baseline Gallium-68 AIP-301 PET/CT scans to evaluate imaging
      properties and behavior in different tumor types.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">August 30, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 30, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 30, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Specific Aims 1: Safety and tolerability assessment using AIP-301 Ga-68 PET/CT imaging in patients with breast neoplasms and other neoplasms: adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>6 Months</time_frame>
    <description>Assess drug safety and tolerability measuring Incidence of adverse events. NCI Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events v5.0, where: Grade 1, mild; Grade 2, moderate; Grade 3, severe; Grade 4, life‐threatening</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Specific Aims 2: Safety and tolerability assessment using AIP-301 Ga-68 PET/CT imaging in patients with breast neoplasms and other neoplasms: incidence of abnormal vital signs</measure>
    <time_frame>6 Months</time_frame>
    <description>Assess drug safety and tolerability measuring incidence of abnormal vital signs. Vital signs will include measurements of respiratory rate, pulse rate, and systolic and diastolic blood pressure.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Specific Aims 3: Safety and tolerability assessment using AIP-301 Ga-68 PET/CT imaging in patients with breast neoplasms and other neoplasms: incidence of abnormal physical examination</measure>
    <time_frame>6 Months</time_frame>
    <description>Assess drug safety and tolerability measuring incidence of abnormal physical examination findings. Physical examination will be summarized for each body system such as head, eyes, ears, nose, and throat, and cardiovascular, dermatological, musculoskeletal, respiratory, gastrointestinal, genitourinary, and neurological systems.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Specific Aims 4: Safety and tolerability assessment using AIP-301 Ga-68 PET/CT imaging in patients with breast neoplasms and other neoplasms: incidence of abnormal clinical laboratory results</measure>
    <time_frame>6 Months</time_frame>
    <description>Assess drug safety and tolerability measuring incidence of abnormal clinical laboratory results. Adequate laboratory function, defined as:
Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) ≥ 1.5 x 109/L.
Hemoglobin (Hb) ≥9 g/dl (transfusion or use of EPO is permitted).
Platelets &gt; 100,000/mm3
Creatinine ≤ 1.5 x normal value based on the Cock Gault (CG) equation.
AST or ALT ≤ 2.5 x ULN (or ≤5 x ULN in case of liver metastasis)
Alkaline phosphatase ≤2.5 x ULN. Alkaline phosphatase may be more than 2.5 x ULN only in the case of bone metastases, and AST and ALT less than 1.5 x ULN.
Total bilirubin ≤1.5 mg/dl (higher bilirubin levels are permitted if the patient has Gilbert's syndrome).
Baseline LVEF ≥50% measured using echocardiogram or equilibrium isotopic ventriculography (MUGA).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Specific Aim 1: Assess uptake in imaging of tumors to determine the ability of AIP-301 Ga-68 to localize breast tumors and other neoplasms as determined by PET imaging.</measure>
    <time_frame>6 Months</time_frame>
    <description>Assess drug uptake using median and maximum standardized uptake values (SUV) .Test the correlation of AIP-301 Ga-68 uptake with phenotypic solid tumors; e.g., (HER2+,HER3+, LBC, TN and BCBM). Comparisons will be made with conventional cancer imaging. Interobserver variation measurements based on the readings of two nuclear medicine physicians. If there are discrepancies, a third reader will adjudicate.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Specific Aims 2: Assess efficacy in imaging of breast tumors and other neoplasms to determine the ability of AIP-301 Ga-68 to localize cancers as determined by PET imaging.</measure>
    <time_frame>6 Months</time_frame>
    <description>Assess efficacy for sensitivity, specificity, accuracy of tumor volume using SUV max. Compare the diagnostic outcome to pathology or clinic follow-up, then to gather statistics of sensitivity and specificity.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Specific Aims 3: Assess efficacy in imaging of breast tumors and other neoplasms to determine the ability of AIP-301 Ga-68 to localize cancers as determined by PET imaging.</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Assess efficacy for sensitivity, specificity, accuracy of the number of lesions visualized using PET. Compare the diagnostic outcome to pathology or clinic follow-up, then to gather statistics of sensitivity and specificity.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">210</enrollment>
  <condition>PET Diagnosis of Breast and Other Neoplasms</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Ga-68 AIP-301 Positron Emission Tomography</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Companion Ga-68 PET diagnostic for tumor targeted therapy</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>AIP-301</intervention_name>
    <description>PET Diagnostic Agent</description>
    <arm_group_label>Ga-68 AIP-301 Positron Emission Tomography</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with solid tumors (either 3+ by immunohistochemistry or with evidence of gene
             amplification (&gt;2.0) by fluorescence in situ hybridization (FISH))

               -  At least 18 years of age

               -  Able to provide informed consent.

        Karnofsky score greater than 50

          -  Females of childbearing potential must have a negative pregnancy test at
             screening/baseline

          -  AIP-301 Ga-68 positive scan define by SUV greater than 10.

          -  Adequate organ function, defined as:

               1. Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) ≥ 1.5 x 109/L.

               2. Hemoglobin (Hb) ≥9 g/dl (transfusion or use of EPO is permitted).

               3. Platelets &gt; 100,000/mm3

               4. Creatinine ≤ 1.5 x normal value based on the Cock Gault (CG) equation.

               5. AST or ALT ≤ 2.5 x ULN (or ≤5 x ULN in case of liver metastasis)

               6. Alkaline phosphatase ≤2.5 x ULN. Alkaline phosphatase may be more than 2.5 x ULN
                  only in the case of bone metastases, and AST and ALT less than 1.5 x ULN.

               7. Total bilirubin ≤1.5 mg/dl (higher bilirubin levels are permitted if the patient
                  has Gilbert's syndrome).

        Baseline LVEF ≥50% measured using echocardiogram or equilibrium

        isotopic ventriculography (MUGA).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  • Serum creatinine &gt;3.0 mg/dL (270 μM/L)

               -  Hepatic enzyme levels more than 5 times upper limit of normal.

               -  Known severe allergy or hypersensitivity to IV radiographic contrast.

               -  Use of any other investigational product or device within 30 days prior to dosing
                  or known requirement for any other investigational agent prior to completion of
                  all scheduled study assessments.

               -  Patients with a body weight of 400 pounds or more or not able to enter the bore
                  of the PET/CT scanner due to BMI, because of the compromise in image quality with
                  CT, PET/CT and MRI that will result.

               -  Inability to lie still for the entire imaging time (e.g. cough, severe arthritis,
                  etc.).

               -  Inability to complete the needed investigational and standard-of-care imaging
                  examinations due to other reasons (severe claustrophobia, radiation phobia, etc.)

               -  Recognized concurrent active infection (e.g., HIV)

               -  Previous Grade 3 or higher allergic reaction to Trastuzumab that resulted in
                  discontinuation of Trastuzumab therapy. Any additional medical condition, serious
                  intercurrent illness, or other extenuating circumstance that, in the opinion of
                  the Investigator, may significantly interfere with study compliance.

                    -  Adult patients who require monitored anesthesia for PET scanning
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Stanley Satz, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <phone>561-561 286-6842</phone>
    <email>ssatz@advancedimagingprojects.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Rose Satz</last_name>
    <phone>5617578666</phone>
    <email>rsatz@advancedimagingprojects.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Postgraduate Institute of Medical and Research</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chandigarh</city>
        <country>India</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>B.R. Mittal, M.D./Ph.D.</last_name>
      <email>brmittal@yahoo.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>All India Institute of Medical Sciences</name>
      <address>
        <city>New Delhi</city>
        <country>India</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>C.S. Ball</last_name>
      <phone>01126546477</phone>
      <email>drcsbal@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Witwatersrand</name>
      <address>
        <city>Johannesburg</city>
        <country>South Africa</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Mboyo Vangu, M.D./Ph.D.</last_name>
      <phone>0832670004</phone>
      <email>Mboyo-Di-Tamba.Vangu@wits.ac.za</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>India</country>
    <country>South Africa</country>
  </location_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Baum RP, Kulkarni HR, Müller D, Satz S, Danthi N, Kim YS, Brechbiel MW. First-In-Human Study Demonstrating Tumor-Angiogenesis by PET/CT Imaging with (68)Ga-NODAGA-THERANOST, a High-Affinity Peptidomimetic for αvβ3 Integrin Receptor Targeting. Cancer Biother Radiopharm. 2015 May;30(4):152-9. doi: 10.1089/cbr.2014.1747.</citation>
    <PMID>25945808</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Kim YS, Nwe K, Milenic DE, Brechbiel MW, Satz S, Baidoo KE. Synthesis and characterization of αvβ₃-targeting peptidomimetic chelate conjugates for PET and SPECT imaging. Bioorg Med Chem Lett. 2012 Sep 1;22(17):5517-22. doi: 10.1016/j.bmcl.2012.07.024. Epub 2012 Jul 14.</citation>
    <PMID>22853992</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 30, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 20, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 21, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 20, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 20, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 21, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Data will be available after completion of clinical trial</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Clinical Study Report (CSR)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>2 years</ipd_time_frame>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

