<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04480931</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>20-257</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04480931</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Pilot Testing a Mobile App to Designed to Increase Physical Activity Among Pregnant and Postpartum Women</brief_title>
  <official_title>Pilot Testing of a Mobile Health Intervention Designed to Increase Physical Activity and Improve Morbidity and Mortality-related Outcomes Among Pregnant and Postpartum Women in a Rural Setting</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Western Kentucky University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Kentucky</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Western Kentucky University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The goal of this pilot project is to test the feasibility and potential efficacy of the
      evidence-based mHealth app (BumptUp) for improving physical activity and subsequent health
      outcomes (i.e. obesity, hypertension, insulin resistance) among pregnant and postpartum women
      in a rural community.

      In order to accomplish this goal, feasibility of the intervention protocol will be tested by
      the assessment of recruitment (how many participants eligible per month), retention (% of
      women who complete the study protocol), adherence to intervention (% of women who utilize the
      app), and acceptability (survey and one-on-one exit interviews) during pregnancy and
      postpartum.

      Potential efficacy will be determined by examining trends in data on physical activity levels
      (achieving the goal of 150 minutes per week of physical activity (surveys and accelerometry))
      between groups. Other secondary outcomes will also be assessed: weight status, body
      composition, blood pressure, insulin resistance, endothelial function, fitness levels, mental
      health, and infant anthropometrics.

      Clinical hypotheses:

        1. The mHealth program will be feasible as evidenced by high rates of enrollment,
           retention, and adherence, moderate-to-high levels of satisfaction, and low participant
           burden.

        2. The mHealth intervention will show promise towards improving physical activity levels
           and other secondary outcomes in pregnant and postpartum women in a rural community.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      After contact is established and eligibility confirmed, Participants (N=30) will come to the
      Body Composition Laboratory on three separate occasions. The first will be baseline (~23-25
      weeks pregnant), late pregnancy (35-37 weeks pregnant), and ~12 weeks postpartum. There will
      also be two check-ins via telephone (one during pregnancy and one during postpartum upon
      medical clearance at ~6 weeks) to aid with retention, as well as allow participants to ask
      any questions about the app or the educational brochure. At each visit, the study procedures
      will be identical and follow the assessment procedures outlined below. Time points were
      chosen as women tend to become the least active during late pregnancy; and transitioning back
      into activity during the early postpartum days is important for long-term sustained activity.
      After the baseline assessment (~23-25 weeks gestation), the women will be randomized to the
      intervention or control group. The control group will receive an evidence-based educational
      brochure about physical activity during pregnancy. The intervention group will receive free
      access to the mobile app developed by our team (BumptUp). BumptUp users will watch an
      introductory video on the app's features and the goal of the app (i.e. to reach the
      recommended 150 minutes per week of physical activity). The app contains evidence-based
      workout information and education as well as a number of resources aimed at increasing
      physical activity for women during and after pregnancy (key features of the app are located
      in Table 1). Adherence will be assessed via how many weeks they used the app (PI will have
      access these data).

      When a participant completes all study procedures, a final satisfaction survey and exit
      interview will take place to determine acceptability of the protocol and participant burden.
      For this reason, a number of secondary outcomes are being included in this pilot in order to
      finalize the study protocol (and not necessarily to determine the result of the intervention
      on outcomes). App satisfaction will be assessed in the intervention group only via a survey
      adapted by our team. If a participant drops out before completing the study, all attempts
      will be made to conduct the exit interview and to determine the reason for drop out. Exit
      interviews will be recorded, transcribed, and coded for themes via standard qualitative
      analyses64.

      Assessment Procedures: Participants will report to the laboratory at approximately 8:00am
      after a 10-hour fast. The participant's weight, height, and vitals (heart rate and blood
      pressure) will be taken upon arrival after resting for ~10minutes. Body composition will be
      measured using skinfold anthropometry in order to determine maternal percent body fat. Body
      fat percentage will be determined by pressing folds of the skin at seven sites with a caliper
      (Harpenden Skinfolds Caliper, Baty International) and entering the data into a standardized
      equation65, a technique that has been used during pregnancy in prior studies66,67. In
      addition, the participant will complete an Air Displacement Plethysmography assessment with a
      certified technician (BodPod) (COSMED), which has been shown to be valid among pregnant
      women, as well as non-gravid (postpartum) women, if thoracic gas volume is measured directly.
      After the baseline vitals and body composition assessments, a blood draw will be obtained via
      standardized procedures successfully used in the Tinius Lab70. Blood draws will be used to
      analyze insulin using standardized protocols in the Exercise Biochemistry Lab at WKU
      (Biosafety Level 2 Certified). A lipid panel (total cholesterol, HDL, LDL, triglycerides, and
      glucose) will be obtained via Cholestech LDX analyzer (Alere). Baseline insulin and glucose
      levels will be used to calculate the homeostatic model assessment-insulin resistance
      (HOMA-IR), an index of insulin resistance. Because endothelial dysfunction is the earliest
      detectable sign of cardiovascular and metabolic disease, and because exercise in non-pregnant
      adults can improve it; endothelial dysfunction will be assessed with a rapid, non-invasive
      technique that records endothelium-mediated changes in the peripheral arterial tone signal
      via a pair of finger probes.73 (Endopat, Itamar Medical). This will provide additional
      information on the potential for development of insulin resistance, hypertension, and
      obesity75 -all of which are linked to maternal morbidity and mortality. To elaborate, the
      intervention may not necessarily change blood pressure or insulin resistance to a clinically
      significant degree (i.e. may not take a patient from hypertensive to normotensive), but it
      may favorably impact endothelial health, which suggests factors underlying the hypertension
      are improving. In addition, the impact of physical activity during pregnancy on endothelial
      function is lacking. Taken together, this additional assessment via the EndoPat adds to the
      novelty of the proposed project, provides another clinically relevant layer of information
      regarding health status during pregnancy, and increases the overall research capacity at WKU
      for this study and future pregnancy and postpartum research.

      Following the blood draw, the participant will complete the 6-minute walk test utilizing
      standardized procedures to estimate their physical fitness76. Dr. Tinius and her team have
      extensive experience conducting this test among pregnant women, and the test has been shown
      to provide a valid estimate of fitness during pregnancy and in non-gravid adults (i.e.
      postpartum)76. In order to assess the primary outcome (Aim 2), participants will be asked to
      wear a Link Accelerometer (ActiGraph LLC,) for seven consecutive days. Wrist-worn tri-axel
      accelerometers are a valid measure of physical activity in pregnant women78. The
      accelerometer will be placed on their non-dominant wrist at the end of their study visit to
      the Exercise Laboratory and will be picked up by a member of the study team one week later.
      The participant will verbally complete the Exercise Vital Sign survey; a survey specifically
      designed to determine whether someone meets 150min of physical activity per week. The
      participant will also be provided with a number of written surveys (See Appendix A). These
      surveys will assess a number of additional outcomes for inclusion in the larger future
      clinical trial the current pilot study will help the study team determine the participant
      burden and whether or not this number of surveys is feasible for the larger trial. Each
      survey has been selected to determine the potential impact of the mHealth program on a
      particular outcome related to morbidity and mortality. As an example, mental health surveys
      are included as postpartum depression plays a significant role in maternal morbidity and
      mortality, and physical activity improves depressive symptoms during and after pregnancy.

      Infant and Delivery Outcome Assessment: Before being discharged from the hospital after
      parturition, the study team will coordinate with the mothers and their nursing team a time to
      assess the infant as well as collect delivery outcome data from the mother (mode of delivery,
      length of labor, complications, mother's end pregnancy weight). Infant measurements will
      include skinfolds at four sites (hip, thigh, arm, and back), length, head circumference, and
      abdominal circumference. In addition, infant body composition will be via measured air
      displacement plethysmography system (PeaPod, COSMED).

      Statistical Analyses:

      Sample Size Determination: Sample size for this pilot study was determined based on
      previously performed physical activity interventions among pregnant women. The effect size
      (0.91) for the main outcome of physical activity was determined from looking at
      post-intervention physical activity data from Asci et al.83. With this effect size, it was
      determined using SAS software with a type I error rate of 0.05 that a sample size of 20 per
      group could detect this difference with 80% power, thus our sample size of 15 per group is
      justified for a pilot project.

      Data Analyses:

      Aim 1: To estimate the success and feasibility of recruitment methods, the number of people
      who will hear about the study via various methods (e.g. health care providers, health fairs,
      word-of-mouth) will be estimated. Then, the number of women who completed initial screening,
      the number of women who meet the eligibility criteria, the number of women who complete each
      of the assessments, the number of women randomized, and the number of women who adhere to the
      intervention will be determined. The exit interview data will be analyzed via standard
      content analyses for qualitative studies as previously described84 (and recently performed by
      our group). Aim 2: Although we may not detect all between group differences because we are
      proposing a pilot project, appropriate statistical tests will be performed in order to
      examine trends, and thus, promise for effect in the larger future trial. Normality of the
      distribution for each variable will be tested using Kolmogorov-Smirnov tests, and
      non-normally distributed data will be transformed as needed. The baseline characteristics of
      the two groups will be compared using t-tests or Chi square tests. The potential effect of
      the intervention on study outcomes will be explored using repeated measures ANOVAs (group x
      time). Specifically, physical activity data between groups will be compared from pre-post
      intervention. All data will be entered in Redcap data management system. Analyses will be
      conducted using SAS or other statistical software.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">August 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Pregnant women will be recruited ~20 weeks pregnant and after baseline assessments, randomized into the control or intervention group. The intervention group will utilize the mhealth intervention, while the control group will receive basic educational materials only.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
    <masking_description>The participant (as well as the study team and the health care provider) will know after randomization whether or not they are being provided access to the mobile app.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Recruitment feasibility during pregnancy</measure>
    <time_frame>Pregnancy (23-25 weeks gestation)</time_frame>
    <description>how many participants eligible and successfully recruited per month</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Protocol retention</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks postpartum</time_frame>
    <description>% of women who complete the study protocol</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Adherence to intervention</measure>
    <time_frame>Pregnancy (35-37 weeks pregnant)</time_frame>
    <description>% of women who use the app daily</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Adherence to intervention</measure>
    <time_frame>Postpartum (12 weeks after delivery)</time_frame>
    <description>% of women who use the app daily</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Acceptability of Intervention</measure>
    <time_frame>Postpartum (12 weeks after delivery)</time_frame>
    <description>measured via exit interviews</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Physical activity levels</measure>
    <time_frame>Pregnancy (23-25 weeks gestation)</time_frame>
    <description>Assess the potential efficacy of the intervention by examining physical activity levels through objective actigraph data</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Physical activity levels</measure>
    <time_frame>Pregnancy (35-37 weeks gestation)</time_frame>
    <description>Assess the potential efficacy of the intervention by examining physical activity levels through objective actigraph data</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Physical activity levels</measure>
    <time_frame>Pregnancy (23-25 weeks gestation)</time_frame>
    <description>Assess the potential efficacy of the intervention by examining physical activity levels through Exercise Vital Sign Survey</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Physical activity levels</measure>
    <time_frame>Pregnancy (35-37 weeks gestation)</time_frame>
    <description>Assess the potential efficacy of the intervention by examining physical activity levels through Exercise Vital Sign Survey</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Physical activity levels</measure>
    <time_frame>Postpartum (12 weeks)</time_frame>
    <description>Assess the potential efficacy of the intervention by examining physical activity levels through objective actigraph data</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Physical activity levels</measure>
    <time_frame>Postpartum (12 weeks)</time_frame>
    <description>Assess the potential efficacy of the intervention by examining physical activity levels through Exercise Vital Sign Survey</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Maternal weight status</measure>
    <time_frame>Pregnancy (23-25 weeks gestation)</time_frame>
    <description>Body weight (lbs)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Maternal weight status</measure>
    <time_frame>Pregnancy (35-37 weeks gestation)</time_frame>
    <description>Body weight (lbs)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Maternal body composition</measure>
    <time_frame>Pregnancy (23-25 weeks gestation)</time_frame>
    <description>Air displacement plethysmography</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Maternal body composition</measure>
    <time_frame>Pregnancy (35-37 weeks gestation)</time_frame>
    <description>Air displacement plethysmography</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Maternal weight status</measure>
    <time_frame>Postpartum (12 weeks post-delivery)</time_frame>
    <description>Body weight (lbs)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Maternal body composition</measure>
    <time_frame>Postpartum (12 weeks post-delivery)</time_frame>
    <description>air displacement plethysmography</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Maternal blood pressure</measure>
    <time_frame>Pregnancy (23-25 weeks gestation)</time_frame>
    <description>Assessed by nurse practitioner using standardized clinical equipment</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Maternal blood pressure</measure>
    <time_frame>Pregnancy (35-37 weeks gestation)</time_frame>
    <description>Assessed by nurse practitioner using standardized clinical equipment</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Maternal blood pressure</measure>
    <time_frame>Postpartum (12 weeks post-delivery)</time_frame>
    <description>Assessed by nurse practitioner using standardized clinical equipment</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Maternal insulin resistance</measure>
    <time_frame>Pregnancy (23-25 weeks gestation)</time_frame>
    <description>Assessing fasting insulin and glucose levels to determine HOMA-IR</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Maternal insulin resistance</measure>
    <time_frame>Pregnancy (35-37 weeks gestation)</time_frame>
    <description>Assessing fasting insulin and glucose levels to determine HOMA-IR</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Maternal insulin resistance</measure>
    <time_frame>Postpartum (12 weeks post-delivery)</time_frame>
    <description>Assessing fasting insulin and glucose levels to determine HOMA-IR</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Maternal endothelial dysfunction</measure>
    <time_frame>Pregnancy (23-25 weeks gestation)</time_frame>
    <description>Assessed with a rapid, non-invasive technique that records endothelium-mediated changes in the peripheral arterial tone signal via a pair of finger probes</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Maternal endothelial dysfunction</measure>
    <time_frame>Pregnancy (35-37 weeks gestation)</time_frame>
    <description>Assessed with a rapid, non-invasive technique that records endothelium-mediated changes in the peripheral arterial tone signal via a pair of finger probes</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Maternal endothelial dysfunction</measure>
    <time_frame>Postpartum (12 weeks post-delivery)</time_frame>
    <description>Assessed with a rapid, non-invasive technique that records endothelium-mediated changes in the peripheral arterial tone signal via a pair of finger probes</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Maternal postpartum depression</measure>
    <time_frame>Postpartum (12 weeks post-delivery)</time_frame>
    <description>Edinburgh postpartum depression survey</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Maternal mood</measure>
    <time_frame>Pregnancy (23-25 weeks gestation)</time_frame>
    <description>Profile of Mood Survey</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Maternal mood</measure>
    <time_frame>Pregnancy (35-37 weeks gestation)</time_frame>
    <description>Profile of Mood Survey</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Maternal mood</measure>
    <time_frame>Postpartum (12 weeks post-delivery)</time_frame>
    <description>Profile of Mood Survey</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mental Health</measure>
    <time_frame>Pregnancy (23-25 weeks gestation)</time_frame>
    <description>Center for Epidemiological Studies Depression Survey</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mental Health</measure>
    <time_frame>Pregnancy (35-37 weeks gestation)</time_frame>
    <description>Center for Epidemiological Studies Depression Survey</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mental Health</measure>
    <time_frame>Postpartum (12 weeks post-delivery)</time_frame>
    <description>Center for Epidemiological Studies Depression Survey</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Infant body composition</measure>
    <time_frame>24-48 hours post-delivery</time_frame>
    <description>Assessed via 4-site skinfolds</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Infant body composition</measure>
    <time_frame>24-48 hours post-delivery</time_frame>
    <description>Assessed via air displacement plethysmography</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Infant birthweight</measure>
    <time_frame>At time of delivery</time_frame>
    <description>Collected at delivery by trained nursing staff</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Pregnancy</condition>
  <condition>Postpartum</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>mHealth Intervention Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>This group will be provided with the mobile health app (including introductory videos on how to use its features).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Sham Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>This group will receive an educational brochure about physical activity during pregnancy.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>mHealth Intervention Group</intervention_name>
    <description>Access to the mobile health application with exercise plans and education</description>
    <arm_group_label>mHealth Intervention Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Educational Brochure</intervention_name>
    <description>An evidence-based educational brochure with general information about the benefits of physical activity during pregnancy</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  1) Age 18-44

          -  2) Confirmed singleton viable pregnancy

          -  3) English-Speaking (the app is currently only available in English)

          -  4) Physician release to participate in exercise

          -  5) Ownership of a smart phone

          -  6) Plans to deliver at The Medical Center in Bowling Green, KY.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  1) Multiple gestation pregnancy

          -  2) Inability to provide voluntary informed consent

          -  3) Any medical condition (pregnancy-related or not) that would preclude exercise.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>44 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Rachel A Tinius, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>270-745-5026</phone>
    <email>rachel.tinius@wku.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Maire Blankenship, DNP</last_name>
    <phone>270-745-3973</phone>
    <email>maire.blankenship@wku.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 8, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 16, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 22, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 16, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 16, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 22, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Western Kentucky University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Rachel Tinius</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>exercise</keyword>
  <keyword>physical activity</keyword>
  <keyword>mobile health</keyword>
  <keyword>intervention</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

