<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04486716</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>COMB157GUS07</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>111,116</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04486716</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Single Arm Study Evaluating the Efficacy, Safety and Tolerability of Ofatumumab in Patients With Relapsing Multiple Sclerosis</brief_title>
  <acronym>OLIKOS</acronym>
  <official_title>A Single-arm, Prospective, Multi-center Study to Explore Maintained Efficacy With Ofatumumab Therapy in Patients With Relapsing Multiple Sclerosis Who Discontinue Intravenously Delivered Anti-CD20 Monoclonal Antibody (aCD20 mAb) Therapy (OLIKOS)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Novartis Pharmaceuticals</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Novartis</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      A single arm study evaluating the continued efficacy, safety and tolerability of ofatumumab
      in patients with relapsing multiple sclerosis who are transitioning from aCD20 mAb therapy
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a single-arm multi-center, study in approximately 100 participants with relapsing
      multiple sclerosis who were previously treated with aCD20 mAb therapy. Eligible participants
      will receive open label ofatumumab 20 mg subcutaneous every 4 weeks for 12 months following
      initial loading regimen of 20 milligrams subcutaneous doses on Days 1, 7 and 14. Assessments
      will include but are not limited to Magnetic Resonance Imaging (MRI) assessed for quality by
      central reading center, multiple Patient Reported Outcome measurements and safety
      assessments..Participants that do not continue onto commercial ofatumumab or another therapy
      within one month of the End of Study Visit must continue into the safety Follow Up phase,
      consisting of every 3 month visits including B cell monitoring until they are able to start
      on commercial ofatumumab or switch to another therapy or until their B cells are repleted
      defined as a B cell concentration greater than the individual participant's baseline value or
      greater than the lower limit of normal. All participants will have a safety follow-up phone
      call at 30 days post study.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">July 30, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 3, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 3, 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Open-label</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with no change or reduction in gadolinium enhancing lesions at 12 months</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline up to 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Magnetic Resonance Imaging (MRI) will be used to measure presence of new or reduction in number of gadolinium enhancing lesions. Each MRI scan will be previewed by a local neuroradiologist. The quality of each scan performed will be assessed by a central MRI reading center and evaluated for quality, completeness and adherence to the protocol.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline for total CD19+ B cell counts and CD3+CD20+ T cell counts,</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline up to 6 and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Total CD19+ B cell counts cell counts, obtained by fluorescence activated cell sorting</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline for CD3+CD20+ T cell counts,</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline up to 6 and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>CD3+CD20+ T cell counts, obtained by fluorescence activated cell sorting</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline for Treatment Satisfaction Questionnaire for Medication (TSQM-9)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline up to 6 and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>The Treatment Satisfaction Questionnaire for Medication (TSQM-9) will be used to evaluate the participants' satisfaction with Ofatumumab. The TSQM-9 is a psychometrically sound and valid participant reported outcome to measure participants' satisfaction with medication and a good predictor of adherence across different types of medication and participant population. The TSQM-9 is a 9 item questionnaire having a global satisfaction score ranging from 0-100. The questionnaire consists of 3 domains: satisfaction, convenience and effectiveness (3 items each). The domain scores range from 0 to 100 with higher scores representing higher satisfaction on that domain.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in Columbia-Suicide Severity Rating Scale (C-SSRS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline up to 6 and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>The C-SSRS rates an individual's degree of suicidal ideation (SI) on a scale, ranging from &quot;wish to be dead&quot; to &quot;active suicidal ideation with specific plan and intent.&quot; The scale identifies SI severity and intensity, which may be indicative of an individual's intent to commit suicide. C-SSRS SI severity subscale ranges from 0 (no SI) to 5 (active SI with plan and intent).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with treatment emergent adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline up 13 months (includes 30 day followup) or up to 21 months for patients entering extra safety follow-up</time_frame>
    <description>Adverse event monitoring should be continued following the last dose of study treatment until B cells are repleted. Repletion is defined as a concentration &gt; the participant's baseline value or &gt; the lower limit of normal, whichever is observed first.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Relapsing Multiple Sclerosis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Ofatumumab</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Investigational drug will be provided in an autoinjector for subcutaneous administration containing 20 mg ofatumumab (20 mg/0.4 ml) administered at baseline, Day 7, Day 14 and monthly thereafter</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ofatumumab</intervention_name>
    <description>Investigational drug will be provided in an autoinjector for subcutaneous administration containing 20 mg ofatumumab (20 mg/0.4 ml)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Ofatumumab</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>OMB157</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Participants eligible for inclusion in this study must meet all of the following criteria:

          1. Written informed consent must be obtained before any assessment is performed.

          2. Male or female participants aged 18 to 55 years (inclusive) at screening.

          3. Diagnosis of relapsing MS (RMS) according to the 2017 Revised McDonald criteria
             (Thompson et al.

        2018), including CIS, RRMS or SPMS with disease activity as defined by (Lublin et al.
        2014).

        4. Disability status at Screening with an EDSS score of 0 to 5.5 (inclusive). 5. Received
        at least 2 but no more than 5 courses of intravenous aCD20 mAb (loading doses are
        considered 1 course):

        • Participants currently treated with ocrelizumab must have received (meet all three
        criteria below):

          1. 2 fully infused initial 300 mg ocrelizumab iv infusions

          2. From 1 to 4 fully infused 600 mg ocrelizumab iv infusions 6 months (+/- one month)

          3. Last fully infused ocrelizumab dose must have occurred within 4-9 months prior to
             baseline

        Participants currently treated with rituximab must have received (meet both criteria
        below):

          1. At least 2, but no more than 5, fully infused courses of rituximab 500 mg - 1000 mg iv
             every 6 months (+/- one month).

             a. Initial loading regimens of rituximab i.e. 500 mg - 1000 mg on day 1 and on day 15,
             are allowed but this is consider a single course and must be followed by additional
             infusion(s) every 6 months (+/- one month)

          2. Last fully infused rituximab dose must have occurred within 4-9 months prior to
             baseline.

        6. Participants discontinuing aCD20 therapy for reasons including, but not limited to:
        physician/participant preference, access to commercial drug (e.g. insurance coverage
        issues) or for other logistical reasons (such as geographical relocation, travel, etc.) are
        eligible for this study. 7. Participants with CD19 B cells that are depleted to &lt; 1% of the
        participant's baseline CD19 B cell concentration. 8. Neurologically stable within 1 month
        prior to first study drug administration. 9. Must be able to use a smart device or have a
        caregiver that can assist.

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Participants meeting any of the following criteria are not eligible for inclusion in this
        study:

          1. Participants that have demonstrated suboptimal response to aCD20 therapy to include:
             documented relapse while on previous aCD20 treatment, or signs of MRI activity,
             defined as ≥ 2 active Gd+ T1 lesions, or any new or newly enlarging T2 lesions, or any
             signs of clinical worsening as measured by EDSS or any clinical measure, documented
             within the last 6 months.

          2. Discontinuing aCD20 mAb therapy due to the following treatment- emergent adverse
             events:

               1. Severe infusion-related reactions (Grade 3 or above)

               2. Recurrent infections defined as ≥ 2 severe infections or ≥ 3 respiratory
                  infections or the need for ≥ 2 courses of antibiotics since starting aCD20
                  therapy

               3. Decreased IgG requiring treatment with Intravenous immunoglobulin

          3. Participants with primary progressive MS (Polman et al 2011) or SPMS without disease
             activity (Lublin et al 2014).

          4. Participants meeting criteria for neuromyelitis optica (Wingerchuk et al 2015).

          5. Pregnant or nursing (lactating) women, where pregnancy is defined as the state of a
             female after conception and until the termination of gestation, confirmed by a
             positive hCG laboratory test.

          6. Women of child-bearing potential, defined as all women physiologically capable of
             becoming pregnant, unless they are using highly effective methods of contraception
             during dosing and for at least 6 months after stopping study medication. Highly
             effective contraception methods include:

               -  Total abstinence

               -  Female sterilization

               -  For female participants on the study, the vasectomized male partner should be the
                  sole partner

               -  Use of oral, (estrogen and progesterone), injected or implanted hormonal methods
                  of contraception or placement of an intrauterine device (IUD) or intrauterine
                  system (IUS) or other forms of hormonal contraception that have comparable
                  efficacy (failure rate &lt;1%), for example hormone vaginal ring or transdermal
                  hormone contraception.

          7. Participants with active chronic disease (or stable but treated with immune therapy)
             of the immune system other than MS (e.g.

             rheumatoid arthritis, scleroderma, Sjögren's syndrome, Crohn's disease, ulcerative
             colitis, etc.) or with immunodeficiency syndrome (hereditary immune deficiency,
             drug-induced immune deficiency).

          8. Participants with active systemic bacterial, viral or fungal infections, or known to
             have acquired immunodeficiency syndrome (AIDS).

          9. Participants with neurological symptoms consistent with PML or with confirmed PML.

         10. Participants at risk of developing or having reactivation of syphilis or tuberculosis
             (eg. Participants with known exposure to, or history of syphilis, or active or latent
             tuberculosis, even if previously treated).

             Testing for syphilis and tuberculosis will be done at Screening. Testing must be done
             by the central lab (for syphilis e.g. by positive rapid plasma reagin (RPR); for
             tuberculosis testing, QuantiFERON®-TB Gold test to assess participant's eligibility at
             Screening).

         11. Participants at risk of developing or having reactivation of hepatitis:

             Positive results at Screening for serological markers for hepatitis (H)

             A, B, C, and E indicating acute orpchronic infection:

               -  anti-HA Immunoglobulin M (IgM)

               -  HBs Ag and/or anti-HBc IgM and/or HB virus deoxyribonucleic acid (DNA)

               -  anti-HBs negative and Anti-HBc positive

               -  anti-HC IgG (if positive IgG, HCV-RNA PCR will be performed and if negative,
                  participant can be enrolled)

               -  anti-HE IgM (if positive IgG and/or IgM, perform HE-RNA PCR and if negative,
                  participant can be enrolled) NOTE: If the Investigator suspects false positive
                  hepatitis serology results, such as an antibody pattern indicating acute
                  hepatitis infection but no corresponding elevated liver enzymes and no signs or
                  symptoms of liver disease, an infectious disease expert may be consulted. If the
                  infectious disease expert finds no evidence of acute or chronic hepatitis
                  infection and considers the serology results false positive and not clinically
                  relevant, the Investigator must document (in source data and as a comment in the
                  eCRF) that the serology results are considered false positive and may then enroll
                  the participant.

         12. Have received any live or live-attenuated vaccines (including for varicella-zoster
             virus or measles) within 2 months prior to first study drug administration.

         13. Have been treated with any of the medications listed below within the time specified
             Medication Exclusionary if used within the timeframe specified below Intravenous,
             oral, intra-articular or intramuscular corticosteroids, adrenocorticotropic hormone
             exclusionary within 30 days prior to Screening MRI scan

             Immunosuppressive, chemotherapeutic medications (e.g. natalizumab, mitoxantrone,
             cyclophosphamide, cladribine, S1P modulators) exclusionary within 2 years prior to
             first study drug administration

             Mitoxantrone (with evidence of cardiotoxicity following treatment or cumulative
             life-time dose &gt; 60mg/m2) Alemtuzumab Lymphoid irradiation; bone marrow
             transplantation Other strongly immunosuppressive treatments (with effects potentially
             lasting over 6 months), Ofatumumab, aCD20+ monoclonal antibodies in development (e.g.
             ublituximab or obinutuzumab) and Daclizumab exclusionary if taken Anytime

         14. Use of other investigational drugs at the time of enrollment (Screening) or within the
             prior 30 days, or five elimination half-lives, or until the expected pharmacodynamic
             effect has returned to baseline, whichever is longer.

         15. History of malignancy of any organ system (other than basal cell carcinoma, in situ
             squamous cell carcinoma of skin, or in situ carcinoma of cervix or the uterus that
             have been radically treated e.g. completely excised with clear margins), within the
             past 5 years, regardless of whether or not there is evidence of local recurrence or
             metastases.

         16. Any of the following conditions or treatments that may impact the safety of the
             participant:

               -  History of, or current, significant cardiac disease including cardiac failure
                  (NYHA functional class II-IV), myocardial infarction (within 6 months), unstable
                  angina (within 6 months), transient ischemic attack (within 6 months), stroke,
                  cardiac arrhythmias requiring treatment or uncontrolled arterial hypertension

               -  Concomitant clinically significant cardiac arrhythmias, e.g. sustained
                  ventricular tachycardia and clinically significant second or third degree AV
                  block without a pacemaker on screening electrocardiogram (ECG)

               -  History of or active severe respiratory disease, including Chronic Obstructive
                  Pulmonary Disease, interstitial lung disease or pulmonary fibrosis

               -  Participants with asthma requiring regular treatment with oral steroids

               -  Severe hepatic impairment (Child-Pugh class C) or any chronic liver or biliary
                  disease

               -  Participants with severe renal impairment (Glomerular Filtration Rate &lt; 30
                  ml/min/1.73 m2)

               -  Any medically unstable condition as determined by the Investigator

         17. Any of the following abnormal laboratory values as confirmed by the central laboratory
             prior to first study drug administration:

               -  Total or conjugated bilirubin (BIL) greater than 3 times upper limit of normal
                  (ULN) range, unless in the context of Gilbert's syndrome

               -  Alkaline phosphatase (ALP) greater than 5 times the ULN range

               -  ALT between 1.5 and 5 times the ULN range and an active infection with
                  hepatotropic viruses (Herpes simplex virus, Cytomegalovirus and Epstein-Barr
                  Virus)

               -  Serum IgG &lt; 300mg/dL (according to central laboratory range) Any other clinically
                  significant laboratory assessment as determined by the Investigator (e.g.
                  significant anemia, neutropenia, thrombocytopenia, signs of impaired bone marrow
                  function)

         18. Participants with severe hypoproteinaemia e.g. in nephrotic syndrome.

         19. Participants with any of the following neurologic/psychiatric disorders prior to first
             study drug administration:

             • Score &quot;yes&quot; on item 4 or item 5 of the Suicidal Ideation section of the Columbia-
             Suicide Severity Rating Scale (C-SSRS), if this ideation occurred in the past 6
             months, or &quot;yes&quot; on any item of the Suicidal Behavior section, except for the
             &quot;Non-Suicidal Self-Injurious Behavior&quot; (item also included in the Suicidal Behavior
             section), if this behavior occurred in the past 2 years.

         20. History of hypersensitivity to any of the study drugs or excipients (including rare
             hereditary problems of galactose intolerance, Lapp lactase deficiency and
             glucose-galactose malabsorption) or to drugs of similar chemical classes.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Novartis Pharmaceuticals</last_name>
    <phone>1-888-669-6682</phone>
    <email>novartis.email@novartis.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Novartis Pharmaceuticals</last_name>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 23, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 23, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 27, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 23, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 23, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 27, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Ofatumumab, Relapsing multiple sclerosis, MS, RMS, CIS, RRMS, SPMS, ocrelizumab, MRI, CD19 B,adult,OMB157,open-label, rituximab</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Multiple Sclerosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sclerosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Ofatumumab</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Novartis is committed to sharing with qualified external researchers, access to patient-level data and supporting clinical documents from eligible studies. These requests are reviewed and approved by an independent review panel on the basis of scientific merit. All data provided is anonymized to respect the privacy of patients who have participated in the trial in line with applicable laws and regulations.
This trial data availability is according to the criteria and process described on www.clinicalstudydatarequest.com</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Statistical Analysis Plan (SAP)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Informed Consent Form (ICF)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Clinical Study Report (CSR)</ipd_info_type>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

