<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04481269</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>20200718</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04481269</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Prospective Randomized Controlled Study on the Clinical Efficacy of a New Surface Modified Composite Coating Orthopedic Implant Device</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Prospective Randomized Controlled Study on the Clinical Efficacy of a New Surface Modified Composite Coating Orthopedic Implant Device</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Second Affiliated Hospital, School of Medicine, Zhejiang University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Second Affiliated Hospital, School of Medicine, Zhejiang University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study is a prospective, randomized, controlled, double-arm, non-inferiority study that
      will be carried out in China. It aims to compare two implant systems (the research group uses
      surface-modified composite coated orthopedic implants, and controls group using conventional
      orthopedic implants) safety and effectiveness. A total of 240 patients were recruited. The
      recruited patients are randomly divided into groups at a ratio of 1:1 to ensure that the
      distribution of patients in the treatment group and the control group is consistent. Patients
      will receive clinical follow-up in the 1, 3, 6, 9 and 12 months postoperatively. The main
      indicator for evaluation is the postoperative infection rate, and the secondary indicators
      include the SF-12 scoring scale, EQ-5D patient questionnaire score, fracture healing,
      malunion, nonunion incidence in the 12th month after surgery, and skin and soft tissue
      complications Symptom incidence rate. The follow-up data will be used to determine the main
      safety and effectiveness of the new surface modified composite coated orthopedic implant
      system.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">October 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 31, 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 31, 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>post-operation infection rate</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>SF-12 score</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>EQ-5D score</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>fracture union, malunion, nonunion rate</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">240</enrollment>
  <condition>Open Fractures, Degenerative Osteoarthritis and Degenerative Spinal Diseases</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Research Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Research group uses surface-modified composite coated orthopedic implants</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Controls Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Controls group uses conventional orthopedic implants</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Surface-modified composite coated orthopedic implants</intervention_name>
    <description>The surface-modified composite coated orthopedic implants have the capacity of high binding strength, high tissue-inducing activity and intelligent bacteria-resistance. The implant devices are expected to be used in the prevention and treatment of plant-related infections in orthopedic surgeries.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Research Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>conventional orthopedic implants</intervention_name>
    <description>conventional orthopedic implants</description>
    <arm_group_label>Controls Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Limb fracture group criteria

               1. Age 18-75 years old, no gender limit

               2. The preoperative diagnosis is clearly Anderson-Gustilo type III open fracture
                  patient

               3. Postoperative diagnosis stage is IIIA or IIIB patients with open fracture

               4. The subject understands the meaning of this project, volunteers to be the
                  subject, and signs to be informed consent

          -  Joint replacement group criteria

               1. Age 40-75 years old, no gender limit

               2. The patient is clearly diagnosed as degenerative osteoarthritis before the
                  operation, and the postoperative diagnosis is the same as before the operation

               3. Patients can tolerate implantation operation

               4. The subject understands the meaning of this project, volunteers to be the
                  subject, and signs to be informed consent

          -  Spine patients group criteria

               1. Age 40-75 years old, no gender limit

               2. Before surgery, it is clearly diagnosed as degenerative spine disease and spine
                  requiring intervertebral fusion

               3. Patients can tolerate implantation operation

               4. The subject understands the meaning of this project, volunteers to be the
                  subject, and signs to be informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  1. The subject is pregnant or breastfeeding, or a woman of childbearing age does not
             agree to take effective contraceptive measures during the period 2. Closed fractures
             or pathological fractures (such as primary or metastatic tumors) 3. Patients with
             symptoms of compartment syndrome 4. According to Gustilo-Anderson classification of
             open fractures into type I and type II patients 5. Multiple injuries, determined by
             the researcher to be unsuitable for research 6. The patient is allergic to metal
             plants 7. Combined with certain medical diseases, it is determined by the investigator
             to be unsuitable for the study, for example metabolic bone disease, sequelae of polio,
             poor bone quality, poor bone healing 8. The patient has participated in other clinical
             trials in the past 3 months 9. The patient has contraindications to anesthesia and
             surgery 10. Patients with congenital malformations, local or systemic infections, skin
             diseases 11. The patient is currently receiving chemotherapy or radiotherapy, systemic
             corticosteroid, long-term use of sedative and hypnotics (using more than 3 consecutive
             months) or non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (continuous use for more than 3
             months) 12. The patient's compliance is poor, and the research staff determines that
             it cannot be completed according to the research plan. No consent for voluntary
             participation in clinical research was provided.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 19, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 21, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 22, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 21, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 21, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 22, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Osteoarthritis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Spinal Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fractures, Open</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

