<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04190342</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>H19094</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04190342</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effects of a Traditional Chinese Exercise Program on Symptom Cluster in Breast Cancer Patients</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effects of a Traditional Chinese Exercise Program- Tai Chi on Symptom Cluster of Fatigue-sleep Disturbance-depression in Female Breast Cancer Patients: a Preliminary Randomized Controlled Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Charles Darwin University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>The Affiliated Hospital Of Southwest Medical University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>The Affiliated Hospital of Putian University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Shenzhen Sixth People's Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Charles Darwin University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The Medical Research Council Framework for Developing and Evaluating Complex Interventions
      (MRC Framework) will be utilized to develop and evaluate an evidence-based tai chi
      intervention for managing the symptom cluster of fatigue-sleep disturbance-depression in
      breast cancer patients.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The fatigue-sleep disturbance-depression symptom cluster (FSDSC) is regarded as one of the
      most common symptom clusters among breast cancer (BC) patients. Considering the fact that no
      specific medications can be recommended to relieve symptom clusters, numerous
      non-pharmacological interventions have therefore been performed with medication as a
      combination intervention for the treatment of symptom clusters in cancer patients. Among
      these interventions, tai chi could be an optimal option for relieving the FSDSC. The overall
      aims are to develop an evidence-based traditional Chinese exercise (TCE) tai chi protocol,
      test the feasibility of the protocol, and preliminarily examine the effectiveness of tai chi
      on the FSDSC and quality of life (QoL) through a pilot randomized controlled trial (RCT).The
      MRC Framework will be used to develop and evaluate an evidence-based intervention for BC
      patients. In phase one, an evidence-based TCE tai chi intervention protocol will be
      developed. An expert panel will then be invited to assess the content validity of the
      intervention protocol. Testing the feasibility of the tai chi intervention protocol, and
      preliminarily examining the effects of tai chi on the FSDSC will be conducted in phase two.
      After completion of the pilot RCT, semi-structured interviews will be conducted to assess the
      participants' experience of participating in the pilot trial and performing the tai chi
      exercise. The evidence-based tai chi intervention protocol for managing the FSDSC in breast
      cancer patients will be developed. The feasibility and effects of utilizing the tai chi
      intervention for BC patients will be explored. A future multicentre large-scale RCT to
      further evaluate the effects of tai chi on the FSDSC in the BC population will benefit from
      the study results of this doctoral research project.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 4, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of referrals made by clinicians</measure>
    <time_frame>Immediately after completion of the 8-week intervention (T2)</time_frame>
    <description>The proportion of referrals made by clinicians in different departments and hospitals from among all referrals</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of subjects completed the study</measure>
    <time_frame>Immediately after completion of the 8-week intervention (T2)</time_frame>
    <description>The proportion of subjects completed the study from among all subjects who participated in the study</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Time taken to recruit enough subjects</measure>
    <time_frame>Immediately after completion of the 8-week intervention (T2)</time_frame>
    <description>The time taken to recruit enough subjects for the trial</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of subjects who dropped out</measure>
    <time_frame>Immediately after completion of the 8-week intervention (T2)</time_frame>
    <description>The proportion of subjects who dropped out after randomization from among all subjects who participated in the study</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Reasons for dropping out</measure>
    <time_frame>Immediately after completion of the 8-week intervention (T2)</time_frame>
    <description>The feedback from the discontinuing subjects to identify their reasons for dropping out</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Acceptability of the questionnaires</measure>
    <time_frame>Immediately after completion of the 8-week intervention (T2)</time_frame>
    <description>The acceptability of the questionnaires will be measured via the percentage of missing values for each item at both item-level and scale-level in each of the questionnaires</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Adherence rates</measure>
    <time_frame>Immediately after completion of the 8-week intervention (T2)</time_frame>
    <description>The adherence rates will be measured by the number of tai chi sessions performed divided by the total possible tai chi sessions</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Participant feedback</measure>
    <time_frame>Immediately after completion of the 8-week intervention (T2)</time_frame>
    <description>The feedback from the participants will be obtained by an investigator-designed questionnaire</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of subjects with uncomfortable feelings</measure>
    <time_frame>Immediately after completion of the 8-week intervention (T2)</time_frame>
    <description>In each tai chi session, the subjects in the intervention group will record whether they had any uncomfortable feelings</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Satisfaction with the intervention</measure>
    <time_frame>Immediately after completion of the 8-week intervention (T2)</time_frame>
    <description>After the completion of the 8-week tai chi intervention, the participants in the tai chi group will be required to rate their satisfaction with the intervention by answering three questions on a scale of 1 to 10, with 10 indicating either &quot;very dissatisfied&quot; or &quot;absolutely yes&quot;; the participants' satisfaction with the tai chi intervention will be recorded on their feedback form</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of patients completed the exercise log</measure>
    <time_frame>Immediately after completion of the 8-week intervention (T2)</time_frame>
    <description>The participants in the tai chi group will be required to keep a diary to monitor their tai chi exercise after each tai chi session</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Symptom cluster assessment: fatigue</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline Assessments (T1); Immediately after completion of the 8-week intervention (T2); 4-week Follow-up (T3)</time_frame>
    <description>Fatigue will be measured by the Brief Fatigue Inventory (BFI). The Brief Fatigue Inventory includes nine items using a 0- to 10-point Likert scale, where 0 = &quot;no fatigue&quot; and 10 = &quot;fatigue as bad as you can imagine&quot; . The global BFI score, with a range between 0 and 90, is calculated as the mean of the nine items, and higher scores correspond to more severe fatigue</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Symptom cluster assessment: sleep disturbance</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline Assessments (T1); Immediately after completion of the 8-week intervention (T2); 4-week Follow-up (T3)</time_frame>
    <description>Sleep disturbance will be measured by the Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index (PSQI). This 19-item questionnaire consists of seven components: subjective sleep quality (one item), sleep latency (two items), sleep duration (one item), habitual sleep efficiency (three items), sleep disturbance (nine items), use of sleeping medications (one item), and daytime dysfunction (two items). Each of the seven component scores are identified based on scoring algorithms, with each item using a 4-point Likert response scale, ranging from 0 to 3. A global (total) score is obtained from the sum of the seven component scores, with a possible range of 0 to 21 points. A higher score on the global (total) score indicates poorer sleep quality.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Symptom cluster assessment: depression</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline Assessments (T1); Immediately after completion of the 8-week intervention (T2); 4-week Follow-up (T3)</time_frame>
    <description>depression will be measured by the Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale (HADS). The HADS is a 14-item, self-report scale that includes two subscales, namely, the Anxiety subscale (HADS-A) and the depression subscale (HADS-D), which has seven items per subscale. The scale uses a 4-point Likert scale, ranging from 0 to 3. The sum of the ratings of 14 items yields a total score; the sum of the ratings of seven items in each subscale yields separate scores for anxiety and depression. The score ranges between 0 and 42 for the total score and between 0 and 21 for each subscale. Higher scores indicate greater severity of anxiety and depression.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of life (QoL) assessment</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline Assessments (T1); Immediately after completion of the 8-week intervention (T2); 4-week Follow-up (T3)</time_frame>
    <description>Quality of life assessment will be measured by the Functional Assessment of Cancer Therapy-Breast (FACT-B). The FACT-B is subdivided into four primary QoL domains, namely, Physical Well-Being (seven items), Social Well-Being (seven items), Emotional Well-Being (six items), and Functional Well-Being (seven items), and contains additional concerns for Beast Cancer (10 items) . The FACT-B has a 5-point Likert-type response scale, ranging from 0 to 4, where 0 = &quot;not at all&quot; and 4 = &quot;very much&quot;. A summing-up of each FACT-B subscale creates the FACT-B total score, ranging from 0 to 148. Moreover, a higher FACT-B score indicates a better QoL status.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">72</enrollment>
  <condition>Breast Neoplasm Female</condition>
  <condition>Symptom Cluster</condition>
  <condition>Tai ji</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>wait list control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Routine methods of treatment and care (intervention provided after the completion of the trial)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>tai chi group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Tai chi intervention + routine methods of treatment and care</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>wait list control</intervention_name>
    <description>regular health education, nutritional care, and health assessments After the pilot RCT is completed, if the participants allocated to the control group are interested in practising tai chi, the intervention will be provided</description>
    <arm_group_label>wait list control</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>tai chi group</intervention_name>
    <description>Around half-hour practising easy tai chi movements/postures twice per week</description>
    <arm_group_label>tai chi group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Female, aged 18 years old or above;

          2. a confirmed diagnosis of non-metastatic stage I, II, or IIIa BC;

          3. have experienced at least a moderate level of tiredness, sleep disturbance, and
             depressive mood, with a score of 3 or more rated on a 10-point numeric rating scale,
             from &quot;0 (no symptom)&quot; to &quot;10 (worst symptom)&quot; for each symptom in the previous one
             month;

          4. have completed adjuvant chemotherapy for at least one month and up to three years; and

          5. able to follow instructions in Mandarin, interested in participating in the study, and
             willing to sign an informed consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Currently using psychostimulants, antidepressant medications, or hypnotics
             medications;

          2. extremely weak or have mental illness and/or intellectual disability;

          3. have been involved in other exercise programs &gt; 30 minutes, three times weekly, for
             past 3 months;

          4. have practised tai chi for the past six months; and

          5. have scheduled elective surgery during the study period.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jing-Yu (Benjamin) Tan, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Charles Darwin University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Li-Qun Yao, PhDc</last_name>
    <phone>(61)889467447</phone>
    <email>s319826@cdu.edu.au</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Jing-Yu (Benjamin) Tan, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>(61)889466942</phone>
    <email>benjamin.tan@cdu.edu.au</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The Affiliated Hospital of Putian University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Putian</city>
        <state>Fujian</state>
        <zip>350011</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Li-Qun Yao, PhDc</last_name>
      <phone>+86 18259068782</phone>
      <email>liqun.yao@students.cdu.edu.au</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The Affiliated Hospital Of Southwest Medical University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Luzhou</city>
        <state>Sichuan</state>
        <zip>646000</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Hou-Qiang Huang, MSc</last_name>
      <phone>+86 18715799162</phone>
      <email>878620130@qq.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Li-Qun Yao, PhDc</last_name>
      <phone>+86 18259068782</phone>
      <email>liqun.yao@students.cdu.edu.au</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>December 3, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 4, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">December 9, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 15, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 15, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 17, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Charles Darwin University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Jing-Yu Tan, BNSc, MMed, PhD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor in Nursing</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>tai chi</keyword>
  <keyword>breast cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>symptom cluster</keyword>
  <keyword>fatigue</keyword>
  <keyword>sleep disturbance</keyword>
  <keyword>depression</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Syndrome</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

