<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04195451</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>46606</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04195451</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Re-Energize Fontan</brief_title>
  <official_title>RE-ENERGIZE FONTAN: A RandomizEd Exercise INtERvention DesiGned to MaximIZE Fitness in Pediatric FONTAN Patients</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Stanford University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>The Methodist Hospital System</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Stanford University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Survival of children with single ventricles (&quot;half a heart&quot;) beyond the neonatal period has
      increased dramatically with the staged Fontan palliation. Yet, long-term morbidity remains
      high. By the age of 40, 50% of Fontan patients will have died or undergone heart
      transplantation. With &gt;1,000 Fontan palliations performed in the US annually, there is a
      burgeoning population of Fontan patients at risk for progressive heart failure and death.
      Factors that contribute to onset and progression of heart failure in Fontan patients remain
      incompletely understood. However, it is established that Fontan patients have poor exercise
      capacity, associated with a greater risk of morbidity and mortality, in addition to decreased
      muscle mass, abnormal muscle function, and endothelial dysfunction contributing to disease
      progression. In adult patients with two ventricles and heart failure, reduced exercise
      capacity, muscle mass, and muscle strength are powerful predictors of poor outcomes, and
      exercise interventions can not only improve exercise capacity and muscle mass, but also
      reverse endothelial dysfunction. Limited exercise interventions in children with congenital
      heart disease have demonstrated that exercise is safe and effective; however, these studies
      have been conducted in small, heterogeneous groups, and most had few Fontan patients.
      Furthermore, none of these interventions have studied the impact of exercise on muscle mass
      or mitochondrial function, or endothelial function. The investigators propose a
      milestone-driven, randomized controlled trial in pediatric Fontan patients to test the
      hypothesis that a live-video-supervised exercise (aerobic + resistance) intervention will
      improve cardiac and physical capacity; muscle mass, strength and function; and endothelial
      function. The investigators' ultimate goal is the translation of this model to clinical
      application as an &quot;exercise prescription&quot; to intervene early in pediatric Fontan patients and
      decrease long-term morbidity and mortality.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">August 6, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 6, 2025</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 6, 2024</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in volume of Oxygen Consumed at Maximal Exertion</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 3 months, 9 months, 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>In Fontan patients, VO2 max is a powerful predictor of poor outcomes. The subjects will undergo progressive cardiopulmonary exercise testing with continuous monitoring by 12-lead EKG and gas exchange by measuring breath-to-breath ventilation. Exercise capacity will be measured by a cardiopulmonary exercise test to obtain the maximal oxygen uptake (VO2 max).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">150</enrollment>
  <condition>Single-ventricle</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Live Video-Supervised Exercise Intervention Arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients randomized to exercise intervention at baseline will participate in live-video-supervised exercise sessions x3/week for 3 months, and then will follow a maintenance regimen for 6 months. During maintenance, patients will continue live-video-supervised exercise sessions, only x1/week, and will be instructed to exercise on their own x2/week following an individualized prescribed exercise program and use their heart rate monitor as an activity tracker.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Live-Video-Supervised Exercise Control Arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients randomized to usual care at baseline will receive usual care for 9 months and will then start the 3-month exercise intervention of live-video-supervised exercise sessions x3/week for 3 months.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Live-Video-Supervised Exercise Intervention</intervention_name>
    <description>The live-video-supervised exercise intervention includes exercise sessions x3/week for 3 months, and then maintenance regimen for 6 months. Maintenance includes live-video-supervised exercise sessions, only x1/week, and self-exercise x2/week following an individualized prescribed exercise program and use their heart rate monitor as an activity tracker.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Live Video-Supervised Exercise Intervention Arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Usual Care then Live-Video Supervised Exercise Intervention</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients randomized to usual care at baseline will receive usual care for 9 months and will then start the live-video-supervised exercise intervention that includes exercise sessions x3/week for 3 months.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Live-Video-Supervised Exercise Control Arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  9-19 years of age

          -  Fontan palliation

          -  Ability to fast overnight

          -  Cardiac clearance to exercise by primary cardiologist

          -  Presence of an adult at home during exercise sessions for patients &lt;14 years old

          -  English-speaking patient.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  NYHA Class IV (severe heart failure)

          -  Acute illness within the past three months

          -  Active protein losing enteropathy (albumin &lt;2.5 mg/dL)

          -  Implanted pacemaker

          -  Cognitive delay deemed severe enough to inhibit the ability to follow the exercise
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>9 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>19 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Seda Tierney</last_name>
    <phone>650-724-9408</phone>
    <email>tierneys@stanford.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Stanford University, Lucile Packard Children Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Palo Alto</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94304</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Seda Tierney, MD</last_name>
      <phone>650-736-7747</phone>
      <email>fontanstudy@stanford.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>December 6, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 9, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">December 11, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 23, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 23, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 27, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Stanford University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Seda Tierney</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor, Pediatrics</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Fontan palliation</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

