<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04198428</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CTN - 0095</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>UG1DA040316</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04198428</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Clinical Decision Support for Opioid Use Disorders in Medical Settings (COMPUTE 2.0)</brief_title>
  <official_title>Clinic-Randomized Trial of Clinical Decision Support for Opioid Use Disorders in Medical Settings (COMPUTE 2.0)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>HealthPartners Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute on Drug Abuse (NIDA)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>The Emmes Company, LLC</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Hennepin Healthcare Research Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>HealthPartners Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Through CTN-0076-Ot (Clinical Decision Support for Opioid Use Disorders in Medical Settings:
      Pilot Usability Testing in an EMR (COMPUTE)), our team has iteratively developed and piloted
      a web-based and electronic health record (EHR)-integrated Opioid Use Disorder (OUD) Clinical
      Decision Support (CDS) system to offer expert guidance to primary care providers (PCPs) on
      the diagnosis and management of OUD. The OUD-CDS has been implemented within the EPIC EHR of
      one large care system and was piloted with 55 providers to ensure content validity and
      provider satisfaction. The team will now implement this OUD-CDS in a large multi-site
      clinic-randomized controlled trial to evaluate its impact on practice process measures and
      patient outcomes. The investigators also aim to prepare for scalability (i.e., integration
      into usual primary care practice after the study is complete) and dissemination by evaluating
      facilitators and barriers to implementation, determining the costs of implementation and
      maintenance, and assessing the short-term cost impacts of the OUD-CDS.

      The study will include three large diverse care systems and randomize a minimum of 30 clinics
      to receive the OUD-CDS intervention or usual care (UC). In intervention clinics, the OUD-CDS
      will identify patients who are at high risk for OUD or diagnosed with OUD; use data stored in
      the EHR for each eligible patient to assemble treatment recommendations tailored to each
      patient's current needs; display these recommendations to PCPs via the OUD-CDS user
      interface; and store analytic data from all targeted visits. In UC clinics, the OUD-CDS will
      run invisibly in the background to identify high-risk or OUD patients, assemble treatment
      recommendations tailored to each eligible patient's needs, and store analytic data from all
      targeted visits.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The proposed study will include 3 large diverse healthcare systems and randomize a minimum of
      30 clinics equally within each system to receive the OUD-CDS intervention or UC. In
      intervention and UC clinics, the OUD-CDS will identify study-eligible patients, those who are
      at high risk for OUD or diagnosed with OUD; and will use data stored in the EHR to assemble
      treatment recommendations tailored to the needs of each study-eligible patient. In
      intervention clinics, these treatment recommendations will be displayed via the OUD-CDS user
      interface. Finally, data from all targeted visits in all randomized clinics will be stored in
      a data repository for analysis and reporting needs. The targeted visits for each
      study-eligible patient in all randomized clinics will be the index visit, the first visit at
      which the OUD-CDS identifies that the patient is study eligible, and all post-index visits
      through the end of the intervention period, regardless of continued eligibility. This
      pragmatic cluster-randomized design is the optimal design to effectively and efficiently
      implement this tool in primary care clinics while protecting against study contamination and
      allowing for collection of process and outcome data at UC clinics.

      Mixed Methods Approach: Virtually every evidence-based intervention in medicine has turned
      out to be difficult to implement and maintain in real life practice and to fall far short of
      fidelity to the process used in randomized trials. As a result, a whole new field of
      dissemination and implementation research has been developing over the last 20 years. These
      studies have now gone well beyond the previous paradigm of focusing on changing the attitudes
      and behaviors of individual physicians to a growing awareness that the need instead is to
      alter the environment in which physicians work so that it is easier to do the desired
      evidence-based thing than to stick with old established habit patterns. That means focusing
      change efforts on organizational factors and practice systems. The Solberg conceptual
      framework has proven to be particularly helpful in clarifying this new approach.

      Simultaneously, there has been increasing interest in transitioning effectiveness clinical
      trials from traditionally highly selective and controlled circumstances to pragmatic trials
      that make use of normal care delivery processes and patients.[35] The measurement of such
      trials has been facilitated by the development of a conceptual framework called RE-AIM, an
      acronym for 5 key facets of such studies - Reach, Effectiveness, Adoption, Implementation,
      and Maintenance. Recently, the developers of RE-AIM have recognized the need for more
      flexible use of this framework, greater use of qualitative methods to understand why
      interventions are not used consistently, and making adaptations in the implementation
      approach based on such understandings. The investigators propose to use the RE-AIM framework
      to guide (1) a monitoring system for intervention problems, (2) a mixed methods evaluation of
      the reasons for those problems, and (3) modification of the intervention to reduce those
      problems. These steps will be reiterated in a cyclic fashion, resulting in a more
      sophisticated approach to the long-standing quality improvement emphasis on Plan-Do-Study-Act
      rapid cycle tests of change. Furthermore, the team will take advantage of the staggered
      implementation of the study through three different care systems to ensure that the solutions
      for intervention problems in Site 1 are not assumed to be the same as the approach in
      subsequent sites without further RE-AIM monitoring and evaluation.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Suspended</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Recruitment and enrollment delayed due to covid-19
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 12, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 31, 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 31, 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Calculate differences in rates of OUD diagnosis</measure>
    <time_frame>This will be calculated at the end of the study, approximately month 53</time_frame>
    <description>Patients previously undiagnosed with OUD but identified as high risk by the OUD-CDS at an index visit have a higher rate of OUD diagnosis (in the problem list or as an ICD-10 visit code) in intervention clinics when compared to UC clinics within 30 days post-index.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Calculate differences in rate of naloxone rescue kit ordering</measure>
    <time_frame>This will be calculated at the end of the study, approximately month 53</time_frame>
    <description>Patients previously diagnosed with OUD or identified as high risk by the OUD-CDS at an index visit will have a higher proportion of naloxone rescue kits ordered in the intervention clinics when compared to the UC clinics within 30 days post-index.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Calculate differences in rate of MOUD orders or referrals</measure>
    <time_frame>This will be calculated at the end of the study, approximately month 53</time_frame>
    <description>Patients identified as having OUD or as being at high-risk for OUD by the OUD-CDS at an index visit will have a higher rate of MOUD orders or referral for OUD treatment within 30 days post-index in intervention clinics when compared to UC clinics.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Calculate differences in average days covered by MOUD prescription</measure>
    <time_frame>This will be calculated at the end of the study, approximately month 53</time_frame>
    <description>Patients identified as having OUD or as being at high-risk for OUD by the OUD-CDS at an index visit will have significantly more days covered by a MOUD prescription at 90 days post-index in intervention clinics when compared to UC clinics.A generalized linear mixed model will compare the average number of covered days among patients in intervention relative to control clinics</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference between number of Emergency Department visits for intervention and control patients</measure>
    <time_frame>This will be calculated at the end of the study, approximately month 53</time_frame>
    <description>Patients with OUD or identified as high-risk for OUD by the OUD-CDS who are cared for in intervention clinics will have significantly fewer post-index ED visits during the observation period (i.e., the period between each patient's index date and last observation) compared to patients cared for in UC clinics.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Differences in the number of hospitalizations for intervention and control patients</measure>
    <time_frame>This will be calculated at the end of the study, approximately month 53</time_frame>
    <description>Patients with OUD or identified as high-risk for OUD by the OUD-CDS who are cared for in intervention clinics will have significantly fewer post-index hospitalizations during the observation period (i.e., the period between each patient's index date and last observation) compared to patients cared for in UC clinics.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Intervention patients will have lower healthcare compared to patients from usual care clinics</measure>
    <time_frame>This will be calculated at the end of the study, approximately month 53</time_frame>
    <description>After controlling for demographics, baseline clinical status and prior costs of care, patients with OUD or identified as high risk for OUD by the OUD-CDS will have lower healthcare costs in intervention clinics compared to UC clinics during the observation period (i.e., savings from lower ED visits and hospitalizations will outweigh increased costs of OUD treatment and naloxone rescue kits and OUD-CDS implementation and maintenance). Healthcare costs will be calculated for each patient using outpatient, inpatient, emergency, and pharmacy utilization and then compared between intervention and control groups.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Comparing all-cause mortality rates between intervention and control clinic patients</measure>
    <time_frame>This will be calculated at the end of the study, approximately month 53</time_frame>
    <description>Comparing rates of of all-cause death among patients with OUD or identified as high-risk for OUD cared for in intervention clinics during the intervention period compared to similar patients in UC clinics during the observation period.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Comparing rates of fatal and non-fatal overdoses between intervention and control clinic patients</measure>
    <time_frame>This will be calculated at the end of the study, approximately month 53</time_frame>
    <description>Among patients with OUD or identified as high-risk for OUD, we will calculate rates of fatal and non-fatal overdoses in patients cared for in intervention clinics and compare to the rates for similar patients in the usual care clinics during the intervention period</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">3600000</enrollment>
  <condition>Opioid-use Disorder</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Receives OUD-CDS</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Clinics will have access to the OUD-CDS (Opioid Wizard)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Does not Receive the OUD-CDS</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Clinics will not have access to the OUD-CDS (Opioid Wizard). These will be &quot;usual care&quot; clinics.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Opioid Wizard</intervention_name>
    <description>The Opioid Wizard is an OUD clinical decision support tool for primary care providers to help assess, diagnose, and treat OUD in primary care (where appropriate).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Receives OUD-CDS</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  be aged 18-75 years, inclusive, at the time of an index visit;

          -  have been diagnosed with OUD, currently prescribed MOUD, or identified by study
             algorithms as being at high risk of OUD.

          -  Be a patient at a study randomized clinic

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  those receiving active parenteral chemotherapy within the last year,

          -  those with stage 4 or equivalent cancer diagnosis

          -  those enrolled in hospice care or palliative care programs.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>HealthPartners</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bloomington</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55425</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>December 3, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 11, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">December 13, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 8, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 8, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 10, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Substance-Related Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Analgesics, Opioid</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <provided_document_section>
    <provided_document>
      <document_type>Study Protocol and Statistical Analysis Plan</document_type>
      <document_has_protocol>Yes</document_has_protocol>
      <document_has_icf>No</document_has_icf>
      <document_has_sap>Yes</document_has_sap>
      <document_date>September 25, 2019</document_date>
      <document_url>https://ClinicalTrials.gov/ProvidedDocs/28/NCT04198428/Prot_SAP_000.pdf</document_url>
    </provided_document>
  </provided_document_section>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

