<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04198259</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>KY20192116-F-1</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04198259</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Interventional Devascularization Plus HVPG‐Guided Carvedilol Therapy vs TIPS</brief_title>
  <official_title>Interventional Devascularization Plus HVPG‐Guided Carvedilol Therapy vs TIPS for the Prevention of Gastric Variceal Rebleeding in Patients With Liver Cirrhosis: A Prospective, Randomized, Controlled Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Fourth Military Medical University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Fourth Military Medical University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Gastric varices (GV) are present in around 20% of patients with cirrhosis. Bleeding from GV
      accounts for 10-20% of all variceal bleeding. For the prevention of gastric variceal
      bleeding, TIPS or BRTO as firstline treatments were suggested.

      No randomized trials have compared BRTO with other therapies. BRTO and its variations might
      increase portal pressure and might worsen complications, such as ascites or bleeding from EV.
      In this regard, if NSBB is combined with BRTO and its variations (we called interventional
      devascularization) for those HVPG responders, the drawbacks of interventional
      devascularization might be overcome. Therefore, the investigators conducted this RCT to
      compare the effectiveness and safety of TIPS with those of interventional devascularization
      in the prevention of rebleeding from gastric varices.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Gastric varices (GV) are present in around 20% of patients with cirrhosis. Bleeding from GV
      accounts for 10-20% of all variceal bleeding. GV are classified according to their location
      in the stomach and their relationship with esophageal varices (EV). Accordingly, GV are
      divided into gastroesophageal varices (GOV) and isolated gastric varices (IGV) . The
      management of type 1 GOV, which extend from the esophagus along the lesser curvature of the
      stomach, is similar to the management of EV. Historically, bleeding from type 2 GOV (i.e. GOV
      extending into the fundus), type 1 IGV (i.e. located in the fundus) and type 2 IGV (i.e.
      located anywhere in the stomach), is considered to be more severe and difficult to treat than
      EV bleeding. Few studies, mostly retrospective and uncontrolled, have focused on the
      management of non-GOV1 GV, and the optimal treatment remains controversial.

      For the prevention of gastric variceal bleeding, treatment principles can be classified into
      two categories: decreasing portal pressure and obstructing GEV. Methods for decreasing portal
      pressure include medications (NSBB), radiological intervention (TIPS) and surgery. In
      contrast, methods for treating the obstruction of GEV include endoscopic approaches (EVL,
      EIS) or radiological intervention (such as BRTO). Recent portal hypertensive bleeding
      suggested TIPS or BRTO as firstline treatments in the prevention of rebleeding.

      BRTO is a procedure for treatment of fundal varices associated with a large
      gastro-/splenorenal collateral. The technique involves retrograde cannulation of the left
      renal vein by the jugular or femoral vein, followed by balloon occlusion and slow infusion of
      sclerosant to obliterate the gastro-/splenorenal collateral and fundal varices. Several
      variations of the technique exist, such as balloon-occluded antegrade transvenous
      obliteration or occlusion of the collateral by the placement of a vascular plug or coils.
      BRTO has the theoretical advantage over TIPS that it does not divert portal blood inflow from
      the liver. On the other hand, BRTO and its variations might increase portal pressure and
      might worsen complications, such as ascites or bleeding from EV. In this regard, if NSBB is
      combined with BRTO and its variations (we called interventional devascularization) for those
      HVPG responders, the drawbacks of interventional devascularization might be overcome.

      Therefore, the investigators conducted this RCT to compare the effectiveness and safety of
      TIPS with those of interventional devascularization in the prevention of rebleeding from
      gastric varices.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">June 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Cumulative incidence of gastric variceal rebleeding</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Confirmed by endoscopy</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cumulative incidence of variceal hemorrhage related death</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cumulative incidence of hepatic encephalopathy (HE)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>HE is classified as covert HE and overt HE</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cumulative incidence of death</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>all cause mortality</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cumulative incidence of adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>number of adverse events and adverse reactions in each arm</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Correlation between hepatic venous pressure gradient response and cardiac index response to Carvedilol</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Investigate non-invasive tools for risk stratification</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">212</enrollment>
  <condition>Gastric Varices Bleeding</condition>
  <condition>Liver Cirrhoses</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>interventional devascularization</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Interventional devascularization includes BRTO and similar procedure. Several variations of the technique exist, such as balloon-occluded antegrade transvenous obliteration or occlusion of the collateral by the placement of a vascular plug or coils.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Transjugular intrahepatic portosystemic shunt</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>TIPS is an artificial channel within the liver that establishes communication between the inflow portal vein and the outflow hepatic vein.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>interventional devascularization</intervention_name>
    <description>Interventional devascularization (BRTO and its variations) is a procedure for treatment of fundal varices associated with a large gastro-/splenorenal collateral.</description>
    <arm_group_label>interventional devascularization</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>TIPS</intervention_name>
    <description>TIPS is very effective in the treatment of bleeding GV, with more than a 90% success rate for initial hemostasis. It frequently requires additional embolization of spontaneous collaterals feeding the varices. The incidence of encephalopathy was higher after TIPS.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Transjugular intrahepatic portosystemic shunt</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Liver cirrhosis diagnosed by clinical examination, imaging or biopsy

          -  Patients with a previous history of variceal hemorrhage

          -  Gastric variceal confirmed by an endoscopic examination, including IGV1 or IGV2

          -  Aged 18 to 75 years

          -  Adequate liver and kidney function, including Child-Turcotte-Pugh score &lt; 12, MELD
             score &lt;19, and serum creatinine less than 2 times the upper limit of normal.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Active variceal bleeding

          -  Esophageal variceal, including GOV1 or GOV2 type, mainly esophageal varices;

          -  Refractory ascites

          -  Patients with contraindication to treatment of TIPS, including congestive heart
             failure, NYHA III and IV, pulmonary arterial hypertension(&gt;50mmHg), polycystic liver,
             intrahepatic duct dilatation, spontaneous bacterial peritonitis, hepatic
             encephalopathy

          -  Patients with contraindication to treatment of Carvedilol, including asthma,
             insulin-dependent diabetes, peripheral vascular diseases

          -  Child-Turcotte-Pugh score &gt;=12, or MELD score &gt;=19

          -  Budd-Chiari syndrome

          -  The main portal vein thrombosis is greater than 50%

          -  Malignancies

          -  An uncontrolled infection

          -  Previously treated with TIPS, splenectomy pericardia vascular disconnection, or
             surgical shunts

          -  HIV or HIV related illness

          -  Allergic to contrast agent

          -  Lactating or pregnant

          -  Non-compliant patients
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jun Tie, M.D.,Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Fourth Military Medical University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Jun Tie, M.D.,Ph.D.</last_name>
    <phone>+862984771537</phone>
    <email>tiejun7776@163.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Hui Chen, M.D.,Ph.D.</last_name>
    <phone>+862984771537</phone>
    <email>qychenhui@163.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <verification_date>February 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>December 9, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 11, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">December 13, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 2, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 2, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 5, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Fourth Military Medical University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Tie Jun</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Director of clinical research</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>TIPS</keyword>
  <keyword>HVPG</keyword>
  <keyword>BRTO</keyword>
  <keyword>NSBB</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Liver Cirrhosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Esophageal and Gastric Varices</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fibrosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

