<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04191785</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>18-HPNCL-08</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04191785</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluation of the Plasmatic NGAL as a Predictive Marker of Renal Injury in Children With Urinary Infection</brief_title>
  <acronym>NGAL</acronym>
  <official_title>Evaluation of the Plasmatic and Urinary Neutrophil Gelatinase - Associated Lipocalin as a Predictive Marker of Renal Injury in Children With Febrile Urinary Infection</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Fondation Lenval</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Fondation Lenval</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Urinary infections in children is very common. Delay in the diagnosis may be followed by
      complications.

      Pyelonephritis is a febrile urinary infection with a renal injury. In local experience, about
      30-40% of the children don't have an inflammatory syndrome or echographical abnormalities. Do
      they really have a renal injury ? In fact, only the scintigraphy or the Magnetic Resonance
      Imaging (MRI) may show these lesions, but are done only in specific cases (diagnosis of
      uropathy or nephropathy). Recent studies have shown that plasmatic Neutrophil
      Gelatinase-Associated Lipocalin (NGAL) is associated traumatic or inflammatory renal lesions.
      But the plasmatic NGAL cutoff is fluctuant depending on the cohorts and gold standards. The
      main goal is to evaluate a new methodology of dosing NGAL, (immuno-dosage turbidimetric
      dosage). The investigators suppose that plasmatic NGAL protein will detect renal injury,
      which would be confirmed by MRI.

      The aim of this study is to evaluate the area under the curve (AUC) of plasmatic NGAL protein
      with an automatised method, for the detection of renal injury. This would be confirmed by
      reno vesical MRI, in children over 2 years old with febrile urinary infections
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Urinary infections in children is very common and should be diagnosed as soon as possible.
      Delay in the diagnosis ma be followed by complications such as sepsis, renal scar, high blood
      pressure, renal insufficiency.

      The diagnosis may be tough when it comes to children because of its unspecific
      symptomatology. Pyelonephritis is a febrile urinary infection associated to renal
      abnormalities. Following the french recommendations (&quot;Sociéte de Pathologie Infectieuse de
      Langue Française&quot; The French Society of Infectious disease SPILF and &quot;Groupe de Pathologies
      Infectieuses Pédiatriques&quot; The Pediatric infectious disease Group GPIP 2015), the
      investigators should first use an intravenous probabilistic antibiotic during minimum 48
      hours to lower the bacterial inoculum. Then, the investigators should switch to an oral
      antibiotic during 8 days to sterilise the urines.

      In local experience, about 30 to 40 % of the children don't have an inflammatory syndrom or
      echographical abnormalities. Do they really have a renal injury? In fact, only the
      scintigraphy or the Magnetic Resonance Imaging (MRI) may show these lesions, but are done
      only in specific cases (diagnosis of uropathy or nephropathy). Recent studies have shown that
      plasmatic Neutrophil Gelatinase-Associated Lipocalin (NGAL) is associated traumatic or
      inflammatory renal lesions. But the plasmatic NGAL cutoff is fluctuant depending on the
      cohorts and gold standards. In those studies, dosing NGAL was non automatised and long.

      the investigators would like to evaluate a new methodology of dosing NGAL, (immuno-dosage
      turbidimetric dosage). The investigators suppose that plasmatic NGAL protein will detect
      renal injury, which would be confirmed by MRI.

      This is an interventional, prospective, multicentered study. It will last for 2 years. The
      aim of this study is to evaluate the AUC of plasmatic NGAL protein with an automatised
      method, for the detection of renal injury. This would be confirmed by reno vesical MRI, in
      children over 2 years old with febrile urinary infections.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 11, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Compare plasmatic Neutrophil Gelatinase-Associated Lipocalin (NGAL) with gold standard Reno vesical Magnetic Resonance Imaging (MRI)</measure>
    <time_frame>48 hours after inclusion</time_frame>
    <description>NGAL will be evaluated in urines, and plasma. The method will be automatised. The dosage will be from 25 to 5000 ng/ml. Gold standard will be MRI (nephritis is defined by hyperintense zones in diffusion sequence and hyposignal in ADC mode)
The primary outcome measure is to estimate the area under the curve (AUC) defining the different measures of the performance (Sensitivity, specificity) of plasmatic NGAL protein in ng/ml according to the presence or not of a kidney lesion diagnosed at the RMI (gold standard).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Define performance of plasmatic NGAL for the diagnostic of renal abnormality due to a pyelonephritis</measure>
    <time_frame>48 hours after inclusion</time_frame>
    <description>The performance of NGAL will be evaluated (sensitivity, specificity, positive predictive value, negative predictive value) using the chosen cutoff of NGAL. Gold standard will be reno vesical MRI</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Performance and area under the curve (AUC) of C-reactive Protein (CRP) for the diagnostic of pyelonephritis</measure>
    <time_frame>48 hours after inclusion</time_frame>
    <description>The performance (sensitivity, specificity, positive predictive value, negative predictive value) and the AUC of CRP will be defined using the following cutoff (CRP &gt; 20 mg/l ) chosen from the litterature. CRP will be dosed by an automatised method on XL Siemens machine.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Performance and area under the curve (AUC) of Procalcitonin (PCT) for the diagnostic of pyelonephritis</measure>
    <time_frame>48 hours after inclusion</time_frame>
    <description>The performance (sensitivity, specificity, positive predictive value, negative predictive value) and the AUC of PCT will be defined using the following cutoff ( PCT &gt; 0,5 ng/ml) chosen from the litterature. PCT will be dosed using a Brahms automat</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Compare the AUC of plasmatic NGAL and CRP</measure>
    <time_frame>48 hours after inclusion</time_frame>
    <description>AUC for plasmatic NGAL will be compared to AUC of CRP, AUC will be calculated using receiver operator characteristic (ROC) curves</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Compare the AUC of plasmatic NGAL and PCT.</measure>
    <time_frame>48 hours after inclusion</time_frame>
    <description>AUC for plasmatic NGAL will be compared to AUC of PCT. AUC will be calculated using receiver operator characteristic (ROC) curves</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Performance of urinary NGAL</measure>
    <time_frame>48 hours after inclusion</time_frame>
    <description>Define an area under receiver operator characteristic (ROC) curve based on the dosage of urinary NGAL used to diagnose renal abnormality. The method will be automatised. The dosage will be from 25 to 5000 ng/ml. Gold standard will be MRI (nephritis is defined by hyperintense zones in diffusion sequence and hyposignal in Apparent Diffusion coefficient (ADC) mode).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Performance of doppler echography</measure>
    <time_frame>48 hours after inclusion</time_frame>
    <description>The performance of doppler echography (sensitivity, specificity, positive predictive value, negative predictive value) will be established using MRI as a gold standard.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Urinary Tract Infections</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>plasmatic NGAL and MRI</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>plasmatic NGAl and MRI</intervention_name>
    <description>Determination of plasma NGAL protein during routine blood test Realization of a reno vesical MRI at 48 hours of inclusion</description>
    <arm_group_label>plasmatic NGAL and MRI</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Children over 2 years old, continent

          -  Fever ≥ 38,5 degrés Celsius for less than 4 days

          -  Positive urine strip

          -  Parental authorisation

          -  Using french Health Care System

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Uropathy

          -  2nd febrile urinary infection

          -  No parental authorisation

          -  Non confirmed Urinary infection on a well done Cyto Bacteriological Urine (CBU)

          -  Urinal contamination defined by : ≥ 2 bacterial, urinal bacteriuria &lt; 10^5 Colony
             Forming Unit (CFU)/ml

          -  Discovery of an uropathy using doppler echography or MRI
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>2 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>18 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Tran Antoine, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Children Hopital of Nice CHU-Lenval Emergency</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Tran Antoine, MD</last_name>
    <phone>0492030020</phone>
    <phone_ext>+33</phone_ext>
    <email>TRAN.A@pediatrie-chulenval-nice.fr</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Ribet Chloé</last_name>
    <email>chloeribet@neuf.fr</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hôpital La Fontonne</name>
      <address>
        <city>Antibes</city>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>CLARA SCHORI FORTIER, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>CHLOE RIBET</last_name>
      <email>chloeribet@neuf.fr</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>CLARA SCHORI FORTIER, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>KHALFI, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>MARRO, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Fondation Lenval Hopitaux Pediatriques de Nice Chu Lenval</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nice</city>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Tran Antoine, MD</last_name>
      <phone>0492030020</phone>
      <email>tran.a@pediatrie-chulenval-nice.fr</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Ribet Chloé</last_name>
      <email>cloeribet@neuf.fr</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 27, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 5, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">December 10, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 20, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 20, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 21, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Infection</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Communicable Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Urinary Tract Infections</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

