<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04193982</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ECR/346/Inst/AP/2013/RR-16</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04193982</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>An Investigator Initiated Prospective, Four Arms Randomized Comparative Study of Efficacy and Safety of Saroglitazar, Vitamin E and Life Style Modification in Patients With Nonalcoholic Fatty Liver Disease (NAFLD)/ Non-alcoholic Steatohepatitis (NASH)</brief_title>
  <official_title>An Investigator Initiated Prospective, Four Arms Randomized Comparative Study of Efficacy and Safety of Saroglitazar, Vitamin E and Life Style Modification in Patients With Nonalcoholic Fatty Liver Disease (NAFLD)/ Non-alcoholic Steatohepatitis (NASH)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Asian Institute of Gastroenterology, India</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Asian Institute of Gastroenterology, India</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Saroglitazar and Vitamin E are both being extensively used in India for non alcoholic fatty
      liver disease, though none of these drugs are FDA approved for this indication.However they
      are backed up by number of studies which shows improvement in liver function , reduction in
      NAS score. However, there is no head to head trial , nor is there any study with a paired
      biopsy comparing two arms for a head to head study. We therefore designed this study to see
      the effect of Vitamin E vs Vitamin E plus saroglitazar vs Saroglitazar alone when compared to
      standard dietary and weight loss treatment for NAFLD with raised ALT levels.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">September 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 31, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 30, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Non alcoholic fatty liver fibrosis score at 8week, 16week and 24week.</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Non alcoholic fatty liver fibrosis score would be assessed . This is a non invasive test calculated by the formula : -1.675 + 0.037 × age (years) + 0.094 × BMI (kg/m2) + 1.13 × IFG/diabetes (yes = 1, no = 0) + 0.99 × AST/ALT ratio - 0.013 × platelet (×109/l) - 0.66 × albumin (g/dl)
Results are interpreted as :
NAFLD Score &lt; -1.455 = F0-F2 NAFLD Score -1.455 - 0.675 = indeterminate score NAFLD Score &gt; 0.675 = F3-F4
Change in the NAFLD fibrosis score from the initiation of treatment and at end of 6 months would be assessed.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Serum Alanine aminotransferase (ALT) changes at 6 months.</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Changes in Alanine aminotransferase at 6 months would be assessed.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Serum triglycerides (TG) level.</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Improvement as evidenced by decrease in triglyceride at 6 months.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in fibrosis on Liver Biopsy at 6 months.</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>The study involves a paired liver biopsy and patients who undergo the second biopsy will be assessed for regression or decrease in fibrosis and steatosis score on biopsy.
Score interpretation:
Steatosis: &lt; 5%- 0, 5-33%- 1, &gt;33-66%- 2, &gt;66%- 3. Fibrosis: F0- No fibrosis, F1- Mild fibrosis, F2- Moderate fibrosis, F3- Severe fibrosis</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Serum Aspartate aminotransferase (AST) level at 6 months.</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Changes in Aspartate aminotransferase at 6 months would be assessed.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Non alcoholic steatosis (NAS) score on liver biopsy at 6 months.</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Change in Non alcoholic Steatosis (NAS) score at 6 months. NAS score interpretation: Range- 0 to 8
≥5- Non-alcoholic steatohepatitis (NASH)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Glycosylated Hemoglobin (HbA1C) Level at 6 months.</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Change in glycosylated hemoglobin level (amount of glucose attached to hemoglobin) from baseline and at 6 months.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">250</enrollment>
  <condition>NAFLD</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Saraglitazar</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients will receive Saraglitazar 4 mg once daily for 6 months</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Vitamin E</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients will receive Vitamin E 400mg twice daily for 6 months</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Combination</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients will receive combination of Saraglitazar 4 mg once daily and Vitamin E 400mg twice daily for 6 months</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Lifestyle</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients will follow instruction from dietician and life style changes advise as per protocol including targeting 7 to 10percent weight loss in 6 months</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Saroglitazar</intervention_name>
    <description>Patient receives Saraglitazar 4mg once daily</description>
    <arm_group_label>Saraglitazar</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Vitamin E</intervention_name>
    <description>Patient receive Vitamin E 400mg twice daily after food for 6 months</description>
    <arm_group_label>Vitamin E</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Combination drug</intervention_name>
    <description>Patient receives Vitamine E 400mg twice daily and Saraglitazar 4 mg once daily for 6 months</description>
    <arm_group_label>Combination</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Lifestyle Changes</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients receives dietary advise and does exercise in form of aerobic and targets 7 to 10 percent weight loss in 6 months</description>
    <arm_group_label>Lifestyle</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  1. Adults (age 18 to 60) 2. Confirmed Diagnosis of NAFLD established either by imaging
             (ultrasound, CT scan or MRI) or liver biopsy showing simple steatosis, within 6 months
             of the Screening Phase for this study. The diagnosis of NAFLD is made according to the
             American Association for the Study of Liver Diseases (AASLD) criteria (Chalasaniet
             al.2017).

               1. There is hepatic steatosis by imaging or histology,

               2. There is no significant alcohol consumption,

               3. There are no competing etiologies for hepatic steatosis

               4. There are no co-existing causes for chronic liver disease. 3. Patient's
                  demonstration of understanding of study requirements and treatment procedures,
                  willingness to comply with all protocol-required evaluations.

                  4. Either take biopsy proven NAFLD or imaging based NAFLD with ALT more than 1.5
                  times the upper limit of normal. (being considered as 32) 5. Liver biopsy would
                  be done in selected cases where the cause of transaminitis was uncertain of
                  possible biopsy would be done on case to case basis.

                  Exclusion Criteria:

                    1. Absence of regular or excessive use of alcohol within 2 years prior to
                       initial screening. History of alcohol will be taken from the patient and one
                       or more family member and patient will be defined as non-alcoholic if he/she
                       is a total abstainer or takes &gt;20g (males) or 10g (females) of alcohol per
                       day or greater than 14 drinks per week in males or greater than 7 drinks per
                       week in females. Approximately 10 g of alcohol equals one 'drink' unit. One
                       unit equals 30 ml of distilled spirits, 355 ml beer, or 120 ml glass of
                       wine.

                    2. Presence of alternative causes of fatty liver, including:

                         -  Weight loss &gt;10% in the 6 months before the Screening Visit

                         -  Total parenteral nutrition, starvation or protein-calorie malnutrition

                         -  Use of drugs associated with NAFLD for more than 12 consecutive weeks
                            in the 1 year before start of the study, including amiodarone,
                            tamoxifen, methotrexate, systemic glucocorticoids, anabolic steroids,
                            tetracycline, estrogens in doses higher than used in oral
                            contraceptives, vitamin A, L asparaginase, valproate, chloroquine, or
                            antiretroviral drugs.

                    3. History of bowel surgery, gastrointestinal (bariatric) surgery or undergoing
                       evaluation for bariatric surgery for obesity, extensive small-bowel
                       resection, or orthotopic liver transplants (OLT) or listed for OLT.

                    4. History of other chronic liver disease (Viral hepatitis B or C, autoimmune
                       hepatitis, cholestatic and metabolic liver diseases) and hemochromatosis.

                    5. Patient has known cirrhosis (compensated /decompensated) either based on
                       clinical criteria or liver histology or Imaging techniques.

                    6. Patients with Hypothyroidism.

                    7. Unstable cardiovascular disease, including:

                         -  unstable angina, (i.e., new or worsening symptoms of coronary heart
                            disease within the past 3 months), acute coronary syndrome within the
                            past 6 months, acute myocardial infarction in the past 3 months or
                            heart failure of New York Heart Association class (III - IV) or
                            worsening congestive heart failure, or coronary artery intervention,
                            within the past 6 months

                         -  history of (within prior 3 months) or current unstable cardiac
                            dysarrhythmias

                         -  uncontrolled hypertension (systolic BP&gt;180 mmHg and/or diastolic BP
                            &gt;110 mmHg on two consecutive occasions)

                         -  stroke or transient ischemic attack within the prior 6 months

                    8. History of myopathies or evidence of active muscle disease.

                    9. History of malignancy in the past 5 years and/or active neoplasm with the
                       exception of resolved superficial non-melanoma skin cancer.

                   10. Participation in any other therapeutic clinical study in the past 3 months,
                       including participation in any other NAFLD clinical trials.

                   11. History of bladder disease and/or hematuria or has current hematuria except
                       due to a urinary tract infection.

                   12. Illicit substance abuse within the past 12 months.

                   13. Pregnant/lactating female (including positive pregnancy test at the
                       Screening Visit)

                   14. History or other evidence of severe illness or any other conditions that
                       would make the patient, in the opinion of the investigator, unsuitable for
                       the study (such as poorly controlled psychiatric disease, HIV, coronary
                       artery disease or active gastrointestinal conditions that might interfere
                       with drug absorption).

                   15. Patients who will not comply with diet and lifestyle changes can be excluded
                       from the final analysis.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>60 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Mithun Sharma, MD</last_name>
    <phone>8790622655</phone>
    <email>drmithunsharma@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Asian Institute of Gastroenterology Hospitals</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hyderabad</city>
        <state>Telangana</state>
        <zip>500089</zip>
        <country>India</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Mithun Sharma, MD</last_name>
      <phone>8790622655</phone>
      <email>drmithunsharma@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Padaki N Rao, MD DM</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Anand Kulkarni, MD DM</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Pramod DA, MD DM</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Nitin Jagtap, MD DNB</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Duvurr Nageshwar Reddy, MD DM</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Syeda Fatima Sultana, Pharm D</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>India</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Duseja A, Singh SP, Saraswat VA, Acharya SK, Chawla YK, Chowdhury S, Dhiman RK, Jayakumar RV, Madan K, Misra SP, Mishra H, Modi SK, Muruganathan A, Saboo B, Sahay R, Upadhyay R. Non-alcoholic Fatty Liver Disease and Metabolic Syndrome-Position Paper of the Indian National Association for the Study of the Liver, Endocrine Society of India, Indian College of Cardiology and Indian Society of Gastroenterology. J Clin Exp Hepatol. 2015 Mar;5(1):51-68. doi: 10.1016/j.jceh.2015.02.006. Epub 2015 Mar 6. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25941433</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dhiman RK, Duseja A, Chawla Y. Asians need different criteria for defining overweight and obesity. Arch Intern Med. 2005 May 9;165(9):1069-70.</citation>
    <PMID>15883250</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chalasani N, Younossi Z, Lavine JE, Diehl AM, Brunt EM, Cusi K, Charlton M, Sanyal AJ; American Gastroenterological Association; American Association for the Study of Liver Diseases; American College of Gastroenterologyh. The diagnosis and management of non-alcoholic fatty liver disease: practice guideline by the American Gastroenterological Association, American Association for the Study of Liver Diseases, and American College of Gastroenterology. Gastroenterology. 2012 Jun;142(7):1592-609. doi: 10.1053/j.gastro.2012.04.001. Epub 2012 May 15. Erratum in: Gastroenterology. 2012 Aug;143(2):503.</citation>
    <PMID>22656328</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Georgescu EF, Georgescu M. Therapeutic options in non-alcoholic steatohepatitis (NASH). Are all agents alike? Results of a preliminary study. J Gastrointestin Liver Dis. 2007 Mar;16(1):39-46.</citation>
    <PMID>17410287</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sanyal AJ, Brunt EM, Kleiner DE, Kowdley KV, Chalasani N, Lavine JE, Ratziu V, McCullough A. Endpoints and clinical trial design for nonalcoholic steatohepatitis. Hepatology. 2011 Jul;54(1):344-53. doi: 10.1002/hep.24376.</citation>
    <PMID>21520200</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 14, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 8, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">December 11, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 8, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 8, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 10, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Saraglitazar</keyword>
  <keyword>Vitamin E</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Liver Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fatty Liver</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Non-alcoholic Fatty Liver Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Vitamin E</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

