<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04196374</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>R01HL143295</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04196374</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Return of Genomic Results and Aggregate Penetrance in Population-Based Cohorts</brief_title>
  <acronym>PopSeq</acronym>
  <official_title>Return of Genomic Results and Aggregate Penetrance in Population-Based Cohorts</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Brigham and Women's Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Framingham Heart Study</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Jackson Heart Study</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Broad Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Mississippi Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Boston University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Partners HealthCare</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Brigham and Women's Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The PopSeq Project is a prospective cohort study that will develop and implement a genomic
      return of results (gRoR) process in the Framingham Heart Study (FHS) and Jackson Heart Study
      (JHS) cohorts and explore associated medical, behavioral, and economic outcomes. The study
      will interpret the genomic sequences of JHS/FHS participants previously sequenced by TOPMed
      who have consented to genomic return of results and/or genetic testing. We will develop and
      apply new methods for scalable screening/ classification of genomic variants and will explore
      genomic penetrance by phenotyping a subset of participants in the FHS and JHS.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The objectives of this project are to: 1) Return clinically actionable genomic results to
      participants and track outcomes. Among living FHS/JHS participants who have consented to
      gRoR, we will contact those in whom a detrimental actionable variant is discovered in one of
      the genes noted on the ACMG recommended secondary findings list (estimate 2% of
      participants). 2) Improve high-throughput methods for identifying valid pathogenic variation.
      Refine and apply methods for high throughput screening of FHS/JHS genomes in a manner that
      retains high sensitivity for the detection of detrimental variants in ~3500 Mendelian
      disease-associated genes while reducing the false discovery rate of variants that are not
      pathogenic/likely pathogenic. 3) Explore aggregate penetrance for Mendelian diseases. Review
      phenotype data from a subset of FHS and JHS participants and compare this to genotypic data.

      Data to be gathered include outcome and phenotypic data on the individuals who agree to gRoR
      and who learn that they have detrimental variant in one of the ACMG listed genes. These data
      will be self-reported through surveys and available medical records will be reviewed.
      Additional phenotypic data may be collected and reviewed for other non-actionable mendelian
      disease genes to explore genomic penetrance.

      Research participants who are identified with a detrimental variant in an actionable gene may
      receive direct health benefits from learning this information; however, returning genomic
      results to healthy individuals not presenting for a medical indication may pose unexpected
      harms related to variant directed increases in screening and management. This study is
      focused on exploring the benefits and any potential harms related to returning genomic
      information in population-based cohorts. It will also allow us to better understand the
      penetrance of these variants in two populations not selected for disease status and will
      allow us to compare outcomes in a primarily African American population vs a Caucasian
      population. Developing methods to streamline variant analysis will help improve laboratory
      efficiency and will progress the field of variant curation and analysis.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">February 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Follow Through with Disclosure</measure>
    <time_frame>From genetic result notification to 8 months post-disclosure</time_frame>
    <description>JHS/FHS participants who have been sequenced through TOPMed, are alive and have consented for result return will be notified if an actionable genetic result is discovered. We will contact them and offer them the opportunity to have their research result clinically confirmed. We will evaluate the proportion of individuals who elect to have their result confirmed and disclosed to their health care provider.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Costs of Disclosure</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year post-disclosure</time_frame>
    <description>We will determine the costs and associated time demands of implementing gRoR using a microcosting approach in which study staff track the amount of time they spend and the resources they use for each step of the protocol. For follow-up medical care, we will use a gross costing approach where we apply Centers for Medicare and Medicaid fee schedules to completed referrals and tests, hospitalizations and medication changes identified as described above.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Guideline Compliance</measure>
    <time_frame>History before disclosure</time_frame>
    <description>Comparison of participants' personal and family histories of disease and their relevant available medical data against existing guidelines to identify instances where genetic testing and/or referral had been warranted but was never ordered.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>New and Modified Diagnoses</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year post-disclosure</time_frame>
    <description>We will examine cases to determine the percentage of individuals with a new or modified diagnosis attributed to results disclosure.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Self-Rated Health</measure>
    <time_frame>Post disclosure and 1 year post-disclosure</time_frame>
    <description>We will administer a single item of self rated health derived from the SF-12v2.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>MD Recommendations</measure>
    <time_frame>From disclosure to 1 month post-disclosure</time_frame>
    <description>We will review chart notes from results disclosure sessions to determine services recommended in response to genetic findings.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Health Care Utilization</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year post-disclosure</time_frame>
    <description>We will track health care utilization in response to results disclosure in the one year follow-up survey, including a) referrals and tests, b) hospitalizations, and c) medication changes</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Health Behaviors</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year post-disclsoure</time_frame>
    <description>The survey includes a series of standardized yes/no questions to assess whether disclosed genetic information motivated participants to make changes to health behaviors. A summary score will be created based on the number of behaviors that participants report.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Disclosure-specific Impact</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months post-disclosure</time_frame>
    <description>The survey assess the disclosure-specific impact of information on distress and positive emotions using an adapted 8-item version of the FaCTOR, a validated instrument developed for genomic sequencing that is sensitive to responses to high- and low-risk genetic risk results.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Satisfaction with Disclsoure</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months post-disclosure and 1 year post-disclosure</time_frame>
    <description>Surveys will assess how helpful participants felt the results disclosure session was using a novel single question.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Decisional Regret</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months post-disclosure and 1 year post-disclosure</time_frame>
    <description>Surveys will assess if participants regretted their decisions to receive their genetic findings using a novel single question.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Sharing with Relatives</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year post-disclsoure</time_frame>
    <description>The survey will assess with how many relatives participants shared their genetic information.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Family Testing</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year post-disclsoure</time_frame>
    <description>The survey will assess whether participants had relatives that received genetic testing based on disclosure to the participant.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>General Anxiety</measure>
    <time_frame>Post-disclosure and 6 months post-disclosure</time_frame>
    <description>We will measure general anxiety using the General Anxiety Disorder Scale 2 (GAD-2), a validated 2-item instrument that will allow investigators to identify individuals with a potential mood disorder.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">200</enrollment>
  <condition>Seemingly Healthy</condition>
  <condition>Genetic Predisposition to Disease</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Genetic</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Genomic Sequencing</intervention_name>
    <description>Whole Genome Sequencing and reporting of actionable genomic results for genes included on the ACMG secondary findings list.</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Living individuals enrolled in the Framingham Heart Study and the Jackson Heart Study who
        have had their genomes sequenced as part of the TOPMed program.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Living individuals enrolled in the Framingham Heart Study and the Jackson Heart Study
             who have had their genomes sequenced as part of the TOPMed program.

          -  Adults over the age of 18 years

          -  Those who have consented to have their DNA samples used for research purposes (and
             those who participate in gRoR who have consented to receive genomic information).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Participants of the Framingham Heart Study or Jackson Heart Study who have not had
             their genomes sequenced as part of TOPMed

          -  Participants who did not opt for genomic/genetic research

          -  Participants who did/do not consent to receiving a genomic result (for the gRoR
             portion of this study only)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>100 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Carrie L Blout, MS</last_name>
    <phone>617-264-5837</phone>
    <email>cblout@bwh.harvard.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Framingham Heart Study</name>
      <address>
        <city>Framingham</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>01702</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Jackson Heart Study</name>
      <address>
        <city>Jackson</city>
        <state>Mississippi</state>
        <zip>39213</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Biesecker LG, Green RC. Diagnostic clinical genome and exome sequencing. N Engl J Med. 2014 Sep 18;371(12):1170. doi: 10.1056/NEJMc1408914.</citation>
    <PMID>25229935</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kalia SS, Adelman K, Bale SJ, Chung WK, Eng C, Evans JP, Herman GE, Hufnagel SB, Klein TE, Korf BR, McKelvey KD, Ormond KE, Richards CS, Vlangos CN, Watson M, Martin CL, Miller DT. Recommendations for reporting of secondary findings in clinical exome and genome sequencing, 2016 update (ACMG SF v2.0): a policy statement of the American College of Medical Genetics and Genomics. Genet Med. 2017 Feb;19(2):249-255. doi: 10.1038/gim.2016.190. Epub 2016 Nov 17. Erratum in: Genet Med. 2017 Apr;19(4):484.</citation>
    <PMID>27854360</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Green RC, Berg JS, Grody WW, Kalia SS, Korf BR, Martin CL, McGuire AL, Nussbaum RL, O'Daniel JM, Ormond KE, Rehm HL, Watson MS, Williams MS, Biesecker LG; American College of Medical Genetics and Genomics. ACMG recommendations for reporting of incidental findings in clinical exome and genome sequencing. Genet Med. 2013 Jul;15(7):565-74. doi: 10.1038/gim.2013.73. Epub 2013 Jun 20. Erratum in: Genet Med. 2017 May;19(5):606.</citation>
    <PMID>23788249</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wolf SM, Lawrenz FP, Nelson CA, Kahn JP, Cho MK, Clayton EW, Fletcher JG, Georgieff MK, Hammerschmidt D, Hudson K, Illes J, Kapur V, Keane MA, Koenig BA, Leroy BS, McFarland EG, Paradise J, Parker LS, Terry SF, Van Ness B, Wilfond BS. Managing incidental findings in human subjects research: analysis and recommendations. J Law Med Ethics. 2008 Summer;36(2):219-48, 211. doi: 10.1111/j.1748-720X.2008.00266.x. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18547191</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wolf SM, Crock BN, Van Ness B, Lawrenz F, Kahn JP, Beskow LM, Cho MK, Christman MF, Green RC, Hall R, Illes J, Keane M, Knoppers BM, Koenig BA, Kohane IS, Leroy B, Maschke KJ, McGeveran W, Ossorio P, Parker LS, Petersen GM, Richardson HS, Scott JA, Terry SF, Wilfond BS, Wolf WA. Managing incidental findings and research results in genomic research involving biobanks and archived data sets. Genet Med. 2012 Apr;14(4):361-84. doi: 10.1038/gim.2012.23.</citation>
    <PMID>22436882</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Burke W, Evans BJ, Jarvik GP. Return of results: ethical and legal distinctions between research and clinical care. Am J Med Genet C Semin Med Genet. 2014 Mar;166C(1):105-11. doi: 10.1002/ajmg.c.31393. Epub 2014 Mar 10.</citation>
    <PMID>24616381</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute working group, Fabsitz RR, McGuire A, Sharp RR, Puggal M, Beskow LM, Biesecker LG, Bookman E, Burke W, Burchard EG, Church G, Clayton EW, Eckfeldt JH, Fernandez CV, Fisher R, Fullerton SM, Gabriel S, Gachupin F, James C, Jarvik GP, Kittles R, Leib JR, O'Donnell C, O'Rourke PP, Rodriguez LL, Schully SD, Shuldiner AR, Sze RK, Thakuria JV, Wolf SM, Burke GL. Ethical and practical guidelines for reporting genetic research results to study participants: updated guidelines from a National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute working group. Circ Cardiovasc Genet. 2010 Dec;3(6):574-80. doi: 10.1161/CIRCGENETICS.110.958827.</citation>
    <PMID>21156933</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Natarajan P, Gold NB, Bick AG, McLaughlin H, Kraft P, Rehm HL, Peloso GM, Wilson JG, Correa A, Seidman JG, Seidman CE, Kathiresan S, Green RC. Aggregate penetrance of genomic variants for actionable disorders in European and African Americans. Sci Transl Med. 2016 Nov 9;8(364):364ra151.</citation>
    <PMID>27831900</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Christensen KD, Phillips KA, Green RC, Dukhovny D. Cost Analyses of Genomic Sequencing: Lessons Learned from the MedSeq Project. Value Health. 2018 Sep;21(9):1054-1061. doi: 10.1016/j.jval.2018.06.013. Epub 2018 Aug 14.</citation>
    <PMID>30224109</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Christensen KD, Vassy JL, Phillips KA, Blout CL, Azzariti DR, Lu CY, Robinson JO, Lee K, Douglas MP, Yeh JM, Machini K, Stout NK, Rehm HL, McGuire AL, Green RC, Dukhovny D; MedSeq Project. Short-term costs of integrating whole-genome sequencing into primary care and cardiology settings: a pilot randomized trial. Genet Med. 2018 Dec;20(12):1544-1553. doi: 10.1038/gim.2018.35. Epub 2018 Mar 22.</citation>
    <PMID>29565423</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Roberts JS, Robinson JO, Diamond PM, Bharadwaj A, Christensen KD, Lee KB, Green RC, McGuire AL; MedSeq Project team. Patient understanding of, satisfaction with, and perceived utility of whole-genome sequencing: findings from the MedSeq Project. Genet Med. 2018 Sep;20(9):1069-1076. doi: 10.1038/gim.2017.223. Epub 2018 Jan 4.</citation>
    <PMID>29300387</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Vassy JL, Christensen KD, Schonman EF, Blout CL, Robinson JO, Krier JB, Diamond PM, Lebo M, Machini K, Azzariti DR, Dukhovny D, Bates DW, MacRae CA, Murray MF, Rehm HL, McGuire AL, Green RC; MedSeq Project. The Impact of Whole-Genome Sequencing on the Primary Care and Outcomes of Healthy Adult Patients: A Pilot Randomized Trial. Ann Intern Med. 2017 Jun 27;167(3):159-169. doi: 10.7326/M17-0188. Print 2017 Aug 1.</citation>
    <PMID>28654958</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Christensen KD, Dukhovny D, Siebert U, Green RC. Assessing the Costs and Cost-Effectiveness of Genomic Sequencing. J Pers Med. 2015 Dec 10;5(4):470-86. doi: 10.3390/jpm5040470. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26690481</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lupo PJ, Robinson JO, Diamond PM, Jamal L, Danysh HE, Blumenthal-Barby J, Lehmann LS, Vassy JL, Christensen KD, Green RC, McGuire AL; MedSeq Project team. Patients' perceived utility of whole-genome sequencing for their healthcare: findings from the MedSeq project. Per Med. 2016 Jan 1;13(1):13-20. Epub 2016 Jan 8.</citation>
    <PMID>27019659</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wolf SM, Branum R, Koenig BA, Petersen GM, Berry SA, Beskow LM, Daly MB, Fernandez CV, Green RC, LeRoy BS, Lindor NM, O'Rourke PP, Breitkopf CR, Rothstein MA, Van Ness B, Wilfond BS. Returning a Research Participant's Genomic Results to Relatives: Analysis and Recommendations. J Law Med Ethics. 2015 Fall;43(3):440-63. doi: 10.1111/jlme.12288.</citation>
    <PMID>26479555</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>McLaughlin HM, Ceyhan-Birsoy O, Christensen KD, Kohane IS, Krier J, Lane WJ, Lautenbach D, Lebo MS, Machini K, MacRae CA, Azzariti DR, Murray MF, Seidman CE, Vassy JL, Green RC, Rehm HL; MedSeq Project. A systematic approach to the reporting of medically relevant findings from whole genome sequencing. BMC Med Genet. 2014 Dec 14;15:134. doi: 10.1186/s12881-014-0134-1.</citation>
    <PMID>25714468</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Machini K, Ceyhan-Birsoy O, Azzariti DR, Sharma H, Rossetti P, Mahanta L, Hutchinson L, McLaughlin H; MedSeq Project, Green RC, Lebo M, Rehm HL. Analyzing and Reanalyzing the Genome: Findings from the MedSeq Project. Am J Hum Genet. 2019 Jul 3;105(1):177-188. doi: 10.1016/j.ajhg.2019.05.017. Epub 2019 Jun 27.</citation>
    <PMID>31256874</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Vassy JL, Lautenbach DM, McLaughlin HM, Kong SW, Christensen KD, Krier J, Kohane IS, Feuerman LZ, Blumenthal-Barby J, Roberts JS, Lehmann LS, Ho CY, Ubel PA, MacRae CA, Seidman CE, Murray MF, McGuire AL, Rehm HL, Green RC; MedSeq Project. The MedSeq Project: a randomized trial of integrating whole genome sequencing into clinical medicine. Trials. 2014 Mar 20;15:85. doi: 10.1186/1745-6215-15-85.</citation>
    <PMID>24645908</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>December 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>December 10, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 10, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">December 12, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 20, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 20, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">December 24, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Brigham and Women's Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Robert C. Green, MD, MPH</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor of Medicine</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Disease Susceptibility</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Genetic Predisposition to Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Individual participant data will not be shared. Aggregate data will be shared through publication and will be considered upon request.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

