<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04197336</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IRB00143169</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04197336</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Bariatric Embolization of Arteries With Imaging Visible Embolics (BEATLES)</brief_title>
  <acronym>BAE2</acronym>
  <official_title>Bariatric Embolization of Arteries With Imaging Visible Embolics</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Johns Hopkins University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Biocompatibles UK Ltd</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Johns Hopkins University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Obesity is defined as a body mass index (BMI) ≥30 kg/m2 and with a subclass of obesity known
      as morbid or severe obesity (BMI of ≥40 kg/m2). These are major issues in medicine for both
      participants and medical providers with &gt;36% of the US population affected. Obesity is one of
      the biggest causes of preventable chronic diseases and healthcare costs in the USA. Obese
      adults spend 42% more on direct healthcare costs and morbidly obese adults overall have 81%
      higher healthcare costs than non-obese adults. Obesity is currently treated with dietary,
      pharmacological, and/or surgical approaches that are often unsuccessful or are associated
      with additional risks. As the incidence and prevalence of obesity and obesity-related
      diseases are steadily increasing, there is a growing need to detect the key risk factors
      involved in disease development and modify standard treatment procedures and protocols.

      The most successful long-term strategy continues to be bariatric and metabolic surgeries,
      such as sleeve gastrectomy and Roux-en-Y gastric bypass (RYGBP). The NIH recommends bariatric
      surgery for participants with a BMI of 40 kg/m2 or greater or a BMI of 35 kg/m2 or greater
      and obesity related comorbidities. These surgeries enable participants to lose between 50%
      and 75% of excess body weight. Despite this success, participants are apprehensive and do not
      undergo bariatric surgery with the biggest fear being the many complications that come with
      the procedure. Studies have shown that 57-77% of participants are not interested in bariatric
      surgery although the participants qualify.(16)

      With the concern of complications from bariatric surgery, interest in endoscopic bariatric
      techniques has increased over the years. The techniques have been shown to be efficacious,
      reversible, relatively safe, and cost effective. Further, these techniques offer a
      therapeutic window for some participants who may otherwise be unable to undergo bariatric
      surgery. The American Society for Gastrointestinal Endoscopy have approved endoscopic
      procedures, such as balloon therapy, for participants with BMI in the 30-40 kg/m2
      range.(17,18) However, the products used in these therapies also have several limitations
      primarily the inability to provide long term weight loss given the temporary nature of these
      balloons.(19) Common adverse events following intragastric balloon insertion include
      abdominal pain (33.7%), gastroesophageal reflux disease (18.3%), anorexia, and nausea (29%).
      Severe complications such as gastric ulcers (2%), small bowel obstruction (0.3%), perforation
      (0.1%), balloon migration (1.4%), and death (0.08%) are less common. Early balloon removal
      occurred in 9.1% of the study participants due to participant intolerance.(20)

      In a pilot study to assess safety and efficacy (BEAT Obesity), 20 morbidly obese participants
      with a BMI of ≥40 kg/m2 with no other comorbid conditions underwent bariatric embolization
      and were followed for 12 months. Participants were embolized with 300-500 µm Embospheres.
      None of the 20 participants in the BEAT Obesity trial (the largest prospective trial to date)
      had any major adverse events. Any gastric ulcers that occurred (40%) were asymptomatic and
      were completely healed by three months after the procedure.(21)

      There were many limitations of this study including the absence of a control cohort and
      non-compliance amongst study participants. A target population of participants with a BMI of
      40 kg/m2 and above was too high considering the bariatric embolization procedure is
      comparable to endoscopic bariatric therapies rather than bariatric surgery. BEAT Obesity
      excluded participants with comorbidities, such as those who suffer from diabetes, who may
      greatly benefit from this procedure and are often the target population for
      endoscopic/surgical bariatric therapies. A larger bead size of 300-500 µm was specifically
      chosen compared to preclinical data and prior clinical reports due to concerns of gastric
      ischemia and ulceration. However, smaller bead size produces greater weight loss and hormonal
      shifts.(22)

      Investigators hypothesize that transvascular bariatric embolization results in safe and
      effective weight loss in obese participants compared to control subjects.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The BEATLES study is an investigator-initiated, prospective, double-blinded, randomized,
      sham-controlled study that will assess the impact of bariatric embolization on the systemic
      levels of obesity-related hormones and, as a consequence, on weight loss. The goal of this
      study is to help treat obesity combining a lifestyle program and a minimally invasive,
      angiographic (i.e., through blood vessels) approach.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 10, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>prospective, double-blinded, randomized, sham-controlled study</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>All procedure images and reports, regardless of the randomization arm, will be kept with the unblinded member of the study team, and will not be housed centrally. All participants will adhere to the same follow-up schedule, meeting with blinded members of the study team only. The procedural team will not have further contact with the participant, the participant will only be followed by the blinded study team. Once the study is closed, all reports and images will be entered into the clinical record.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Efficacy of Bariatric Embolization procedure: Change in body weight</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Change in body weight 12 months after randomization</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">59</enrollment>
  <condition>Obesity</condition>
  <condition>Morbid Obesity</condition>
  <condition>Weight Loss</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control Arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Sham Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>27 participants enrolled in the procedure arm. Participants randomized to the control arm will follow the same screening. Pre-procedure assessment will take the same pre-procedure meds. Procedure day, interventional radiologist will determine radial or groin access. After the participant and procedure area are prepped, participants will be under standard moderate sedation medications; all participants will receive lidocaine &amp; a skin nick to their groin or their wrist as determined by the operating physician. Participant will have a blind fold placed &amp; their hearing damped either with ear plugs or noise cancelling headphones. Participants randomized to the control arm will not receive other procedural intervention. Procedural team will follow a prescribed simulated protocol. Participants randomized to the control arm will be given under skin lidocaine and receive a skin nick on the wrist or groin.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Bariatric Embolization Procedure</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>27 subjects will be enrolled in the bariatric embolization(BM) procedure arm. BM procedure will be performed under moderate sedation. Procedure will take 1.5 hr to 3 hr subject will be placed on the X-ray fluoroscopy table. Radial or femoral vascular access will be achieved using a small gauge needle, dilated over a guidewire to accommodate a 5 French vascular sheath. Standard catheters, 3 dimensional imaging will be acquired of the stomach, the arteries supplying the fundus arising off the celiac vessel. Microcatheter into the left gastric and/or gastroepiploic arteries supplying the fundus and small calibrated spheres will be infused until stasis of anterograde arterial flow is achieved, with particular care to avoid infusion of non-target arteries. The left gastric and/or gastroepiploic arteries will be embolized. Repeat 3 dimensional imaging: assess bead distribution and fundal coverage. Subject will be monitored in the recovery room and will be observed overnight.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Bariatric Embolization of Arteries with imaging visible Embolics</intervention_name>
    <description>The BEATLES study is an investigator-initiated, prospective, doubleblind, randomized, sham-controlled study that will assess the impact of bariatric embolization on the systemic levels of obesity related hormones and, as a consequence, on weight loss. The goal of this study is to help treat obesity combining a lifestyle program and a minimally invasive, angiographic (i.e., through blood vessels) approach.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Bariatric Embolization Procedure</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>100-200 µm radiopaque microspheres</other_name>
    <other_name>Biocompatibles-001933</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Control Arm</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants randomized to the control arm will follow the same screening and pre-procedure assessment, and will also take the same pre-procedure medications. The procedural team instead will follow a prescribed simulated protocol that will mimic an actual embolization procedure.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control Arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Male or female, aged ≥21 and ≤70 years

          -  Willing, able, and mentally competent to provide written informed consent

          -  Obese patients with a BMI ≥35 kg/m2

          -  Weight ≤400 lb

          -  Vascular anatomy (including celiac, hepatic, and gastric arteries) that in the opinion
             of the interventional radiologist is amendable to bariatric embolization, as assessed
             via 3D CT angiography

          -  Suitable for protocol therapy, as determined by the interventional radiology
             investigator

          -  Adequate hematologic (neutrophils&gt;1.5x109/L, platelets&gt;70x109/L, INR&lt;1.5), hepatic
             (bilirubin≤2.0mg/dL, albumin≥2.5g/L), and renal (estimated GFR&gt;60mL/min. 1.73m2)
             function

          -  For females of reproductive potential: agreement to use of highly effective
             contraception

          -  for duration of study participation

          -  Patients who have failed conservative weight loss therapies such as supervised low
             calorie diets combined with behavior therapy and exercise

          -  Live or work within 65 miles of the enrolling institution in case a catastrophic post
             embolization event occurs

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  hemoglobin A1c greater than 8%

          -  Patients who are currently taking either Insulin or sulfonylurea (medication changes
             are allowed)

          -  Prior history of gastric, pancreatic, hepatic, and/or splenic surgery

          -  Prior radiation therapy to the upper abdomen

          -  Prior embolization to the stomach, spleen, or liver

          -  Cirrhosis

          -  Known portal venous hypertension

          -  Active peptic ulcer disease

          -  Significant risk factors for peptic ulcer disease, including daily NSAID use

          -  Large hiatal hernia, defined as &gt;5 cm in size

          -  Active H. Pylori infection

          -  Known aortic pathology, such as aneurysm or dissection

          -  Renal insufficiency, as evidenced by an estimated glomerular filtration rate of &lt;60
             mL/min

          -  Major comorbidity, such as active cancer, significant cardiovascular disease, or
             peripheral arterial disease

          -  Pregnancy

          -  Pre-existing chronic abdominal pain

          -  Positive stool occult blood study

          -  GI bleeding or bleeding diathesis within 5 years

          -  Weight loss (intentional or unintentional) of more than or equal to 5% of body weight
             in the 6 months prior to randomization

          -  A weight loss greater than 6lb during the weight management run- in

          -  Endoscopic findings that would preclude bariatric embolization (at the discretion of
             the study team)

          -  History of gastric motility disorders or an abnormal nuclear gastric motility
             examination (to be performed in diabetic subjects only)

          -  American Society of Anesthesiologists Class 4 or 5 (very high risk surgical
             candidates: class 4=incapacitating disease that is a constant threat to life) at the
             time of screening for enrollment into the study - this exclusion criterion exists,
             because of the possibility that surgical intervention will be needed if the study
             intervention subsequently leads to severe adverse effects

          -  Inflammatory bowel disease

          -  Autoimmune disease or HIV+

          -  History of allergy to iodinated contrast media

          -  Failure to comply with pre-procedure weight management &quot;run-in&quot;, or other
             pre-procedural visits (specifically, participants must complete 80% of weight
             management and Lose It! Food tracking, and 100% of one-time visits, i.e. MRI, CTA,
             endoscopy)

          -  Applicability of any contraindication regarding patient's vasculature as per
             Instruction for Use

          -  Inability to have an MRI scan (i.e., metal implants or claustrophobia)

          -  Smokers/vape users/tobacco use

          -  Active or new-onset endocrine disorders (stable disease acceptable)

          -  Other unforeseen conditions that may make patients unsuitable for the procedure (study
             team discretion)

        Exclusion Criteria (Psychiatric):

          -  As determined by clinical judgment based on Clinical Interview,
             psychological/behavioral measures, medical records, previous mental health
             records/other collateral information (as available) and consistent with DSM -5
             criteria:

          -  Diagnosis of severe mental illness (i.e., chronic psychotic spectrum disorders,
             clinically significant mood disorders) AND/OR one or more of the following:

          -  Evidence of active relapse or active impairing symptoms (e.g., suicidal ideation,
             audio or visual hallucinations, paranoia, thought disturbance, severe impairment)

          -  Evidence of minimal supports or limited adherence to ongoing mental health care

          -  Failure to provide comprehensive aftercare plan that includes emergency plan for
             addressing future mental health relapse

          -  History of treatment refractory mental illness/recurrent relapse (multiple suicide
             attempts or inpatient psychiatric hospitalizations in the past 5 years)

          -  Within past 3 years: Inpatient psychiatric hospitalization

          -  Within past 5 years: Suicide attempt

          -  Declining to provide mental health records, a letter of support from mental health
             professionals, or consent for verbal consultation with mental health professionals
             when determined to be essential to evaluation.

          -  Cognitive impairment, if judged to have

          -  Limited capacity to make informed decision about procedure and inability to verbalize
             an understanding of the surgical procedure, risks and benefits.

          -  Inability to demonstrate an understanding of the permanency of lifestyle change
             required

          -  History of Anorexia or History of/Active Bulimia: If determined to be of low enough
             severity not to be a clear contraindication, minimum of 5 years abstinence from
             bulimia, current moderate to severe binge eating or night eating syndrome

          -  Active or History of Substance Abuse with less than 5 years of abstinence

          -  Current use of anti-tricyclic anti-depressants or steroids, psychiatric medications
             associated with weight gain.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>21 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Clifford Weiss, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Johns Hopkins University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Clifford Weiss, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>410-614-1046</phone>
    <email>cweiss@jhmi.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Johns Hopkins University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21287</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Clifford Weiss</last_name>
      <email>BEATLES@jhmi.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hu Z, Cha SH, van Haasteren G, Wang J, Lane MD. Effect of centrally administered C75, a fatty acid synthase inhibitor, on ghrelin secretion and its downstream effects. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2005 Mar 15;102(11):3972-7. Epub 2005 Feb 23.</citation>
    <PMID>15728730</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Loftus TM, Jaworsky DE, Frehywot GL, Townsend CA, Ronnett GV, Lane MD, Kuhajda FP. Reduced food intake and body weight in mice treated with fatty acid synthase inhibitors. Science. 2000 Jun 30;288(5475):2379-81.</citation>
    <PMID>10875926</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cummings DE, Purnell JQ, Frayo RS, Schmidova K, Wisse BE, Weigle DS. A preprandial rise in plasma ghrelin levels suggests a role in meal initiation in humans. Diabetes. 2001 Aug;50(8):1714-9.</citation>
    <PMID>11473029</PMID>
  </reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Kojima M, Hosoda H, Date Y, Nakazato M, Matsuo H, Kangawa K. Ghrelin is a growth-hormone-releasing acylated peptide from stomach. Nature. 1999 Dec 9;402(6762):656-60.</citation>
    <PMID>10604470</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>December 11, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 12, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">December 13, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 19, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 19, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 20, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Obesity</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Obesity, Morbid</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Weight Loss</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

