<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04196465</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2019-0988</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04196465</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Phase II Study of Neoadjuvant Immune Checkpoint Inhibitor in Patients With Resectable Gastrointestinal Cancers</brief_title>
  <acronym>NeoChance</acronym>
  <official_title>Phase II Study of Neoadjuvant Immune Checkpoint Inhibitor in Patients With Resectable Gastrointestinal Cancers(Neo-Chance Study)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Asan Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Asan Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>Yes</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a phase II, open-label, prospective single-centered study. Subjects who meet the
      inclusion/exclusion criteria will be allocated to appropriate cohorts: 1) gastric cancer, 2)
      esophageal cancer and 3) hepatocellular carcinoma. Each cancer cohort group will be treated
      with two cycles of neoadjuvant immune checkpoint inhibitor of IMC-001 (1 cycle = 2 weeks)
      followed by curative resection and be followed up consecutively.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a phase II, open-label, prospective single-centered study. Subjects who meet the
      inclusion/exclusion criteria will be allocated to appropriate cohorts: 1) gastric cancer, 2)
      esophageal cancer and 3) hepatocellular carcinoma. Each cancer cohort group will be treated
      with two cycles of neoadjuvant immune checkpoint inhibitor of IMC-001 (1 cycle = 2 weeks)
      followed by curative resection and be followed up consecutively.

      The sample size of the study is determined based on a major pathologic response rate (primary
      endpoint) and by using Simon's single stage design from the subjects who receive preoperative
      neoadjuvant therapy of IMC-001.

      In each cancer cohort group, the null and alternative response rates are assumed as 5% and
      20%, respectively. This provides a power of 80% when calculating the difference between major
      pathologic response rates of 5% and 20% in two-tailed significance level of 0.153 (Type I
      error[two-tailed] of 15.3%). In order to reject the null hypothesis, at least two major
      pathological respondents are needed among 14 assessable subjects for each cancer cohort.
      After choosing the margin of safety as 10%, each cancer cohort will require 16 subjects and
      therefore a total of 48 subjects will be enrolled into the study.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 9, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 26, 2026</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 9, 2026</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>This study is a prospective, IMC-001 single arm, open label, single center, phase II study.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Major pathologic response rate</measure>
    <time_frame>After surgical resection within 28days</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluation of major pathologic response rate (a proportion of residual viable tumor cells &lt;10%) after administration of pre-operative immune checkpoint inhibitor IMC-001</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The safety and feasibility</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 14 days after the end of Cycle 2 (+,- 4days)</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluation of safety assessed by NCI CTCAE v. 4.03 and evaluation of feasibility assessed by the occurrence of delays in prearranged surgery.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>R0 resection rate</measure>
    <time_frame>After surgical resection within 1 month</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluation of R0 resection rate</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical tumor response rate</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluation of clinical tumor response rate by RECIST v1.1</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clnical disease control rate</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluation of clinical disease control rate by RECIST v1.1</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression-free survival</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluation of progression-free survival</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Relapse-free survival</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluation of relapse-free survival</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluation of overall survival</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The rates and patterns of cancer progression/relapse</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluation of the rates of cancer progression/relapse</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patterns of cancer progression/relapse</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluation of the pattern of cancer progression/relapse</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Discovery of predictive and/or prognostic biomarkers</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Discovery of predictive and/or prognostic biomarkers using pre- and post- treatment tumor tissue, blood (circulating tumor DNA, immune cells, etc.), and stool (microbiome) by performing immune profiling and genome analysis</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">48</enrollment>
  <condition>Subjects With Resectable and Localized Gastric Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Subjects With Resectable Esophageal Cancer or Liver Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Subjects With Resectable Liver Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Neoadjuvant IMC-001</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Neoadjuvant immune check point inhibitor of IMC-001 in participants with resectable and localized gastric cancer, esophageal cancer, and hepatocellular carcinoma</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>IMC-001</intervention_name>
    <description>IMC-001 is a fully human anti-programmed cell death ligand 1 (PD-L1) recombinant monoclonal antibody that strongly binds to PD-L1 to inhibit its binding to programmed cell death protein 1 (PD-1) or B7-1 (CD80). IMC-001 showed robust dose-dependent efficacy in animal models and no evidence of toxicity in cynomolgus monkeys</description>
    <arm_group_label>Neoadjuvant IMC-001</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        &lt;Disease-related inclusion criteria&gt;

          1. Histologically confirmed localized gastric adenocarcinoma, esophageal squamous cell
             carcinoma, hepatocellular carcinoma or clinically diagnosed hepatocellular carcinoma
             according to American Association for the Study of Liver Disease (AASLD)
             guidelines.However, in cases of hepatic carcinoma that can be clinically diagnosed
             according to AASLD guideline, no biopsy is performed.

          2. Curatively resectable gastric adenocarcinoma, esophageal squamous cell carcinoma or
             hepatocellular carcinoma

             A. Gastric adenocarcinoma: clinical stage ≥T2 or regional lymph node metastasis (N+)
             (AJCC 8th)

             B. Esophageal squamous cell carcinoma: clinical stage ≥T1b or N+ (AJCC 8th)

             C. Hepatocellular carcinoma: a single hepatocellular carcinoma limited to liver or 3
             or less hepatocellular carcinoma limited to liver without invasion to main portal
             trunk

          3. The requirements for hematology, blood chemistry, and functionality in major organs
             are as follows (should be met within 7 days prior to the first administration of
             investigational medicinal product):

             A. Absolute neutrophil count ≥1,000/μL

             B. Platelets count ≥75,000/μL

             C. Total bilirubin ≤1.5 × Upper limit of Normal (ULN) (subjects with Gilbert syndrome:
             bilirubin ≤ 3.0 × ULN)

             D. Aspartate aminotransferase (AST) or alanine aminotransferase (ALT) ≤ 2.5 × ULN;
             alkaline phosphatase ≤ 2.5 × ULN

             E. Serum creatinine ≤1.5 × ULN or creatinine clearance ≥50 mL/minute (creatinine
             clearance is first calculated by the formula of Cockcroft-Gault and in case of the
             value less than 50 mL/min, by collecting and examining 24-hour urine the subjects with
             the creatine clearance ≥50 mL/minute can be enrolled) (Refer to Supplement 1).

             F. Urine protein-creatinine ratio (UPC) ≤1 (in case of UPC &gt;1, by collecting and
             examining 24-hour urine the subjects with the urine protein &lt;2 g/day can be enrolled)

             G. Also, in case of hepatocellular carcinoma, liver function with Child-Pugh grade A
             (Refer to Supplement 2) and encephalopathy grade 0.

          4. Measurable or evaluable lesion(s) according to Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid
             Tumors (RECIST) version 1.1 (Refer to Supplement 3).

          5. Tumor tissue specimen, classified as appropriate for biomarker analysis, must be
             provided (in case of hepatocellular carcinoma, subjects, without tissue specimen prior
             to the administration of investigational medicinal product, are allowed for enrollment
             into the study).

             &lt;General inclusion criteria&gt;

          6. Aged ≥ 19 years old

          7. Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status 0-1

          8. Signed informed consent form

          9. In the case of fertility men and women, Those who should be using adequate
             contraceptive measures while on study drug and for 3months following the last dose of
             study drug.

        Exclusion Criteria:

        &lt;Tumor-related exclusion criteria&gt;

          1. Curatively unresectable or metastatic disease

          2. Any prior treatment for gastric adenocarcinoma, esophageal squamous cell carcinoma or
             hepatocellular carcinoma. However, in case of hepatocellular carcinoma, it is possible
             for subjects to be enrolled into the study only if the treatment for local lesion was
             carried out ≥6 months ago and the treated area showed disease progression, or a
             curatively resectable new lesion has occurred outside the previously treated area, and
             other inclusion/exclusion criteria are met.

          3. Patients with history of other cancers within three years prior to the study
             treatment. However, patients with other cancers with less influence on their prognosis
             such as carcinoma in situ or thyroid papillary carcinoma, in the opinion of the
             investigator, can be enrolled into the study.

          4. History of hepatic encephalopathy.

          5. Clinically significant ascites defined as follows:

             A. When screening, the physical examination reveals ascites or

             B. Previous ascites that required treatment and continuous prevention or current
             ascites that require treatment.

             &lt;Investigational medicinal product-related exclusion criteria&gt;

          6. History of active autoimmune disease with systematic treatment (i.e. immunomodulator,
             corticosteroid, or immunosuppressant) required within the past 2 years. Replacement
             therapy (e.g. physiological corticosteroid replacement therapy due to dysfunction of
             thyroxine, insulin, adrenal gland, or pituitary gland, etc.) is not regarded as a form
             of systematic treatment and would be allowed.

          7. Diagnosis of immunodeficiency or within 7 days prior to the first administration of
             investigational medicinal product treatments with chronic systematic steroids (the
             dose equivalent to 10 mg/day of prednisone) or immunosuppressive therapy in any other
             forms are not permitted.

          8. History of non-infectious interstitial pneumonia requiring treatment of steroids or
             currently diagnosed.

          9. Any prior treatment with anti-PD-1, anti-PD-L1, anti-PD-L2, anti-CTLA-4 antibody or
             other antibodies or drugs, specifically target co-stimulatory T cells or immune
             checkpoint pathways.

             &lt;General exclusion criteria&gt;

         10. Any known hypersensitivity or anaphylaxis of severeness to recombinant proteins
             containing monoclonal antibodies.

         11. Active infection with systematic treatment required.

         12. From the viewpoint of the investigator, medical conditions, treatments, or laboratory
             test abnormalities that are likely to cause confusion in clinical trial results, or
             that are likely to interfere with subjects' participation throughout the entire study,
             or that are not considered to be in the best interests of the subjects.

         13. Positive urine test or blood pregnancy test in childbearing females within 7 days
             prior to the first administration of investigational medicinal product.

         14. Pregnant or lactating, or during the scheduled study period of 90 days after the final
             administration of investigational medicinal product, subjects have a plan to have
             conception.

         15. Diagnosis of symptomatic congestive heart failure (i.e. New York Heart Association
             Classification class II and up) or history of clinically significant heart arrhythmia
             that requires other antiarrhythmic drugs other than beta blockers and digoxin, or
             currently diagnosed or occurrence of conduction disorders (atrial fibrillation,
             paroxysmal supraventricular tachycardia are exceptional) within 6 months prior to the
             study, active coronary artery diseases, unstable angina, new occurrence of angina
             within 3 months before enrollment of the study, cardiac infarction within 6 months
             before enrollment of the study.

         16. History of human immunodeficiency virus (HIV 1/2 antibody)

         17. Subjects with active hepatitis B (HBsAg-positive or detectable HBV DNA) or hepatitis C
             (detectable HCV RNA). Patients with hepatitis B can be enrolled in the study, only if
             HBV DNA &lt;500 IU/mL (or 2500 copies/mL). Patients with positive-HCV antibody can be
             enrolled only if negative HCV RNA.

         18. History of allogeneic tissue/solid organ transplant.

         19. Inoculation with live vaccine 28 days prior to the first administration of
             investigational medicinal product.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>19 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Sook Ryun Park, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <phone>+82-2-3010-3210</phone>
    <email>srpark@amc.seoul.kr</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Woo Ri JO</last_name>
    <phone>+82-2-3010-8463</phone>
    <email>dotory5595@naver.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Asan Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seoul</city>
        <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sook Ryun Park, Ph.D.</last_name>
      <phone>+82-2-3010-3210</phone>
      <email>srpark@amc.seoul.kr</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 28, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 10, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">December 12, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 10, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 10, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">December 12, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Asan Medical Center</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Sook Ryun Park</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associated professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Liver Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Gastrointestinal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

