<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04194827</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ADDORA</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04194827</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Adalimumab Drug Optimisation in Rheumatoid Arthritis Using Therapeutic Drug Monitoring</brief_title>
  <acronym>ADDORA</acronym>
  <official_title>Adalimumab Drug Optimisation in Rheumatoid Arthritis Using Therapeutic Drug Monitoring (ADDORA): Multi-centre Open Label Randomised Controlled Trail</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Reade Rheumatology Research Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>ZonMw: The Netherlands Organisation for Health Research and Development</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Sint Maartenskliniek</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Reade Rheumatology Research Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Several prior studies have shown that dose reduction of Tumor Necrosis Factor
      (TNF)-inhibitors like adalimumab is possible in substantial number of rheumatic disease
      patients without an increase in disease activity. Biologic therapy is expensive, and is
      associated with patient burden as dose dependant risk for serious infections . A dose
      reduction will decrease the risk of side effects and result in substantial cost savings.
      Currently, most clinicians use Disease Activity Score in 28 joints (DAS28) and the Clinical
      Disease Activity Index (CDAI) to monitor dose tapering strategies. Although this approach is
      cost-effective, it might be improved by information on the extent of drug levels, as several
      studies have shown that adalimumab drug levels are associated with clinical outcome.
      Therefore, a study comparing dose reduction strategy using drug concentration with dose
      reduction strategy using disease activity is timely
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Since the introduction of biologics in rheumatology, as well as treat-to-target (measuring
      disease activity and adapting treatment accordingly) the prognosis of patients has improved
      substantially. Obviously, patient burden due to self-injection or infusion, the risk of
      adverse events and costs demand responsible use of these agents. Multiple studies have shown
      that a large proportion of patients with rheumatoid arthritis with stable low disease
      activity can taper their dose or stop without relapse of disease activity. This can be done
      by using disease activity guided tapering. Drawbacks, however, include increased risk for
      short lived flares, the effort of slowly and carefully tapering, and somewhat more risk of
      radiographic damage due to higher mean disease activity. As most biologics are characterized
      by wide variation in pharmacokinetics between patients, therapeutic drug monitoring (TDM),
      i.e. dose based on serum trough concentration, might be an attractive approach to lower the
      dose quickly while remaining clinical efficacy. Although some data suggest that the minimal
      effective concentration varies between patients, we demonstrated in an earlier study that
      serum adalimumab concentration of 5 mg/L is enough for initial response to adalimumab. In the
      first phase of treatment, drug concentration must be high enough to control immunogenicity.
      To control disease activity after 28 weeks, lower concentrations than 5 mg/L are probably
      sufficient. Since around 70% of the patients have an adalimumab concentration above 5 mg/l,
      we assume that dose reduction to achieve these lower targets (for example direct doubling of
      interval in patients with levels &gt; 10 mg/L) will result in the lowest effective drug dose.
      Our study group illustrated in 2018 that dose reduction by extending the dosing interval with
      50% is non inferior to continuation of standard dose in patients with adalimumab levels &gt;
      8mg/L. In other words, measuring drug concentrations can help clinicians to select
      overexposed patients to reduce the dose of adalimumab without adversely affecting clinical
      efficiency. We posit that therapeutic drug monitoring can attribute to a more efficient dose
      reduction strategy. Since steady state drug concentrations are achieved within 16 weeks of
      treatment, we expect that the dose can be reduced from this point. This is earlier in
      treatment compared to the strategy using disease activity alone, namely after 6 months of
      treatment. Conceptually, such a test can improve disease activity guided dose reduction in
      two ways: 1) flaring caused by empirical tapering (i.e. through trial and error) below the
      minimal effective concentration would be avoided, and 2) patients can be directly given their
      minimum effective dose instead of empirical tapering, thereby saving time and drugs. Our aim
      is to investigate whether the use of drug levels can attribute to a more efficient dose
      reduction strategy of adalimumab in patients with RA. In this study we will compare costs and
      clinical efficiency of two dose reduction strategies: a strategy using drug concentration
      versus a strategy using disease activity scores. We expect that direct medical costs will be
      lower in the 'drug concentration guided' strategy because: 1) overexposed patient can reduce
      the dose more timely and, 2) adalimumab dose can be further reduced after 6 months of
      treatment since we posit that adalimumab concentration of 2 mg/L is sufficient to control
      disease.

      In this multi-centre, randomised, open-label trail we will evaluate whether dose reduction of
      adalimumab using drug concentration can reduce medical costs compared to a strategy using
      disease activity scores. Furthermore we will evaluate the clinical efficiency of these two
      strategies.

      Patients with a good or moderate EULAR response to adalimumab will be randomised to
      adalimumab dose reduction strategy using drug concentration or disease activity scores.
      Patients in the 'drug concentration guided' group will reduce adalimumab dose by prolonging
      the dose-interval using TDM algorithm (a new developed algorithm is used to determine the
      interval prolongation for each patient). The dose reduction will start at week 16 if trough
      drug level is higher than 5mg/L, aiming a drug level of 5mg/L in week 16 until 28 and a drug
      level of 2mg/L from week 28 until week 52. In the initial 16 weeks patients are treated with
      adalimumab at registered dose of 40mg every other week.

      Patients in the 'disease activity guided' group will reduce adalimumab dose at week 28 if
      DAS28-CRP is lower than 2.9. This dose reduction will be attained by extending the dosing
      interval to every 3 weeks in weeks 28 until 40 and to every 4 weeks from week 40 until week
      52.

      Patients who successfully prolonged the dose interval to 40 mg every 4 weeks in the 'disease
      activity guided' group and patients who successfully prolonged their dose-interval and
      achieve a serum concentration of 2.0 mg/L in the 'drug concentration guided' group will be
      approached to participate to the extension phase (week 52-80). After informed consent is
      obtained patients will discontinue adalimumab and they will be followed up to week 80.

      Data regarding disease status, functioning, adalimumab serum concentrations, anti-drug
      antibodies and medical costs will be collected during this study.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">December 3, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Rheumatoid arthritis patients treated with adalimumab will be randomly assigned to a dose reduction strategy using disease activity scores or to a dose reduction strategy using serum drug concentrations</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>During every study visit the joints of all patients will be examined for pain and swelling by a blinded nurse or physician. The number of painful and swollen joints will be used to calculate the DAS28 score, the primary outcome of the study</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Medical costs</measure>
    <time_frame>52 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Direct medical costs associated with adalimumab dose reduction using drug concentration versus using disease activity scores</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean time weighted DAS28-CRP</measure>
    <time_frame>at 16, 28, 52 and 80 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Difference in mean time weighted DAS28-CRP</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Direct medical costs</measure>
    <time_frame>at week 28 and week 80</time_frame>
    <description>Direct medical costs (medication, visits, cost TDM testing) at the separate time points</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Indirect medical costs</measure>
    <time_frame>at 28, 52 and 80 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Costs due to RA-related work absenteeism and presentism for patients with paid jobs and days of inactivity for patients without a paid job. Indirect costs will be estimated by three-monthly questionnaires, monitoring these items in the previous month (based on the SF-HLQ).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patients with DAS28-CRP&lt;2.9</measure>
    <time_frame>at 52 and 80 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of patients with DAS28-CRP&lt;2.9</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of flares</measure>
    <time_frame>at 52 and 80 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of dose-interval shortenings</measure>
    <time_frame>at 52 and 80 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Drug levels</measure>
    <time_frame>at 4,16, 28, 40, 52 and 80 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The difference in drug levels between the measured drug level and the predicted drug level with the (newly developed) algorithm at different timepoints</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">267</enrollment>
  <condition>Rheumatoid Arthritis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Concentration guided dose reducion</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Dose reduction of adalimumab will be based on adalimumab through concentration after 16 weeks of treatment with adalimumab.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Disease activity quided dose reduction</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Dose reduction of adalimumab will be based on disease activity after 28 weeks of treatment with adalimumab</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Adalimumab serum trough concentration</intervention_name>
    <description>Dose reduction based on adalimumab serum trough concentration</description>
    <arm_group_label>Concentration guided dose reducion</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Disease activity</intervention_name>
    <description>Dose reduction based on adalimumab diseas activity</description>
    <arm_group_label>Disease activity quided dose reduction</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Adalimumab</intervention_name>
    <description>Adalimumab</description>
    <arm_group_label>Concentration guided dose reducion</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Disease activity quided dose reduction</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Rheumatoid arthritis patient, according to ACR 1987 or ACR/EULAR 2010 criteria;

          -  Starting adalimumab as the first biological therapy

          -  Who has agreed to participate (written informed consent);

          -  Age 18 years or older.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Scheduled surgery during the follow-up of the study or other pre-planned reasons for
             treatment discontinuation;

          -  Life expectancy shorter than follow-up period of the study;

          -  Other disease that might flare if adalimumab is tapered like psoriasis, inflammatory
             bowel disease.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Gertjan Wolbink, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Reade Rheumatology Research Institute</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Sadaf Atiqi, MD</last_name>
    <phone>0031-202421641</phone>
    <email>s.atiqi@reade.nl</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Femke Hooijberg</last_name>
    <phone>0031202421633</phone>
    <email>f.hooijberg@reade.nl</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Reade Rheumatology Research Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Amsterdam</city>
        <state>Noord Holland</state>
        <zip>1056AB</zip>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sadaf Atiqi, MD</last_name>
      <phone>0031-202421641</phone>
      <email>s.atiqi@reade.nl</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Femke Hooijberg</last_name>
      <phone>0031-202421633</phone>
      <email>f.hooijberg@reade.nl</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Netherlands</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chen DY, Chen YM, Hsieh TY, Hung WT, Hsieh CW, Chen HH, Tang KT, Lan JL. Drug trough levels predict therapeutic responses to dose reduction of adalimumab for rheumatoid arthritis patients during 24 weeks of follow-up. Rheumatology (Oxford). 2016 Jan;55(1):143-8. doi: 10.1093/rheumatology/kev298. Epub 2015 Aug 31.</citation>
    <PMID>26324949</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kievit W, van Herwaarden N, van den Hoogen FH, van Vollenhoven RF, Bijlsma JW, van den Bemt BJ, van der Maas A, den Broeder AA. Disease activity-guided dose optimisation of adalimumab and etanercept is a cost-effective strategy compared with non-tapering tight control rheumatoid arthritis care: analyses of the DRESS study. Ann Rheum Dis. 2016 Nov;75(11):1939-1944. doi: 10.1136/annrheumdis-2015-208317. Epub 2016 Jan 13.</citation>
    <PMID>26764260</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>l'Ami MJ, Krieckaert CL, Nurmohamed MT, van Vollenhoven RF, Rispens T, Boers M, Wolbink GJ. Successful reduction of overexposure in patients with rheumatoid arthritis with high serum adalimumab concentrations: an open-label, non-inferiority, randomised clinical trial. Ann Rheum Dis. 2018 Apr;77(4):484-487. doi: 10.1136/annrheumdis-2017-211781. Epub 2017 Sep 22.</citation>
    <PMID>28939629</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pouw MF, Krieckaert CL, Nurmohamed MT, van der Kleij D, Aarden L, Rispens T, Wolbink G. Key findings towards optimising adalimumab treatment: the concentration-effect curve. Ann Rheum Dis. 2015 Mar;74(3):513-8. doi: 10.1136/annrheumdis-2013-204172. Epub 2013 Dec 10.</citation>
    <PMID>24326008</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>December 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>December 3, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 10, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">December 11, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 10, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 10, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">December 11, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Adalimumab</keyword>
  <keyword>Rheumatoid arthritis</keyword>
  <keyword>Therapeutic Drug Monitoring</keyword>
  <keyword>Drug level</keyword>
  <keyword>Dose reduction</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Arthritis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Arthritis, Rheumatoid</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Adalimumab</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>To avoid duplication of research, the gathered data will be shared once all desirable data analysis have been performed and the results are published</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Statistical Analysis Plan (SAP)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>Six months after the study is published the data will be shared</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>Researchers with demonstrable interest in autoimmunity, biologicals, or TDM can contact the investigators of the trial if they are interested in gaining access to the data. Depending on their research objectives the data will be shared</ipd_access_criteria>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

