<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04190108</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HPrato-2</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04190108</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Frequency of Elevated Fecal Calprotectin Levels in Psoriatic Arthritis.</brief_title>
  <official_title>Frequency of Elevated Fecal Calprotectin Levels in Psoriatic Arthritis and Its Predictive Role for Inflammatory Bowel Disease Occurrence: a Prospective, Long-term, Controlled Study.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Hospital of Prato</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Giulia Franchi,Department of Rheumatology, Hospital of Prato</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Maurizio Benucci,S.Giovanni di Dio Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Raffaele Scarpa, Rheumatology Unit, University of Naples Federico II, Naples</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Francesco Caso, Rheumatology Unit, University of Naples Federico II, Naples</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Rosario Foti,Rheumatology Unit, A.O.U. Policlinico Vittorio Emanuele, Catania</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Antonio Carletto,Rheumatology Unit, AOUI, Verona.</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Elisa Visalli,Rheumatology Unit, A.O.U. Policlinico Vittorio Emanuele, Catania</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Laura Niccoli,Department of Rheumatology, Hospital of Prato</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Hospital of Prato</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background.Recent epidemiologic studies have shown an association between psoriasis,
      psoriatic arthritis (PsA) and inflammatory bowel diseases (IBD). Recently, measurement of
      fecal calprotectin (FC) demonstrated a good sensitivity and specificity for intestinal
      inflammation.

      Primary objective of present study was to evaluate the presence of occult bowel inflammation
      in patients with PsA as expressed by elevated levels of FC. Secondary objectives were to
      investigate the correlation between the levels FC and clinical and laboratory features, and
      the outcome of CF-positive patients in terms of IBD development.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      A number of studies evaluated the presence of occult intestinal inflammation by using FC
      assay in patients with axial SpA. In 2000, a study conducted in PsA patients without bowel
      symptoms showed at mucosa biopsies the presence of microscopic changes, increase in lamina
      propria cellularity, consisting of plasma cells and lymphocytes, and lymphoid
      aggregates.Present prospective case-control study was designed to investigate occult
      intestinal inflammation by using FC assay in consecutive patients with PsA at onset, and who
      had no abdominal symptoms. Five Italian Centers contributed to patients recruitment adopting
      the same inclusion and exclusion criteria over a 3 year period.

      FC levels were measured at baseline with Bühlmann fCAL Turbo, Switzerland® kit. This
      automated method is a particle enhanced turbidimetric immunoassay employing polyclonal
      antibodies. The manufacturer cut-off for FC positivity was 50 μg/g, with a sensitivity of
      100% and a specificity of 53.1%.

      The number of patients developing IBD was evaluated at the end of follow-up. Clinical and
      laboratory data collection was centralized and two experts statisticians performed the data
      analysis.

      Statistical analysis. All demographic, clinical, and laboratory data were collected and
      descriptive statistics, presented as mean value and standard deviation, were calculated using
      Microsoft ® Office Excel for Windows and ©2019 Minitabs, LLC for Windows. Chi-square test was
      used for categorical variables. FC test sensitivity, specificity, positive (PPV) and negative
      (NPV) predictive values were calculated. Bayes's theorem was used to calculate the 95%
      confidence interval (95%CI). Correlations were calculated using Spearman's correlation (rs).
      P values ≤ 0.05 were accepted as statistically significant.

      The median follow-up was 30 months.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 2, 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">October 31, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 31, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Control</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The percentage of elevated FC levels in cases and controls</measure>
    <time_frame>3 YEARS</time_frame>
    <description>Comparison of FC levels between cases and controls</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Correlations of FC levels with laboratory data</measure>
    <time_frame>3 YEARS</time_frame>
    <description>Spearman's correlation (rs)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The percentage of patients developing IBD over the follow up</measure>
    <time_frame>3 YEARS</time_frame>
    <description>The occurrence of IBD over the follow up</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">259</enrollment>
  <condition>Psoriatic Arthritis</condition>
  <condition>Inflammatory Bowel Diseases</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Case patients</arm_group_label>
    <description>All consecutive, new patients older than 18 years with PsA (CASPAR criteria) at onset observed over 3-year period, who had any abdominal symptoms.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Controls</arm_group_label>
    <description>All consecutive new patients meeting the ACR/EULAR 2010 classification criteria for rheumatoid arthritis (RA) at onset.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Fecal calprotectin assay</intervention_name>
    <description>FC levels were measured at baseline with Bühlmann fCAL Turbo, Switzerland® kit.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Case patients</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Controls</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Both cases and controls were abdominal symptom-free.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  age &gt;18 years

          -  absence of any abdominal symptoms or diarrhoea

          -  non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drug (NSAIDs) interruption 10 days before enrollment

          -  Corticosteroids (CS) at stable low dose (prednisone 10 mg/day or equivalent) during
             the preceding 2 weeks were permitted in both groups.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  age &lt; 18 years

          -  previous diagnosis of CD or UC or current diagnosis of infectious colitis

          -  previous therapy with traditional DMARDs or any biologic therapies

          -  CS at high doses.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Fabrizio Cantini</name>
      <address>
        <city>Prato</city>
        <state>Tuscany</state>
        <zip>59100</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Italy</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fu Y, Lee CH, Chi CC. Association of Psoriasis With Inflammatory Bowel Disease: A Systematic Review and Meta-analysis. JAMA Dermatol. 2018 Dec 1;154(12):1417-1423. doi: 10.1001/jamadermatol.2018.3631.</citation>
    <PMID>30422277</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Scher JU, Ubeda C, Artacho A, Attur M, Isaac S, Reddy SM, Marmon S, Neimann A, Brusca S, Patel T, Manasson J, Pamer EG, Littman DR, Abramson SB. Decreased bacterial diversity characterizes the altered gut microbiota in patients with psoriatic arthritis, resembling dysbiosis in inflammatory bowel disease. Arthritis Rheumatol. 2015 Jan;67(1):128-39. doi: 10.1002/art.38892.</citation>
    <PMID>25319745</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Klingberg E, Strid H, Ståhl A, Deminger A, Carlsten H, Öhman L, Forsblad-d'Elia H. A longitudinal study of fecal calprotectin and the development of inflammatory bowel disease in ankylosing spondylitis. Arthritis Res Ther. 2017 Feb 2;19(1):21. doi: 10.1186/s13075-017-1223-2.</citation>
    <PMID>28148281</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Adarsh MB, Dogra S, Vaiphei K, Vaishnavi C, Sinha SK, Sharma A. Evaluation of subclinical gut inflammation using faecal calprotectin levels and colonic mucosal biopsy in patients with psoriasis and psoriatic arthritis. Br J Dermatol. 2019 Aug;181(2):401-402. doi: 10.1111/bjd.17745. Epub 2019 May 6.</citation>
    <PMID>30729502</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Scarpa R, Manguso F, D'Arienzo A, D'Armiento FP, Astarita C, Mazzacca G, Ayala F. Microscopic inflammatory changes in colon of patients with both active psoriasis and psoriatic arthritis without bowel symptoms. J Rheumatol. 2000 May;27(5):1241-6.</citation>
    <PMID>10813294</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>December 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 26, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 6, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">December 9, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 9, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 9, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">December 11, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Hospital of Prato</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Fabrizio Cantini</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>MD</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Arthritis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Arthritis, Psoriatic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Intestinal Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Inflammatory Bowel Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

