<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04190225</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>182070</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>R01NR017876</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04190225</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Physical Activity Intervention for Adolescent Girls</brief_title>
  <official_title>Individually Tailored Physical Activity Intervention for Latina Adolescents: Chicas Fuertes</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of California, San Diego</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Nursing Research (NINR)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Brown University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of California, San Diego</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will conduct a randomized trial to evaluate the efficacy of a theory-based,
      individually tailored, multi-technology intervention on increasing physical activity in
      Latina adolescents, compared to a control group receiving only a physical activity tracker (a
      Fitbit). The investigators will recruit adolescent (age 13-17) Latinas (N=200) who are
      currently underactive to participate in the 12-month trial. Those randomized to the
      Intervention arm will receive a one-on-one counseling session and access to an individually
      tailored multi-media website. Key intervention components will be reinforced through text
      messaging to aid goal setting, a physical activity tracker (Fitbit) to set goals, track and
      log activity, and access to a study Instagram account to reinforce exposure to web content.
      The primary outcome will be increases in moderate-to-vigorous activity between baseline and 6
      months. Secondary outcomes will include changes in activity at 12 months, potential mediators
      of the intervention, costs of delivering the intervention, behavior change trajectories from
      continuous data from Fitbits, potential moderators, and changes in physiological and
      psychological variables.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Latina adolescents report low levels of physical activity, with only 3% meeting national
      physical activity guidelines, and are at high lifetime risk for conditions related to
      inactivity, such as obesity, metabolic syndrome, and diabetes. Interventions grounded in
      sound psychosocial theory and leveraging growing technology use in Latina adolescents are
      needed to reverse patterns of inactivity, establish healthy lifetime habits and reduce
      widening disparities. The research team has developed and tested individually tailored,
      culturally adapted web-based interventions to increase moderate-to-vigorous physical activity
      (MVPA) for Latinos, which significantly increased MVPA in adult Latino men and women. In a
      recent pilot study (R03NR014329), this intervention was adapted based on formative interviews
      to make it appropriate for Latina adolescents and tested it in a single-arm pilot trial
      (N=21). After 12 weeks, retention was high (90.5%) and self-reported MVPA increased from
      24.7(26.11) minutes/week at baseline to 79.4(46.8) at follow up (p&lt;0.001), suggesting good
      potential efficacy. In closeout interviews, girls expressed a preference to increase
      audiovideo components of the website and to incorporate other mobile-health technologies,
      such as texting, smartphone apps, social media, and wearables. Thus, the aim of this study is
      to conduct a randomized controlled trial (N=200) of an individually tailored, theory-based,
      multi-technology intervention to increase MVPA in Latina adolescents. The intervention will
      comprise a counseling session to teach behavior change techniques, an interactive multimedia
      website with individually tailored content based on principles of the Transtheoretical Model
      and Social Cognitive Theory, a wearable tracker and smartphone app to reinforce key behavior
      change techniques, connection with a study Instagram account to reinforce exposure to
      intervention content, and automated text messages guide continued goal setting. Participants
      will be randomly assigned to receive the intervention or only a wearable tracker with
      smartphone app. Activity will be measured at baseline and six-month follow-up using
      well-established MVPA measures (accelerometers and the 7-Day Physical Activity Recall
      Interview). It is hypothesized that those randomized to receive the intervention will show
      significantly greater increases in MVPA at six months than those in the control group. The
      investigators will also evaluate whether changes in MVPA are mediated by changes in targeted
      psychosocial constructs (e.g. self-efficacy, social support) or engagement with technology,
      assess longer-term changes in MVPA at 12 months, and evaluate whether intervention effects
      are moderated by baseline personal and environmental variables (e.g. age, BMI, neighborhood
      environment). Costs to deliver the intervention (e.g. staff time, materials, overhead) will
      be tracked to evaluate costs and cost-effectiveness of both study arms, and the investigators
      will track contact time to assess whether staff contact is related to study outcomes. The
      investigators will also explore trajectories of daily activity in both the intervention and
      control groups using continuous data from wearable trackers. The proposed study will promote
      a critical preventive health behavior, physical activity, in Latina adolescents using
      technologies that are pervasive in this high risk, quickly growing population and highly
      scalable, laying the groundwork for cost-effective, broad reaching interventions with great
      potential for preventing chronic disease and promoting health and wellbeing throughout the
      lifespan.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">July 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 30, 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 31, 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>1:1 treatment: control</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Objective Changes in Physical Activity (Weekly Minutes) from Baseline to 6 Months</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 6 Months (MO)</time_frame>
    <description>The ActiGraph GT3X+ accelerometer will be the primary measure to assess objective changes in physical activity from baseline to 6 months. (waking hours only) to measure movement and intensity of activity</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Self-Report Changes in Physical Activity (Weekly Minutes) from Baseline to 6 Months</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 6 Months (MO)</time_frame>
    <description>The 7-Day Physical Activity Recall (PAR) will also assess self-reported changes in physical activity from baseline to 6 months. The 7-Day PAR is an interviewer administered instrument that uses multiple strategies for increasing accuracy of participant recall regarding many types of activities such as time spent sleeping and moderate, hard, and very hard intensity activities. The 7-Day PAR is used across many studies assessing physical activity and has consistently demonstrated acceptable reliability, internal consistency, and congruent validity with other objective measures of activity levels.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">200</enrollment>
  <condition>Physical Activity</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Multi-technology physical activity intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Digital/social media</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Control group receives a Fitbit but none of the intervention components.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Digital/social media intervention</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will receive individual counseling, access to an individually tailored website, guided goal setting via texts, access to a study Instagram account, and a wearable tracker (Fitbit)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Multi-technology physical activity intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  self identify as Latina

          -  13-17 years old

          -  read, write, speak English

          -  under active (participating in &lt;150 minutes of moderate to vigorous physical activity
             per week)

          -  regular access to the Internet (at least 2 times per week)

          -  regular access to a cell phone that can send and receive text messages

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  inability to safely engage in physical activity, as determined by the Physical
             Activity Readiness Questionnaire

          -  BMI &gt; 45

          -  Plan to move from the area within 12 months
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>13 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>17 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Britta Larsen, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>UCSD</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Emily D Greenstadt, MPH</last_name>
    <phone>858-246-5329</phone>
    <email>edgreenstadt@ucsd.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <verification_date>May 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 20, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 4, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">December 9, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 13, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 13, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 15, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of California, San Diego</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Britta Larsen</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>physical activity</keyword>
  <keyword>adolescents</keyword>
  <keyword>teenagers</keyword>
  <keyword>Latina</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

