<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04197128</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>02_D012_101329</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04197128</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Lateral Ridge Augmentation Around Implants</brief_title>
  <official_title>Comparative Evaluation of Novel Ribose Cross Linked Volumising Collagen Matrix v/s Ribose Cross Linked Resorbable Collagen Membrane and Bone Graft for Lateral Ridge Augmentation Around Implants: A Randomised Controlled Clinical Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Krishnadevaraya College of Dental Sciences &amp; Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Krishnadevaraya College of Dental Sciences &amp; Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The rehabilitation of dentoalveolar defects and tooth loss has seen remarkable advancements
      over time. Extraction of tooth leads to reduction in physiologic dimension of bone and it is
      imperative to evaluate the site before implant placement. To overcome the loss of volume and
      to avoid complications, procedures to restore the resorbed alveolar bones prior to or during
      implant placement are usually performed.

      Lateral bone augmentation procedures with guided bone regeneration (GBR) are well documented
      in the literature with predictable results. It generally involves bone substitute xenograft
      and bioresorbable membrane combined with implant placement in single stage procedure or
      separately in two- stage procedure. As the search for better and improved materials
      continues, a porcine derived ribose cross-linked volumising collagen matrix (VCMX) based on
      GLYMATRIX® technology has been introduced which showed benefits over the conventional
      membranes in terms of simplified procedure, degradation, membrane exposure and healing. The
      collagen scaffold has been reportedly used as a core material for guided bone regeneration,
      when there is sufficient bone to place an implant but a horizontal defect is present in the
      crestal ridge. As part of augmentation VCMX is designed to expand and ossify during healing.
      The advantage of the material is that when placed in one or two layers, it may eliminate the
      use of bone substitute or connective tissue graft thus simplifying the augmentation
      procedure. In addition, adding a bone substitute is a valid option based on indication.

      In the quest of better material and simplified procedures, few authors have performed case
      studies based on application of VCMX for guided bone regeneration around dental implants and
      has shown promising results. However, there are no controlled clinical trials on application
      of VCMX for lateral ridge augmentation. Thus, the present study aims to assess the efficiency
      of VCMX compared to resorbable collagen membrane (RCM) and bone graft (BG) for lateral ridge
      augmentation around implants through a well designed, controlled clinical trial.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Source of data Patient visiting the Outpatient Section of the Department of Periodontology,
      Krishnadevaraya College of Dental Sciences and Hospital for replacement of lost teeth will be
      screened and randomly recruited for the study as per inclusion and exclusion criteria. The
      eligible subjects will be informed of the nature and benefits of the participation of the
      study and a written signed consent will be obtained.

      Method of collection of data Sample Size The study would be a prospective, randomized
      controlled clinical trial. A sample size of 28 subjects with equal number of males and
      females who are eligible as per the inclusion criteria, belonging to 20 - 50 years of age
      group would be considered for the study. Sample size is calculated using online software
      (OpenEpi) Open Source Epidemiologic Statistics for Public Health, Version 3.01. Estimation is
      done considering a similar previous study to acquire 80% power and 5% type 1 error in power
      calculation.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">August 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 20, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 30, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>The subjects are randomly divided into 2 groups i.e., Control and Test group each consisting of equal number of participants who are age and sex matched.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Ridge width</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Ridge width would be measured pre-operatively and post-operatively using Cone beam computed tomography.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Gingival thickness</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Clinical and radiographic assessment would be performed</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient- reported outcome 1</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Post operative pain and discomfort would be measured using Visual analogue scale</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient reported outcome 2</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Number of analgesics consumed would be assessed during post- operative period</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety evaluation 1</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Number of subjects with adverse healing</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety evaluation 2</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Number of subjects who had membrane exposure</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">28</enrollment>
  <condition>Alveolar Bone Resorption</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Resorbable collagen membrane and bone graft</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects will receive bovine derived bone graft and resorbable collagen membrane for augmentation.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Ribose cross-linked collagen matrix</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects will receive ribose cross linked collagen matrix for augmentation</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Resorbable Collagen membrane with bone graft for augmentation</intervention_name>
    <description>Local anaesthesia Lignocaine and Adrenaline 1:80000 Injection (Lignox® 2% A, Indoco remedies Ltd, Mumbai) will be administered and midcrestal incison will be made and full thickness flap would be raised buccally. To obtain tension free adaptation of flap margins, the buccal flap advancement will be done using periosteal releasing incision. Implant osteotomies will be performed with sequential drilling and with standardised drills. All the subjects will receive the same implant system. (Norris medical ltd. Hatasia street, Nesher, Israel) For augmentation of deficient ridge, bovine bone graft will be place with overlying resorbable collagen membrane. Stabilisation would be achieved with internal resorbable horizontal mattress suture.
The tension free flap margins will be adapted around the healing abutment with simple interrupted Vicryl 4.0, 3/8, reverse cutting resorbable sutures (Ethicon, Hamburg, Germany)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Resorbable collagen membrane and bone graft</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Cerabone®</other_name>
    <other_name>Ossix Plus®</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ribose cross linked collagen matrix for augmentation</intervention_name>
    <description>Local anaesthesia Lignocaine and Adrenaline 1:80000 Injection (Lignox® 2% A, Indoco remedies Ltd, Mumbai) will be administered and midcrestal incison will be made and full thickness flap would be raised buccally. To obtain tension free adaptation of flap margins, the buccal flap advancement will be done using periosteal releasing incision.
Implant osteotomies will be performed with sequential drilling and with standardised drills. All the subjects will receive the same implant system. (Norris medical ltd. Hatasia street, Nesher, Israel) For augmentation of deficient ridge, ribose cross linked collagen matrix will be cut and adapted to the buccal wall and ridge around the buccal aspect of healing abutment. Stabilisation would be achieved with internal resorbable horizontal mattress suture.
The tension free flap margins will be adapted around the healing abutment with simple interrupted 4.0, 3/8, reverse cutting resorbable sutures (Ethicon, Hamburg, Germany).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Ribose cross-linked collagen matrix</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Ossix Volumax®</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Cooperative patients willing to participate in the study belonging to 20-50 years of
             age group

          2. Patients indicated for implant placement

          3. Based on SAC classification (Straight forward, Advanced, Complex), if the bone defect
             has at least two walls intact and implant placement is possible within the confines of
             ridge.10 In the present study, subjects belonging to Advanced category i.e., where
             simultaneous guided bone regeneration and implant placement is possible it would be
             considered.

          4. Full mouth plaque score (FMPS) &lt; 20 %, Full mouth bleeding score (FMBS) &lt; 20 %.11

          5. Ability to comply with the study related procedures such as exercising good oral
             hygiene and attending all follow-up examinations.

          6. Ability to fully understand the nature of the proposed surgery and ability to sign the
             informed consent form.

             -

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Smokers

          2. Probing depth &gt;4 mm

          3. General contraindications for dental and/or surgical treatment

          4. History of malignancy, radiotherapy, or chemotherapy for malignancy within the past 5
             yrs

          5. Pregnancy or breast feeding

          6. Previous and concurrent medication affecting mucosal healing in general (e.g.
             steroids, large doses of anti-inflammatory drugs)

          7. History of any allergic diseases -
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>20 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>50 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Prabhuji MLV, MDS</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Krishnadevaraya College of Dental Sciences</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Karthikeyan Bangalore Varadhan, MDS</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Krishnadevaraya College of Dental Sciences</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Ashwin P S, MDS</last_name>
    <phone>8050364485</phone>
    <phone_ext>91</phone_ext>
    <email>psbhatashwin@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Prabhuji MLV, MDS</last_name>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Krishnadevaraya College of Dental Sciences and Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bengaluru</city>
        <state>Karnataka</state>
        <zip>562157</zip>
        <country>India</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ashwin P S, MDS</last_name>
      <phone>8050364485</phone>
      <email>psbhatashwin@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>India</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Friedmann A, Gissel K, Soudan M, Kleber BM, Pitaru S, Dietrich T. Randomized controlled trial on lateral augmentation using two collagen membranes: morphometric results on mineralized tissue compound. J Clin Periodontol. 2011 Jul;38(7):677-85. doi: 10.1111/j.1600-051X.2011.01738.x. Epub 2011 May 10.</citation>
    <PMID>21557757</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zubery Y, Nir E, Goldlust A. Ossification of a collagen membrane cross-linked by sugar: a human case series. J Periodontol. 2008 Jun;79(6):1101-7. doi: 10.1902/jop.2008.070421 .</citation>
    <PMID>18533790</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Smidt A, Gutmacher Z, Sharon E. A nouveau collagen scaffold to simplify lateral augmentation of deficient ridges between natural teeth. Quintessence Int. 2019;50(7):576-582. doi: 10.3290/j.qi.a42652.</citation>
    <PMID>31161157</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>December 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>December 9, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 11, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">December 12, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 31, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 31, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 3, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Krishnadevaraya College of Dental Sciences &amp; Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Dr Prabhuji MLV</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor and Head of the Department</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Lateral augmentation</keyword>
  <keyword>Ribose cross-linked collagen</keyword>
  <keyword>Dental Implant</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Bone Resorption</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

