<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04195503</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>19-5581</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04195503</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Liver Transplant for Stable, Advanced Intrahepatic Cholangiocarcinoma</brief_title>
  <official_title>Liver Transplantation in Locally- Advanced, Unresectable, Non-Metastatic Intrahepatic Cholangiocarcinoma Treated With Neoadjuvant Systemic Therapy: A Single-centre, Pilot Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University Health Network, Toronto</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University Health Network, Toronto</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Diagnosis of intrahepatic cholangiocarcinoma (iCCA) is an increasingly common form of primary
      liver cancer, but patients with this diagnosis are not currently eligible for LT. This study
      proposes to offer LT as an option to patients with advanced, unresectable iCCA who
      demonstrate at least 6 months of disease stability /regression while receiving standard
      chemotherapy. Patients will be referred and screened for study participation if they have
      achieved 6 months of disease stability.

      They will be worked up for transplant and if eligible, will be listed. Disease must remain
      controlled while awaiting transplantation. After transplantation, patients will be followed
      for disease recurrence and overall survival, while receiving standard post-transplantation
      followup.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Patients treated with standard of care chemotherapy for unresectable, biopsy-proven
      intrahepatic cholangiocarcinoma, and who demonstrate stability/regression of disease for a
      minimum of 6 months, may be eligible for study. Following informed consent and screening,
      eligible patients with a potential live liver donor (an interested, ABO-compatible
      individual, without obvious contraindications for donation) will be evaluated for
      transplantation. During this period, patients will continue to receive chemotherapy and
      imaging at the usual intervals. Once a patient completes the pre-transplant assessments and
      is deemed &quot;suitable for transplantation&quot; , the living donor's assessments may begin. If the
      donor is found suitable, a tentative date will be set for the surgeries. Systemic
      chemotherapy will be stopped approximately 4 weeks before the surgery date.

      At that point, the potential recipient will be reimaged (CT scan). Test results, and
      inclusion and exclusion criteria will be reviewed to ensure the participant remains eligible
      to proceed to transplant. If these scans reveal any suspicion of tumor infiltration to
      surrounding tissues, an exploratory laparotomy or endoscopic ultrasound procedure will be
      scheduled to allow for visual examination and sampling of those tissues. Tissue samples, such
      as perihilar fat and/or lymph nodes, will be sent to the pathology department for urgent
      review. If extrahepatic disease is identified, the participant will be excluded from the
      study and the transplant will not be performed. Any excluded participants will continue to be
      followed for the study as &quot;drop outs&quot;.

      Otherwise, the donor and recipient surgeries will be performed in the standard fashion and
      with the preferred technique of the surgeon. The patient and donor will receive standard of
      care post-operative care.

      Participants (recipients) will be monitored closely for evidence of tumor recurrence with
      imaging and blood tests. Results of these tests will be collected until completion of the
      study follow-up period (5-years after LT). In addition to tumor surveillance, liver
      transplant status will be assessed at each study timepoint (including graft loss, rejection,
      liver function tests, and details of immunosuppression). The study will also collect details
      of any biopsies performed, re-hospitalizations and surgical complications
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">January 2, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2026</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>patient survival</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>disease-free survival</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>patient survival</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">10</enrollment>
  <condition>Cholangiocarcinoma, Intrahepatic</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>liver transplantation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Surgical Intervention - Liver transplantation</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Liver Transplantation</intervention_name>
    <description>Surgical removal of liver containing tumor(s) and transplantation of new healthy liver graft</description>
    <arm_group_label>liver transplantation</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Male or female, aged 18 years or older, at time of consent

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) score : 0 or 1 at all times from study entry
             to LT

          -  Able and willing to provide written informed consent.

          -  Women of child-bearing potential must agree to use adequate birth control

          -  Histologically-confirmed diagnosis of iCCa

          -  Disease is deemed unresectable based on tumor location or underlying liver dysfunction

          -  No vascular invasion, extra-hepatic disease, or lymph node involvement detected on
             imaging

          -  Patients must have ≥ 6 months of disease stability or tumor regression on
             gemcitabine-based therapy. For patients who have progressed to second-line therapy,
             disease must also be controlled for ≥ 6 months on that regimen

          -  At least 1 living donor has stepped forward, is blood group compatible and has
             completed a &quot;Health History form&quot; which, upon review by the Living Donor team, is
             deemed acceptable and demonstrates no obvious contraindications to donation.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Previous or concurrent cancer (some exceptions permitted)

          -  Patients who have extrahepatic metastases, lymph node involvement, invasion or
             encasement of major hepatic vascular structures, perforation of the visceral
             peritoneum, invasion of extrahepatic structures, invasion of perihilar fat,
             periductular invasion, concurrent hepatoma or mixed hepatocellular cholangiocarcinoma

          -  Patients having received prior locoregional therapies or radiation to the tumor

          -  Renal dysfunction with an estimated creatinine clearance of less than 50 ml/min

          -  Known history of human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) infection.

          -  Prior history of solid organ or bone marrow transplantation

          -  Substance abuse, medical, psychological or social conditions that may interfere with
             the patient's participation in the study or evaluation of the study results

          -  Any condition that is unstable or which could jeopardize the safety of the patient and
             his/her compliance in the study

          -  Pregnant or breast-feeding patients (unless willing to abstain from breast-feeding)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Gonzalo Sapisochin, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>UHN</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Erin Winter, BSc</last_name>
    <phone>416-340-4800</phone>
    <phone_ext>6093</phone_ext>
    <email>erin.winter@uhn.ca</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Health Network</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toronto</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>M5G 2C4</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lunsford KE, Javle M, Heyne K, Shroff RT, Abdel-Wahab R, Gupta N, Mobley CM, Saharia A, Victor DW, Nguyen DT, Graviss EA, Kaseb AO, McFadden RS, Aloia TA, Conrad C, Li XC, Monsour HP, Gaber AO, Vauthey JN, Ghobrial RM; Methodist–MD Anderson Joint Cholangiocarcinoma Collaborative Committee (MMAJCCC). Liver transplantation for locally advanced intrahepatic cholangiocarcinoma treated with neoadjuvant therapy: a prospective case-series. Lancet Gastroenterol Hepatol. 2018 May;3(5):337-348. doi: 10.1016/S2468-1253(18)30045-1. Epub 2018 Mar 13. Erratum in: Lancet Gastroenterol Hepatol. 2018 Jun;3(6):e3.</citation>
    <PMID>29548617</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>December 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>December 9, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 9, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">December 12, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 9, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 9, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">December 12, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cholangiocarcinoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

