<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03806556</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PRO18100519</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03806556</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Pediatric Trial Using Tranexamic Acid in Thrombocytopenia</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Pediatric Trial Using Tranexamic Acid in Thrombocytopenia</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Triulzi, Darrell, MD</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Pittsburgh</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study evaluates the use of tranexamic acid (TXA) in addition to standard therapy in
      children receiving chemotherapy or blood and/or marrow transplantation to decrease the risk
      of bleeding. Half of participants will receive tranexamic acid and half of participants will
      receive placebo.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to conduct a prospective, randomized, blinded, placebo
      controlled trial to evaluate the safety and feasibility of the addition of antifibrinolytic
      therapy with tranexamic acid to the standard care in patients who are thrombocytopenic due to
      primary bone marrow disorders or chemotherapy, immunotherapy and/or radiation therapy in
      order to prevent bleeding. The results of this study will change practice by providing
      evidence as to whether or not TXA is effective and safe treatment when used as an adjunct to
      platelet transfusion therapy in the thrombocytopenic patient.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Suspended</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Enrollment suspended for COVID-19 related reasons
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date type="Actual">April 22, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>This trial is designed as a prospective, randomized, controlled, blinded (patient, caregiver, physician, assessor) trial with two parallel groups and a primary endpoint of feasibility and safety. Randomization will be performed as block randomization with a 1:1 allocation within blocks of size four.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>The investigational pharmacy will be notified when patients enroll on trial. When participants meet criteria for randomization, this will be completed by the Investigational Pharmacy. The pharmacy will prepare and distribute to floor nursing staff all doses of tranexamic acid (available in IV form as a colorless liquid) or placebo (as an equal volume of normal saline). Labels will not carry identifiers of which study arm the enrolled patient is on.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety and tolerability of tranexamic acid in participants as the number of patients with any adverse events and serious adverse events (SAE) as assessed by CTCAE v4.03</measure>
    <time_frame>From activation of the study drug (maximum 30 days) through 30 days from discontinuation of study drug</time_frame>
    <description>Adverse Events and Serious Adverse Events (SAE) will be collected on subjects throughout their participation in the study and up to 30 days following discontinuation of the study drug, regardless of attribution. Adverse events and serious adverse events will be tabulated by type and grade according to the NCI CTCAE v 4.03.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Feasibility of tranexamic acid as an adjunct to standard therapy: Number of participants eligible and recruited</measure>
    <time_frame>From time of recruitment of the first patient until the last patient is enrolled, up to 18 months in duration</time_frame>
    <description>Number of participants eligible for study enrollment and recruited</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>World Health Organization (WHO) Bleeding Scale Grade 2 or Higher Bleeding</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days after activation of study drug</time_frame>
    <description>Proportion of patients with bleeding of WHO grade 2 or above, after activation of study drug</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of platelet and red blood cell transfusions</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days after activation of study drug</time_frame>
    <description>Number of platelet and red blood cell transfusions per patient during the first 30 days post prescription activation of study drug</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of days alive and without WHO grade 2 bleeding or greater</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days after activation of study drug</time_frame>
    <description>Number of days alive and without WHO grade 2 bleeding or greater during the first 30 days post activation of study drug</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The Occurrence of thromboembolic adverse events and serious adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>From activation of the study drug (maximum 30 days) through 30 days from discontinuation of study drug</time_frame>
    <description>Any venous or arterial thrombosis on standard diagnostic imaging post-randomization</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Bleeding of any Grade</measure>
    <time_frame>From activation of the study drug (maximum 30 days) through 30 days from discontinuation of study drug</time_frame>
    <description>Proportion of patients with bleeding of any grade as assessed by WHO bleeding score, after activation of study drug</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Highest observed grade of bleeding (as measured on WHO bleeding scale) during the study period</measure>
    <time_frame>From activation of the study drug (maximum 30 days) through 30 days from discontinuation of study drug</time_frame>
    <description>Highest grade of bleeding (as measured on WHO bleeding scale) during study period in each enrolled patient</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Pediatric Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Thrombocytopenia</condition>
  <condition>Hemostatic Disorder</condition>
  <condition>Coagulation Defect; Acquired</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Tranexamic Acid</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Doses will be given intravenous (IV). Doses are administered every 8 hours or three times daily (TID) per the discretion of the treating investigator. TXA dose will be 10mg/kg, diluted in normal saline to a total volume of 15 milliliters (mL).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Doses will be given intravenous (IV). Doses are administered every 8 hours or TID per the discretion of the treating investigator. Normal saline will be administered at a total volume of 15mL.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Tranexamic Acid</intervention_name>
    <description>IV medication administered after patient meets inclusion/exclusion criteria</description>
    <arm_group_label>Tranexamic Acid</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>TXA</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Normal saline</intervention_name>
    <description>IV medication administered after patient meets inclusion/exclusion criteria</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>NS</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients must have a confirmed diagnosis of hematologic malignancy or solid tumor
             malignancy

          -  Patients must be undergoing or planned chemotherapy or BMT

          -  Patients will only be eligible to receive study drug or placebo during inpatient
             periods

          -  Patients must be predicted to have thrombocytopenia ≤20,000/microliter (uL) for ≥5
             days

          -  Patient must have a platelet transfusion threshold of ≤30,000/uL

          -  Patients must be &gt;14 days beyond their last dose of Pegylated(PEG)-Asparaginase or &gt;72
             hours beyond their last dose of Erwinia Asparaginase

          -  Patients must be able to comply with treatment and monitoring

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Diagnosis of acute promyelocytic leukemia (APL)

          -  History of Immune Thrombocytopenic Purpura (ITP), Thrombotic Thrombocytopenic Purpura
             (TTP) or Hemolytic Uremic Syndrome (HUS)

          -  Diagnosis of Disseminated Intravascular Coagulopathy (DIC)

          -  History of inherited or acquired bleeding disorder AND/OR inherited or acquired
             prothrombotic disorder

          -  Patient must not have WHO Grade 2 bleeding or greater within 48 hours prior to
             enrollment or study drug activation

          -  Patient must not have received PEG-Asparaginase within the 7 day period prior to
             enrollment. If given within the 8-14 day period prior to enrollment patients are
             eligible if prothrombin time (PT), partial thromboplastin time (PTT), international
             normalized ratio (INR) and fibrinogen are obtained and are within 1.5 times the upper
             limits of normal.

          -  Patient must not be receiving tranexamic acid or other anti-fibrinolytic agent or any
             other agent to promote hemostasis (which includes DDAVP, recombinant Factor VII,
             Prothrombin Complex Concentrate, Estrogen Derivatives and Progestins)

          -  Patient must not be receiving therapy with anticoagulation or antiplatelet therapy
             (which includes heparin infusion, enoxaparin, aspirin. If anticoagulant/antiplatelet
             therapy is discontinued when platelet count is &lt;50,000/uL patient will be eligible for
             enrollment)

          -  Patient must not be receiving platelet growth factors

          -  Current thromboembolic event

          -  History of thromboembolic event &lt;6 months prior to enrollment

          -  Current/prior history of sinusoidal obstruction disease

          -  Visible hematuria

          -  Renal dysfunction (as defined by age-specific creatinine values calculated by Schwartz
             equation) or hemodialysis or anuria (defined as &lt;10 mL urine/hour over 24 hours)

          -  History of seizures

          -  Allergy to tranexamic acid

          -  Pregnancy

          -  Unwilling to accept blood product transfusions
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>2 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>21 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Meghan McCormick, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>UPMC Childrens Hospital of Pittsburgh</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UPMC Childrens Hospital of Pittsburgh</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pittsburgh</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>15224</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 4, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 11, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 16, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 1, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 1, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 2, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Pittsburgh</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Meghan McCormick</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator, Fellow</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>tranexamic acid</keyword>
  <keyword>anti-fibrinolytic agents</keyword>
  <keyword>chemotherapy-induced thrombocytopenia</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hemostatic Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Thrombocytopenia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Blood Coagulation Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Tranexamic Acid</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Anonymized public data set will be available after publication of primary results</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Statistical Analysis Plan (SAP)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Clinical Study Report (CSR)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>Beginning within 1 year and ending 5 years after trial completion</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>Researchers who provide a methodologically sound proposal may request data. Proposals should be directed to meghan.mccormick3@chp.edu. To gain access data requestors will need to sign a data access agreement.</ipd_access_criteria>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

