<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03803098</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NI18035J</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03803098</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluation of the Metrological Reliability of Connected Objects in the Measurement of Medical Physiological Parameters</brief_title>
  <acronym>EVALEXPLO</acronym>
  <official_title>Evaluation of the Metrological Reliability of Connected Objects Available to the Public in the Measurement of Medical Physiological Parameters</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Assistance Publique - Hôpitaux de Paris</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Assistance Publique - Hôpitaux de Paris</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Many connected objects available over-the-counter to the general public claim to measure
      physical quantities that may have a medical application. Examples include heart rate, oxygen
      saturation, respiratory rate, blood pressure, body composition between body fat, lean mass
      and bone mass, and motion analysis. .

      The continuous collection of these quantities by a cheap and easily accessible device opens
      important medical perspectives in the areas of home monitoring of chronic diseases or
      preventive medicine in general. Nevertheless, the medical decisions that could be made on the
      basis of the information provided by these objects require that the measurement be reliable,
      which is not always the case.

      The evaluation of the accuracy of measurements made by these objects therefore seems to be a
      prerequisite for future use in a medical context. This study therefore proposes to test the
      adequacy between &quot;gold-standard&quot; measurements carried out in consultation in the department
      of functional explorations of the Bichat Claude-Bernard hospital and the measurements of the
      same parameters by connected objects, under the conditions of intended uses by their
      manufacturer.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Primary objective : Evaluate, in patients consulting for polysomnography, respiratory
      functional explorations or osteodensitometry, or as part of a day hospital cardiology. The
      accuracy of the measurement provided by a connected object in relation to the &quot;gold standard&quot;
      measurement made during the visit. The parameters studied will be:

        -  For polysomnography, pulse oxygen saturation (SpO2), heart rate (HR) and respiratory
           rate (RF), sleep quality (efficacy, duration of mild slow sleep, deep slow sleep and REM
           sleep)

        -  For bone densitometry, body composition in lean mass, fat mass and bone mass, weight •
           For respiratory function tests, pulse oxygen saturation (SpO2) and heart rate (HR)

        -  For day hospitalization in cardiology, blood pressure (BP), heart rate (HR) and heart
           rate, existence of rhythm disorders or conduction

      Secondary objectives:

        -  Evaluate the ease of use of the device (evaluated by an ad-hoc questionnaire completed
           by the nursing staff)

        -  Describe the temporal evolution of the recorded parameters (excluding osteodensitometry
           for which the measurement is unique)

        -  For day hospitalization in cardiology, evaluate the diagnostic performance of objects
           tested on the existence of cardiac rhythm disorders (sinus bradycardia, sinus
           tachycardia, atrial fibrillation, presence of extrasystoles) or conduction disorders
           (atrioventricular block). -ventricular, branch block)
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">January 10, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 10, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Other</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Cross-Sectional</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>relative error between the gold-standard measure of the physiological parameter and the corresponding measure with the tested device,</measure>
    <time_frame>the two measures are succesive of the day of the examination</time_frame>
    <description>relative error expressed on a percentage</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>absolute error between the gold-standard measure of the physiological parameter and the corresponding measure with the tested device,</measure>
    <time_frame>the two measures are succesive of the day of the examination</time_frame>
    <description>absolute error expressed on the unit of the reference measurement</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">400</enrollment>
  <condition>Respiratory; Disorder, Functional, Impaired</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>reference measure</intervention_name>
    <description>measure of a physiological parameter performed with the gold standard medical device</description>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>alternative measure</intervention_name>
    <description>measure of a physiological parameter performed with the connected device under evaluation</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        patients referred to the physiology department for at least one examination among :
        polysomnography, bone densitometry, respiratory functino test, day hospital of cardiology.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion criteria :

          -  Patient over 18 years old

          -  Patient sent to the functional exploration department of Bichat hospital to perform
             one of the following exams: polysomnography, bone densitometry, respiratory function
             tests, cardiology day hospital assessment

          -  Patient agreement to participate in the study,

          -  Affiliated to a social security scheme (benefiting or entitled)

        Exclusion criteria :

        No defined
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Justine FRIJA MASSON, Doctor</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Assistance Publique - Hôpitaux de Paris</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Justine FRIJA MASSON, Doctor</last_name>
    <phone>00 33 1 40 25 84 01</phone>
    <email>justine.frija@aphp.fr</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <verification_date>October 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 22, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 10, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 14, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 10, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 10, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 14, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Respiration Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

