<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03809780</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>LENDER</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03809780</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study to Demonstrate Clinical Benefit of Lenalidomide and Dexamethasone</brief_title>
  <acronym>LENDER</acronym>
  <official_title>Multicenter Phase II Study to Demonstrate Clinical Benefit of Lenalidomide and Dexamethasone in Elderly Unfit Patients With Newly Diagnosed Multiple Myeloma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Kosin University Gospel Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Celgene</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Kosin University Gospel Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Recent prospective multicenter phase II study assessed the efficacy and tolerability of lower
      dose lenalidomide (15mg) and dexamethasone (20mg) in frail patients with relapsed or
      refractory MM. The overall response rate was 71% including complete remission of 15%. Median
      progression free survival and overall survival were 8.9 and 30.5 months. In addition, grade
      3-4 toxicities such as neutropenia, and infections were reduced. This study supported that
      lower dose lenalidomide may be optimal stating dose for elderly patients with frailty.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Multiple myeloma (MM) is a malignant plasma cell disorder that occurs mainly in older adults.
      The median age at diagnosis is approximately 70 years, and two-thirds of patients with newly
      diagnosed MM are older than 65years. As life expectancy increases, the population of older
      individuals grows. Consequently, the number of patients with MM, especially elderly patients,
      is expected to increase considerably in the next two decades. Elderly patients may have a
      variety of comorbidities and reduced physical function at diagnosis, and may be intolerable
      to standard chemotherapy.

      Recent prospective multicenter phase II study assessed the efficacy and tolerability of lower
      dose lenalidomide (15mg) and dexamethasone (20mg) in frail patients with relapsed or
      refractory MM[8]. The overall response rate was 71% including complete remission of 15%.
      Median progression free survival and overall survival were 8.9 and 30.5 months. In addition,
      grade 3-4 toxicities such as neutropenia, and infections were reduced. This study supported
      that lower dose lenalidomide may be optimal stating dose for elderly patients with frailty.

      Therefore, investigators thought that the use of lower dose of lenalidomide in the frail
      group is expected to increase the effectiveness as it is used for a long time while reducing
      toxicity.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 11, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 3, 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 1, 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>multiple myeloma</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Survival</measure>
    <time_frame>2year</time_frame>
    <description>Progression Free Survival rates</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">102</enrollment>
  <condition>Multiple Myeloma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Lenalidomide,dexamethasone</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>high dose: lenalidomide 25mg day 1-21 plus dexamethasone 20mg weekly
low dose: lenalidomide 15mg day 1-21 plus dexamethasone 10mg weekly Schedule</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Lenalidomide</intervention_name>
    <description>-high dose: [lenalidomide 25mg day 1-21 plus dexamethasone 20mg weekly] -Low dose: [lenalidomide 15mg day 1-21 plus dexamethasone 10mg weekly]</description>
    <arm_group_label>Lenalidomide,dexamethasone</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Dexamethasone</intervention_name>
    <description>-high dose: [lenalidomide 25mg day 1-21 plus dexamethasone 20mg weekly] -Low dose: [lenalidomide 15mg day 1-21 plus dexamethasone 10mg weekly]</description>
    <arm_group_label>Lenalidomide,dexamethasone</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients ≥ 70 years unfit and ineligible transplantation in patients with newly
             diagnosed MM

          -  Patient is, in the investigator(s) opinion, willing and able to comply with the
             protocol requirements.

          -  Patient has given voluntary written informed consent before performance of any
             study-related procedure not part of normal medical care, with the understanding that
             consent may be withdrawn by the patient at any time without prejudice to their future
             medical care.

          -  Symptomatic MM based on standard CRAB criteria.

          -  Patient has measurable disease, defined as follows: any quantifiable serum monoclonal
             protein value (generally, but not necessarily, ≥ 0.5 g/dL of M-protein) and, where
             applicable, urine light-chain excretion of &gt;200 mg/24 hours. For patients with oligo
             or non-secretory MM, it is required that they have

          -  Measurable plasmacytoma &gt; 2 cm as determined by clinical examination or applicable
             radiographs (i.e. MRI, CT-Scan) or an abnormal free light chain ratio (n.v.:
             0.26-1.65). The investigators anticipate that less than 10% of patients admitted to
             this study will be oligo- or non-secretory MM with free light chains only in order to
             maximize interpretation of benefit results.

          -  The frailty of the patient will be calculated by R-MCI and scoring according to renal
             function, pulmonary function, activity, frailty, age, and cytogenetics, 0-3 points are
             low risk (fit) risk (inadequate) and 7 or higher will be classified as high risk
             (frail). Only inadequate and frail can be included.

          -  Patients must meet the following clinical laboratory criteria with 21 days of starting
             treatment:

          -  Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) ≥ 1,000/mm3 and platelet ≥ 50,000/mm3 (≥ 30,000/mm3 if
             myeloma involvement in the bone marrow is &gt;50%)

          -  Total bilirubin ≤ 1.5 x the upper limit of the normal range (ULN). Alanine
             aminotransferase (ALT) and aspartate aminotransferase (AST) ≤ 5 x ULN.

          -  Calculated creatinine clearance ≥ 30mL/min or creatinine &lt; 3mg/dL

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Pregnant or lactating females.

          -  Male patients not agreeing to use an acceptable method for contraception (i.e., condom
             or abstinence) for the duration of the study.

          -  Females of childbearing potential not agreeing to use two acceptable methods for
             contraception (e.g. a hormonal contraceptive, intrauterine device, diaphragm with
             spermicide, condom with spermicide, or abstinence) for the duration of the study.

          -  Previous treatment with anti-myeloma therapy (does not include radiotherapy,
             bisphosphonates, or a single short course of steroid &lt; to the equivalent of
             dexamethasone 40 mg/day for 4 days).

          -  Any significant medical disease or conditions that, in the investigator's opinion, may
             interfere with protocol adherence or subject's ability to give informed consent or
             could place the subject at unacceptable risk.

          -  Presence of clinical active infectious hepatitis type B or C, classified into
             Child-Pugh class C (see Appendix V) and HIV.

          -  Presence of acute active infection requiring antibiotics or infiltrative pulmonary
             disease.

          -  Contraindication to any of the required drugs or supportive treatments.

          -  prior history of malignancies, other than MM, unless the subject had been free of
             disease for &gt;= 3 years with the following exceptions: Basal cell CA of skin, Squamous
             cell CA of skin, CA in situ of cervix and breast, incidental histologic finding of
             prostate cancer (TNM stage of T1a or T1b)

          -  Known allergy to any of the study medications, their analogues, or excipients in the
             various formulations.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Kosin University Gospel Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Busan</city>
        <state>Western</state>
        <zip>49267</zip>
        <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ho Sup Lee, MI</last_name>
      <phone>82-51-990-6363</phone>
      <email>hs3667@hanmail.net</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>August 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 15, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 17, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 18, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 13, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 13, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">August 14, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Kosin University Gospel Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Ho Sup Lee</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>MD, PhD. associate professor,Division of hematology-Oncology</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Multiple Myeloma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms, Plasma Cell</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Dexamethasone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lenalidomide</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

