<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03808727</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>W81XWH-17-2-0067</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03808727</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Massed Cognitive Processing Therapy for Combat-related PTSD</brief_title>
  <official_title>Massed Cognitive Processing Therapy for Combat-related PTSD</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>VA Boston Healthcare System</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Fort Belvoir Community Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>The University of Texas Health Science Center at San Antonio</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>VA Boston Healthcare System</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to determine if cognitive processing therapy (CPT) delivered in
      a massed format (MCPT) is as effective as standard delivery of CPT. MCPT will be delivered in
      an intensive outpatient setting (12 sessions in 5 days) composed of both group and individual
      sessions. Standard delivery of CPT consists of 12 sessions over 6 weeks and involves only
      individual sessions. Assessment of PTSD and related symptoms will be conducted at
      pre-treatment and 1 month and 4 months following treatment in both conditions. Additionally,
      in order to compare the treatment groups at the same point in actual time, each group will be
      assessed at the one month posttreatment time point for the other condition.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Cognitive Processing Therapy (CPT) is identified as one of the most effective treatments for
      posttraumatic stress disorder (PTSD) in a wide range of trauma populations, with a higher
      effect size than any other evidence-based treatments for PTSD. However, CPT has been shown to
      be somewhat less effective in active duty and veteran populations when compared to civilian
      trauma victims. One reason may be that service members have difficulty committing to a
      six-week course of therapy due to the demanding nature of active duty military operations
      schedules. In addition, limited availability of clinical providers may reduce access to care.
      One way to address these barriers may be to administer CPT in an intensive, 5-day format.
      This format may increase rates of treatment completion and produce faster symptom improvement
      than the standard administration of CPT. This study will test the efficacy of massed CPT
      (MCPT) compared to standard CPT delivery. MCPT will be delivered in an intensive outpatient
      setting (12 sessions in 5 days) composed of both group and individual sessions. Standard
      delivery of CPT consists of 12 sessions over 6 weeks and involves only individual sessions.

      The sample includes 140 active duty service members randomized to receive either MCPT or
      standard CPT. Participants will be assessed 4 times during the course of the study. In order
      to test the equivalence of the treatment conditions, outcomes will be compared at a
      consistent number of weeks posttreatment for each condition (e.g., at baseline, and one month
      and 4 months following the conclusion of the therapy). Additionally, in order to compare the
      treatment groups at the same point in actual time, each group will be assessed at the one
      month posttreatment time point for the other condition. The timing of these assessment
      intervals allows for the comparison groups to be assessed similarly at each important
      juncture of therapy (baseline and post-treatment) and also to be assessed for maintenance of
      treatment gains following a similar passage of time (4 months post-treatment). Those who drop
      out of treatment will be asked to return for the follow-up assessments based on their
      projected end date for inclusion in the intent to treat analyses.

      Aim 1: To evaluate the efficacy of massed CPT in a sample of active duty military in
      reductions of clinician-rated and self-reported PTSD symptoms, as well as secondary outcomes
      including depression, psychosocial functioning, and physical health after treatment
      completion (assessed at one month and 4 months posttreatment for each condition). Rates of
      treatment completion and speed of recovery will also be compared between conditions.

      Aim 2: To examine predictors of symptom reduction in each treatment condition including
      demographic characteristics, military factors, psychosocial variables, and comorbid mental
      health symptoms.

      Aim 3 (Exploratory): To evaluate the tolerability of massed versus standard administration of
      CPT. Important nonspecific factors such as therapeutic alliance, patient preference,
      treatment expectancy, perceived burden, and emotional factors such as anxiety and avoidance
      will be examined with regard to treatment outcome.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 5, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in PTSD symptoms as assessed by the Clinician Administered PTSD Scale (CAPS-5)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, one-month posttreatment, 4 months posttreatment (weeks 0, 5, 10, 17, 22, depending on tx condition)</time_frame>
    <description>The CAPS is a semi-structured interview to assess presence and severity of PTSD symptoms. The total score on the CAPS will be used as the primary outcome measure in this study.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in PTSD symptoms as assessed by the PTSD Check List - DSM-5 (PCL-5)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, one-month posttreatment, 4 months posttreatment (weeks 0, 5, 10, 17, 22, depending on tx condition) and weekly or daily during treatment</time_frame>
    <description>The PCL-5 is a 20-item self-report measure based upon the Diagnostic and Statistical Manual (DSM-5) criteria for PTSD</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in depressive symptoms as measured by the Patient Health Questionnaire-9 (PHQ-9)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, one-month posttreatment, 4 months posttreatment (weeks 0, 5, 10, 17, 22, depending on tx condition) and weekly or daily during treatment</time_frame>
    <description>The PHQ-9 is a widely used and well-validated instrument for measuring the severity of depressive symptoms</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in suicidality as measured by the Depressive Symptom Index - Suicidality Subscale (DSI-SS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, one-month posttreatment, 4 months posttreatment (weeks 0, 5, 10, 17, 22, depending on tx condition) and weekly or daily during treatment</time_frame>
    <description>The DSI-SS is a 4-item self-report measure of suicidal ideation that focuses on ideation, plans, perceived control over ideation, and impulses for suicide.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in functioning as measured by the Well-Being Inventory (WBI)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, one-month posttreatment, 4 months posttreatment (weeks 0, 5, 10, 17, 22, depending on tx condition)</time_frame>
    <description>The WBI provides a multidimensional assessment of status, functioning, and satisfaction in the four key life domains of vocation, finances, health, and social relationships.This study will only include the subscales measuring functioning and satisfaction in the domains of work, health, and social relationships.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in alcohol use as measured by the Alcohol Use Disorders Identification Test (AUDIT)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, one-month posttreatment, 4 months posttreatment (weeks 0, 5, 10, 17, 22, depending on tx condition)</time_frame>
    <description>The AUDIT is a 10-item screening measure, developed by the World Health Organization (WHO), with three subscales (alcohol consumption, drinking behavior, and alcohol-related problems)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in anger as measured by the Dimensions of Anger Reactions-5 (DAR-5)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, one-month posttreatment, 4 months posttreatment (weeks 0, 5, 10, 17, 22, depending on tx condition)</time_frame>
    <description>The DAR-5 63 is a short form version of the original Dimensions of Anger Reactions. 64 It addresses anger frequency, intensity, duration, aggression, and interference with social functioning.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in health functioning as measured by the Veterans Rand 12-Item Health Survey (VR-12)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, one-month posttreatment, 4 months posttreatment (weeks 0, 5, 10, 17, 22, depending on tx condition)</time_frame>
    <description>The Veterans VR-12 was developed from the Veterans VR-36 and adapted from the Short Form -36 (SF-36), and spans the range of health domains from physical to psychological health status.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in somatic symptoms as measured by the Patient Health Questionnaire - 15 (PHQ-15)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, one-month posttreatment, 4 months posttreatment (weeks 0, 5, 10, 17, 22, depending on tx condition)</time_frame>
    <description>The PHQ-15 70 is an abbreviated version of the original PHQ that asks about somatic symptoms and symptom clusters</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in sleep disturbance as measured by the Insomnia Severity Index (ISI)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, one-month posttreatment, 4 months posttreatment (weeks 0, 5, 10, 17, 22, depending on tx condition)</time_frame>
    <description>The ISI is a 7-item self-report measure that assesses perceived severity of insomnia.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">140</enrollment>
  <condition>PTSD, Post Traumatic Stress Disorder</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Massed Cognitive Processing Therapy (MCPT)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Cognitive Processing Therapy is an evidence-based form of Cognitive Behavioral Therapy (CBT) used to treat PTSD. CPT is a 12-session manualized program that focuses on challenging beliefs and assumptions related to the trauma, oneself, and the world. MCPT will be delivered in an intensive outpatient setting (12 sessions in 5 days) composed of both group and individual sessions.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Standard Cognitive Processing Therapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Cognitive Processing Therapy is an evidence-based form of Cognitive Behavioral Therapy (CBT) used to treat PTSD. CPT is a 12-session manualized program that focuses on challenging beliefs and assumptions related to the trauma, oneself, and the world. Standard CPT will be delivered in 12 one-hour sessions over 6 weeks and involves only individual sessions.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cognitive Processing Therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>Cognitive Processing Therapy is an evidence-based form of Cognitive Behavioral Therapy (CBT) used to treat PTSD. CPT is a 12-session manualized program that focuses on challenging beliefs and assumptions related to the trauma, oneself, and the world.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Massed Cognitive Processing Therapy (MCPT)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Standard Cognitive Processing Therapy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Adult male or female (age 18+) active duty military seeking treatment for PTSD

          -  Diagnosis of PTSD determined by a clinician-administered Posttraumatic Stress Scale
             (CAPS-5)

          -  Speak and read English

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Current suicide or homicide risk meriting crisis intervention

          -  Active psychosis

          -  Moderate to severe brain damage (as determined by the inability to comprehend the
             baseline screening questionnaires)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jennifer Wachen, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>VA Boston Healthcare System</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Jennifer S Wachen, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <phone>857-364-5444</phone>
    <email>jennifer.wachen@va.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Kris Morris, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <phone>571-231-1254</phone>
    <email>kristy.l.morris8.civ@mail.mil</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Fort Belvoir Community Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Fort Belvoir</city>
        <state>Virginia</state>
        <zip>22060</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Kris Morris, Ph.D.</last_name>
      <phone>571-231-1254</phone>
      <email>kristy.l.morris8.civ@mail.mil</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Jennifer Weaver, M.D.</last_name>
      <phone>571-231-4623</phone>
      <email>jennifer.j.weaver6.civ@mail.mil</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 16, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 16, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 18, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 18, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 18, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 19, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>VA Boston Healthcare System</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Jennifer Schuster Wachen, Ph.D.</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>cognitive processing therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>CPT</keyword>
  <keyword>PTSD</keyword>
  <keyword>military</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Stress Disorders, Traumatic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Stress Disorders, Post-Traumatic</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

