<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03558243</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PT-18-075</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03558243</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Prevention of Radial Artery Occlusion: Comparison of Three HEmostatiC Methods in Transradial Intervention</brief_title>
  <acronym>PROTHECT</acronym>
  <official_title>Prevention of Radial Artery Occlusion: Comparison of Three HEmostatiC Methods in Transradial Vascular Access for Diagnostic or Therapeutic Coronary Angiography</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Heart Institute, Mexico</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Heart Institute, Mexico</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study evaluates three hemostatic methods for prevention of radial artery occlusion. One
      third of patients will receive patent hemostasis, another third will receive patent
      hemostasis plus ulnar compression and the last third will receive the StatSeal hemostatic
      disc.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The main complication of the transradial access is the occlusion of the radial artery, which
      although clinically silent in most cases, has been associated with critical hand ischemia,
      more importantly it limits the radial approach for future coronary interventions, and limits
      the use of this conduit for coronary revascularization surgery and arteriovenous fistulas.

      Factors that prevent occlusion of the radial artery have been identified, including the use
      of several hemostatic techniques at the conclusion of cardiac catheterization.

      The patent hemostasis defined as a technique that allows permeability of the radial artery
      and at the same time ensures the absence of bleeding was the first hemostatic method that
      showed a decrease in the incidence of radial artery occlusion, it is currently the quality
      standard for hemostasis in transradial access worldwide. Recently, the patent hemostasis plus
      ulnar compression was described, which proved in a randomized clinical trial to be superior
      to conventional patent haemostasis, decreasing the incidence of radial artery occlusion to
      0.8% at 30 days. These hemostatic methods are a subject of current research worldwide. And
      more clinical trials are expected to confirm the superiority of patent hemostasis plus ulnar
      compression.

      The hemostatic discs used at the beginning as an attempt to reduce the times for the
      hemostasis of the radial access and therefore the recovery times in units of high volume have
      attracted attention for their effectiveness and their low incidence of radial artery
      occlusion, there are few reports who place it as a potential strategy to reduce the incidence
      of radial artery occlusion. Its effectiveness should be validated in dedicated trials with an
      adequate sample size.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 1, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 30, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 30, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Randomized clinical trial</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>The investigator who will evaluate the primary end point will be blinded to which hemostatic technique the patient received.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Radial artery occlusion (RAO) according to hemostatic technique at 24 hrs and evaluate change at 30 days</measure>
    <time_frame>24 Hours and 30 days</time_frame>
    <description>2 Items.
RAO at 24 hrs
RAO at 30 days
Measured with Barbeau test.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Vascular Complications</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days</time_frame>
    <description>1. 2 items
Radial arteriovenous fistula
Radial pseudoaneurysm</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hemorrhagic Complications</measure>
    <time_frame>24 hours</time_frame>
    <description>1. 2 items
Thrombolysis In Myocardial Infarction criteria, Non Coronary Artery Bypass Grafting related bleeding
Major bleeding
Minor bleeding
Minimal bleeding
Hematoma formation EASY hematoma scale
Grade 1
Grade II
Grade III
Grade IV
Grade V</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Radial artery occlusion according to heparin dose</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days</time_frame>
    <description>1. 3 items
RAO with &lt; 5000 Ui heparin dose
RAO with 5000-8000 Ui heparin dose
RAO with &gt; 8000 heparin dose</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Radial artery occlusion according to sheath size</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days</time_frame>
    <description>1. 3 items
RAO with 5 Fr Sheath's
RAO with 6 Fr Sheath's
RAO with 7 Fr Sheath´s</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to TR Band removal</measure>
    <time_frame>300 Minutes</time_frame>
    <description>1. 1 Item
- Averaged time until TR band removal</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Radial artery occlusion according to type of procedure</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days</time_frame>
    <description>1. 2 items
RAO in diagnostic procedures
RAO in therapeutic procedures</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">1425</enrollment>
  <condition>Occlusion of Artery</condition>
  <condition>Radial Artery Injury</condition>
  <condition>Complication</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Patent Hemostasis Arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The TR Band (Terumo medical) will be placed on the sheath entry site, the air bladder of the TR Band will be filled with 18 mL of air to achieve initial hemostasis. The sheath will be removed, air will be withdrawn slowly until a pulsatile bleeding is observed through the sheath's orifice, once this phenomenon occurs, 2 ml of air will be added to the air bladder and the absence of bleeding will be corroborated, immediately afterwards a pulse oximeter will be placed on the index finger of the patient and transient manual compression of the ipsilateral ulnar artery will be performed, patency of the radial artery will be corroborated by means of oxygen saturation and adequate pulse curve (Barbeau reverse test), if it is not possible to achieve patent hemostasis, it will be retried deflating 1-2 ml of the TR Band every 15 minutes until a positive reverse Barbeau test with absence of bleeding is achieved. TR Band removal will be attempted 2 hours after the procedure.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>ULTRA Arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The TR Band will be placed at the sheath entry site, the ipsilateral ulnar artery will be compressed at the Guyon's canal by placing a cylindrical composite made by wrapping 4 inch x 4 inch gauze around a 1-inch plastic needle cap, and compressing it using a circumferentially applied Hemoband. After occlusive compression of ulnar artery is confirmed by means of plethysmography, patent hemostasis protocol will be used for radial artery hemostasis as described at the patent hemostasis arm. The needle cap and hemoband that compresses the ulnar artery will be removed 1 hour after the procedure. TR Band removal will be attempted 2 hours after the procedure.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Hemostatic Disc Arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The StatSeal hemostatic disc will be placed above sheath entry site, the TR Band will be placed above the disc, according to the manufacturer's specifications the air bladder will be filled with 8 ml of air, the sheath will be then removed, corroborating the absence of bleeding, 20 minutes later 3 ml of air will be removed, 20 minutes after that 5 ml of air will be removed, finally the investigators will try to remove the deflated TR Band 60 minutes after the procedure.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Patent Hemostasis arm</intervention_name>
    <description>Patent hemostasis with TR BAND</description>
    <arm_group_label>Patent Hemostasis Arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ULTRA arm</intervention_name>
    <description>Patent hemostasis protocol plus ipsilateral ulnar compression</description>
    <arm_group_label>ULTRA Arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Hemostatic disc arm</intervention_name>
    <description>StatSeal disc plus TR Band</description>
    <arm_group_label>Hemostatic Disc Arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients over 18 years of age, both genders, in whom successful transradial access is
             obtained for elective and urgent diagnostic or therapeutic coronary procedures.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients over 18 years of age, both genders, in whom successful transradial access is
             not achieved and crossover is performed to femoral access.

          -  Patients over 18 years of age, both genders, who do not give their informed consent to
             participate in the study.

          -  Patients over 18 years, both genders, with cardiogenic shock.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Guering Eid-Lidt, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>National Heart Institute, Mexico</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Marco A Peña, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>National Heart Institute, Mexico</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Jesus E Reyes, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+525555732911</phone>
    <phone_ext>1235</phone_ext>
    <email>jesus1912@hotmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Heart Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Mexico City</city>
        <state>Tlalpan</state>
        <zip>14080</zip>
        <country>Mexico</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jesus E Reyes, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+525555732911</phone>
      <phone_ext>1235</phone_ext>
      <email>jesus1912@hotmail.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Guering Eid-Lidt, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+525555732911</phone>
      <phone_ext>1235</phone_ext>
      <email>guering@yahoo.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Mexico</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 8, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 13, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 15, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 18, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 18, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 19, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>National Heart Institute, Mexico</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Jesus Reyes</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Interventional Cardiology Fellow</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>radial artery occlusion</keyword>
  <keyword>prevention</keyword>
  <keyword>patent hemostasis</keyword>
  <keyword>transradial intervention</keyword>
  <keyword>ulnar compression</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Arterial Occlusive Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hemostatics</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>The individual patient data will not be shared with other researchers</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

