<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03554265</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>17-0313</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03554265</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Brain and Gut Plasticity in Mild TBI Following Growth Hormone Therapy</brief_title>
  <official_title>Brain and Gut Plasticity in Mild TBI Following Growth Hormone Therapy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>The University of Texas Medical Branch, Galveston</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>The University of Texas Medical Branch, Galveston</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Patients with a history of mild traumatic brain injury (mTBI) and abnormal growth hormone
      secretion, as measured by glucagon stimulation test, will be treated with replacement growth
      hormone therapy for a period of 6 months. Testing of cognition, exercise, fatigue, brain
      activation and morphology, body composition and measurements of quality of life will be
      performed before and after the treatment period. Fecal sampling for characterization of the
      GI microbiome will occur monthly over the treatment period. Each mTBI subject will be
      required to enroll with an eligible control from their household that will also provide fecal
      samples monthly during the treatment period of their mTBI partner. GI microbiomes will be
      compared between mTBI patients and their household controls at baseline as well as over the
      treatment period.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The investigators will study subjects (aged 18-70 years) with a history of mild TBI (n=25)
      and their household controls (aged 18-70 years) (n=25). mTBI subjects will undergo a 6-month
      intervention of rhGH therapy. Household controls will be asked to participate in
      questionnaires, blood draws (amino acid analysis), and fecal sampling (GI microbiome
      analysis). Household controls will not receive any growth hormone treatment.

      mTBI group

      All patients presenting with a prior mTBI will undergo a phone pre-screen including the Brief
      Fatigue Inventory (BFI) questions 1-3. If they score ≥ 3 on any BFI questions 1-3, and are
      interested in participating in the study, they will be scheduled for a formal consenting and
      medical screening at the UTMB Clinical Research Center (CRC). During the medical screening,
      eligibility will be confirmed and a glucagon stimulation test (GST) will be performed. A
      glucagon stimulation with a growth hormone peak of &lt;10 ng/mL is required to qualify for
      enrollment.

      Household control group

      All household controls will undergo a phone pre-screen and if interested in participating in
      the study, will be scheduled for a formal consenting and medical screening at the UTMB
      Clinical Research Center (CRC).

      Experimental Protocol.

      mTBI Group

      Before and at completion (month 6) of the rhGH intervention, mTBI subjects will report to the
      UTMB Institute for Translational Sciences (ITS) Clinical Research Center (CRC) for testing,
      which will consist of cognitive function assessment (MoCA), determination of brain morphology
      and connectivity using fMRI, determination of lean mass and fat mass using DEXA, resting
      energy expenditure, functional testing including leg strength and 6 minute walk test, fatigue
      measurements, and questionnaires of mood and quality of life, gastrointestinal health, sleep,
      and food preferences. Blood sampling for measurement of amino acid levels, hormones, and
      metabolites will be drawn before and 90 minutes (+/- 10 minutes) after a standardized meal.
      In addition, fecal samples for analysis of the GI microbiome will be collected monthly for
      the duration of the study. Insulin Growth Factor 1 (IGF-1) levels will monitored at a month 1
      safety visit for all mTBI subjects. The month 1 safety visit will occur +/- 5 days from the
      expected date based on the baseline study visit. The monthly fecal sampling will occur +/- 7
      days from the expected date based on the baseline study visit. The month 6 post study will
      occur +/- 7 days from the expected date based on the baseline study visit. A member of the
      study team will contact the subject each month to coordinate fecal sample transport to UTMB,
      check for adverse events and overall well-being, and ensure compliance and ongoing consent.

      Household control group

      Before and at completion (month 6) of the rhGH intervention of their mTBI subject partners,
      household controls will report to the UTMB Institute for Translational Sciences (ITS)
      Clinical Research Center (CRC) for testing, which will consist of questionnaires of food
      preferences and gastrointestinal health and blood sampling for measurement of amino acid
      levels, hormones, and metabolites which will be drawn before and 90 minutes (+/ 10 minutes)
      after a standardized meal. In addition, fecal samples for the analysis of the GI microbiome
      will be collected monthly for the duration of the study, as well as questionnaire assessing
      gastrointestinal health. The monthly fecal sampling will occur +/- 7 days from the expected
      date based on the baseline study visit. The post study (month 6) will occur +/- 7 days from
      the expected date based on the baseline study visit. A member of the study team will contact
      the subject each month to coordinate fecal sample transport to UTMB, check for adverse events
      and overall well-being, and ensure compliance and ongoing consent.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">August 6, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 1, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 1, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>mTBI patients will be in the growth hormone arm Household control subjects will be in the control arm</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Lean Body Mass as Measured by Dual Energy X-Ra Absorptiometry (DEXA) at Baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Lean body mass will be measured in mTBI subjects by GE Lunar iDEXA at baseline.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Lean Body Mass as Measured by Dual Energy X-Ra Absorptiometry (DEXA) at 6 months</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Lean body mass will be measured in mTBI subjects by GE Lunar iDEXA after 6 months of growth hormone treatment.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Fat Mass as Measured by Dual Energy X-Ra Absorptiometry (DEXA) at Baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Fat mass will be measured in mTBI subjects by GE Lunar iDEXA at baseline.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Fat Mass as Measured by Dual Energy X-Ra Absorptiometry (DEXA) at 6 months</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Fat mass will be measured in mTBI subjects by GE Lunar iDEXA after 6 months of growth hormone treatment.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Basal Metabolic rate as measured by Resting Energy Expenditure at baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Resting Energy Expenditure will be measured by capturing the expired breath of mTBI subjects while at rest with a metabolic cart over a 30 minute time period. Data will be reported as kilocalories/day. This will be measured at baseline in mTBI subjects only.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Basal Metabolic rate as measured by Resting Energy Expenditure at 6 months</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Resting Energy Expenditure will be measured by capturing the expired breath of mTBI subjects while at rest with a metabolic cart over a 30 minute time period. Data will be reported as kilocalories/day. This will be measured after 6 months of growth hormone treatment in mTBI subjects only.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Cognitive Function as measured by Montreal Cognitive Assessment at baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline</time_frame>
    <description>The Montreal Cognitive Assessment (MoCA) will be used to assess cognition at baseline in mTBI subjects only.
The Montreal Cognitive Assessment (MoCA) is a rapid assessment of cognition. The MoCA consists of 9 questions with the following subcategories: visuospatial/executive, naming, memory, language, abstraction, delayed recall and orientation. The MoCA has been used extensively to detect cognitive impairment in many conditions, including head trauma. Version 7.1 will be used at the Month 0 testing and Version 7.2 will be used at the Month 6 testing. Scores range from 0 to 30, higher score being a better outcome.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Cognitive Function as measured by Montreal Cognitive Assessment at 6 months</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>The Montreal Cognitive Assessment (MoCA) will be used to assess cognition after 6 months of growth hormone treatment in mTBI subjects only.
The Montreal Cognitive Assessment (MoCA) is a rapid assessment of cognition. The MoCA consists of 9 questions with the following subcategories: visuospatial/executive, naming, memory, language, abstraction, delayed recall and orientation. The MoCA has been used extensively to detect cognitive impairment in many conditions, including head trauma. Version 7.1 will be used at the Month 0 testing and Version 7.2 will be used at the Month 6 testing. Scores range from 0 to 30, higher score being a better outcome.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Global Fatigue Score as Measured by Brief Fatigue Inventory (BFI) at baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline</time_frame>
    <description>The Brief Fatigue Inventory is a 9 item questionnaire that assesses perceptual fatigue as well as fatigue interferences (e.g. interference with enjoyment of life), with &quot;0&quot; being no fatigue and &quot;10&quot; being as bad as you can imagine. The Global Fatigue score is calculated by averaging the answers of all the questions. Brief Fatigue Inventory is measured in mTBI subjects at baseline.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Global Fatigue Score as Measured by Brief Fatigue Inventory (BFI) at 6 months</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>The Brief Fatigue Inventory is a 9 item questionnaire that assesses perceptual fatigue as well as fatigue interferences (e.g. interference with enjoyment of life), with &quot;0&quot; being no fatigue and &quot;10&quot; being as bad as you can imagine. The Global Fatigue score is calculated by averaging the answers of all the questions. Brief Fatigue Inventory is measured in mTBI subjects after 6 months of growth hormone treatment.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Personal Perception of Fatigue as Measured by Multidimensional Fatigue Symptom Inventory - Short Form at Baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Multidimensional Fatigue Symptom Inventory Short Form (MFSI-SF) from the Moffitt Cancer Center, University of South Florida The MFSI-SF is a 30 question assessment designed to assess the principal manifestations of fatigue.
There 5 subscales used to calculate a total score. The subscales are: General Fatigue, Physical Fatigue, Emotional Fatigue, Mental Fatigue, and Vigor (an estimate of the patient's energy level). The total score is calculated with the equation: (general + physical + emotional + mental) - vigor = total score.
The range of the total score is -24 to 96, with the higher the number meaning more fatigue.
The MFSI is measured at baseline.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Personal Perception of Fatigue as Measured by Multidimensional Fatigue Symptom Inventory - Short Form at 6 months</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Multidimensional Fatigue Symptom Inventory Short Form (MFSI-SF) from the Moffitt Cancer Center, University of South Florida The MFSI-SF is a 30 question assessment designed to assess the principal manifestations of fatigue.
There 5 subscales used to calculate a total score. The subscales are: General Fatigue, Physical Fatigue, Emotional Fatigue, Mental Fatigue, and Vigor (an estimate of the patient's energy level). The total score is calculated with the equation: (general + physical + emotional + mental) - vigor = total score.
The range of the total score is -24 to 96, with the higher the number meaning more fatigue.
The MFSI is measured after 6 months of growth hormone treatment.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Gastrointestinal Health as measured by the gastrointestinal symptom rating scale at baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline</time_frame>
    <description>The Gastrointestinal Symptom Rating Scale (GSRS) is a specific 15-item questionnaire. Subjects are asked to numerically score their subjective symptoms on a scale of 1-7 (1 = no discomfort at all; 7 = very severe discomfort) . The sum of the scores for all 15 items is regarded as the GSRS total score. Total scores range from 15 (best outcome) to 105 (worst outcome). GSRS will be measured monthly at baseline mTBI and household control subjects.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Gastrointestinal Health as measured by the gastrointestinal symptom rating scale at 1 month</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month</time_frame>
    <description>The Gastrointestinal Symptom Rating Scale (GSRS) is a specific 15-item questionnaire. Subjects are asked to numerically score their subjective symptoms on a scale of 1-7 (1 = no discomfort at all; 7 = very severe discomfort) . The sum of the scores for all 15 items is regarded as the GSRS total score. Total scores range from 15 (best outcome) to 105 (worst outcome). GSRS will be measured monthly in both mTBI and household control subjects.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Gastrointestinal Health as measured by the gastrointestinal symptom rating scale at 2 months</measure>
    <time_frame>2 months</time_frame>
    <description>The Gastrointestinal Symptom Rating Scale (GSRS) is a specific 15-item questionnaire. Subjects are asked to numerically score their subjective symptoms on a scale of 1-7 (1 = no discomfort at all; 7 = very severe discomfort) . The sum of the scores for all 15 items is regarded as the GSRS total score. Total scores range from 15 (best outcome) to 105 (worst outcome). GSRS will be measured monthly in both mTBI and household control subjects.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Gastrointestinal Health as measured by the gastrointestinal symptom rating scale at 3 months</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>The Gastrointestinal Symptom Rating Scale (GSRS) is a specific 15-item questionnaire. Subjects are asked to numerically score their subjective symptoms on a scale of 1-7 (1 = no discomfort at all; 7 = very severe discomfort) . The sum of the scores for all 15 items is regarded as the GSRS total score. Total scores range from 15 (best outcome) to 105 (worst outcome). GSRS will be measured monthly in both mTBI and household control subjects.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Gastrointestinal Health as measured by the gastrointestinal symptom rating scale at 4 months</measure>
    <time_frame>4 months</time_frame>
    <description>The Gastrointestinal Symptom Rating Scale (GSRS) is a specific 15-item questionnaire. Subjects are asked to numerically score their subjective symptoms on a scale of 1-7 (1 = no discomfort at all; 7 = very severe discomfort) . The sum of the scores for all 15 items is regarded as the GSRS total score. Total scores range from 15 (best outcome) to 105 (worst outcome). GSRS will be measured monthly in both mTBI and household control subjects.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Gastrointestinal Health measured by the gastrointestinal symptom rating scale at 5 months</measure>
    <time_frame>5 months</time_frame>
    <description>The Gastrointestinal Symptom Rating Scale (GSRS) is a specific 15-item questionnaire. Subjects are asked to numerically score their subjective symptoms on a scale of 1-7 (1 = no discomfort at all; 7 = very severe discomfort) . The sum of the scores for all 15 items is regarded as the GSRS total score. Total scores range from 15 (best outcome) to 105 (worst outcome). GSRS will be measured monthly in both mTBI and household control subjects.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Gastrointestinal Health measured by the gastrointestinal symptom rating scale at 6 months</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>The Gastrointestinal Symptom Rating Scale (GSRS) is a specific 15-item questionnaire. Subjects are asked to numerically score their subjective symptoms on a scale of 1-7 (1 = no discomfort at all; 7 = very severe discomfort) . The sum of the scores for all 15 items is regarded as the GSRS total score. Total scores range from 15 (best outcome) to 105 (worst outcome). GSRS will be measured monthly in both mTBI and household control subjects.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Mood Measured by Profile of Mood States at Baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Profile of Mood States (POMS) is a questionnaire by MultiHealth Systems, that measures mood. In this 65 item questionnaire, subjects are asked to rate their feelings toward a statement from 0-4, with 0 being &quot;not at all' and 4 being &quot;extremely&quot;. There are 6 subscales which include, tension-anxiety, depression, anger-hostility, vigor, fatigue, and confusion. To calculate the total mood disturbance, which is what is reported here, the subscales tension-anxiety, depression, anger-hostility, fatigue and confusion are summed and vigor is subtracted. The scale range for total mood disturbance is 200 (worst) to -32 (best). POMS will be measured at baseline in mTBI subjects only.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Mood Measured by Profile of Mood States at 6 months</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Profile of Mood States (POMS) is a questionnaire by MultiHealth Systems, that measures mood. In this 65 item questionnaire, subjects are asked to rate their feelings toward a statement from 0-4, with 0 being &quot;not at all' and 4 being &quot;extremely&quot;. There are 6 subscales which include, tension-anxiety, depression, anger-hostility, vigor, fatigue, and confusion. To calculate the total mood disturbance, which is what is reported here, the subscales tension-anxiety, depression, anger-hostility, fatigue and confusion are summed and vigor is subtracted. The scale range for total mood disturbance is 200 (worst) to -32 (best). POMS will be measured after 6 months of treatment with Growth hormone in mTBI subjects only.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Sleep Quality measured by Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index at baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index (PSQI) is a self-rated questionnaire which assesses sleep quality and disturbances over a 1 month-time interval. Minimum Score = 0 (better); Maximum Score = 21 (worse). Interpretation: Total &lt; 5 associated with good sleep quality. Total &gt; 5 associated with poor sleep quality. PSQI will be measured at baseline in mTBI subjects only.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Sleep Quality measured by Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index at 6 months</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index (PSQI) is a self-rated questionnaire which assesses sleep quality and disturbances over a 1 month-time interval. Minimum Score = 0 (better); Maximum Score = 21 (worse). Interpretation: Total &lt; 5 associated with good sleep quality. Total &gt; 5 associated with poor sleep quality. PSQI will be measured after 6 months of treatment with growth hormone in mTBI subjects only.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Symptoms of Growth Hormone Deficiency measured by the questionnaire Quality of Life - Assessment of Growth Hormone Defiency in Adults at baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Symptoms of growth hormone deficiency will be measured in mTBI subjects using the Quality of Life - Assessment of Growth Hormone Deficiency in Adults (QoL-AGHDA). This 25-item questionnaire measures specific symptoms associated with growth hormone deficiency, with a score range of 0 to 25, with a higher score indicating worse symptoms. The QoL-ADGHA will be measured at baseline in mTBI subjects only.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Symptoms of Growth Hormone Deficiency measured by the questionnaire Quality of Life - Assessment of Growth Hormone Deficiency in Adults at 6 months</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Symptoms of growth hormone deficiency will be measured in mTBI subjects using the Quality of Life - Assessment of Growth Hormone Deficiency in Adults (QoL-AGHDA). This 25-item questionnaire measures specific symptoms associated with growth hormone deficiency, with a score range of 0 to 25, with a higher score indicating worse symptoms. The QoL-ADGHA will be measured after 6 months of growth hormone treatment in mTBI subjects only.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Depression measured by the Beck Depression Inventory-II at baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline</time_frame>
    <description>The Beck Depression Inventory- II assesses depressive symptom severity. The BDI-II is comprised of 21 individual items reflecting specific cognitive, affective, and physical symptoms of depression. Each item includes four statements that vary in the description of symptom of severity. Scores range from 0 to 3, with a score of &quot;3&quot; indicating a severe symptoms and a score of &quot;0&quot; indicating an absence of concern with that particular aspect of depressive symptomology. The total score is the sum of all endorsed statements. The maximum total score is 63. The BDI-II Manual designates the following raw score classifications depression severity: ≤13 = minimal; 14-19 = mild; 20-28 = moderate; ≥ 29 = severe. The BDI will be measured at baseline in mTBI subjects only.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Depression measured by the Beck Depression Inventory-II at 6 months</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>The Beck Depression Inventory- II assesses depressive symptom severity. The BDI-II is comprised of 21 individual items reflecting specific cognitive, affective, and physical symptoms of depression. Each item includes four statements that vary in the description of symptom of severity. Scores range from 0 to 3, with a score of &quot;3&quot; indicating a severe symptoms and a score of &quot;0&quot; indicating an absence of concern with that particular aspect of depressive symptomology. The total score is the sum of all endorsed statements. The maximum total score is 63. The BDI-II Manual designates the following raw score classifications depression severity: ≤13 = minimal; 14-19 = mild; 20-28 = moderate; ≥ 29 = severe. The BDI will be measured after 6 months of growth hormone treatment in mTBI subjects only.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum Peak Isometric Leg Strength as Measured by Biodex Pro4 at Baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Peak isometric strength is measured on a Biodex System 4 Pro. This test is isolated to the quadricep muscle of one leg. Isometric test is performed at 90 degrees with 15 seconds of force production for each contraction and 15 seconds of rest. 1 set of 3 contractions at 100% force performed. Isometric strength will be measured at baseline.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum Peak Isometric Leg Strength as Measured by Biodex Pro4 at 6 months</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Peak isometric strength is measured on a Biodex System 4 Pro. This test is isolated to the quadricep muscle of one leg. Isometric test is performed at 90 degrees with 15 seconds of force production for each contraction and 15 seconds of rest. 1 set of 3 contractions at 100% force performed. Isometric strength will be measured after 6 months of growth hormone treatment.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum Peak Isokinetic Leg Strength as Measured by Biodex Pro4 at baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Isokinetic strength (knee extension) is measured on a Biodex System Pro 4 within a 75 degree range of motion. Subjects performed concentric contractions at a fixed speed of 120 degree/sec. 1 set of 3 contractions were performed at 100% force. Isokinetic strength will be measured at baseline.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum Peak Isokinetic Leg Strength as Measured by Biodex Pro4 at 6 months</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Isokinetic strength (knee extension) is measured on a Biodex System Pro 4 within a 75 degree range of motion. Subjects performed concentric contractions at a fixed speed of 120 degree/sec. 1 set of 3 contractions were performed at 100% force. Isokinetic strength will be measured after 6 months of growth hormone treatment.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Walking Distance at 25% Perceptual Effort as measured by walking test at baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Walking performance will be assessed in mTBI patients during 6 minutes of walking in long corridor hallways. This is a standard test of walking performance that has been validated in similar studies. Here, the test will be slightly modified, with subjects asked to walk at a 25% perceived effort from minute 0 - 2, at a 50% perceived effort from minute 2 - 4, and at a 100% effort (as quickly as they can safely walk without running) from minute 4 -6. Distance traveled for each 2-minute category will be recorded. The 6-minute walking test will be completed at baseline.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Walking Distance at 25% Perceptual Effort as measured by walking test at 6 months</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Walking performance will be assessed in mTBI patients during 6 minutes of walking in long corridor hallways. This is a standard test of walking performance that has been validated in similar studies. Here, the test will be slightly modified, with subjects asked to walk at a 25% perceived effort from minute 0 - 2, at a 50% perceived effort from minute 2 - 4, and at a 100% effort (as quickly as they can safely walk without running) from minute 4 -6. Distance traveled for each 2-minute category will be recorded. The 6-minute walking test will be completed at month 6.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Walking Distance at 50% Perceptual Effort as measured by walking test at baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Walking performance will be assessed in mTBI patients during 6 minutes of walking in long corridor hallways. This is a standard test of walking performance that has been validated in similar studies. Here, the test will be slightly modified, with subjects asked to walk at a 25% perceived effort from minute 0 - 2, at a 50% perceived effort from minute 2 - 4, and at a 100% effort (as quickly as they can safely walk without running) from minute 4 -6. Distance traveled for each 2-minute category will be recorded. The 6-minute walking test will be completed at baseline.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Walking Distance at 50% Perceptual Effort as measured by walking test at 6 months</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Walking performance will be assessed in mTBI patients during 6 minutes of walking in long corridor hallways. This is a standard test of walking performance that has been validated in similar studies. Here, the test will be slightly modified, with subjects asked to walk at a 25% perceived effort from minute 0 - 2, at a 50% perceived effort from minute 2 - 4, and at a 100% effort (as quickly as they can safely walk without running) from minute 4 -6. Distance traveled for each 2-minute category will be recorded. The 6-minute walking test will be completed at month 6.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Walking Distance at 100% Effort as measured by walking test at baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Walking performance will be assessed in mTBI patients during 6 minutes of walking in long corridor hallways. This is a standard test of walking performance that has been validated in similar studies. Here, the test will be slightly modified, with subjects asked to walk at a 25% perceived effort from minute 0 - 2, at a 50% perceived effort from minute 2 - 4, and at a 100% effort (as quickly as they can safely walk without running) from minute 4 -6. Distance traveled for each 2-minute category will be recorded. The 6-minute walking test will be completed at baseline.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Walking Distance at 100% Effort as measured by walking test at 6 months</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Walking performance will be assessed in mTBI patients during 6 minutes of walking in long corridor hallways. This is a standard test of walking performance that has been validated in similar studies. Here, the test will be slightly modified, with subjects asked to walk at a 25% perceived effort from minute 0 - 2, at a 50% perceived effort from minute 2 - 4, and at a 100% effort (as quickly as they can safely walk without running) from minute 4 -6. Distance traveled for each 2-minute category will be recorded. The 6-minute walking test will be completed at month 6.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Traumatic Brain Injury</condition>
  <condition>Fatigue</condition>
  <condition>Cognitive Impairment</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>mTBI subjects</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>mTBI subjects will receive recombinant human growth hormone replacement therapy daily for 6 months.
Drug: recombinant human growth hormone (rhgH); somatropin, Genotropin
Dose: month 0 - month 1 will be dosed at 0.4 mg / day month 1 - month 6 will be dosed at 0.6 mg / day</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Household Control Subjects</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>household control subjects will not receive any intervention.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Somatropin</intervention_name>
    <description>Genotropin given by injection</description>
    <arm_group_label>mTBI subjects</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Genotropin</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        mTBI Inclusion criteria

          1. Male or female with a diagnosis of mild TBI.

          2. At least 6-month post-injury.

          3. Ages 18 to 70 years.

          4. Lives in same household as paired control that meets inclusion/exclusion criteria.

          5. Participant is willing and able to give informed consent for participation in the
             study.

        mTBI Exclusion criteria

          1. Unable to walk unassisted.

          2. Significant heart, liver, kidney, blood or respiratory disease.

          3. History of chest pain or coronary heart disease.

          4. Uncontrolled Diabetes mellitus.

          5. Any history of a recently (12 months) diagnosed cancer other than a skin cancer
             (excluding melanoma).

          6. Recent (within 6 months) treatment with anabolic steroids or corticosteroids.

          7. Current alcohol or drug abuse.

          8. Premorbid history of psychiatric disorder.

          9. Premorbid history of head trauma.

         10. Pregnancy or become pregnant during the trial.

         11. Coumadin because of the risk of bleeding with daily injections of rhGH.

         12. Subjects who are deficient in cortisol or thyroid at screening will be excluded until
             hormone abnormalities have been corrected.

         13. Subjects with chronic pain who are being managed with narcotics will be excluded as
             the effects of central nervous system depressants may interfere with study test
             results.

         14. Subjects with a history of inflammatory bowel disease, Celiac disease or active
             diverticular disease.

         15. Subjects with a history of oral or IV antibiotics within the past 3 months.

        Household Control Inclusion criteria

          1. Ages 18 to 70 years.

          2. Lives in same household as paired mTBI subject that meets inclusion/exclusion
             criteria.

          3. Participant is willing and able to give informed consent for participation in the
             study.

        Household Control Exclusion criteria

          1. Significant heart, liver, kidney, blood or respiratory disease.

          2. Uncontrolled Diabetes mellitus.

          3. Any history of a recently (12 months) diagnosed cancer other than a skin cancer
             (excluding melanoma).

          4. Recent (within 6 months) treatment with anabolic steroids or corticosteroids.

          5. Current alcohol or drug abuse.

          6. Premorbid history of psychiatric disorder.

          7. Premorbid history of head trauma.

          8. Pregnancy or become pregnant during the trial.

          9. Subjects who are deficient in thyroid at screening will be excluded until thyroid
             hormone is replaced.

         10. Subjects with a history of inflammatory bowel disease, Celiac disease or active
             diverticular disease.

         11. Subjects with a history of oral or IV antibiotics within the past 3 months.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Randall J Urban, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Texas</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Kate M Randolph, BS</last_name>
    <phone>409-772-8126</phone>
    <email>kmrandol@utmb.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Christopher P Danesi, MS</last_name>
    <phone>409-772-8126</phone>
    <email>cpdanesi@utmb.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Texas Medical Branch</name>
      <address>
        <city>Galveston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77555</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Kate M Randolph, BS</last_name>
      <phone>409-772-8126</phone>
      <email>kmrandol@utmb.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Christopher P Danesi, MS</last_name>
      <phone>409-772-8126</phone>
      <email>cpdanesi@utmb.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Randall J Urban, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Edgar L Dillon, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>April 9, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 30, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 13, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 24, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 24, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">July 28, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>growth hormone</keyword>
  <keyword>Traumatic Brain injury</keyword>
  <keyword>concussion</keyword>
  <keyword>mTBI</keyword>
  <keyword>fatigue</keyword>
  <keyword>cognitive impairment</keyword>
  <keyword>BIAFAC</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Brain Injuries</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Brain Injuries, Traumatic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fatigue</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cognitive Dysfunction</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

