<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03554278</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>STU 092017-028</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03554278</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Alteration of Stool Microbiota in Preterm Infants With Anemia</brief_title>
  <official_title>Alteration of Stool Microbiota in Preterm Infants Less Than 32 Weeks With Anemia, and Following Blood Transfusion</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Texas Southwestern Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Texas Southwestern Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study evaluates the relationship between anemia and stool microbiota in premature
      infants. It also evaluates the relationship between blood transfusion and stool microbiota.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Necrotizing enterocolitis (NEC) is a leading cause of death in preterm infants, yet the
      disease mechanism is not well understood. Among the factors that have been studied are the
      change in stool microbiota (dysbiosis), severe anemia, and transfusion. Studies suggest that
      dysbiosis occurs in neonates with NEC. Large studies and meta-analyses have shown a
      predominance of Gammaproteobacteria, a decrease in Firmicutes, and decreased bacterial
      diversity in stool from infants with NEC. Studies do not support a relationship between
      transfusions and NEC since there are conflicting findings on this topic. There is a
      suggestion, however, that severe anemia may be associated with NEC though this requires
      further study.

      No studies have been done evaluating the relationship between anemia and change in stool
      microbiota, or blood transfusion and change in stool microbiota. This study aims to primarily
      evaluate the relationship between anemia and stool microbiota, and secondarily evaluate the
      relationship between transfusion and stool microbiota.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Suspended</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Covid-19
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 9, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 30, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 30, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>qRT-PCR (polymerase chain reaction) quantitative stool analysis</measure>
    <time_frame>qRT-PCR will be analyzed for infant stool samples from enrollment until infants are 38 weeks corrected, or until they are discharged from the hospital. This time frame will be an average of 10 weeks per infant.</time_frame>
    <description>Quantify major bacterial groups, including Proteobacteria, Firmicutes, and Bacteroides in stool samples</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Alpha diversity</measure>
    <time_frame>Infant stool samples will be analyzed from enrollment until infants are 38 weeks corrected, or until they are discharged from the hospital. This time frame will be an average of 10 weeks per infant.</time_frame>
    <description>Use next generation sequencing to assess changes in alpha diversity of bacteria between non-anemic and anemic stool samples</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">70</enrollment>
  <condition>Anemia, Neonatal</condition>
  <condition>Necrotizing Enterocolitis</condition>
  <condition>Dysbiosis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Anemia</arm_group_label>
    <description>Stool samples from infants with anemia. Severe anemia defined as hematocrit less than 25%. Anemia defined as hematocrit greater than or equal to 25% and less than 30%.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>No Anemia</arm_group_label>
    <description>Stool samples from infants without anemia. No anemia defined as hematocrit equal to or greater than 30%.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <biospec_retention>Samples Without DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Stool
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        The study will enroll preterm infants that are less than 32 weeks gestational age at birth.
        At time of enrollment, these infants must be between 7 days of age up to (and including) 30
        days of age. They must also be on enteral feeds of at least 100mL/kg/day. The investigators
        will exclude infants who have developed NEC prior to enrollment, who have had surgery prior
        to enrollment, who have major congenital anomalies, or who are requiring FiO2 &gt;50% at time
        of enrollment.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Preterm infants less than 32 weeks gestation at birth

          -  Age at enrollment between 7 days and less than/equal to 30 days

          -  Minimum 100 mL/kg/day enteral feeds

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Development of necrotizing enterocolitis (NEC) prior to enrollment

          -  Prior surgery

          -  Major congenital anomalies

          -  Oxygen requirement with FiO2 (fraction of inspired oxygen) &gt;50% (at time of
             enrollment)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>30 Days</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Julie Mirpuri Hathiramani, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>UT Southwestern Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Parkland Health &amp; Hospital System</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dallas</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>75235</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gritz EC, Bhandari V. The human neonatal gut microbiome: a brief review. Front Pediatr. 2015 Mar 5;3:17. doi: 10.3389/fped.2015.00017. eCollection 2015. Review. Erratum in: Front Pediatr. 2015;3:60.</citation>
    <PMID>25798435</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Patel RM, Denning PW. Intestinal microbiota and its relationship with necrotizing enterocolitis. Pediatr Res. 2015 Sep;78(3):232-8. doi: 10.1038/pr.2015.97. Epub 2015 May 20. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25992911</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Warner BB, Tarr PI. Necrotizing enterocolitis and preterm infant gut bacteria. Semin Fetal Neonatal Med. 2016 Dec;21(6):394-399. doi: 10.1016/j.siny.2016.06.001. Epub 2016 Jun 22. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>27343151</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Warner BB, Deych E, Zhou Y, Hall-Moore C, Weinstock GM, Sodergren E, Shaikh N, Hoffmann JA, Linneman LA, Hamvas A, Khanna G, Rouggly-Nickless LC, Ndao IM, Shands BA, Escobedo M, Sullivan JE, Radmacher PG, Shannon WD, Tarr PI. Gut bacteria dysbiosis and necrotising enterocolitis in very low birthweight infants: a prospective case-control study. Lancet. 2016 May 7;387(10031):1928-36. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(16)00081-7. Epub 2016 Mar 9.</citation>
    <PMID>26969089</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zhou Y, Shan G, Sodergren E, Weinstock G, Walker WA, Gregory KE. Longitudinal analysis of the premature infant intestinal microbiome prior to necrotizing enterocolitis: a case-control study. PLoS One. 2015 Mar 5;10(3):e0118632. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0118632. eCollection 2015.</citation>
    <PMID>25741698</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pammi M, Cope J, Tarr PI, Warner BB, Morrow AL, Mai V, Gregory KE, Kroll JS, McMurtry V, Ferris MJ, Engstrand L, Lilja HE, Hollister EB, Versalovic J, Neu J. Intestinal dysbiosis in preterm infants preceding necrotizing enterocolitis: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Microbiome. 2017 Mar 9;5(1):31. doi: 10.1186/s40168-017-0248-8. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>28274256</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Patel RM, Knezevic A, Shenvi N, Hinkes M, Keene S, Roback JD, Easley KA, Josephson CD. Association of Red Blood Cell Transfusion, Anemia, and Necrotizing Enterocolitis in Very Low-Birth-Weight Infants. JAMA. 2016 Mar 1;315(9):889-97. doi: 10.1001/jama.2016.1204.</citation>
    <PMID>26934258</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hay S, Zupancic JA, Flannery DD, Kirpalani H, Dukhovny D. Should we believe in transfusion-associated enterocolitis? Applying a GRADE to the literature. Semin Perinatol. 2017 Feb;41(1):80-91. doi: 10.1053/j.semperi.2016.09.021. Epub 2016 Nov 17. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>27866662</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 3, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 30, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 13, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 12, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 12, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 14, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>NEC</keyword>
  <keyword>transfusion</keyword>
  <keyword>microbiome</keyword>
  <keyword>premature</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Enterocolitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Enterocolitis, Necrotizing</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Anemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Anemia, Neonatal</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dysbiosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <provided_document_section>
    <provided_document>
      <document_type>Study Protocol</document_type>
      <document_has_protocol>Yes</document_has_protocol>
      <document_has_icf>No</document_has_icf>
      <document_has_sap>No</document_has_sap>
      <document_date>November 22, 2017</document_date>
      <document_url>https://ClinicalTrials.gov/ProvidedDocs/78/NCT03554278/Prot_000.pdf</document_url>
    </provided_document>
  </provided_document_section>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

