<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03552328</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Pro00034170</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03552328</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effects of a Volunteer-based Lunch Program on Feelings of Loneliness in Elders</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effects of a Pilot Volunteer-based Lunch Program on Feelings of Loneliness in Elders: a Randomized Control Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of South Florida</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>The Arnold P. Gold Foundation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of South Florida</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background: There is a need for stronger community involvement with the elderly, specifically
      those with feelings of loneliness. Large proportions of elders in previous studies reported
      feelings of loneliness, and loneliness at advanced ages is a growing trend seen within the
      last thirty years despite advances in technology and social media. We propose a randomized
      control trial to determine the effectiveness of a volunteer-based lunch program on decreasing
      feelings of loneliness in elderly participants.

      Methods: Lonely elders in the community will be identified and matched with a trained medical
      student. Each student will bring provided lunches once a week to their elder participant's
      residence, and they will share lunch together for an hour once a week for six weeks.
      Enrollees are eligible for the study if they are over 60 years of age, speak English, have
      feelings of loneliness on the three-item scale, and display no cognitive impairment. The
      participants will be assessed pre and post intervention using the R-UCLA scale for
      loneliness, PHQ-9 for depressive symptoms, and GAD-7 for feelings of anxiety. Participant
      satisfaction will be assessed using Likert items as well as open-ended questions.
      Intervention group responses will be compared to responses of participants that did not
      receive the lunch meeting intervention.

      Discussion: Success of such a companion lunch program would provide an effective route to
      combat loneliness in the elderly.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Since the 1960's, the elderly population in the United States has grown steadily. By 2030,
      one in three people in the U.S. will be over the age of 65. In addition to being at a greater
      risk for chronic disease, the elderly are also more vulnerable to being socially isolated and
      lonely. Simply living alone does not appear to be a significant predictor of loneliness, as
      the elderly could still have a strong support network while living alone, but prevalence data
      suggests that one in three adults over the age of 65 are lonely. Furthermore, the oldest of
      the elderly seem to be the loneliest. Dykstra et al. in a 2009 study estimate 40 to 50
      percent of those aged 80 or older to be lonely.

      Loneliness has been previously defined as the difference between desired and actual
      relationships, and there is a distinction between loneliness and social isolation. While
      being considered socially isolated is due to lack of social contact, loneliness is assessed
      by perceptions of social isolation. Feelings of disconnect, isolation, and not belonging are
      much more indicative of loneliness than simple aloneness and lack of social contact. Not
      having a support network or anyone to confide in can lead to feelings of social isolation,
      and despite advances in technology and the development of social media, feelings of
      loneliness have increased in the past thirty years. The proportion of Americans who said they
      had no one to talk to about important matters increased from 10% in 1985 to 25% in 2004. This
      is an alarming trend because social support has been consistently shown to increase the
      likelihood of survival. In a meta-analytic review from 2009, participants with strong social
      relationships and support were found to have a 50 percent increased likelihood of survival.
      Additionally, a 2013 study found that mortality rates were significantly higher among
      socially isolated and lonely elders. Loneliness has a profound effect on our healthcare
      system and has been linked to a higher degree of healthcare utilization. In a Swedish study
      from 2014, researchers found that lonely elders use more outpatient services than non-lonely
      elders. In 2015, Gerst et al. found that the large proportion of elders over 60 years old
      that reported feelings of loneliness had a significantly higher physician visit rate.

      There is a demonstrated need for intervention in this lonely, elderly population, with
      significant public health implications. A randomized control trial from 1999 implementing a
      visitor volunteer program for the elderly showed that strong community involvement increased
      the participants' feelings of worth, social integration, and life satisfaction. More
      recently, a local food delivery project in Tampa showed that weekly food delivery to an
      at-risk elderly population decreased participants' feelings of loneliness and increased their
      measured well-being over the course of two months. While both pilot programs had short
      evaluation periods, they demonstrated the effectiveness of volunteer-based community
      involvement. Combining a visitor volunteer program with a food delivery service could serve
      to effectively combat the elderly community's feelings of loneliness and social isolation.

      A local food delivery project in Tampa showed that weekly food delivery to an at-risk elderly
      population decreased participants' feelings of loneliness and increased their measured
      well-being over the course of two months. Even though it demonstrated the effectiveness of
      volunteer-based community involvement, the project was constructed as a pretest-posttest,
      descriptive study using convenience sampling, and feelings of loneliness were evaluated as a
      secondary objective using a three-item loneliness screener. In our study, we plan to measure
      the effects of adding a volunteer visitor to the lunch program; that is, to see if eating
      meals with a medical student can decrease feelings of loneliness when compared with simply
      receiving meals through Meals on Wheels. Our study is designed as a randomized control trial
      in which seniors will be randomly assigned to two groups: paired with a medical student for
      lunch or not paired with a medical student while still receiving meals.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 15, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 15, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">February 17, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Eligible and consenting participants are randomized to one of the two study groups in a 1:1 allocation ratio. A block-stratified method using the computer will be used for generation of randomization sequence. The block size will be random.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>The randomization sequence will be implemented centrally with one of the co-investigator (Ambuj Kumar) who is off site will retain the list. Once a participant is identified the primary investigator will call the off-site co-investigator for assignment. Given that the co-investigator is not on site will ensure adequate allocation concealment.
Also, since the outcome data will be collected using a questionnaire, the possibility of interpretation does not exist. Data analysts will not be informed of the subject assignment and the coding for participant will be as group 1 or 2.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Revised-UCLA (R-UCLA) Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>Survey will be administered on both study groups twice; once before and once after the six-week period.</time_frame>
    <description>Investigators will measure change from baseline feelings of loneliness in elderly participants. Responses are scored from 20 (minimum) to 80 (maximum). Only total scores are reported. Lower values represent a better outcome, i.e. less feelings of loneliness.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient Health Questionnaire-9 (PHQ-9)</measure>
    <time_frame>Survey will be administered on both study groups twice; once before and once after the six-week period.</time_frame>
    <description>We will measure change from baseline feelings of depression in elderly participants. Responses are scored from 0 (minimum) to 27 (maximum). Only total scores are reported. Lower values represent a better outcome, i.e. less feelings of depression.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Generalized Anxiety Disorder 7-item (GAD-7) Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>Survey will be administered on both study groups twice; once before and once after the six-week period.</time_frame>
    <description>We will measure change from baseline feelings of anxiety in elderly participants. Responses are scored from 0 (minimum) to 21 (maximum). Only total scores are reported. Lower values represent a better outcome, i.e. less feelings of anxiety.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">16</enrollment>
  <condition>Aged</condition>
  <condition>Loneliness</condition>
  <condition>Depression</condition>
  <condition>Anxiety</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Seniors receiving daily meals from Meals on Wheels. Intervention: Lunch with Medical Student.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Seniors receiving daily meals from Meals on Wheels</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Lunch with Medical Student</intervention_name>
    <description>Each student will bring provided lunches once a week to their elder participant's residence, and they will share lunch together for an hour once a week for six weeks. Students will enroll as Meals on Wheels volunteers and participate in the Meals on Wheels pre-program training. On the day of their scheduled lunch, students will first arrive at the Meals on Wheels designated meal-drop location and pick up two lunches, one for them and one for their assigned elder. They will then drive to their assigned elder's residence and eat lunch with them for one hour.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Control</intervention_name>
    <description>Students will not bring provided lunches to an elder participant's residence. The elder participants in this arm will simply continue receiving daily meals from Meals on Wheels with no accompanying student.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Enrollees are eligible for the study if they speak English, have feelings of
             loneliness on the three-item scale, are able to give written consent, and answer
             surveys.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Elders who are unable to give informed consent or complete trial documentation.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>60 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Lucy Guerra, MD, MPH</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Associate Professor, USF College of Medicine Internal Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Morsani College of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tampa</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33620</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lawson, V. and K. Kinsella, Aging in the United States: Past, present, and future. 1996, International Programs Center, Population Division, US Bureau of the Census, Washington, DC.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Perissinotto CM, Stijacic Cenzer I, Covinsky KE. Loneliness in older persons: a predictor of functional decline and death. Arch Intern Med. 2012 Jul 23;172(14):1078-83. doi: 10.1001/archinternmed.2012.1993.</citation>
    <PMID>22710744</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dykstra PA. Older adult loneliness: myths and realities. Eur J Ageing. 2009 Jun;6(2):91-100. Epub 2009 Apr 4.</citation>
    <PMID>19517025</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hughes ME, Waite LJ, Hawkley LC, Cacioppo JT. A Short Scale for Measuring Loneliness in Large Surveys: Results From Two Population-Based Studies. Res Aging. 2004;26(6):655-672.</citation>
    <PMID>18504506</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Holt-Lunstad J, Smith TB, Layton JB. Social relationships and mortality risk: a meta-analytic review. PLoS Med. 2010 Jul 27;7(7):e1000316. doi: 10.1371/journal.pmed.1000316. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20668659</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>McPherson, M., L. Smith-Lovin, and M.E. Brashears, Social isolation in America: Changes in core discussion networks over two decades. American sociological review, 2006. 71(3): p. 353-375.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Steptoe A, Shankar A, Demakakos P, Wardle J. Social isolation, loneliness, and all-cause mortality in older men and women. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2013 Apr 9;110(15):5797-801. doi: 10.1073/pnas.1219686110. Epub 2013 Mar 25.</citation>
    <PMID>23530191</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Taube E, Kristensson J, Sandberg M, Midlöv P, Jakobsson U. Loneliness and health care consumption among older people. Scand J Caring Sci. 2015 Sep;29(3):435-43. doi: 10.1111/scs.12147. Epub 2014 May 14.</citation>
    <PMID>24826811</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gerst-Emerson K, Jayawardhana J. Loneliness as a public health issue: the impact of loneliness on health care utilization among older adults. Am J Public Health. 2015 May;105(5):1013-9. doi: 10.2105/AJPH.2014.302427. Epub 2015 Mar 19.</citation>
    <PMID>25790413</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>MacIntyre I, Corradetti P, Roberts J, Browne G, Watt S, Lane A. Pilot study of a visitor volunteer programme for community elderly people receiving home health care. Health Soc Care Community. 1999 May;7(3):225-232.</citation>
    <PMID>11560637</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wright L, Vance L, Sudduth C, Epps JB. The Impact of a Home-Delivered Meal Program on Nutritional Risk, Dietary Intake, Food Security, Loneliness, and Social Well-Being. J Nutr Gerontol Geriatr. 2015;34(2):218-27. doi: 10.1080/21551197.2015.1022681.</citation>
    <PMID>26106989</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cattan M, Kime N, Bagnall AM. The use of telephone befriending in low level support for socially isolated older people--an evaluation. Health Soc Care Community. 2011 Mar;19(2):198-206. doi: 10.1111/j.1365-2524.2010.00967.x. Epub 2010 Nov 29.</citation>
    <PMID>21114564</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>July 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 26, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 7, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 11, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 18, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 18, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 22, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of South Florida</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Brennan Ninesling</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Medical Student</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Depression</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>We will ensure that all data collected during the trial is handled confidentially and accessed only by members of the team. We will store participants' details on a secure database. We will assign participants an individual specific trial number and we will anonymize their details.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <provided_document_section>
    <provided_document>
      <document_type>Study Protocol</document_type>
      <document_has_protocol>Yes</document_has_protocol>
      <document_has_icf>No</document_has_icf>
      <document_has_sap>No</document_has_sap>
      <document_date>May 26, 2018</document_date>
      <document_url>https://ClinicalTrials.gov/ProvidedDocs/28/NCT03552328/Prot_000.pdf</document_url>
    </provided_document>
    <provided_document>
      <document_type>Informed Consent Form</document_type>
      <document_has_protocol>No</document_has_protocol>
      <document_has_icf>Yes</document_has_icf>
      <document_has_sap>No</document_has_sap>
      <document_date>March 14, 2018</document_date>
      <document_url>https://ClinicalTrials.gov/ProvidedDocs/28/NCT03552328/ICF_001.pdf</document_url>
    </provided_document>
  </provided_document_section>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

