<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03552146</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>17-136</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03552146</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluating the Effects of Propofol vs. Dexmedetomidine</brief_title>
  <official_title>Evaluation of the Effects on Efficiency of a Sedation Service by Switching From Propofol to Dexmedetomidine</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Children's Healthcare of Atlanta</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Morehouse School of Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Children's Healthcare of Atlanta</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>Yes</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The primary purpose of this observational study is to compare what drugs work best in
      sedating children (&gt; 3 months to &lt; 36 months) who need an MRI. This type of research may help
      clinicians (healthcare providers) learn more about how dexmedetomidine works compared to
      propofol. The investigators are planning to have 60 children complete the study at Children's
      Healthcare of Atlanta at Scottish Rite. Half (30) of the patients will be randomized to
      receive dexmedetomidine and the other half will receive propofol. (Both drugs are licensed
      and approved for the sedation performed for consented patients.)
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      There are several different medications commonly being used to facilitate the administration
      of radiologic procedures on children. Procedures such as Magnetic Resonance Imaging (MRIs)
      require that the patient remain still for the duration of the test. Propofol has become the
      drug of choice for many sedation services due to its rapid onset of action, rapid recovery
      time, ability to achieve sedation reliably and favorable safety profile. Dexmedetomidine, a
      selective alpha-2- adrenergic agonist, has also gained popularity with sedation services. Its
      main advantage over propofol is that it has minimal respiratory complications when compared
      to propofol. The sedative effect from dexmedetomidine preserves a natural sleep pattern and
      induces cooperative sedation in which patients are easily arousable. In pediatric studies,
      the most frequent adverse effect have been related to its potential to cause hypotension and
      bradycardia, which resolve with dose reduction. Additionally, dexmedetomidine does not seem
      to have as much impairment of cognitive function and has an opioid sparing effect.
      Dexmedetomidine, however, has a longer onset of action and longer recovery time compared to
      propofol, which has limited its use with many sedation services.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 24, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 30, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 30, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Procedural times to achieve optimal sedation</measure>
    <time_frame>Start of procedure to discharge (up to 8 hours)</time_frame>
    <description>Measuring the amount of time it takes for a patient to be discharged starting from induction (start of infusion).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Sedation related events</measure>
    <time_frame>Start of procedure to up to 36 hours post-discharge</time_frame>
    <description>Adverse events related to the sedation (i.e., apnea, desaturation, change in heart rate)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Post-discharge clinical status</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to 24 hours post discharge</time_frame>
    <description>Recording any events post-discharge that are possibly sedation-related</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Sedative Adverse Reaction</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sedation Group 1</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients will receive standard of care dose of Propofol, based on the provider's assessment, prior to radiologic procedure.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sedation Group 2</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients will receive standard of care dose of dexmedetomidine, based on the provider's assessment, prior to radiologic procedure.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Propofol</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients will be randomized to either propofol or dexmedetomidine and then observed for sedation-related events from time of drug administration to discharge.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Sedation Group 1</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Diprivan</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Dexmedetomidine</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients will be randomized to either propofol or dexmedetomidine and then observed for sedation-related events from time of drug administration to discharge.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Sedation Group 2</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Precedex</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        The study will draw from children who are scheduled for non emergent sedation to undergo a
        brain non contrast, magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) study. Children are otherwise healthy
        and fall within the age span of 3 months to 36 months. This is an observational study of
        the outcomes outlined, when patients agree to be randomized to either of 2 drugs which are
        FDA approved to provide optimal sedation for this MRI procedure.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Patient (or Parent/Guardian) is English speaking

          2. Patient is undergoing a scheduled, elective non-contrast MRI of the brain

          3. Patient is &gt; 3 months to &lt;36 months of age

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients undergoing MRI with contrast

          2. Patients older than 36 months of age or younger than 3 months of age

          3. Patients presenting to Emergency Department (ED) out of screening hours

          4. Patients who are not English speaking

          5. Patients who have history or record of propofol or dexmedetomidine allergy

          6. Patients with known or history of anaphylaxis to eggs, egg products, soybeans, or soy
             based products; if patient has a history of a hypersensitivity reaction associated
             with exposure to eggs, egg products, soybeans, or soy based products, approval must be
             given by the treating attending physician and documented on the patient's medical
             record.

          7. Patients with unstable cardiac or respiratory status as determined by treating
             attending physician

          8. Patients who are receiving digoxin
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>3 Months</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>36 Months</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>David Fagin, MD</last_name>
    <phone>404-785-6000</phone>
    <email>david.fagin@pema.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Lilly H Immergluck, MD</last_name>
    <phone>404-785-6000</phone>
    <email>lilly.immergluck@pema.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Children's Healthcare of Atlanta</name>
      <address>
        <city>Atlanta</city>
        <state>Georgia</state>
        <zip>30342</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 30, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 29, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 11, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 23, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 23, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 24, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Children's Healthcare of Atlanta</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>David Fagin, MD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Medical Director</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>sedation</keyword>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Dexmedetomidine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Propofol</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>This is a pilot study of observations made of patients who are randomized to receive 1 of 2 sedation medications, which are currently FDA approved for the proposed study. The data will help researchers determine the feasibility to conduct a large scale multi-center study to look specifically at primary outcomes as outlined in the proposal.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

