<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03557008</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IRB00101567</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03557008</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Systems Biology of Inactivated Rabies Vaccine in Healthy Adults With or Without Use of Broad Spectrum Antibiotics</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Prospective Randomized Open Label Trial to Study the Systems Biology of Inactivated Rabies Vaccine in Healthy Adults With or Without Use of Broad Spectrum Antibiotics</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Emory University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Emory University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The study is a prospective randomized, unblinded study looking to enroll 54 subjects at Emory
      University. The use of antibiotics changes micro-organisms in the intestines. The change to
      micro-organisms in the intestines may change the body's vaccine immune response and alter the
      effectiveness of the rabies vaccine.

      There will be two randomized groups (1:1 randomization). Group A will start taking an
      antibiotic regimen by mouth 3 days prior to vaccination and continue taking antibiotics the
      day of rabies vaccination and one day after vaccination for a total of 5 days. Group B will
      only receive the rabies vaccination and will not take any antibiotics. The dosage of each
      antibiotic is taken from their respective package inserts and does not exceed the maximum
      dose allowed for each antibiotic.

      The purpose of the study is to look at certain markers (immune responses) in blood and lymph
      nodes after rabies vaccination with or without the use of antibiotics from day of vaccination
      to 28 days post vaccination in both groups.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Vaccination has been one of the most important and cost-effective public health interventions
      to provide protection against infectious diseases. Since the introduction of the first
      vaccine in 1796, there have been countless advances in the field. However, numerous gaps
      remain to be addressed. An important gap is understanding the mechanisms that lead to
      suboptimal immune responses to vaccination. It has been shown that the magnitude of the
      immune response produced by vaccines is highly variable among individuals, with both genetic
      and environmental factors playing an important role. More recently, emphasis is being placed
      on the role of the microbiota in vaccine immunogenicity. The microbiome is the collection of
      all microbial cells in and on the human body, with the majority being in the gastrointestinal
      tract. Due to this link between microbiome and the immune system, it is important to further
      understand the impact of the microbiome on the immune response to vaccination. This can be
      done using systems vaccinology, which is the application of systems biology in vaccinology to
      predict vaccine efficacy. The aim is to find molecular signatures, or patterns of gene
      expression induced after vaccination, which can be used to correlate and predict the
      development of protective immunity. The goal of this study is to determine whether alteration
      of microbiota by antibiotic exposure can negatively impact the immunogenicity of rabies
      vaccine, and to assess the innate and adaptive immune mechanisms responsible for that
      phenomenon. The study also wants to evaluate the safety profile of the different antibiotics
      and the lymph node sampling methods.

      Half of the study participants will receive the rabies vaccine alone and half will receive
      the rabies vaccine along with a 5 day course of antibiotics. The primary objective of this
      study is to compare antibody titers after vaccination with the rabies vaccine in adults with
      or without use of antibiotics.

      Prior to the clinical trial portion of this study comparing the antibody titers between the
      study arms, the researchers will evaluate lymph node sampling methods. The study will
      determine whether Fine Needle Aspiration (FNA) or Core Needle Biopsy (CNB) is the best
      technique for sampling lymph nodes. Once the best technique is determined, the ideal timing
      of lymph node sampling will be examined by comparing follow up sampling at 1, 3 or 7 days
      after vaccination. The technique and timing found to be best will be used throughout the
      remainder of the trial.Subjects are followed on days 1, 3, 7, 14, 28, 180, and 365 post
      randomization. Any grade 2 solicited adverse event (AE) (until D28 or up to 7 days after
      lymph node sampling) or serious adverse event (SAE) (for the duration of the study) which may
      not have been reported by the subject by calling the site as directed at a prior visit.

      Blood samples for immunologic testing will be collected at screening (from D -35 to D -2), on
      D0 (at vaccination), D1, D3, D7 (+/- 1 day), D14 (+/- 2 day), D28 (+/- 5 days), D29, D35 (+/-
      1 day), D56 (+/- 5 days), D180 (+/- 14 days), D365 (+/- 14 days) post vaccination for both
      groups to study innate and/or adaptive immune responses.

      Stool samples will be collected in both groups at screening (from D -35 to D -2), on D0 (at
      vaccination), D1, D3, D7 (+/- 1 day), D14 (+/- 2 day), D28 (+/- 5 days), D29, D35 (+/- 1
      day), D56 (+/- 5 days), D180 (+/- 14 days), D365 (+/- 14 days) post vaccination to study the
      gut microbiome. For Group A, stools will be screened for Clostridium difficile carriage by
      PCR at screening (from D-35 to D-2).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 5, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Longitudinal and Randomized</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Antibody Titers</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 28</time_frame>
    <description>The comparison of antibody titers will be examined by direct comparison of antibody titers expressed in international units (IU) per milliliter (mL) of blood. The first data analysis route is directly comparing the means of the antibody titers between the two groups at 28 days after vaccination. Rabies antibody titer levels range from 0.1 to 15.0 IU/mL and titer levels of at least 0.5 IU/mL indicate there has been an adequate immune response after rabies vaccination.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">54</enrollment>
  <condition>Rabies Human</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Rabies Vaccine with Antibiotics</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants in this group will receive the rabies vaccines as well as an antibiotic regimen consisting of metronidazole, vancomycin, and neomycin sulfate.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Rabies Vaccine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants in this group will receive the rabies vaccine.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Rabies Vaccine</intervention_name>
    <description>A single 1.0 milliliter (mL) dose of Imovax® will be given to participants on Day 0 and Day 28 of the study.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Rabies Vaccine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Rabies Vaccine with Antibiotics</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Imovax</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Metronidazole</intervention_name>
    <description>The antibiotic regimen will be given for five days beginning 3 days prior to vaccination, on the vaccination day, and one day after vaccination for a total for 5. The regimen will include 500 milligrams (mg) of Flagyl taken by mouth three times a day.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Rabies Vaccine with Antibiotics</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Flagyl</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Vancomycin</intervention_name>
    <description>The antibiotic regimen will be given for five days beginning 3 days prior to vaccination, on the vaccination day, and one day after vaccination for a total for 5. The regimen will include 125 mg of Vancocin taken by mouth four times a day.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Rabies Vaccine with Antibiotics</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Vancocin</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Neomycin Sulfate</intervention_name>
    <description>The antibiotic regimen will be given for five days beginning 3 days prior to vaccination, on the vaccination day, and one day after vaccination for a total for 5. The regimen will include 500 milligrams (mg) of Neomycin sulfate taken by mouth three times a day.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Rabies Vaccine with Antibiotics</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Mycifradin</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Healthy individuals aged 18-49 years.

          -  Able to understand and give informed consent.

          -  Women of child-bearing potential (not surgically sterile via tubal ligation, bilateral
             oophorectomy or hysterectomy or who are not postmenopausal for ≥1 year) must agree to
             practice adequate contraception that may include, but is not limited to, abstinence,
             monogamous relationship with vasectomized partner, barrier methods such as condoms,
             diaphragms, spermicides, intrauterine devices, and licensed hormonal methods for 28
             days before and 28 days after Rabies vaccination.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Receipt of the following:

               -  Receipt of blood products 3 months prior to vaccination or expected receipt
                  through 12 months after vaccination.

               -  Receipt of any live virus vaccines within 28 days prior to vaccination or
                  expected receipt within 28 days after vaccination.

               -  Receipt of any inactivated vaccine within 14 days or expected receipt within 14
                  days after vaccination.

               -  Receipt of any antibiotic 3 months prior to vaccination or expected receipt 28
                  days after vaccination.

               -  Receipt of probiotics and prebiotics 3 months prior to vaccination or expected
                  receipt 28 days after vaccination.

               -  Receipt of proton pump inhibitors, H2 receptor blockers, or antacids 3 months
                  prior to vaccination or expected receipt 28 days after vaccination.

          -  Presence of co-morbidities or immunosuppressive states such as:

               -  Chronic medical problems including (but not limited to) insulin dependent
                  diabetes, severe heart disease (including arrhythmias), severe lung disease, auto
                  immune diseases, thrombocytopenia and grade 4 hypertension. Grade 4 hypertension
                  per CTCAE criteria is defined as Life-threatening consequences (e.g., malignant
                  hypertension, transient or permanent neurologic deficit, hypertensive).

               -  Chronic neurologic conditions including seizure disorder, Parkinson's disease,
                  myasthenia gravis, neuropathy, or history of encephalopathy, meningitis or
                  ototoxicity.

               -  Any history of gastrointestinal disease including (but not only): documented
                  bacterial gastroenteritis or gastroenteritis associated with fever or associated
                  with presence of blood/mucus in stools in the last 3 months; inflammatory bowel
                  disease, and/or gastrointestinal surgery.

               -  Any history of kidney or liver diseases.

               -  Alcohol abuse, drug abuse, or psychiatric conditions that in the opinion of the
                  investigator would preclude compliance with the trial or interpretation of safety
                  or endpoint data.

               -  Any history of lymphoma involving axillary nodes or any history of breast cancer.

               -  Impaired immune function or known chronic infections including, but not limited
                  to, known HIV, tuberculosis, hepatitis B or C; organ transplantation (bone
                  marrow, hematopoietic stem cell, or solid organ transplant); immunosuppression
                  due to cancer; current and/or expected receipt of chemotherapy, radiation
                  therapy, steroids (i.e., more than 20 mg of prednisone given daily or on
                  alternative days for 2 weeks or more in the past 90 days , or high dose inhaled
                  corticosteroids); and any other immunosuppressive therapies (including anti-TNF
                  therapy), functional or anatomic asplenia, or congenital immunodeficiency.
                  Subjects receiving &gt; 20 mg/day of prednisone or its equivalent daily or on
                  alternate days for more than 2 weeks may enter the study after therapy has been
                  discontinued for more than 3 months and Subjects are excluded if on high dose
                  intranasal steroids defined as &gt; 960 mcg/day of beclomethasone dipropionate or
                  equivalent.

               -  Pregnancy or breast feeding

          -  Conditions that could affect the safety of the volunteers, such as:

               -  Severe reactions to prior vaccinations, including anaphylaxis

               -  History of Guillain-Barré syndrome

               -  History of bleeding disorders or current use of warfarin, aspirin, heparin,
                  nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs) or other blood
                  thinner/anticoagulant medications in the past week (for subjects undergoing lymph
                  node sampling)

               -  Use of anticonvulsants

               -  Use of digoxin or other forms of digitalis

               -  Any allergy to any component of the vaccine or lidocaine (for subjects undergoing
                  lymph node sampling)

               -  Allergy to vancomycin, metronidazole or neomycin as well as other aminoglycosides
                  (gentamicin, tobramycin, amikacin, streptomycin)

          -  Volunteers with any acute illness, including any fever (&gt; 100.4 F [&gt; 38.0C],
             regardless of the route) within 3 days prior to vaccination.

          -  Social, occupational, or any other condition that in the opinion of the investigator
             might interfere with compliance with the study and vaccine evaluation.

          -  Positive C difficile testing by PCR at screening or history of C difficile infection.

          -  Any grade 2 safety lab test results at screening

          -  Previously received any rabies vaccine or immunoglobulin.

          -  Are at high risk of exposure to rabies: veterinarians, animal handlers, rabies
             laboratory workers, spelunkers, frequent contact with rabies virus or with possibly
             rabid animals, international travelers who are likely to come in contact with animals
             in parts of the world where rabies is common, and rabies biologics production workers.

          -  Bilateral inflammatory process of upper arms in the past 2 weeks.

          -  Prior breast or axillary biopsy and/or surgery.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>49 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Nadine Rouphael, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Emory University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Nadine Rouphael, MD</last_name>
    <phone>404-712-1435</phone>
    <email>nroupha@emory.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Eileen Osinski</last_name>
    <phone>404-712-1371</phone>
    <email>gosinsk@emory.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Winship Cancer Institute of Emory University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Atlanta</city>
        <state>Georgia</state>
        <zip>30322</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Nadine Rouphael, MD</last_name>
      <phone>404-712-1435</phone>
      <email>nroupha@emory.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The Hope Clinic of the Emory Vaccine Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Decatur</city>
        <state>Georgia</state>
        <zip>30030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Nadine Rouphael, MD</last_name>
      <phone>404-712-1435</phone>
      <email>nroupha@emory.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Nadine Rouphael, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 4, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 4, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 14, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 20, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 20, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 23, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Emory University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Nadine Rouphael</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Rabies Vaccine</keyword>
  <keyword>Antibiotics</keyword>
  <keyword>Biopsy</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Rabies</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Metronidazole</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vancomycin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neomycin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

