<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03559192</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CR108487</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>67953964MDD2001</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>2019-000695-41</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03559192</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study to Explore the Efficacy of JNJ-67953964 in the Treatment of Depression</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase 2a Randomized, Double-blind, Placebo-Controlled, Parallel-Group, Multi-center Study Investigating the Efficacy, Safety, Tolerability and Pharmacokinetics of JNJ-67953964 in Subjects With Major Depressive Disorder</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Janssen Research &amp; Development, LLC</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Janssen Research &amp; Development, LLC</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to evaluate the efficacy of JNJ-67953964 compared to placebo
      when administered as adjunctive treatment in participants with Major Depressive Disorder
      (MDD) partially responsive to selective serotonin reuptake inhibitor/
      serotonin-norepinephrine reuptake inhibitor (SSRI/SNRI) treatment in terms of reduction of
      symptoms of depression, as assessed by the change from baseline on the Montgomery Asberg
      Depression Rating Scale (MADRS) in non-responders during the placebo lead-in period.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 16, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 6, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 6, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change From Baseline in Montgomery Asberg Depression Rating Scale (MADRS) Score up to Treatment Week 6</measure>
    <time_frame>Treatment Baseline up to Treatment Week 6</time_frame>
    <description>The MADRS is a clinician-rated scale designed to measure depression severity and detects changes due to antidepressant treatment. The scale consists of 10 items, each of which is scored from 0 (item not present or normal) to 6 (severe or continuous presence of the symptoms), for a total possible score of 60. Higher scores represent a more severe condition.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change From Baseline in Snaith-Hamilton Pleasure Scale (SHAPS) Score up to Treatment Week 6</measure>
    <time_frame>Treatment Baseline up to Treatment Week 6</time_frame>
    <description>The SHAPS is a self-report 14-item, instrument, developed for the assessment of hedonic capacity. Participants score whether they experience pleasure in performing a list of activities or experiences. Participants can rate the answers as &quot;definitely/strongly agree&quot;, &quot;agree&quot;, &quot;disagree&quot; or &quot;strongly disagree&quot;. &quot;Definitely agree&quot; will be rated 1, &quot;Agree&quot; will be rated 2, &quot;Disagree&quot; will be rated 3, and &quot;Definitely disagree&quot; will be rated 4. The participant's item responses are summed to provide a total score ranging from 14 to 56. A higher total SHAPS score indicates higher levels of current anhedonia.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change From Baseline in Clinical Global Impression - Severity (CGI-S) Scores up to Treatment Week 6</measure>
    <time_frame>Treatment Baseline up to Treatment Week 6</time_frame>
    <description>The CGI-S evaluates the severity of psychopathology on a scale of 0 to 7. Considering total clinical experience, a participant is assessed on severity of mental illness at the time of rating according to: 0=not assessed; 1=normal (not at all ill); 2=borderline mentally ill; 3=mildly ill; 4=moderately ill; 5=markedly ill; 6=severely ill; 7=among the most extremely ill patients. The CGI-S permits a global evaluation of the participant's condition at a given time.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change From Baseline in Symptoms of Major Depressive Disorder Scale (SMDDS) Total Scores up to Treatment Week 6</measure>
    <time_frame>Treatment Baseline up to Treatment Week 6</time_frame>
    <description>The SMDDS is a 16-item patient reported outcome (PRO) measure. Each item will be rated by the participant according to a 5-point Likert scale. Participants respond to each question using a rating scale between 0 (&quot;Not at all&quot; or &quot;Never&quot;) to 4 (&quot;Extremely&quot; or &quot;Always&quot;). The total score ranges from 0 to 60 with a higher score indicating more severe depressive symptomatology. The SMDDS uses a 7-day recall period and verbal rating scales.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change From Baseline in Self-Assessment of Treatment Experience (SATE) Score up to Treatment Week 6</measure>
    <time_frame>Treatment Baseline up to Treatment Week 6</time_frame>
    <description>The SATE questionnaire is a 1- or 2-item self-report scale designed to provide additional information regarding the participant's subjective experience on depression since starting the study medication. This is a qualitative scale and the responses will be recorded as 'very much improved', 'much improved', 'improved', 'no change', 'worse', 'much worse', and 'very much worse'.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change From Baseline in Hamilton Anxiety Scale 6 (HAM-A6) Score up to Treatment Week 6</measure>
    <time_frame>Treatment Baseline up to Treatment Week 6</time_frame>
    <description>The HAM-A scale assesses the severity of different anxiety-related symptoms with a score range of 0 to 52. Each of the 14 items is rated by the clinician on a 5-point scale ranging from 0 (not present) to 4 (maximum degree). The 6 item subscale from HAM-A (HAM-A6) is a uni-dimensional, 6-item subscale derived from the original HAM-A. The HAM-A6 comprises of five psychic anxiety symptoms: anxious mood, psychic tension, fears, intellectual disturbances, and anxious behaviour observed at the interview, as well as one somatic item, muscular tension, with a score range of 0 to 24. Higher scores represent more severe anxiety symptoms.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change From Baseline in Structured Interview Guide for the Hamilton Anxiety Rating Scale (SIGH-A) Score up to Treatment Week 6</measure>
    <time_frame>Treatment Baseline up to Treatment Week 6</time_frame>
    <description>SIGH-A is a 14-item scale to measure severity of different anxiety-related symptoms in participants. Each of the 14 items is rated by the clinician on a 5-point scale ranging from 0 (not present) to 4 (maximum degree) with a total score range of 0 to 52 where higher score indicates worsening.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">181</enrollment>
  <condition>Depressive Disorder, Major</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Lead-in Period: Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will receive matching placebo for the entire duration of the lead-in period.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment Period: JNJ-67953964 or Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants who respond or do not respond (based on reduction from lead-in baseline in MADRS) in the placebo lead-in period will receive either matching placebo or 10 (2*5) milligram (mg) JNJ-67953964 capsules in a 1:1 ratio for 6 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Withdrawal Period: Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants who complete the double-blind treatment period prior to the end of Week 11 will receive matching placebo for the remaining time of the treatment phase of the study.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>JNJ-67953964</intervention_name>
    <description>JNJ-67953964 10 mg will be administered as two 5-mg capsules orally once daily.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment Period: JNJ-67953964 or Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Matching placebo will be administered as 2 capsules orally once daily.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Lead-in Period: Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment Period: JNJ-67953964 or Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Withdrawal Period: Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Have a Body Mass Index (BMI) between 18 and 35 kilogram per meter square (kg/m^2)
             inclusive (BMI = weight/height^2)

          -  Participants must be medically stable based on clinical laboratory tests, medical
             history, vital signs, and 12-lead electrocardiogram (ECG) performed at screening and
             baseline

          -  Participants must have a primary Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders
             5th edition (DSM-5) diagnosis of Major Depressive Disorder (MDD)

               1. The current episode should be less than 18 months

               2. Participants should be currently treated with an SSRI or SNRI at an adequate dose
                  and for at least 6 weeks but no more than 12 months

               3. Have a Montgomery-Asberg Depression Rating Scale (MADRS) total score greater than
                  or equal to (&gt;=) 25 at screening

          -  A woman of childbearing potential must have a negative serum pregnancy test at
             screening and a negative urine pregnancy test before the first dose

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  History of documented gastric disease (including documented peptic ulcer disease,
             gastritis, upper gastrointestinal [GI] bleeding, esophagitis, or any GI precancerous
             condition), current clinically evident GI complaints

          -  Chronic use of a proton pump inhibitors (PPIs). History of incidental use of PPIs is
             allowed but should have been stopped at least 4 weeks before screening. A history of
             chronic nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drug (NSAID) or aspirin use. (Low dose aspirin
             for example in cardiovascular disease prevention is allowed)

          -  Has a history of alcohol use disorder within the past year

          -  Has failed (no more than 25 percent [%] response on Antidepressant Treatment History
             Questionnaire [ATRQ]) three or more antidepressant treatments including the current
             Selective serotonin reuptake inhibitor/ serotonin-norepinephrine reuptake inhibitor
             (SSRI/SNRI) during the current depressive episode despite an adequate dose (per ATRQ)
             and duration (at least 6 weeks)

          -  Has signs or symptoms of Cushing's Disease, Addison's Disease, primary amenorrhea, or
             other evidence of significant medical disorders of the hypothalamus pituitary adrenal
             (HPA) axis

          -  Participant has received an investigational drug (including investigational vaccines)
             or used an invasive investigational medical device within 3 months before the planned
             first dose of study drug or has participated in any interventional clinical studies on
             MDD in the previous 1 year or is currently enrolled in an interventional study

          -  Has one or more of the following diagnoses:

               1. A primary DSM (5th edition) diagnosis of generalized anxiety disorder (GAD),
                  panic disorder, obsessive compulsive disorder (OCD), posttraumatic stress
                  disorder (PTSD). Participants with comorbid GAD, social anxiety disorder (SAD),
                  or panic disorder for whom MDD is considered the primary diagnosis are not
                  excluded

               2. A current diagnosis or diagnosis in the past 1 year of psychotic disorder, MDD
                  with psychosis, anorexia nervosa or bulimia nervosa, chronic fatigue syndrome,
                  bipolar disorder (BD), mental retardation, antisocial or borderline personality
                  disorder, autism spectrum disorder

          -  Has a current or recent history of clinically significant suicidal ideation within the
             past 6 months, corresponding to a score of 4 (active suicidal ideation with some
             intent to act, without specific plan) or 5 (active suicidal ideation with specific
             plan and intent) for ideation on the Colombia suicide severity rating scale (C-SSRS),
             or a history of suicidal behavior within the past 1 year

          -  Ongoing psychological treatments (example, Cognitive Behavior Therapy, Interpersonal
             Psychotherapy, Psychodynamic Psychotherapy, etcetera [etc.]), initiated within 1 month
             prior to the screening phase. A participant who has been receiving ongoing
             psychological treatment for a period of greater than 1 month from the screening visit
             is eligible, if the investigator deems the psychological treatment to be of stable
             duration and frequency

          -  Participant has a history of substance use disorder according to DSM-5 criteria,
             except nicotine or caffeine, within 6 months before screening. Mild cases can be
             reviewed on a case by case basis. Participants who have completed a treatment for
             (alcohol) addiction more than 1 year prior to first dose administration, may be
             included if the risk of relapse is considered minimal, total duration of alcohol use
             disorder was less than a year, and no significant abnormalities are shown in clinical
             laboratory or other pre-dose safety assessments

          -  Participant has used:

               1. Monoamine oxidase inhibitors (MAOIs) within 12 weeks before screening

               2. St. John's wort, ephedra, ginkgo, ginseng, or kava within 2 weeks before
                  screening

               3. Antipsychotic drugs (D2-antagonists) within 2 weeks before screening. However,
                  Seroquel (quetiapine) in a dose less than or equals to (&lt;=)100 milligram (mg) is
                  allowed when used in a stable dose for at least 8 weeks prior to screening.
                  Quetiapine treatment should be continued unchanged during the study

               4. Opioids within 2 weeks before screening

               5. Psychostimulants such as methylphenidate or dextroamphetamine within 2 weeks
                  before screening

               6. Psychotropics with antidepressant effects such as atomoxetine or thyroid
                  supplementation, in addition to their SSRI or SNRI treatment within 2 weeks
                  before screening

          -  Participant is unable to stop the following medication from the baseline visit (Visit
             2) and throughout the study (tapering during screening period allowed): Any hypnotics
             including but not limited to: i. Benzodiazepines when used only as needed (PRN) are
             not allowed ii. Sedating antihistamines, including chronic use of diphenhydramine iii.
             Continuous use of zolpidem, zoplicon, eszopiclone and ramelteon. Note:
             Nonbenzodiazepines sleep aids (including: zolpidem, zaleplon, and eszopliclone) are
             allowed on an as needed (PRN) basis during the study but NOT within 24 hours before
             being in the clinic and not more than 2 nights in a row iv. S-adenosyl methionine
             (SAMe) v. Melatonin, agomelatine

          -  Has received any prior treatment with electroconvulsive therapy, vagal nerve
             stimulation, or a deep brain stimulation device or treatment with ketamine or
             esketamine for MDD
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>64 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Janssen Research &amp; Development, LLC Clinical Trial</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Janssen Research &amp; Development, LLC</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Noble Clinical Research</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tucson</city>
        <state>Arizona</state>
        <zip>85704</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Preferred Research Partners</name>
      <address>
        <city>Little Rock</city>
        <state>Arkansas</state>
        <zip>72211</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Behavioral Research Specialists, LLC</name>
      <address>
        <city>Glendale</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>91206</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>NRC Research Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Orange</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>92868</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Artemis Institute for Clinical Research</name>
      <address>
        <city>Riverside</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>92503</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Artemis Institute for Clinical Research</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Marcos</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>92078</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Pacific Clinical Research Medical Group</name>
      <address>
        <city>Upland</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>91786</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Galiz Research</name>
      <address>
        <city>Miami Springs</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33166</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Innova Clinical Trials</name>
      <address>
        <city>Miami</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33133</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>APG Research, LLC</name>
      <address>
        <city>Orlando</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>32803</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Olympian Clinical Research</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tampa</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33614</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Meridien Research</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tampa</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33634</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Atlanta Behavioral Research, LLC</name>
      <address>
        <city>Atlanta</city>
        <state>Georgia</state>
        <zip>30338</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Chicago Research Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chicago</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60634</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Psychiatric Medicine Associates LLC</name>
      <address>
        <city>Skokie</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60076</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Lake Charles Clinical Trials</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lake Charles</city>
        <state>Louisiana</state>
        <zip>70629</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Princeton Medical Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Princeton</city>
        <state>New Jersey</state>
        <zip>08540</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Integrative Clinical Trials, LLC</name>
      <address>
        <city>Brooklyn</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>11229</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Richmond Behavioural Associates</name>
      <address>
        <city>Staten Island</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10312</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Clinical Trials of America</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hickory</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>28601</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ohio State University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Columbus</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>43210</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Midwest Clinical Research Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dayton</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>45417</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>IPS Research Company</name>
      <address>
        <city>Oklahoma City</city>
        <state>Oklahoma</state>
        <zip>73106</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Paradigm Research Professionals, LLC</name>
      <address>
        <city>Oklahoma City</city>
        <state>Oklahoma</state>
        <zip>73118</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Lehigh Center for Clinical Research</name>
      <address>
        <city>Allentown</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>18104</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Medical University of South Carolina</name>
      <address>
        <city>Charleston</city>
        <state>South Carolina</state>
        <zip>29425</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Clinical NeuroScience Solutions, Inc</name>
      <address>
        <city>Memphis</city>
        <state>Tennessee</state>
        <zip>38119</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Advanced Clinical Research</name>
      <address>
        <city>West Jordan</city>
        <state>Utah</state>
        <zip>84088</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Emovis GmbH</name>
      <address>
        <city>Berlin</city>
        <zip>10629</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Somni Bene GmbH</name>
      <address>
        <city>Schwerin</city>
        <zip>19053</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>ARENSIA</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chisinau</city>
        <zip>MD2025</zip>
        <country>Moldova, Republic of</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sverdlovsk Regional Clinical Psychiatric Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ekaterinburg</city>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Clinical Psychiatric Hospital #3 Named After V.A. Gilyarovsky</name>
      <address>
        <city>Moscow</city>
        <zip>107076</zip>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Orenburg Regional Clinical Psychiatric Hospital #1</name>
      <address>
        <city>Orenburg</city>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Medical and Rehabilitation Research Center Phoenix</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rostov-on-Don</city>
        <zip>344002</zip>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Engels psychiatric hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Saratov Region</city>
        <zip>413124</zip>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>SHI 'Saratov City Clinical Hospital 2 n.a V.I. Razumovsky</name>
      <address>
        <city>Saratov</city>
        <zip>410028</zip>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Saratov Regional Psychiatric hospital named after St. Sofia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Saratov</city>
        <zip>410060</zip>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>City Psychiatric hospital 7 named after I.P.Pavlov</name>
      <address>
        <city>St-Petersburg</city>
        <zip>199034</zip>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Psychoneurological dispensary 1</name>
      <address>
        <city>St-Petersburg</city>
        <zip>199178</zip>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>St-Petersburg Bekhterev Psychoneurological Research Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>St. Petersburg</city>
        <zip>192019</zip>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Institute of Mental Health</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tomsk</city>
        <zip>634014</zip>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>MNCE of Kyiv RC Regional Psychiatric and Narcological Medical Association</name>
      <address>
        <city>Glevakha</city>
        <zip>8630</zip>
        <country>Ukraine</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>SI Institute of Neurology, Psychiatry and Narcology of NAMSU</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kharkiv</city>
        <zip>61068</zip>
        <country>Ukraine</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CNPE'Kherson Regional Institution of Mental Care'of Kherson Regional Council</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kherson</city>
        <zip>73488</zip>
        <country>Ukraine</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Kyiv Psychiatry Hospital #2</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kyiv</city>
        <zip>2660</zip>
        <country>Ukraine</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CI Kirovograd RPH Male dept#11,Female dep#17 Donetsk NMU</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nove, Kropyvnytskiy</city>
        <zip>25491</zip>
        <country>Ukraine</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CNCE 'Cherkasy Regional Psychiatric Hospital of Cherkasy Regional Council'</name>
      <address>
        <city>Smila</city>
        <zip>20708</zip>
        <country>Ukraine</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>MAC Clinical Research</name>
      <address>
        <city>Barnsley</city>
        <zip>S75 3DL</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>MAC Clinical Research</name>
      <address>
        <city>Blackpool</city>
        <zip>FY2 0JH</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>MAC Clinical Research</name>
      <address>
        <city>Liverpool</city>
        <zip>L34 1BH</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hammersmith Medicines Research Ltd</name>
      <address>
        <city>London</city>
        <zip>NW10 7EW</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>MAC Clinical Research</name>
      <address>
        <city>Manchester</city>
        <zip>M139NQ</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Germany</country>
    <country>Moldova, Republic of</country>
    <country>Russian Federation</country>
    <country>Ukraine</country>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 6, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 6, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 18, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 3, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 3, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 7, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depression</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder, Major</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

