<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03559582</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>18452</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>U01AI115594</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03559582</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Diagnostics and Pharmacotherapy for Severe Forms of TB (DMID 15-0100)</brief_title>
  <official_title>Diagnostics and Pharmacotherapy for Severe Forms of TB</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Virginia</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Scientific Center for Family Health and Human Reproduction Problems, Russia</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Kilimanjaro Christian Medical Centre, Tanzania</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Haydom Lutheran Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Mbarara University of Science and Technology</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>International Centre for Diarrhoeal Disease Research, Bangladesh</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Florida</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Virginia</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Major Research Aim: To study novel molecular diagnostics and the pharmacokinetic variability
      among a spectrum of TB disease states, including severe forms of TB like disseminated TB, TB
      meningitis and drug resistant TB, among adults and children from multiple international
      sites.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Aim 1. Measure pharmacokinetics to anti-tuberculosis (TB) medications in severe TB syndromes
      (including multidrug-resistant TB, pediatric TB, TB sepsis and TB meningitis) from diverse
      geographies (including Tanzania, Uganda, Bangladesh, and Siberia) and correlate these
      findings to TB treatment outcome (TB treatment failure: death/ default/ relapse/ further
      acquired drug resistance).

      Aim 2. Decipher mechanisms of pharmacokinetic variability to TB drugs, particularly
      malabsorption due to concurrent gastrointestinal disease.

      Aim 3. Deployment of quantitative susceptibility testing (minimum inhibitory
      concentration-MIC) and rapid MIC-informed molecular methods (e.g., TaqMan Array Card-TAC) for
      M. tuberculosis.

      In addition to the stated aims, the primary elements of capacity building requisite for this
      project include the training in and deployment of the fieldable molecular diagnostic
      platforms, onsite pharmacokinetic monitoring, and a broad strengthening of longitudinal
      cohort management for clinical research.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Enrolling by invitation</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">April 28, 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Measure area under the concentration curve (AUC) to anti-tuberculosis (TB) medications relative to TB treatment outcome in severe TB syndromes</measure>
    <time_frame>December 2019</time_frame>
    <description>Severe TB syndromes include multidrug-resistant TB, pediatric TB, TB sepsis and TB meningitis from diverse geographies (including Tanzania, Uganda, Bangladesh, and Siberia). The parameter of most importance to cidal activity of anti-TB medications among the cohort is AUC. TB treatment outcome will be defined as death, microbiological failure, relapse or acquired drug resistance, and machine learning algorithms such as classification and regression tree analyses will be used to define AUC threshold for each anti-TB medication predictive of poor TB treatment outcome. Conventional logistic regression will then be used to determine the additive odds for a patient with one of more medications below an algorithm derived threshold being significantly more likely to have a poor TB treatment outcome.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Collect stool in patients undergoing pharmacokinetic testing to measure the environmental enteropathy index</measure>
    <time_frame>December 2019</time_frame>
    <description>Stool will be collected in patients with severe TB syndromes undergoing pharmacokinetic testing and assayed for stool biomarkers of malabsorption (environmental enteropathy index) and modeled as a determinant of those with AUC values of one or more anti-TB medications below thresholds predictive of TB treatment outcome.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Collect stool in patients undergoing pharmacokinetic testing to measure the quantitative burden and species distribution of enteric pathogens by the enteric TAC assay- 35 bacterial, viral, parasitic species)</measure>
    <time_frame>December 2019</time_frame>
    <description>Stool will be collected in patients with severe TB syndromes undergoing pharmacokinetic testing and assayed for detection of molecular targets of enteric pathogens by TaqMan Array Card (TAC) platform. Enteric pathogen burden (including the effect of multiple pathogens in a single sample) will be modeled as a determinant of those with AUC values of one or more anti-TB medications below thresholds predictive of TB treatment outcome.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">713</enrollment>
  <condition>Tuberculosis</condition>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      This study will use clinical and related phenotypic data and saliva samples to identify and
      characterize genetic and molecular biological markers that will enrich our understanding of
      the biological basis of an individual's response to anti-TB drugs.
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Subjects will be recruited by medical officer review of new admissions to the TB hospitals
        at the study sites- Kibong'oto National TB Hospital (Tanzania), Haydom Lutheran Hospital
        (Tanzania), Irkutsk Regional Clinical Tuberculosis Hospital (Siberia/Russian Federation),
        National Institute of Diseases of the Chest Hospital (Bangladesh), ICDDRB Hospital
        (Bangladesh), Mbarara Regional Referral Hospital (Uganda).
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Patients admitted to one of the study site hospitals with at least ONE of the following:

          1. Clinical suspicion for TB in a child, as defined by NIH Consensus Case Definitions for
             TB research in children, and started on TB treatment

          2. Clinical suspicion for TB meningitis, as defined by the International TB Meningitis
             Workshop Consensus Case Definitions for TB Meningitis

          3. Clinical suspicion for TB sepsis, as defined by the Uganda/PRISM-U definitions

          4. Microbiologic evidence of MDR-TB from a respiratory specimen within the past 6 months

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Pregnant women-self reported

          2. Patient unable per treating physician discretion to undergo sample collection

          3. Patient or representative/guardian unable to sign written informed consent

          4. Patient unable to return for follow-up or be contacted by phone for follow-up
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Scott K Heysell, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Virginia</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <verification_date>June 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 22, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 5, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 18, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 11, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 11, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 13, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Virginia</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Scott Heysell, MD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor of Medicine, Division of Infectious Diseases and International Health</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Tuberculosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

