<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03556904</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>UMCC 2017.163</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>HUM00138918</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03556904</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>FOcal Radiation for Oligometastatic Castration-rEsistant Prostate Cancer (FORCE)</brief_title>
  <official_title>FOcal Radiation for Oligometastatic Castration-rEsistant Prostate Cancer (FORCE): A Phase II Randomized Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Michigan Rogel Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Michigan Rogel Cancer Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This clinical trial will determine whether the addition of radiotherapy to standard of care
      early systemic therapy improves objective progression-free survival rate (combined
      radiographic and clinical) at 18 months, compared to systemic therapy alone in patients with
      oligometastatic castration-resistant prostate cancer.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Suspended</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Enrollment and/or interactions/interventions temporarily paused due to COVID-19 and expected to
    resume in the future. This is not a suspension of IRB approval.
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date type="Actual">December 10, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 1, 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 1, 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The proportion of patients who are progression-free and alive at 18 months</measure>
    <time_frame>18 Months</time_frame>
    <description>The number of patients who are objective progression-free and alive at 18 months will be counted in each treatment arm and divided by the number of patients who received any protocol treatment to provide the 18-month objective PFS (progression free survival) proportion.
Response and progression definitions used will be a combination of the criteria proposed by the Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors (RECIST) Committee v1.1 and the Prostate Cancer Working Group 3.
For target/measurable disease progression will be defined as at least a 20% increase in the sum of the LD (longest diameter) of target lesions, taking as reference the smallest sum LD recorded since the treatment started, or the appearance of one or more new lesions. The sum must also demonstrate an absolute increase of at least 5 mm. The appearance of one or more new target lesions is also considered progression.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Median objective progression free survival time</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Objective progression-free survival (PFS) is defined as the duration of time from start of treatment to date that progression is objectively documented or death occurs (whichever is first).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Median PSA progression free survival time</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 24 months</time_frame>
    <description>The Median PSA progression free survival time is defined as the median duration of time from start of treatment to date that PSA progression is documented or death occurs (whichever is first). PSA (prostate specific antigen) progression is defined as a 25% increase over baseline or nadir whichever is lower and an increase in the absolute value of PSA level by 2 ng/ml.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Median radiographic progression free survival</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Radiographic progression-free survival (PFS) is defined as the duration of time from start of treatment to date that progression is radio-graphically documented or death occurs (whichever is first).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival time</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Overall survival (OS) is defined as the duration of time from start of treatment to death.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Prostate cancer specific survival time</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Prostate Cancer Specific Survival (PCSS) is defined as the duration of time from start of treatment to death from prostate cancer.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Non-irradiated metastases free survival time</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Non-irradiated metastases free survival is defined as the duration of time from start of treatment to the date of progressive disease of a new target lesion, a new non-measurable/non-target lesion or emergence of 2 or more new skeletal lesions on a bone scan.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The proportion of patients with complete PSA response</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 24 months</time_frame>
    <description>The number of patients whose PSA becomes undetectable (≤0.2 ng/ml) will be counted in each treatment arm and divided by the number of patients who received any protocol treatment to provide the proportion of patients with complete PSA response. Complete PSA response is defined as an undetectable PSA (≤0.2 ng/ml).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The proportion of patients with a PSA Partial Response 50 (PR50)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 24 months</time_frame>
    <description>The number of patients whose PSA declines by 50% decline (PSA partial response 50 (PR50)) will be counted in each treatment arm and divided by the number of patients who received any protocol treatment to provide the proportion of patients with PR50. PR50 response is defined as a decrease in PSA value by ≥ 50%.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The proportion of patients with a PSA Partial Response 90 (PR90)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 24 months</time_frame>
    <description>The number of patients whose PSA declines by 90% decline (PSA partial response 90 (PR90)) will be counted in each treatment arm and divided by the number of patients who received any protocol treatment to provide the proportion of patients with PR90. PR90 response is defined as a decrease in PSA value by ≥ 90%.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The proportion of patients that respond to treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>The measurable disease response rate (CR + PR) will be calculated for patients evaluable for measurable disease response.
Complete response (CR) is defined as a disappearance of all target lesions. Any pathological lymph nodes (whether target or non-target) must have reduced in short axis to &lt;10 mm. There can be no appearance of new lesions.
Partial Response (PR) is defined as at least a 30% decrease in the sum of the longest diameter (LD) of target lesions, taking as reference the baseline sum LD. There can be no appearance of new lesions.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">72</enrollment>
  <condition>Prostate Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Standard of Care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The choice of agent will be up to the treating medical oncologist and is not the study intervention. Current first line systemic therapy is most commonly a second generation androgen pathway inhibitor, including enzalutamide or abiraterone, although docetaxel is allowed. Patients should begin systemic treatment within 3 weeks of randomization.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Standard of Care + Radiotherapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Standard of care therapy will be up to the treating medical oncologist and is not the study intervention. Current systemic therapy is most commonly a second generation androgen pathway inhibitor, including enzalutamide or abiraterone, although docetaxel is allowed.
Radiotherapy will be delivered to a total EQD2 (Equivalent dose in 2Gy fractions) that ranges between conventional 30 Gy in 10 fractions, to SBRT (Stereotactic Body Radiation Therapy) with 50 Gy in 5 fractions. Patients should start systemic therapy within 3 weeks of randomization (unless radiation is begun within 3 weeks and the provider may hold systemic therapy until completion of radiation) and receive radiotherapy within 8 weeks of randomization.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Radiation</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Radiation Therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>Radiotherapy will be delivered to a total EQD2 (Equivalent dose in 2Gy fractions) that ranges between conventional 30 Gy in 10 fractions, to SBRT with 50 Gy in 5 fractions.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Standard of Care + Radiotherapy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Enzalutamide</intervention_name>
    <description>Current standard of care dosing</description>
    <arm_group_label>Standard of Care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Standard of Care + Radiotherapy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Abiraterone</intervention_name>
    <description>Current standard of care dosing</description>
    <arm_group_label>Standard of Care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Standard of Care + Radiotherapy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Docetaxel</intervention_name>
    <description>Current standard of care dosing</description>
    <arm_group_label>Standard of Care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Standard of Care + Radiotherapy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects must have biopsy-confirmed adenocarcinoma of the prostate

          -  Subjects must discontinue all systemic or experimental therapies started for
             metastatic hormone-sensitive prostate cancer (mHSPC) for at least 2 weeks prior to
             registration with no evidence of a falling PSA (prostate specific antigen) after
             washout. LHRH (luteinizing hormone-releasing hormone) analogues must be continued if
             they have not undergone orchiectomy. (Subjects who recently started systemic therapy
             for metastatic castration-resistant prostate cancer (mCRPC) are eligible to enroll if
             new therapy was started ≤ 14 days to consent date.)

          -  Subjects must have progressive metastatic castration-resistant prostate cancer based
             on at least one of the following criteria while having castrate levels (&lt;50 ng/dL) of
             testosterone:

          -  A) PSA progression defined as a 25% increase over baseline value with an increase in
             the absolute value of at least 2.0 ng/mL that is confirmed by another PSA level with a
             minimum of a 1-week interval.

          -  B) Progression of bidimensionally measurable soft tissue or nodal metastasis by CT
             scan or MRI based on RECIST criteria

          -  C) Progression of bone disease on bone scan as defined by two new lesions arising

          -  Subjects must have oligometastatic prostate cancer, defined as between 1 and ≤5
             treatment sites that can be treated within a radiotherapy treatment field.

          -  Subjects must be medically fit to undergo radiotherapy and systemic therapy as
             determined by the treating physician.

          -  Age ≥ 18

          -  ECOG ≤ 2 (Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group scoring system used to quantify general
             well-being and activities of daily life; scores range from 0 to 5 where 0 represents
             perfect health and 5 represents death)

          -  No prior invasive malignancy in the past 3-years unless disease free for a minimum of
             2 years. Exceptions include non-melanomatous skin cancer and in situ cancers of the
             bladder or head and neck are permissible.

          -  Subjects must freely sign informed consent to enroll in the study.

          -  Subjects must use contraception up to 90 days after last drug dose.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Planned systemic therapy with Radium-223 dichloride or sipuleucel-T

          -  Life expectancy estimate of &lt;3 months

          -  Presence of known parenchymal brain metastasis

          -  Uncontrolled intercurrent illness

          -  Inability to undergo radiotherapy, systemic treatment, CTs or bone scans

          -  Biopsy proven pure small cell or neuroendocrine prostate cancer
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <gender_based>Yes</gender_based>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Zachery Reichert, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Michigan Rogel Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Michigan Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ann Arbor</city>
        <state>Michigan</state>
        <zip>48109</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 16, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 1, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 14, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 29, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 29, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 1, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Prostatic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Docetaxel</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

