<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03550430</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Neurofeedback for tinnitus</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03550430</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Neurofeedback for Tinnitus - Does Frequency Specificity Matter?</brief_title>
  <official_title>Study Protocol for a Single-blind Randomized Controlled Trial, Assessing the Specificity of an Alpha/Delta Ratio Neurofeedback Training Protocol in Chronic Tinnitus.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Philipps University Marburg Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Eriksholm Research Centre</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Linkoeping University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University Hospital of Gießen and Marburg</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Philipps University Marburg Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will evaluate the efficacy of an alpha/delta ratio (ADR) neurofeedback training
      protocol on tinnitus distress. 1/3 of the participants in the study will undergo ADR
      neurofeedback training, 1/3 an active comparator, beta/theta ratio (BTR) neurofeedback
      training, whilst the final 1/3 of participants will fill in daily diaries of tinnitus
      complaints and symptoms for two weeks.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Tinnitus is hypothesized to originate as a result of a disturbance in the balance of
      excitatory and inhibitory neurons in central auditory structures. More specifically,
      inhibitory neurons hyperpolarize, by which their functional role is weakened . Consequently,
      this allows auditory neurons, deprived of input from a lesioned auditory system, to
      spontaneously synchronize their activity, resulting in the tinnitus percept.

      In the normal functioning auditory system, neurons firing synchronously in the alpha
      frequency region (8 - 12 Hz) have a gating function of inhibiting task-irrelevant regions in
      the brain. In people with chronic tinnitus, it has been observed, that alpha activity over
      temporal regions is weakened, thus leading to the spontaneous activity characterizing the
      condition. By upregulating alpha activity with neurofeedback training, it is hypothesized
      that the excitatory/inhibitory balance in temporal regions can be restored, thus minimizing
      the tinnitus percept.

      The coupling or exchange of information of distinct brain regions, leading to an integrated
      conscious perception, is assumed to be mediated by delta oscillations. In tinnitus, the
      distress associated with the condition arises as a consequence of coupling prefrontal areas,
      responsible for allocation of attentional resources with limbic (arousal) and temporal
      (auditory processing) regions. In neurofeedback, the downregulation of delta activity is
      hypothesized to lead to a de-coupling of the communication between the areas associated with
      the distress.

      No studies to date have tested the specific role of alpha and delta in the origin and
      perpetuation of tinnitus distress and intrusiveness. The present study seeks to compensate
      for this, by comparing an alpha and delta neurofeedback ratio training protocol with one
      assumed to have no direct association with the pathophysiology of tinnitus.

      In addition to the ten neurofeedback training sessions, all participants undergo diagnostic
      assessments at three time points throughout the trial (pre-neurofeedback training,
      post-neurofeedback training and at three months follow-up). For the first 40 participants,
      electroencephalographic (EEG) activity is recorded and cognitive capacity assessed with two
      attention tests, the Attention Network Test and Sustained Attention Response Task,
      respectively at all three time points. For the remaining 80 participants, the EEG recording
      is abandoned, and only cognitive capacity assessed in the pre- post, and follow-up phase of
      the study.

      EEG recording and attention processes is similarly measured in a control group (n=40) at the
      pre-neurofeedback training stage. The group is comprised of healthy, age and gender matched
      participants. Their inclusion serve the purpose of comparing the brain activity, both at rest
      and during cognitive activity between people with- and people without tinnitus.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 1, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 1, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Tinnitus Handicap Inventory (THI; Newman, Sandridge, &amp; Jacobson, 1998)</measure>
    <time_frame>16 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Self-report measure of tinnitus handicap assessed pre-intervention, mid-treatment (five sessions), post-intervention and at three month follow-up. The Tinnitus Handicap Inventory is a 25 item questionnaire. Each item is scored 0 - 4 (0 = No, 2 = Sometimes, 4 = Yes), yielding a total between 0 (no handicap) - 100 (catastrophic impact).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Tinnitus Magnitude Index (TMI; Schmidt, Kerns, Griest, Theodoroff, Pietrzak, &amp; Henry, 2014).</measure>
    <time_frame>16 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>TMI measures tinnitus intensity, three-item scale assessing self-reported severity, loudness and awareness.
- Visual analogue scale ranges from 0-10 or 0-100, respectively: item 1 (loudness): Range 0 (not at all strong or loud) to 10 (extremely strong or loud) item 2 (awareness): 0 to 100 in increments of 10, with verbal anchors of 0=&quot;never aware&quot; and 100=&quot;always aware&quot; item 3 (severity): 0-100 with verbal anchors of 0=&quot;no tinnitus present&quot; to 100=&quot;the worst tinnitus you can imagine&quot;
for all items higher values indicate higher tinnitus magnitude
values of the three items can be summed up to a total score. For standardisation, items are converted from 0-100 to 0-10.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Tinnitus Functional Index (TFI; Brüggemann, Szczepek, Kleinjung, Ojo, &amp; Mazurek, 2017)</measure>
    <time_frame>16 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The Tinnitus Functional Index (TFI) is a self-report measure of both perceived severity and negative impact of tinnitus. It covers multiple severity domains including but not exclusively quality of sleep, relaxation, sense of control. The TFI questionnaire consists of 25 items, predominantly scored between 0 - 10 bar item 1 and 3, which are expressed as percentages from 0 - 100%.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Brief Illness Perception Questionnaire (B-IPQ; Broadbent, Petrie, Main, &amp; Weinman, 2006)</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The B-IPQ is a nine item self-report measure of individual cognitive and emotional representations of illness. It includes the following domains: consequences of the illness; perception of duration of illness; control over illness; treatment control; symptoms; understanding of illness; emotional response and causes.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Insomnia Severity Index (ISI; Bastien, Vallières, &amp; Morin, 2001)</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>A brief scanning measure of insomnia. It consists of 7 items assessing insomnia severity, interference in daily functioning, noticeability of impairment and distress/concern about sleep problems.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Credibility and Expectancy Questionnaire (CEQ; Devilly &amp; Borkovec, 2000)</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>a quick and easy-to-administer scale for measuring treatment expectancy and rationale credibility for use in clinical outcome studies</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Sustained Attention Response Task (SART; Robertson, Manly, Andrade, Baddeley, &amp; Yiend, 1997)</measure>
    <time_frame>16 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>measures the ability to sustain attention</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Attention Network Test (ANT; Fan, McCandliss, Sommer, Raz, &amp; Posner, 2002)</measure>
    <time_frame>16 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>assesses orienting, alerting and executive attention processing respectively</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient Health Questionnaire (PHQ-9; Gräfe, Zipfel, Herzog, &amp; Löwe, 2004)</measure>
    <time_frame>16 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Assessment of depressive symptoms</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Satisfaction with treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>self-developed scale to assess satisfaction with neurofeedback</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">120</enrollment>
  <condition>Tinnitus</condition>
  <condition>Subjective Tinnitus</condition>
  <condition>Chronic Tinnitus</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>ADR neurofeedback</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Ten ADR neurofeedback training sessions. The first five sessions comprise four training blocks. The latter five sessions consists of five training blocks each. All training blocks are seven minutes in duration. Participants take between two to three sessions each week.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>BTR neurofeedback</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Ten BTR neurofeedback training sessions. The first five sessions comprise four training blocks. The latter five sessions each consists of five training blocks. All training blocks are seven minutes in duration. Participants take between two to three sessions each week.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Diary Control Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Daily diary completion for two weeks in the period between baseline and end-point assessments (total period baseline to end-point = four weeks).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>alpha/delta neurofeedback</intervention_name>
    <description>neurofeedback training protocol seeking to decrease the alpha/delta ratio, by simultaneous rewarding alpha and inhibiting delta activity.</description>
    <arm_group_label>ADR neurofeedback</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>beta/theta neurofeedback</intervention_name>
    <description>neurofeedback training protocol seeking to decrease the beta/theta ratio, by simultaneous rewarding beta and inhibiting theta activity.</description>
    <arm_group_label>BTR neurofeedback</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Diary completion</intervention_name>
    <description>completion of diary relating to participants' experience of tinnitus intensity, interference, coping, harm and disability. Rated three times daily on numerical scale (0 - 10) for two weeks.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Diary Control Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Chronic subjective tinnitus, i.e. tinnitus with a duration &gt; 6 months

          -  At least moderate tinnitus distress, corresponding to a score of &gt; 38 on the Tinnitus
             Handicap Inventory

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Moderately severe or severe depression

          -  Objective tinnitus, where causes are classified according to whether they are vascular
             or non-vascular in origin

          -  Current use of psychotropic drugs for a mental health condition

          -  Bipolar disorder, Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder (ADHD), Psychosis

          -  Substance abuse

          -  Current psychotherapeutic treatment for tinnitus, previous biofeedback- or
             neurofeedback treatment

          -  A history of seizures, strokes and/or brain hemorrhages
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Cornelia Weise, Dr.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Philipps Universität Marburg</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Martin Jensen, MSc</last_name>
    <phone>+4551176802</phone>
    <email>martin.jensen@staff.uni-marburg.de</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Eva Hüttenrauch, MSc</last_name>
    <email>eva.huettenrauch@staff.Uni-Marburg.de</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Philipps University Marburg, Dept. of Psychology, Division of Clinical Psychology and Psychotherapy</name>
      <address>
        <city>Marburg</city>
        <state>Hessen</state>
        <zip>35037</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Martin Jensen, M.Sc.</last_name>
      <phone>+49-6421-2823794</phone>
      <email>martin.jensen@uni-marburg.de</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Weise Cornelia, Dr.</last_name>
      <email>weise@uni-marburg.de</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Cornelia Weise, Dr.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Germany</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Balkenhol T, Wallhäusser-Franke E, Delb W. Psychoacoustic tinnitus loudness and tinnitus-related distress show different associations with oscillatory brain activity. PLoS One. 2013;8(1):e53180. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0053180. Epub 2013 Jan 10.</citation>
    <PMID>23326394</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dohrmann K, Weisz N, Schlee W, Hartmann T, Elbert T. Neurofeedback for treating tinnitus. Prog Brain Res. 2007;166:473-85. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>17956812</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Weisz N, Dohrmann K, Elbert T. The relevance of spontaneous activity for the coding of the tinnitus sensation. Prog Brain Res. 2007;166:61-70. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>17956772</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Weisz N, Hartmann T, Müller N, Lorenz I, Obleser J. Alpha rhythms in audition: cognitive and clinical perspectives. Front Psychol. 2011 Apr 26;2:73. doi: 10.3389/fpsyg.2011.00073. eCollection 2011.</citation>
    <PMID>21687444</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Newman CW, Sandridge SA, Jacobson GP. Psychometric adequacy of the Tinnitus Handicap Inventory (THI) for evaluating treatment outcome. J Am Acad Audiol. 1998 Apr;9(2):153-60.</citation>
    <PMID>9564679</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schmidt CJ, Kerns RD, Griest S, Theodoroff SM, Pietrzak RH, Henry JA. Toward development of a tinnitus magnitude index. Ear Hear. 2014 Jul-Aug;35(4):476-84. doi: 10.1097/AUD.0000000000000017.</citation>
    <PMID>24603542</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Brüggemann P, Szczepek AJ, Kleinjung T, Ojo M, Mazurek B. [Validation of the German Version of Tinnitus Functional Index (TFI)]. Laryngorhinootologie. 2017 Sep;96(9):615-619. doi: 10.1055/s-0042-122342. Epub 2017 May 12. German.</citation>
    <PMID>28499301</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Broadbent E, Petrie KJ, Main J, Weinman J. The brief illness perception questionnaire. J Psychosom Res. 2006 Jun;60(6):631-7.</citation>
    <PMID>16731240</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bastien CH, Vallières A, Morin CM. Validation of the Insomnia Severity Index as an outcome measure for insomnia research. Sleep Med. 2001 Jul;2(4):297-307.</citation>
    <PMID>11438246</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Devilly GJ, Borkovec TD. Psychometric properties of the credibility/expectancy questionnaire. J Behav Ther Exp Psychiatry. 2000 Jun;31(2):73-86.</citation>
    <PMID>11132119</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fan J, McCandliss BD, Sommer T, Raz A, Posner MI. Testing the efficiency and independence of attentional networks. J Cogn Neurosci. 2002 Apr 1;14(3):340-7.</citation>
    <PMID>11970796</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Robertson IH, Manly T, Andrade J, Baddeley BT, Yiend J. 'Oops!': performance correlates of everyday attentional failures in traumatic brain injured and normal subjects. Neuropsychologia. 1997 Jun;35(6):747-58.</citation>
    <PMID>9204482</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gräfe, K., Zipfel, S., Herzog, W., &amp; Löwe, B. (2004). Screening psychischer Störungen mit dem &quot;Gesundheitsfragebogen für Patienten (PHQ-D)&quot;. Diagnostica, 50(4), 171-181.</citation>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 27, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 27, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 8, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 2, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 2, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 3, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>tinnitus distress</keyword>
  <keyword>tinnitus intrusiveness</keyword>
  <keyword>synchronization by loss of inhibition model (SLIM)</keyword>
  <keyword>neurofeedback</keyword>
  <keyword>alpha/delta neurofeedback</keyword>
  <keyword>beta/theta neurofeedback</keyword>
  <keyword>electroencephalography (EEG)</keyword>
  <keyword>tinnitus intensity</keyword>
  <keyword>tinnitus loudness</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Tinnitus</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Anonymized individual participant data for all primary and secondary outcome measures will be made available.</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>Data available within one year of study completion</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>Data access request will be reviewed by the Principal Investigator. Requestors will be required to sign a data access agreement.</ipd_access_criteria>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

