<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03559244</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>09.2018.328</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03559244</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Dynamic Compression Brace for Pectus Carinatum</brief_title>
  <official_title>Investigating the Effects of Exercises in Addition to Dynamic Compression Brace in Patients With Pectus Carinatum: a Single Blinded Randomized Controlled Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Marmara University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Marmara University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Pectus carinatum (PC) is a deformity of the anterior chest wall which is a common pediatric
      condition, characterized by an idiopathic overgrowth of the costal cartilages resulting in
      protrusion of the sternum. Chest pain or discomfort, especially when lying in prone position,
      increased respiratory effort during exercise, scoliosis, impaired shoulders and kyphotic
      position are some of the physical signs and symptoms. Unlike pectus excavatum, PC is rarely
      associated with significant cardiopulmonary involvement except in severe cases. Pectus
      carinatum is not just a simple aesthetical problem. The effect of patient's self-esteem, body
      image and confidence can be variable and lead to significant deterioration in mental health.
      It can be responsible of physical signs and symptoms and also has significant psychological
      impact. Deformity and its psychological impact tend to worsen during pubertal rapid phases of
      growth and even during adult life. The management of pectus deformities used to include
      surgical techniques, however, recently compression brace which is a dynamic orthosis which is
      custom-fitted, rigid aluminum brace that is adjustable to any thoracic shape is widely
      applied instead of surgery. Pressure applied to the patient, in the most protruding area of
      the chest, needed to accomplish a proper shape of the thorax, the pressure of correction can
      be measured via a pressure measuring device in pounds per square inches (PSI). Treatment
      choices of surgery or bracing is determined according to pressure of correction and type of
      deformity. Surgical correction is indicated if the presence of chondro-manubrial type PC and
      pressure of correction &gt; 10 PSI. Chest pain or discomfort, especially when lying in prone
      position, increased respiratory effort during exercise, scoliosis, impaired shoulders and
      kyphotic position are some of the physical signs and symptoms. Despite the fact that patients
      with PC have impaired posture, exercise intolerance and increased scoliosis occurrence, there
      is no consensus on the exercise program for patients with PC. Also, there is not enough
      scientific evidence about the wear time of orthosis. The aim of this study is to investigate
      the effects of exercises and compression brace in children with PC.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Pectus carinatum (PC) is a deformity of the anterior chest wall which is a common pediatric
      condition, characterized by an idiopathic overgrowth of the costal cartilages resulting in
      protrusion of the sternum. There are two subtypes of PC: the chondro-gladiolar variant, which
      is the most common type, and presents with protrusion of the sternal body, and the
      chondro-manubrial variant, showing protrusion of the component of the sternum (manubrium). PC
      usually involves the lower sternal costal cartilages, pushing the sternum forwards and can be
      symmetrical (bilateral) or often asymmetrical (unilateral) with the right for some reason
      being more obviously affected. PC may occur as a solitary abnormality or in association with
      other genetic disorders or syndromes (eg, trisomy 18, Marfan syndrome, homocystinuria,
      Morquio syndrome, and Ehlers-Danlos syndrome). Of the musculoskeletal abnormalities,
      scoliosis is most frequently associated with PC.

      Chest pain or discomfort, especially when lying in prone position, increased respiratory
      effort during exercise, scoliosis, impaired shoulders and kyphotic position are some of the
      physical signs and symptoms. Unlike pectus excavatum, PC is rarely associated with
      significant cardiopulmonary involvement except in severe cases. Pectus carinatum is not just
      a simple aesthetical problem. It can be responsible of physical signs and symptoms and also
      has significant psychological impact. Deformity and its psychological impact tend to worsen
      during pubertal rapid phases of growth and even during adult life. It has been demonstrated
      that patients with PC are at risk for a disturbed body image and reduced quality of life and
      many patients refer feelings of discomfort, shame, shyness, anxiety, and even depression.

      The classical management of pectus deformities, both carinatum and excavatum, has been
      primarily surgical. Modification of the Ravitch technique involves resection of the deformed
      costal cartilages along with sternal osteotomy. Because the results of this technique
      resulted in worse cosmetic results, a new less invasive procedure, the Nuss procedure was
      developed. Nuss procedure includes remodeling of the chest wall cartilage with an internal
      support bar. These techniques have demonstrated the plasticity of the chest wall and led
      clinicians to hypothesize that carinatum defects would also remodel in response to chronic
      pressure, leading to a cosmetically superior, nonoperative technique: compression brace.
      Compression brace is a dynamic orthosis which is custom-fitted, rigid aluminum brace that is
      adjustable to any thoracic shape. Complications of brace use include uncommon (4.6%), mild
      and easy to resolve: back pain, hematoma and skin ulceration. Pressure of correction is the
      pressure applied to the patient, in the most protruding area of the chest, needed to
      accomplish a proper shape of the thorax. It is an indirect parameter of the chest wall's
      flexibility. It can be measured with a pressure measuring device in pounds per square inches
      (PSI). Some special designed braces contain a part in which pressure measuring device can be
      docked. This enables measuring of pressure of treatment. Pressure of treatment can be
      different from pressure of correction since skin breakdown occurs with corrections at high
      pressure.

      In the Calgary protocol, wearing brace 23 hours a day during the correction phase until the
      development of the axial skeleton is completed and afterwards 8 hours of wear is recommended
      in the continuation phase.Martinez-Ferro et al developed pressure measuring device and
      special designed braces contain a part in which pressure measuring device can be docked. They
      suggested that patients with pressure of correction &lt;10 should be braced. De Beer et al. also
      recommended the surgical treatment in the presence of chondro-manubrial type PC and pressure
      of correction &gt; 10 PSI. However, recommendations are based on prospective or retrospective
      cohort studies other than randomized controlled trials which corresponds to low level of
      evidence.

      Despite the fact that patients with PC have impaired posture, exercise intolerance and
      increased scoliosis occurrence, there is no consensus on the exercise program for patients
      with PC. Postural impairment aggravates psychological burden caused by disease itself.
      Patients with pectus carinatum may get benefit from exercises to improve posture. Also,
      disease itself or compression brace use may result in abdominal flare and increased lateral
      diameter of chest wall as an unwanted effect. Strengthening of abdominal muscles may prevent
      from abdominal flare. Strengthening of chest wall muscles, strengthening the pectoralis and
      sacrospinalis muscles as well as expanding the chest through deep breathing, strengthening
      core muscles including abdominal muscles, increasing flexibility of muscles, manipulation and
      mobilization of costae may lead improvements in the management of PC.

      There is no consensus about exercises, and there is not enough scientific evidence about the
      wear time of orthosis. The existing treatment protocols are non-standardized protocols
      developed by the researchers of previous studies investigating the effectiveness of orthosis.
      Martinez-Ferro et al., the developer of the dynamic compression brace, recommends the daytime
      wear of orthosis for patients with low pressure of correction. They recommend duration of
      clothing to be shorter and the pressure of treatment should be kept lower in patients with
      high pressure of correction. However, every compression brace may not contain dock and
      pressure of treatment cannot be measured. In the present study we aimed to investigate the
      effects of exercises and compression brace in children with PC. Also, safety and feasibility
      of the orthosis will be evaluated. Patients with chondro-gladiolar, symmetrical or
      asymmetric, compressible PC (compression test positive) and with correction pressure ≤10 PSI,
      aged 5-18 years old will be included to study. They will be randomized to three groups using
      closed envelope system. All groups will be given exercises to strengthen the muscles of the
      respiratory muscles of the posture exercises, deep breathing exercises, ribs manipulation and
      mobilization exercises and core exercises for 1 hour a day, five days a week for 3 weeks. The
      first group will use the orthosis for 8 hours during the night and the second group for 23
      hours except for sports activities, exercise and bath. The control group who will receive
      exercise therapy only will be selected from the wait-in list for the orthosis. Pectus
      carinatum protrusion, pressure of correction, anteroposterior and lateral diameter of thorax
      at the most protruded part of deformity, Haller index, Cobb and kyphosis angle, Pectus
      Evaluation Questionnaire will be assessed at before treatment and after treatment, 1 month
      and 3 months and 6 months after treatment.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 1, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Parallel group randomized controlled study</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>outcome assessor blinded to participants' allocated group</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pectus carinatum protrusion</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 0</time_frame>
    <description>distance from the point of maximum protrusion to the estimated normal level of chest wall</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pectus carinatum protrusion</measure>
    <time_frame>3 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>distance from the point of maximum protrusion to the estimated normal level of chest wall</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>T1 (external measurement of chest wall at the upper age of manubrium)</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 0</time_frame>
    <description>external measurement of the anterior chest wall using a thorax caliper at the upper edge of the manubrium</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>T1 (external measurement of chest wall at the upper age of manubrium)</measure>
    <time_frame>3 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>external measurement of the anterior chest wall using a thorax caliper at the upper edge of the manubrium</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>T2 (external measurement of chest wall at Angulus Ludovici)</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 0</time_frame>
    <description>the external measurement of the anterior chest wall using a thorax caliper at the T2 point (Angulus Ludovici)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>T2 (external measurement of chest wall at Angulus Ludovici)</measure>
    <time_frame>3 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>the external measurement of the anterior chest wall using a thorax caliper at the T2 point (Angulus Ludovici)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>T3 (external measurement of chest wall at the most protruded point from the chest wall)</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 0</time_frame>
    <description>the external measurement of the anterior chest wall using a thorax caliper at the T3 (the most protruded point from the chest wall)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>T3 (external measurement of chest wall at the most protruded point from the chest wall)</measure>
    <time_frame>3 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>the external measurement of the anterior chest wall using a thorax caliper at the T3 (the most protruded point from the chest wall)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Haller index</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 0</time_frame>
    <description>maximal transverse diameter/narrowest anteroposterior(AP) length of chest</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Haller index</measure>
    <time_frame>3 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>maximal transverse diameter/narrowest AP length of chest</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cobb angle</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 0</time_frame>
    <description>The angle between the lines which are drawn parallel to the upper endplate of the superior end vertebra and lower endplate of inferior end vertebra forms the Cobb angle (CA).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cobb angle</measure>
    <time_frame>3 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The angle between the lines which are drawn parallel to the upper endplate of the superior end vertebra and lower endplate of inferior end vertebra forms the CA.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Kyphotic angle</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 0</time_frame>
    <description>the angle between the lines drawn along the upper endplate of T4 vertebra and lower endplate of T12 vertebra is calculated.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Kyphotic angle</measure>
    <time_frame>3 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>the angle between the lines drawn along the upper endplate of T4 vertebra and lower endplate of T12 vertebra is calculated.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pressure of correction</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 0</time_frame>
    <description>Pressure of correction (PC): an indirect parameter of the chest wall's flexibility. It is defined as the pressure applied to the patient, in the most protruding area of the chest, needed to accomplish a proper shape of the thorax.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pressure of correction</measure>
    <time_frame>3 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Pressure of correction (PC): an indirect parameter of the chest wall's flexibility. It is defined as the pressure applied to the patient, in the most protruding area of the chest, needed to accomplish a proper shape of the thorax.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pectus Evaluation Questionnaire patient form</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 0</time_frame>
    <description>The Nuss Questionnaire modified for Adults (NQmA) is a disease-specific health-related quality of life assessment tool for patients with pectus deformities.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pectus Evaluation Questionnaire patient form</measure>
    <time_frame>3 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The Nuss Questionnaire modified for Adults (NQmA) is a disease-specific health-related quality of life assessment tool for patients with pectus deformities.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pectus Evaluation Questionnaire parent form</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 0</time_frame>
    <description>The Nuss Questionnaire modified for Adults (NQmA) is a disease-specific health-related quality of life assessment tool for patients with pectus deformities.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pectus Evaluation Questionnaire parent form</measure>
    <time_frame>3 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The Nuss Questionnaire modified for Adults (NQmA) is a disease-specific health-related quality of life assessment tool for patients with pectus deformities.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Thorax AP diameter measurement</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 0</time_frame>
    <description>Thorax AP diameter measurement with a thoracic caliper at the most protruded region</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Thorax AP diameter measurement</measure>
    <time_frame>3 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Thorax AP diameter measurement with a thoracic caliper at the most protruded region</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Thorax lateral diameter measurement</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 0</time_frame>
    <description>Thorax lateral measurement with a thoracic caliper at the most protruded region</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Thorax lateral diameter measurement</measure>
    <time_frame>3 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Thorax lateral measurement with a thoracic caliper at the most protruded region</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">27</enrollment>
  <condition>Pectus Carinatum</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Dynamic compression brace 8 hours</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Children with pectus carinatum who will wear dynamic compression brace 8 hours a day plus exercises for three weeks</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Dynamic compression brace 23 hours</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Children with pectus carinatum who will wear dynamic compression brace 23 hours (except for bathing and sports activities) a day plus exercises for three weeks</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Only exercises</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The children who are in wait in list for dynamic compression brace will receive only posture exercises, deep breathing exercises, exercises for manipulation and mobilization of ribs, and core exercises for three weeks</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Dynamic compression brace</intervention_name>
    <description>custom-fitted brace adjusts the pressure on the thoracic wall and enables lateral expansion of the thorax</description>
    <arm_group_label>Dynamic compression brace 23 hours</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Dynamic compression brace 8 hours</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Exercises</intervention_name>
    <description>posture exercises, deep breathing exercises, exercises for manipulation and mobilization of ribs, and core exercises</description>
    <arm_group_label>Dynamic compression brace 23 hours</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Dynamic compression brace 8 hours</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Only exercises</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Male patients with pectus carinatum

          2. Symmetric or asymmetric pectus carinatum

          3. Compression test positive

          4. Pressure of correction &lt;10 PSI

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. History of orthosis use

          2. Chondro-manubrial pectus carinatum

          3. Concomitant severe scoliosis (Cobb angle&gt;20)

          4. Having history of chronic disease

          5. History of surgery for scoliosis or pectus carinatum
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>5 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>20 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mustafa Yuksel, Prof</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Marmara University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Gulseren Akyuz, Prof</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Marmara University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Marmara University School of Medicine Department of Physical Medicine and Rehabilitation</name>
      <address>
        <city>Istanbul</city>
        <zip>34899</zip>
        <country>Turkey</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Turkey</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fokin AA, Steuerwald NM, Ahrens WA, Allen KE. Anatomical, histologic, and genetic characteristics of congenital chest wall deformities. Semin Thorac Cardiovasc Surg. 2009 Spring;21(1):44-57. doi: 10.1053/j.semtcvs.2009.03.001. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19632563</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Martinez-Ferro M, Bellia Munzon G, Fraire C, Abdenur C, Chinni E, Strappa B, Ardigo L. Non-surgical treatment of pectus carinatum with the FMF(®) Dynamic Compressor System. J Vis Surg. 2016 Mar 17;2:57. doi: 10.21037/jovs.2016.02.20. eCollection 2016.</citation>
    <PMID>29078485</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kravarusic D, Dicken BJ, Dewar R, Harder J, Poncet P, Schneider M, Sigalet DL. The Calgary protocol for bracing of pectus carinatum: a preliminary report. J Pediatr Surg. 2006 May;41(5):923-6.</citation>
    <PMID>16677884</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>de Beer SA, Gritter M, de Jong JR, van Heurn ELW. The Dynamic Compression Brace for Pectus Carinatum: Intermediate Results in 286 Patients. Ann Thorac Surg. 2017 Jun;103(6):1742-1749. doi: 10.1016/j.athoracsur.2016.12.019. Epub 2017 Mar 6.</citation>
    <PMID>28274516</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Banever GT, Konefal SH, Gettens K, Moriarty KP. Nonoperative correction of pectus carinatum with orthotic bracing. J Laparoendosc Adv Surg Tech A. 2006 Apr;16(2):164-7.</citation>
    <PMID>16646710</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lee RT, Moorman S, Schneider M, Sigalet DL. Bracing is an effective therapy for pectus carinatum: interim results. J Pediatr Surg. 2013 Jan;48(1):184-90. doi: 10.1016/j.jpedsurg.2012.10.037.</citation>
    <PMID>23331813</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>July 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 20, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 5, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 18, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 2, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 2, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">December 4, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>exercise</keyword>
  <keyword>pectus carinatum</keyword>
  <keyword>orthosis</keyword>
  <keyword>dynamic compression brace</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pectus Carinatum</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

