<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03558256</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MBCT2018</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03558256</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Study of Mindfulness-based Cognitive Therapy and Major Depressive Disorder</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Study of Mindfulness-based Cognitive Therapy and Major Depressive Disorder</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Shanghai Mental Health Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Shanghai Mental Health Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The primary objective of the study is to evaluate the clinical curative effect of
      mindfulness-based cognitive therapy(MBCT) for major depressive disorder(MDD). Moreover, we
      will also explore the relationship between P300 potential and erroneous negative potential
      (ERN) variation and clinical symptoms in MDD and MBCT.

      This study is a randomized-control trial with two study arms: half of patient cases will
      receive usual medication treatment with the serotonin reuptake inhibitors (SSRIs) and half of
      patient cases will receive MBCT added to the usual medication treatment. This study is also a
      case-control trial, there will be matched normal controls compared with patient cases through
      a range of psychological scales and electroencephalogram.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The study is designed as a prospective, assessor-blinded, randomized-control, case-control
      clinical trial with 70 MDD cases and 35 matched normal controls.After signed the Informed
      consents, MDD cases will be assigned to two groups randomly by the table generated by
      Microsoft Excel 2010 to ensure the random distribution between groups. The group of each
      patient will be allotted by the research coordinator so that evaluators will be blind about
      it, and patients will be asked to not mention the intervention conditions to evaluators.

      As the research tools, a range of self-rating scales, other-rating scales and behavioral
      tests and EEG will be mainly applied to assess clinical symptoms and brain state of
      participants at baseline (week 0), during the intervention (week 2, 4 and 6), at the end of
      the intervention (week 8), and during the maintenance phase (week 12, 20 and 32).

      After 8-week intervention, all of the participants including MDD cases and normal controls
      will enter the follow-up. Participants of medication group will continue their treatment
      options without changing the types and doses of medication compared with what they used in
      the intervention period. MBCT group is the same that participants will maintain their
      medication treatment and practice MBCT exercises at home.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 16, 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of Hamilton Depression Scale-24 from baseline to 32 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline (week 0), during the treatment (week 2, 4, 6), end of treatment (week 8), and during the maintenance phase (weeks 12, 20 and 32)</time_frame>
    <description>The Hamilton Depression Scale-24 (HAMD-24) is the most common other-rating scale to measure the severity of depression symptoms for adult. It is a clinical instrument with good validity and reliability, and most of the 24 items weighted from 0 to 4.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of Hamilton Anxiety Scale from baseline to 32 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline (week 0), during the treatment (week 2, 4, 6), end of treatment (week 8), and during the maintenance phase (weeks 12, 20 and 32)</time_frame>
    <description>The Hamilton Anxiety Scale (HAMA) is a common clinician-administered scale to measure the state of anxiety among adults with anxiety symptoms. There are 14 items of the 5-point rated scale.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of Self Compassion Scale from baseline to 32 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline (week 0), during the treatment (week 2, 4, 6), end of treatment (week 8), and during the maintenance phase (weeks 12, 20 and 32)</time_frame>
    <description>The Self Compassion Scale (SCS) is proved to be an instrument featured good characteristics for reliability and validity. There are 26 items divided into 6 Subscales (out of 5 points from almost never to almost always), including self-kindness, self-judgment, common humanity, isolation, mindfulness and over-identification.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">105</enrollment>
  <condition>Major Depressive Disorder</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Mindfulness-based Cognitive Therapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>MBCT group is a treatment group used mindfulness- based cognitive therapy added to the usual medication treatment, and guided by two therapists for 8 sessions. Every group of 6 people can form a closed structural group. Each session lasts 2 hours once a week, and has daily homework assignments.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Medication</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Medication group is a control group that can choose to use the serotonin reuptake inhibitors (SSRIs) approved by China food and Drug Administration (SFDA) for the treatment of depression (fluoxetine, paroxetine, fluvoxamine, sertraline, citalopram and escitalopram).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Mindfulness-based Cognitive Therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients participating in the experimental group will receive the MBCT intervention besides the usual medication treatment. The intervention is implemented by the manual adapted from the MBCT for Depression (Segal et al. 2013). The modified version of the program has the same structure with the original manual combined the mindfulness training and the cognitive elements from CBT, but the content is more suitable for the Chinese. The instructors in this study are trained and certificated psychiatrists and psychotherapists with rich experience of working with MDD, and they will receive a weekly supervision conducted by a senior supervisor.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Mindfulness-based Cognitive Therapy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Medication</intervention_name>
    <description>Both of the MBCT group and the medication group will receive the medication treatment. The initial dose conforms the drug instructions, the dosage can be adjusted once a week, and the maximum dosage should not exceed the maximum amount by the instructions. MDD patients with sleep disorders can use drugs combined with benzodiazepine drugs, but not continuing for more than two weeks; while other psychotropic drugs are not allowed. All of the drugs used in this study are usual clinical drugs with good security, the common adverse reactions include nausea, dry mouth, constipation, diarrhea, indigestion, dizziness, drowsiness, fatigue, sweating, heart palpitations, delayed ejaculation in male, increasing blood aminotransferase without symptoms occasionally and so on.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Medication</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Mindfulness-based Cognitive Therapy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion criteria for patient cases:

          -  Male or female, age between 18-55 years.

          -  Junior/middle school education or above.

          -  Meet the DSM- IV diagnosis of MDD by the evaluation of Chinese version of M.I.N.I. and
             the clinical diagnosis of one associate chief and above psychiatrist.

          -  HAMD24 score ≥ 8.

          -  Have not yet accepted psychiatric medication, or had received irregular medication
             treatment and had discontinued it for 8 weeks.

          -  Have enough visual and acoustic ability to complete the inspection required for the
             study.

          -  Each patient should be willing to participate in this study, he/she and his/her
             guardian must sign the informed consent form after understanding the nature of this
             study.

        Inclusion criteria for normal controls:

          -  Healthy population matched patient cases in age, sex and education; Male or female;
             age between 18-55 years; Junior/middle school education or above.

          -  Excluded the possibility of mental disorders by the evaluation of Chinese version of
             M.I.N.I. and the psychiatric interview of one associate chief and above psychiatrist.

          -  HAMD24 score &lt; 8; HAMA score &lt; 7.

          -  No psychotropic drug history.

          -  No history of two lines of three generations of mental disorders.

          -  Have enough visual and acoustic ability to complete the inspection required for the
             study.

          -  Each patient should be willing to participate in this study, he/she and his/her
             guardian must sign the informed consent form after understanding the nature of this
             study.

        Exclusion criteria for patient cases:

          -  Meet DSM-IV Axis I disorder diagnostic criteria for other psychiatric disorders.

          -  Have severe depression symptoms (HAMD24 score &gt; 35), psychotic symptoms, negative
             self-concept or a risk of suicide.

          -  Persons with severe physical disease or central nervous system disease, and with
             substance abuse.

          -  Pregnancy or ready to be pregnant and lactating women.

          -  Had previously received systematic MBCT intervention, with no significant effect.

        Exclusion criteria for normal controls:

          -  Have negative self-concept or a risk of suicide.

          -  Persons with severe physical disease or central nervous system disease, and with
             substance abuse.

          -  Pregnancy or ready to be pregnant and lactating women.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>55 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Yifeng Shen, Senior</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Shanghai Mental Health Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Yifeng Shen, Senior</last_name>
    <phone>13611890930</phone>
    <email>shenyifeng@yahoo.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Shanghai Mental Health Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Shanghai</city>
        <state>Shanghai</state>
        <zip>200030</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jianyin Qiu, Senior</last_name>
      <phone>13524376330</phone>
      <email>jianyin_qiu@163.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 30, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 13, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 15, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 11, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 11, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 15, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Mindfulness-Based Cognitive Therapy</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depression</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder, Major</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

