<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03557606</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>RSI2017-CASE01</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03557606</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Case Series on Using Bone Marrow Concentrate for Alar Ligament Injuries</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Case Series Evaluating the Use of Bone Marrow Concentrate for the Treatment of Alar, Accessory, and Transverse Ligament Injuries</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Regenexx, LLC</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Regenexx, LLC</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      A prospective case series of 200 patients who have been treated with Bone Marrow Concentrate
      using anterior approach through posterior oropharynx for treating alar, accessory, and
      transverse injuries for patients with craniocervical junction instability.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The primary objective of this study is to evaluate the clinical outcomes for patient who are
      treated with with bone marrow concentrate (BMC) using an anterior approach through the
      posterior oropharynx for treating alar and transverse ligament injuries as part of their
      clinical care. The case series will observe pre and post-treatment subject-reported clinical
      outcomes. Secondary objectives include evaluation of post-treatment complications, adverse
      events, re-injections, and surgical intervention, change in use of pain medications, and
      changes on post treatment imaging.

      The treatment consists of patients undergoing a bone marrow aspiration of approximately 30-60
      cc. Platelet rich plasma (PRP) and platelet lysate (PL) will be derived from the bone marrow
      aspirate and later mixed with the bone marrow cell layer. While under anesthesia, the
      injectate is then injected under fluoroscopy into the area in need of treatment using an
      anterior approach through the posterior oropharynx.

      One of the challenges of treating the upper cervical ligaments through injection is that they
      can't be accessed from the posterior due to obstruction from the cervical spinal cord. The
      investigator's group has developed an injection technique using an anterior approach through
      the posterior oropharynx, which allows direct access to the ligaments for injection. The goal
      of this study is to evaluate the effectiveness of this procedure in CCJ instability patients.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Withdrawn</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Collecting data as part of a Patient Registry; redundant study.
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">August 20, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 1, 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Only</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Headache Impact Test score change from baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from Baseline to 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>The within patient mean change from baseline to 6 months in Headache Impact Test scores. Scale of 36-78; HIT-6 scores 36-49 (little to no impact), HIT-6 scores 50-55 (moderate impact), HIT-6 scores 56-59 (substantial impact), HIT-6 scores 60-78 (severe impact ).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Headache Impact Test score change from baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline to 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>The within patient mean change from baseline to 6 months in Headache Impact Test scores. Scale of 36-78; HIT-6 scores 36-49 (little to no impact), HIT-6 scores 50-55 (moderate impact), HIT-6 scores 56-59 (substantial impact), HIT-6 scores 60-78 (severe impact ).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Neck Disability Index score change from baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline to 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>The within patient mean change from baseline to 6 months in Neck Disability Index scores. Scale of 0-50; 0-4 points (no disability), 5-14 points (mild disability), 15-24 points (moderate disability), 25-34 points (severe disability), 35-50 points (complete disability).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Neck Disability Index score change from baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline to 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>The within patient mean change from baseline to 12 months in Neck Disability Index scores.scores. Scale of 0-50; 0-4 points (no disability), 5-14 points (mild disability), 15-24 points (moderate disability), 25-34 points (severe disability), 35-50 points (complete disability).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Short Form Health Survey score change from baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline to 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>The within patient mean change from baseline to 6 months in Short Form Health Survey. Two summary scores are derived; the Physical component scale and the Mental component scale, each on a scale of 0-100, where the higher the score, the better the health.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Short Form Health Survey score change from baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline to 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>The within patient mean change from baseline to 12 months in Short Form Health Survey. The within patient mean change from baseline to 6 months in Short Form Health Survey. Two summary scores are derived; the Physical component scale and the Mental component scale, each on a scale of 0-100, where the higher the score, the better the health.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Numeric Pain scale change from baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline to 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>The within patient mean change from baseline to 6 months in Numeric Pain scale, where 0=no pain and 10=worst possible pain.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Numeric Pain scale change from baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline to 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>The within patient mean change from baseline to 12 months in Numeric Pain scale, where 0=no pain and 10=worst possible pain.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Single Assessment Numeric Evaluation improvement rating-modified</measure>
    <time_frame>Mean at 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Mean improvement scores at 6 months, where -100=100% worse from baseline and 100=100% better or improved from baseline.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Single Assessment Numeric Evaluation improvement rating-modified</measure>
    <time_frame>Mean at 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Mean improvement scores at 12 months, where -100=100% worse from baseline and 100=100% better or improved from baseline.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>Thru 12 months post-procedure</time_frame>
    <description>Any complication or adverse event</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>C1-C2 overhang</measure>
    <time_frame>At least 6 months post-procedure</time_frame>
    <description>Post-op DMX studies to quantify any reduction in C1-C2 overhang or ADI.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">0</enrollment>
  <condition>Craniocervical Injuries</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Alar treatment with BMC</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients with CCJ instability that receive Alar treatment with BMC using anterior approach.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Alar treatment with BMC using anterior approach</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients with CCJ instability will undergo a bone marrow aspiration of approximately 30-60 cc. Platelet rich plasma (PRP) and platelet lysate (PL) will be derived from the bone marrow aspirate and later mixed with the bone marrow cell layer. While under TIVA anesthesia, the injectate is then injected under fluoroscopy into the area in need of treatment using an anterior approach through the posterior oropharynx with direct visualization of the injection site via endoscopy. The alar, transverse, and accessory ligaments are the target areas to be treated with the bone marrow concentrate.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Alar treatment with BMC</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients seeking treatment at an orthopedic pain management and regenerative medicine
        clinic.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  1) Voluntary signature of the IRB approved Informed Consent, 2) Skeletally mature Male
             or Female ages 18 to 65 3) Disabling symptoms of headache, dizziness, neck pain, or
             other neuro-musculoskeletal symptoms, that based on physical exam or diagnostic blocks
             is attributable to the upper cervical spine for &gt;12 months 4) Symptoms exacerbated by
             activity and relieved by rest 5) Failed all conservative care 6) Hasn't responded
             long-term to:

               1. C0-C3 facet injections

               2. Upper cervical prolotherapy or PRP into the posterior stabilizing ligaments
                  (nuchal, supraspinous, interspinous ligaments) 7) Considered a likely cervical
                  fusion candidate 8) Imaging (one of the three)

               1. Upper cervical MRI showing decreased signal in alar, transverse, PAOM, AAOM, or
                  Tectorial membrane

               2. DMX showing 2 mm or greater lateral overhang of C1 on C2 in lateral bending open
                  mouth view or a V shaped ADI in flexion of increased ADI in flexion

               3. Upper cervical rotatory CT that shows excessive C0-C1 rotation 9) Exam is c/w
                  upper cervical injury (i.e. tenderness along upper cervical facet joints and/or
                  musculature/skull base, good anesthetic block response (&gt;50% pain relief) to
                  C0-C3 intra-articular facet injections, proprioceptive difficulties) 10) Is
                  independent, ambulatory, and can comply with all post-operative evaluations and
                  visits 11) Patient states strong desire to avoid surgery

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  1) Unable to tolerate injections due to central sensitization (i.e. significant
             intolerance to manual therapy such as massage, activity such as physical therapy, or
             an exaggerated pain response to prior injection therapy)

             2) Previous neck surgery that has caused chronic neck pain or radiculopathy 3) Prior
             epidural or other milligram dose steroid injection in any area or other neck injection
             therapy within the past 6 months 4) Physical infirmity that is incompatible with the
             procedure and/or anesthesia required for same 5) Unable to tolerate the injection
             position 6) Abnormal anatomy seen on MRI imaging that would make the procedure higher
             risk (e.g. congenital atlanto-axial fusion, atlas assimilation, upper cervical
             fracture or surgical fusion)

             7) Inflammatory or auto-immune based pathology (e.g., rheumatoid arthritis, systemic
             lupus erythematosus, psoriatic arthritis, polymyalgia, polymyositis, gout, pseudo
             gout) 8) Quinolone or Statin induced myopathy/tendinopathy

             9) Condition represents a worker's compensation case 10) Currently involved in a
             health-related litigation procedure 11) Is pregnant 12) Bleeding disorders 13)
             Currently taking anticoagulant or immunosuppressive medication 14) Allergy or
             intolerance to study medication 15) Use of and significant physical dependence on a
             chronic opioid (&gt;20 mg oxycodone equivalent per day) 16) Documented history of drug
             abuse within six months of treatment 17) Any other condition, that in the opinion of
             the investigator, that would preclude the patient from enrollment
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Christopher Centeno, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Centeno-Schultz Clinic</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Centeno-Schultz Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Broomfield</city>
        <state>Colorado</state>
        <zip>80021</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Centeno CJ, Elliott J, Elkins WL, Freeman M. Fluoroscopically guided cervical prolotherapy for instability with blinded pre and post radiographic reading. Pain Physician. 2005 Jan;8(1):67-72.</citation>
    <PMID>16850045</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Panjabi MM, Crisco JJ 3rd, Lydon C, Dvorak J. The mechanical properties of human alar and transverse ligaments at slow and fast extension rates. Clin Biomech (Bristol, Avon). 1998 Mar;13(2):112-120.</citation>
    <PMID>11415778</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rajwanshi A, Rohilla M, Singh P. Trans-oral fine needle aspiration cytology in cervical (C1 and C2) vertebral lesions: a novel diagnostic approach. Cytopathology. 2017 Feb;28(1):31-34. doi: 10.1111/cyt.12361. Epub 2016 Aug 3.</citation>
    <PMID>27489015</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Centeno CJ, Pitts J, Al-Sayegh H, Freeman MD. Anterior cruciate ligament tears treated with percutaneous injection of autologous bone marrow nucleated cells: a case series. J Pain Res. 2015 Jul 31;8:437-47. doi: 10.2147/JPR.S86244. eCollection 2015.</citation>
    <PMID>26261424</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 9, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 4, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 15, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 29, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 29, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 2, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>CCJ</keyword>
  <keyword>Bone Marrow Concentrate</keyword>
  <keyword>Stem Cell Therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Alar Ligament</keyword>
  <keyword>Transverse Ligament</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Trauma, Nervous System</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Wounds and Injuries</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

