<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03553888</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PO18056</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03553888</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Hidradenitis Suppurativa and Periodontal Diseases</brief_title>
  <acronym>HSPDA</acronym>
  <official_title>Relationship Between Hidradenitis Suppurativa and Periodontal Diseases</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>CHU de Reims</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Association Française pour la Recherche sur l'Hidrosadénite (Financial sponsor)</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Association Française d'épargne et de retraite (Financial sponsor)</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>CHU de Reims</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Hidradenitis suppurativa or Verneuil's disease (HS) is a neglected and often overlooked
      chronic inflammatory skin disease. Nevertheless, it is frequent (1% of the general
      population) and deeply affects quality of life in patients with moderate and severe forms of
      HS. This disease is characterized by the occurrence of deep, recurrent and painful nodules,
      progressing to abscess formation and suppuration. It is usually localized in the axillary,
      inguinal and anogenital areas. The pathogenesis of HS remains partly unknown but is probably
      multifactorial (inflammatory, genetic, infectious, etc.) and related to many risk factors
      (mostly smoking and obesity). An association can be found with other inflammatory diseases
      such as gastrointestinal and rheumatic diseases like Crohn's disease and spondylo-arthritis
      respectively.

      Periodontal diseases are a heterogeneous group of infectious diseases with an inflammatory
      component. Their clinical expression results in more or less rapid destruction of tooth
      supporting tissues. Without treatment, these lesions may progress ultimately to tooth
      exfoliation, the rate of disease progression being unevenly distributed in the population.
      Various epidemiological studies in France indicate that 12 to 13% of middle-aged adults have
      severe periodontal damage. In addition, a recent study shows that while 50% of adults in
      France are suffering from severe attachment loss, generalized forms are rare and about 10% of
      individuals seem to require special care. The bacterial factor is the main etiological factor
      of these diseases but their progression depends primarily on the host immune response and on
      modifying factors (genetic, systemic, environmental and behavioural). Some of these factors
      are identified such as uncontrolled diabetes, smoking, stress, etc.. Finally, it is well
      established that periodontal disease may also trigger the development of some systemic
      diseases such as diabetes.

      Thus, many common etiopathogenic factors between HS and periodontal diseases such as
      inflammatory components and tobacco are found. This is corroborated by observations collected
      from some patients with HS complaining of oral pain exacerbated during acute flares of HS.
      Hence the aim of this project is to clarify existing potential association between
      Hidradenitis suppurativa and periodontal diseases using a multicenter cross-sectional
      descriptive clinical approach.

      One hundred patients with HS will be included in the departments of dermatology at the
      University Hospital in Reims and at the Pasteur Institute in Paris. They will be compared
      with one hundred patients without HS recruited from &quot;general practice&quot; consultations in the
      departments of Odontology at the University Hospital in Reims and at Bretonneau Hospital in
      Paris.

      The severity of HS will be assessed with Hurley's score by the dermatologist. The periodontal
      status will be evaluated with clinical indices and radiographical parameters by a
      periodontist according to the &quot;Armitage&quot; classification of periodontal disease and to CDC-AA
      case definitions updated in 2012. Meanwhile, human saliva is a biological fluid taken to
      reflect the health status of an individual and is or may be used for diagnosis and prognosis
      of some oral cancers, some systemic diseases (type 2 diabetes, sarcoidosis, etc.) or
      periodontal diseases. The saliva will be collected and analysed by proteomics and
      metabolomics techniques in order to identify biomarkers for diagnosis and prognostic of HS
      associated or not to periodontal diseases.

      These unpublished works could demonstrate a predisposition to develop periodontal disease in
      a subgroup of HS patients and help to unravel new etiopathogenic mechanisms common to both
      diseases as well as ultimately lead to early periodontal management in order to avoid disease
      progression and tooth losses.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The principal hypothesis of this project is the existence of an association between
      Hidradenitis suppurativa (HS) and periodontal diseases (PD).

      The primary objective is to evaluate this association using a multicenter cross-sectional
      clinical approach.

      The secondary objectives are:

        -  To study the association between the severity of PD and the severity of HS.

        -  To search, using saliva collected from a population with clinical signs of HS and from
           no HS population, proteomic and metabolomic biosignatures by liquid chromatography
           tandem-mass spectrometry (LC-MS), by vibrational spectroscopies and by 1H-NMR
           spectroscopy.

        -  To compare vibrational biosignatures from saliva from patients with and without HS and /
           or MP to determine a unique salivary spectral profile of HS patients with and without
           PD.

        -  To compare the relevance of vibrational spectroscopy versus that of LC-MS and LC-MS / MS
           and 1H-NMR in the analysis of salivary markers identified from an overall non-targeted
           spectroscopy profile.

        -  To analyse and to compare proteomic and metabolomic biosignatures of unstimulated saliva
           samples depending on the severity of HS.

      Will be included patients with HS (regardless of Hurley score) followed in the dermatology
      department of Reims University Hospital or the Institut Pasteur in Paris, and patients
      without HS from the service Odontology of the University Hospital of Reims or the Bretonneau
      Hospital (Paris) (whatever the reason for consultation), even also from the dermatology
      departments.

      One hundred patients with HS will be included. At the same time, 100 patients without HS will
      be also included. Subjects without HS will be matched to subjects with HS on age (± 5 years).
      Given the percentage of non-HS patients for whom periodontal disease will be diagnosed
      (approximately 40%), this included number of patients will demonstrate an odds ratio of 2.6
      (ie a percentage of patients with periodontal disease of 63% in the group with HS) with an α
      risk of 5% and a power of 90%.

      The primary endpoint is the presence of periodontal disease in both patients with HS and
      without HS.

      Diagnostic of periodontal disease will be posed in consultation by a periodontist and will be
      determined by clinical and radiographic assessments including in this research context:

      i. Gingival bleeding (Bleeding on Probing, BOP) ii. Depth of periodontal pockets using a
      calibrated periodontal probe iii. Clinical attachment loss iiii. Interproximal bone loss.
      Bone loss will be taken in consideration when the distance between the alveolar ridge and the
      cement-enamel junction will be ≥ 2mm. A digital orthopantomogram will be performed with or
      without six retroalveolar X-rays of Ramfjord teeth.

      Considering the bacterial etiology of periodontal diseases, it is important to note the
      amount of dental plaque directly in relation with the oral hygiene level performed with the
      dichotomous index &quot;Plaque Control Record&quot;.

      All these indexes will be assessed at six sites per tooth corresponding to a maximum of 168
      values per patient. The third molar was excluded from analysis. The reliability of clinical
      measurements intra and inter- periodontists was verified. In retrospect, the causes of tooth
      loss will be sought.

      The clinical diagnosis of HS will be based on the presence of recurrent abscesses in the
      folds, which can be multi-site, with residual scars according to the diagnosis criteria of
      European guidelines published in 2015.

      Secondary endpoints

        -  The severity of HS will be based on the score of Hurley.

        -  The extent and severity of PD, their progression will be posed according to the
           &quot;consensus&quot; classification of periodontal diseases (Armitage et al., 1999).
           Periodontitis cases were defined according to CDC-AAP case definitions updated in 2012
           (Eke et al., 2015).

        -  Semi-quantification and characterization of spectral biosignatures will be performed on
           saliva samples from patients with HS and non-HS patients.

      Thus, at least 5mL of unstimulated saliva will be collected from HS or non-HS patients. The
      pH will be measured. They will be frozen at -80°C before analysis by liquid chromatography
      tandem-mass spectrometry and vibrational spectroscopies and, at -20°C by 1H-NMR spectroscopy.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 7, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 7, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 7, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Other</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Cross-Sectional</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentatge of peridontal disease in each groupe</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 0</time_frame>
    <description>Peridontal disease will be diagnosed based on clinical and radiographic examination</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 0</time_frame>
    <description>Socio-demographic data (age, sex, etc.) and clinical data (medical history, skin symptoms, etc.) will be collected for all patients included in the study.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Salivary collection</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 0</time_frame>
    <description>During the periodontal consultation</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Salivary proteomic and metabolomic biosignatures in each group</measure>
    <time_frame>Month 6</time_frame>
    <description>These will be investigated using spectroscopy and liquid chromatography coupled with tandem mass spectrometry</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">200</enrollment>
  <condition>Hidradenitis Suppurativa</condition>
  <condition>Periodontal Diseases</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>HS patient</arm_group_label>
    <description>patients with HS</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>no HS patients</arm_group_label>
    <description>patients without HS</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Will be included in the study as HS-patients who:

          -  Have a HS (regardless of the Hurley score) according to the criteria of EU Guidelines
             on the HS.

          -  Are followed-up in departments of dermatology in Reims University Hospital or at
             Pasteur Institute in Paris.

          -  Are older than 18 years.

          -  Signed the informed consent form to take part in the study.

          -  Are affiliated to a social insurance.

        Will be included in the study as no-HS patients who:

          -  Are not suffering from HS. Are followed-up in departments of odontology in Reims or at
             Bretonneau hospital in Paris (regardless of the reason for consultation), even also
             from the dermatology departments.

          -  Are older than 18 years.

          -  Signed the informed consent form to take part in the study.

          -  Are affiliated to a social insurance.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Will be included in the study as HS-patients who:

          -  Have a HS (regardless of the Hurley score) according to the criteria of EU Guidelines
             on the HS.

          -  Are followed-up in departments of dermatology in Reims University Hospital or at
             Pasteur Institute in Paris.

          -  Are older than 18 years.

          -  Signed the informed consent form to take part in the study.

          -  Are affiliated to a social insurance.

        Will be included in the study as no-HS patients who:

          -  Are not suffering from HS. Are followed-up in departments of odontology in Reims or at
             Bretonneau hospital in Paris (regardless of the reason for consultation), even also
             from the dermatology departments.

          -  Are older than 18 years.

          -  Signed the informed consent form to take part in the study.

          -  Are affiliated to a social insurance.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Are suffering from a systemic disease or condition known to have an impact on
             periodontal level (leukemia, Down syndrome, uncontrolled diabetes, etc.).

          -  Are pregnant or lactating: these will be excluded because of the changes of
             periodontal status associated with pregnancy.

          -  Have a history of periodontal treatment of less than 3 months.

          -  Show an infectious risk contraindicating periodontal probing (considered as an
             invasive act because of the induced bacteremia). ANDEM and the Consensus Conference of
             2011 identified these patients.

          -  Are under medication known to cause changes in the gingival level as drug gingival
             hypertrophy including sodium diphenylhydantoïne, nifedipine, ciclosporin A.

          -  Are protected by law.

        Exposed and unexposed patients having periodontal disease known before inclusion can take
        part in this research protocol.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Sandrine LORIMIER</last_name>
    <phone>03 26 78 90 83</phone>
    <email>sandrine.lorimier@univ-reims.fr</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Stéphane DERRUAU</last_name>
    <email>sderruau@chu-reims.fr</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Damien JOLLY</name>
      <address>
        <city>Reims</city>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sandrine LORIMIER (GRESPI, EA4694, Reims)</last_name>
      <phone>03 26 78 90 83</phone>
      <email>sandrine.lorimier@univ-reims.fr</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Stéphane DERRUAU (Biospect, EA7506; Oral Medicine Department,Reims)</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Manuelle VIGUIER (Department of Dermatology, Reims)</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Yohann RENARD (Department of surgery, Reims)</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Aude NASSIF (Institut Pasteur, Paris)</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Dominique GUEZ (Department of Odontology, Hôpital Bretonneau; Paris)</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Maia DELAGE-TORIEL (Institut Pasteur, Paris)</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>April 16, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 30, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 12, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 24, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 24, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 26, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Hidradenitis Suppurativa</keyword>
  <keyword>Periodontal diseases</keyword>
  <keyword>Multicenter cross-sectional study</keyword>
  <keyword>Vibrational spectroscopies</keyword>
  <keyword>Salivary biomarkers</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hidradenitis Suppurativa</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Periodontal Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hidradenitis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

