<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03558048</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>STU00207583</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03558048</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Effect of IBD Flares on Serum PSA</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Effect of Inflammatory Bowel Disease Flares on Serum Prostate Specific Antigen</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Northwestern University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Northwestern University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will measure Prostate Specific Antigen (PSA) values in men with Inflammatory Bowel
      Disease (IBD) before, during, and following a flare. In addition, the effect of any PSA
      increase will be analyzed and correlated to the location of disease (rectal vs. other). Study
      findings may help men with IBD by identifying pitfalls in prostate cancer screening for this
      population and help to stratify and understand the effect IBD has on the prostatic milieu. By
      optimizing how men with IBD are screened for prostate cancer, future unnecessary healthcare
      encounters and expenditures may be reduced for this patient group.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Over one million adults in the U.S. are estimated to suffer from Inflammatory Bowel Disease
      (IBD), accounting for more than 2 million ambulatory and emergency room visits annually. This
      healthcare utilization may lead to an average increase of $5,000-$8,000 in annual medical
      expenditure per patient. Reducing unnecessary medical interactions and expenditures in this
      patient group is paramount and requires individualized disease monitoring and healthcare
      screening

      One screening test that may lead to additional exams and costs is the Prostate Specific
      Antigen (PSA) test used to screen for prostate cancer. While PSA screening can reduce
      prostate cancer mortality, false-positive elevations are common, especially in the setting of
      non-malignant prostate inflammation. This research group recently reported in a large
      retrospective case-control series that after age 65, men with IBD who underwent prostate
      cancer screening at Northwestern Memorial Hospital (NMH) had higher serum PSA values than
      non-IBD controls. In addition, men with IBD had a significantly higher risk of clinically
      significant prostate cancer even when controlling for differences in PSA and other relevant
      covariates. However, whether the elevation in PSA is related to inflammation in these men
      with IBD versus a true reflection of an increased risk of prostate cancer is unclear.
      Furthermore, the interplay of IBD status and screening PSA values is currently unknown.

      This study will measure PSA values in men with IBD before, during, and following a flare. In
      addition, the effect of any PSA increase will be analyzed and correlated to the location of
      disease (rectal vs. other). Study findings may help men with IBD by identifying pitfalls in
      prostate cancer screening for this population and help to stratify and understand the effect
      IBD has on the prostatic milieu. By optimizing how men with IBD are screened for prostate
      cancer, future unnecessary healthcare encounters and expenditures may be reduced for this
      patient group.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">August 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 1, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 1, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Relationship between IBD and PSA</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Measure PSA values in men with IBD before, during, and following a flare</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Location of disease</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Analyze and correlate PSA increase with location of disease</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">400</enrollment>
  <condition>Inflammatory Bowel Diseases</condition>
  <condition>Prostate Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Men with Inflammatory Bowel Disease</arm_group_label>
    <description>Men with a confirmed diagnosis of IBD between the ages of 40-69 years old. These subjects will have their prostate specific antigen checked via a blood draw during clinic visits over the course of the study period.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Blood draw</intervention_name>
    <description>Subjects will have their blood drawn during clinic visits over the course of the study period to measure their serum prostate specific antigen levels.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Men with Inflammatory Bowel Disease</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        This study will include men ages 40 to 69 presenting to the Northwestern Memorial Hospital
        Gastroenterology Clinic with a diagnosis of IBD. Men with a history of prostate cancer or
        prior prostate procedures (transurethral resection or biopsies) will be excluded.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Men, ages 40-69 years old

          -  Confirmed diagnosis of IBD presenting to the Northwestern Memorial Hospital
             Gastroenterology Clinic

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  History of prostate cancer or prior prostate procedures (biopsies or transurethral
             resection)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>40 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>69 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Shilajit Kundu, MD</last_name>
    <phone>312-695-8146</phone>
    <email>shilajit.kundu@nm.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Faizan Khawaja, BS</last_name>
    <phone>312-694-2417</phone>
    <email>urology@northwestern.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kappelman MD, Moore KR, Allen JK, Cook SF. Recent trends in the prevalence of Crohn's disease and ulcerative colitis in a commercially insured US population. Dig Dis Sci. 2013 Feb;58(2):519-25. doi: 10.1007/s10620-012-2371-5. Epub 2012 Aug 29.</citation>
    <PMID>22926499</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ananthakrishnan AN, McGinley EL, Saeian K, Binion DG. Trends in ambulatory and emergency room visits for inflammatory bowel diseases in the United States: 1994-2005. Am J Gastroenterol. 2010 Feb;105(2):363-70. doi: 10.1038/ajg.2009.580. Epub 2009 Oct 6.</citation>
    <PMID>19809414</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kappelman MD, Rifas-Shiman SL, Porter CQ, Ollendorf DA, Sandler RS, Galanko JA, Finkelstein JA. Direct health care costs of Crohn's disease and ulcerative colitis in US children and adults. Gastroenterology. 2008 Dec;135(6):1907-13. doi: 10.1053/j.gastro.2008.09.012. Epub 2008 Sep 17.</citation>
    <PMID>18854185</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Oesterling JE, Jacobsen SJ, Chute CG, Guess HA, Girman CJ, Panser LA, Lieber MM. Serum prostate-specific antigen in a community-based population of healthy men. Establishment of age-specific reference ranges. JAMA. 1993 Aug 18;270(7):860-4.</citation>
    <PMID>7688054</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>July 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 5, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 5, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 15, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 2, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 2, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 5, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Northwestern University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Shilajit Kundu</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor of Medicine - Urology</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Prostate Specific Antigen</keyword>
  <keyword>IBD</keyword>
  <keyword>PSA</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Intestinal Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Inflammatory Bowel Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>There are no plans at this time to share individual participant data with other researchers. All patient identifying data will be removed prior to transfer to a statistician. No individual research subject will be identified in any reports from the study which will be statistical in nature.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

