<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02025530</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>GN2156</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02025530</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Midlands and North of England Stillbirth Study</brief_title>
  <acronym>MiNESS</acronym>
  <official_title>The Midlands and North of England Stillbirth Study - A Case-Control Study of Modifiable Factors in Late Stillbirth</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Manchester</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Manchester</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The United Kingdom has one of the highest rates of stillbirth in Europe, with more than 4,000
      stillbirths every year; which equates to more than 11 deaths every day. Furthermore, this
      rate has changed very little over the last 20 years. This loss of life and the adverse
      psychological consequences urgently needs addressing.

      A recent New Zealand study investigating modifiable factors associated with stillbirth (the
      Auckland Stillbirth Study) found that mothers who did not go to sleep on their left side had
      a twofold risk of late stillbirth (≥28 weeks gestation) compared to mothers who did go to
      sleep on their left side. These novel findings need urgent confirmation.

      This proposed study aims to confirm or refute these findings and to ascertain whether a
      preventative programme should be introduced. This proposed study aims to confirm or refute
      the findings of the Auckland Stillbirth Study.

      Participants will be recruited from maternity units in the Midlands and North of England (led
      by centres in Liverpool, Manchester, West Yorkshire and Birmingham). 291 women with a
      singleton late stillbirth without congenital abnormality will be interviewed by research
      midwives shortly after the birth. A control group of 580 women with ongoing pregnancies will
      be interviewed at a gestation group matched to that at which stillbirths occurred. These data
      will determine whether an intervention study should be considered. If there is a causal
      relationship between maternal sleep position and late stillbirth we estimate that upto 37% of
      late stillbirths might be prevented.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The death of an unborn child is a prevalent and tragic public health problem which currently
      affects millions of families worldwide. Late stillbirth (at or beyond 28 weeks of gestation)
      is one of the few potentially avoidable maternal and child health problems where the rate of
      decline in high income countries has slowed in recent decades [1]. The United Kingdom
      currently has one of the highest rates of stillbirth in Europe, ranking 33rd out of 35 high
      income countries.

      The variations in stillbirth rates between high income countries suggest that it should be
      possible to make further reductions in late stillbirths. The estimated annual reduction in
      rates of late stillbirth over recent decades is about 1.1% [1], compared to 2.1% for neonatal
      death rates, with a resultant increase in the proportion of perinatal deaths (stillbirths
      plus neonatal deaths) attributable to stillbirth [2]. The Lancet Stillbirth Series [1, 3, 4]
      has highlighted the silent but prevalent public health problem of stillbirth and together
      with Sands and the Royal College Of Obstetricians and Gynaecologists has called for research
      to address these unacceptably high rates.

      Current established risk factors for late stillbirth in high income countries include:
      advanced maternal age (&gt;35 years) [5], high pre-pregnancy body mass index (BMI) [6], smoking
      [7], reduced antenatal care attendance [8], low socioeconomic status [8] and small for
      gestational age (SGA) infants [9]. A meta-analysis of population based studies addressing
      risk factors for stillbirth found that the three most important modifiable risk factors were
      overweight and obesity (population attributable risk 818%) advanced maternal age (population
      attributable risk 68%), and smoking (population attributable risk 47%) [3]. Of these only,
      cigarette smoking may be realistically addressed after pregnancy has started. There has been
      limited research investigating the role of novel, modifiable factors which have the potential
      to advance knowledge and address the important gaps in the field of stillbirth research.

      This study aims to explore modifiable risk factors for late stillbirth in the UK and to
      substantiate the recent identification of a new modifiable risk factor for unexpected late
      pregnancy stillbirths. In the Auckland Stillbirth Study [10] our New Zealand collaborators
      discovered an approximately two-fold increase in late stillbirth with non-left sided maternal
      sleep position on the night before the baby died. In addition, women who did not get up at
      night and those who slept during the day were also at increased risk of stillbirth. The
      strength of this primary finding was unanticipated and now maternal sleep position requires
      urgent, rigorous evaluation in another population. MiNESS aims to address these factors.

      This multi-centered case control study will recruit 291 women who have experienced a late
      (≥28 weeks gestation) matched with 580 women who have a continuing pregnancy at the same
      gestation (controls). The women will be interviewed by an experienced research midwife and an
      in depth questionnaire will be completed.

      Analysis will be carried out using the standard Mantel-Haenszel odds ratio analysis used in
      case-control studies. Unconditional logistic regression will be used to adjust for potential
      confounders and to determine the presence of interactions.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">April 1, 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 31, 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 31, 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Control</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Maternal Sleep Practices During Pregnancy</measure>
    <time_frame>One night prior to questionnaire</time_frame>
    <description>Self-reported going to sleep position in late pregnancy</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Maternal Perception of Fetal Activity</measure>
    <time_frame>Two weeks prior to stillbirth / interview</time_frame>
    <description>Maternal Perception of Fetal Activity reported via the researcher-administered questionnaire.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">1030</enrollment>
  <condition>Stillbirth</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cases</arm_group_label>
    <description>A structured questionnaire will be administered to women who have experienced a late ≥ 28 weeks gestation stillbirth, who have a singleton pregnancy with no congenital abnormality.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Controls</arm_group_label>
    <description>A structured questionnaire will be administered to controls. These are women matched to the case group by gestation and unit of birth, who have a normal ongoing singleton pregnancy with no congenital abnormality.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Questionnaire</intervention_name>
    <description>An indepth interview will be carried out and a structured questionnaire will be completed by both cases and controls</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cases</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Controls</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <biospec_retention>None Retained</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Hair
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        The sample will be recruited from maternity units in the Midlands and the North of England.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria: CASES

          -  Women who experience a stillbirth ≥28 weeks gestation in a participating unit.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Fetal death prior to 28 weeks gestation.

          -  Women who's babies have a significant congenital abnormality.

          -  Women with multiple pregnancy.

          -  Maternal age below 16 years.

          -  Women unable to give informed consent.

        Inclusion Criteria: CONTROLS

          -  Women with a normal pregnancy matched to gestation and unit of birth to the cases.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Pregnancy under 28 weeks gestation.

          -  Women who's babies have a significant congenital abnormality.

          -  Women with multiple pregnancy.

          -  Maternal age below 16 years.

          -  Women unable to give informed consent.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>16 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>50 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Tomasina Stacey</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Mid Yorkshire NHS Trust</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Edwin Mitchell</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Auckland, New Zealand</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Lesley McCowan</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Auckland, New Zealand</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Bill Martin</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Birmingham Women's Hospital NHS Foundation Trust</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Devender Roberts</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Liverpool Women's NHS Foundation Trust</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Liverpool Women's NHS Foundation Trust</name>
      <address>
        <city>Liverpool</city>
        <state>Merseyside</state>
        <zip>L8 7SS</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Birmingham Women's Hospital NHS Foundation Trust</name>
      <address>
        <city>Birmingham</city>
        <state>West Midlands</state>
        <zip>B15 2TG</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mid Yorkshire NHS Trust</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dewsbury</city>
        <state>Yorkshire</state>
        <zip>WF13 4HS</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Central Manchester University Hospitals NHS Foundation Trust</name>
      <address>
        <city>Manchester</city>
        <zip>M13 9WL</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cousens S, Blencowe H, Stanton C, Chou D, Ahmed S, Steinhardt L, Creanga AA, Tunçalp O, Balsara ZP, Gupta S, Say L, Lawn JE. National, regional, and worldwide estimates of stillbirth rates in 2009 with trends since 1995: a systematic analysis. Lancet. 2011 Apr 16;377(9774):1319-30. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(10)62310-0.</citation>
    <PMID>21496917</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rajaratnam JK, Marcus JR, Flaxman AD, Wang H, Levin-Rector A, Dwyer L, Costa M, Lopez AD, Murray CJ. Neonatal, postneonatal, childhood, and under-5 mortality for 187 countries, 1970-2010: a systematic analysis of progress towards Millennium Development Goal 4. Lancet. 2010 Jun 5;375(9730):1988-2008. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(10)60703-9. Epub 2010 May 27. Erratum in: Lancet. 2010 Aug 28;376(9742):686. Lancet. 2010 Jun 19;375(9732):2142.</citation>
    <PMID>20546887</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Flenady V, Koopmans L, Middleton P, Frøen JF, Smith GC, Gibbons K, Coory M, Gordon A, Ellwood D, McIntyre HD, Fretts R, Ezzati M. Major risk factors for stillbirth in high-income countries: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Lancet. 2011 Apr 16;377(9774):1331-40. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(10)62233-7. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21496916</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Frøen JF, Cacciatore J, McClure EM, Kuti O, Jokhio AH, Islam M, Shiffman J; Lancet's Stillbirths Series steering committee. Stillbirths: why they matter. Lancet. 2011 Apr 16;377(9774):1353-66. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(10)62232-5. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21496915</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rasmussen S, Albrechtsen S, Irgens LM, Dalaker K, Maartmann-Moe H, Vlatkovic L, Markestad T. Risk factors for unexplained antepartum fetal death in Norway 1967-1998. Early Hum Dev. 2003 Feb;71(1):39-52.</citation>
    <PMID>12614949</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Stephansson O, Dickman PW, Johansson A, Cnattingius S. Maternal weight, pregnancy weight gain, and the risk of antepartum stillbirth. Am J Obstet Gynecol. 2001 Feb;184(3):463-9.</citation>
    <PMID>11228504</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wisborg K, Kesmodel U, Henriksen TB, Olsen SF, Secher NJ. Exposure to tobacco smoke in utero and the risk of stillbirth and death in the first year of life. Am J Epidemiol. 2001 Aug 15;154(4):322-7.</citation>
    <PMID>11495855</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Huang DY, Usher RH, Kramer MS, Yang H, Morin L, Fretts RC. Determinants of unexplained antepartum fetal deaths. Obstet Gynecol. 2000 Feb;95(2):215-21.</citation>
    <PMID>10674582</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cnattingius S, Haglund B, Kramer MS. Differences in late fetal death rates in association with determinants of small for gestational age fetuses: population based cohort study. BMJ. 1998 May 16;316(7143):1483-7.</citation>
    <PMID>9582131</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Stacey T, Thompson JM, Mitchell EA, Ekeroma AJ, Zuccollo JM, McCowan LM. Association between maternal sleep practices and risk of late stillbirth: a case-control study. BMJ. 2011 Jun 14;342:d3403. doi: 10.1136/bmj.d3403.</citation>
    <PMID>21673002</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>October 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>December 20, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 27, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 1, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <results_first_submitted>December 3, 2018</results_first_submitted>
  <results_first_submitted_qc>April 30, 2019</results_first_submitted_qc>
  <results_first_posted type="Actual">July 15, 2019</results_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 9, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 9, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 11, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Manchester</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Dr Alexander Heazell</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Senior Clinical Lecturer in Obstetrics</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Stillbirth</keyword>
  <keyword>Modifiable risk factors</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Stillbirth</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>

  <clinical_results>

    <participant_flow>
      <recruitment_details>Participants were recruited between April 2014 and March 2016 from 41 maternity units around the United Kingdom.</recruitment_details>
      <pre_assignment_details>This was a case-control study, so participants were not assigned to a specific arm/group. 5 cases (women who had a stillbirth) were excluded prior to analysis because the baby was found to have a congenital anomaly at post-mortem examination. One control (women with a live baby at interview) was excluded because she had a stillborn baby.</pre_assignment_details>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="P1">
          <title>Cases</title>
          <description>A structured questionnaire was administered to women who have experienced a late ≥ 28 weeks gestation stillbirth, who have a singleton pregnancy with no congenital abnormality.
Questionnaire: An indepth interview will be carried out and a structured questionnaire will be completed by both cases and controls.
Clinical information was obtained from maternal case notes following the interview.</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="P2">
          <title>Controls</title>
          <description>A structured questionnaire was administered to controls. These are women matched to the case group by gestation and unit of birth, who have a normal ongoing singleton pregnancy with no congenital abnormality.
Questionnaire: An indepth interview will be carried out and a structured questionnaire will be completed by both cases and controls.
Clinical information was obtained from maternal case notes following the interview.</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <period_list>
        <period>
          <title>Overall Study</title>
          <milestone_list>
            <milestone>
              <title>STARTED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="296"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="734"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>COMPLETED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="291"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="733"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>NOT COMPLETED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="5"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="1"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
          </milestone_list>
          <drop_withdraw_reason_list>
            <drop_withdraw_reason>
              <title>No longer met elligibility criteria</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="5"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="1"/>
              </participants_list>
            </drop_withdraw_reason>
          </drop_withdraw_reason_list>
        </period>
      </period_list>
    </participant_flow>

    <baseline>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="B1">
          <title>Cases (Stillbirth)</title>
          <description>A structured questionnaire was administered to women who have experienced a late ≥ 28 weeks gestation stillbirth, who have a singleton pregnancy with no congenital abnormality.
Questionnaire: An indepth interview will be carried out and a structured questionnaire will be completed by both cases and controls.
Clinical information was obtained from maternal case notes following the interview.</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="B2">
          <title>Controls (Live Pregnancy)</title>
          <description>A structured questionnaire was administered to controls. These are women matched to the case group by gestation and unit of birth, who have a normal ongoing singleton pregnancy with no congenital abnormality.
Questionnaire: An indepth interview will be carried out and a structured questionnaire will be completed by both cases and controls.
Clinical information was obtained from maternal case notes following the interview.</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="B3">
          <title>Total</title>
          <description>Total of all reporting groups</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <analyzed_list>
        <analyzed>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <scope>Overall</scope>
          <count_list>
            <count group_id="B1" value="291"/>
            <count group_id="B2" value="733"/>
            <count group_id="B3" value="1024"/>
          </count_list>
        </analyzed>
      </analyzed_list>
      <measure_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Age</title>
          <units>years</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>Standard Deviation</dispersion>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="30.0" spread="5.9"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="30.4" spread="5.1"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="30.3" spread="5.3"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Sex: Female, Male</title>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <param>Count of Participants</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <title>Female</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="291"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="733"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="1024"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Male</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </measure_list>
    </baseline>

    <outcome_list>
      <outcome>
        <type>Primary</type>
        <title>Maternal Sleep Practices During Pregnancy</title>
        <description>Self-reported going to sleep position in late pregnancy</description>
        <time_frame>One night prior to questionnaire</time_frame>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Cases (Stillbirth)</title>
            <description>A structured questionnaire was administered to women who have experienced a late ≥ 28 weeks gestation stillbirth, who have a singleton pregnancy with no congenital abnormality.
Questionnaire: An indepth interview will be carried out and a structured questionnaire will be completed by both cases and controls.
Clinical information was obtained from maternal case notes following the interview.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>Controls (Live Pregnancy)</title>
            <description>A structured questionnaire was administered to controls. These are women matched to the case group by gestation and unit of birth, who have a normal ongoing singleton pregnancy with no congenital abnormality.
Questionnaire: An indepth interview will be carried out and a structured questionnaire will be completed by both cases and controls.
Clinical information was obtained from maternal case notes following the interview.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Maternal Sleep Practices During Pregnancy</title>
          <description>Self-reported going to sleep position in late pregnancy</description>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <param>Count of Participants</param>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="291"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="733"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <title>Left</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="140"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="383"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Right</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="73"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="220"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Back</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="19"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="24"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Tummy</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="3"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="4"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Propped</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="9"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="15"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Variable</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="32"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="76"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Unknown</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="15"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="11"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Secondary</type>
        <title>Maternal Perception of Fetal Activity</title>
        <description>Maternal Perception of Fetal Activity reported via the researcher-administered questionnaire.</description>
        <time_frame>Two weeks prior to stillbirth / interview</time_frame>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Cases (Stillbirth)</title>
            <description>A structured questionnaire was administered to women who have experienced a late ≥ 28 weeks gestation stillbirth, who have a singleton pregnancy with no congenital abnormality.
Questionnaire: An indepth interview will be carried out and a structured questionnaire will be completed by both cases and controls.
Clinical information was obtained from maternal case notes following the interview.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>Controls (Live Pregnancy)</title>
            <description>A structured questionnaire was administered to controls. These are women matched to the case group by gestation and unit of birth, who have a normal ongoing singleton pregnancy with no congenital abnormality.
Questionnaire: An indepth interview will be carried out and a structured questionnaire will be completed by both cases and controls.
Clinical information was obtained from maternal case notes following the interview.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Maternal Perception of Fetal Activity</title>
          <description>Maternal Perception of Fetal Activity reported via the researcher-administered questionnaire.</description>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <param>Count of Participants</param>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="291"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="733"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <title>In last 2 weeks did movements increase?</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="37"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="254"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>In last 2 weeks did movements decrease?</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="86"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="63"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Movements stayed the same</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="153"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="397"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Unsure</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="15"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="19"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Post-Hoc</type>
        <title>Screening for Gestational Diabetes and Fasting Plasma Glucose</title>
        <description>Performance of 75g oral glucose tolerance test and the results of glucose tolerance test in cases and controls</description>
        <time_frame>During index pregnancy</time_frame>
        <population>Women were excluded from this analysis if they had pre-existing diabetes. Women should have been screened using oral glucose tolerance test if they had a positive family history, were of South Asian or Black Caribbean ethnicity, had a body mass index ≥ 30 kg/m2, or previous pregnancy effected by GDM or macrosomic (birthweight ≥4.5 kg) birth.</population>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Cases (Stillbirth)</title>
            <description>A structured questionnaire was administered to women who have experienced a late ≥ 28 weeks gestation stillbirth, who have a singleton pregnancy with no congenital abnormality.
Questionnaire: An indepth interview will be carried out and a structured questionnaire will be completed by both cases and controls.
Clinical information was obtained from maternal case notes following the interview.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>Controls (Live Pregnancy)</title>
            <description>A structured questionnaire was administered to controls. These are women matched to the case group by gestation and unit of birth, who have a normal ongoing singleton pregnancy with no congenital abnormality.
Questionnaire: An indepth interview will be carried out and a structured questionnaire will be completed by both cases and controls.
Clinical information was obtained from maternal case notes following the interview.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Screening for Gestational Diabetes and Fasting Plasma Glucose</title>
          <description>Performance of 75g oral glucose tolerance test and the results of glucose tolerance test in cases and controls</description>
          <population>Women were excluded from this analysis if they had pre-existing diabetes. Women should have been screened using oral glucose tolerance test if they had a positive family history, were of South Asian or Black Caribbean ethnicity, had a body mass index ≥ 30 kg/m2, or previous pregnancy effected by GDM or macrosomic (birthweight ≥4.5 kg) birth.</population>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <param>Count of Participants</param>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="283"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="729"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>Women screened by Oral Glucose Tolerance Test</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="94"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="277"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Proportion Diagnosed with GDM</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="6"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="30"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
    </outcome_list>

    <reported_events>
      <time_frame>For the duration of participation in the study (e.g. from recruitment until pregnancy outcome for participants in the control arm). As this was an observational study no SAEs were attributed to completion of the maternal questionnaire.</time_frame>
      <desc>Stillbirth was not recorded as an adverse event in the case group because it was an entry criteria for the study.</desc>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="E1">
          <title>Cases (Stillbirth)</title>
          <description>A structured questionnaire was administered to women who have experienced a late ≥ 28 weeks gestation stillbirth, who have a singleton pregnancy with no congenital abnormality.
Questionnaire: An indepth interview will be carried out and a structured questionnaire will be completed by both cases and controls.
Clinical information was obtained from maternal case notes following the interview.</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="E2">
          <title>Controls (Live Pregnancy)</title>
          <description>A structured questionnaire was administered to controls. These are women matched to the case group by gestation and unit of birth, who have a normal ongoing singleton pregnancy with no congenital abnormality.
Questionnaire: An indepth interview will be carried out and a structured questionnaire will be completed by both cases and controls.
Clinical information was obtained from maternal case notes following the interview.</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <serious_events>
        <category_list>
          <category>
            <title>Total</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, all-cause mortality</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="296"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="734"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, serious adverse events</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="296"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="734"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
        </category_list>
      </serious_events>
      <other_events>
        <frequency_threshold>0</frequency_threshold>
        <category_list>
          <category>
            <title>Total</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, other adverse events</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="296"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="734"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
        </category_list>
      </other_events>
    </reported_events>

    <certain_agreements>
      <pi_employee>All Principal Investigators ARE employed by the organization sponsoring the study.</pi_employee>
      <restrictive_agreement>There is NOT an agreement between Principal Investigators and the Sponsor (or its agents) that restricts the PI's rights to discuss or publish trial results after the trial is completed. </restrictive_agreement>
    </certain_agreements>
    <point_of_contact>
      <name_or_title>Professor Alexander Heazell</name_or_title>
      <organization>University of Manchester</organization>
      <phone>+441612766484</phone>
      <email>alexander.heazell@manchester.ac.uk</email>
    </point_of_contact>
  </clinical_results>
</clinical_study>

