<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04166487</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>19-523</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04166487</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Plasma-Adapted First-Line Pembro In NSCLC</brief_title>
  <official_title>Pilot Study of Serial Plasma Genotyping to Guide the Adaptive Treatment of Advanced NSCLC Receiving First-line Pembrolizumab</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Dana-Farber Cancer Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Inivata</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Dana-Farber Cancer Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This research study is studying to see if a blood test, collected at different times during
      the treatment of metastatic non-small lung cancer, can be used to detect early response in
      patients being treated with pembrolizumab and use that information to determine whether
      patients should continue treatment with pembrolizumab or switch treatment to pembrolizumab in
      combination with chemotherapy.

      The names of the study drugs involved in this study are:

        -  Pembrolizumab

        -  Platinum doublet chemotherapy, which may include the following:

             -  Carboplatin and pemetrexed

             -  Carboplatin and paclitaxel

      The name of the blood test:

      - InVision (Inivata, Ltd.)
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is an open label, single institution, prospective pilot study.

      The purpose of this research study is to determine if a blood test, collected at different
      times during treatment, can be used to detect early response in patients being treated with
      pembrolizumab for lung cancer and use that information to determine whether patients should
      continue treatment with pembrolizumab or switch treatment to pembrolizumab in combination
      with chemotherapy.

      -The research study procedures include screening for eligibility and study treatment
      including evaluations approximately every 3 weeks.

      The names of the study drugs involved in this study are:

        -  Pembrolizumab

        -  Platinum doublet chemotherapy, which may include the following:

             -  Carboplatin and pemetrexed

             -  Carboplatin and paclitaxel

      The name of the blood test:

        -  InVision- Inivata

             -  This blood test that will help study how participants respond to the study
                treatment. ---

             -  Blood will be collected for this test at a few time points, both before and after
                participants receive treatment on study.

        -  Participants will be on the research study for up to 12 months.

        -  It is expected that about 40 people will take part in this research study.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 13, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 1, 2025</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 1, 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Sequential Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>6-month Progression Free Survival rate</measure>
    <time_frame>6 Months</time_frame>
    <description>Kaplan-Meier method</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Early Plasma Response</measure>
    <time_frame>42 Days (each cycle is 21 days)</time_frame>
    <description>Early plasma response is defined as ≥50% reduction in plasma ctDNA max AF between Cycle 1 Day 1 and Cycle 2 Day 1 for patients with high shed [≥0.5% max AF] at Cycle 1 Day 1, or persistent low shed [&lt;0.5% max AF] for patients with low shed at Cycle 1 Day 1.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression Free Survival</measure>
    <time_frame>he time from registration to the earlier of progression or death due to any cause or 30 Months</time_frame>
    <description>Kaplan-Meier method will be used to estimate event-time distributions and medians for time-to-event data</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall Survival</measure>
    <time_frame>time from registration to death from any cause, and patients who are thought to be alive at the time of final analysis will be censored at the last date of contact or 30 months</time_frame>
    <description>Kaplan-Meier method will be used to estimate event-time distributions and medians for time-to-event data</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Feasibility-adherence to protocol therapy for 4 cycles</measure>
    <time_frame>84 Days (each cycle is 21 days)</time_frame>
    <description>Feasibility is defined as a patient's adherence to protocol therapy for 4 cycles</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>NSCLC Stage IV</condition>
  <condition>Metastatic Non-Small Cell Lung Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Pembrolizumab Cycles 1-2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>For the first two cycles, Pembrolizumab will be administered at a predetermined dose every 3 weeks.
InVision plasma draw will take place at Cycle 1 Day 1 and Cycle 2 Day 1, with return of results to the treating oncologist prior to Cycle 3 Day 1.
At Cycle 3, patients will be re-registered per the inclusion criteria into 3 arms;
PEMBROLIZUMAB Alone
PEMBROLIZUMAB + Doublet Chemotherapy</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Pembrolizumab Alone, Cycle 3+</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>- Following imaging assessment at Cycle 3, participants will continue pembrolizumab alone if the following responses are observed:
Response of Partial Response/Complete Response
Response of Stable Disease with plasma response
Response of Progressive Disease without worsening cancer symptoms AND plasma response</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Pembrolizumab + Doublet Chemotherapy, Cycles 3+</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Following imaging assessment at Cycle 3, participants will receive pembrolizumab in combination with platinum doublet chemotherapy if they have a response of stable disease without plasma response, OR no plasma response and response of progressive disease without worsening cancer systems. Platinum doublet should be histology-appropriate and will be given on-label, per treating oncologist.
PEMBROLIZUMAB
Chemotherapy multiple agents systemic
PEMETREXED
CARBOPLATIN
PACLITAXEL</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pembrolizumab</intervention_name>
    <description>predetermined dose, once per cycle via IV will be administered every 3 weeks, with 21 consecutive days defined as a treatment cycle.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Pembrolizumab + Doublet Chemotherapy, Cycles 3+</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Pembrolizumab Alone, Cycle 3+</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Pembrolizumab Cycles 1-2</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Keytruda®</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>PEMETREXED</intervention_name>
    <description>administered per standard practice, once per cycle via IV will be administered every 3 weeks, with 21 consecutive days defined as a treatment cycle.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Pembrolizumab + Doublet Chemotherapy, Cycles 3+</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Alimta®</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>CARBOPLATIN</intervention_name>
    <description>administered per standard practice once per cycle via IV will be administered every 3 weeks, with 21 consecutive days defined as a treatment cycle.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Pembrolizumab + Doublet Chemotherapy, Cycles 3+</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Paraplatin ®</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>PACLITAXEL</intervention_name>
    <description>administered per standard practice once per cycle via IV will be administered every 3 weeks, with 21 consecutive days defined as a treatment cycle.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Pembrolizumab + Doublet Chemotherapy, Cycles 3+</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Taxol®,</other_name>
    <other_name>Onxal</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>InVision</intervention_name>
    <description>Plasma draw for clinical test performed at C1D1 and C2D1; plasma draw for research testing performed at other timepoints per protocol.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Pembrolizumab Cycles 1-2</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        - Participants must have histologically or cytologically confirmed stage IV NSCLC (AJCC 8th
        edition).

        - Participants must have evaluable disease on imaging per RECIST (measurable disease is not
        required).

          -  No prior treatment with a systemic anti-cancer therapy of any kind for the treatment
             of stage IV NSCLC. Prior definitive chemoradiation for locally advanced disease, or
             prior adjuvant or neoadjuvant therapy for early stage disease is permitted if
             completed ≥6 months prior to initiating study treatment.

          -  Age ≥18 years.

          -  ECOG performance status 0-2 (see Appendix A)

          -  Candidate for combination chemoimmunotherapy per physician assessment.

          -  Participants must have normal organ and marrow function as defined below:

             -- absolute neutrophil count ≥1000/mcL

               -  platelets ≥100,000/mcL

               -  total bilirubin &lt;1.3 mg/dL

               -  creatinine &lt;1.6 mg/dL

          -  PD-L1 tumor proportion score (TPS) ≥1%, as determined by a CLIA-laboratory.

          -  The effects of pembrolizumab on the developing human fetus are unknown. For this
             reason and because immune checkpoint blockade agents as well as other therapeutic
             agents used in this trial are known to be teratogenic, women of child-bearing
             potential and men must agree to use adequate contraception (hormonal or barrier method
             of birth control; abstinence) prior to study entry and for the duration of study
             participation. Should a woman become pregnant or suspect she is pregnant while she or
             her partner is participating in this study, she should inform her treating physician
             immediately. Men treated or enrolled on this protocol must also agree to use adequate
             contraception prior to the study, for the duration of study participation, and 4
             months after completion of pembrolizumab administration.

             -- NOTE: a pregnancy test will be required at screening for women of childbearing
             potential.

          -  Ability to understand and the willingness to sign a written informed consent document.

          -  Inclusion Criteria for Treatment Continuation at Cycle 3 -- Completion of repeat
             plasma NGS (InVision) on study, with plasma response defined as ≥50% reduction in
             plasma ctDNA max AF between C1D1 and C2D1 for patients with high shed [≥0.5% max AF]
             at C1D1, or continued low shed [&lt;0.5% max AF] for patients with low shed at C1D1.

               -  Completion of restaging scans on study, with response determined by central
                  review per RECIST 1.1 criteria

               -  For participants continuing pembrolizumab alone:

                    -  Response of Partial Response or Complete Response at Cycle 3 imaging
                       assessment (as determined by TIMC).

        OR --- Response of Stable Disease at Cycle 3 imaging assessment (as determined by TIMC) AND
        plasma response.

        OR

          -  Response of Progressive Disease at Cycle 3 imaging assessment (as determined by TIMC)
             without worsening cancer symptoms (as determined by the treating investigator) AND
             plasma response.

             -- For participants continuing pembrolizumab + doublet chemotherapy:

          -  Response of Stable Disease at Cycle 3 imaging assessment (as determined by TIMC) AND
             no plasma response.

        OR --- Response of Progressive Disease at Cycle 3 imaging assessment (as determined by
        TIMC) without worsening cancer symptoms (as determined by the treating investigator) AND no
        plasma response.

        - NOTE: Patients with a response of Progressive Disease at Cycle 3 imaging assessment (as
        determined by TIMC) with worsening cancer symptoms (as determined by the treating
        investigator) must come off treatment.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Participants with known sensitizing alterations in EGFR, ALK, ROS1 or BRAF.

          -  Participants who have had chemotherapy or radiotherapy within 1 week prior to entering
             the study.

          -  Participants who are receiving any other investigational agents.

          -  Participants with uncontrolled brain metastases, leptomeningeal disease, or spinal
             cord compression. Patients with asymptomatic untreated brain metastases are eligible.
             Patients with treated CNS disease are eligible if stable disease is clinically
             confirmed ≥2 weeks after definitive CNS therapy (radiation or surgery), and the
             patient is not receiving systemic steroids ≥10mg of prednisone equivalent at the time
             of enrollment.

          -  History of allergic reactions attributed to compounds of similar chemical or biologic
             composition to pembrolizumab or other agents used in study.

          -  Ongoing or active autoimmune disease requiring systemic steroids of ≥10mg of
             prednisone equivalent or other systemic immunomodulatory agents at the time of
             enrollment. Type I diabetes mellitus, hypothyroidism only requiring hormone
             replacement, skin disorders (such as psoriasis, vitiligo, and alopecia) not requiring
             systemic therapy, or conditions not expected to recur in the absence of an external
             trigger are allowed.

          -  Uncontrolled intercurrent illness including, but not limited to, ongoing or active
             infection, symptomatic congestive heart failure, unstable angina pectoris, cardiac
             arrhythmia, or psychiatric illness/social situations that would limit compliance with
             study requirements.

          -  Pregnant women are excluded from this study because pembrolizumab is a Pregnancy
             Category D agent with the potential for teratogenic or abortifacient effects. Because
             there is an unknown but potential risk for adverse events in nursing infants secondary
             to treatment of the mother with pembrolizumab, breastfeeding should be discontinued if
             the mother is treated with pembrolizumab. These potential risks may also apply to
             other agents used in this study.

          -  Participants with a known history of testing positive for human immunodeficiency virus
             (HIV) or known acquired immunodeficiency syndrome (AIDS) are excluded from this study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Michael L Cheng, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Dana-Farber Cancer Institute</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Michael L Cheng, MD</last_name>
    <phone>michael_cheng@dfci.harvard.edu</phone>
    <email>michael_cheng@dfci.harvard.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Clinical Trials Hotline</last_name>
    <phone>877-338-7425</phone>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Brigham and Women's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02115</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Michael L Cheng, MD</last_name>
      <phone>877-338-7425</phone>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Michael L Cheng, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Dana Farber Cancer Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02115</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Michael L Cheng, MD</last_name>
      <phone>877-338-7425</phone>
      <email>michael_cheng@dfci.harvard.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Michael L Cheng, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Dana-Farber at Steward St. Elizabeth's Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Brighton</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02135</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Christopher Lathan, MD</last_name>
      <phone>617-789-2903</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Dana-Farber/Brigham and Women's Cancer Center (DF/BWCC) in clinical affiliation with South Shore Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>South Weymouth</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02190</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>David Dougherty, MD</last_name>
      <phone>781-624-4800</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 13, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 14, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">November 18, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 16, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 16, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 20, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Dana-Farber Cancer Institute</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Michael L. Cheng</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>NSCLC Stage IV</keyword>
  <keyword>Metastatic Non-Small Cell Lung Cancer</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Non-Small-Cell Lung</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Paclitaxel</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carboplatin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pembrolizumab</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pemetrexed</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>The Dana-Farber / Harvard Cancer Center encourages and supports the responsible and ethical sharing of data from clinical trials. De-identified participant data from the final research dataset used in the published manuscript may only be shared under the terms of a Data Use Agreement. Requests may be directed to Sponsor Investigator or designee. The protocol and statistical analysis plan will be made available on Clinicaltrials.gov only as required by federal regulation or as a condition of awards and agreements supporting the research.</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Statistical Analysis Plan (SAP)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Informed Consent Form (ICF)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>Data can be shared no earlier than 1 year following the date of publication</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>DFCI - Contact the Belfer Office for Dana-Farber Innovations (BODFI) at innovation@dfci.harvard.edu</ipd_access_criteria>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

