<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04165109</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ATRI-006</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>1R61AG066543-01</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04165109</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Trial-Ready Cohort-Down Syndrome (TRC-DS)</brief_title>
  <acronym>TRC-DS</acronym>
  <official_title>Alzheimer's Clinical Trial Consortium for Down Syndrome (ACTC-DS) Trial-Ready Cohort - Down Syndrome (TRC-DS)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Southern California</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute on Aging (NIA)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Alzheimer's Clinical Trial Consortium</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Alzheimer's Therapeutic Research Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Southern California</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of the Trial-Ready Cohort - Down Syndrome (TRC-DS) is to enroll 120 non-demented
      adults (ages 35-55) with Down syndrome (DS) into a trial ready cohort (TRC). Participants
      enrolled in the TRC-DS will undergo longitudinal cognitive and clinical assessment, genetic
      and biomarker testing, as well as imaging and biospecimen collection. Using these outcome
      measures, researchers will analyze the relationships between cognitive measures and
      biomarkers of Alzheimer's disease (AD) to identify endpoints for AD clinical trials in DS
      that best reflect disease progression.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">September 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2025</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2025</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Enrollment of 120 participants into the Trial-Ready Cohort in DS (TRC-DS).</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <description>The primary aim of the TRC-DS is enrollment of 120 participants into the trial ready cohort to support future referral and enrollment into primary Alzheimer's disease (AD) prevention trials for adults with DS.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in cognition as measured by the Cued Recall Test</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and every 16 months through end of study or enrollment into a clinical trial, up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <description>The Cued Recall Test is modified from a version developed for adults from the typical population. Twelve items are presented for learning, 4 at a time, with each item accompanied by a unique category cue. The testing phase consists of 3 trials. Each trial begins with free recall of the test items; following free recall, a category cue is provided for those items not spontaneously recalled. Two scores are generated from the test, a Free Recall Score and a Total Score (Free Recall plus items recalled when the category cue is provided). A cut-off of &lt; 23 on the Total Score resulted in a sensitivity of 91% and a specificity of 84% when individuals with DS and a diagnosis of dementia were compared to their healthy peers without dementia.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in behavior as measured by the Neuropsychiatric Inventory- Questionnaire (NPI-Q)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and every 16 months through end of study or enrollment into a clinical trial, up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <description>The NPI-Q is a 12-item questionnaire that assesses behaviors in dementia patients and has been used in Down syndrome.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in cognition as measured by the Down Syndrome Mental Status Exam (DSMSE)</measure>
    <time_frame>Screening and every 16 months through end of study or enrollment into a clinical trial, up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <description>The DSMSE is an omnibus measure of neuropsychological function that assesses a broad range of skills and is easy to administer. It is divided into items that test recall for personal information, orientation to season and day of week, memory, language, visuospatial function, and praxis. Recall for personal information is tested with questions about the subject's name, age and birth date. Orientation items ask the day of the week and season of the year. Memory in the DSMSE is assessed with items that require immediate and delayed recall of three objects and for the location of three hidden objects. Language items include confrontation naming, sentence repetition, and comprehension of one, two, and three step commands. Visuospatial items are three-dimensional block constructions. Praxis items include transitive and intransitive limb movements and a sequential task.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in behavior as measured by the Vineland 3</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and every 16 months through end of study or enrollment into a clinical trial, up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <description>The Vineland 3 is a normed assessment tool that assesses adaptive behavior across the areas of communication, activities of daily living, and socialization. The tool is administered via interview to a caregiver and takes approximately 45 minutes to complete.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in cognition as measured by the National Task Group Early Detection Screen for Dementia (NTG-EDSD)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, every 8 months (over the phone) and every 16 months (in person) through end of study or enrollment into a clinical trial, up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <description>The National Task Group Early Detection Screen for Dementia (NTG-EDSD) is a screening tool which measures changes typically observed in dementia. It is composed of four primary sections about relative demographics, ratings of health, mental health, and life stressors, a review of multiple domains associated with adult functioning, and a review of chronic medical conditions. The NTG-EDSD is completed by a staff member who interviews the caregiver. It contains 40 questions/question groups and takes 15 mins to administer.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in cognition as measured by the Stroop Dog and Cat Task</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and every 16 months through end of study or enrollment into a clinical trial, up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <description>In the Stroop Dog and Cat Task, a linear sequence of 16 pictures (8 cats, 8 dogs) are presented in a pre-determined random order. In the control condition the subject says the name of each picture and is urged to do so rapidly. In the experimental (inhibition) condition the participant is required to say 'cat' for the picture of each dog and 'dog' for the cat. For each condition the participant is given a brief practice period. Performance on the Stroop Dog and Cat was significantly related to informant-reported memory changes in 103 adults with DS with mild-moderate intellectual disability in the age range of 36 - 72 years.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in verbal learning and cognition as measured by the modified Selective Reminding Test (SRT)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and every 16 months through end of study or enrollment into a clinical trial, up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <description>The modified SRT is a test designed to measure verbal learning and memory through the use of a list-learning procedure over multiple trials. This paradigm is believed to separate verbal memory into distinct processes. The modified SRT involves reading the participant a list of 12 unrelated words and then having the participant immediately recall as many of these 12 words as possible. Every trial after the first involves selectively presenting only those words in which the participant did not recall on the immediately preceding trial. The selective reminding trials proceed in this manner until the participant is able to correctly recall all 12 words on three consecutive trials.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in cognition as measured by the Brief Praxis Test (BPT)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and every 16 months through end of study or enrollment into a clinical trial, up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <description>The Brief Praxis Test (BPT), evaluates simple sequences of voluntary movements expected to deteriorate with the onset and progression of dementia in AD among persons at all levels of premorbid intellectual disability. Participants are given points for each task they are able to perform.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in amyloid deposition as measured by SUVR on Positron Imaging Tomography (PET) scan</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and every 16 months through end of study or enrollment into a clinical trial, up to 5 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in brain volume as measured by magnetic resonance imaging (MRI)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and every 16 months through end of study or enrollment into a clinical trial, up to 5 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in plasma Amyloid Beta (Abeta) biomarkers</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and every 16 months through end of study or enrollment into a clinical trial, up to 5 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in plasma tau biomarkers</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and every 16 months through end of study or enrollment into a clinical trial, up to 5 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">120</enrollment>
  <condition>Down Syndrome</condition>
  <condition>Alzheimer Disease</condition>
  <condition>Dementia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Trial Ready Cohort</arm_group_label>
    <description>Non-demented adults with Down syndrome (DS)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Blood, Urine, CSF
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        120 non-demented adults with Down Syndrome
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Diagnosis of DS (including mosaic DS or partial trisomy 21) who are capable of
             providing consent to participate, or for whom a legally authorized representative
             (LAR) may give permission on behalf of the individual to participate. Adults with DS
             who cannot consent for themselves but can provide assent would need to provide assent

          2. Provision of signed and dated informed consent form and if needed, assent with signed
             consent by legally authorized representative (LAR)

          3. Stated availability and willingness to comply with all study procedures and
             availability for the duration of the study (i.e. 2 years) or until referred to a
             clinical trial

          4. Male or female, aged 35-55 inclusive

          5. In good general health as evidenced by medical history with no diagnosis of dementia

          6. Permitted CNS-active medications, stable in dose for at least 4 weeks or longer. If
             new medications have been started, medical monitoring team will review on case by case
             basis to recommend timing of baseline cognitive testing

          7. Adequate visual and auditory acuity to allow neuropsychological testing

          8. Mental Age of 4 years or greater (based upon the Kaufman Brief Intelligence Test,
             Second Edition)

          9. IQ less than 40 (based upon the Kaufman Brief Intelligence Test, Second Edition)

         10. Must speak English or Spanish fluently

         11. Must have a reliable Study Partner (may be caregiver, sibling, parent) who is capable
             of providing correct information about the participant's clinical symptoms and history

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Any significant disease or unstable medical condition that could affect
             neuropsychological testing (i.e., unstable cardiac problems, chronic renal failure,
             chronic hepatic disease, severe pulmonary disease)

          2. Participants in whom magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) is contraindicated including,
             but not limited to, those with a pacemaker, presence of metallic fragments near the
             eyes or spinal cord, or cochlear implant (Dental fillings do not present a risk for
             MRI)

          3. Participants unable to complete MRI and PET procedures

          4. For females who are not surgically sterile or post-menopausal by two years: Positive
             Pregnancy test 48 hours prior to amyloid PET scan, or currently breast-feeding

          5. History, within the last 5 years of a primary or recurrent malignant disease with the
             exception of non-melanoma skin cancers, resected cutaneous squamous cell carcinoma in
             situ, basal cell carcinoma, cervical carcinoma in situ, or in situ prostate cancer
             with normal prostate-specific antigen post-treatment

          6. Clinically significant abnormalities in B12 or TFTs that might interfere with the
             study. A low B12 is exclusionary, unless follow-up labs (homocysteine (HC) and
             methylmalonic acid (MMA)) indicate that it is not physiologically significant. A high
             TSH is exclusionary unless follow up T3/T4 levels indicate that it is not
             physiologically significant

          7. Clinically significant abnormalities in screening ECG or laboratories

          8. Answer &quot;Yes&quot; to C-SSRS suicidal ideation Type 4 or 5 or behavior

          9. For participants undergoing CSF collection: a current blood clotting or bleeding
             disorder, or significantly abnormal PT or PTT at screening or if on anti-coagulation
             therapy (e.g. warfarin)

         10. Concurrent participation in a clinical trial for an investigational product or
             concurrent participation in longitudinal study with overlapping outcome
             measures/procedures is prohibited

         11. Participants whom the investigator deems to be otherwise ineligible. The Investigators
             should consult with the Coordinating Center on any issues that may disqualify the
             participant from participation in future clinical trials to determine whether
             enrollment into TRC-DS would be appropriate.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>35 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>55 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Michael Rafii, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>USC Alzheimer's Therapeutic Research Institute (ATRI)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>ATRI Recruitment Team</last_name>
    <phone>858-964-0638</phone>
    <email>atri-recruit@usc.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <link>
    <url>https://keck.usc.edu/atri/research/studies/</url>
    <description>ATRI Studies</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>https://www.actcinfo.org/</url>
    <description>Alzheimer's Clinical Trials Consortium</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>https://www.nih.gov/include-project</url>
    <description>The INCLUDE Project</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.actc-ds.org</url>
    <description>Alzheimer's Clinical Trials Consortium - Down syndrome</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hardy J. The discovery of Alzheimer-causing mutations in the APP gene and the formulation of the &quot;amyloid cascade hypothesis&quot;. FEBS J. 2017 Apr;284(7):1040-1044. doi: 10.1111/febs.14004. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>28054745</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Selkoe DJ, Hardy J. The amyloid hypothesis of Alzheimer's disease at 25 years. EMBO Mol Med. 2016 Jun 1;8(6):595-608. doi: 10.15252/emmm.201606210. Print 2016 Jun. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>27025652</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Handen BL, Cohen AD, Channamalappa U, Bulova P, Cannon SA, Cohen WI, Mathis CA, Price JC, Klunk WE. Imaging brain amyloid in nondemented young adults with Down syndrome using Pittsburgh compound B. Alzheimers Dement. 2012 Nov;8(6):496-501. doi: 10.1016/j.jalz.2011.09.229.</citation>
    <PMID>23102120</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rafii MS, Wishnek H, Brewer JB, Donohue MC, Ness S, Mobley WC, Aisen PS, Rissman RA. The down syndrome biomarker initiative (DSBI) pilot: proof of concept for deep phenotyping of Alzheimer's disease biomarkers in down syndrome. Front Behav Neurosci. 2015 Sep 14;9:239. doi: 10.3389/fnbeh.2015.00239. eCollection 2015.</citation>
    <PMID>26441570</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lao PJ, Betthauser TJ, Hillmer AT, Price JC, Klunk WE, Mihaila I, Higgins AT, Bulova PD, Hartley SL, Hardison R, Tumuluru RV, Murali D, Mathis CA, Cohen AD, Barnhart TE, Devenny DA, Mailick MR, Johnson SC, Handen BL, Christian BT. The effects of normal aging on amyloid-β deposition in nondemented adults with Down syndrome as imaged by carbon 11-labeled Pittsburgh compound B. Alzheimers Dement. 2016 Apr;12(4):380-90. doi: 10.1016/j.jalz.2015.05.013. Epub 2015 Jun 13.</citation>
    <PMID>26079411</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rafii MS, Lukic AS, Andrews RD, Brewer J, Rissman RA, Strother SC, Wernick MN, Pennington C, Mobley WC, Ness S, Matthews DC; Down Syndrome Biomarker Initiative and the Alzheimer’s Disease Neuroimaging Initiative. PET Imaging of Tau Pathology and Relationship to Amyloid, Longitudinal MRI, and Cognitive Change in Down Syndrome: Results from the Down Syndrome Biomarker Initiative (DSBI). J Alzheimers Dis. 2017;60(2):439-450. doi: 10.3233/JAD-170390.</citation>
    <PMID>28946567</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>McCarron M, McCallion P, Reilly E, Dunne P, Carroll R, Mulryan N. A prospective 20-year longitudinal follow-up of dementia in persons with Down syndrome. J Intellect Disabil Res. 2017 Sep;61(9):843-852. doi: 10.1111/jir.12390. Epub 2017 Jun 29.</citation>
    <PMID>28664561</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Firth NC, Startin CM, Hithersay R, Hamburg S, Wijeratne PA, Mok KY, Hardy J, Alexander DC; LonDownS Consortium, Strydom A. Aging related cognitive changes associated with Alzheimer's disease in Down syndrome. Ann Clin Transl Neurol. 2018 May 20;5(6):741-751. doi: 10.1002/acn3.571. eCollection 2018 Jun.</citation>
    <PMID>29928657</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Startin CM, Hamburg S, Hithersay R, Al-Janabi T, Mok KY, Hardy J; LonDownS Consortium, Strydom A. Cognitive markers of preclinical and prodromal Alzheimer's disease in Down syndrome. Alzheimers Dement. 2019 Feb;15(2):245-257. doi: 10.1016/j.jalz.2018.08.009. Epub 2018 Nov 28.</citation>
    <PMID>30503169</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hithersay R, Startin CM, Hamburg S, Mok KY, Hardy J, Fisher EMC, Tybulewicz VLJ, Nizetic D, Strydom A. Association of Dementia With Mortality Among Adults With Down Syndrome Older Than 35 Years. JAMA Neurol. 2019 Feb 1;76(2):152-160. doi: 10.1001/jamaneurol.2018.3616.</citation>
    <PMID>30452522</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 25, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 14, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">November 15, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 16, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 16, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 20, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Southern California</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Michael Rafii, MD, PhD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Trial-Ready Cohort</keyword>
  <keyword>Observational</keyword>
  <keyword>Alzheimer's</keyword>
  <keyword>Prevention</keyword>
  <keyword>Down Syndrome</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Alzheimer Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Down Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Syndrome</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

