<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04169633</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>0000302</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04169633</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Spanish Adaptation and Validation of the Everyday Cognition Battery (ECB).</brief_title>
  <official_title>Spanish Adaptation and Validation of the Everyday Cognition Battery of Assessment of Daily Cognition in Older Adults.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Salamanca</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Salamanca</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      HYPOTHESIS:

      The Spanish version of the Everyday Cognition Battery Scale (ECB) is valid and reliable in
      the Spanish population.

      OBJECTIVES:

      • Providing a validated scale in Spanish to evaluate daily cognition in older adults.

      SPECIFIC OBJECTIVES:

        -  Translating the original English version of the ECB into Spanish.

        -  Adapting the scale to the sociocultural context of Spain.

        -  Checking the psychometric characteristics (reliability and validity) of the translated
           version .

      STUDY DESIGN:

      Cross-sectional descriptive study. Permission to use the ECB scale will be requested to the
      author, Allaire JC. Translation and adaptation of the scale.

      Administration of the four tests of the ECB to the individuals participating in the study.

      Administration of the Rapid Evaluation of Cognitive Functions (RECF) and Lawton and Brody
      scales.

      Analysis of the psychometric characteristics of the translated version.

      The protocol has been authorized by the Ethics Committee of the Salamanca health area to make
      the project possible.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      OBJECTIVES:

      • Providing a validated scale in Spanish that evaluates daily cognition in older adults.

      SPECIFIC OBJECTIVES:

        -  Translating the original English version of the ECB into Spanish.

        -  Adapting the scale to the sociocultural context of Spain.

        -  Checking the psychometric characteristics (reliability and validity) of the translated
           version.

      STUDY DESIGN:

      Cross-sectional descriptive study. Permission to use the ECB scale will be requested from the
      author, Allaire JC.

      Translation and adaptation of the scale. For the translation and adaptation of the scale, the
      investigators will follow the steps proposed by Beaton et al. (Spine. 2000;25(24):3186-91):

        -  Stage I: translation of the scale from the original English version to Spanish. Two
           translations will be performed: one by the principal investigator and another by the
           Central Language Service of the University of Salamanca.

        -  Stage II: synthesis of translations and solution of discrepancies, carried out by the
           research team.

        -  Stage III: reverse translation or retro-translation, from the target language (Spanish)
           to the original language (English).

        -  Stage IV: pilot test (pre-test). Administration of the four tests of the translated
           version to the ECB to the individuals participating in the study.

      Administration of the Rapid Evaluation of Cognitive Functions (RECF) and Lawton and Brody
      scales (adapted and validated in Spanish instruments that will be used as reference
      standards).

      Analysis of the psychometric characteristics of the translated version.

      The study was carried out over three years.

      This research study was approved by the Bioethics Committee of the University of Salamanca.

      SITE - SAMPLE SELECTION:

      The study will include healthy older adults, of both sexes who voluntarily participate in the
      Geriatric Revitalization, Muscle Reeducation and Occupation Therapy Program and Fall
      Prevention Program, during the years 2018-2020, carried out by the City Council of Salamanca
      in collaboration with the University School Of Nursing and Physiotherapy of the University of
      Salamanca, and the students of the Interuniversity Program of Experience based in Ávila,
      during the years 2019-2020, carried out with the collaboration of the University of
      Salamanca.

      SAMPLE SIZE:

      The sample size of the study will be calculated according to the recommendations of Carretero
      H (International Journal of Clinical and Healthpsychology; 2005;5(3):521-551) which advises
      that there should be at least five participants for each variable to be studied; and taking
      into account the sample size used by the author, Allaire JC, for the preparation of the
      original ECB.

      Participants must meet the inclusion/exclusion criteria, who authorized their participation
      in the study voluntarily and altruistically, through the signature of an informed consent for
      people with full capacity, having previously received a Participant Information Sheet.

      INDEPENDENT VARIABLES:

      • Demographic data of the subject: age, sex, marital status, level of education, lifestyle
      (lives alone yes/no), physical exercise (yes/no).

      DEPENDENT VARIABLES:

        -  Score obtained in each ECB test

        -  Score obtained in the Rapid Evaluation of Cognitive Functions (RECF).

      DESCRIPTION OF THE INTERVENTION: Process description

        1. Subjects interested in participating in the study will receive a Participant Information
           Sheet, explaining the objectives and procedures of the research study. It also refers to
           the principles of non-maleficence, autonomy and participation and voluntary withdrawal,
           data protection and confidentiality.

        2. After the clarifications requested, informed consent will be given to people with full
           capacity, who will read and sign if they agree to be part of the study.

        3. Next, a document called Clinical History will be delivered to collect personal data and
           demographic characteristics of the participant.

        4. The four component tests of the ECB will be administered:

           The sequence of the ECB tests will be:

             -  ECB Knowledge Test

             -  ECB Recognition Test - Declarative Memory

             -  ECB Inductive Reasoning Test

             -  ECB Calculation Test - Retention Capaccity of the ECB The time taken to complete
                the self-administered tests will be that required by each participant, and the
                estimated time to complete the hetero-administered test is about 7 minutes.

        5. Subsequently, the RECF and a scale of assessment of Instrumental Activities of Daily
           Life (IADL), Lawton &amp; Brody Scale will be administered.

        6. The number of sessions will be necessary until the statistically calculated sample is
           obtained.

      ETHICAL-LEGAL ASPECTS OF THE PROJECT: The protocol has been authorized by the Ethics
      Committee of the Salamanca health area to make the project possible
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">April 1, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Everyday cognition</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>The daily cognition battery called &quot;Everyday Cognition Battery (ECB)&quot; will be used.
The ECB assesses cognitive competence in three instrumental activities of daily life: use of medication, management of finances and nutrition and meal preparation. Within the ECB, there are 4 tests, each designed to assess a single cognitive ability: ECB Inductive Reasoning Test or ECU Knowledge Test or Knowledge Test, ECB Computation Span Test (Working Memory) or Amplitude Test Calculation and ECB Recognition Test (Declarative Memory) or Recognition Test (Declarative Memory). For the present study we have selected the latter since it evaluates memory, which led us to think about the importance of memory in the elderly, both measured objectively and subjectively. Within the ECB Recognition Test (Declarative Memory) we have focused on the tests that valued the use of medication.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">200</enrollment>
  <condition>Occupational Therapy</condition>
  <condition>Nursing Caries</condition>
  <condition>Aging Disorder</condition>
  <condition>Cognitive Disorders</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cognitive Function Evaluation</intervention_name>
    <description>Evaluation of cognitive function and evaluation of daily cognition</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Older adults without clinical cognitive impairment
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Being older than 60 years old.

          2. Voluntary participation in the Geriatric Revitalization, Muscle Reeducation and
             Occupation Therapy Program and Fall Prevention Program or in the Interuniversity
             Program of Experience.

          3. Signing an informed consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Cognitive impairment with clinical diagnosis.

          2. Absence of numerical and literacy skills.

          3. Not authorizing the participation in the study.

        Withdrawal Criteria:

          1. Participants who decide to leave the study in any of its phases, despite having signed
             the informed consent.

          2. Not having completed more tan 50% of the administered scale.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>60 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Eduardo José IP Fernández, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Salamanca</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Eduardo José IP Fernández, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>699244390</phone>
    <email>edujfr@usal.es</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Eduardo José Fernández</name>
      <address>
        <city>Salamanca</city>
        <zip>37002</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Eduardo JOsé IP Fernández, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>699244390</phone>
      <email>edujfr@usal.es</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Spain</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 13, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 15, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">November 20, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 15, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 15, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 20, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Salamanca</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Prof. Dr. Eduardo J Fernández Rodríguez</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Everyday cognition</keyword>
  <keyword>Older adult, aging</keyword>
  <keyword>test Validation</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cognition Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>A specific database will be created to which any external researcher can access after contacting by email with the PI (mail: Raquel.jimenez@usal.es)</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Statistical Analysis Plan (SAP)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Informed Consent Form (ICF)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Clinical Study Report (CSR)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>We do not establish a specific period of time, access will be permanent.</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>Researcher upon invitation by mail.</ipd_access_criteria>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

