<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04166877</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>1440730</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04166877</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Magnesium Infusion for Pain Management in Critically Ill Trauma Patients</brief_title>
  <official_title>Magnesium Infusion for Pain Management in Critically Ill Trauma Patients</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of California, Davis</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of California, Davis</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Magnesium is a naturally occurring mineral that is important for your body and brain.
      Magnesium sulfate (study drug) is a medication containing magnesium that is commonly used to
      improve low blood levels of magnesium. Magnesium sulfate has also proven to be successful in
      managing pain before and after surgery. However, this drug has primarily been used for pain
      control in patients undergoing surgery. Patients in the ICU with injuries also need good pain
      control. Using magnesium may assist in decreasing narcotic (pain reliever) requirements and
      provide another non-narcotic drug for pain control.

      The purpose of this study is to test the effectiveness of continuous, intravenous (into or
      within a vein using a needle) administration of magnesium sulfate for pain control in trauma
      patients admitted to the adult Intensive Care Unit. This will be compared to intravenous
      normal saline (salt solution).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a single center, double blind, randomized controlled study to demonstrate the
      effectiveness of continuous, intravenous administration of magnesium sulfate as compared to
      placebo in decreasing pain in critically injured patients.

      Study Hypothesis The primary hypothesis is that continuous infusion magnesium sulfate will
      significantly decrease opioid requirements and pain scores in critically ill patients.

      Background Magnesium is one of the most abundant cations in the human body. The
      physiologically active form of magnesium, ionized magnesium, is involved in hundreds of
      enzyme reactions that are important for homeostasis, action potentials, and membrane
      stability, among others.[Seo, et al] Hypomagnesemia is one of the most common electrolyte
      disturbances in the hospitalized patient, especially in the critically ill population.
      Studies have established that low magnesium levels increase mortality and morbidity in the
      critically ill patient,[Upala, et al] and thus magnesium is often repleted with intermittent
      infusion. Outside of its role in enzyme reactions, magnesium was discovered to have analgesic
      effects approximately twenty years ago.[Albrecht, et al] It appears to potentiate morphine
      analgesia, attenuate morphine tolerance, and suppress neuropathic pain.[Albrecht, et al] At a
      mechanistic level, these effects are thought to be secondary to magnesium regulating calcium
      influx into cells and antagonizing NMDA receptors in the central nervous system.

      Magnesium has long been utilized in prevention and management of preeclampsia and eclampsia.
      A typical dosing regimen in this setting involves a 4 g loading dose of magnesium sulfate,
      followed by a magnesium infusion of 1-2 g/hr. When compared to eclampsia regimens, studies
      investigating the role of magnesium sulfate in multimodal surgical pain management
      consistently use lower doses. Even with this dosing, multiple trials have shown reduced
      postoperative pain and analgesic requirements.[Albrecht, et al, Sousa, et al, Hwang, et al,
      Shariat, et al] In one example, Shariat Moharari and others used a regimen of 40 mg/kg
      magnesium bolus followed by 10 mg/kg/hr infusion in perioperative gastrointestinal surgery
      patients, without adverse effects.[Shariat, et al]

      Normal reference range for serum magnesium has been defined as approximately 0.7-1 mmol/L
      (1.5-2 mEq/L or 1.7-2.4 mg/dL).[Williamson, et al] Tramer et al. reported that a 3 g bolus
      dose of magnesium sulfate followed with 0.5 g/hr infusion for 20 hours resulted in an
      increase from baseline serum magnesium of approximately 0.6 mmol/L. Despite the higher
      post-treatment serum magnesium levels in the treatment group, no difference in safety
      outcomes was noted in comparison to the control group receiving 0.9% sodium
      chloride.[Tramer,et al] Similarly, Ozcan et al. found that 30 mg/kg bolus dose of magnesium
      sulfate followed by infusion of 10 mg/Kg/hr for 48 hours resulted in an increased serum
      magnesium level from baseline by approximately 0.7 mmol/L. The noted increase in serum
      magnesium level in this study also did not translate into any difference in safety endpoints
      between the intervention group and control group receiving 0.9% sodium chloride.[Ozcan, et
      al] Initial signs of magnesium toxicity following administration of magnesium sulfate have
      been reported to occur at serum magnesium levels greater than 3.5-5 mmol/L.[Lu, et al,
      Jahnen-Dechent, et al]

      Despite the successful use of magnesium in perioperative pain management, it has yet to be
      applied in patient populations outside of the operating room. Given the need for adequate
      pain control among critically ill patients with traumatic injuries, the use of magnesium for
      pain management may assist in decreasing opioid requirements and provide another non-opioid
      adjunct for pain control.

      Methods:

      All trauma patients admitted to an adult ICU are screened during the first 24 hours after
      admission. If they meet criteria for admission to the study, an informed consent will be
      obtained. Patients meeting eligibility will be randomized by the Investigational Drug Service
      in a computer-generated, blinded block, 1:1 ratio to treatment with either magnesium sulfate
      (diluted appropriately in normal saline per standard procedures) or placebo (normal saline).&quot;

      Opioid administration will be recorded per usual nursing protocol in the electronic medial
      record. Heart rate, mean arterial pressure (MAP), respiratory rate, and RASS will be recorded
      at least every two hours per unit protocol.

      A study worksheet will be posted at bedside for consistent collection of pain scores and CAM.
      Pain will be assessed per unit protocol using the numeric rating scale, with zero
      representing no pain and ten representing the worst pain imaginable.

      The EMR will be reviewed; opioid administration, pain scores, and vital signs will be
      transferred to a separate data sheet through REDCap (Research Electronic Data Capture)
      software.

      The primary outcome measure will be the total opioid requirement during the 24 hours of
      magnesium infusion. We performed this power analysis based on a recent retrospective cohort
      study performed at our institution.[Hamrick, et al] We estimate that the 24 hour OME
      requirement will decrease from 70 mg in the control group to 50 mg in the treatment group,
      with a standard deviation of 50 mg in each group, leading to an effect size of 0.4. Using the
      statistical program G*Power 3.0.1 with an effect size of 0.4, alpha of 0.05, power of 0.8,
      and equal allocation ratios, a sample size of 78 patients per group would be required.

      Data will be assessed for normality by assessing distribution skewness and kurtosis.
      Depending on these results, t-tests or Wilcoxon rank-sum tests for two groups will be used to
      assess the primary outcome of total opioid dose. Other data, including pain scores, that is
      collected repeatedly will be analyzed with two-way repeated measures analysis of variance,
      with subsequent pair-wise comparison for any significant findings. Statistical significance
      will be set at a P value of less than 0.05. We will use SAS to perform the statistical
      analysis.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">December 7, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 1, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 1, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Single center, investigator-initiated, randomized, double-blinded, placebo controlled study</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>total opioid requirements during study drug infusion</measure>
    <time_frame>24 hours during study drug infusion</time_frame>
    <description>oral morphine equivalents, OME</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>pain scores</measure>
    <time_frame>daily x 4 days</time_frame>
    <description>numeric pain rating scale as reported by patient</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Total oral morphine equivalents</measure>
    <time_frame>daily x 4 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>ICU length of stay</measure>
    <time_frame>through the patient's hospitalization for this injury, an average of 10 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>ICU-free days</measure>
    <time_frame>14 days</time_frame>
    <description>14 days minus the number of ICU days</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hospital length of stay</measure>
    <time_frame>through the patient's hospitalization for this injury, an average of 10 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Development of bradycardia</measure>
    <time_frame>24 hours during study drug infusion</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Development of other dysrhythmia</measure>
    <time_frame>24 hours during study drug infusion</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Respiratory depression</measure>
    <time_frame>24 hours during study drug infusion</time_frame>
    <description>Episodes of respiratory depression as measured by a respiratory rate less than 8</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Prevalence of Richmond Agitation-Sedation Scale of -3 to -5</measure>
    <time_frame>24 hours during study drug infusion</time_frame>
    <description>Episodes of a -3 to -5 Richmond Agitation-Sedation Scale score</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">156</enrollment>
  <condition>Trauma</condition>
  <condition>Acute Pain</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Magnesium Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The magnesium group arm will receive a 40 mg/kg IBW (maximum 4 g) bolus of intravenous magnesium sulfate, followed by a continuous infusion of 0.5 g/hr for a total of 24 hours.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The control arm will receive the same volume and rate of saline as if they were in the experimental group.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Magnesium Sulfate in Parenteral Dosage Form</intervention_name>
    <description>IV bolus followed by continuous infusion for 24 hours</description>
    <arm_group_label>Magnesium Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Normal saline placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>IV bolus followed by continuous infusion for 24 hours</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  All trauma patients admitted to an adult intensive care unit

          -  Signed informed consent

          -  Hospital or trauma multimodal pain management order set used for pain management

          -  Ages 18-99

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Admission to the Pediatric Intensive Care Unit.

          -  Head Abbreviated Injury Score (AIS) of greater than 1

          -  Known heart failure with reduced ejection fraction (EF &lt; 40%)

          -  Renal failure (GFR &lt; 60)

          -  Cardiac arrhythmia (except for sinus tachycardia)

          -  Greater than 5% TBSA burn injuries

          -  Moderate to severe alcohol withdrawal protocol ordered for patient

          -  Regular use of opioids in the week prior to injury

          -  Receiving continuous infusion of opioids

          -  Patients expected to require general anesthesia between 24 and 48 hours after
             admission (during study drug administration)

          -  Patients unable to provide consent is unavailable

          -  Patients unable to provide a pain score

          -  Pregnancy

          -  Prisoners
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Christine S Cocanour, MD</last_name>
    <phone>9167347330</phone>
    <email>cscocanour@ucdavis.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>G J Jurkovich, MD</last_name>
    <phone>9167348298</phone>
    <email>gjjurkovich@ucdavis.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UC Davis Health</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sacramento</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>95817</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Christine S Cocanour, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Seo JW, Park TJ. Magnesium metabolism. Electrolyte Blood Press. 2008 Dec;6(2):86-95. doi: 10.5049/EBP.2008.6.2.86. Epub 2008 Dec 31. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24459527</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Upala S, Jaruvongvanich V, Wijarnpreecha K, Sanguankeo A. Hypomagnesemia and mortality in patients admitted to intensive care unit: a systematic review and meta-analysis. QJM. 2016 Jul;109(7):453-459. doi: 10.1093/qjmed/hcw048. Epub 2016 Mar 24. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>27016536</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Albrecht E, Kirkham KR, Liu SS, Brull R. Peri-operative intravenous administration of magnesium sulphate and postoperative pain: a meta-analysis. Anaesthesia. 2013 Jan;68(1):79-90. doi: 10.1111/j.1365-2044.2012.07335.x. Epub 2012 Nov 1. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23121612</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sousa AM, Rosado GM, Neto Jde S, Guimarães GM, Ashmawi HA. Magnesium sulfate improves postoperative analgesia in laparoscopic gynecologic surgeries: a double-blind randomized controlled trial. J Clin Anesth. 2016 Nov;34:379-84. doi: 10.1016/j.jclinane.2016.05.006. Epub 2016 Jun 5.</citation>
    <PMID>27687417</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hwang JY, Na HS, Jeon YT, Ro YJ, Kim CS, Do SH. I.V. infusion of magnesium sulphate during spinal anaesthesia improves postoperative analgesia. Br J Anaesth. 2010 Jan;104(1):89-93. doi: 10.1093/bja/aep334.</citation>
    <PMID>19933175</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shariat Moharari R, Motalebi M, Najafi A, Zamani MM, Imani F, Etezadi F, Pourfakhr P, Khajavi MR. Magnesium Can Decrease Postoperative Physiological Ileus and Postoperative Pain in Major non Laparoscopic Gastrointestinal Surgeries: A Randomized Controlled Trial. Anesth Pain Med. 2013 Dec 6;4(1):e12750. doi: 10.5812/aapm.12750. eCollection 2014 Feb.</citation>
    <PMID>24660146</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hamrick KL, Beyer CA, Lee JA, Cocanour CS, Duby JJ. Multimodal Analgesia and Opioid Use in Critically Ill Trauma Patients. J Am Coll Surg. 2019 May;228(5):769-775.e1. doi: 10.1016/j.jamcollsurg.2019.01.020. Epub 2019 Feb 21.</citation>
    <PMID>30797081</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Williamson M. A., Snyder L. M., Wallach J. B. Wallach's Interpretation of Diagnostic Tests. 9th. Philadelphia, PA, USA: Wolters Kluwer/Lippincott Williams &amp; Wilkins; 2011. xvi, 1143.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tramer MR, Schneider J, Marti RA, Rifat K. Role of magnesium sulfate in postoperative analgesia. Anesthesiology. 1996 Feb;84(2):340-7.</citation>
    <PMID>8602664</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ozcan PE, Tugrul S, Senturk NM, Uludag E, Cakar N, Telci L, Esen F. Role of magnesium sulfate in postoperative pain management for patients undergoing thoracotomy. J Cardiothorac Vasc Anesth. 2007 Dec;21(6):827-31. Epub 2007 Feb 7.</citation>
    <PMID>18068060</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lu JF, Nightingale CH. Magnesium sulfate in eclampsia and pre-eclampsia: pharmacokinetic principles. Clin Pharmacokinet. 2000 Apr;38(4):305-14. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>10803454</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jahnen-Dechent W, Ketteler M. Magnesium basics. Clin Kidney J. 2012 Feb;5(Suppl 1):i3-i14. doi: 10.1093/ndtplus/sfr163.</citation>
    <PMID>26069819</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 13, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 14, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">November 18, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 25, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 25, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 28, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of California, Davis</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Christine S. Cocanour</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor of Surgery</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>magnesium sulfate</keyword>
  <keyword>trauma</keyword>
  <keyword>acute pain</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Acute Pain</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Wounds and Injuries</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Magnesium Sulfate</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

