<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04165447</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>AG-2014-001</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04165447</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluating the Effectiveness of Within Versus Across-Category Front-of-Package Lower-Calorie Labelling on Food Demand</brief_title>
  <official_title>Randomized Trial Evaluating the Effectiveness of Within Versus Across-Category Front-of-Package Lower-Calorie Labelling on Food Demand</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Duke-NUS Graduate Medical School</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National University, Singapore</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Duke-NUS Graduate Medical School</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The important role that diet plays in health and disease is well established, as is its
      association with rising rates of obesity—a phenomenon of increasing concern in Singapore.
      Changes in lifestyle patterns, including a movement towards a more western-style diet with an
      emphasis on pre-packaged and fast food, have contributed to the upward trend in weight. This
      study aims to test two competing approaches for calorie labelling in efforts to reduce total
      calories purchased. In Arm 1 (termed across category labelling) a low calorie logo will be
      displayed on the 20% of products on the web store that are lowest in calories per serving.
      Arm 2 will display this logo on the 20% of products that are lowest in calories per serving
      within each product category (termed within category labelling). Arm 3 is the Control
      condition which will not display any logo on any products.

      For our primary outcome, the investigators hypothesize that the proportion of labelled
      products (or those that would have been labelled if not in control arm) purchased in each
      intervention arm will be greater than in control.

      For secondary hypotheses the investigators expect the following ordering across the three
      (Control, Within category, Across category) arms:

        1. total calories (adjusted for household size): C &gt; A &gt; W

        2. calories per serving: C &gt; A &gt; W

        3. calories per dollar spent: W &gt; A &gt; C

        4. total dollars spent (adjusted for household size) : W &gt; A &gt; C
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      For this study an online grocery store was developed that contains over 3200 products
      commonly purchased in local supermarkets. The products available for purchase include foods
      from many different categories such as dairy products, snacks, processed meats and soft
      drinks. The web-based grocery store was designed to mirror an actual web-based grocery store
      in look and feel. All products include a picture of the item, current retail price, the Lower
      Calorie logo (where applicable), and other package size and nutrition information currently
      required for products in Singapore. The online grocery store features a grocery cart that
      shows the items purchased. The NUS Online Collection Facility payment system has been
      integrated with the online grocery store for participants to make payments.

      Study design: This will be a crossover study design with all participants exposed once to 3
      shopping conditions (1xControl, 1xIntervention 1 (I1), 1x Intervention 2(I2)) in random
      order. The total study duration for each participant is 3 weeks, with each participant
      spending 1 week in each shopping condition.

      For the Control condition the participants are not exposed to the lower calorie logo. For
      Intervention 1 (Across), the participant will see the lower calorie logo applied to foods
      with the lowest calories per serving across all food categories. For intervention 2, the
      participant will see the lower calorie logo applied to the 20% of foods with the lowest
      calories per serving within each food category. These foods will be tagged with the 'Lower
      Calorie' logo.

      Participants will be asked to shop once a week during each of the 3 weeks of the study, and
      will therefore shop for a total of 3 times during the study. This will include 1 shop within
      each shopping condition (control, I1, and I2). Participants will purchase and receive at
      least 1 and up to 3 of their grocery orders. This ensures that purchases will be an accurate
      reflection of their actual shopping experience.

      Since there are 3 shopping conditions (Control, I1, and I2) and the specific weeks that the
      participant's shopping trips will be pre-determined for purchase (but unknown to
      participants), each participant will be randomly assigned at baseline to 1 of 6 groups that
      vary the sequence of shopping conditions and which shops will result in an actual food
      delivery.

      For each shop there will be a minimum spend of SGD50 and a maximum spend of SGD250. A minimum
      spend ensures that participants complete a typical weekly grocery order. A maximum spend is
      to make the study more manageable given foods will need to be reordered and delivered. The
      grocery orders that participants purchase will be ordered by Duke-NUS using RedMart, a
      popular online grocery store in Singapore, and RedMart will deliver the grocery items. The
      store was created using products currently available on the RedMart website to allow us to
      repurchase from a single location.

      Redmart is engaged in this project as our collaborator. As such, the relationship between the
      Parties is that of independent contractor and contractee. Neither party is an agent of the
      other nor have any right or authority to create any obligation or responsibility on behalf of
      the other. Neither is Duke-NUS in any way endorsing or marketing the services of Redmart.

      At the end of the study participants who have completed all 3 shops as instructed will
      receive a RedMart e-Voucher worth $75 payment that can be redeemed against any products on
      RedMart.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 1, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">April 30, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">April 30, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Health Services Research</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of the basket represented by Lower Calorie products per shopping trip</measure>
    <time_frame>Once a week for three weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Proportion of products that are designated as labelled in the interventions</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Calories purchased per dollar spent per shopping trip</measure>
    <time_frame>Once a week for three weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Calories purchased per dollar spent in kcal per $</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Total spending per shopping trip</measure>
    <time_frame>Once a week for three weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Total spending ($)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Total calories purchased per shopping trip</measure>
    <time_frame>Once a week for three weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Total calories purchased (in kcal)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Calories per serving per shopping trip</measure>
    <time_frame>Once a week for three weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Calories per serving (in kcal/serving)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">146</enrollment>
  <condition>Food Selection</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>No labeling Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Arm 1 was the Control condition, which did not display the label on any products.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Within-category labeling</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Arm 2 displayed the label on the 20% of products that were lowest in calories per serving within each product category (termed Within-category Labeling, WC).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Across-category labeling</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Arm 3 displayed the label on the 20% of all products that were lowest in calories per serving (termed Across-category Labeling, AC).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Front-of-pack labeling strategy</intervention_name>
    <description>We designed a simple 'Lower Calorie' directive logo. We labeled the 20% of products with the lowest calories per serving within or across categories. All serving sizes used in this study were the average of the serving sizes within each category. Prior to conducting the analysis, we standardized the serving size by using the mean serving size within each subcategory. This standardization ensures that similar products are compared equally as serving sizes can be arbitrarily set by the manufacturers. The labels were displayed below the product images.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Across-category labeling</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Within-category labeling</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Adults aged 21 years and above

          -  Primary grocery shopper for the household

          -  Registered RedMart (an online grocery store) shoppers

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Under 21 years of age

          -  Not the primary grocery shopper for the household

          -  Not a resident in Singapore

          -  Not a registered online shopper of RedMart
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>21 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Duke-NUS Medical School</name>
      <address>
        <city>Singapore</city>
        <zip>169857</zip>
        <country>Singapore</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Singapore</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 11, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 13, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">November 18, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 13, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 13, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 18, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Duke-NUS Graduate Medical School</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Eric A. Finkelstein</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator, Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>nutrition</keyword>
  <keyword>front-of-pack label</keyword>
  <keyword>calories</keyword>
  <keyword>online grocery store</keyword>
  <keyword>diet</keyword>
  <keyword>groceries</keyword>
  <keyword>obesity</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>The datasets used and/or analysed during the current study are available from the corresponding author on reasonable request. All data will be de-identified.</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Informed Consent Form (ICF)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Clinical Study Report (CSR)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Analytic Code</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>Up to 10 years after study conclusion.</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>Reasonable request.</ipd_access_criteria>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

