<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04162873</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HCI124211</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2019-07104</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>HCI124211</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>P30CA042014</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04162873</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Celecoxib Through Surgery and Radiation Therapy for the Treatment of Advanced Head and Neck Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>RESILIENCE: Effect of Comprehensive Celecoxib Through Treatment for Advanced-Stage Head and Neck Cancer: A Randomized, Double-Blinded, Placebo-Controlled Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Utah</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Utah</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This phase II trial studies how well celecoxib works through surgery and radiation therapy in
      treating patients with head and neck cancer that has spread to other places in the body
      (advanced). Celecoxib is Food and Drug Administration approved to treat arthritis, acute
      pain, and painful menstrual periods. Adding celecoxib to standard of care treatment may help
      to decrease the amount of time between surgery and radiation therapy.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PRIMARY OBJECTIVE:

      I. To assess the number of days from surgery to initiation of radiation and adjuvant therapy
      with the addition of celecoxib compared to placebo.

      SECONDARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To assess overall pain control and management for patients on celecoxib compared to
      placebo.

      II. To assess functional outcomes for patients on celecoxib compared to placebo.

      III. To assess the effect of celecoxib therapy on Quality of Life (QoL) compared to placebo.

      IV. To assess the average number of treatment days missed during adjuvant therapy for
      patients on celecoxib compared to placebo.

      OUTLINE: Patients are randomized to 1 of 2 arms.

      ARM I: Patients receive celecoxib orally (PO) or via feeding tube twice daily (BID) starting
      5 days prior to surgery and continues until the completion of radiation therapy (up to 6
      months in total) in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.

      ARM II: Patients receive placebo PO or via feeding tube BID starting 5 days prior to surgery
      and continues until the completion of radiation therapy (up to 6 months in total) in the
      absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 27, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 12, 2025</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 12, 2024</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The number of days from surgery to the initiation of radiation and adjuvant therapy</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>The day of surgery will be considered day 0 and the number of days will be counted until the first dose of adjuvant therapy. A Gaussian mixed effects regression model will be used to compare the average number of days from surgery to the initiation of radiation and adjuvant therapy between treatment and control groups. The model will contain fixed effects for treatment arm and provider and a nested random effect for patient within provider. The mean difference between treatment groups, two-sided p-value and 95% confidence interval will be calculated from the model.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assessment of overall pain control and management for patients on celecoxib compared to placebo.</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Assessment of subjective pain scores on the visual analog scale of pain intensity averaged over a week at rest, with a swallow, and with a cough. Pain intensity scale is a range from 0-10. 0= No Pain, 5= Moderate pain, 10= Unbearable paining</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assessment of functional outcomes for patients on celecoxib compared to placebo</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Assessment of current activity level and swallowing capabilities, including food and liquid variety and assessment of G tube utilization.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To assess the effect of celecoxib therapy on Quality of Life (QoL) compared to placebo.</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Completion of quality of life questionnaire EORTC QLQ-H&amp;N43 as per the protocol described schedule.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assessment of the average number of treatment days missed during adjuvant therapy for patients on celecoxib compared to placebo.</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Assess the number of treatment days missed or delayed during adjuvant therapy.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assessment of overall pain control and management for patients on celecoxib compared to placebo.</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Narcotic consumption will be assessed in daily total morphine equivalents averaged over a week</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assessment of overall pain control and management for patients on celecoxib compared to placebo.</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Patient satisfaction will be assessed with pain control questionnaire.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To assess the effect of celecoxib therapy on Quality of Life (QoL) compared to placebo.</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Completion of quality of life questionnaire MDASI-HN as per the protocol described schedule.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Clinical Stage III HPV-Mediated (p16-Positive) Oropharyngeal Carcinoma AJCC v8</condition>
  <condition>Clinical Stage IV HPV-Mediated (p16-Positive) Oropharyngeal Carcinoma AJCC v8</condition>
  <condition>Nasal Cavity and Paranasal Sinus Carcinoma</condition>
  <condition>Oral Cavity Carcinoma</condition>
  <condition>Pathologic Stage III HPV-Mediated (p16-Positive) Oropharyngeal Carcinoma AJCC v8</condition>
  <condition>Pathologic Stage IV HPV-Mediated (p16-Positive) Oropharyngeal Carcinoma AJCC v8</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Hypopharyngeal Carcinoma</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Laryngeal Carcinoma</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Nasal Cavity and Paranasal Sinus Carcinoma</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Oral Cavity Carcinoma</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Oropharyngeal Carcinoma</condition>
  <condition>Stage III Hypopharyngeal Carcinoma AJCC v8</condition>
  <condition>Stage III Laryngeal Cancer AJCC v8</condition>
  <condition>Stage III Oropharyngeal (p16-Negative) Carcinoma AJCC v8</condition>
  <condition>Stage IV Hypopharyngeal Carcinoma AJCC v8</condition>
  <condition>Stage IV Laryngeal Cancer AJCC v8</condition>
  <condition>Stage IV Oropharyngeal (p16-Negative) Carcinoma AJCC v8</condition>
  <condition>Stage IVA Hypopharyngeal Carcinoma AJCC v8</condition>
  <condition>Stage IVA Laryngeal Cancer AJCC v8</condition>
  <condition>Stage IVA Oropharyngeal (p16-Negative) Carcinoma AJCC v8</condition>
  <condition>Stage IVB Hypopharyngeal Carcinoma AJCC v8</condition>
  <condition>Stage IVB Laryngeal Cancer AJCC v8</condition>
  <condition>Stage IVB Oropharyngeal (p16-Negative) Carcinoma AJCC v8</condition>
  <condition>Stage IVC Hypopharyngeal Carcinoma AJCC v8</condition>
  <condition>Stage IVC Laryngeal Cancer AJCC v8</condition>
  <condition>Stage IVC Oropharyngeal (p16-Negative) Carcinoma AJCC v8</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Celecoxib Arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive celecoxib PO or via feeding tube BID starting 5 days prior to surgery and continues until the completion of radiation therapy (up to 6 months in total) in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo Arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive placebo PO or via feeding tube BID starting 5 days prior to surgery and continues until the completion of radiation therapy (up to 6 months in total) in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Celecoxib</intervention_name>
    <description>Given PO or via feeding tube</description>
    <arm_group_label>Celecoxib Arm</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Benzenesulfonamide, 4-[5-(4-methylphenyl)-3-(trifluoromethyl)-1H-pyrazol-1-yl]-</other_name>
    <other_name>Celebrex</other_name>
    <other_name>SC-58635</other_name>
    <other_name>YM 177</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Given PO or via feeding tube</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo Arm</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>placebo therapy</other_name>
    <other_name>PLCB</other_name>
    <other_name>sham therapy</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Quality-of-Life Assessment</intervention_name>
    <description>Ancillary studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Celecoxib Arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo Arm</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Quality of Life Assessment</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Questionnaire Administration</intervention_name>
    <description>Ancillary studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Celecoxib Arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo Arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Advanced-stage (overall stage III and IV) head and neck cancers (sinonasal oral
             cavity, oropharynx, larynx, and hypopharynx) undergoing surgical resection and then
             adjuvant therapy. Primary and recurrence cases are acceptable

          -  Karnofsky performance status of &gt;= 80

          -  Hemoglobin &gt;= 10 g/dL

          -  Total bilirubin =&lt; 2 mg/dL

          -  Aspartate aminotransferase (AST) (serum glutamic-oxaloacetic transaminase
             [SGOT])/alanine aminotransferase (ALT) (serum glutamate pyruvate transaminase [SGPT])
             =&lt; 2.5 x institutional upper limit of normal (ULN)

          -  Albumin &gt; 3.5 g/dL

          -  Estimated glomerular filtration rate (eGFR) &gt;= 30 mL/min/1.73 m^2 or creatinine
             clearance &gt;= 30 mL/min by Cockcroft-Gault

          -  Serum potassium within normal limits

          -  Negative serum or urine pregnancy test at screening for women of childbearing
             potential

          -  Highly effective contraception for female subjects throughout the study and for at
             least 5 days after the last dose of celecoxib if the risk of conception exists

          -  Recovery to baseline or =&lt; grade 1 Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events
             (CTCAE) version (v)5.0 from toxicities related to any prior treatments, unless AE(s)
             are clinically nonsignificant and/or stable on supportive therapy

          -  Willing to maintain a diary of all opioids used during the trial for the treatment of
             pain

          -  Able to provide informed consent and willing to sign an approved consent form that
             conforms to federal and institutional guidelines

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Known metastatic disease or the tumor is deemed not surgically resectable

          -  Established in a pain management clinic or has taken opioids regularly &gt;= 6 months

          -  Known or suspected to be poor CYP2C9 metabolizers based on previous history/experience
             with other CYP2C9 substrates (such as warfarin, phenytoin)

          -  Known hypersensitivity to celecoxib, aspirin, other non-steroidal anti-inflammatory
             drug (NSAID)s, or sulfonamides

          -  Uncontrolled hypertension defined as blood pressure (BP) &gt; 150 mmHg systolic or &gt; 90
             mmHg diastolic on three separate readings despite optimal antihypertensive treatment

          -  Patients with a known history of the following:

               -  Cerebrovascular accident (CVA), stroke, or cardiovascular thrombotic events (e.g.
                  acute myocardial infarction).

               -  Chronic heart failure.

               -  Gastrointestinal bleeding, ulceration, peptic ulcer disease, or perforation of
                  the stomach or intestines.

               -  Aspirin-sensitive asthma.

               -  Chronic kidney disease, stage 4 or 5

          -  Patients with a prior or concurrent malignancy whose natural history or treatment has
             the potential to interfere with the safety or efficacy assessment of the
             investigational regimen are eligible for this trial

          -  The subject has uncontrolled, significant intercurrent or recent illness requiring
             systemic therapy, would preclude safe study participation, or is deemed clinically
             significant by the investigator

          -  Known human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) infection with a detectable viral load within
             6 months of the anticipated start of treatment.

               -  Note: Patients on effective anti-retroviral therapy with an undetectable viral
                  load within 6 months of the anticipated start of treatment are eligible for this
                  trial

          -  Known chronic hepatitis B virus (HBV) or hepatitis C virus infection with a detectable
             viral load.

               -  Note: Patients with an undetectable HBV viral load on appropriate suppressive
                  therapy are eligible. Patients with an undetectable hepatitis C virus (HCV) viral
                  load on appropriate treatment are eligible

          -  Subjects taking prohibited medications . A washout period of prohibited medications
             for a period of at least 5 half-lives or as clinically indicated should occur prior to
             the start of treatment
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Richard Cannon, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Huntsman Cancer Institute/ University of Utah</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Marissa Muse</last_name>
    <phone>801-587-9834</phone>
    <email>marissa.muse@hci.utah.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Huntsman Cancer Institute/University of Utah</name>
      <address>
        <city>Salt Lake City</city>
        <state>Utah</state>
        <zip>84112</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Richard B. Cannon</last_name>
      <phone>801-585-0255</phone>
      <email>Richard.Cannon@hsc.utah.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Richard B. Cannon</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 4, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 11, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">November 14, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 7, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 7, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 8, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Head and Neck Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Laryngeal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Oropharyngeal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Paranasal Sinus Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Celecoxib</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Benzenesulfonamide</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

