<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04167137</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>SYNB1891-CP-001</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04167137</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Safety and Tolerability of SYNB1891 Injection Alone or in Combination With Atezolizumab in Adult Subjects</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase 1, Open-label, Multicenter Study of SYNB1891 Administered by Intratumoral Injection to Patients With Advanced/Metastatic Solid Tumors and Lymphoma Alone and in Combination With Atezolizumab</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Synlogic</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>IQVIA Biotech</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Synlogic</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will evaluate SYNB1891 (investigational product) administered as intratumoral
      injections in subjects diagnosed with advanced/metastatic solid tumors and lymphoma for
      possible treatment. Eligible subjects will receive SYNB1891 intratumorally and will undergo
      imaging to assess tumor response, safety monitoring and subsequent follow-up after
      investigational product (IP) administration. Once dose limiting toxicity (DLT) for SYNB1891
      is determined, it will be administered at one log dose level lower in combination with
      atezolizumab.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This phase 1, open-label, multicenter, 2-arm study of SYNB1891 in subjects diagnosed with
      advanced/metastatic solid tumors and lymphoma will evaluate safety and tolerability of
      escalating doses of intratumoral injections of SYNB1891 to determine single-agent maximum
      tolerated dose (MTD) as monotherapy and the recommended Phase 2 dose (RP2D) in combination
      with atezolizumab. The incidence of dose-limiting toxicities (DLTs), kinetics and
      pharmacodynamics will be evaluated in 2 arms:

      Arm 1 comprises escalating doses of intratumoral injections of SYNB1891 monotherapy for up to
      four 21-day cycles with up to 24 months following initial treatment for those determined not
      to have progressive disease at the end of Cycle 4. Up to 7 dose cohorts will be evaluated to
      identify MTD within the dose range studied. Up to 35 patients may be enrolled in this arm of
      the study. Following attainment of MTD, Arm 2 will be initiated.

      Arm 2 comprises escalating doses of intratumoral injections of SYNB1891 for up to four 21-day
      cycles with up to 24 months following initial treatment for those determined not to have
      progressive disease at the end of Cycle 4. In addition, atezolizumab will be administered as
      an intravenous (IV) infusion in accordance with its recommended dose and schedule during each
      of the planned 4 cycles with up to 24 months following initial treatment for those determined
      not to have progressive disease at the end of Cycle 4. Up to 3 dose cohorts will be evaluated
      to identify RP2D in combination with atezolizumab. Up to 12 patients may be enrolled in Arm
      2. An additional 20 subjects may be enrolled in an extension combination.

      Safety will be monitored continuously by documentation of adverse events (AEs), serious
      adverse events (SAEs), clinical laboratory measurements, vital signs and physical
      examinations. DLTs will be evaluated at the end of Cycle 1 in both Arms 1 and 2.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 17, 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 17, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Dose-escalating, open-label</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of dose-limiting toxicities (DLTs)</measure>
    <time_frame>Evaluated through the end of the first 21-day cycle.</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of patients who experience a DLT</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Nature, incidence and severity of all adverse events (AEs) and serious adverse events (SAEs)</measure>
    <time_frame>Monitored continuously from time of informed consent signing through the Safety Follow-up visit which occurs 30 ± 5 days after the last dose of study treatment (up to 26 months).</time_frame>
    <description>Rated according to the National Cancer Institute (NCI) Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE) version 5.0</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Objective response rate (ORR)</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed every 2 cycles (each cycle is 21 days) for the duration of study treatment administration (up to 24 months).</time_frame>
    <description>Determined by the Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors, version 1.1 (RECIST 1.1), immune-related RECIST (iRECIST), and/or the Lymphoma Response to Immunomodulatory Therapy Criteria (LYRIC), with evaluations of the SYNB1891-injected tumor(s) and an overall response of up to 5 target (noninjected) lesions. Assessed by the local investigator using appropriate imaging.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">70</enrollment>
  <condition>Metastatic Solid Neoplasm</condition>
  <condition>Lymphoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 1: SYNB1891 Monotherapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>SYNB1891 is to be administered as an intratumoral injection in up to four 21-day cycles of escalating doses on days 1, 8 and 15 of cycle 1 and day 1 of cycles 2-4. The starting dose of SYNB1891 in the first cohort will be 1 × 10^6 live cells and will be increased in approximately 3-fold increments in subsequent cohorts until MTD determination. A de-escalation dose of 3 × 10^5 live cells is available if the starting dose is deemed not tolerable. Patients without progressive disease at the end of cycle 4 may receive additional cycles of SYNB1891 on day 1 of each cycle for up to 24 months after initial dose of study treatment.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 2: SYNB1891 in Combination with Atezolizumab</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Once the MTD has been established in Arm 1, dosing of SYNB1891 will begin in Arm 2 at a 10-fold lower dose than the Arm 1 maximum tolerated dose (MTD) and will be increased in approximately 3-fold increments in subsequent cohorts until recommended Phase 2 dose (RP2D) determination. SYNB1891 is to be administered in the same manner and frequency as Arm 1. Atezolizumab will be administered in accordance with its recommended dose and schedule (1200 mg IV every 3 weeks) on day 1 of each of the 4 planned cycles. On days when atezolizumab and SYNB1891 are both administered, SYNB1891 will be administered first, followed by at least 1 hour of observation prior to the atezolizumab infusion. Combination doses will not be escalated above the SYNB1891 single-agent MTD established in Arm 1. Patients without progressive disease at the end of cycle 4 may receive additional cycles of SYNB1891 and atezolizumab on day 1 of each cycle for up to 24 months after initial dose of study treatment.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>SYNB1891</intervention_name>
    <description>Up to four 21-day cycles of escalating doses of SYNB1891 intratumoral injection on Days 1, 8 and 15 of Cycle 1 and Day 1 of cycles 2-4.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 1: SYNB1891 Monotherapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 2: SYNB1891 in Combination with Atezolizumab</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Atezolizumab</intervention_name>
    <description>Administered in accordance with its recommended dose and schedule (1200 mg IV Q3W) on Day 1 of each of the 4 planned 21-day cycles.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 2: SYNB1891 in Combination with Atezolizumab</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Able and willing to voluntarily complete the informed consent process (patient or
             patient's representative).

          2. Adults aged ≥ 18 years (on the day of signing informed consent) with histologically-
             or cytologically-confirmed stage III or IV advanced/metastatic solid tumor or lymphoma
             that is not surgically resectable and for which no therapeutic options are available
             to extend survival or for which the patient is not a candidate for standard-of-care
             therapy.

          3. Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group performance status ≤ 1.

          4. Life expectancy ≥ 3 months.

          5. ≥ 1 injectable, measurable (≥ 10 mm in diameter, or ≥ 15 mm for nodal lesions),
             eligible lesion as defined by RECIST 1.1 (Eisenhauer et al 2009), iRECIST (Seymour et
             al 2017), and/or LYRIC (Cheson et al 2016) and as assessed by the Investigator.
             Eligible lesions must be nonvisceral and must not be located in either the thoracic,
             abdominal or pelvic cavities or in the cranium and must be amenable to percutaneous
             injection and away from major blood vessels or neurological structures.

          6. Able to provide biopsies for biomarker analysis from injected and (if available)
             noninjected lesions at baseline and other time points during the study.

          7. Normal oxygenation without the use of supplemental oxygen.

          8. Adequate cardiac function, defined as follows:

               1. Left ventricular ejection fraction (LVEF) &gt; 50% by multi-gated acquisition (MUGA)
                  scan or echocardiogram (ECHO) performed within 6 months prior to the first dose
                  of study treatment provided the patient has not received any potential
                  cardiotoxic agents in the intervening period. Symptoms relating to left
                  ventricular dysfunction, cardiac arrhythmia, or cardiac ischemia must all be &lt;
                  Grade 1.

               2. QTc interval corrected for heart rate using Fridericia's formula (QTcF) &lt; 480
                  msec at screening.

          9. Laboratory values within the following ranges:

               -  Absolute neutrophil count ≥ 1500/µL

               -  Lymphocyte count ≥ 500/µL

               -  Platelets ≥ 100,000/µL without transfusion

               -  Hemoglobin ≥ 9.0 g/dL or ≥ 5.6 mmol/L1 (patients may be transfused to meet this
                  criterion)

               -  Estimated glomerular filtration rate (eGFR) &gt; 50 mL/min/1.73 m2

               -  Total bilirubin ≤ 1.5 × the upper limit of normal (ULN) OR direct bilirubin ≤ ULN
                  for participants with total bilirubin levels &gt; 1.5 × ULN (elevated indirect
                  bilirubin because of Gilbert's syndrome is permitted)

               -  Aspartate Aminotransferase (AST), Alanine Transaminase (ALT), and alkaline
                  phosphatase ≤ 2.5 × ULN (AST and ALT ≤ 5 × ULN for participants with liver
                  metastases and alkaline phosphatase ≤ 5 × ULN for participants with liver or bone
                  metastases)

               -  Albumin ≥ 2.5 g/dL

               -  International normalized ratio (INR) or prothrombin time (PT) or activated
                  partial thromboplastin time (aPTT) ≤ 1.5 × ULN unless participant is receiving
                  anticoagulant therapy as long as PT or aPTT is within therapeutic range of
                  intended use of anticoagulants

               -  (Thyroid stimulating hormone) TSH within the normal reference range or on stable
                  thyroid replacement therapy

         10. Agree to use an acceptable method of contraception after informed consent, throughout
             the study, and for 5 months after the last dose of SYNB1891 or atezolizumab.

             Additional inclusion criteria that apply only to Arm 2 study participants are as
             follows:

         11. Patients must have progressed on treatment with an anti-PD-1/L1 monoclonal antibody
             (mAb) administered either as monotherapy, or in combination with other checkpoint
             inhibitors (CPIs) or other therapies, if indicated (if CPI therapy is not indicated as
             a part of standard of care therapy, patients may be CPI naïve).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Chemotherapy, radiation, or biological cancer therapy within 14 days prior to the
             first dose of study treatment, or failure of any AEs to recover to Baseline or NCI
             CTCAE Grade 1, except for any grade of alopecia from AEs caused by cancer therapeutics
             administered &gt; 28 days earlier.

          2. Systemic immunostimulatory agents (including, but not limited to, interferon (IFN) and
             (interleukin) IL-2) within 28 days or 5 drug elimination half-lives (whichever is
             longer) prior to initiation of study treatment.

          3. Allogeneic hematopoietic stem cell transplantation within the last 5 years (patients
             who have had a transplant &gt; 5 years ago are eligible provided that no symptoms of
             graft versus-host disease are present) that requires current use of immunosuppressors.

          4. Receipt of a live vaccine within 90 days prior to the first dose of study treatment or
             anticipation of a need for such a vaccine during treatment.

          5. Receipt of warfarin or other oral anticoagulants within 7 days prior to the first dose
             of study treatment. Patients may switch to enoxaparin, with holding of the dose the
             day before i.t. injection of SYNB1891 (if holding the dose is not contraindicated).

          6. Receipt of antibiotics within 7 days prior to the first dose of study treatment.

          7. Participation in a study of an investigational agent and receipt of study therapy or
             use of an investigational device within 28 days prior to the first dose of study
             treatment.

          8. Diagnosed immunodeficiency or current use of chronic systemic steroid therapy in
             excess of replacement doses (prednisone ≤ 10 mg/day or equivalent is acceptable) or
             any other form of immunosuppressive medication within 7 days prior to the first dose
             of study treatment.

          9. Anticipated requirement of any other form of antineoplastic therapy while on study.

         10. History of a second malignancy, unless potentially curative treatment has been
             completed, with no evidence of malignancy for 2 years.

         11. Clinically active central nervous system (CNS) metastases and/or carcinomatous
             meningitis (stable brain metastases are permitted if treatment was completed ≥ 28 days
             prior to the first dose of study treatment).

         12. History of immune-mediated vasculitis, pancreatitis, colitis, hepatitis, or nephritis.

         13. History of immune-related AEs requiring discontinuation of prior PD-1/PD-L1 therapy.

         14. Active or history of autoimmune disease or immune deficiency, including, but not
             limited to, myasthenia gravis, myositis, autoimmune hepatitis, systemic lupus
             erythematosus, rheumatoid arthritis, inflammatory bowel disease, antiphospholipid
             antibody syndrome, Wegener granulomatosis, Sjögren syndrome, Guillain-Barré syndrome,
             or multiple sclerosis, with the following exceptions:

               1. Patients with a history of autoimmune-related hypothyroidism who are on thyroid
                  replacement hormone are eligible for the study.

               2. Patients with controlled Type 1 diabetes mellitus who are on an insulin regimen
                  are eligible for the study.

               3. Patients with eczema, psoriasis, lichen simplex chronicus, or vitiligo with
                  dermatologic manifestations only (e.g., patients with psoriatic arthritis are
                  excluded) are eligible for the study provided all of following conditions are
                  met:

               1. Rash must cover &lt; 10% of body surface area;

               2. Disease is well controlled at baseline and requires only low-potency topical
                  corticosteroids;

               3. No occurrence of acute exacerbations of the underlying condition requiring
                  psoralen plus ultraviolet A radiation, methotrexate, retinoids, biologic agents,
                  oral calcineurin inhibitors, or high potency or oral corticosteroids within the
                  previous 12 months.

         15. Allergy to antibiotics that precludes treatment for infection with E. coli Nissle
             1917.

         16. Human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) and/or hepatitis B or C infection(s) unless
             screening tests indicate negative viral load.

         17. Known active tuberculosis.

         18. Grade 3 or higher infection according to NCI CTCAE within 28 days prior to initiation
             of study treatment, including, but not limited to, hospitalization for complications
             of infection, bacteremia, or severe pneumonia.

         19. Failure to fully recover from the effects of major surgery. Surgeries that required
             general anesthesia must be completed &gt; 14 days before the first dose of study drug.
             Surgery requiring regional/epidural anesthesia must be completed &gt; 72 hours before the
             first dose of study treatment and participants should be recovered.

         20. Heart failure of New York Heart Association Class 3 or greater, history of pericardial
             disease, restrictive cardiomyopathy, or unstable angina or recent myocardial
             infarction within 3 to 6 months prior to the first dose of study treatment.

         21. Any other medical condition that might confound the results of the study, interfere
             with the participant's participation, or is not in the best interest of the
             participant, in the opinion of the treating Investigator.

         22. Pregnant or breastfeeding or anticipated conception or fathering of children within
             the projected duration of the study and for 5 months after the last dose of SYNB1891
             or atezolizumab.

             Additional exclusion criteria that apply only to Arm 2 study participants are as
             follows:

         23. History of a severe allergic anaphylactic reaction following treatment with a PD-1 mAb
             or to chimeric or humanized antibodies or fusion proteins.

         24. History of idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis, organizing pneumonia (e.g., bronchiolitis
             obliterans), drug-induced pneumonitis requiring treatment, or idiopathic pneumonitis,
             or evidence of active pneumonitis on screening chest CT scan.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Richard Riese, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Synlogic</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Andrew Marsh</last_name>
    <phone>(617) 401-9975</phone>
    <email>andrew.marsh@synlogictx.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Colorado Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Aurora</city>
        <state>Colorado</state>
        <zip>80045</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Matthew Skoch</last_name>
      <phone>720-848-0668</phone>
      <email>matthew.skoch@cuanschutz.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Karl D Lewis, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hackensack University John Theurer Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hackensack</city>
        <state>New Jersey</state>
        <zip>07601</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Chelsea McCabe</last_name>
      <email>chelsea.mccabe@hackensackmeridian.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Martin Gutierrez, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Pittsburgh</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pittsburgh</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>15232</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Krystle Eaton</last_name>
      <phone>412-623-7957</phone>
      <email>mientkiewiczk@upmc.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jason J Luke, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mary Crowley Cancer Research</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dallas</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>75230</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Karina Martinez</last_name>
      <phone>972-566-3032</phone>
      <email>kmartinez@marycrowley.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>James Strauss, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>MD Anderson Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Abha Adat</last_name>
      <phone>713-745-4297</phone>
      <email>aadat@mdanderson.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Filip Janku, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 12, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 15, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">November 18, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 23, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 23, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 25, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>solid tumor</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Atezolizumab</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

