<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04167839</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>TWU protocol# 19711</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04167839</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effects of Sensory Diets on Children's Sensory Processing Skills, Psychosocial Skills, and Classroom Engagement</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effects of Sensory Diets on a Child's Sensory Processing Skills, Psychosocial Skills, and Classroom Engagement</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Pingale, Vidya, OTR</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Tina S. Fletcher, EdD, MFA, OTR</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Catherine Candler, PhD, OTR</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Noralyn Pickens, PhD, OT</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Karen Dunlap, EdD</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Pingale, Vidya, OTR</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study investigated the effects of a sensory diet intervention program on five children
      with a sensory processing disorder. The effect was investigated on children's sensory
      processing skills, psychosocial skills, and classroom engagement.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Sensory diets are one of the interventions occupational therapists use in school-based
      settings to manage manifestations of sensory processing disorder. However, very few studies
      have investigated the effectiveness of sensory diets, and the results of these studies were
      mixed. Past studies also had methodological limitations. Therefore, this study investigated
      the effect of sensory diets on children's sensory processing skills, psychosocial skills, and
      engagement in classroom activities. This study used a single-subject ABCA design. Five
      children between the ages of five and eleven years participated in the study. The study
      consisted of an initial baseline phase A1, the control intervention phase B, sensory diets
      intervention phase C, and the second baseline phase A2. Each phase lasted for seven days. The
      PI videotaped each participant for fifteen minutes each school day during all phases to
      collect the data. The participants were videotaped during classroom group activities. Visual
      analysis of the data showed that sensory diets had a positive effect on participants' sensory
      processing, psychosocial skills, and classroom engagement.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 6, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">February 15, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">February 15, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>Second observers were masked from participants' evaluation data and treatment phase</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in frequency of a target behaviors related to psycho-social behaviors</measure>
    <time_frame>The data was collected for 28 days; each day for each phase for 15 minutes.</time_frame>
    <description>This outcome measure was individualized for each participant and detected change in frequency of psycho-social behaviors. The target behavior was identified and individualized based on the analysis of the intake data using classroom observations, Sensory profile school companion 2nd edition results, Behavior assessment system for children 3rd edition results, and teacher interview.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in duration of a target behavior related to off-task behaviors.</measure>
    <time_frame>The data was collected for 28 days; each day for each phase for 15 minutes.</time_frame>
    <description>This outcome measure individualized for each participant and detected change in duration of off-task behaviors. The target behavior was identified and individualized based on the analysis of the intake data using classroom observations, Sensory profile school companion 2nd edition results, Behavior assessment system for children 3rd edition results, and teacher interview.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in duration of a target behavior related to sensory seeking behaviors.</measure>
    <time_frame>The data was collected for 28 days; each day for each phase for 15 minutes.</time_frame>
    <description>This outcome measure individualized for each participant and detected change in duration of sensory seeking behaviors. The target behavior was identified and individualized based on the analysis of the intake data using classroom observations, Sensory profile school companion 2nd edition results, Behavior assessment system for children 3rd edition results, and teacher interview.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">5</enrollment>
  <condition>Sensory Processing Disorder</condition>
  <condition>Special Education</condition>
  <condition>Autism</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sensory diet</intervention_name>
    <description>Sensory diets are one of the interventions occupational therapists use in school-based settings to manage manifestations of sensory processing disorder. Sensory diets are composed of exercises and multisensory activities that are tailored for children and provide them sensorimotor experiences to facilitate their participation in daily activities.</description>
    <other_name>Non-therapeutic activities or activities without a therapeutic goal (Placebo)</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        - Children between the ages of four and eleven years and attending pre-kindergarten through
        fourth grade

          -  Children eligible for occupational therapy services under the special education
             eligibility criteria or under section 504 of the Rehabilitation Act of 1973-subpart D.
             This subpart of section 504 ensures children with disabilities who do not meet the
             eligibility criteria for special education services and are placed in general
             education classrooms receive the necessary support and related services (such as
             occupational therapy) to fully participate in general education classrooms.

          -  Children who scored in the Definite Difference range (+ 2 SD) or Probable Difference
             (+ 1 SD) ranges on two or more sections or quadrants on the Sensory Profile-2, Teacher
             Questionnaire (SP-2 Teacher Questionnaire; Dunn, 2015) were included in this study

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Children with medical concerns, such as cardiac conditions, posing risk to participate in
        resistive (strenuous) gross motor activities or children who used mobility devices were
        excluded from the study as these conditions may have hindered their participation in
        sensory diet activities.

          -  Children who were on medications, such as stimulants, anti-anxiety or anti-convulsive
             medications were excluded from the study as these medications may influence the
             clinical representation of SPD and interfere with the study outcomes.

          -  Children who were currently receiving sensory diets or received sensory diets six
             months prior to the beginning of the study were excluded from the study to control for
             confounding.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>4 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>11 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Vidya Pingale</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cliffside Park</city>
        <state>New Jersey</state>
        <zip>07010</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fazlioğlu Y, Baran G. A sensory integration therapy program on sensory problems for children with autism. Percept Mot Skills. 2008 Apr;106(2):415-22.</citation>
    <PMID>18556898</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lopez, M., &amp; Swinth, Y. (2008). A group proprioceptive program's effect on physical aggression in children. Journal of Occupational Therapy, Schools &amp; Early Intervention, 1(2), 147-166. doi: 10.1080/19411240802313044</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Case-Smith J, Weaver LL, Fristad MA. A systematic review of sensory processing interventions for children with autism spectrum disorders. Autism. 2015 Feb;19(2):133-48. doi: 10.1177/1362361313517762. Epub 2014 Jan 29. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24477447</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Watling R, Hauer S. Effectiveness of Ayres Sensory Integration® and Sensory-Based Interventions for People With Autism Spectrum Disorder: A Systematic Review. Am J Occup Ther. 2015 Sep-Oct;69(5):6905180030p1-12. doi: 10.5014/ajot.2015.018051. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26356655</PMID>
  </reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Devlin S, Healy O, Leader G, Hughes BM. Comparison of behavioral intervention and sensory-integration therapy in the treatment of challenging behavior. J Autism Dev Disord. 2011 Oct;41(10):1303-20. doi: 10.1007/s10803-010-1149-x.</citation>
    <PMID>21161577</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>November 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 11, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 16, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">November 19, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 16, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 16, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 19, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Texas Woman's University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Pingale, Vidya, OTR</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Doctoral Student</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

