<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04163627</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>RECHMPL19_0505</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04163627</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Changing Trends in HCC Procedures</brief_title>
  <official_title>Epidemiology of Technical Procedures for the Treatment of Hepatocellular Carcinoma: Country-wide Trends From 2009 to 2019</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University Hospital, Montpellier</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University Hospital, Montpellier</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      In France, as in most countries, the incidence of primary liver cancer has increased
      significantly since the 1980s. In the United States, a study estimating cancer incidence and
      mortality rates in the coming years predicts that primary liver cancer will become the 3rd
      leading cause of cancer death from 2030 onwards, behind lung and pancreatic cancer, but ahead
      of colorectal cancer. This increase in incidence could be explained on the one hand by an
      increase in the incidence of chronic liver diseases, particularly those related to alcohol
      and metabolic steatopathies in the West, and on the other hand by improved management of the
      consequences of cirrhotic disease, which in turn increases the time needed for hepatocellular
      carcinoma (HCC) to form and develop. The management of a patient with hepatocellular
      carcinoma is complex because of the underlying cirrhotic disease, which hinders the
      development of many therapies. Thus, the patient's prognosis depends as much on the tumour
      extension as on the severity of the underlying chronic liver disease, and the choice of
      appropriate treatment is based on optimizing the balance between maximum antitumor efficacy
      and limited liver toxicity.

      It is in this context that minimally invasive technical acts, whether local or
      local-regional, have developed significantly in recent years. Percutaneous tumor destruction
      techniques have become highly diversified with the development of microwave ablatherm,
      multipolar radiofrequency, or irreversible electroporation. For intra-arterial treatments,
      hepatic arterial chemoembolization remains the reference treatment for BCLC B stages.
      Alongside it, Yttrium 90 radio-embolization is booming, although its precise place remains to
      be defined in the therapeutic arsenal. Surgical techniques have also progressed, with the
      development of laparoscopic resections and improved liver transplant management. Finally,
      external radiotherapy is a recourse solution that can make it possible to propose a
      therapeutic solution in selected patients.

      This multidisciplinary management of the HCC is in constant evolution and improvement, which
      justifies regularly carrying out an inventory of the frequency of these various technical
      acts at the national level. The objective of our study is to analyze the evolution, over the
      last 10 years and at a national level, of the various technical procedures available in the
      HCC therapeutic arsenal based on data from the french national PMSI database.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Design Observational retrospective epidemiological nationwide cohort

      Data source Data will be obtained from the French Programme for the Medicalisation of
      Information Systems (PMSI) database, which contains all discharge abstracts from all
      hospitals nationwide. The PMSI includes data on all hospital activities, whether acute
      (Medecine chirurgiae Obstetrique [MCO]), chronic (Soins de Suite et de Réadaptation [SSR]),
      or home-care (Hospitalization à Domicile [HAD]). Discharge abstracts include information on
      the patient's demographics, principal and associated diagnosis codes according to the tenth
      revision of the International Classification of Diseases (ICD-10) [10], procedure codes, mode
      of hospitalization (elective, emergency, or hospital transfer), mode of discharge (home,
      hospital transfer, death; the latter was used to compute survival), duration of hospital
      stay, patient's home address, and hospital identification code. In addition, each patient has
      an anonymous alphanumerical identifier that enables all hospital admissions throughout the
      country to be traced. The databases will be provided for the calendar years 2009 to 2018
      included.

      Data extraction

        -  date: 01/01/2009 to 31/12/2018

        -  ICD-10 diagnostic code: C22.0 (liver cell carcinoma - HCC or hepatoma) and C22.9
           (malignant neoplasm of liver, unspecified)

        -  Patient: age, gender, co-morbidities, postal code

        -  Cause of chronic liver disease, presence of cirrhosis and severity

        -  1st diagnosis of HCC or recurrence

        -  Hospital of care, status and postal code

        -  Number and type of therapeutic procedures performed per year (each procedure will be
           counted according to whether it is the first treatment of HCC or the treatment of a
           recurrence):

             -  Liver transplantation

             -  Destruction of hepatic tumor by radiofrequency, percutaneous

             -  Destruction of hepatic tumor by radiofrequency, intraoperatively

             -  Hepatectomy and liver resection:

             -  Preoperative portal embolization

             -  Liver arterial chemo-embolization:

             -  Yttrium 90 Radio Embolization

        -  Survival from diagnosis and 1st treatment

      The expected results of this study are of major importance. On the one hand, this study will
      provide an overview of the current situation regarding the management of HCC at a national
      level, by analysing the evolutionary trends of the various therapeutic solutions. The
      analysis of the geographical variability of care that may exist between different health
      structures at different levels of expertise, but also at regional or departmental level, is
      of major importance in order to detect and explain possible differences in terms of
      prognosis. These data may be of great interest to health authorities or to potential future
      investigators who will be committed to conducting new prospective projects based on solid and
      up-to-date data.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 30, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 25, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 1, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Retrospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Technical procedures evolutiveness</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day</time_frame>
    <description>Quantify at the national level the progression from 2009 to 2019 in the number of procedures performed as part of the treatment of HCC, divided into percutaneous or intraoperative tumour destruction, chemo-embolisation, radio-embolisation, liver surgery and liver transplantation.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Regional disparities</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day</time_frame>
    <description>look for possible regional disparities according to prognosis and access to innovative care</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">1000</enrollment>
  <condition>Hepatocellular Carcinoma</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        patient with hepatocellular carcinoma with a technical procedure for the treatment of HCC:
        liver transplantation, liver resection, thermal ablation, chemoembolization or
        radioembolization
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion criteria:

        An individual must fulfill all of the following criteria in order to be eligible for study
        enrollment:

          -  Aged above 18 years

          -  ICD-10 diagnostic code: C22.0 (liver cell carcinoma - HCC or hepatoma) and C22.9
             (malignant neoplasm of liver, unspecified)

          -  Having had at least one technical procedure for management of an HCC

          -  Date of procedure: 01/01/2009 to 31/12/2018

        Exclusion criteria:

          -  Age under 18

          -  Histological type different of HCC

          -  Systemic/oral or palliative treatment
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>BORIS GUIU, PU-PH</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>University Hospital, Montpellier</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>BORIS GUIU, PU-PH</last_name>
    <phone>467337546</phone>
    <phone_ext>33</phone_ext>
    <email>b-guiu@chu-montpellier.fr</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Christophe Cassinotto, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>67337380</phone>
    <phone_ext>33</phone_ext>
    <email>c-cassinotto@chu-montpellier.fr</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Uhmontpellier</name>
      <address>
        <city>Montpellier</city>
        <zip>34295</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>BORIS GUIU, PU-PH</last_name>
      <phone>467337546</phone>
      <phone_ext>33</phone_ext>
      <email>b-guiu@chu-montpellier.fr</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Christophe Cassinotto, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>467337380</phone>
      <phone_ext>33</phone_ext>
      <email>c-cassinotto@chu-montpellier.fr</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 13, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 13, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">November 15, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 9, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 9, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 10, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Technical procedure for treatment of HCC: either liver transplantation, liver resection, thermal ablation, chemoembolization, or radioembolization</keyword>
  <keyword>Chronic liver diseases</keyword>
  <keyword>Interventional Radiology</keyword>
  <keyword>Liver surgery</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Hepatocellular</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>NC</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

