<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04165473</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>EK1592/2019</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04165473</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Training Program for Developing Social- and Personal Resources</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Training Program for Developing Social- and Personal Resources and Its Effects on Emotional, Physical and Social Wellbeing in Adults</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Medical University of Vienna</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Medical University of Vienna</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      In this study, a new psychosocial training for social relationships for mildly and heavily
      stressed adults will be evaluated. In a 6-module course, with four 3-day modules and two
      5-day modules in the timeframe of one year, participants learn ways to strengthen their
      personal resources to establish effective social relationships and to develop skills as a
      social being. In between the module courses, the participants take 5 single sessions with an
      instructed trainer and document 10 conversations/social situations where they successfully
      applied the new skills. Each group consists of 15 to 35 participants. For this study, a total
      of 400 persons will be recruited. Approx. one hundred participants self-select to the
      intervention-social- and personal resources-course group and 100 individuals to the control
      group (matched for gender, age, employment status, family status, relationship status,
      perceived stress, daily stressors, and stressful life events in the past year) as well as 100
      partner controls having a close relationship to the participants and 100 partner controls
      having a close relationship to the matched controls are planned. During the course of the
      training, the participants are thought to develop in a way that lowers their perceived stress
      level in daily life, improves their health behaviour and health status, leads to a higher
      satisfaction with their lives, improves the quality of their social relationships and results
      in higher wellbeing.

      Before, during and 6 months after the training the participants and the control group will be
      evaluated with standardized questionnaires.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Human beings perceive stress differently and several bio-psycho-social factors, as well as
      personal and environmental factors influence how persons can manage and cope with stress.
      Concepts, such as resilience, facilitate positive attitudes towards self-management of
      stressful life situations. Phylogenetically, (positive) stress produced/s adequate reactions
      of humans in difficult or dangerous situations, like to fight or run away in the time when
      human beings were predominantly hunter-gatherers. However, persistent stress, as well as the
      inability to sufficiently cope with stress have several negative consequences for the
      physical and mental health of humans. Negative stress is a major contributor to chronic
      diseases, like cardiovascular diseases, cancer, respiratory disorders, mental diseases
      including depression, but also the occurrence of accidental injuries. Insufficient coping can
      result in a harmful health behaviour at first and in the long term to a higher overall
      morbidity and mortality. This means not only a personal, emotional and physical burden but
      also a financial burden for the society as a whole, as well as the health system of a
      country.

      On the other hand, satisfactory social relationships were found to have a stress buffering,
      positive effect on how people deal with stress and are beneficial for one's own health over
      the course of life. Satisfactory social relationships might even lead to longevity.

      The following research questions will be addressed in this study:

        1. Has a 1-year training program for social- and personal resources an influence on the
           perceived stress level, health behavior, health status, satisfaction with life, quality
           of social relationships, and wellbeing of the participants and the person they have a
           close relationship with compared to a matched control group in a quasi-experimental
           longitudinal study?

        2. Do the different items addressed during training (life goals, meaning in life, sense of
           coherence, social- and personal resources and transcendence) change in their perception
           by the participants or by persons the participants have a close relationship with
           compared to matched controls?

        3. Are the changes of these perceptions (concerning life goals, meaning in life, sense of
           coherence, social- and personal resources and transcendence) predictive for the changes
           of perceived stress level, health behaviour, health status, satisfaction with life,
           quality of social relationships, and wellbeing and how much does each of them
           contribute?

        4. If any changes occur, how sustainable are they during the longer-term observational
           period of 6 months after the training? In case the concepts underlying the development
           of the training can be corroborated, this would indicate a potential for developing
           personal resources in adult stage, foster a new understanding of how health can be
           maintained and improved, and give insight into healthy functioning and the role of
           social relationships.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 14, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 31, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 31, 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>The study has a parallel group, quasi-experimental, longitudinal design. The control group (CG) is matched with the intervention group (IG) by gender (male/female/divers), age (+/-5), employment status (full time employed/part-time employed/unemployed/in education/educational leave/maternity or paternity leave/retired), family status (children/no children), relationship status (single/in a permanent relationship/undecided), perceived stress (+/-3), daily stressors (+/-30) and stressful life events within the last 3 months (yes/no). The matching is performed stepwise beginning with 7 matching characteristics down until 4 characteristics in case a large enough sample size cannot be reached. Control group members with less than 4 matching characteristics will be excluded from the study. For each participant of the training group and the matched control group a person they have a close relationship to will be included in the study.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Perceived Stress Scale score change between T0 and T5</measure>
    <time_frame>before the intervention and at the end of the intervention (on average one year after first assessment)</time_frame>
    <description>the change on the self-reported Perceived Stress Scale (PSS) (score range: 0-40) from baseline (start of the training program = T0) until end of the training program (= T5)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Perceived Stress Scale score change between T0 and T6</measure>
    <time_frame>before the intervention and 6 months after the intervention has ended</time_frame>
    <description>the change on the self-reported Perceived Stress Scale (PSS) (score range: 0-40) from baseline (start of the training program = T0) until end of the follow-up period, 6 months after the training program has ended (= T6)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of Health Status between T0 and T5</measure>
    <time_frame>before the intervention and at the end of the intervention (on average one year after first assessment)</time_frame>
    <description>the change on the Giessen physical complaints questionnaire (GBB-24) (score range: 0-96) from baseline (start of the training program = T0) until end of the training program (= T5)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of Health Status between T0 and T6</measure>
    <time_frame>before the intervention and 6 months after the intervention has ended</time_frame>
    <description>the change on the Giessen physical complaints questionnaire (GBB-24) (score range: 0-96) from baseline (start of the training program = T0) until end of the follow-up period, 6 months after the training program has ended (= T6)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of Wellbeing between T0 and T5</measure>
    <time_frame>before the intervention and at the end of the intervention (on average one year after first assessment)</time_frame>
    <description>the change on the World Health Organisation questionnaire (WHO-5) (score range: 0-25) from baseline (start of the training program = T0) until end of the training program (= T5)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of Wellbeing between T0 and T6</measure>
    <time_frame>before the intervention and 6 months after the intervention has ended</time_frame>
    <description>the change on the World Health Organisation questionnaire (WHO-5) (score range: 0-25) from baseline (start of the training program = T0) until end of the follow-up period, 6 months after the training program has ended (= T6)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of Quality of Relationships between T0 and T5</measure>
    <time_frame>before the intervention and at the end of the intervention (on average one year after first assessment)</time_frame>
    <description>the change on the Evaluation of Social Systems questionnaire (EVOS) (score range: 0-120) and Experience in Social Systems questionnaire (EXIS) (score range: 1-6) from baseline (start of the training program = T0) until end of the training program (= T5)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of Quality of Relationships between T0 and T6</measure>
    <time_frame>before the intervention and 6 months after the intervention has ended</time_frame>
    <description>the change on the Evaluation of Social Systems questionnaire (EVOS) (score range: 0-120) and Experience in Social Systems questionnaire (EXIS) (score range: 1-6) from baseline (start of the training program = T0) until end of the follow-up period, 6 months after the training program has ended (= T6)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of Satisfaction with Life between T0 and T5</measure>
    <time_frame>before the intervention and at the end of the intervention (on average one year after first assessment)</time_frame>
    <description>the change on the Life Satisfaction questionnaire (LS-4) (score range: 4-20) from baseline (start of the training program = T0) until end of the training program (= T5)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of Satisfaction with Life between T0 and T6</measure>
    <time_frame>before the intervention and 6 months after the intervention has ended</time_frame>
    <description>the change on the Life Satisfaction questionnaire (LS-4) (score range: 4-20) from baseline (start of the training program = T0) until end of the follow-up period, 6 months after the training program has ended (= T6)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of Health Behavior between T0 and T5</measure>
    <time_frame>before the intervention and at the end of the intervention (on average one year after first assessment)</time_frame>
    <description>the change on the Questionnaire for Health Behaviour Evaluation (FEG) questionnaire, sections physical activity (score range: -20-26), sleep (score range: 10-50), psychosocial burden (score range: 2-46) from baseline (start of the training program = T0) until end of the training program (= T5)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of Health Behavior between T0 and T6</measure>
    <time_frame>before the intervention and 6 months after the intervention has ended</time_frame>
    <description>the change on the Questionnaire for Health Behaviour Evaluation (FEG) questionnaire, sections physical activity (score range: -20-26), sleep (score range: 10-50), psychosocial burden (score range: 2-46) from baseline (start of the training program = T0) until end of the follow-up period, 6 months after the training program has ended (= T6)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">400</enrollment>
  <condition>Stress, Psychological</condition>
  <condition>Stress, Emotional</condition>
  <condition>Health Behavior</condition>
  <condition>Satisfaction, Personal</condition>
  <condition>Health Status</condition>
  <condition>Psychophysiology</condition>
  <condition>Family Relations</condition>
  <condition>Program Evaluation</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>In a 6-module course, with four 3-day modules and two 5-day modules in the timeframe of one year, participants learn ways to strengthen their personal resources to establish effective social relationships and to develop skills as a social being. In between the module courses, the participants take 5 single sessions with an instructed trainer and document 10 conversations/social situations where they successfully applied the new skills.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention Group - Close Relationship</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Individuals having a close relationship to participants of the Intervention Group</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Individuals matched to the participants of the Intervention Group</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control Group - Close Relationship</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Individuals having a close relationship to participants of the Control Group</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Training Program for Developing Social- and Personal Resources</intervention_name>
    <description>The training-method shows how one's own resonance can be exposed in order to live the balance between one's own needs and those of others.
Living one's own resonance means: more quality of life, work-life balance, holistic health through living feelings and talents, live equal, respectful and loving relationships, more personal responsibility, authentic decision making find new role models in private and professional areas.
The teaching and learning methods of the trainings and seminars are implemented according to the latest state of brain research and enable new perspectives with regard to new learning strategies, goals, enthusiasm and motivation.
With the Kutschera-Resonanz® method we teach and learn to consciously use this unconscious reservoir so that completely new dimensions in thinking and acting open up.
In this training program the basic tools of communication and interaction according to the Kutschera-Resonanz® method are taught and experienced by the participants.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention Group</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Kutschera-Resonance-Practitioner</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  male, female, divers

          -  fluently German speaking

          -  between 18-70 years of age

          -  given informed consent

        Intervention Arm:

          -  a value of greater or equal to 19 on the perceived stress scale

          -  having completed 2 or more modules of the training

          -  intention or not sure yet to complete the whole training

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  not speaking German fluently

          -  being below 18 or above 70 years of age

          -  not given an informed consent

        Intervention Arm:

          -  a value smaller than 19 on the perceived stress scale

          -  plans to take only the first module or already has taken other modules first

          -  not having completed 2 or more modules of the training
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Christoph Janka, DI</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Medical Universtiy of Vienna</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Christoph Janka, DI</last_name>
    <phone>+4369917142413</phone>
    <email>n0025927@students.meduniwien.ac.at</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Institut Kutschera</name>
      <address>
        <city>Vienna</city>
        <country>Austria</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Christoph Janka, DI</last_name>
      <phone>+4369917142413</phone>
      <email>n0025927@students.meduniwien.ac.at</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Austria</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cohen S, Wills TA. Stress, social support, and the buffering hypothesis. Psychol Bull. 1985 Sep;98(2):310-57. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>3901065</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>House JS, Landis KR, Umberson D. Social relationships and health. Science. 1988 Jul 29;241(4865):540-5.</citation>
    <PMID>3399889</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Holt-Lunstad J, Smith TB, Layton JB. Social relationships and mortality risk: a meta-analytic review. PLoS Med. 2010 Jul 27;7(7):e1000316. doi: 10.1371/journal.pmed.1000316. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20668659</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sebanz N, Bekkering H, Knoblich G. Joint action: bodies and minds moving together. Trends Cogn Sci. 2006 Feb;10(2):70-6. Epub 2006 Jan 10.</citation>
    <PMID>16406326</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Garrod S, Pickering MJ. Joint action, interactive alignment, and dialog. Top Cogn Sci. 2009 Apr;1(2):292-304. doi: 10.1111/j.1756-8765.2009.01020.x.</citation>
    <PMID>25164934</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Melis AP. The evolutionary roots of human collaboration: coordination and sharing of resources. Ann N Y Acad Sci. 2013 Sep;1299:68-76. doi: 10.1111/nyas.12263. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25708081</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Melis AP, Grocke P, Kalbitz J, Tomasello M. One for You, One for Me: Humans' Unique Turn-Taking Skills. Psychol Sci. 2016 Jul;27(7):987-96. doi: 10.1177/0956797616644070. Epub 2016 May 25.</citation>
    <PMID>27225221</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Melis AP, Semmann D. How is human cooperation different? Philos Trans R Soc Lond B Biol Sci. 2010 Sep 12;365(1553):2663-74. doi: 10.1098/rstb.2010.0157. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20679110</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Warneken F, Tomasello M. Altruistic helping in human infants and young chimpanzees. Science. 2006 Mar 3;311(5765):1301-3.</citation>
    <PMID>16513986</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Warneken F, Tomasello M. The roots of human altruism. Br J Psychol. 2009 Aug;100(Pt 3):455-71. doi: 10.1348/000712608X379061. Epub 2008 Dec 5. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19063815</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nelson SK, Layous K, Cole SW, Lyubomirsky S. Do unto others or treat yourself? The effects of prosocial and self-focused behavior on psychological flourishing. Emotion. 2016 Sep;16(6):850-61. doi: 10.1037/emo0000178. Epub 2016 Apr 21.</citation>
    <PMID>27100366</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wedekind C, Braithwaite VA. The long-term benefits of human generosity in indirect reciprocity. Curr Biol. 2002 Jun 25;12(12):1012-5.</citation>
    <PMID>12123575</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Scott S, Knapp M, Henderson J, Maughan B. Financial cost of social exclusion: follow up study of antisocial children into adulthood. BMJ. 2001 Jul 28;323(7306):191.</citation>
    <PMID>11473907</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cacioppo JT, Hawkley LC, Crawford LE, Ernst JM, Burleson MH, Kowalewski RB, Malarkey WB, Van Cauter E, Berntson GG. Loneliness and health: potential mechanisms. Psychosom Med. 2002 May-Jun;64(3):407-17.</citation>
    <PMID>12021415</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Paradis AD, Koenen KC, Fitzmaurice GM, Buka SL. Impact of persistent and adolescent-limited antisocial behaviour on adult health outcomes. J Epidemiol Community Health. 2016 Oct;70(10):1004-10. doi: 10.1136/jech-2014-205140. Epub 2016 Apr 11.</citation>
    <PMID>27069087</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Twenge JM, Baumeister RF, DeWall CN, Ciarocco NJ, Bartels JM. Social exclusion decreases prosocial behavior. J Pers Soc Psychol. 2007 Jan;92(1):56-66.</citation>
    <PMID>17201542</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Layous K, Chancellor J, Lyubomirsky S. Positive activities as protective factors against mental health conditions. J Abnorm Psychol. 2014 Feb;123(1):3-12. doi: 10.1037/a0034709. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24661154</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Uchino BN. Social support and health: a review of physiological processes potentially underlying links to disease outcomes. J Behav Med. 2006 Aug;29(4):377-87. Epub 2006 Jun 7. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>16758315</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ackard DM, Neumark-Sztainer D, Story M, Perry C. Parent-child connectedness and behavioral and emotional health among adolescents. Am J Prev Med. 2006 Jan;30(1):59-66.</citation>
    <PMID>16414425</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Procidano ME, Heller K. Measures of perceived social support from friends and from family: three validation studies. Am J Community Psychol. 1983 Feb;11(1):1-24.</citation>
    <PMID>6837532</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ren XS. Marital status and quality of relationships: the impact on health perception. Soc Sci Med. 1997 Jan;44(2):241-9.</citation>
    <PMID>9015876</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gouin JP, Carter CS, Pournajafi-Nazarloo H, Glaser R, Malarkey WB, Loving TJ, Stowell J, Kiecolt-Glaser JK. Marital behavior, oxytocin, vasopressin, and wound healing. Psychoneuroendocrinology. 2010 Aug;35(7):1082-90. doi: 10.1016/j.psyneuen.2010.01.009. Epub 2010 Feb 9.</citation>
    <PMID>20144509</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kiecolt-Glaser JK, Gouin JP, Hantsoo L. Close relationships, inflammation, and health. Neurosci Biobehav Rev. 2010 Sep;35(1):33-8. doi: 10.1016/j.neubiorev.2009.09.003. Epub 2009 Sep 12. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19751761</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kiecolt-Glaser JK, McGuire L, Robles TF, Glaser R. Emotions, morbidity, and mortality: new perspectives from psychoneuroimmunology. Annu Rev Psychol. 2002;53:83-107. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>11752480</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Seeman TE. Social ties and health: the benefits of social integration. Ann Epidemiol. 1996 Sep;6(5):442-51. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>8915476</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Waldinger RJ, Cohen S, Schulz MS, Crowell JA. Security of attachment to spouses in late life: Concurrent and prospective links with cognitive and emotional wellbeing. Clin Psychol Sci. 2015 Jun 1;3(4):516-529.</citation>
    <PMID>26413428</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chopik WJ, O'Brien E. Happy you, healthy me? Having a happy partner is independently associated with better health in oneself. Health Psychol. 2017 Jan;36(1):21-30. doi: 10.1037/hea0000432. Epub 2016 Sep 19.</citation>
    <PMID>27642761</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Roberson PNE, Shorter RL, Woods S, Priest J. How health behaviors link romantic relationship dysfunction and physical health across 20 years for middle-aged and older adults. Soc Sci Med. 2018 Mar;201:18-26. doi: 10.1016/j.socscimed.2018.01.037. Epub 2018 Feb 3.</citation>
    <PMID>29427892</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rydstedt LW, Head J, Stansfeld SA, Woodley-Jones D. Quality of workplace social relationships and perceived health. Psychol Rep. 2012 Jun;110(3):781-90.</citation>
    <PMID>22897084</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Uchino BN, Cawthon RM, Smith TW, Light KC, McKenzie J, Carlisle M, Gunn H, Birmingham W, Bowen K. Social relationships and health: is feeling positive, negative, or both (ambivalent) about your social ties related to telomeres? Health Psychol. 2012 Nov;31(6):789-96. doi: 10.1037/a0026836. Epub 2012 Jan 9.</citation>
    <PMID>22229928</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fredrickson BL. The role of positive emotions in positive psychology. The broaden-and-build theory of positive emotions. Am Psychol. 2001 Mar;56(3):218-26.</citation>
    <PMID>11315248</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pressman SD, Cohen S. Does positive affect influence health? Psychol Bull. 2005 Nov;131(6):925-971. doi: 10.1037/0033-2909.131.6.925. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>16351329</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wang CS, Kenneth T, Ku G, Galinsky AD. Perspective-taking increases willingness to engage in intergroup contact. PLoS One. 2014 Jan 22;9(1):e85681. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0085681. eCollection 2014.</citation>
    <PMID>24465648</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ruiz-Aranda D, Extremera N, Pineda-Galán C. Emotional intelligence, life satisfaction and subjective happiness in female student health professionals: the mediating effect of perceived stress. J Psychiatr Ment Health Nurs. 2014 Mar;21(2):106-13. doi: 10.1111/jpm.12052. Epub 2013 Apr 12.</citation>
    <PMID>23578272</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yang SX, Jowett S, Chan DK. Effects of big-five personality traits on the quality of relationship and satisfaction in Chinese coach-athlete dyads. Scand J Med Sci Sports. 2015 Aug;25(4):568-80. doi: 10.1111/sms.12329. Epub 2014 Nov 4.</citation>
    <PMID>25367655</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gudsnuk K, Champagne FA. Epigenetic influence of stress and the social environment. ILAR J. 2012;53(3-4):279-88. doi: 10.1093/ilar.53.3-4.279. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23744967</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Daskalakis NP, Bagot RC, Parker KJ, Vinkers CH, de Kloet ER. The three-hit concept of vulnerability and resilience: toward understanding adaptation to early-life adversity outcome. Psychoneuroendocrinology. 2013 Sep;38(9):1858-73. doi: 10.1016/j.psyneuen.2013.06.008. Epub 2013 Jul 7. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23838101</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Romeo RD. Perspectives on stress resilience and adolescent neurobehavioral function. Neurobiol Stress. 2014 Nov 8;1:128-33. doi: 10.1016/j.ynstr.2014.11.001. eCollection 2015 Jan. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>27589663</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Masten AS. Ordinary magic. Resilience processes in development. Am Psychol. 2001 Mar;56(3):227-38.</citation>
    <PMID>11315249</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kobasa SC. Stressful life events, personality, and health: an inquiry into hardiness. J Pers Soc Psychol. 1979 Jan;37(1):1-11.</citation>
    <PMID>458548</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Baram TZ, Davis EP, Obenaus A, Sandman CA, Small SL, Solodkin A, Stern H. Fragmentation and unpredictability of early-life experience in mental disorders. Am J Psychiatry. 2012 Sep;169(9):907-15. doi: 10.1176/appi.ajp.2012.11091347. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22885631</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Krugers HJ, Arp JM, Xiong H, Kanatsou S, Lesuis SL, Korosi A, Joels M, Lucassen PJ. Early life adversity: Lasting consequences for emotional learning. Neurobiol Stress. 2016 Nov 27;6:14-21. doi: 10.1016/j.ynstr.2016.11.005. eCollection 2017 Feb. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>28229105</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Seedat S, Stein DJ, Jackson PB, Heeringa SG, Williams DR, Myer L. Life stress and mental disorders in the South African stress and health study. S Afr Med J. 2009 May;99(5 Pt 2):375-82.</citation>
    <PMID>19588801</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ansell EB, Gu P, Tuit K, Sinha R. Effects of cumulative stress and impulsivity on smoking status. Hum Psychopharmacol. 2012 Mar;27(2):200-8. doi: 10.1002/hup.1269.</citation>
    <PMID>22389084</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Laloyaux J, Dessart G, Van der Linden M, Lemaire M, Larøi F. Maladaptive emotion regulation strategies and stress sensitivity mediate the relation between adverse life events and attenuated positive psychotic symptoms. Cogn Neuropsychiatry. 2016;21(2):116-29. doi: 10.1080/13546805.2015.1137213. Epub 2016 Feb 1.</citation>
    <PMID>26829655</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Woodhead EL, Cronkite RC, Moos RH, Timko C. Coping strategies predictive of adverse outcomes among community adults. J Clin Psychol. 2014 Dec;70(12):1183-95. doi: 10.1002/jclp.21924. Epub 2013 Apr 29.</citation>
    <PMID>23629952</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Littleton H, Horsley S, John S, Nelson DV. Trauma coping strategies and psychological distress: A meta-analysis. J Trauma Stress. 2007 Dec;20(6):977-88.</citation>
    <PMID>18157893</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hanssen LM, Schutte NS, Malouff JM, Epel ES. The Relationship Between Childhood Psychosocial Stressor Level and Telomere Length: A Meta-Analysis. Health Psychol Res. 2017 May 16;5(1):6378. doi: 10.4081/hpr.2017.6378. eCollection 2017 May 16.</citation>
    <PMID>28603779</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schaakxs R, Wielaard I, Verhoeven JE, Beekman AT, Penninx BW, Comijs HC. Early and recent psychosocial stress and telomere length in older adults. Int Psychogeriatr. 2016 Mar;28(3):405-13. doi: 10.1017/S1041610215001155. Epub 2015 Aug 12.</citation>
    <PMID>26265356</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wu G, Feder A, Cohen H, Kim JJ, Calderon S, Charney DS, Mathé AA. Understanding resilience. Front Behav Neurosci. 2013 Feb 15;7:10. doi: 10.3389/fnbeh.2013.00010. eCollection 2013.</citation>
    <PMID>23422934</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Oliveira BS, Zunzunegui MV, Quinlan J, Fahmi H, Tu MT, Guerra RO. Systematic review of the association between chronic social stress and telomere length: A life course perspective. Ageing Res Rev. 2016 Mar;26:37-52. doi: 10.1016/j.arr.2015.12.006. Epub 2015 Dec 28. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26732034</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Epel ES, Blackburn EH, Lin J, Dhabhar FS, Adler NE, Morrow JD, Cawthon RM. Accelerated telomere shortening in response to life stress. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2004 Dec 7;101(49):17312-5. Epub 2004 Dec 1.</citation>
    <PMID>15574496</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cohen S, Tyrrell DA, Smith AP. Negative life events, perceived stress, negative affect, and susceptibility to the common cold. J Pers Soc Psychol. 1993 Jan;64(1):131-40.</citation>
    <PMID>8421249</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Buysse DJ. Sleep health: can we define it? Does it matter? Sleep. 2014 Jan 1;37(1):9-17. doi: 10.5665/sleep.3298.</citation>
    <PMID>24470692</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Prather AA, Puterman E, Lin J, O'Donovan A, Krauss J, Tomiyama AJ, Epel ES, Blackburn EH. Shorter leukocyte telomere length in midlife women with poor sleep quality. J Aging Res. 2011;2011:721390. doi: 10.4061/2011/721390. Epub 2011 Oct 20.</citation>
    <PMID>22046530</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hirotsu C, Tufik S, Andersen ML. Interactions between sleep, stress, and metabolism: From physiological to pathological conditions. Sleep Sci. 2015 Nov;8(3):143-52. doi: 10.1016/j.slsci.2015.09.002. Epub 2015 Sep 28. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26779321</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kent RG, Uchino BN, Cribbet MR, Bowen K, Smith TW. Social Relationships and Sleep Quality. Ann Behav Med. 2015 Dec;49(6):912-7. doi: 10.1007/s12160-015-9711-6.</citation>
    <PMID>25976874</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Masoudnia E. Impact of weak social ties and networks on poor sleep quality: A case study of Iranian employees. Asian J Psychiatr. 2015 Dec;18:42-8. doi: 10.1016/j.ajp.2015.10.005. Epub 2015 Oct 19.</citation>
    <PMID>26494526</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hintsanen M, Puttonen S, Smith K, Törnroos M, Jokela M, Pulkki-Råback L, Hintsa T, Merjonen P, Dwyer T, Raitakari OT, Venn A, Keltikangas-Järvinen L. Five-factor personality traits and sleep: evidence from two population-based cohort studies. Health Psychol. 2014 Oct;33(10):1214-23. doi: 10.1037/hea0000105. Epub 2014 Aug 18.</citation>
    <PMID>25133841</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zhi TF, Sun XM, Li SJ, Wang QS, Cai J, Li LZ, Li YX, Xu MJ, Wang Y, Chu XF, Wang ZD, Jiang XY. Associations of sleep duration and sleep quality with life satisfaction in elderly Chinese: The mediating role of depression. Arch Gerontol Geriatr. 2016 Jul-Aug;65:211-7. doi: 10.1016/j.archger.2016.03.023. Epub 2016 Mar 30.</citation>
    <PMID>27100684</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ben Simon E, Walker MP. Sleep loss causes social withdrawal and loneliness. Nat Commun. 2018 Aug 14;9(1):3146. doi: 10.1038/s41467-018-05377-0.</citation>
    <PMID>30108218</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Puterman E, Lin J, Blackburn E, O'Donovan A, Adler N, Epel E. The power of exercise: buffering the effect of chronic stress on telomere length. PLoS One. 2010 May 26;5(5):e10837. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0010837.</citation>
    <PMID>20520771</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Iwasaki Y, Zuzanek J, Mannell RC. The effects of physically active leisure on stress-health relationships. Can J Public Health. 2001 May-Jun;92(3):214-8.</citation>
    <PMID>11496634</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Almeida OP, Khan KM, Hankey GJ, Yeap BB, Golledge J, Flicker L. 150 minutes of vigorous physical activity per week predicts survival and successful ageing: a population-based 11-year longitudinal study of 12 201 older Australian men. Br J Sports Med. 2014 Feb;48(3):220-5. doi: 10.1136/bjsports-2013-092814. Epub 2013 Sep 3.</citation>
    <PMID>24002240</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Arem H, Moore SC, Patel A, Hartge P, Berrington de Gonzalez A, Visvanathan K, Campbell PT, Freedman M, Weiderpass E, Adami HO, Linet MS, Lee IM, Matthews CE. Leisure time physical activity and mortality: a detailed pooled analysis of the dose-response relationship. JAMA Intern Med. 2015 Jun;175(6):959-67. doi: 10.1001/jamainternmed.2015.0533.</citation>
    <PMID>25844730</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ekblom-Bak E, Ekblom B, Vikström M, de Faire U, Hellénius ML. The importance of non-exercise physical activity for cardiovascular health and longevity. Br J Sports Med. 2014 Feb;48(3):233-8. doi: 10.1136/bjsports-2012-092038. Epub 2013 Oct 28.</citation>
    <PMID>24167194</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bize R, Johnson JA, Plotnikoff RC. Physical activity level and health-related quality of life in the general adult population: a systematic review. Prev Med. 2007 Dec;45(6):401-15. Epub 2007 Jul 21. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>17707498</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fox KR. The influence of physical activity on mental well-being. Public Health Nutr. 1999 Sep;2(3A):411-8. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>10610081</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Paluska SA, Schwenk TL. Physical activity and mental health: current concepts. Sports Med. 2000 Mar;29(3):167-80. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>10739267</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Böhm AW, Mielke GI, da Cruz MF, Ramirez VV, Wehrmesister FC. Social Support and Leisure-Time Physical Activity Among the Elderly: A Population-Based Study. J Phys Act Health. 2016 Jun;13(6):599-605. doi: 10.1123/jpah.2015-0277. Epub 2015 Dec 21.</citation>
    <PMID>26696310</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bessey D. Preferences, personality and health behaviors: results from an explorative economic experiment. Int J Health Econ Manag. 2018 Dec;18(4):437-456. doi: 10.1007/s10754-018-9236-1. Epub 2018 Feb 23.</citation>
    <PMID>29476285</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Diener E, Emmons RA, Larsen RJ, Griffin S. The Satisfaction With Life Scale. J Pers Assess. 1985 Feb;49(1):71-5.</citation>
    <PMID>16367493</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Boehm JK, Winning A, Segerstrom S, Kubzansky LD. Variability Modifies Life Satisfaction's Association With Mortality Risk in Older Adults. Psychol Sci. 2015 Jul;26(7):1063-70. doi: 10.1177/0956797615581491. Epub 2015 Jun 5.</citation>
    <PMID>26048888</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Amati V, Meggiolaro S, Rivellini G, Zaccarin S. Social relations and life satisfaction: the role of friends. Genus. 2018;74(1):7. doi: 10.1186/s41118-018-0032-z. Epub 2018 May 4.</citation>
    <PMID>29755134</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hong SM, Giannakopoulos E. The relationship of satisfaction with life to personality characteristics. J Psychol. 1994 Sep;128(5):547-58.</citation>
    <PMID>7983611</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tugade MM, Fredrickson BL. Resilient individuals use positive emotions to bounce back from negative emotional experiences. J Pers Soc Psychol. 2004 Feb;86(2):320-33.</citation>
    <PMID>14769087</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hunger C, Bornhäuser A, Link L, Geigges J, Voss A, Weinhold J, Schweitzer J. The Experience in Personal Social Systems Questionnaire (EXIS.pers): Development and Psychometric Properties. Fam Process. 2017 Mar;56(1):154-170. doi: 10.1111/famp.12205. Epub 2016 Feb 8.</citation>
    <PMID>26858173</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Klein EM, Brähler E, Dreier M, Reinecke L, Müller KW, Schmutzer G, Wölfling K, Beutel ME. The German version of the Perceived Stress Scale - psychometric characteristics in a representative German community sample. BMC Psychiatry. 2016 May 23;16:159. doi: 10.1186/s12888-016-0875-9.</citation>
    <PMID>27216151</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Koivumaa-Honkanen H, Honkanen R, Viinamäki H, Heikkilä K, Kaprio J, Koskenvuo M. Self-reported life satisfaction and 20-year mortality in healthy Finnish adults. Am J Epidemiol. 2000 Nov 15;152(10):983-91.</citation>
    <PMID>11092440</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wild D, Grove A, Martin M, Eremenco S, McElroy S, Verjee-Lorenz A, Erikson P; ISPOR Task Force for Translation and Cultural Adaptation. Principles of Good Practice for the Translation and Cultural Adaptation Process for Patient-Reported Outcomes (PRO) Measures: report of the ISPOR Task Force for Translation and Cultural Adaptation. Value Health. 2005 Mar-Apr;8(2):94-104.</citation>
    <PMID>15804318</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Uchino BN, Uno D, Holt-Lunstad J. Social Support, Physiological Processes, and Health. Curr Dir Psychol Sci. 1999;8(5):145-8</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tomasello M, Melis AP, Tennie C, Wyman E, Herrmann E. Two Key Steps in the Evolution of Human Cooperation. Curr Anthropol. [2012;53(6):673-92</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>European Commission. European platform against poverty and social exclusion - A European framework for social and territorial cohesion. 2014. 1-2 p</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Poverty, social exclusion and health systems in the WHO European Region [Internet]. World Health Organization. 2010 [cited 23 August 2018]. Available from: http://www.euro.who.int/__data/assets/pdf_file/0004/127525/e94499.pdf</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jaffee SR, Caspi A, Moffitt TE, Polo-Tomás M, Taylor A. Individual, family, and neighborhood factors distinguish resilient from non-resilient maltreated children: a cumulative stressors model. Child Abuse Negl. 2007 Mar;31(3):231-53. Epub 2007 Mar 28.</citation>
    <PMID>17395260</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gilman R. The Relationship Between Life Satisfaction, Social Interest, and Frequency of Extracurricular Activities Among Adolescent Students. J Youth Adolesc. 2001;30(6):749-67</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Myers D. Close Relationships and Quality of Life. Well-being: The foundations of hedonic psychology. 1999. 374-391 p.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Social Networks, Host Resistance, and Mortality: A Nine-Year Follow-up Study of Alameda County Residents. Am J Epidemiol. 2017 Jun 1;185(11):1070-1088. doi: 10.1093/aje/kwx103.</citation>
    <PMID>30052734</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Waidhofer M. Soziale Kompetenz im Diskurs [Dissertation]. JKU Linz; 2004. German</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zautra AJ, Hall JS, Murray KE. Resilience: A New Definition of Health for People and Communities. In: Handbook of Adult Resilience. 2010. p. 3-30</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Henry JP, Stephens PM. Stress, Health and the Social Environment, A Sociobiologic Approach to Medicine. New York, Heidelberg, Berlin: Springer Verlag; 1977. 282 p.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>World Health Organization. Promoting Mental Health - Concepts, Emerging Evidence, Practice [Internet]. 2004. Available from: http://www.who.int/mental_health/evidence/en/promoting_mhh.pdf</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mental health: a state of well-being [Internet]. World Health Organization. 2014 [cited 26 August 2018]. Available from: http://www.who.int/features/factfiles/mental_health/en/</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rhodes RE, Boudreau P. Physical Activity and Personality Traits. Oxford Res Encycl Psychol .2017;1(February):online. Available from: http://psychology.oxfordre.com/view/10.1093/acrefore/9780190236557.001.0001/acrefore-9780190236557-e-210 [Accessed 31 Aug. 2018]</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fernández-Ballesteros R, Zamarrón MD, Ruíz MA. The contribution of socio-demographic and psychosocial factors to life satisfaction. Ageing Soc. 2001;21(1):25-43</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Luhmann M, Lucas RE, Eid M, Diener E. The Prospective Effect of Life Satisfaction on Life Events. Soc Psychol Personal Sci. 2013;4(1):39-45</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ryff CD, Singer BH. Know thyself and become what you are: A eudaimonic approach to psychological well-being. J Happiness Stud. 2008;9(1):13-39.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Huppert FA. Psychological Well-being: Evidence Regarding its Causes and Consequences. Appl Psychol Heal Well-Being. 2009;1(2):137-64.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Reeves BC, Gaus W. Guidelines for reporting non-randomised studies. Forsch Komplementarmed Klass Naturheilkd. 2004 Aug;11 Suppl 1:46-52.</citation>
    <PMID>15353903</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kutschera, G. (2018). Entstehung und Entwicklung der Kutschera- Resonanz® Methode. [pdf] Institut Kutschera. Available at: https://www.kutschera.org-/fileadmin/kutschera/pdf/Entwicklung_der_Resonanzmethode.pdf [Accessed 31 Aug. 2018].</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tosey P, Langley D, Mathison J. Bateson's Levels Of Learning: a Framework For Workplace Learning. In: van Woerkom M, Poell R, editors. Workplace Learning: Concepts, Measurement, and Application. Routledge; 2010. p. 55-68.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sandu A. Using the Pyramid of Neurological Levels in the Human Resources Motivation Management. Rev Rom pentru Educ Multidimens. 2016;8(2):31-44.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Necşoi DV, Porumbu D, Beldianu IF. Self-Reflexivity - Transversal Competence in Teachers' Training. Procedia - Soc Behav Sci. 2013;82:186-91.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kutschera G. Tanz zwischen Bewusst-sein und Unbewusst-sein. Paderborn: Junfermann; 2007. 513 p.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kutschera, G. and Hoffmann, A. (2008). Theorie Sozialkompetenz in der Resonanzmethode®. [pdf] Wien: Institut Kutschera. Available at: https://www.kutschera.org/fileadmin/kutschera/pdf/Publikationen/KutscheraG-KutscheraA_2008_Theorie-Sozialkompetenz-in-der-Resonanzmethode.pdf [Accessed 31 Aug. 2018]</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kutschera (2015). Ausbildung zum Kutschera-Resonanz Practitioner. [pdf] Institut Kutschera. Available at: https://www.kundenmeister.com/crm/index.php/-filemanager/getById/1869/22/2_Leitfaden_Practitioner.pdf [Accessed 31 Aug. 2018].</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Stress - Belastungen besser bewältigen [Internet]. Techniker Krankenkasse; 2017 [cited 31 August 2018]. Available from: https://www.tk.de/resource/blob/2023234/5535b9478a9be8fcabb0a1c6ea7f677e/tk-broschuere--stress--data.pdf</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Aguilar-Raab C, Mühlhan L, Schweitzer J. EVOS - Evaluation of Social Systems. Kemper CJ, Zenger M, Brähler E, editors. Handbuch Kurzskalen psychologischer Merkmale. Berlin: Medizinisch-Wissenschaftliche Verlagsgesellschaft; 2014. S. 72-75.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Klusmann U, Trautwein U, Lüdtke O. Intrinsische und extrinsische Lebensziele: Rehabilität und Validität einer deutschen Fassung des Aspirations Index. Diagnostica. 2005;51(1):40-51.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Steger MF, Frazier P, Oishi S, Kaler M. The Meaning in Life Questionnaire: Assessing the Presence of and Search for Meaning in Life. J Couns Psychol. 2006;53(1):80-93.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schumacher J, Wilz G, Gunzelmann T, Brähler E. [The Antonovsky Sense of Coherence Scale. Test statistical evaluation of a representative population sample and construction of a brief scale]. Psychother Psychosom Med Psychol. 2000 Dec;50(12):472-82. German.</citation>
    <PMID>11199111</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ruch W, Martínez-Martí ML, Proyer RT, Harzer C. The Character Strengths Rating Form (CSRF): Development and initial assessment of a 24-item rating scale to assess character strengths. Pers Individ Dif. Elsevier Ltd; 2014;68:53-8.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Psychiatric Research Unit - WHO Collaborating Centre in Mental Health. WHO (fünf) - Fragebogen zum Wohlbefinden. Hillerod; 1998</citation>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>November 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 8, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 13, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">November 18, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 24, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 24, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 26, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Medical University of Vienna</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Christoph Janka</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Training Program</keyword>
  <keyword>Personal Resources</keyword>
  <keyword>Social Resources</keyword>
  <keyword>Adults</keyword>
  <keyword>Emotional Wellbeing</keyword>
  <keyword>Physical Wellbeing</keyword>
  <keyword>Social Wellbeing</keyword>
  <keyword>Perceived Stress</keyword>
  <keyword>Satisfaction with Life</keyword>
  <keyword>Health Behavior</keyword>
  <keyword>Quality of Relationships</keyword>
  <keyword>Health Status</keyword>
  <keyword>Sense of Coherence</keyword>
  <keyword>Life Goals</keyword>
  <keyword>Meaning in Life</keyword>
  <keyword>Transcendence</keyword>
  <keyword>Evaluation</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Stress, Psychological</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <provided_document_section>
    <provided_document>
      <document_type>Study Protocol and Statistical Analysis Plan</document_type>
      <document_has_protocol>Yes</document_has_protocol>
      <document_has_icf>No</document_has_icf>
      <document_has_sap>Yes</document_has_sap>
      <document_date>August 5, 2019</document_date>
      <document_url>https://ClinicalTrials.gov/ProvidedDocs/73/NCT04165473/Prot_SAP_000.pdf</document_url>
    </provided_document>
    <provided_document>
      <document_type>Informed Consent Form: Group A - Intervention Group</document_type>
      <document_has_protocol>No</document_has_protocol>
      <document_has_icf>Yes</document_has_icf>
      <document_has_sap>No</document_has_sap>
      <document_date>October 20, 2019</document_date>
      <document_url>https://ClinicalTrials.gov/ProvidedDocs/73/NCT04165473/ICF_001.pdf</document_url>
    </provided_document>
    <provided_document>
      <document_type>Informed Consent Form: Group B - Intervention Group - Close Relationship</document_type>
      <document_has_protocol>No</document_has_protocol>
      <document_has_icf>Yes</document_has_icf>
      <document_has_sap>No</document_has_sap>
      <document_date>October 20, 2019</document_date>
      <document_url>https://ClinicalTrials.gov/ProvidedDocs/73/NCT04165473/ICF_002.pdf</document_url>
    </provided_document>
    <provided_document>
      <document_type>Informed Consent Form: Group C - Control Group</document_type>
      <document_has_protocol>No</document_has_protocol>
      <document_has_icf>Yes</document_has_icf>
      <document_has_sap>No</document_has_sap>
      <document_date>October 20, 2019</document_date>
      <document_url>https://ClinicalTrials.gov/ProvidedDocs/73/NCT04165473/ICF_003.pdf</document_url>
    </provided_document>
    <provided_document>
      <document_type>Informed Consent Form: Group D - Control Group - Close Relationship</document_type>
      <document_has_protocol>No</document_has_protocol>
      <document_has_icf>Yes</document_has_icf>
      <document_has_sap>No</document_has_sap>
      <document_date>October 20, 2019</document_date>
      <document_url>https://ClinicalTrials.gov/ProvidedDocs/73/NCT04165473/ICF_004.pdf</document_url>
    </provided_document>
  </provided_document_section>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

