<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04168125</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Ceap</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04168125</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Use of Tilapia Skin for Palate Repair and Protection After Graft Removal</brief_title>
  <official_title>Use of Tilapia Skin for Palate Repair and Protection After Graft Removal</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Sao Paulo</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Sao Paulo</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Randomised Clinical Study to evaluate the efficacy of tilapia skin as an occlusive biological
      dressing on palatal wound healing after free gingival graft harvesting.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Autogenous grafts are currently considered the gold standard in regenerative and
      reconstructive procedures. However, these procedures require a second surgical site to
      provide the tissue graft. In autogenous gingival grafts, the area commonly selected for graft
      harvesting is the palate, which is linked to great discomfort and morbidity for the patient.
      In order to overcome these limitations, xenogeneic and alloplastic materials have been tested
      as tissue substitutes, but their results are still considerably inferior when compared to
      autogenous grafts. Faced with this superiority, another approach to favor the use of
      autogenous grafting is to develop materials that provide greater postoperative comfort and
      patient safety. Since the main complaint arising from the technique is related to pain
      resulting from the remaining surgical wound on the palate, it is interesting to look for
      mechanisms to reduce this sensitivity and accelerate the healing process. For this, the use
      of tilapia skin as a postoperative dressing seems to be a good alternative. Thus, the purpose
      of this study is to evaluate the use of tilapia skin, with the intention of accelerating the
      palate healing process, and to serve as a protector barrier during the healing process.
      Patients treated according to three techniques for palate protection after autogenous
      gingival graft harvesting will be evaluated: G1- use of Hawley plaque; G2- use of surgical
      cement and G3- use of tilapia skin. Will be selected 60 patients of both sexes,&gt; 18 years
      old, requiring the removal of the palate graft for periodontal surgery. At the time of graft
      removal, palate thickness and graft dimensions will be measured. After 7, 14 and 30 days, the
      patient's discomfort and the difficulty in chewing and speaking will be recorded through a
      visual analog scale, the consumption of analgesic, and the dimensions of the surgical wound
      on the palate. For statistical analysis, two-way ANOVA will be performed and t-test paired on
      the obtained results.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 26, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 24, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 23, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2/Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Self-reported pain perception evaluated by a visual analog scale</measure>
    <time_frame>14 days after the surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Patient's self-reported pain perception will be evaluated using a visual analog scale with a score ranging from 0 (no pain) to 10 (unbearable pain).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Self-reported discomfort evaluated by a visual analog scale</measure>
    <time_frame>14 days after the surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Patient's self-reported discomfort will be evaluated using a visual analog scale with a score ranging from 0 (no discomfort) to 2 (high discomfort).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Self-reported trouble with speech evaluated by a visual analog scale</measure>
    <time_frame>14 days after the surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Patient's self-reported trouble with speech will be evaluated using a visual analog scale with a score ranging from 0 (no trouble) to 2 (high trouble).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Self-reported trouble with eating evaluated by a visual analog scale</measure>
    <time_frame>14 days after the surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Patient's self-reported trouble with eating will be evaluated using a visual analog scale with a score ranging from 0 (no trouble) to 2 (high trouble).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Comparison of the palate healing process evaluated through linear measurements (millimiter)</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days after the surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Pictures will be taken immediately after the gingival graft harvesting and compared with post-operativa pictures through the use of linear measurements at Image J.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of analgesic pills taken after surgery</measure>
    <time_frame>14 days after the surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluate the patient's perception of postoperative pain and discomfort by counting the number of analgesic pills taken after the surgery.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Pain, Postoperative</condition>
  <condition>Palate; Wound</condition>
  <condition>Cicatrization</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Tilapia skin</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Procedure/Surgery: Free gingival graft harvesting from hard palate. After gingival graft harvesting from hard palate, it will be placed a tilapia skin as an occlusive biological dressing for palatal wound healing.
Device: Tilapia skin. A xenogeneic collagen dressing will be placed over palate wound and stabilized with sutures during the healing process.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Platelet-Rich Fibrin membrane</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Procedure/Surgery: Free gingival graft harvesting from hard palate. After gingival graft harvesting from hard palate, it will be placed a platelet-rich fibrin membrane as an occlusive biological dressing for palatal wound healing.
Device: Platelet-rich fibrin membrane A platelet-rich fibrin membrane will be placed over palate wound and stabilized with compressive sutures during the healing process.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Hawley Retainer</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Procedure/Surgery: Free gingival graft harvesting from hard palate. After gingival graft harvesting from hard palate, it will be placed a Hawley retainer as a mechanical protection during palatal wound healing.
Device: Hawley retainer A Hawley retainer will be placed over palate wound during the healing process to provide mechanical protection.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Surgical Wound Dressing</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Procedure/Surgery: Free gingival graft harvesting from hard palate. After gingival graft harvesting from hard palate, it will be placed a surgical wound dressing as a mechanical protection during palatal wound healing.
Device: Surgical wound dressing A surgical wound dressing will be placed over palate wound during the healing process to provide mechanical protection.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Tilapia skin</intervention_name>
    <description>Application tilapia skin as an occlusive biological dressing for palatal wound healing after free gingival graft harvesting.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Tilapia skin</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Platelet-Rich Fibrin</intervention_name>
    <description>Application Platelet-Rich Fibrin as an occlusive biological dressing for palatal wound healing after free gingival graft harvesting.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Platelet-Rich Fibrin membrane</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Hawley Retainer</intervention_name>
    <description>Application Hawley Retainer as an occlusive biological dressing for palatal wound healing after free gingival graft harvesting.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Hawley Retainer</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Surgical Wound Dressing</intervention_name>
    <description>Application surgical wound dressing as an occlusive biological dressing for palatal wound healing after free gingival graft harvesting.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Surgical Wound Dressing</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients need periodontal or peri-implant surgical procedures requiring palate
             gingival graft

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with an infectious condition that compromises the procedures

          -  Users of drugs that can act on periodontal tissues or the healing process

          -  Pregnant

          -  Smokers

          -  Diabetes

          -  Irradiated
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Adriana CP Sant'Ana, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Bauru School of Dentistry - University of Sao Paulo</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Gustavo GP Manfredi, MSc</last_name>
    <phone>+5518981711825</phone>
    <email>gustavo.manfredi@usp.br</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Bauru School of Dentistry</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bauru</city>
        <zip>17012-901</zip>
        <country>Brazil</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Gustavo Gonçalves do P Manfredi, MSc</last_name>
      <phone>18981711825</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Brazil</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 27, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 17, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">November 19, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 17, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 17, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 19, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Sao Paulo</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Gustavo Gonçalves do Prado Manfredi</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pain, Postoperative</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cicatrix</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

