<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04169529</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>LINQ for COPD</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04169529</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Reveal LINQ for Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease (COPD)</brief_title>
  <official_title>Reveal LINQ for Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease (COPD)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Medtronic Cardiac Rhythm and Heart Failure</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Medtronic Cardiac Rhythm and Heart Failure</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of the LINQ™ for COPD study is to characterize Reveal LINQ™ derived data from
      patients with COPD by assessing the relationship between changes in LINQ™ derived data with
      COPD exacerbation events.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease (COPD) is progressive and currently incurable and
      refers to a collection of diseases that lead to the key feature of irreversible airflow
      limitation and breathing related problems. Of those with COPD, 46% experienced at least one
      exacerbation within the previous year and 19% needed hospitalization. The financial burden of
      COPD is also evident, in that over $32 billion was spent for COPD care in the United States
      in 2010 and it is expected to be close to $50 billion in 2020.

      Reducing healthcare utilization associated with COPD patient management (i.e. short-term
      readmission and chronic disease management) is a critically important unmet need for
      patients, caregivers, and hospitals. Early detection, prevention, and treatment of COPD
      exacerbation would aim to reduce this high morbidity and cost. To help reduce these
      exacerbations and improve disease management, sensors in a minimally invasive device can be
      used to identify factors that are associated with exacerbations.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">January 31, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 1, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 1, 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Only</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Reveal LINQ™ derived data in patients with COPD</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Characterizing LINQ derived data with COPD events</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease (COPD)</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Reveal LINQ</intervention_name>
    <description>Insertion of Reveal LINQ device to characterize collected data from patients with COPD.</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        The subject population for the LINQ for COPD study is COPD patients who are known to have
        frequent exacerbations (at least two in the past year). Patients will be selected via
        Primary care physicians involved in the trial.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patient is ≥ 45 years old

          -  Patient (or patient's legally authorized representative) is willing and able to
             provide written informed consent

          -  Patient is willing and able to comply with the protocol, including follow-up visits,
             electronic diary submissions and CareLink transmissions

          -  FEV1 (post bronchodilator) ≤ 70% of predicted

          -  Current or former smoker with lifetime cigarette consumption of &gt; 10 pack-years

          -  Two COPD exacerbations within the previous 12 months defined as taking antibiotics
             and/or prednisone for respiratory symptoms, hospitalization or emergency department
             visit for respiratory illness.

          -  The patient's medical records must be accessible by the enrolling site over the
             follow-up period

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Less than 30 days from treatment from a COPD exacerbation as defined as taking
             antibiotics and/or prednisone for respiratory symptoms, hospitalization or emergency
             department visit for respiratory illness.

          -  Less than 30 days from treatment from a HF event as defined as any
             cardiovascular-related (including hypervolemia) Health Care Utilizations (HCUs) for
             any one of the following events.

               -  Admission with primary diagnosis of HF

               -  Intravenous HF therapy (e.g. IV diuretics/vasodilators) or ultrafiltration at any
                  one of the following settings:

                    -  Admission with secondary/tertiary diagnosis of HF

                    -  Emergency Department

                    -  Ambulance

                    -  Observation Unit

                    -  Urgent Care

                    -  HF/Cardiology Clinic

          -  Active respiratory infection being treated by health care professional.

          -  Class IV heart failure

          -  Clinical diagnosis of unstable angina, asthma, bronchiectasis, or cystic fibrosis

          -  Any concomitant condition that might endanger the patient through participation in the
             study or interfere with study procedures, as assessed by the investigator

          -  Patient is pregnant (all females of child-bearing potential must have a negative
             pregnancy test within 1 week of enrollment)

          -  Patient is enrolled in another study that could confound the results of this study,
             without documented pre-approval from a Medtronic study manager

          -  Patient has an existing or planned implantation of Medtronic IPG, ICD, CRT-D or CRT-P
             device in the near future

          -  Patient has an existing and active insertable cardiac monitor, regardless of
             manufacturer

          -  Concurrent disease with life expectancy less than 1 year
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>45 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Troy D Penz, B.S</last_name>
    <phone>+1-763-337-2477</phone>
    <email>troy.d.penz@medronic.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <verification_date>November 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 18, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 18, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">November 20, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 18, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 18, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 20, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>COPD</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lung Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lung Diseases, Obstructive</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pulmonary Disease, Chronic Obstructive</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

