<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04165200</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IF18-00008</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04165200</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Fecal Microbiota Transplantation as a Therapeutic Strategy for Patients Infected With HIV</brief_title>
  <official_title>Fecal Microbiota Transplantation as a Therapeutic Strategy for Patients Infected With HIV</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Hospital Universitario Dr. Jose E. Gonzalez</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Hospital Universitario Dr. Jose E. Gonzalez</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Patients eligible for the study will be selected on Fridays during the HIV consultation at
      the Infectious Diseases Department. Patients that meet the inclusion and exclusion criteria,
      will be randomized and assigned in two groups 1:1. A group will start intervention with FMT
      (fecal matter transplant) through frozen capsules and after seven days, antiretroviral
      therapy (ART) will be started. Patients in the other group will be given placebo capsules and
      after seven days ART will be started. The frozen capsules of FMT will be ingested orally with
      a frequency of 15 capsules every 12 hours for 4 doses 7 days prior ART start and on weeks 0,
      4, 8 and 12 after ART start. Subsequently, blood samples will be taken to monitor the immune
      status with CD4 T lymphocytes and HIV viral load during week 0, 4, 8, 12 and 24 after ART
      start.

      Throughout the study period, subjects can carry out a free diet, moderate alcohol intake,
      perform their daily activities and abstain from any of the elimination criteria. Medical
      consultations will be made on days -7 to ART start, day 1, 30, 60, 90 and 120 after ART
      start, where clinical examination and elimination criteria will be evaluated.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Study design: Prospective controlled study experimental comparative Study duration: 1 year
      The number of patients to enroll: 20 patients. After being randomized, selected patients who
      meet the criteria for inclusion and exclusion will be assigned 1:1 in two groups. A group
      will start treatment with FMT through frozen capsules, and ART at the same time; and another
      group will star placebo capsules and ART.

      The frozen capsules will be ingested orally at a frequency of 15 capsules every 12 hours for
      four doses 7 days prior ART start and on weeks 0, 4, 8 and 12 after ART start. Each capsule
      must be ingested over a period no longer than 1 hour of the anterior capsule.

      Subsequently, blood samples will be taken through peripheral vein puncture with the
      extraction of 10 ml of venous blood to monitor the immune status with CD4 T lymphocytes and
      HIV viral load. A total of 4 blood samples will be taken during week 4, 8, 12 and 24 after
      ART start.

      Medical consultations will be made every 4 weeks, on days -7 days prior ART start, day 1, 30,
      60, 90 and 120 where vital signs, symptoms or signs of organ systems, determination of
      weight, BMI, adverse effects and elimination criteria will be assessed.

      In addition, feces samples from each patient will be taken during medical consultation on
      week 0, 8 and 24 after ART start to evaluate the modification of the intestinal microbiome
      after the intervention on both groups.

      During the study period, subjects may carry a free diet, moderate intake of alcohol and
      perform their daily activities as they refrain free from any of the elimination criteria.

      The study will last 1 year and the samples taken will be frozen and stored in the Infectious
      Diseases Department of the Hospital.

      Selection of Fecal Microbiota donors:

      The selection of fecal microbiota donors is based on:

        -  Medical history, body weight, no medication uses such as antibiotics and proton pump
           inhibitors, no trips and no diarrhea 6 months prior donation.

        -  The absence of chronic infections such as Hepatitis B, Hepatitis C, and HIV determined
           by immunoassay.

        -  Negative Rose Bengal test and V.D.R.L

        -  Normal complete blood count and liver function tests.

      Fecal sample analysis:

        1. Fresh microscopy analysis to detect leukocytes and parasites (including protozoa and
           helminths)

        2. Stool culture to rule out the presence of enteropathogens, including Salmonella spp.,
           Shigella spp., Aeromonas spp., Plesiomonas spp., Vibrio spp. and Clostridiodes diffcile.

        3. Gastrointestinal panel by multiple polymerase chain reaction (PCR) using BioFire
           Filmarray which includes the detection of:

           Bacteria: Campylobacter (C. jejuni, C. coi, C. upsaliensis), Clostridiodes difficile
           (toxins A / B), Plesiomonas shigelloides, Salmonella spp., Yersinia enterocolitica,
           Vibrio (V. parahaemolytic , V. vulnificus and V. cholerae), Escherichia coli O157: H7,
           enteroaggregative E. coli (EAEC), enteropathogenic E. coli (EPEC), enterotoxigenic E.
           coli (ETEC), Shiga toxin producing E. coli (STEC) stx1 / stx2, Shigella sp.
           enteroinvasive E. coli (EIEC).

           Virus: Adenovirus F 40/41, Astrovirus, Norovirus GI / GII, Rotavirus A, Sapovirus (I,
           II, IV and V) Parasites: Cryptosporidium sp., Cyclospora cayetanensis, Entamoeba
           histolytica and Giardia lamblia.

        4. Detection of genes associated with drug resistance by endpoint PCR; including genes
           encoding extended spectrum beta-lactamases (TEM, CTX; SHV, CMY) and carbapenemases (VIM,
           NDM, IMP, KPC, OXA-48).

      Once all the stages of evaluation are completed only negative subjects for all the tests and
      in which there is no evidence of infection are selected as donors. The scrutiny and
      laboratory tests are considered valid during the following 4 weeks, so if new donation of
      feces is required, the process will be carried out again.

      Sample Preparation fecal microbiota All samples will be mixed with 10% glycerol and frozen at
      -70°C in a period not exceeding 60 minutes after collection. They will be mixed and then
      suspended in saline 0.9%. The final mixture will be filtered to remove particles greater than
      330 microns, finally adding glycerol as cryoprotectant. This mixture is carried to the
      encapsulation process using sterile capsules for enteral liberation, in two sizes. The first
      capsule is filled with a mixture of feces and sealed with its counterpart, and then the
      sealed capsule becomes encapsulated in a second capsule. The final product is stored frozen
      until 60 minutes before use. The administration will only be oral.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 6, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">January 20, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 10, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Prospective controlled study experimental comparative</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator)</masking>
    <masking_description>Neither patients, nor investigators are allowed to know about which group of patients is going to receive placebo and which one faecal microbiota capsules. The laboratory that provide us the capsules is going to divide and randomize our sample of patients, and also register the information in a data base.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Levels of CD4 cells</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>The efficacy of FMT in obtaining a faster immunologic response measured in rise of CD4 lymphocyte countTMF capsules, will have a faster rise in cell count than those who don´t receive them.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Tolerability of FMT capsules</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Number of Participants with FMT related Adverse Events</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">22</enrollment>
  <condition>HIV Infections</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Patients receiving FMT capsules and ART</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>ART Start at week 0 non-stop.
FMT. The frozen capsules will be ingested orally at a frequency of 15 capsules every 12 hours for four doses 7 days prior ART start and on weeks 0, 4, 8 and 12 after ART start. Each capsule must be ingested over a period no longer than 1 hour of the anterior capsule.
Blood samples Week 0, 4, 8, 12 and 24. Taken through peripheral vein puncture with the extraction of 10 ml of venous blood to monitor the CD4 lymphocytes count and HIV viral load.
Feces samples from each patient will be taken during medical consultation on week 0, 8 and 24 after ART start to evaluate the modification of the intestinal microbiome.
Medical consultations will be made on days -7 to ART start, day 1, 30, 60, 90 and 120 after ART start, where clinical examination and elimination criteria will be evaluated.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Patients receiving placebo capsules</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>ART Start at week 0 non-stop.
Placebo capsules. The frozen capsules will be ingested orally at a frequency of 15 capsules every 12 hours for four doses 7 days prior ART start and on weeks 0, 4, 8 and 12 after ART start. Each capsule must be ingested over a period no longer than 1 hour of the anterior capsule.
Blood samples Week 0, 4, 8, 12 and 24. Taken through peripheral vein puncture with the extraction of 10 ml of venous blood to monitor the CD4 lymphocytes count and HIV viral load.
Feces samples from each patient will be taken during medical consultation on week 0, 8 and 24 after ART start to evaluate the modification of the intestinal microbiome.
Medical consultations will be made on days -7 to ART start, day 1, 30, 60, 90 and 120 after ART start, where clinical examination and elimination criteria will be evaluated.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Blood and feces samples</intervention_name>
    <description>Blood samples are going to be taken by puncturing peripheral vein extraction with 10 ml of venous blood for later biweekly to monitor in person and therefore monitor immune status with biomarkers T lymphocyte subclass CD4 and viral load. A total of four blood samples will be taken at weeks 4, 8, 12 and 24 of recruitment.
A total of four feces samples are going to be required during the study, to evaluate the changes on the microbiota of the patient. 1 week before the patients start their HAART, the same day the patients initiate their HAART, 8 weeks after they started HAART and 24 weeks after HAART.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Patients receiving FMT capsules and ART</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Patients receiving placebo capsules</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion criteria:

          -  Patients over 18 years

          -  Confirmed HIV infection with any CD4 lymphocyte count

          -  Patients at the beginning of the study only taking antibiotic prophylaxis according to
             the CD4 lymphocyte count

          -  Patients agree to participate in the study through a signed informed consent

        Exclusion criteria:

          -  Patients receiving probiotics

          -  Patients with anatomical abnormalities of the digestive tract such as colostomy or
             ileostomy

          -  Patients with previous bowel resection

          -  Patients with impaired AST and / or ALT greater than 4 times its normal value

          -  Hemodialysis patients Patients with gastrointestinal bleeding in the last 12 weeks

          -  Patients undergoing colonoscopy in the last 12 weeks
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Universitario José E. Gonzalez</name>
      <address>
        <city>Monterrey</city>
        <state>Nuevo Leon</state>
        <zip>64460</zip>
        <country>Mexico</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Mexico</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Arts EJ, Hazuda DJ. HIV-1 antiretroviral drug therapy. Cold Spring Harb Perspect Med. 2012 Apr;2(4):a007161. doi: 10.1101/cshperspect.a007161. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22474613</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zulfiqar HF, Javed A, Sumbal, Afroze B, Ali Q, Akbar K, Nadeem T, Rana MA, Nazar ZA, Nasir IA, Husnain T. HIV Diagnosis and Treatment through Advanced Technologies. Front Public Health. 2017 Mar 7;5:32. doi: 10.3389/fpubh.2017.00032. eCollection 2017. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>28326304</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Brenchley JM, Paiardini M, Knox KS, Asher AI, Cervasi B, Asher TE, Scheinberg P, Price DA, Hage CA, Kholi LM, Khoruts A, Frank I, Else J, Schacker T, Silvestri G, Douek DC. Differential Th17 CD4 T-cell depletion in pathogenic and nonpathogenic lentiviral infections. Blood. 2008 Oct 1;112(7):2826-35. doi: 10.1182/blood-2008-05-159301. Epub 2008 Jul 29.</citation>
    <PMID>18664624</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mutlu EA, Keshavarzian A, Losurdo J, Swanson G, Siewe B, Forsyth C, French A, Demarais P, Sun Y, Koenig L, Cox S, Engen P, Chakradeo P, Abbasi R, Gorenz A, Burns C, Landay A. A compositional look at the human gastrointestinal microbiome and immune activation parameters in HIV infected subjects. PLoS Pathog. 2014 Feb 20;10(2):e1003829. doi: 10.1371/journal.ppat.1003829. eCollection 2014 Feb.</citation>
    <PMID>24586144</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dillon SM, Lee EJ, Kotter CV, Austin GL, Dong Z, Hecht DK, Gianella S, Siewe B, Smith DM, Landay AL, Robertson CE, Frank DN, Wilson CC. An altered intestinal mucosal microbiome in HIV-1 infection is associated with mucosal and systemic immune activation and endotoxemia. Mucosal Immunol. 2014 Jul;7(4):983-94. doi: 10.1038/mi.2013.116. Epub 2014 Jan 8.</citation>
    <PMID>24399150</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hunt PW. Th17, gut, and HIV: therapeutic implications. Curr Opin HIV AIDS. 2010 Mar;5(2):189-93. doi: 10.1097/COH.0b013e32833647d9. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20543599</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Samji H, Cescon A, Hogg RS, Modur SP, Althoff KN, Buchacz K, Burchell AN, Cohen M, Gebo KA, Gill MJ, Justice A, Kirk G, Klein MB, Korthuis PT, Martin J, Napravnik S, Rourke SB, Sterling TR, Silverberg MJ, Deeks S, Jacobson LP, Bosch RJ, Kitahata MM, Goedert JJ, Moore R, Gange SJ; North American AIDS Cohort Collaboration on Research and Design (NA-ACCORD) of IeDEA. Closing the gap: increases in life expectancy among treated HIV-positive individuals in the United States and Canada. PLoS One. 2013 Dec 18;8(12):e81355. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0081355. eCollection 2013.</citation>
    <PMID>24367482</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bandera A, De Benedetto I, Bozzi G, Gori A. Altered gut microbiome composition in HIV infection: causes, effects and potential intervention. Curr Opin HIV AIDS. 2018 Jan;13(1):73-80. doi: 10.1097/COH.0000000000000429. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>29045252</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Desai SN, Landay AL. HIV and aging: role of the microbiome. Curr Opin HIV AIDS. 2018 Jan;13(1):22-27. doi: 10.1097/COH.0000000000000433. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>29035948</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lozupone CA, Li M, Campbell TB, Flores SC, Linderman D, Gebert MJ, Knight R, Fontenot AP, Palmer BE. Alterations in the gut microbiota associated with HIV-1 infection. Cell Host Microbe. 2013 Sep 11;14(3):329-39. doi: 10.1016/j.chom.2013.08.006.</citation>
    <PMID>24034618</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 4, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 13, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">November 15, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 26, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 26, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 28, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Hospital Universitario Dr. Jose E. Gonzalez</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Dr. Adrian Camacho-Ortiz</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Dr. Adrian Camacho Ortiz</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>HIV infection, fecal microbiota transplantation</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>HIV Infections</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

