<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04167306</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>COMB-BO8</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2018-000048-24</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04167306</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Varenicline and Bupropion for Alcohol Use Disorder</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized, Double-blind, Placebo-controlled Multicenter Trial on the Efficacy of Varenicline and Bupropion in Combination and Alone, for Treatment of Alcohol Use Disorder</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Vastra Gotaland Region</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Vastra Gotaland Region</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The COMB study is a randomized double-blind placebo-controlled multicenter trial in Sweden on
      the efficacy of varenicline and bupropion, in combination and alone, for treatment of alcohol
      use disorder (AUD).

      Study design overview: A 13-weeks (91 days) multicenter clinical trial with four parallel
      groups. 95 subjects per treatment arm will be randomized into the study. 380 subjects with
      AUD will be randomized in total.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Varenicline (Champix®) and bupropion (Zyban®, patent time expired) are approved and marketed
      in Europe and US for smoking cessation in nicotine use disorder, and for treatment of major
      depression (bupropion). There is clinical evidence of an additive effect of the drug
      combination of varenicline and bupropion on smoking cessation. Varenicline has been shown in
      two RCTs to reduce also alcohol intake in subjects with AUD. It is hypothesized that
      bupropion will enhance the effect of varenicline and that the combined effect size will be
      greater than that of approved therapies for AUD. As efficacy endpoint, the trial uses the
      alcohol specific biomarker for alcohol intake, phosphatidylethanol in blood (B-PEth). Outcome
      will also be measured by self-reported alcohol consumption, the standard effect measure in
      AUD trials.This will be the first trial using the biomarker B-PEth as primary outcome
      variable. The use of a specific objective marker is expected to increase chances for
      detecting treatment effects.

      Development phase: II Number of randomized subjects: 380 subjects with AUD. 95 subjects per
      treatment arm will be randomized into the study.

      Number of sites: Approximately 5 study sites in Sweden

      Investigational medicinal products, dosages and administration:

      There will be two separate study kits for IMP 1 and IMP 2

      Investigational medicinal product 1 (IMP1): Varenicline 1 mg x 2 p.o. daily. The
      pharmaceutical formulation will be encapsulated tablets for oral use. Varenicline will be
      escalated from 0.5 to 2 mg daily during the first week.

      Investigational medicinal product 2 (IMP 2): Bupropion SR 150 mg x 2 p.o. daily. The
      pharmaceutical formulation will be encapsulated sustained release (SR) tablets for oral use.
      Bupropion will be escalated from 150 to 300 mg daily during the first week.

      IMP 1 and IMP 2 are distributed at 7 occasions: Day 0, Day 7, Day 21, Day 35, Day 49, Day 63
      and Day 77. The doses and route of administration for varenicline and bupropion are those
      approved and recommended as oral formulations for smoking cessation.

      The trial comprises 9 study visits over 91 days: Screening visit,Day 0, Day 7, Day 21, Day
      35, Day 49, Day 63, Day 77 and Day 91. Randomization is carried out according to block
      randomization and eligible subjects are randomized to one of the below described intervention
      arms.

      The study will be performed in accordance with the study protocol, with the latest version of
      the Declaration of Helsinki, in accordance with GCP principles (ICH-GCP E6-R2), and
      applicable regulatory requirements in Sweden . The study is approved by competent authority
      (the Swedish Medical Product Agency) and the Etics committee. The trial is monitored by an
      independent monitor according to GCP principles.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 4, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 30, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 30, 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>Appointed manufacturer produces, packs and labels the IMPs in two separate IMP kits and uses a blinding procedure accordance with internal standard operating procedure. IMP 1 and IMP 2, will have an unique Randomization Number generated randomly. For each randomization number, a sealed emergency code envelope will follow the shipment.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Alcohol consumption as measured by phosphatidylethanol (PEth) in blood</measure>
    <time_frame>PEth is calculated as the mean value over the active steady state period (Day 21-Day77) compared to baseline (=screening visit value)</time_frame>
    <description>B-PEth: Objective marker for alcohol consumption measured in blood,measured at every study visit</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Alcohol consumption as measured by heavy drinking days (HDD)</measure>
    <time_frame>Number of HDD by 14 days is defined as a mean over the 8-week steady state active treatment period (Day 21-Day77) . ( D21-D77)/4 in order to get a 14 day-period measurment.</time_frame>
    <description>HDD is obtained by the time Line Follow Back procedure, defined in two ways; as ≥60 grams for men and ≥40 for women according to EMA's guideline and as ≥70 grams for men and ≥56 grams for women according to FDA's guidelines</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>CDT</measure>
    <time_frame>CDT is calculated as the mean value over the active steady state period (Day 21-Day77) compared to baseline (=screening visit value)</time_frame>
    <description>The indirect alcohol marker carbohydrate deficient transferrin</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>GGT</measure>
    <time_frame>GGT calculated as the mean value over the active steady state period (Day 21-Day77) compared to baseline (=screening visit value)</time_frame>
    <description>The indirect alcohol marker gamma glutamyl transferase</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Self-reported alcohol consumption measured by time-lime-follow-back</measure>
    <time_frame>CDT is calculated as the mean value over the active steady state period (Day 21-Day77) compared to baseline (=screening visit value)</time_frame>
    <description>Mean grams of alcohol per day
Number of drinking days
Number of drinks per drinking days
Number of abstaining days</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Alcohol Use Identification Test</measure>
    <time_frame>Mean difference between total score obtained at baseline and visit 1</time_frame>
    <description>Total score of Alcohol Use Identification Test</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Self-reported Alcohol Craving</measure>
    <time_frame>Scale range: 0-100 mm. Minimum value: 0 = No craving. Maxumum value: 100 Maximum= Very strong craving. Craving is calculated as the mean value over the active steady state period (Day 21-Day77) compared to baseline (=screening visit value)</time_frame>
    <description>Alcohol craving as measured by a Visual Analogue Scale (VAS)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Nicotine use</measure>
    <time_frame>77 day-interval. Mean difference between cotinine concentration assessed at Day o and Day 77</time_frame>
    <description>Nicotine use measured by the nicotine saliva marker cotinine in saliva</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The Temporal Experience of Pleasure Scale (TEPS)</measure>
    <time_frame>77 day-interval. Mean difference between total scale score assessed at Day 0 and Day 77</time_frame>
    <description>A 17-item scale with anticipatory and consummatory components of the experience of pleasure. The scale is used as a proxy to assess a hypodopaminergic state. Worse Outcome: A lower score indicates low experience of pleasure (=proxy for hypodopaminergic state). Better outcome:A high score indicates high experience of pleasure.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The Continous Performance Test + Activity test</measure>
    <time_frame>77 day-interval. Mean difference between outcome measure assessed at Day o and Day 7.</time_frame>
    <description>A neuropsychiatric tool addressing inattention, impulsivity and activity</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Plasma concentration of varenicline (ng/ml)</measure>
    <time_frame>14 day-interval. Obtained twice, at Day 21 and Day 49 during IMP steady state. Correlation between plasma concentration of varenicline and above described outcome measures</time_frame>
    <description>Mean concentration of values obtained at visit 4 and visit 6</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Plasma concentration of bupropion (ng/ml)</measure>
    <time_frame>14 day-interval. Obtained twice, at Day 21 and Day 49 during IMP steady state. Correlation between plasma concentration of bupropion and above described outcome measures</time_frame>
    <description>Mean concentration of values obtained at visit 4 and visit 6</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">380</enrollment>
  <condition>Alcohol Use Disorder</condition>
  <condition>Alcoholism</condition>
  <condition>Alcohol Dependence</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>1) Varenicline + Bupropion</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Investigational medicinal product (IMP) 1: Varenicline 0.5 mg and 1.0 mg and Investigational medicinal product (IMP) 2: Bupropion SR 150 mg</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>2) Varenicline + Placebo for Bupropion</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Investigational medicinal product (IMP) 1: Varenicline 0.5 mg and 1.0 mg and Placebo capsule for IMP 2 (bupropion)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>3) Bupropion + Placebo for Varenicline</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Investigational medicinal product (IMP) 2: Bupropion SR 150 mg and Placebo capsule for IMP 1 (varenicline)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>4) Placebo for Varenicline + Placebo for Bupropion</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Placebo capsule for IMP 1 (varenicline) and Placebo capsule for IMP 2 (bupropion)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Varenicline Tartrate 1 mg b.i.d</intervention_name>
    <description>Capsules for oral use</description>
    <arm_group_label>1) Varenicline + Bupropion</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>2) Varenicline + Placebo for Bupropion</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Champix</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Bupropion Hydrochloride 150 mg b.i.d</intervention_name>
    <description>Capsules for oral use</description>
    <arm_group_label>1) Varenicline + Bupropion</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>3) Bupropion + Placebo for Varenicline</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Bupropion Sandoz</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo for varenicline</intervention_name>
    <description>Capsules for oral use</description>
    <arm_group_label>3) Bupropion + Placebo for Varenicline</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>4) Placebo for Varenicline + Placebo for Bupropion</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo for bupropion</intervention_name>
    <description>Capsules for oral use</description>
    <arm_group_label>2) Varenicline + Placebo for Bupropion</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>4) Placebo for Varenicline + Placebo for Bupropion</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Signed informed consent

          2. Blood alcohol level below &lt;0.1‰ (0.1 g/L) at signing informed consent

          3. 25-70 years of age at screening

          4. Moderate and severe AUD according to DSM-V (meeting ≥4 out of 11 criteria)

          5. B-PEth levels of ≥0.5 µmol/L at screening visit (visit 1)

          6. Continuous high alcohol consumption over the last 3 months prior to screening as
             defined by at least 2 HDD per week on a typical week

          7. Available phone number for contact

          8. Ability to speak and write in Swedish

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Total abstinence between screening and randomization visit

          2. Treatment of alcohol withdrawal within 30 days of study initiation

          3. Pharmacological treatment within 3 months of study initiation and during the study
             period that may affect alcohol consumption, including but not exclusive to,
             varenicline, bupropion, disulfiram, acamprosate, naltrexone, nalmefene, baclofen,
             topiramate, ondansetron, mirtazapine, methylphenidate, dexamphetamine, atomoxetine,
             pregabalin, buprenorphine and methadone

          4. Non-pharmacological treatment within 3 months of study initiation and during the study
             period that may affect alcohol consumption

          5. Current continuous use of antidepressants, opioid analgesics, benzodiazepines,
             zopiclone, zolpidem, hydroxyzine, alimemazine, propiomazine, or other sedatives. (The
             sporadic use of these compounds is accepted.)

          6. Any concurrent medication that may affect the results of the trial or is considered to
             compromise the safety of the participants in the trial. (See SmPCs for possible
             interactions.)

          7. Laboratory hepatic values of &gt;3 times the upper limit of the normal range, creatinine
             clearance &lt;30 ml/min, or other clinically significant abnormalities in the screening
             laboratory values

          8. Blood pressure ≥180/110 at screening

          9. Pregnancy, breast-feeding and for premenopausal women, not using one of the
             contraceptive methods oral contraceptive, intrauterine contraceptive device (copper or
             hormonal) or subcutaneous inplant.

         10. Diabetes mellitus type 1 and diabetes mellitus type 2 in need of insulin treatment

         11. Any current psychiatric or somatic disorder or condition that may affect assessments
             or compromise participant's safety during the trial

         12. ASRS- v1.1, part A score ≥4 in the marked cut-off section

         13. MADRS score ≥ 20

         14. Current depression that is not mild (mild depression is accepted)

         15. Suicidality

         16. Current illicit drug use based on urine-toxicity test and DUDIT

         17. History of delirium tremens or abstinence-induced seizures within 5 years of study
             initiation

         18. Epilepsy or seizures other than alcohol-induced, lifetime

         19. Severe sleep disturbances

         20. Need of alcohol detoxification

         21. Living conditions not appropriate to fulfil study requirements

         22. Use of herbal drugs/tea and supplementations possibly affecting outcome or safety

         23. Previous randomization in this trial or participation in another trial within 3 months
             of enrollment into this trial.

         24. Additional factors that render the participant unable to complete the study, as judged
             by the investigator
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>25 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Bo Söderpalm, Prof, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Sahlgrenska University Hospital, Västra Götaland</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Helga Lidö, PhD, Pharm</last_name>
    <phone>+46709179311</phone>
    <email>helga.lido@gu.se</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Andrea deBejczy, PhD, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+46735930501</phone>
    <email>andrea.debejczy@neuro.gu.se</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Psykiatrin Halland</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kungsbacka</city>
        <state>Region Halland</state>
        <country>Sweden</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Hans Ackerot, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Linköping University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Linköping</city>
        <state>Region Östergötland</state>
        <country>Sweden</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Markus Heilig, MD, Prof</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Stockholm Centre for Dependency Disorders,</name>
      <address>
        <city>Stockholm</city>
        <state>Stockholms Läns Sjukvårdområde</state>
        <country>Sweden</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Johan Franck, MD, Prof</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Psykiatrin Borås/Vuxenpsykiatrisk mottagning beroende, Borås, Västra Götalandsregionen</name>
      <address>
        <city>Borås</city>
        <state>VGR</state>
        <country>Sweden</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ulrika T. Ekman, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Beroendekliniken, Sahlgrenska University Hospital, Västra Götalandsregionen</name>
      <address>
        <city>Gothenburg</city>
        <country>Sweden</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Bo Söderpalm, MD, Prof</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Sweden</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 30, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 14, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">November 18, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 26, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 26, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 29, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Alcoholism</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Alcohol Drinking</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Bupropion</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Varenicline</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

