<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04163107</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2019/922</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2019-000986-19</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04163107</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Combined Carfilzomib and Hydroxychloroquine in Patients With Relapsed/Refractory Multiple Myeloma</brief_title>
  <acronym>MYELOMA-HCQ</acronym>
  <official_title>Combined Carfilzomib and Hydroxychloroquine in Patients With Relapsed/Refractory Multiple Myeloma - a Phase 1 Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Norwegian University of Science and Technology</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>St. Olavs Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Oslo University Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Norwegian University of Science and Technology</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Multiple myeloma (MM) is a neoplastic expansion of bone marrow plasma cells. Despite advances
      in treatment in recent years, MM is still a fatal disease. MM is characterized by the ability
      of malignant cells to produce large amounts of monoclonal immunoglobulin. The secretion of
      these immunoglobulins can be detected as the &quot;M-protein&quot; in serum, and the measurement of the
      M-component is used both for diagnosis and to evaluate treatment response and relapse. The
      high load of secreted proteins in MM cells requires a efficient way to clear these proteins
      from the cells and targeting protein degradation is an important therapeutic target in MM.
      This is today done by inhibiting the proteasome, one of the two central ways cells can
      degrade proteins, by drugs named proteasome inhibitors (including bortezomib, ixazomib and
      carfilzomib). Patients become resistant to these drugs, and it is therefore likely that
      myeloma cells also utilise another important system for protein degradation, called
      autophagy. Pre-clinical studies have shown that the combination of the proteasome inhibitor
      carfilzomib and the autophagy inhibitor hydroxychloroquine increases myeloma cell death and
      that hydroxychloroquine is able to reverse MM cell resistance to carfilzomib. This is the
      rationale for this study, where the investigators add the autophagy inhibitor
      hydroxychloroquine to a standard regime of carfilzomib and dexamethasone, to determine a
      maximum tolerated dose of this combination and to study tolerability.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 7, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>A single arm, dose escalation study in two centers. 3+3 design in five dose levels.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>maximum tolerated dose of hydroxychloroquine when added to standard-dose regimen of carfilzomib/dexamethasone</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>estimate of toxicity rate of hydroxychloroquine when added at a maximum tolerated dose to standard-dose regimen of carfilzomib/dexamethasone</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">15</enrollment>
  <condition>Multiple Myeloma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Combination treatment of carfilzomib/dexamethasone/HCQ</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Hydroxychloroquine</intervention_name>
    <description>All patients start with a 14 days run-in with monotherapy with hydroxychloroquine (HCQ) at their assigned dose level. Then they continue with 6 28-day cycles of HCQ/Carfilzomib/Dexamethasone. 3 patients at each dose level.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Combination treatment of carfilzomib/dexamethasone/HCQ</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Carfilzomib Injection</intervention_name>
    <description>All patients start with a 14 days run-in with monotherapy with hydroxychloroquine (HCQ) at their assigned dose level. Then they continue with 6 28-day cycles of HCQ/Carfilzomib/Dexamethasone. 3 patients at each dose level.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Combination treatment of carfilzomib/dexamethasone/HCQ</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Dexamethasone</intervention_name>
    <description>All patients start with a 14 days run-in with monotherapy with hydroxychloroquine (HCQ) at their assigned dose level. Then they continue with 6 28-day cycles of HCQ/Carfilzomib/Dexamethasone. 3 patients at each dose level.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Combination treatment of carfilzomib/dexamethasone/HCQ</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Demographic and diagnosis

          -  A prior diagnosis of multiple myeloma according to International Myeloma Working Group
             (IMWG) criteria with documented disease progression in need of treatment at time of
             screening.

             - Must meet all of the following criteria:

          -  Patients must have received at least two prior therapies including bortezomib and an
             immunomodulatory agent (may include autologous bone marrow transplantation)

          -  Patients must not be refractory to carfilzomib

          -  Relapsed or progressive disease documented according to IMWG criteria

          -  Patients must have evaluable multiple myeloma with at least one of the following
             (assessed within 21 days prior to registration)

          -  Serum M-protein ≥ 10 g/L, or

          -  Urine M-protein ≥ 200 mg/24 hours

          -  Involved serum immunoglobulin free light chain (SFLC) &gt; 100 mg/L AND abnormal
             kappa/lambda ratio

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status 0-2

          -  Life expectancy ≥ 6 months

        Laboratory:

          -  Absolute neutrophil count ≥ 1.0 x 109/L

          -  Hemoglobin ≥ 7 g/dL (with or without transfusion support)

          -  Platelets ≥ 50 x 109/L (with or without transfusion support)

          -  Total bilirubin ≤ 2 x upper limit of normal (ULN)

          -  Aspartate amino transferase/alanine amino transferase ratio (ASAT/ALAT) ≤ 2.5 x ULN

          -  Creatinine ≤ 2 x ULN

        Concurrent conditions

          -  Left ventricular ejection fraction (LVEF) ≥ 40 % determined by 2D transthoracic
             echocardiogram (ECHO) or Multigated Acquisition Scan (MUGA)

          -  No baseline peripheral neuropathy ≥ grade 2

          -  No history of allergic reactions to compounds of similar chemical or biological
             composition to carfilzomib, dexamethasone or hydroxychloroquine, including Captisol (a
             cyclodextrin derivate used to solubilize carfilzomib)

          -  No macular degeneration or retinopathy (diabetic or otherwise) as examined during
             screening or known porphyria or psoriasis

          -  Well-controlled psoriasis allowed under care of a specialist who agrees to monitor the
             patient for exacerbations

          -  No other condition that would require therapy with hydroxychloroquine, including but
             not limited to, any of the following:

          -  Systemic lupus erythematosus

          -  Rheumatoid arthritis

          -  Porphyria cutanea tarda

          -  Malaria treatment or prophylaxis

          -  No concurrent or prior malignancy except for the following:

          -  Basal cell or squamous cell carcinoma of the skin

          -  Treated carcinoma in situ

          -  Localized prostate adenocarcinoma (stage T1a or T1b) with a stable prostate-specific
             antigen (PSA) for a period fo at least 4 months allowed

          -  Patients with a prior malignancy treated with chemotherapy, biologic agents, and/or
             radiation are eligible for this study if they have completed therapy ≥ 2 years
             previously with no evidence of recurrent disease

          -  Patients with a prior malignancy treated with surgery alone are eligible for this
             study if they have completed therapy ≥ 2 years previously with no evidence of
             recurrent disease

          -  No uncontrolled intercurrent illness including, but not limited to, any of the
             following:

          -  Uncontrolled ongoing infection

          -  Known acute or chronic hepatitis B, active hepatitis A or C or human immunodeficiency
             virus (HIV)

          -  Symptomatic congestive heart failure, defined as New York Heart Association (NYHA)
             Class III or IV

          -  Unstable angina pectoris

          -  Myocardial infarction within 6 months of enrollment

          -  Cardiac arrhythmia

          -  Clinically significant pericardial disease

          -  Cardiac amyloidosis

          -  Severe lung disease

          -  Psychiatric illness or social situations that would prevent compliance with study
             requirements

        Prior and concurrent therapy

          -  No prior dose reductions of carfilzomib administration in previous lines

          -  At least 14 days since prior antimyeloma agents, not including
             carfilzomib/dexamethasone

          -  Concurrent therapy with bisphosphonates allowed at the discretion of the treating
             physician

          -  Concurrent hematopoetic growth factors allowed, including filgrastim granulocyte
             colony-stimulating factor (G-CSF) or pegfilgrastim, epoetin alpha, and darbepoetin
             alpha

          -  Concurrent participation in non-treatment studies allowed, if it will not interfere
             with participation in this study

          -  No concurrent radiotherapy except local radiotherapy during the treatment phase of
             this study for palliation of pain or prevention of fracture

          -  No concurrent treatment with a different investigational regimen

          -  No concurrent treatment with other anticancer agents

          -  No concurrent participation in other investigational trials that involve novel
             therapies

        Ethical/other

          -  Female patients of child-bearing potential (FCBP) must have negative serum pregnancy
             test within 21 days prior to registration and agree to use an effective method of
             contraception during and for 3 months following last dose of drug.

          -  Male patients must use an effective barrier method of contraception during study and
             for 3 months following the last dose if sexually active with a FCBP.

          -  Ability to understand and willingness to sign the informed consent document

          -  Signed informed consent and expected cooperation of the patients for the treatment and
             follow up must be obtained and documented according to International Council for
             Harmonisation of Technical Requirements for Pharmaceuticals for Human Use - Good
             Clinical Practice (ICH-GCP), and national/local regulations.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Not meeting inclusion criteria

          -  Female patients who are pregnant or lactating.

          -  Any reason why, in the opinion of the investigator, the patient should not participate
             (e.g. not able to comply with study procedures, including being unable to perform full
             ophthalmologic examination).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Torstein Baade Rø</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>NTNU Department of Clinical and Molecular Medicine (IKOM)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Tobias S Slørdahl, MD PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+47 72 82 51 00</phone>
    <email>tobias.s.slordahl@ntnu.no</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Fredrik Schjesvold, MD PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+47 23 07 04 60</phone>
    <email>fredrikschjesvold@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Oslo University Hospital, Department of Hematology, Oslo Myeloma Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Oslo</city>
        <country>Norway</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Fredrik Schjesvold, MD PhD</last_name>
      <email>fredrikschjesvold@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>St. Olavs Hospital, Department of Hematology</name>
      <address>
        <city>Trondheim</city>
        <country>Norway</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Tobias S Slørdahl, MD PhD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Norway</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 11, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 11, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">November 14, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 25, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 25, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 28, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Drug Therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Administration and Dosage</keyword>
  <keyword>Hydroxychloroquine</keyword>
  <keyword>Carfilzomib</keyword>
  <keyword>Dexamethasone</keyword>
  <keyword>Drug Therapy, Combination</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Multiple Myeloma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms, Plasma Cell</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hydroxychloroquine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dexamethasone</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>tba</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

