<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04395066</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2018KY149</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04395066</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Molecular Diagnosis and Prognosis of Severe Pulmonary Infection Immunosuppressed Hosts</brief_title>
  <official_title>Molecular Diagnosis and Prognosis of Severe Pulmonary Infection in Immunosuppressed Hosts</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Shanghai General Hospital, Shanghai Jiao Tong University School of Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Shanghai General Hospital, Shanghai Jiao Tong University School of Medicine</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Serious pneumonia is a serious inflammation of the lungs caused by various pathogens,
      resulting in severe bacteraemia or toxemia, which in turn causes blood pressure drop, shock,
      blurred consciousness, restlessness, delirium and coma, etc., and requires intensive care and
      treatment in intensive care unit (ICU) because of its seriousness. There is an upward trend
      in the number of clinically immunosuppressed host patients, including long-term use of
      glucocorticoids for rheumatoid immune diseases and kidney diseases, tumor chemotherapy, organ
      transplantation, etc. A huge risk for these patients is the diagnosis and treatment of
      infections, especially lung infections. We have previously observed a significant increase in
      mortality from severe pneumonia in immunosuppressed patients, and our recent analysis of 204
      patients with novel coronavirus pneumonia found that low lymphatic counts, immunosuppression,
      etc. were independent risk factors for death in patients. Early diagnosis and timely
      treatment are the main means to reduce the mortality rate of severe pneumonia. CD55 is an
      important complement regulatory protein that inhibits C3 and C5 activation by blocking the
      formation and accelerating the decay of new C3 and C5 convertases, both of which mediate the
      downstream action of all three complement activation pathways, and CD55 protects host cells
      from complement attack. Our previous study found that CD55 was significantly elevated in
      patients with severe pneumonia. Therefore, this project proposes &quot;Early diagnosis of severe
      pneumonia based on combination of biomarkers with new generation pathogenesis and early
      clinical manifestations&quot;. It is proposed to validate the predictive effects of recently
      discovered markers such as CD55, HBP and CD64 on severe pneumonia through prospective
      single-center clinical studies, explore the establishment of new predictive models for early
      diagnosis of severe pneumonia, and optimize the diagnosis and treatment strategy of severe
      pneumonia, and provide new ideas for accurate treatment of severe pneumonia.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">June 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 1, 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 1, 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational [Patient Registry]</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <target_duration>28 Days</target_duration>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of patient diagnosed with severe pneumonia within 28 days</measure>
    <time_frame>28 days</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">171</enrollment>
  <condition>Severe Pneumonia</condition>
  <condition>Immunosuppressed Hosts</condition>
  <condition>Diagnosis</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>CD55</intervention_name>
    <description>CD55 is an important complement regulatory protein that inhibits C3 and C5 activation by blocking the formation and accelerating the decay of new C3 and C5 convertases, both of which mediate downstream actions of all three complement activation pathways, and CD55 protects host cells from complement attack.</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        ICU immunosuppressed pneumonia patients
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  ① Age ≥ 18 years, ≤ 75 years, male or female

               -  Patients diagnosed with severe pneumonia ③ Immunosuppressed patients

                    -  Patient informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  ① Pregnant women, lactating women and women who are at risk of pregnancy.

               -  Patients with malignant neoplasms that have metastasized extensively and are
                  expected to have a short survival period.

                    -  Patients with obstructive pneumonia and interstitial fibrosis due to lung
                       tumours.

                         -  refusal of the patient or the patient's family to participate in the
                            study.

                              -  Refusal of invasive mechanical ventilation and tracheal intubation
                                 by the patient or the patient's family.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
  </eligibility>
  <verification_date>May 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 15, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 19, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 20, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 19, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 19, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 20, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Shanghai General Hospital, Shanghai Jiao Tong University School of Medicine</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Ruilan Wang</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>PhD</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pneumonia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

