<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04399200</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2019-A03085-52</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2019-A03085-52</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04399200</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Apnea, Stroke and Incident Cardiovascular Events</brief_title>
  <acronym>ASCENT</acronym>
  <official_title>Sleep Apnea Syndrome and Incidence of Major Adverse Cardiac and Cerebrovascular Events (MACCEs) After a First Stroke</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University Hospital, Grenoble</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University Hospital, Grenoble</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This prospective cohort study aims to compare the proportion of cardiac or cerebrovascular
      events after a first stroke, a first transient ischemic attack (TIA) or recurrent TIA,
      between sleep-disordered breathing (SDB) and non-SDB (control) patients, one year after SDB
      diagnosis, performed 3 months after stroke onset.

      The primary outcome is a composite endpoint composed of cardiac or cerebrovascular events
      regrouping: death from any cardiac or cerebrovascular cause, non-fatal stroke, and non-fatal
      acute coronary disease.

      1620 patients, in the acute phase of a first stroke, TIA or recurrent TIA will be included in
      the cohort.

      Clinical, neuroimaging, sensorimotor, cognitive and biological parameters will be collected
      at inclusion. Three months after stroke or TIA onset, polysomnography will be performed for
      SDB diagnosis. Patients will be considered as having SDB for an Apnea-Hypopnea Index (AHI) &gt;
      15 events/hour, or to the control group otherwise. The same clinical, imaging, cognitive and
      biological assessments than during the first visit will be performed; incident (new)
      cardiovascular events will be collected. Three months later, and at 1, 2, 3, 4 and 5 years
      after SDB diagnosis, the same clinical, cognitive, sensorimotor, and sleep-related
      evaluations will be performed. In addition to the aforementioned parameters, incident
      cardiovascular outcomes will be collected, at the same time points. The primary study outcome
      will be retrieved one year after stroke onset.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a prospective cohort study that aims at comparing the proportion of incident
      cardiovascular events after a first stroke, first transient ischemic attack (TIA) or
      recurrent TIA, between sleep-disordered breathing patients (SDB, defined as an apnea-hypopnea
      index &gt; 15 events/hour) and non-SDB patients, one year after SDB diagnosis performed by
      polysomnography 3 months after the cerebrovascular event.

      The primary outcome is a composite endpoint composed of cardiac or cerebrovascular events
      (Major Adverse Cardiovascular Events, MACCEs), regrouping: death from any cardiac or
      cerebrovascular cause, non-fatal stroke, non-fatal acute coronary event. Secondary outcomes
      include secondary cardiac and cerebrovascular events; stroke-related functional criteria;
      lesion-related criteria obtained from morphological MRI; scores on questionnaires assessing
      the quality of life, depression and sleep; functional, cognitive and sensorimotor
      evaluations; locomotion tests; and sleep-related criteria.

      1620 patients, aged 18 to 85 years, in the acute phase (&lt;72h) of a first stroke, first or
      recurrent TIA, and with a score on the modified Rankin Scale (mRS) ≤1 before stroke onset,
      will be included in the cohort. All patients included in the study will be followed for 5
      years. The schedule of follow-up will be as follow :

        -  Selection visit (Days 0 to 3): verification of eligibility criteria, patients' or
           relatives' information, informed consent signature.

        -  Inclusion visit (Days 4 to 7): clinical history and treatments, clinical evaluation and
           anthropometrical parameters, stroke-related criteria (including score on the National
           Institute of Health Stroke Scale), functional, cognitive, and sensorimotor evaluation,
           walking and locomotion tests, questionnaires, stroke imagery by magnetic resonance
           imagery, blood sampling.

        -  SDB diagnosis (Month 3): the same clinical, MRI and biological parameters will be
           collected and the same questionnaires will be fulfilled by the patients. In addition,
           they will undergo polysomnography to assess their SDB status. Patients will be assigned
           to the SDB group if the AHI &gt; 15 events/hour; otherwise they will be assigned to the
           control group. Patients assigned to the SDB group will be proposed a treatment for their
           SDB according to standard care procedures.

        -  Clinical follow-up: sleep and neurological; (initial 3 months and then annually after
           SDB diagnosis up to 5 years after SDB diagnosis): retrieval of new cardiac or
           cerebrovascular events (primary study outcome (MACCEs)), stroke-related parameters,
           questionnaires, functional, cognitive, and sensorimotor evaluations, locomotion tests,
           sleep follow-up (adherence to SDB treatment, tolerance, efficacy). Biological sampling
           will also be done at 1, 2 and 5 years after SDB diagnosis.

      Ancillary study - CAtSS (Carotid, Atherosclerosis, Stroke and Sleep apnea) Conjointly to the
      previously described ASCENT protocol, an ancillary study will be proposed to the subgroup of
      patients eligible for carotid surgery (endarterectomy) following their cerebrovascular event.

      The purpose of this ancillary study is to evaluate the impact of SDB and SDB treatment on the
      evolution of the carotid plaque after surgery. For the patients who accepted to participate
      to this ancillary study, the degree of carotid stenosis and the artery wall thickness
      (intima-media thickness, assessed by echo-Doppler) will be measured during the inclusion
      visit, at 3 months, 6 months, and at each annual visit. During surgery, a fragment of carotid
      plaque will be kept for morphologic and histologic analyses as well as miRNAs dosing, miARNs
      being recognized as indicators of carotid plaque instability. Plasmatic and urine samples
      will also be collected for miRNA analyses.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">June 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 1, 2035</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 1, 2030</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Prevalence of Major Adverse Cardiac or Cerebrovascular Events (MACCEs)</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year after SDB diagnosis</time_frame>
    <description>Composite endpoint composed of cardiac or cerebrovascular events regrouping: death from cardiac of cerebrovascular cause, non fatal stroke (either ischemic or hemorrhagic), and non-fatal acute coronary disease</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Prevalence of Major Adverse Cardiac or Cerebrovascular Events (MACCEs)</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years after SDB diagnosis</time_frame>
    <description>Composite endpoint composed of cardiac or cerebrovascular events regrouping: death from cardiac of cerebrovascular cause, non fatal stroke (either ischemic or hemorrhagic), and non-fatal acute coronary disease</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Prevalence of secondary cardiac or cerebrovascular events</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years after SDB diagnosis</time_frame>
    <description>Composite endpoint composed of cardiac or cerebrovascular events regrouping: transient ischemic attack (TIA), any acute coronary disease, hospitalization for any cardio-vascular cause and peripheral artery disease</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in BMI from inclusion to 5 years</measure>
    <time_frame>at inclusion, and at each visit up to 5 years after SDB diagnosis</time_frame>
    <description>Change in body mass index (BMI), defined as weight (Kg)/height (m)². This will be calculated at inclusion and at each visit</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in waist, neck, and abdominal circumferences, from inclusion visit to 5 years</measure>
    <time_frame>at inclusion, and at each visit up to 5 years after SDB diagnosis</time_frame>
    <description>Change in waist, neck and abdominal circumferences in cm. This will be measured at inclusion and at each visit.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in NIHSS score from inclusion to 5 years</measure>
    <time_frame>at inclusion, and at each visit up to 5 years after SDB diagnosis</time_frame>
    <description>Stroke severity assessed by National Institute of Health Stroke Scale (NIHSS). This tool is composed of 15 items, each assessing specific abilities. (0: no stroke symptoms; 1 to 4: minor stroke; 5 to 15: moderate stroke; 16-20: moderate to severe stroke; &gt;20 : severe stroke). The scale will be administered at each visit.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>ABCD² score at inclusion</measure>
    <time_frame>at inclusion</time_frame>
    <description>Score evaluating the risk for stroke after a transient ischemic attack (TIA). The scale ranges from 0 (low level) to 7 (high level). 0 to 3: low risk; 4 to 5: moderate, 6 to 7: high risk</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical outcome: change in modified Ranking Sale (mRS) from inclusion to 5 years</measure>
    <time_frame>at inclusion, and at each visit up to 5 years after SDB diagnosis</time_frame>
    <description>Scale assessing functional outcome after stroke, ranging from 0 (no symptoms at all) to 5 (severe disability), measured at each visit</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical outcome: change in Functional Independence Measure (FIM) from inclusion to 5 years</measure>
    <time_frame>at inclusion, and at each visit up to 5 years after SDB diagnosis</time_frame>
    <description>Scale assessing functional outcome after stroke, ranging from 18 (totally dependent) to 126 (totally independent), measured at each visit</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical outcome: change in Stroke Impact Scale (SIS-16) from inclusion to 5 years</measure>
    <time_frame>at inclusion, and at each visit up to 5 years after SDB diagnosis</time_frame>
    <description>This scale assess patient's health after stroke, through 16 items evaluating functional independence and mobility. This scale ranges from 16 (total independance) to 80 (total dependancy). The scale will be administer at each visit</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical outcome: change Patient Health Questionnaire (PHQ-9) from inclusion to 5 years</measure>
    <time_frame>at inclusion, and at each visit up to 5 years after SDB diagnosis</time_frame>
    <description>Scale assessing patient's depression symptoms, administered at each visit. The scale ranges from 0 (no depression) to 27 (severe depression).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical outcome: change Fugl-Meyer Assessment Scale from inclusion to 5 years</measure>
    <time_frame>at inclusion, and at each visit up to 5 years after SDB diagnosis</time_frame>
    <description>Scale assessing sensori-motor upper extremity function in post-stroke patients, administered at each visit. The maximal possible score is 226, which corresponds to a complete sensori-motor recovery.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in walking and locomotion abilities: nFAC score, from inclusion to 5 years</measure>
    <time_frame>at inclusion, and at each visit up to 5 years after SDB diagnosis</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluation of ambulation abilities, from 0 (cannot walk) to 8 (able to walk independantly)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in walking and locomotion abilities: 10m walking test, from inclusion to 5 years</measure>
    <time_frame>at inclusion, and at each visit up to 5 years after SDB diagnosis</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluation of speed on the 10m walking test</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in daytime sleepiness: score on the Epworth Sleepiness Scale, from inclusion to 5 years</measure>
    <time_frame>at inclusion, and at each visit up to 5 years after SDB diagnosis</time_frame>
    <description>Daytime sleepiness score measured by Epworth Sleepiness Scale. The scale ranges from 0 (no sleepiness) to 24 (severe sleepiness)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in daytime sleepiness: score Berlin Questionnaire for Sleep Apnea (BQSA)</measure>
    <time_frame>at inclusion, and at each visit up to 5 years after SDB diagnosis</time_frame>
    <description>Sleep apnea screening questionnaire that identifies the risk (from low to high) of sleep disordered breathing</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assessment of sleep and fatigue: score change on Chalder Fatigue Scale from inclusion to 5 years</measure>
    <time_frame>at inclusion, and at each visit up to 5 years after SDB diagnosis</time_frame>
    <description>Questionnaire evaluating the severity of tiredness, on a scale ranging from 0 (no fatigue) to 33 (severe), administered at each visit</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assessment of sleep and fatigue: score change on Fatigue Severity Scale (FSS) from inclusion to 5 years</measure>
    <time_frame>at inclusion, and at each visit up to 5 years after SDB diagnosis</time_frame>
    <description>Questionnaire evaluating the severity of tiredness, on a scale ranging from 9 (no fatigue) to 63 (severe), administered at each visit</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assessment of sleep and fatigue: score change on Pichot's Fatigue Scale from inclusion to 5 years</measure>
    <time_frame>at inclusion, and at each visit up to 5 years after SDB diagnosis</time_frame>
    <description>Questionnaire evaluating the severity of tiredness, on a scale ranging from 0 (no fatigue) to 32 (severe), administered at each visit</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in depression symptoms from inclusion to 5 years : Pichot's Depression Scale (QD2A)</measure>
    <time_frame>at inclusion, and at each visit up to 5 years after SDB diagnosis</time_frame>
    <description>Questionnaire evaluating depression symptoms through right/false responses to 13 items, administered at each visit (score: 0 to 13)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in cognitive abilities from inclusion to 5 years: scores on the Montreal Cognitive Assessment Test</measure>
    <time_frame>at inclusion, and at each visit up to 5 years after SDB diagnosis</time_frame>
    <description>Global assessment of cognitive functions, evaluating on 30 points and in 10 minutes short-term memory, verbal fluency, visuoconstructive abilities, executive functions, attention, working memory, language and spatiotemporal orientation. The test will be administered at each visit.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in cognitive abilities from inclusion to 5 years : scores on the Frontal Assessment Battery</measure>
    <time_frame>at inclusion, and at each visit up to 5 years after SDB diagnosis</time_frame>
    <description>Short screening test evaluating executive function, on a scale from 0 (severe disability) to 18 (no disability)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in cognitive abilities from inclusion to 5 years : Language Screening Test (LAST)</measure>
    <time_frame>at inclusion, and at each visit up to 5 years after SDB diagnosis</time_frame>
    <description>Rapid evaluation of language abilities (oral expression and comprehension) through 15 items (total score: 15).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Prevalence of SDB assessed by polysomnography</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months post-stroke</time_frame>
    <description>Prevalence of SDB, assessed by polysomnography, and defined as AHI (Apnea-Hypopnea Index &gt;15/h)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Prevalence of respiratory disorders</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months post-stroke</time_frame>
    <description>Respiratory assessments : spirometry, plethysmography, CO diffusion, blood gas measurement, measurement of ventilatory response to CO2</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in adherence to SDB treatments, from 6 months to 5 years after SDB diagnosis</measure>
    <time_frame>from 6 months and at each visit up to 5 years after SDB diagnosis</time_frame>
    <description>Treatment adherence, assessed by CPAP monitoring (mean hours/night) if applicable</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Stroke characteristics : lesion volume</measure>
    <time_frame>At inclusion</time_frame>
    <description>Stroke volume in mm3, determined on MRI/CT scan</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Concentration of C-Reactive protein</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Concentration of C-Reactive protein by blood sampling</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in degree of carotid stenosis (ancillary study)</measure>
    <time_frame>from 3 months to 5 years after SDB diagnosis</time_frame>
    <description>NASCET (North American Symptomatic Carotid Endarterectomy) evaluation of carotid stenosis in percent by Echo-doppler</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in intima-media thickness (ancillary study) from 3 months to 5 years</measure>
    <time_frame>from 3 months to 5 years after SDB diagnosis</time_frame>
    <description>Measurement of carotid intima-media thickness (in mm) by Echo-Doppler</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Plasmatic and urinary miRNAs (ancillary study)</measure>
    <time_frame>from 3 months to 5 years after SDB diagnosis</time_frame>
    <description>miRNA expression and modulation in plasma and urine</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>miRNAs in carotid artery plaque (ancillary study)</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline (carotid surgery)</time_frame>
    <description>miARNs expression and modulation in carotid artery plaque</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Prevalence of post-operative complication (ancillary study)</measure>
    <time_frame>from 3 months to 5 years after SDB diagnosis</time_frame>
    <description>Prevalence of post-operative complication defined as post-operative hematomy, nerve palsy of nerves X and XII, per - post-operative ischemic or hemorragic strokes, myocardial infarction, death</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adipose tissue analysis (ancillary study)</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline (carotid surgery)</time_frame>
    <description>Morphological analysis of adipose tissue collected during endarteriectomy, expression of membrane and lipidic and glycemic markers, expression of inflammatory markers</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">1620</enrollment>
  <condition>Stroke</condition>
  <condition>Sleep-disordered Breathing</condition>
  <condition>Sleep Apnea Syndromes</condition>
  <condition>Sleep Apnea, Obstructive</condition>
  <condition>Sleep Apnea, Central</condition>
  <condition>Fragmentation, Sleep</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sleep-disordered breathing group</arm_group_label>
    <description>Sleep-disordered breathing (SDB) patients (AHI&gt;15/h, measured by polysomnography performed 3 months after stroke)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control group</arm_group_label>
    <description>Control patients with no SDB (AHI&lt;15/h, measured by polysomnography performed 3 months after stroke)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Treatment according to standard care recommandation</intervention_name>
    <description>SDB treatment according to standard care recommandation: Continuous Positive Airway Pressure (CPAP), Mandibular Advancement Device, Positionnal Therapy, Adaptive Servo-Ventilation (ASV), Non-Invasive Ventilation (NIV)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Sleep-disordered breathing group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Blood Urine Carotid plaque
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients in the acute phase (&lt;72h) of a first stroke or initial/recurrent TIA, admitted in
        the stroke unit of the Grenoble Alpes University Hospital.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Male or female, aged 18 to 85 years

          -  Admitted in the stroke unit no later than 72h after the onset of stroke symptoms:

               -  First stroke confirmed by computed tomography scan or magnetic resonance imaging,
                  whatever the localization

               -  Initial or recurrent TIA, as defined by a brief and sudden neurological
                  dysfunction for which an ischemic cause is presumed, with symptoms lasting less
                  than 24 hours, and/or with no visible lesion on neuroimaging evaluation.

          -  Score on the Modified Ranking scale (mRS) ≤1 before stroke

          -  Signed informed consent by patient or his/her relative if not able

          -  Patient eligible to carotid endarterectomy (for ancillary study only)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Pregnant or breastfeeding women

          -  Past history of stroke

          -  Inability to follow rehabilitation procedure

          -  Patients with ongoing treatment for SDB

          -  Exclusion period for another study

          -  Patients not affiliated to a French social and health insurance system or equivalent

          -  Prisoners or patients who require protection by the law
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>85 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Renaud Tamisier, MD, PhD, MBA</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University Hospital, Grenoble</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Sébastien Baillieul, MD, MSc</last_name>
    <phone>+33 (0)4 76 76 87 66</phone>
    <email>sbaillieul@chu-grenoble.fr</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Marjorie Dole, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+33 (0)4 76 76 69 18</phone>
    <email>mdole2@chu-grenoble.fr</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Hospital Grenoble</name>
      <address>
        <city>Grenoble</city>
        <zip>38043</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sébastien Baillieul, MD, MSc</last_name>
      <phone>+33 (0)4 76 76 87 66</phone>
      <email>sbaillieul@chu-grenoble.fr</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Marjorie Dole, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>+33 (0)4 76 76 69 18</phone>
      <email>mdole2@chu-grenoble.fr</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jean-Louis Pépin, Pr</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Marie Destors, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Chrystel Saint Raymond, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Olivier Detante, Pr</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Isabelle Favre-Wiki, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Katia Garambois, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Raphaëlle Spear, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>GBD 2016 Stroke Collaborators. Global, regional, and national burden of stroke, 1990-2016: a systematic analysis for the Global Burden of Disease Study 2016. Lancet Neurol. 2019 May;18(5):439-458. doi: 10.1016/S1474-4422(19)30034-1. Epub 2019 Mar 11.</citation>
    <PMID>30871944</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Javaheri S, Barbe F, Campos-Rodriguez F, Dempsey JA, Khayat R, Javaheri S, Malhotra A, Martinez-Garcia MA, Mehra R, Pack AI, Polotsky VY, Redline S, Somers VK. Sleep Apnea: Types, Mechanisms, and Clinical Cardiovascular Consequences. J Am Coll Cardiol. 2017 Feb 21;69(7):841-858. doi: 10.1016/j.jacc.2016.11.069. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>28209226</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hermann DM, Bassetti CL. Role of sleep-disordered breathing and sleep-wake disturbances for stroke and stroke recovery. Neurology. 2016 Sep 27;87(13):1407-16. doi: 10.1212/WNL.0000000000003037. Epub 2016 Aug 3. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>27488603</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Seiler A, Camilo M, Korostovtseva L, Haynes AG, Brill AK, Horvath T, Egger M, Bassetti CL. Prevalence of sleep-disordered breathing after stroke and TIA: A meta-analysis. Neurology. 2019 Feb 12;92(7):e648-e654. doi: 10.1212/WNL.0000000000006904. Epub 2019 Jan 11.</citation>
    <PMID>30635478</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lisabeth LD, Sánchez BN, Lim D, Chervin RD, Case E, Morgenstern LB, Tower S, Brown DL. Sleep-disordered breathing and poststroke outcomes. Ann Neurol. 2019 Aug;86(2):241-250. doi: 10.1002/ana.25515. Epub 2019 Jun 19.</citation>
    <PMID>31155749</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Brill AK, Horvath T, Seiler A, Camilo M, Haynes AG, Ott SR, Egger M, Bassetti CL. CPAP as treatment of sleep apnea after stroke: A meta-analysis of randomized trials. Neurology. 2018 Apr 3;90(14):e1222-e1230. doi: 10.1212/WNL.0000000000005262. Epub 2018 Mar 9.</citation>
    <PMID>29523641</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Amarenco P, Lavallée PC, Labreuche J, Albers GW, Bornstein NM, Canhão P, Caplan LR, Donnan GA, Ferro JM, Hennerici MG, Molina C, Rothwell PM, Sissani L, Školoudík D, Steg PG, Touboul PJ, Uchiyama S, Vicaut É, Wong LK; TIAregistry.org Investigators. One-Year Risk of Stroke after Transient Ischemic Attack or Minor Stroke. N Engl J Med. 2016 Apr 21;374(16):1533-42. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa1412981.</citation>
    <PMID>27096581</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Amarenco P, Lavallée PC, Monteiro Tavares L, Labreuche J, Albers GW, Abboud H, Anticoli S, Audebert H, Bornstein NM, Caplan LR, Correia M, Donnan GA, Ferro JM, Gongora-Rivera F, Heide W, Hennerici MG, Kelly PJ, Král M, Lin HF, Molina C, Park JM, Purroy F, Rothwell PM, Segura T, Školoudík D, Steg PG, Touboul PJ, Uchiyama S, Vicaut É, Wang Y, Wong LKS; TIAregistry.org Investigators. Five-Year Risk of Stroke after TIA or Minor Ischemic Stroke. N Engl J Med. 2018 Jun 7;378(23):2182-2190. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa1802712. Epub 2018 May 16.</citation>
    <PMID>29766771</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wardlaw JM, Brazzelli M, Chappell FM, Miranda H, Shuler K, Sandercock PA, Dennis MS. ABCD2 score and secondary stroke prevention: meta-analysis and effect per 1,000 patients triaged. Neurology. 2015 Jul 28;85(4):373-80. doi: 10.1212/WNL.0000000000001780. Epub 2015 Jul 1. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26136519</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Broderick JP, Adeoye O, Elm J. Evolution of the Modified Rankin Scale and Its Use in Future Stroke Trials. Stroke. 2017 Jul;48(7):2007-2012. doi: 10.1161/STROKEAHA.117.017866. Epub 2017 Jun 16. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>28626052</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wahlund LO, Barkhof F, Fazekas F, Bronge L, Augustin M, Sjögren M, Wallin A, Ader H, Leys D, Pantoni L, Pasquier F, Erkinjuntti T, Scheltens P; European Task Force on Age-Related White Matter Changes. A new rating scale for age-related white matter changes applicable to MRI and CT. Stroke. 2001 Jun;32(6):1318-22.</citation>
    <PMID>11387493</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Benjamin EJ, Blaha MJ, Chiuve SE, Cushman M, Das SR, Deo R, de Ferranti SD, Floyd J, Fornage M, Gillespie C, Isasi CR, Jiménez MC, Jordan LC, Judd SE, Lackland D, Lichtman JH, Lisabeth L, Liu S, Longenecker CT, Mackey RH, Matsushita K, Mozaffarian D, Mussolino ME, Nasir K, Neumar RW, Palaniappan L, Pandey DK, Thiagarajan RR, Reeves MJ, Ritchey M, Rodriguez CJ, Roth GA, Rosamond WD, Sasson C, Towfighi A, Tsao CW, Turner MB, Virani SS, Voeks JH, Willey JZ, Wilkins JT, Wu JH, Alger HM, Wong SS, Muntner P; American Heart Association Statistics Committee and Stroke Statistics Subcommittee. Heart Disease and Stroke Statistics-2017 Update: A Report From the American Heart Association. Circulation. 2017 Mar 7;135(10):e146-e603. doi: 10.1161/CIR.0000000000000485. Epub 2017 Jan 25. Review. Erratum in: Circulation. 2017 Mar 7;135(10 ):e646. Circulation. 2017 Sep 5;136(10 ):e196.</citation>
    <PMID>28122885</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cramer SC, Wolf SL, Adams HP Jr, Chen D, Dromerick AW, Dunning K, Ellerbe C, Grande A, Janis S, Lansberg MG, Lazar RM, Palesch YY, Richards L, Roth E, Savitz SI, Wechsler LR, Wintermark M, Broderick JP. Stroke Recovery and Rehabilitation Research: Issues, Opportunities, and the National Institutes of Health StrokeNet. Stroke. 2017 Mar;48(3):813-819. doi: 10.1161/STROKEAHA.116.015501. Epub 2017 Feb 7.</citation>
    <PMID>28174324</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kernan WN, Ovbiagele B, Black HR, Bravata DM, Chimowitz MI, Ezekowitz MD, Fang MC, Fisher M, Furie KL, Heck DV, Johnston SC, Kasner SE, Kittner SJ, Mitchell PH, Rich MW, Richardson D, Schwamm LH, Wilson JA; American Heart Association Stroke Council, Council on Cardiovascular and Stroke Nursing, Council on Clinical Cardiology, and Council on Peripheral Vascular Disease. Guidelines for the prevention of stroke in patients with stroke and transient ischemic attack: a guideline for healthcare professionals from the American Heart Association/American Stroke Association. Stroke. 2014 Jul;45(7):2160-236. doi: 10.1161/STR.0000000000000024. Epub 2014 May 1. Erratum in: Stroke. 2015 Feb;46(2):e54.</citation>
    <PMID>24788967</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Benjafield AV, Ayas NT, Eastwood PR, Heinzer R, Ip MSM, Morrell MJ, Nunez CM, Patel SR, Penzel T, Pépin JL, Peppard PE, Sinha S, Tufik S, Valentine K, Malhotra A. Estimation of the global prevalence and burden of obstructive sleep apnoea: a literature-based analysis. Lancet Respir Med. 2019 Aug;7(8):687-698. doi: 10.1016/S2213-2600(19)30198-5. Epub 2019 Jul 9. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>31300334</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lévy P, Kohler M, McNicholas WT, Barbé F, McEvoy RD, Somers VK, Lavie L, Pépin JL. Obstructive sleep apnoea syndrome. Nat Rev Dis Primers. 2015 Jun 25;1:15015. doi: 10.1038/nrdp.2015.15. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>27188535</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Berry RB, Budhiraja R, Gottlieb DJ, Gozal D, Iber C, Kapur VK, Marcus CL, Mehra R, Parthasarathy S, Quan SF, Redline S, Strohl KP, Davidson Ward SL, Tangredi MM; American Academy of Sleep Medicine. Rules for scoring respiratory events in sleep: update of the 2007 AASM Manual for the Scoring of Sleep and Associated Events. Deliberations of the Sleep Apnea Definitions Task Force of the American Academy of Sleep Medicine. J Clin Sleep Med. 2012 Oct 15;8(5):597-619. doi: 10.5664/jcsm.2172.</citation>
    <PMID>23066376</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lévy P, Tamisier R, Minville C, Launois S, Pépin JL. Sleep apnoea syndrome in 2011: current concepts and future directions. Eur Respir Rev. 2011 Sep 1;20(121):134-46. doi: 10.1183/09059180.00003111. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21881142</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>McEvoy RD, Antic NA, Heeley E, Luo Y, Ou Q, Zhang X, Mediano O, Chen R, Drager LF, Liu Z, Chen G, Du B, McArdle N, Mukherjee S, Tripathi M, Billot L, Li Q, Lorenzi-Filho G, Barbe F, Redline S, Wang J, Arima H, Neal B, White DP, Grunstein RR, Zhong N, Anderson CS; SAVE Investigators and Coordinators. CPAP for Prevention of Cardiovascular Events in Obstructive Sleep Apnea. N Engl J Med. 2016 Sep 8;375(10):919-31. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa1606599. Epub 2016 Aug 28.</citation>
    <PMID>27571048</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Alexiev F, Brill AK, Ott SR, Duss S, Schmidt M, Bassetti CL. Sleep-disordered breathing and stroke: chicken or egg? J Thorac Dis. 2018 Dec;10(Suppl 34):S4244-S4252. doi: 10.21037/jtd.2018.12.66. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>30687540</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Loke YK, Brown JW, Kwok CS, Niruban A, Myint PK. Association of obstructive sleep apnea with risk of serious cardiovascular events: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Circ Cardiovasc Qual Outcomes. 2012 Sep 1;5(5):720-8. Epub 2012 Jul 24. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22828826</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Duss SB, Brill AK, Bargiotas P, Facchin L, Alexiev F, Manconi M, Bassetti CL. Sleep-Wake Disorders in Stroke-Increased Stroke Risk and Deteriorated Recovery? An Evaluation on the Necessity for Prevention and Treatment. Curr Neurol Neurosci Rep. 2018 Sep 7;18(10):72. doi: 10.1007/s11910-018-0879-6. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>30194550</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bassetti CL, Milanova M, Gugger M. Sleep-disordered breathing and acute ischemic stroke: diagnosis, risk factors, treatment, evolution, and long-term clinical outcome. Stroke. 2006 Apr;37(4):967-72. Epub 2006 Mar 16.</citation>
    <PMID>16543515</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yaggi HK, Concato J, Kernan WN, Lichtman JH, Brass LM, Mohsenin V. Obstructive sleep apnea as a risk factor for stroke and death. N Engl J Med. 2005 Nov 10;353(19):2034-41.</citation>
    <PMID>16282178</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sahlin C, Sandberg O, Gustafson Y, Bucht G, Carlberg B, Stenlund H, Franklin KA. Obstructive sleep apnea is a risk factor for death in patients with stroke: a 10-year follow-up. Arch Intern Med. 2008 Feb 11;168(3):297-301. doi: 10.1001/archinternmed.2007.70.</citation>
    <PMID>18268171</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Aaronson JA, van Bennekom CA, Hofman WF, van Bezeij T, van den Aardweg JG, Groet E, Kylstra WA, Schmand BA. The effect of obstructive sleep apnea and treatment with continuous positive airway pressure on stroke rehabilitation: rationale, design and methods of the TOROS study. BMC Neurol. 2014 Feb 25;14:36. doi: 10.1186/1471-2377-14-36.</citation>
    <PMID>24568360</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kaneko Y, Hajek VE, Zivanovic V, Raboud J, Bradley TD. Relationship of sleep apnea to functional capacity and length of hospitalization following stroke. Sleep. 2003 May 1;26(3):293-7.</citation>
    <PMID>12749548</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Duss SB, Seiler A, Schmidt MH, Pace M, Adamantidis A, Müri RM, Bassetti CL. The role of sleep in recovery following ischemic stroke: A review of human and animal data. Neurobiol Sleep Circadian Rhythms. 2016 Nov 29;2:94-105. doi: 10.1016/j.nbscr.2016.11.003. eCollection 2017 Jan. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>31236498</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lovett JK, Dennis MS, Sandercock PA, Bamford J, Warlow CP, Rothwell PM. Very early risk of stroke after a first transient ischemic attack. Stroke. 2003 Aug;34(8):e138-40. Epub 2003 Jul 10.</citation>
    <PMID>12855835</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Johnston SC, Gress DR, Browner WS, Sidney S. Short-term prognosis after emergency department diagnosis of TIA. JAMA. 2000 Dec 13;284(22):2901-6.</citation>
    <PMID>11147987</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kendzerska T, Wilton K, Bahar R, Ryan CM. Short- and long-term continuous positive airway pressure usage in the post-stroke population with obstructive sleep apnea. Sleep Breath. 2019 Dec;23(4):1233-1244. doi: 10.1007/s11325-019-01811-9. Epub 2019 Feb 28.</citation>
    <PMID>30820850</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tsivgoulis G, Alexandrov AV, Katsanos AH, Barlinn K, Mikulik R, Lambadiari V, Bonakis A, Alexandrov AW. Noninvasive Ventilatory Correction in Patients With Acute Ischemic Stroke: A Systematic Review and Meta-Analysis. Stroke. 2017 Aug;48(8):2285-2288. doi: 10.1161/STROKEAHA.117.017661. Epub 2017 Jun 8. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>28596449</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Parra O, Sánchez-Armengol Á, Capote F, Bonnin M, Arboix A, Campos-Rodríguez F, Pérez-Ronchel J, Durán-Cantolla J, Martínez-Null C, de la Peña M, Jiménez MC, Masa F, Casadon I, Alonso ML, Macarrón JL. Efficacy of continuous positive airway pressure treatment on 5-year survival in patients with ischaemic stroke and obstructive sleep apnea: a randomized controlled trial. J Sleep Res. 2015 Feb;24(1):47-53. doi: 10.1111/jsr.12181. Epub 2014 Jul 21. Erratum in: J Sleep Res. 2015 Aug;24(4):474.</citation>
    <PMID>25040553</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Martínez-García MA, Campos-Rodríguez F, Soler-Cataluña JJ, Catalán-Serra P, Román-Sánchez P, Montserrat JM. Increased incidence of nonfatal cardiovascular events in stroke patients with sleep apnoea: effect of CPAP treatment. Eur Respir J. 2012 Apr;39(4):906-12. doi: 10.1183/09031936.00011311. Epub 2011 Sep 29.</citation>
    <PMID>21965227</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Barbé F, Durán-Cantolla J, Sánchez-de-la-Torre M, Martínez-Alonso M, Carmona C, Barceló A, Chiner E, Masa JF, Gonzalez M, Marín JM, Garcia-Rio F, Diaz de Atauri J, Terán J, Mayos M, de la Peña M, Monasterio C, del Campo F, Montserrat JM; Spanish Sleep And Breathing Network. Effect of continuous positive airway pressure on the incidence of hypertension and cardiovascular events in nonsleepy patients with obstructive sleep apnea: a randomized controlled trial. JAMA. 2012 May 23;307(20):2161-8. doi: 10.1001/jama.2012.4366.</citation>
    <PMID>22618923</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kim Y, Koo YS, Lee HY, Lee SY. Can Continuous Positive Airway Pressure Reduce the Risk of Stroke in Obstructive Sleep Apnea Patients? A Systematic Review and Meta-Analysis. PLoS One. 2016 Jan 5;11(1):e0146317. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0146317. eCollection 2016. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26731604</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Adams HP Jr, Bendixen BH, Kappelle LJ, Biller J, Love BB, Gordon DL, Marsh EE 3rd. Classification of subtype of acute ischemic stroke. Definitions for use in a multicenter clinical trial. TOAST. Trial of Org 10172 in Acute Stroke Treatment. Stroke. 1993 Jan;24(1):35-41.</citation>
    <PMID>7678184</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Amarenco P, Bogousslavsky J, Caplan LR, Donnan GA, Hennerici MG. Classification of stroke subtypes. Cerebrovasc Dis. 2009;27(5):493-501. doi: 10.1159/000210432. Epub 2009 Apr 3. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19342825</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Naylor AR, Ricco JB, de Borst GJ, Debus S, de Haro J, Halliday A, Hamilton G, Kakisis J, Kakkos S, Lepidi S, Markus HS, McCabe DJ, Roy J, Sillesen H, van den Berg JC, Vermassen F, Esvs Guidelines Committee, Kolh P, Chakfe N, Hinchliffe RJ, Koncar I, Lindholt JS, Vega de Ceniga M, Verzini F, Esvs Guideline Reviewers, Archie J, Bellmunt S, Chaudhuri A, Koelemay M, Lindahl AK, Padberg F, Venermo M. Editor's Choice - Management of Atherosclerotic Carotid and Vertebral Artery Disease: 2017 Clinical Practice Guidelines of the European Society for Vascular Surgery (ESVS). Eur J Vasc Endovasc Surg. 2018 Jan;55(1):3-81. doi: 10.1016/j.ejvs.2017.06.021. Epub 2017 Aug 26.</citation>
    <PMID>28851594</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schulz R, Seeger W, Fegbeutel C, Hüsken H, Bödeker RH, Tillmanns H, Grebe M. Changes in extracranial arteries in obstructive sleep apnoea. Eur Respir J. 2005 Jan;25(1):69-74.</citation>
    <PMID>15640325</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ehrhardt J, Schwab M, Finn S, Guenther A, Schultze T, Witte OW, Rupprecht S. Sleep apnea and asymptomatic carotid stenosis: a complex interaction. Chest. 2015 Apr;147(4):1029-1036. doi: 10.1378/chest.14-1655.</citation>
    <PMID>25429400</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Suzuki M, Shimamoto K, Sekiguchi H, Harada T, Satoya N, Inoue Y, Yamaguchi K, Kawana M. Arousal index as a marker of carotid artery atherosclerosis in patients with obstructive sleep apnea syndrome. Sleep Breath. 2019 Mar;23(1):87-94. doi: 10.1007/s11325-018-1664-0. Epub 2018 May 19.</citation>
    <PMID>29779142</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Eken SM, Jin H, Chernogubova E, Li Y, Simon N, Sun C, Korzunowicz G, Busch A, Bäcklund A, Österholm C, Razuvaev A, Renné T, Eckstein HH, Pelisek J, Eriksson P, González Díez M, Perisic Matic L, Schellinger IN, Raaz U, Leeper NJ, Hansson GK, Paulsson-Berne G, Hedin U, Maegdefessel L. MicroRNA-210 Enhances Fibrous Cap Stability in Advanced Atherosclerotic Lesions. Circ Res. 2017 Feb 17;120(4):633-644. doi: 10.1161/CIRCRESAHA.116.309318. Epub 2016 Nov 28.</citation>
    <PMID>27895035</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wang LQ, Wang CL, Xu LN, Hua DF. The expression research of miR-210 in the elderly patients with COPD combined with ischemic stroke. Eur Rev Med Pharmacol Sci. 2016 Nov;20(22):4756-4760.</citation>
    <PMID>27906445</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Duncan PW, Lai SM, Bode RK, Perera S, DeRosa J. Stroke Impact Scale-16: A brief assessment of physical function. Neurology. 2003 Jan 28;60(2):291-6.</citation>
    <PMID>12552047</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nadarajah M, Mazlan M, Abdul-Latif L, Goh HT. Test-retest reliability, internal consistency and concurrent validity of Fatigue Severity Scale in measuring post-stroke fatigue. Eur J Phys Rehabil Med. 2017 Oct;53(5):703-709. doi: 10.23736/S1973-9087.16.04388-4. Epub 2016 Oct 21.</citation>
    <PMID>27768012</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dubois B, Slachevsky A, Litvan I, Pillon B. The FAB: a Frontal Assessment Battery at bedside. Neurology. 2000 Dec 12;55(11):1621-6.</citation>
    <PMID>11113214</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Flamand-Roze C, Falissard B, Roze E, Maintigneux L, Beziz J, Chacon A, Join-Lambert C, Adams D, Denier C. Validation of a new language screening tool for patients with acute stroke: the Language Screening Test (LAST). Stroke. 2011 May;42(5):1224-9. doi: 10.1161/STROKEAHA.110.609503. Epub 2011 Apr 12.</citation>
    <PMID>21487118</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Spitzer RL. More on pseudoscience in science and the case for psychiatric diagnosis. A critique of D.L. Rosenhan's &quot;On Being Sane in Insane Places&quot; and &quot;The Contestual Nature of Psychiatric Diagnosis&quot;. Arch Gen Psychiatry. 1976 Apr;33(4):459-70.</citation>
    <PMID>938183</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Birkbak J, Clark AJ, Rod NH. The effect of sleep disordered breathing on the outcome of stroke and transient ischemic attack: a systematic review. J Clin Sleep Med. 2014 Jan 15;10(1):103-8. doi: 10.5664/jcsm.3376. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24426829</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 25, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 18, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 22, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 18, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 18, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 22, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Stroke</keyword>
  <keyword>Sleep-disordered Breathing</keyword>
  <keyword>Cardio-Vascular Events</keyword>
  <keyword>Atherosclerosis</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Apnea</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sleep Apnea Syndromes</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Respiratory Aspiration</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sleep Apnea, Obstructive</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sleep Apnea, Central</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Stroke</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sleep Deprivation</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Syndrome</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

