<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04396366</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CQBW251C12201</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04396366</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study of Safety, Tolerability, Pharmacokinetics and Pharmacodynamics of QBW251 in Subjects With Bronchiectasis</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized, Subject- and Investigator-blinded, Placebo-controlled, Parallel Group Study to Assess the Safety, Tolerability, Pharmacokinetics and Pharmacodynamics of QBW251 in Patients With Bronchiectasis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Novartis Pharmaceuticals</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Innovative Medicines Initiative</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Novartis</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to determine whether potentiating the cystic fibrosis
      transmembrane conductance regulator (CFTR) with QBW251 in patients with bronchiectasis will
      demonstrate clinical safety and efficacy related to improved mucociliary clearance with
      reduced bacterial colonization as potential drivers of airway obstruction, reduced airway
      inflammation, exacerbations and mucus load, improved lung function, clinical symptoms and
      quality of life to support further development in bronchiectasis.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a randomized, subject- and investigator-blinded, placebo-controlled, parallel-group
      study investigating the preliminary efficacy and safety of QBW251 administered orally for 12
      weeks in subjects with bronchiectasis. Approximately 72 subjects will be randomized in a 1:1
      ratio to receive either QBW251 or placebo in order to achieve 60 subjects who complete the
      treatment period based on the assumption of a 16% drop-out rate. The sample size assumptions
      will be reviewed in an interim analysis in a blinded manner when approximately 14 subjects
      complete the treatment period.

      The study consists of the following periods: Screening, baseline/Day 1, treatment period, and
      end of study assessments (EOS) visit followed by an additional post-treatment safety follow
      up via phone call. The total duration for each patient in the study is up to approximately 18
      weeks.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">November 30, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 1, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 1, 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in bacterial load Colony forming units (CFU/mL) of potentially pathogenic microorganisms in sputum at week 12</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Bacterial load is measured by the number of colony forming units (CFU/ml) of potentially pathogenic microorganisms in sputum</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of subjects with absence of any colony forming units (CFU/mL) of porentially pathogenic bacteria sputum</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Change from baseline on sputum bacterial clearance</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of Life Questionnaire for Bronchiectasis (QOL-B) (Respiratory symptoms domain)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The Quality of Life Questionnaire for Bronchiectasis (QOL-B) is a disease-specific questionnaire developed for non-cystic fibrosis bronchiectasis. It covers 8 dimensions: physical functioning, role functioning, emotional functioning, social functioning, vitality, treatment burden, health perceptions, and respiratory symptoms. Each dimension is scored separately on a scale of 0 to 100, and higher scores represent better outcomes. Only the respiratory symptoms domain score is reported for this outcome measure.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Fibrinogen plasma concentration</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>To assess the change from baseline of fibrinogen plasma</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in rescue medication use (salbutamol/albuterol)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>To assess the effect of QBW251 compared to placebo after 12 weeks of treatment on rescue medication use</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>FEV1</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>To assess the effect of QBW251 compared to placebo after 12 weeks of treatment on spirometry (Forced Exploratory Volume in the first second).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Airway wall</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Change from baseline in airway wall after 12 weeks of treatment, as measured by high resolution computed tomography (HRCT).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>FVC</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>To assess the effect of QBW251 compared to placebo after 12 weeks of treatment on spirometry (Forced Vital Capacity).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cmax of QBW251</measure>
    <time_frame>1h, 2h, 3h, 4h, 6h and 8h post-dose on Days 1 and 28, and 3h post-dose on Day 56 and Day 84</time_frame>
    <description>Maximum (peak) plasma concentration of QBW251</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Ctrough of QBW251</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-dose Day 1, Day 28, Day 56, Day 84</time_frame>
    <description>Trough (pre-dose) plasma concentration of QBW251.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Airway lumen</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Change from baseline in airway lumen after 12 weeks of treatment, as measured by high resolution computed tomography (HRCT).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Airway extent of global and regional air trapping</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Change from baseline in the extent of global and regional air trapping after 12 weeks of treatment, as measured by high resolution computed tomography (HRCT)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>AUC of QBW251</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-dose, 1h, 2h, 3h, 4h, 6h and 8h post-dose on Day 1 and Day 28</time_frame>
    <description>Area under the concentration-time curve (AUC) of QBW251</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">72</enrollment>
  <condition>Bronchiectasis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Placebo controlled arm</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>QBW251</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Active comparator drug arm</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Active drug</intervention_name>
    <description>QBW251 Capsule 300mg Oral use, one capsule twice daily.</description>
    <arm_group_label>QBW251</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Placebo Capsule 300mg Oral use, one capsule twice daily.</description>
    <arm_group_label>placebo</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Comparator</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Written informed consent must be obtained before any assessment is performed.

          -  Male or female patients aged ≥18 years at screening.

          -  Proven diagnosis of bronchiectasis by chest HRCT

          -  Evidence of sputum bacterial load of ≥106 CFU/mL with at least one potentially
             pathogenic microorganism at screening (H. Influenzae, M catarrhalis, S aureus, S
             pneumoniae, Enterobacteriaceae, P aeruginosa, Stenotrophomonous maltophilia, or any
             potential pathogenic non-fermenting Gram negative bacteria measured by
             dilution/outgrowth.) Any organism that is to be included and that is not included in
             the list of 7 protocol defined pathogens, requires approval by the steering committee
             in collaboraton with Novartis for inclusion

          -  Documented history of at least one bronchiectasis exacerbation in the 12 months prior
             to screening.

          -  Patients with bronchial hypersecretion, defined as productive cough that occurs on
             most days (defined as &gt;50% days) for at least three consecutive months within 12
             months prior to screening, as assessed by documentation of patient recollection
             (anamnesis) or documented in patients' record.

          -  Patients are allowed to stay on fixed or free combinations of LABA/LAMA or LABA/ICS or
             LABA/LAMA/ICS as maintenance therapy if they are treated with them at a stable dose
             for the last 3 months prior to screening. Patients are also allowed to stay on
             macrolides as maintenance therapy if they are treated with them at a stable dose 3
             months before screening. If prescribed, patients are included in the study with
             unchanged chest physiotherapy for at least 4 weeks prior to screening.

          -  Clinically stable pulmonary status in the opinion of the investigator and unlikely to
             require any change in the standard regimen of care during the course of the study.

          -  Able to perform reliable, reproducible pulmonary function test maneuvers per American
             Thoracic Society/European Respiratory Society (ATS/ERS) guidelines at screening. At
             screening, patients who have failed to meet ATS/ERS requirements for acceptability and
             reproducibility for spirometry will be allowed one additional repeat testing session
             during the screening period.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Use of other investigational drugs at the time of enrollment, or within 5 half-lives
             of enrollment, or within 30 days, whichever is longer; or longer if required by local
             regulations. Current or planned participation to another clinical trial during this
             study.

          -  History of hypersensitivity to the study drugs or to drugs of similar chemical classes
             or excipients.

          -  Patients with a history of long-QT syndrome or the QTcF interval at Screening or
             baseline is prolonged (QTcF &gt;450 ms in males, &gt;460 ms in females).

          -  Patients who have a clinically significant ECG abnormality before randomization Note:
             Clinically significant abnormalities may include but are not limited to the following:
             left bundle branch block, Wolff-Parkinson-White syndrome, clinically significant
             arrhythmias (e.g. atrial fibrillation, ventricular tachycardia).

          -  Patients with a history or current treatment for hepatic disease including but not
             limited to acute or chronic hepatitis, cirrhosis or hepatic failure or an aspartate
             aminotransferase (AST) to alanine aminotransferase(ALT) ratio(AST/ALT) or prothrombin
             time international normalized ratio(PT/INR) of more than 1.5xULN at screening.

          -  History of lung transplant or malignancy of any organ system (other than localized
             basal cell carcinoma of the skin), treated or untreated, within the past 5 years,
             regardless of whether there is evidence of local recurrence or metastases, with the
             exception of localized basal cell carcinoma of the skin. Patients with segmentectomy
             for other reasons than cancer are allowed to be included in the study. Patients with a
             history of cancer and 5 years or more disease free survival time may be included in
             the study by agreement with Novartis Medical Monitor on a case-by-case basis.

          -  Pregnant or nursing (lactating) women, where pregnancy is defined as the state of a
             female after conception and until the termination of gestation, confirmed by a
             positive hCG laboratory blood test.

          -  Women of child-bearing potential, defined as all women physiologically capable of
             becoming pregnant, unless they are using acceptable effective methods of contraception
             during study participation.

          -  Use of prescription drugs prohibited as stated in the Section 6.2.2 within 1 week
             prior to Day 1.

          -  Clinical significant laboratory values abnormalities (including G-GT, AST, ALT, total
             bilirubin or creatinine) in the opinion of the investigator at screening. For
             additional guidance on hepatic parameters refer to exclusion criterion #5

          -  Patients requiring long-term oxygen therapy for chronic hypoxemia. This is typically
             patients requiring oxygen therapy &gt;12 h per day delivered by home oxygen cylinder or
             concentrator. Note: Nocturnal oxygen therapy for transient oxygen desaturations during
             sleep is allowed.

          -  Patients with bronchiectasis who have had a pulmonary exacerbation with a
             deterioration in three or more of key symptoms for at least 48 h and a clinicians
             determines that a change bronchiectasis treatment is required within 4 weeks prior to
             screening.

          -  Hemoptysis, requiring medical intervention at any time within 4 weeks prior to
             screening.

          -  Bronchiectasis predominantly characterized by isolated cavitary lung lesions.

          -  Patients with bronchiectasis requiring therapy that may interfere with the assessment
             of QBW251 efficiency or that are unlikely to respond to QBW251

          -  Current or ex-smokers with severe emphysema.

          -  Patients with another concomitant pulmonary disease according to the definition of the
             International ERS/ATS guidelines, including but not limited to COPD, asthma,
             interstitial pulmonary fibrosis (IPF), sarcoidosis or other granulomatous or
             infectious process. Concomitant COPD and asthma with characteristics of airway
             hyperresponsiveness as well as COPD-Asthma overlap syndrome are allowed as long as it
             is not the main, primary diagnosis.

          -  Patients currently receiving treatment for nontuberculous mycobacterial (NTM)
             pulmonary disease.

          -  Patients with a known history of non-compliance to medication or who are unable or
             unwilling to complete an electronic patient diary or patient reported outcome
             questionnaire.

          -  Recent (within three years of screening) and/or recurrent history of autonomic
             dysfunction (e.g., recurrent episodes of fainting, palpitations, etc.).

          -  Patients with a major vascular surgery in the 6 months prior to the screening visit.

          -  Patients who have clinically significant renal, cardiovascular (such as but not
             limited to unstable ischemic heart disease, NYHA Class III/IV left ventricular
             failure, myocardial infarction), neurological, endocrine, immunological, psychiatric,
             gastrointestinal, or hematological abnormalities, which could interfere with the
             assessment of the efficacy and safety of the study treatment, or patients with Type I
             diabetes or uncontrolled Type II diabetes.

          -  Known or suspected history of ongoing, chronic or recurrent infectious disease of HIV,
             Hepatitis B/C.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Novartis Pharmaceuticals</last_name>
    <phone>+41613241111</phone>
    <email>novartis.email@novartis.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Novartis Pharmaceuticals</last_name>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <verification_date>May 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 18, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 18, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 20, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 18, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 18, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 20, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Bronchiectasis</keyword>
  <keyword>QBW251</keyword>
  <keyword>colony forming units</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Bronchiectasis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Novartis is committed to sharing with qualified external researchers, access to patient-level data and supporting clinical documents from eligible studies. These requests are reviewed and approved by an independent review panel on the basis of scientific merit. All data provided is anonymized to respect the privacy of patients who have participated in the trial in line with applicable laws and regulations. This trial data availability is according to the criteria and process described on www.clinicalstudydatarequest.com.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

