<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04394260</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IRB00113264</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04394260</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Equality in Caregiving</brief_title>
  <acronym>EIC</acronym>
  <official_title>Equality in Caregiving: Intervention to Facilitate Caregiver Mastery Among LGBT Caregivers of PLWD</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Emory University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Emory University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The primary goal of this pilot clinical trial is to establish the readiness of an
      intervention addressing the unique challenges facing lesbian, gay, bisexual, and transgender
      (LGBT) informal caregivers of person living with dementia (PLWD), and geared toward achieving
      caregiver mastery in this high-risk population, for a larger efficacy trial.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Over 15 million family caregivers provide more than $200 billion in unpaid care to a person
      living with dementia (PLWD). Informal caregiving for PLWD by lesbian, gay, bisexual, and
      transgender (LGBT) individuals continues to receive limited attention, and current research
      rarely examines how caregiving for PLWD affects the LGBT community.

      The primary goal of this pilot clinical trial is to establish the readiness of an
      intervention addressing the unique challenges facing LGBT informal caregivers of PLWD, and
      geared toward achieving caregiver mastery in this high-risk population for a larger efficacy
      trial.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">July 30, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Caregiver Depression Center for Epidemiologic Studies Depression Scale (CES-〖D)〗score</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 6-week follow up</time_frame>
    <description>A 20-item scale that represents a symptom cluster consisting of negative affect, positive affect, interpersonal problems, and somatic activity based on feelings over the past week.Scores range 0 - 60. A score of 0-16 indicates little to no symptomatology, a score of 16 or more indicates depression with higher scores indicating increased severity.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Caregiver Burden The Zarit Burden Interview score</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 6-week follow up</time_frame>
    <description>The interview was developed to measure subjective burden among caregivers of adults with dementia. The 22-item self-report inventory examines burden associated with functional/behavioral impairments and the home care situation. The items are worded subjectively, focusing on the affective response of the caregiver. Scores range 0 - 88. Lower scores indicate little to no burden. Higher scores indicate greater burden. A score of 17 or more is considered high burden.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Caregiver Stress Perceived Stress Survey score</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 6-week follow up</time_frame>
    <description>This questionnaire is comprised of 10 items from the Perceived Stress Scale. Scores range 0 - 40. Higher scores indicating higher perceived stress. A score of 0-13 would be considered low stress. Scores from 14-26 would be considered moderate stress. Scores from 27-40 indicate high perceived stress.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Caregiver Mastery Pearlin Caregiver Stress Scale score</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 6-week follow up</time_frame>
    <description>Comprised of 6 domains from the full Pearlin Stress Scale. 1. Relational Deprivation: 6-24, higher scores indicate increased relational deprivation. 2. Role Captivity: 3 - 12, higher scores indicate an increased feeling of being trapped in the caregiver role. 3. Loss of Self: 2 - 8, higher scores indicate a greater loss of self. 4. Caregiving competence: 4 - 16, higher scores indicate greater caregiving competence. 5. Management of Situation: 4 - 16, higher scores indicate better management of the caregiving situation. 6. Management of Meaning: 9 - 36, higher scores indicate a better management of the meaning of the caregiving role.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Positive Aspects of Caregiving (PCOS) Scale score</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 6-week follow up</time_frame>
    <description>Caregivers will be instructed that &quot;In spite of all the difficulties involved in giving care to a family member with memory or health problems, good things can come out of caregiving experiences.&quot; The scale has 11 items, and overall scores range 0 - 44. Higher scores indicate a more positive view of the caregiving role while lower scores indicate less positive views of the caregiver role.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Care recipient quality of life DEMQOL: Dementia Quality of Life Measure (Carer v4) score</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 6-week follow up</time_frame>
    <description>This 32 item questionnaire will be used to assess mood, cognitive status, and overall quality of life of the care recipient. Scores range 31 - 124. Lower scores indicate no subjective concerns about cognition or general health, while higher scores indicate a greater subjective concern about cognition and general health.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Behavioral and Psychological Symptoms of Dementia Revised Memory and Behavior Problem Checklist (RMBPC) score</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 6-week follow up</time_frame>
    <description>This 24 item instrument measures the frequency of the care recipient's problem behaviors in the following domains: disruptive behavior (wandering, aggression), memory-related behavior (repeating questions and stories), and depression. Scores range 0 - 96 for frequency. Lower scores indicate little to no behavioral problems while higher scores indicate greater behavioral issues. Scores range 0 - 96 for reaction. Lower scores indicate little concern regarding the behavior on the part of the caregiver while higher scores indicate greater concern.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Family Quality of Life in Dementia Scale score</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 6-week follow up</time_frame>
    <description>Yet unpublished survey is about how the caregiver feels their life together is as a &quot;family&quot;. The family can include many different people. Scores range 41 - 205. Lower scores indicate poor quality of life as a family dealing with a loved one with dementia while higher scores indicate a higher quality of life as a family.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Nursing Skills Questionnaire score</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 6-week follow up</time_frame>
    <description>Adapted from an AARP survey, this questionnaire assesses the likelihood of a caregiver to engage in nursing type skills with their care recipient. Scores range 0 - 34. Lower scores indicate the caregiver is less likely to complete nursing tasks with their care recipient while higher scores indicate the caregiver is more likely to complete nursing tasks.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in systolic blood pressure</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 6-week follow up</time_frame>
    <description>Blood pressure will be measured using sphygmomanometer</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in diastolic blood pressure</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 6-week follow up</time_frame>
    <description>Blood pressure will be measured using sphygmomanometer</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in cortisol level</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 6-week follow up</time_frame>
    <description>Blood test will be used to measure the stress marker</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in C-reactive protein (CRP) level</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 6-week follow up</time_frame>
    <description>Blood test will be used to measure the inflammatory marker</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in interleukin-7 level</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 6-week follow up</time_frame>
    <description>Blood test will be used to measure the inflammatory marker</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in interleukin-8 level</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 6-week follow up</time_frame>
    <description>Blood test will be used to measure the inflammatory marker</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in interleukin-9 level</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 6-week follow up</time_frame>
    <description>Blood test will be used to measure the inflammatory marker</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in interleukin-10 level</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 6-week follow up</time_frame>
    <description>Blood test will be used to measure the inflammatory marker</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in interferon induced protein 10 level</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 6-week follow up</time_frame>
    <description>Blood test will be used to measure the inflammatory marker</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in macrophage derived chemokine level</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 6-week follow up</time_frame>
    <description>Blood test will be used to measure the inflammatory marker</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in monocyte chemoattractant protein 1 level</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 6-week follow up</time_frame>
    <description>Blood test will be used to measure the inflammatory marker</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in itransforming growth factor alpha level</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 6-week follow up</time_frame>
    <description>Blood test will be used to measure the inflammatory marker</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in tumor necrosis factor alpha level</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 6-week follow up</time_frame>
    <description>Blood test will be used to measure the inflammatory marker</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in ICAM-1 level</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 6-week follow up</time_frame>
    <description>Blood test will be used to measure the endothelial marker</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in VCAM-1 level</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 6-week follow up</time_frame>
    <description>Blood test will be used to measure the endothelial marker</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">45</enrollment>
  <condition>Dementia</condition>
  <condition>Caregiver Burnout</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Savvy Caregiver Program (SCP)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The SCP program is comprised of weekly, two-hour interactive classes, over six consecutive weeks, the same duration as the proposed intervention. The SCP consists of educational instruction and in-class exercises that engage participants on a functional level. Course material was designed to provide informal caregivers with the knowledge, skills, and attitude needed to carry out their role as a caregiver for a person living with dementia (PLWD). Course learning objectives include: 1) introduction to dementing disorder; 2) caregiver self-care; 3) the anchors of enjoyable involvement; 4) levels of thinking and performance; 5) strengthening the family as a resource for caregiving; and 6) review and integration of the previous sections.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Modified LGBT Savvy Group program</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>LGBT-friendly SCP is designed to assess the stressors and unique needs of LGBT caregivers of PLWD, not reflected in the existing SCP. Modifications to the SCP include themes of physical, interpersonal, financial, social, and environmental stressors specific to LGBT caregivers.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Savvy Caregiver Program</intervention_name>
    <description>The SCP program is comprised of weekly, two-hour interactive classes, over six consecutive weeks, the same duration as the proposed intervention. The SCP consists of educational instruction and in-class exercises that engage participants on a functional level. Course learning objectives include: 1) introduction to dementing disorder; 2) caregiver self-care; 3) the anchors of enjoyable involvement; 4) levels of thinking and performance; 5) strengthening the family as a resource for caregiving; and 6) review and integration of the previous sections.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Savvy Caregiver Program (SCP)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Savvy Caregiver Program provided via Zoom</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Modified LGBT Savvy Group program</intervention_name>
    <description>The LGBT adapted SCP is the same duration as the existing SCP (i.e., 6 weeks, 2 hours per week, for a total of 12 hours). The program facilitators, clinical study visits and standardized questionnaires are similar for LGBT SCP intervention, however addition or removal of questionnaires is possible.Modifications to the SCP include themes of physical, interpersonal, financial, social, and environmental stressors specific to LGBT caregivers.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Modified LGBT Savvy Group program</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Modified LGBT Savvy Group program provided via Zoom</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Focus group</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will be asked to return to take part in a 90-minute focus group to discuss their experience with the SCP and how the course material applies to them as a LGBT caregiver. Focus Group: Semi-structured discussion will include, but not be limited to the following questions: 1) Can you tell me about your role as a caregiver? (Probes: living situation, experiences, challenges). 2) What went well with the SCP, and what could be improved? 3) How relevant to your situation as an LGBT caregiver were the course materials? 4) How well did the questionnaire reflect your experiences with discrimination due to sexual orientation and/or gender identity? (Probe about when working with your care recipient's health care providers, in-home aides/visiting nurses, adult day care staff, respite, etc? 5) What are some of the additional caregiver challenges that should be considered in these questionnaires? (Probes: mental health, physical health, and social life strain, Quality of life, stress).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Modified LGBT Savvy Group program</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Savvy Caregiver Program (SCP)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Self-identification as a LGBT adult (18 yrs. and over)

          2. Provides informal care to a community dwelling family member or friend with dementia

          3. Available to attend all SCP classes and one focus group and

          4. Consent to blood draw

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Residence in a skilled nursing facility

          2. Significant neurological disease, stroke, TBI, or significant head trauma

          3. Any significant systemic illness or unstable medical condition which could affect
             cognition, cause difficulty complying with the protocol or consenting for study
             procedures

          4. History of alcohol substance abuse or dependence

          5. Currently participating in a study with an intervention (i.e., social/behavioral,
             drug, or device)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <gender_based>Yes</gender_based>
    <gender_description>Self-identification as a LGBT adult</gender_description>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Whitney Wharton, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Emory University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Whitney Wharton, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>404-712-7359</phone>
    <email>w.wharton@emory.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Morgan Hecker</last_name>
    <phone>404-712-2654</phone>
    <email>morgan.hecker@emory.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Emory Goizueta Alzheimer's Disease Research Center (ADRC)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Atlanta</city>
        <state>Georgia</state>
        <zip>30322</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Whitney Wharton, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>404-712-7359</phone>
      <email>w.wharton@emory.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 15, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 15, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 19, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 20, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 20, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 22, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Emory University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Whitney Wharton</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>PLWD</keyword>
  <keyword>LGBT</keyword>
  <keyword>Informal caregiver</keyword>
  <keyword>Savvy Caregiving Program</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Burnout, Psychological</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Individual participant data that underlies the results reported in this article, after deidentification (text, tables, figures, and appendices) will be shared</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Informed Consent Form (ICF)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>Immediately following publication with no end date</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>Researchers who provide a methodologically sound proposal to achieve aims in the approved proposal will get access. Proposals should be directed to (w.wharton@emory.edu). To gain access, data requestors will need to sign a data access agreement. Data will then be shared directly via csv or excel file.</ipd_access_criteria>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

