<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04395469</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>UHN REB 19-6358-C</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04395469</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>FAZA PET/MRI Pancreas</brief_title>
  <official_title>Feasibility Study of Hypoxia and Re-oxygenation Imaging in Pancreatic Cancer Using Positron Emission Tomography (PET) With [18F] Fluoroazomycin-arabinoside (FAZA PET) and Magnetic Resonance Imaging (MRI)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University Health Network, Toronto</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University Health Network, Toronto</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a single arm, single centre, investigator initiated study to investigate the use of
      FAZA-PET in combination with MRI. FAZA is an investigational radiotracer used in PET scans.
      FAZA PET-MRI will be used to measure hypoxia in up to 20 patients with unresectable,
      non-metastatic, locally advanced un-resectable pancreatic adenocarcinoma (LAPAC).

      After each FAZA PET-MRI scan, patients will be followed up via telephone, 48 hours after the
      imaging session to assure that the procedure was tolerated without side effects. Patients
      will undergo a FAZA PET-MRI scans before and after their standard of care radiation
      treatment.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The success of hypoxia-targeted therapies has so far been limited, a fact widely attributed
      to the absence of a reliable imaging biomarker for hypoxia that could easily be implemented
      into a routine clinical workflow. A compelling study has found the presence of hypoxia in
      pancreatic tumors using FAZA-PET imaging. The data derived from this alternative dual-imaging
      approach can be used to establish a patient-specific perfusion-to-hypoxia mapping, accounting
      for differences in tumour metabolisms. This technique was recently validated in a
      pre-clinical FAZA-PET/CE-MRI study of mice with orthotopically-implanted pancreatic
      patient-derived tumour xenografts.

      The purpose of this study is to look for hypoxia in tumours using a PET scan in combination
      with MRI. The use of PET/MRI scans to measure hypoxia may be better and simpler than the
      approaches used previously. This study will assess whether or not PET/MRI scans can provide
      useful information about hypoxia in pancreatic cancer. Additionally, a recent study at the
      Princess Margaret Cancer Centre found varying levels of hypoxia in patients with pancreatic
      tumors, providing a rationale for incorporating hypoxia imaging and patient-specific
      treatment adaptation into the clinical management of pancreatic cancer.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">August 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Tumor Hypoxia</measure>
    <time_frame>2.5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Hypoxic regions in the tumour are defined as regions for which the voxel-scale activity exceeds the mean activity in the left-ventricle blood pool by a ratio of 1.2. The fraction of such voxels in a given tumour defines the hypoxic fraction.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Pancreatic Adenocarcinoma Non-resectable</condition>
  <condition>Locally Advanced Pancreatic Adenocarcinoma</condition>
  <condition>Unresectable Pancreatic Cancer</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>18F-FAZA</intervention_name>
    <description>18F-FAZA is a radiotracer used for PET imaging (in combination with MRI) to detect hypoxia in tumours. This scan will be done before and after radiation treatment.</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Participants who have histologically confirmed new diagnosis of unresectable,
             non-metastatic, LAPAC as assessed by the multidisciplinary tumor board based on pre-RT
             imaging and clinical assessment, and are amenable to SBRT.

          2. Patients who received prior systemic therapy for unresectable LAPAC may be consented
             and enrolled if they still have localized unresectable LAPAC amenable to SBRT.

          3. Participants with newly diagnosed LAPAC who received systemic therapy for borderline
             resectable pancreatic adenocarcinoma and have become unresectable following
             preoperative multidisciplinary assessment, are eligible for the study if the patient
             meets the eligibility criteria based on staging following systemic therapy.

          4. Age ≥18 years.

          5. ECOG performance status ≤2 (see Appendix A).

          6. Life expectancy of greater than 6 months.

          7. A negative serum pregnancy test prior to PET-MR imaging, for women of child-bearing
             age.

          8. Ability to understand and the willingness to sign a written informed consent document.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients who have had prior RT to upper abdomen.

          2. Patients who are receiving any other concomitant investigational agents. Participants
             who have entered the follow-up phase of an investigational study may participate as
             long as it has been 4 weeks after the last dose of the previous investigational agent.

          3. Patients with early stage resectable (I-II) pancreatic cancer, or known distant
             metastases.

          4. Contraindication to MRI scan as per current institutional guidelines.

          5. Uncontrolled intercurrent illness including, but not limited to, ongoing or active
             infection, symptomatic congestive heart failure, unstable angina pectoris, cardiac
             arrhythmia, or psychiatric illness/social situations that would limit compliance with
             study requirements.

          6. Pregnant women are excluded from this study because of the potential teratogenic or
             abortifacient effects. Because there is an unknown but potential risk for adverse
             events in nursing infants, breastfeeding should be discontinued.

          7. Patients who have a known additional malignancy that is progressing or has required
             active treatment within the past 3 years. Participants with basal cell carcinoma of
             the skin, squamous cell carcinoma of the skin (other than head and neck region), or
             carcinoma in situ (e.g., in situ cervical cancer or breast carcinoma) that have
             undergone potentially curative therapy are not excluded.

          8. History or current evidence of any condition, therapy, or laboratory abnormality,
             known psychiatric or substance abuse disorders that might confound the results of the
             study, interfere with the participant's participation for the full duration of the
             study, or is not in the best interest of the participant to participate, in the
             opinion of the treating investigator.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Princess Margaret Cancer Centre</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toronto</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>M5G 2C1</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ali Hosni, MD</last_name>
      <phone>416-946-2360</phone>
      <email>ali.hosni.abdalaty@rmp.uhn.ca</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 15, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 15, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 20, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 15, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 15, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 20, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Hypoxia</keyword>
  <keyword>FAZA</keyword>
  <keyword>PET Imaging</keyword>
  <keyword>FAZA PET MRI</keyword>
  <keyword>locally advanced un-resectable pancreatic adenocarcinoma</keyword>
  <keyword>Unresectable</keyword>
  <keyword>Non-metastatic</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Adenocarcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pancreatic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Fluoroazomycin arabinoside</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

