<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04393896</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>71804197</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04393896</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Assessing a WeChat-based Integrative Family Intervention (WIFI) for Schizophrenia</brief_title>
  <official_title>Assessing a WeChat-based Integrative Family Intervention (WIFI) for Schizophrenia: a Stepped-wedge Cluster Randomized Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Xiangya Hospital of Central South University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Xiangya Hospital of Central South University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The study aims to test both the effectiveness and implementation strategy of a WeChat-based
      integrative family intervention (WIFI) to support family caregiving of schizophrenia in
      China.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The investigators will conduct a type 2 hybrid effectiveness-implementation study to test
      both the effect of and the implementation process of a WeChat-based integrative family
      intervention (WIFI) program. The program will include three core components: 1)
      psycho-education through WeChat Official Account (WOA), 2) peer support through WeChat chat
      group, and 3) professional support through WeChat video chat. A rigorous stepped wedge
      cluster randomized trial will be used to evaluate the implementation, effectiveness, and cost
      of the WIFI program. The WIFI program will be implemented in 12 communities affiliated with
      the Changsha psychiatric hospital through the free medicine delivery process in the 686
      Program. 20 families of schizophrenia will be selected from each community. The 12
      communities will be randomized to one of four fixed sequences every two months during an
      8-month intervention period in four clusters of 3 communities each. All clusters will receive
      the usual financial benefit of the Reward Policy as the control condition, and then
      successively and in random order, will cross over to the WIFI program at 2-month intervals
      until the study ends. Outcomes will be assessed for both family caregivers and the family
      member with schizophrenia. Family caregivers will be assessed for their knowledge and skills
      about caregiving, social support and coping, perceived stigma, caregiver burden, family
      functioning, positive feelings, and psychological distress. Schizophrenia individuals will be
      assessed for their symptoms and functioning, quality of life, recovery and
      re-hospitalization. Cost data such as costs of the intervention, health care utilization, and
      costs associated with lost productivity will also be collected. In addition, the
      investigators will collect process data including fidelity and quality of program
      implementation as well as users' attitudes will also be collected. Treatment effects will be
      estimated using generalized linear maximum likelihood mixed modeling (GLMM) with clusters as
      a random effect and time as a fixed effect. Cost-effectiveness analysis will be performed
      from the societal perspective using incremental cost effectiveness ratios (ICERs).
      Qualitative analysis will use the grounded theory approach and immersion-crystallization
      process. All statistical analyses will be conducted according to the intention-to-treat
      principle.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">September 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>This is a stepped-wedge cluster randomized trial. The WeChat-based integrative family intervention (WIFI) program will be implemented in 12 communities affiliated with the Changsha psychiatric hospital through the free medicine delivery process in the 686 Program. The 12 communities will be randomized to one of four fixed sequences every two months during an 8-month intervention period in four clusters of 3 communities each. All clusters will receive the usual financial benefit of the Reward Policy as the control condition, and then successively and in random order, will cross over to the WIFI intervention at 2-month intervals until the study ends.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Health Services Research</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>people living with schizophrenia, family caregivers, psychiatrists and researchers cannot be blinded for the allocated treatment. The program team conducting the intervention will not be involved in assessing any of the outcomes. The analyses of the data by the researcher will be blinded.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>caregiver burden at baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline</time_frame>
    <description>caregiver burden will be measured using the internationally standard caregiving burden scale---Zarit Burden Interview (ZBI) at baseline. The total score ranges from 0 to 88, with higher composite score indicating higher caregiver burden.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>caregiver burden at month 2</measure>
    <time_frame>2 months</time_frame>
    <description>caregiver burden will be measured using the internationally standard caregiving burden scale---Zarit Burden Interview (ZBI) after 2 months. The total score ranges from 0 to 88, with higher composite score indicating higher caregiver burden.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>caregiver burden at month 4</measure>
    <time_frame>4 months</time_frame>
    <description>caregiver burden will be measured using the internationally standard caregiving burden scale---Zarit Burden Interview (ZBI) after 4 months. The total score ranges from 0 to 88, with higher composite score indicating higher caregiver burden.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>caregiver burden at month 6</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>caregiver burden will be measured using the internationally standard caregiving burden scale---Zarit Burden Interview (ZBI) after 6 months. The total score ranges from 0 to 88, with higher composite score indicating higher caregiver burden.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>caregiver burden at month 8</measure>
    <time_frame>8 months</time_frame>
    <description>caregiver burden will be measured using the internationally standard caregiving burden scale---Zarit Burden Interview (ZBI) after 8 months. The total score ranges from 0 to 88, with higher composite score indicating higher caregiver burden.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Depression</measure>
    <time_frame>8 months</time_frame>
    <description>Depression will be measured using the internationally standard depression scale---Patient Health Questionnaire-9 (PHQ-9) at baseline, 2 months, 4 months, 6 months, 8 months. The total score ranges from 0 to 27, with higher score indicating more depressive symptoms.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Anxiety</measure>
    <time_frame>8 months</time_frame>
    <description>Anxiety will be measured using the internationally standard anxiety scale---Generalized Anxiety Disorder Scale-7 (GAD-7) at baseline, 2 months, 4 months, 6 months, 8 months. The total score ranges from 0 to 27, with higher score indicating more anxiety symptoms.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">240</enrollment>
  <condition>Schizophrenia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>intervention group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants in the intervention group will receive the usual financial benefits of the Reward Policy as well as the WIFI program which will include three key components: psycho-education through WOA publications, peer-support through a WeChat chat group, and professional support through WeChat private chat and video call.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>control group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants in the control group will receive the usual financial benefits of the Reward Policy and receive payment from the Changsha psychiatric hospital. However, they will not have access to the WIFI program since they cannot scan the WeChat barcode for the research.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>WeChat-based integrative family intervention (WIFI)</intervention_name>
    <description>The WIFI program will include three key components: psycho-education through WeChat Official Account publications, peer-support through a WeChat chat group, and professional support through WeChat private chat and video call</description>
    <arm_group_label>intervention group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        For people living with schizophrenia:

          -  being registered in the &quot;686 Program&quot;

          -  fulfilling the Chinese Classification of Mental Disorders-3 (CCMD-3) or the
             International Classification of Diseases-10 (ICD-10) criteria for schizophrenia

          -  living with at least one family member

          -  able to use a smartphone and WeChat to read and communicate

        For family members:

          -  joining the Reward Policy and receiving a subsidy for family care

          -  living with schizophrenia individuals for at least the past two years

          -  involved with caregiving activities of schizophrenia individuals

          -  able to use a smartphone and WeChat to read and communicate

          -  at least one family member having a smartphone with WeChat app installed.

        Exclusion Criteria:

        For people living with schizophrenia:

          -  diagnosed with mental illness other than schizophrenia

          -  living alone with no family members

          -  not able to use smartphones or WeChat

        For family members:

          -  not involved with caregiving activities for the schizophrenia individuals

          -  not able to use smartphones or WeChat
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Yu Yu, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Xiangya Hospital of Central South University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Yu Yu, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+8618774897811</phone>
    <email>403616846@qq.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Tongxin Li, Master</last_name>
    <phone>+15274984256</phone>
    <email>tongxin@csu.edu.cn</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Xiangya Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Changsha</city>
        <state>Hunan</state>
        <zip>410008</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yu Y, Liu ZW, Tang BW, Zhao M, Liu XG, Xiao SY. Reported family burden of schizophrenia patients in rural China. PLoS One. 2017 Jun 19;12(6):e0179425. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0179425. eCollection 2017.</citation>
    <PMID>28628657</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yu Y, Liu ZW, Zhou W, Chen XC, Zhang XY, Hu M, Xiao SY. Assessment of Burden Among Family Caregivers of Schizophrenia: Psychometric Testing for Short-Form Zarit Burden Interviews. Front Psychol. 2018 Dec 19;9:2539. doi: 10.3389/fpsyg.2018.02539. eCollection 2018.</citation>
    <PMID>30618960</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yu Y, Tang BW, Liu ZW, Chen YM, Zhang XY, Xiao S. Who cares for the schizophrenia individuals in rural China - A profile of primary family caregivers. Compr Psychiatry. 2018 Jul;84:47-53. doi: 10.1016/j.comppsych.2018.04.002. Epub 2018 Apr 11.</citation>
    <PMID>29684660</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yu Y, Zhou W, Xiao S. China's Reward Policy for Family Care of Persons With Serious Mental Illness. Psychiatr Serv. 2018 Dec 1;69(12):1210-1211. doi: 10.1176/appi.ps.201800114. Epub 2018 Oct 18.</citation>
    <PMID>30332924</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yu Y, Zhou W, Liu ZW, Hu M, Tan ZH, Xiao SY. Gender differences in caregiving among a schizophrenia population. Psychol Res Behav Manag. 2018 Dec 20;12:7-13. doi: 10.2147/PRBM.S187975. eCollection 2019.</citation>
    <PMID>30588138</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 27, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 17, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 19, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 7, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 7, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 9, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Schizophrenia</keyword>
  <keyword>Family intervention</keyword>
  <keyword>WeChat</keyword>
  <keyword>Stepped wedge</keyword>
  <keyword>Psycho-education</keyword>
  <keyword>Peer support</keyword>
  <keyword>Professional support</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Schizophrenia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Statistical Analysis Plan (SAP)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Informed Consent Form (ICF)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>Since the official start of the trial to the end of the trial</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>Describe clearly about the reason of review</ipd_access_criteria>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

