<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04399772</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>69712</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04399772</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>COgNitive FuncTional Therapy+ for Chronic Low Back paIn</brief_title>
  <acronym>CONFeTTI</acronym>
  <official_title>COgNitive FuncTional Therapy+ Versus Interdisciplinary Pain Management for Chronic Low Back Pain (the CONFeTTI Trial): a Randomized Controlled Trial of a Combined Physical/Psychological Intervention</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Odense University Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Southern Denmark</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Curtin University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Manchester Metropolitan University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Odense University Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study is a patient-blinded 2-arm randomized controlled trial (RCT) assessing the
      effectiveness (in the short and long term) as well as total healthcare costs of CFT+ (a
      combined physiotherapist/psychologist intervention) compared with interdisciplinary pain
      management program (usual care) for patients with chronic low back pain referred to
      interdisciplinary pain treatment.

      The primary aim of this RCT is to investigate the change in disability at 3 months in
      patients randomized to CFT+ compared with patients randomized to the interdisciplinary pain
      management program.

      Secondary aims are 1) to explore whether the difference in disability change scores is
      sustained at 12 months, and 2) whether the total healthcare costs differ between CFT+ and the
      interdisciplinary pain management program.

      In addition the study will explore changes in pain intensity, quality of life, thoughts and
      beliefs about back pain, and analgesic consumption in patients randomized to CFT+ compared
      with patients randomized to the interdisciplinary pain management program.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Evidence suggests that chronic low back pain (LBP) is a multidimensional biopsychosocial
      problem including various contributing factors, such as negative pain cognitions,
      pain-related fear and emotional distress, avoidant and protective movement behaviors,and
      unhelpful lifestyle factors such as activity avoidance and sleep problems. Current guidelines
      recommend that patients with chronic LBP who do not benefit from primary care treatment
      should be referred to interdisciplinary pain rehabilitation in secondary care settings.
      However, such treatments are often expensive, not easily accessible, and have only modest
      effects.

      Cognitive Functional Therapy (CFT) is a newer physiotherapeutic treatment approach for
      patients with chronic low back pain, involving all important elements for the individual
      patient. Physical factors are handled via change in pain-provoking movement patterns.
      Psychological factors are handled in relation to fear, avoidance behaviour,
      catastrophization, stress, anxiety, depression and negative thoughts. Lifestyle factors are
      addressed in relation to physical inactivity and sleep problems. The approach is
      individualized and provides the patient with opportunities for action in relation to his or
      her own situation via information, reflection, change of movement and training of functions
      and physical level.

      CFT has been shown to reduce fear and worry in patients with chronic low back pain compared
      to other interventions, and the effect of CFT alone on patients with severe chronic low back
      pain has been recently investigated in an observational study (without randomization) in our
      Pain Center (publication attached in link). In this study, we found a good and clinically
      relevant effect of CFT compared to standard treatment in a University Hospital
      Interdisciplinary Pain Center. However, not all patients improved from the CFT intervention,
      and there was a high dropout rate in the beginning of the CFT pathway suggesting that it did
      not suit the expectations of all patients.

      This fully-powered randomized controlled study compares effectiveness of this
      physiotherapeutic intervention including psychologist support (CFT+) with effectiveness of
      interdisciplinary pain treatment (recommended care) in patients with severe chronic low back
      pain.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">September 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>This study is a patient-blinded 2-arm randomized controlled trial with a parallel group design and 1:1 group allocation.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>This study has ethical approval that the patients involved are not aware that there is a difference between the two treatment strategies in the study. Patient masking in this study is done to ensure that included patients are as representative as possible.
The randomization sequence is distributed and stored in sealed opaque envelopes handled only by an independent study secretary who has no other involvement in the trial. All outcome measurements are completed via an electronic questionnaire system sent via personal links to the patients' official digital inbox, e-Boks (used by public hospitals, municipalities and other institutions to send official documents to citizens of Denmark). The researcher responsible for the statistical analyzes are blinded to group allocation.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pain-related disability during the last 7 days</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline to after 3 months of treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Assessed with the Oswestry Disability Index (ODI) that asks patients to choose statements that reflect their ability to manage their everyday life despite their back pain for the following domains pain intensity, personal care, lifting, walking, sitting, standing, sleeping, sex life, social life, and travelling.
Each item is scored between 0 and 5 with a total score between 0 and 50, and a percentage score is calculated based on the patients' total score divided by the total possible score. A lower score indicates lower disability.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Trajectory of Pain-related disability during the last 7 days</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed after 0, 3, 6, 9, and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Assessed with the Oswestry Disability Index (ODI) that asks patients to choose statements that reflect their ability to manage their everyday life despite their back pain for the following domains pain intensity, personal care, lifting, walking, sitting, standing, sleeping, sex life, social life, and travelling.
Each item is scored between 0 and 5 with a total score between 0 and 50, and a percentage score is calculated based on the patients' total score divided by the total possible score. A lower score indicates lower disability.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Average pain intensity during the last 24 hours</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed at 0, 3, 6, 9, and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Assessed by asking the participants about the level of average pain during the last 24 hours on a 11 point rating scale, ranging from 0-10 (0 = &quot;no pain&quot; and 10 = &quot;worst pain&quot;) using the 5th item from the Brief Pain Inventory Short Form. A lower score indicates lower pain intensity.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Health-related quality of life</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed at 0, 3 and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Measured by European Quality of Life 5 Dimensions (EQ-5D-3L) and the Visual Analogue Scale (EQ-VAS).
For the 5 dimensions the EQ5D-3L asks the participants to rate their ability for each domain (mobility, self-care, usual activities, pain/discomfort, and anxiety/depression), respectively on a 1-3 Verbal Rating Scale, a score of 1 indicating no problems/severity, and a score of 3 indicating extreme problems/severity. The EQ-VAS asks the participant to rate their overall health 'today' on a 0-100 VAS. A higher score indicates a better quality of life.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Level of pain catastrophization</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed at 0, 3 and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Measured by the Pain Catastrophizing Scale; asking participants to indicate the degree to which they experienced each of 13 thoughts or feelings when experiencing pain, on a 5-point Likert scale with 0 = not at all and 4 = all the time. The score is 0 to 52 with a higher score indicating a high level of pain catastrophizing.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Level of patient enablement</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed at 0, 3 and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Measured by the Patient Enablement Instrument for Back Pain; asking participants to indicate on a 11 point rating scale, ranging from 0-10 (0 = &quot;to a very low degree&quot; and 10 = &quot;to a very high degree&quot;) the degree to which they during the past week were able to 1) Cope with life, 2) Understand your back problem, 3) Cope with your back problem, 4) Keep your back healthy, 5) Feel confident about your health, and 6) Help yourself.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Economical evaluation</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed at 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>The economic evaluation of the RCT will estimate the cost per quality adjusted life year (QALY) gained from the CFT+ intervention, compared to interdisciplinary pain program treatment. The economic analyses will utilize the EQ5D data collected during the trial for the utility weights, and total healthcare costs will be obtained from linking the trial data to Danish registries.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Analgesics</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed at 0, 3 and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Use of analgesics (opioids, NSAIDs, Paracetamol, TCA) within the last week reported by the patient by a Yes or No answer.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse reactions</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed at 3, 6, 9 and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Assessed by asking the patient to report the occurence of any serious adverse reactions or adverse reactions during the last 3 months.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Depression (for patient description)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Depressive symptoms are assessed using the Patient Health Questionnaire-9 (PHQ-9). Nine items related to the core symptoms of depression are assessed on a 4-point Likert scale, ranging from 0 = 'not at all' to 3 = 'nearly every day', getting a score between 0 and 27 with a higher score indicating higher depression severity.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Anxiety (for patient description)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Anxiety symptoms are assessed with the Generalized Anxiety Disorder-7 (GAD-7) questionnaire. Seven items are assessed on a 4-point Likert scale, ranging from 0 = 'not at all' to 3 = 'nearly every day', getting a score between 0 and 21 with a higher score indicating higher anxiety severity.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Kinesiophobia (for patient description)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Kinesiophobia is assessed using the 17-item Tampa Scale of Kinesiophobia (TSK) questionnaire. Each of the 17 items is rated on a 4-point Likert scale with 1 = 'strongly disagree' and 4 = 'strongly agree', getting a score between 17 and 68 with a higher score indicating higher levels of fear of movement/kinesiophobia</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Pain distribution (for patient description)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Self-reported drawing on body chart</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">150</enrollment>
  <condition>Chronic Low-back Pain</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cognitive Functional Therapy+</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The CFT+ intervention includes treatment performed by a CFT trained physiotherapists and a psychologist in the Pain Center. Each patient receives a maximum of 10 consultations over a period of 3 months. The first two sessions is combined with the physiotherapist and psychologist who investigates potential maintaining factors for pain and disability in the patient's everyday life. Remaining sessions are primarily run by the physiotherapist, and the treatment is individually tailored to the needs of the individual patient, aiming to provide the patient with skills in dealing with his / her own situation via information, reflection, change of movement and training of functions and physical level. The psychologist provide extra support for 2-3 sessions focusing on coping strategies to reinforce the physiotherapist work.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Interdisciplinary pain management</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Treatment at the Interdisciplinary University Pain Center are based on elements from cognitive-behavioral therapy, Acceptance and Commitment Therapy, and Mindfulness-Based Stress Reduction programs.
Treatment can be diverse, but based on an individual assessment it consists of a combination of (1) medical treatment with a specialist pain consultant+specialist pain nurse (ie, individual adjustment of analgesics to improve effect and reduce side effects) AND (2) one or more of the following: individual consultations with a specialist pain psychologist, physiotherapist or social worker with cognitive-behavioral therapy training as well as participation in a group program with relaxation therapy, acceptance and commitment therapy or standardized mindfulness-based stress reduction programs. On average patients in the pain center receives 9-10 sessions.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cognitive Functional Therapy+</intervention_name>
    <description>The CFT+ intervention comprises 4 main components: (1) making sense of pain: context-based patient education focusing on the multidimensional nature of pain and disability, while reducing the threat of structural damage and correcting unhelpful beliefs; (2) exposure with control: graded exposure to painful, feared, or avoided activities with body relaxation; (3) lifestyle changes: encouraged to perform physical activity based on preference and taught strategies to manage stress and poor sleep, (4) focus on coping strategies in life and how these strategies influence the current situation.
Following the 3 months of CFT, cross-over to the active comparator is possible if one or more of the following is present: 1) Analgesic treatment is inappropriate, 2) Social situation is problematic and requires attention by social worker, 3) Significantly psychological distress that requires further treatment by psychologist. This decision is based on a multidisciplinary team conference.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cognitive Functional Therapy+</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Interdisciplinary pain management</intervention_name>
    <description>Treatment at the Interdisciplinary University Pain Center are based on elements from cognitive-behavioral therapy, Acceptance and Commitment Therapy, and Mindfulness-Based Stress Reduction programs.
Individualized combination of (1) medical treatment with a specialist pain consultant+specialist pain nurse (ie, individual adjustment of analgesics to improve effect and reduce side effects), (2) one or more of the following: individual consultations with a specialist pain psychologist, physiotherapist or social worker with cognitive-behavioral therapy training as well as participation in a group program with relaxation therapy, acceptance and commitment therapy or standardized mindfulness-based stress reduction programs.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Interdisciplinary pain management</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Referred to interdisciplinary pain management at the Pain Center at the University
             Hospital Odense, Denmark

          -  Understands and writes Danish

          -  Low back pain lasting more than 6 months

          -  Low back pain reported as primary pain complaint

          -  Low back pain reported as significant contributor to daily disability

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Wheel chair bound

          -  Psychotic diseases

          -  Inflammatory rheumatic diseases

          -  Previously attended a interdisciplinary pain management program

          -  Suicide ideation - evaluated using Patient Health Questionnaire-9 (Item 9 has to be
             answered &quot;never&quot;)

          -  Self-reported pregnancy

          -  Self-reported former/ present addictive behavior
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Henrik B Vægter, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Odense University Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Henrik B Vægter, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>004560616864</phone>
    <email>hbv@rsyd.dk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Jonas B Thorlund, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>004529125499</phone>
    <email>jthorlund@health.sdu.dk</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Pain Center, University Hospital Odense</name>
      <address>
        <city>Odense</city>
        <state>Funen</state>
        <zip>5000</zip>
        <country>Denmark</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Henrik B Vægter, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>004560616864</phone>
      <email>hbv@rsyd.dk</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Gitte Handberg, MD</last_name>
      <phone>004565413869</phone>
      <email>gitte.handberg@rsyd.dk</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Henrik B Vægter, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Denmark</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://journals.lww.com/painrpts/pages/articleviewer.aspx?year=2020&amp;issue=02000&amp;article=00004&amp;type=Fulltext</url>
    <description>CFT pilot study in the Pain Center</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>May 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 19, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 19, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 22, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 24, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 24, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 27, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Odense University Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Henrik Bjarke Vægter</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor in Physiotherapy</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Low back pain</keyword>
  <keyword>Cognitive Functional Therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Interdisciplinary pain management</keyword>
  <keyword>RCT</keyword>
  <keyword>Disability</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Back Pain</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Low Back Pain</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

