<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04398082</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>TRANQUiL</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04398082</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>TRANslating Sleep Health Into QUaLity of Recovery (TRANQUiL) Study</brief_title>
  <acronym>TRANQUiL</acronym>
  <official_title>TRANslating Sleep Health Into QUaLity of Recovery (TRANQUiL) Study: A Multi-center Prospective Cohort Study of Sleep Health and Activity Measures Predicting Meaningful and Patient-centric Outcomes Following Non-cardiac Surgeries.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Women's College Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University Health Network, Toronto</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Women's College Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a novel observational study to evaluate the association between poor sleep health and
      poor quality of recovery in the surgical setting.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Surgery and pain may cause sleep disturbances that affect both physical and mental
      well-being. Sleep disturbance can cause increased risk of confusion after surgery, increased
      pain need medication and untoward events (heart and breathing problems), delayed recovery and
      increased length of hospital stay. Hospitalization interferes with sleep patterns which may
      cause poor quality sleep due to noise, light, pain, medication administration and nursing
      checks. The circadian rhythm which meant the &quot;body clock&quot; is 24-hour cycle that tells bodies
      when to sleep, rise-regulating many physiological processes. But sleep disruption can affect
      the body clock, which changes the hormonal level can cause poor wound healing. There are few
      sleep health measurements such as sleep quality, sleep timing, and sleep efficiency. This
      study is aimed to evaluate sleep problems before sleep disruption immediately after surgery
      and also evaluate the relation between poor sleep health and quality of recovery

      Objectives of the study:

        1. To examine the associations between specific preoperative sleep-health parameters
           predicting poor sleep health and patient-centered outcomes such as pain control,
           delirium, sleep-related quality of life and quality of recovery scores in the
           perioperative period.

        2. To estimate the association between presence of intrinsic sleep disorders and patient
           centric outcomes such as pain control, delirium, sleep-related quality of life and
           quality of recovery scores in the postoperative period.

        3. To validate a set of subjective and objective measures that measure various sleep health
           domains in the post-operative setting.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">June 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 31, 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 28, 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of recovery-15 score at 48 hrs postoperatively</measure>
    <time_frame>48 hours postoperatively</time_frame>
    <description>QoR-15 Score is a validated patient-reported outcome questionnaire that measures the quality of recovery after surgery and anesthesia. Aggregate changes in QoR-15 scores (e.g., mean and SD) will be reported.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The diagnostic accuracy of each of the actigraphy derived measures</measure>
    <time_frame>48 hours postoperatively</time_frame>
    <description>The diagnostic accuracy of each of the actigraphy derived measures with reference to the standard test will be calculated using the Receiver Operating Characteristic (ROC) curve, Sensitivity, Specificity, Positive predictive value (PPV), Negative predictive value (NPV), Positive Likelihood ratio, Negative Likelihood ratios, and Diagnostic Odds Ratio (DOR).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index (PSQI) Scores</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months postoperatively</time_frame>
    <description>The Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index (PSQI) is a standardized sleep questionnaire for multiple populations. It has seven component scores and a composite score to assess sleep health and daytime dysfunction in the past month.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Consensus Sleep Diary (CSD) Scores</measure>
    <time_frame>7 days prior surgery, 7 days, and 3 months postoperatively</time_frame>
    <description>The Consensus Sleep Diary (CSD) is a standardized, prospective tool for tracking nightly subjective sleep.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Functional Outcomes in Sleep Questionnaire (FOSQ)</measure>
    <time_frame>7 days prior surgery and 3 months postoperatively</time_frame>
    <description>The short-form FOSQ-10 scale has good psychometric properties with increased usability. It is a disease-specific instrument designed to assess the sleep-related quality of life measures.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale (HADS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 3 months postoperatively</time_frame>
    <description>The HADS is a very brief, easy to use screening measure comprising of 14 items measuring cognitive and emotional aspects of anxiety and depression. It has good psychometric properties for medical patients.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Fluid Intake and Output</measure>
    <time_frame>48 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Postoperative assessment of the fluid intake and output.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Visual analogue pain scores (VAS)</measure>
    <time_frame>48 hours</time_frame>
    <description>The VAS is a simple way for patients to rate the intensity of their pain. This pain scale shows a 10-centimeter line printed on a piece of paper, with anchors at either end and marked from 0-10. At one end is &quot;no pain,&quot; and at the other end are &quot;pain as bad as it could be&quot; or &quot;the worst imaginable pain.&quot;</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Postoperative complications</measure>
    <time_frame>48 hours and 30 days</time_frame>
    <description>Assessment of the severity of the postoperative complications</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Western Ontario and McMaster Universities Osteoarthritis Index (WOMAC) score</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 3 months postoperatively</time_frame>
    <description>The WOMAC questionnaire assesses the three dimensions of pain, disability and joint stiffness in knee and hip osteoarthritis using a battery of 24 questions in 5-point Likert, 100mm Visual Analogue and 11-box Numerical Rating Scale formats. It is a valid, reliable and responsive measure of outcome, and has been used in diverse clinical and interventional environments.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Epworth Sleepiness Scale (ESS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 3 months postoperatively</time_frame>
    <description>The ESS is self-administered where the subjects are asked to rate on 0-3 scales how likely they would be to doze off or fall asleep in the eight situations. A summary score is generated where total score of &gt;10 indicates excessive daytime sleepiness.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">260</enrollment>
  <condition>Poor Quality Sleep</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        260 patients will be recruited from the preoperative clinics at major academic centers:
        Women's College Hospital (WCH) (coordinating center), Toronto Western Hospital (TWH),
        University Health Network (UHN); and St. Michaels Hospital (SMH), Toronto, Ontario.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Adult patients (&gt;18 years).

          2. ASA physical status I - IV.

          3. Undergoing elective primary or revision lower limb joint replacement surgeries (such
             as total or partial hip or knee replacement).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients undergoing emergency surgeries; cardiac, trauma, organ transplantation or
             organ retrieval, obstetric or intracranial neurosurgeries.

          2. Pregnant or lactating patients.

          3. Inability to wear study-related monitoring devices per instruction or provide informed
             consent limiting adherence to protocol.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mandeep Singh, MD, MSc</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Women's College Hospital and Toronto Western Hospital, University Health Network</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Vivek Kumar</last_name>
    <phone>416-323-6400</phone>
    <phone_ext>2532</phone_ext>
    <email>Vivek.Kumar@wchospital.ca</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>MaryJane Salpeter</last_name>
    <email>MaryJane.Salpeter@wchospital.ca</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Women's College Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toronto</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>M5S 1B2</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Vivek Kumar</last_name>
      <phone>416-323-6400</phone>
      <phone_ext>2532</phone_ext>
      <email>Vivek.Kumar@wchospital.ca</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>MaryJane Salpeter</last_name>
      <email>MaryJane.Sapleter@wchospital.ca</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Mandeep Singh, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Richard Brull, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 24, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 20, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 21, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 20, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 20, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 21, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

