<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04397809</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>14BGF-10</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04397809</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Utility of CD64 and TLR2 Assays to Diagnose Acute Pulmonary Exacerbations in Cystic Fibrosis</brief_title>
  <official_title>Utility of CD64 and TLR2 Assays to Diagnose Acute Pulmonary Exacerbations in Cystic Fibrosis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Jewish Health</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Jewish Health</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Cystic fibrosis (CF) is the most common inherited disease in the western world. On a yearly
      basis, 56% of CF patients, or nearly 17,000 individuals in the US, suffer from acute
      pulmonary exacerbations (APE). The purpose of this study is to test a candidate assay for its
      ability to diagnose APE, the most important disease event in CF. While previous studies have
      been able to identify biomarkers of CF prognosis and risk stratification, three markers have
      demonstrated characteristics ideal for APE diagnosis: CD64, TLR2, and GILT. CD64 is a
      cellular receptor, expressed on numerous cells of the immune system, whose role is to bind
      antibodies which are attached to infected cells or pathogens. TLR2 plays a major role in
      early host-microbial interactions. GILT has been shown to be more precise in targeting immune
      responses against antigens and influences T lymphocyte response. This study looks to identify
      the differences in the expression of neutrophil CD64 and CD4+ T cell TLR2 and GILT between
      acute illness and baseline health as a sensitive marker of acute pulmonary exacerbation so
      that it may facilitate rapid hematologic diagnosis of the condition. The study also looks to
      compare sensitivity and specificity of the assays above to standard measures, such as health
      related quality of life scores (CFQ-R), loss of lung function, white blood cell counts and
      CRP, for diagnosing acute exacerbations.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 10, 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 23, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference in neutrophil CD64 expression</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 24 hours of initiation of IV antibiotic treatment for CF pulmonary exacerbation or at Baseline health</time_frame>
    <description>The primary outcome measure is the difference in expression of neutrophil CD64 as measured by flow cytometry from circulating blood between the two groups (APE and baseline).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference in CD4+ T cell TLR2 expression</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 24 hours of initiation of IV antibiotic treatment for CF pulmonary exacerbation or at Baseline health</time_frame>
    <description>The primary outcome measure is the difference in expression of CD4+ T cell TLR2 as measured by flow cytometry from circulating blood between the two groups (APE and baseline).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference in GILT expression</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 24 hours of initiation of IV antibiotic treatment for CF pulmonary exacerbation or at Baseline health</time_frame>
    <description>The primary outcome measure is the difference in expression of GILT as measured by flow cytometry from circulating blood between the two groups (APE and baseline).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Correlation of primary outcome measurements with lung function tests</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 24 hours of initiation of IV antibiotic treatment for CF pulmonary exacerbation or at Baseline health</time_frame>
    <description>A secondary outcome measure is the correlation of the differences in expression of neutrophil CD64, CD4+ T cell TLR2, and GILT with changes in FEV1 as measured by spirometry.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Correlation of primary outcome measurements with C-Reactive Protein</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 24 hours of initiation of IV antibiotic treatment for CF pulmonary exacerbation or at Baseline health</time_frame>
    <description>A secondary outcome measure is the correlation of the differences in expression of neutrophil CD64, CD4+ T cell TLR2, and GILT with differences in C-Reactive Protein (CRP)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Correlation of primary outcome measurements with total white blood cell counts</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 24 hours of initiation of IV antibiotic treatment for CF pulmonary exacerbation or at Baseline health</time_frame>
    <description>A secondary outcome measure is the correlation of the differences in expression of neutrophil CD64, CD4+ T cell TLR2, and GILT with differences in total white blood cell counts (WBC).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Correlation of primary outcome measurements with sputum inflammatory markers</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 24 hours of initiation of IV antibiotic treatment for CF pulmonary exacerbation or at Baseline health</time_frame>
    <description>A secondary outcome measure is the correlation of the differences in expression of neutrophil CD64, CD4+ T cell TLR2, and GILT with differences in sputum inflammatory markers as measured by sputum neutrophil counts and neutrophil elastase expression.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Correlation of primary outcome measurements with phagocytosis</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 24 hours of initiation of IV antibiotic treatment for CF pulmonary exacerbation or at Baseline health</time_frame>
    <description>A secondary outcome measure is the correlation of the differences in expression of neutrophil CD64, CD4+ T cell TLR2, and GILT with differences in the percentage of phagocytosis by isolated neutrophils.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Correlation of primary outcome measurements with quality of life questionnaire score</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 24 hours of initiation of IV antibiotic treatment for CF pulmonary exacerbation or at Baseline health</time_frame>
    <description>A secondary outcome measure is the correlation of the differences in expression of neutrophil CD64, CD4+ T cell TLR2, and GILT with differences in patient reported health related quality of life scores as measured by the Cystic Fibrosis Questionnaire-Revised (CFQ-R).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">150</enrollment>
  <condition>Cystic Fibrosis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Acute Pulmonary Exacerbation (APE)</arm_group_label>
    <description>Those subjects presenting with APE will be treated with at least two pathogen specific I.V. antibiotics, as dictated by their treating physician and compliant with standard guidelines for care of an APE.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Baseline Health</arm_group_label>
    <description>Those subjects presenting at baseline health will be identified by their treating physician as such and will not be starting on any treatments for APE.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        CF patients aged 18 years or older at the time of an acute pulmonary exacerbation or at
        baseline health who are followed by the Adult CF Program at National Jewish Health will be
        eligible to enroll in this study.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Documented diagnosis of CF.

          -  Age 18 years old or greater.

          -  Presentation at baseline health OR at the start of treatment for a pulmonary
             exacerbation of CF.

          -  Ability to perform reproducible Pulmonary Function Tests

          -  Ability to produce sputum.

          -  Willingness to complete a health-related quality of life questionnaire

          -  Willingness to comply with study procedure and provide written consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

        • Presence of a condition or abnormality that, in the opinion of the Principal Investigator
        (PI), would compromise the safety of the patient or the quality of the data.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Jewish Health</name>
      <address>
        <city>Denver</city>
        <state>Colorado</state>
        <zip>80206</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 18, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 18, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 21, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 18, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 18, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 21, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cystic Fibrosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fibrosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

