<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04396028</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>OSMAMI-04/05/2020-0015998-U</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04396028</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Measurement of Lung Area at Chest Radiography Could Help to Define the Prognosis in Newborns With Congenital Diaphragmatic Hernia</brief_title>
  <acronym>NeoAPACHE</acronym>
  <official_title>Assessment of the Pulmonary Area in Newborn With Congenital Diaphragmatic Hernia: a Retrospective Analysis of Respiratory Function, Risk of Recurrence and Mortality</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Fondazione IRCCS Ca' Granda, Ospedale Maggiore Policlinico</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Fondazione IRCCS Ca' Granda, Ospedale Maggiore Policlinico</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Congenital Diaphragmatic Hernia (CDH) represents a rare and severe malformative disorder
      characterized by an incomplete diaphragm formation, which allows abdominal organs to pass
      into the thoracic cavity and alter normal lung formation during fetal life. This results in
      poor lung development (pulmonary hypoplasia), associated with altered vascularization of the
      lung (pulmonary hypertension), determining respiratory and cardiovascular insufficiency at
      birth. CDH shows high mortality and significant morbidity so that its prognostic evaluation
      remains challenging.

      The measurement of lung area at chest radiography is considered an alternative method to
      assess lung development in the newborn. A correlation between lung area and functional
      residual capacity (FRC) was demonstrated in newborns with CDH. Severe forms of CDH,
      characterized by a high degree of pulmonary hypoplasia and poor prognosis, present with lower
      lung area at birth, predicting survival to discharge from the neonatal intensive care unit.

      However, the relationship between lung area and other aspects of respiratory function has
      never been investigated. Since CDH compromises lung development as a whole, it is likely to
      assume that lung area at birth may have an impact on patient's performance at pulmonary
      function tests during follow-up. In particular, as lung area increased, a trend towards
      normalization in respiratory function would be expected.

      Moreover, the role of the radiographic area at birth as a possible predictor of death should
      be further characterized, aiming to clarify the complex association between lung area and
      mortality, which is strongly influenced by both pulmonary hypoplasia and pulmonary
      hypertension.

      Finally, provided that poor lung development comes with low lung area at birth, the
      investigators suppose that lung area could indirectly reflect defect size and be therefore
      associated with the risk of hernia recurrence.

      The principal aim of this study is to determine if changes in the radiographic pulmonary area
      measured on the first day of life are related to patients' pulmonary function at one year of
      life, considering two main respiratory parameters: tidal volume (VT) and respiratory rate
      (RR).

      Secondary objectives are the analysis of the association between radiographic pulmonary area
      and: 1) risk of death during the first year of life; 2) risk of hernia recurrence during the
      first year of life.

      The investigators will retrospectively consider a cohort of newborns with CDH. For each
      patient, the investigators will measure lung area at chest radiography performed
      preoperatively within 24 hours after birth and will collect data regarding demographics,
      clinical course, and follow-up.

      Through our study, the investigators aim to improve the current understanding of the role of
      radiographic lung area in characterizing lung development and prognosis in CDH patients, with
      a more comprehensive view on survival chances, recurrence risk, and lung function impairment
      during the first year of life. The investigators believe that this could become a low-cost
      and straightforward tool that will assist the clinician in making decisions regarding the
      patient's management and follow up.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The study period considered will be January 2012 - December 2018. From the medical record of
      each patient, the investigators will collect the following data: prenatal history, hernia
      severity, fetal endoscopic tracheal occlusion (FETO) procedure, demographics, respiratory
      insufficiency, and mechanical ventilation, cardiocirculatory insufficiency and
      pharmacological hemodynamic support, pulmonary hypertension and need for pulmonary
      vasodilators, need for extracorporeal life support (ECMO), comorbidities, timing of surgical
      repair, use of prosthetic patch, intra- and post-operative complications, clinical and
      instrumental follow-up, pulmonary function tests, recurrence, death. The confidentiality of
      all data will be maintained.

      Regarding the assessment of the radiographic pulmonary area, two operators (a neonatologist
      and a pediatric radiologist) will independently review all preoperative digital radiograms
      performed within 24 hours of life. For each patient, the radiogram showing the best
      lung-recruitment will be selected. Lung area will be assessed by freehand tracing of the
      perimeter of the thoracic area, as outlined by the diaphragm and the rib cage, excluding the
      mediastinal structures and abdominal contents herniated in the thorax. The only aerated
      portion of the lungs will be considered. The corresponding area will be automatically
      calculated by the software. Three measures will be performed: 1) ipsilateral lung area (cm2);
      2) contralateral lung area (cm2); 3) total lung area (cm2), derived from the sum of the
      preceding two. The agreement between lung measurements performed by the two operators will be
      evaluated to verify the reproducibility of the method.

      Pulmonary function test performed during spontaneous sleeping at the age of 1 year will be
      reviewed. The measurements of VT and RR will be recorded. The predicted value of VT and RR
      will be obtained, and their Z-Score will be calculated using reference equations of a
      population of healthy children. Z-Score is a numerical measure used to express how much an
      observed value deviates from the mean expected normal value in terms of standard deviation.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">May 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Retrospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Association between radiographic pulmonary area and respiratory function</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>To evaluate the association between changes in radiographic pulmonary area at birth and trend in VT and RR measured at pulmonary function tests performed during follow-up at the age of 1 year. The association will be studied through linear regression models.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Association between radiographic pulmonary area and mortality</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>To evaluate the association between changes in radiographic pulmonary area and the risk of death during the first year of life, following logistic regression models.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Association between radiographic pulmonary area and hernia recurrence</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>To evaluate the association between changes in radiographic pulmonary area and the risk of hernia recurrence during the first year of life, following logistic regression models.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">85</enrollment>
  <condition>Congenital Diaphragmatic Hernia</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>data collection</intervention_name>
    <description>retrospective data collection</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Infants with CDH born between January 2012 and December 2018, hospitalized at birth or
        within 24 hours of life at the Neonatal Intensive Care Unit of Fondazione IRCCS Ca' Granda
        Ospedale Maggiore Policlinico, Milan, Italy, and followed-up longitudinally during the
        first year of life.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Inborn and outborn patients admitted to the NICU within 24 hours after birth.

          -  Prenatal or postnatal (within 24 hours after birth) diagnosis of CDH.

          -  Preoperative chest radiograph performed for clinical purposes within 24 hours after
             birth in our NICU.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Diagnosis of CDH made beyond 24 hours after birth

          -  Admission to the NICU beyond 24 hours after birth

          -  Preoperative chest radiograph performed beyond 24 hours after birth,
             rotated/asymmetric, with air leak (pneumothorax, pneumoperitoneum), not performed in
             our NICU or not accessible

          -  Early death (within 1 hour after birth)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>24 Hours</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Giacomo Cavallaro, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Neonatal Intensive Care Unit, Fondazione IRCCS Ca' Granda, Ospedale Maggiore Policlinico, Milano</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Giacomo Cavallaro, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+390255032234</phone>
    <email>giacomo.cavallaro@policlinico.mi.it</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <reference>
    <citation>Deprest J, Brady P, Nicolaides K, Benachi A, Berg C, Vermeesch J, Gardener G, Gratacos E. Prenatal management of the fetus with isolated congenital diaphragmatic hernia in the era of the TOTAL trial. Semin Fetal Neonatal Med. 2014 Dec;19(6):338-48. doi: 10.1016/j.siny.2014.09.006. Epub 2014 Nov 11. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25447987</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Snoek KG, Greenough A, van Rosmalen J, Capolupo I, Schaible T, Ali K, Wijnen RM, Tibboel D. Congenital Diaphragmatic Hernia: 10-Year Evaluation of Survival, Extracorporeal Membrane Oxygenation, and Foetoscopic Endotracheal Occlusion in Four High-Volume Centres. Neonatology. 2018;113(1):63-68. doi: 10.1159/000480451. Epub 2017 Oct 28.</citation>
    <PMID>29080897</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Coughlin MA, Werner NL, Gajarski R, Gadepalli S, Hirschl R, Barks J, Treadwell MC, Ladino-Torres M, Kreutzman J, Mychaliska GB. Prenatally diagnosed severe CDH: mortality and morbidity remain high. J Pediatr Surg. 2016 Jul;51(7):1091-5. doi: 10.1016/j.jpedsurg.2015.10.082. Epub 2015 Nov 10.</citation>
    <PMID>26655216</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bagolan P, Morini F. Long-term follow up of infants with congenital diaphragmatic hernia. Semin Pediatr Surg. 2007 May;16(2):134-44. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>17462566</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>American Academy of Pediatrics Section on Surgery; American Academy of Pediatrics Committee on Fetus and Newborn, Lally KP, Engle W. Postdischarge follow-up of infants with congenital diaphragmatic hernia. Pediatrics. 2008 Mar;121(3):627-32. doi: 10.1542/peds.2007-3282. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18310215</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rocha G, Azevedo I, Pinto JC, Guimarães H. Follow-up of the survivors of congenital diaphragmatic hernia. Early Hum Dev. 2012 Apr;88(4):255-8. doi: 10.1016/j.earlhumdev.2011.08.025. Epub 2011 Sep 23.</citation>
    <PMID>21945360</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chen C, Jeruss S, Chapman JS, Terrin N, Tighiouart H, Glassman E, Wilson JM, Parsons SK. Long-term functional impact of congenital diaphragmatic hernia repair on children. J Pediatr Surg. 2007 Apr;42(4):657-65.</citation>
    <PMID>17448762</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jancelewicz T, Chiang M, Oliveira C, Chiu PP. Late surgical outcomes among congenital diaphragmatic hernia (CDH) patients: why long-term follow-up with surgeons is recommended. J Pediatr Surg. 2013 May;48(5):935-41. doi: 10.1016/j.jpedsurg.2013.02.005.</citation>
    <PMID>23701763</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dimitriou G, Greenough A, Kavvadia V, Shute M, Karani J. A radiographic method for assessing lung area in neonates. Br J Radiol. 1999 Apr;72(856):335-8.</citation>
    <PMID>10474492</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>May C, Prendergast M, Salman S, Rafferty GF, Greenough A. Chest radiograph thoracic areas and lung volumes in infants developing bronchopulmonary dysplasia. Pediatr Pulmonol. 2009 Jan;44(1):80-5. doi: 10.1002/ppul.20952.</citation>
    <PMID>19085927</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dassios T, Curley A, Krokidis M, Morley C, Ross-Russell R. Correlation of radiographic thoracic area and oxygenation impairment in bronchopulmonary dysplasia. Respir Physiol Neurobiol. 2016 Jan;220:40-5. doi: 10.1016/j.resp.2015.09.009. Epub 2015 Sep 26.</citation>
    <PMID>26410458</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dimitriou G, Greenough A, Davenport M, Nicolaides K. Prediction of outcome by computer-assisted analysis of lung area on the chest radiograph of infants with congenital diaphragmatic hernia. J Pediatr Surg. 2000 Mar;35(3):489-93.</citation>
    <PMID>10726694</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dassios T, Ali K, Makin E, Bhat R, Krokidis M, Greenough A. Prediction of Mortality in Newborn Infants With Severe Congenital Diaphragmatic Hernia Using the Chest Radiographic Thoracic Area. Pediatr Crit Care Med. 2019 Jun;20(6):534-539. doi: 10.1097/PCC.0000000000001912.</citation>
    <PMID>30925570</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Putnam LR, Gupta V, Tsao K, Davis CF, Lally PA, Lally KP, Harting MT; Congenital Diaphragmatic Hernia Study Group. Factors associated with early recurrence after congenital diaphragmatic hernia repair. J Pediatr Surg. 2017 Jun;52(6):928-932. doi: 10.1016/j.jpedsurg.2017.03.011. Epub 2017 Mar 16.</citation>
    <PMID>28359590</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Al-Iede MM, Karpelowsky J, Fitzgerald DA. Recurrent diaphragmatic hernia: Modifiable and non-modifiable risk factors. Pediatr Pulmonol. 2016 Apr;51(4):394-401. doi: 10.1002/ppul.23305. Epub 2015 Sep 7.</citation>
    <PMID>26346806</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nguyen TT, Hoo AF, Lum S, Wade A, Thia LP, Stocks J. New reference equations to improve interpretation of infant lung function. Pediatr Pulmonol. 2013 Apr;48(4):370-80. doi: 10.1002/ppul.22656. Epub 2012 Sep 4.</citation>
    <PMID>22949414</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Van der Veeken L, Russo FM, De Catte L, Gratacos E, Benachi A, Ville Y, Nicolaides K, Berg C, Gardener G, Persico N, Bagolan P, Ryan G, Belfort MA, Deprest J. Fetoscopic endoluminal tracheal occlusion and reestablishment of fetal airways for congenital diaphragmatic hernia. Gynecol Surg. 2018;15(1):9. doi: 10.1186/s10397-018-1041-9. Epub 2018 May 8.</citation>
    <PMID>29770109</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Snoek KG, Reiss IK, Greenough A, Capolupo I, Urlesberger B, Wessel L, Storme L, Deprest J, Schaible T, van Heijst A, Tibboel D; CDH EURO Consortium. Standardized Postnatal Management of Infants with Congenital Diaphragmatic Hernia in Europe: The CDH EURO Consortium Consensus - 2015 Update. Neonatology. 2016;110(1):66-74. doi: 10.1159/000444210. Epub 2016 Apr 15.</citation>
    <PMID>27077664</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hollinger LE, Buchmiller TL. Long term follow-up in congenital diaphragmatic hernia. Semin Perinatol. 2020 Feb;44(1):151171. doi: 10.1053/j.semperi.2019.07.010. Epub 2019 Jul 31. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>31451197</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 15, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 19, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 20, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 19, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 19, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 21, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Fondazione IRCCS Ca' Granda, Ospedale Maggiore Policlinico</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Giacomo Cavallaro</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>congenital diaphragmatic hernia</keyword>
  <keyword>radiographic pulmonary area</keyword>
  <keyword>lung hypoplasia</keyword>
  <keyword>respiratory function</keyword>
  <keyword>mortality</keyword>
  <keyword>recurrence</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hernias, Diaphragmatic, Congenital</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hernia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hernia, Diaphragmatic</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

