<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03615313</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>SHSY-IEC-4.0/18-09/02</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03615313</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>PD-1 Antibody Expressing mesoCAR-T Cells for Mesothelin Positive Advanced Solid Tumor</brief_title>
  <acronym>PAEMCMPAST</acronym>
  <official_title>A Clinical Study of PD-1 Antibody Expressing mesoCAR-T Cells for Patients With Mesothelin Positive Advanced Solid Tumors</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Shanghai Cell Therapy Research Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Shanghai Cell Therapy Research Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a single-arm, open-label, one center clinical study, to determine the safety and
      efficacy of infusion of autologous T cells engineered to target mesothelin and express PD-1
      antibodies in adult patients with advanced recurrent or refractory malignant solid tumors,
      which were positive expression of mesothelin.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study will be conducted using a phase I/II trial design to assess the safety and
      efficacy of the PD-1 antibody expressing mesoCAR-T for patients with mesothelin positive,
      advanced recurrent or refractory malignant solid tumors. MesoCAR-T can specifically and
      effectively kill the mesothelin positive cancer cells, PD-1 antibody are secreted from the
      CAR-T cells could improve immunosuppression microenvironment, new CAR-T cells contain the
      advantages of CAR-T and immune checkpoint inhibitor, which is a promising therapeutic method
      for advanced solid tumors.

      The new CAR-T therapy is applied to clinical practice as bellow. T cells are prepared from
      peripheral blood mononuclear cells (PBMC) by leukapheresis, and then activated and engineered
      to express chimeric antigen receptors (CARs) targeting mesothelin and PD-1 antibody. Cells
      are proliferated in culture and returned to the patients by venous transfusion therapy. A
      total of 50 patients may be enrolled in the study. The total duration of the study is
      expected to be approximately 24 months.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">August 6, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 3, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 3, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of treatment-related adverse events of infusion of autologous PD-1 antibody expressing mesothelin-targeted CAR-Tcells</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Incidence of treatment-related adverse events are assessed using the NCI CTCAE V4.0 criteria.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Objective response rate (ORR) of the treatment using PD-1 antibody expressing mesoCAR-T cells for advanced solid tumors</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Objective response rate (ORR) of the treatment is assessed according to the response evaluation criteria in solid tumor version 1.1 (RECIST1.1), which contains complete response (CR) and partial response (PR).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression free survival</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Progression free survival is defined as the time from the day in which the patient is enrolled to the date on which tumor progresses or the date on which the patient dies for any cause.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Overall survival is defined as the time from the day in which the patient is enrolled to the date on which the patient dies for any cause.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Proliferation and persistence of mesothelin specific CAR-T cells in peripheral blood of the patients</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>CAR-T proportionin in peripheral blood of the patients is detected by flow cytometry assay to study the proliferation and persistence of mesothelin specific CAR-T cells.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>PD-1 antibody level in peripheral blood of the patients after treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>PD-1 antibody level are detected by ELISA assay to assess the expressing level of PD-1 antibody from CAR-T cells.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Advanced Solid Tumor</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>PD-1 antibody expressing mesoCAR-T cells</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients will receive two cycles of PD-1 antibody expressing mesoCAR-T cells treatment. Every cycle, peripheral blood mononuclear cells (PBMC) are collected on day -18, CAR-T cells are cultured in a GMP standard workshop. Patients are given a three-day regimen of chemotherapy consisting of fludarabine and cyclophosphamide aimed to deplete the lymphocytes before cells infusion. Then the patients will receive an i.v.gtt infusion of PD-1 antibody expressing mesoCAR-T cells from day 1 to day 3 (±3days).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>PD-1 antibody expressing mesoCAR-T cells</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients with mesothelin positive cancer will be infused the PD-1 antibody expressing mesoCAR-T cells. The modified mesoCAR-T cells can specifically kill mesothelin positive cancer cells and secrete PD-1 antibody, which could enhance the cytotoxicity of mesoCAR-T cells and activate the tumor infiltrating lymphocytes.</description>
    <arm_group_label>PD-1 antibody expressing mesoCAR-T cells</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients with relapsed or refractory advanced solid malignancies (diagnosed by
             histology or cytology detection), including malignant mesothelioma, pancreatic cancer,
             bile duct cancer, ovarian cancer, lung cancer, gastric cancer, etc.

          2. Patients who failed after second-line treatment, or who are unwilling to receive
             second-line treatment after failed to recieve first-line treatment.

          3. Gender unlimited, age from 18 years to 80 years.

          4. Life expectancy ≥ 3 months.

          5. Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status of 0-1.

          6. Adequate venous access for Peripheral blood mononuclear cell (PBMC) apheresis, and no
             other contraindications.

          7. Immunohistochemistry (IHC) score of mesothelin on tumor tissue ≥ 1+.

          8. The requirements of laboratory examination: Neutrophilic granulocyte ≥ 1.0×10^9/L;
             Platelet ≥ 50×10^9/L; Hemoglobin ≥ 90g/L; total bilirubin ≤ 2 times the upper limit of
             the normal value; Alanine aminotransferase and Aspartate transaminase (ALT and AST) ≤
             2.5 times the upperlimit of the normal value (If there is liver metastasis, they
             should be ≤ 5 times the upperlimit of the normal value); Serum creatinine ≤ 1.5 times
             the upper limit of the normalvalue.

          9. There is at least one measurable tumor lesion; According to RECIST 1.1 standard, it is
             suitable to evaluate the therapeutic response and progress of tumor.

         10. Patients have adequate ability to understand, sign informed consents and take part in
             the clinical research voluntarily.

         11. Female patients in child bearing period must have evidence of negative pregnancy test
             or male patients, and they agree to take effective contraceptive measures until 30
             days after cells infusion.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients with active viral or bacterial infection, and have failed to be controlled by
             anti-infective treatment.

          2. Patients with seropositive response of Human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) and
             syphilis, or fail to control the hepatitis B virus or hepatitis C virus infection.

          3. Patients who are undergoing treatment of autoimmune or organ transplantation diseases,
             or patients who need long-term use of immunosuppressive drugs such as glucocorticoid.

          4. Patients with severe heart and lung dysfunction, high blood pressure and cannot be
             controlled with medicine, unstable coronary artery disease (uncontrolled arrhythmias,
             unstable angina pectoris), uncompensated congestive heart failure, myocardial
             infarction within six months.

          5. Patients with any other illness that the investigators consider it will may affect the
             patient's treatments, follow-up or assessment, including any uncontrolled clinically
             significant neurological or psychiatric disorders, immunoregulatory diseases,
             metabolic diseases, infectious diseases and so on.

          6. Received cancer treatment prior to enroll the group within the following time
             (including drug clinical trials):

        (1) The withdrawal time of chemotherapy before enrollment was shorter than the treatment
        cycle of chemotherapy.

        (2) The use of anti-tumor therapy within 4 weeks before the study or less than 5 times of
        the half-life period of the drugs (including radiation therapy, chemotherapy, small
        molecules and biological therapy or immunotherapy), the shortest period of time was as the
        criterion (but the shortest time should not be less than 21 days).

        7. Women patients in pregnancy period or suckling period.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Qijun Qian, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Shanghai Cell Therapy Research Institute</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Huajun Jin, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Shanghai Cell Therapy Research Institute</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Qing Xu, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Shanghai 10th People's Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Zhiwei Zhang, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Shanghai Cell Therapy Research Institute</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Yan Sun</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Shanghai Cell Therapy Research Institute</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Huimei Li, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Shanghai Cell Therapy Research Institute</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Juemin Fang, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Shanghai 10th People's Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Song Gao, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Shanghai 10th People's Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Xianling Guo</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Shanghai 10th People's Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Hui Wang</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Shanghai 10th People's Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Zhongzheng Zhu</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Shanghai 10th People's Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jianhua Chen</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Shanghai 10th People's Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Zhiwei Zhang, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>0086-021-59593168</phone>
    <phone_ext>8008</phone_ext>
    <email>zhangzw@shcell.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>China</name>
      <address>
        <city>Shanghai</city>
        <state>Shanghai</state>
        <zip>200072</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Xue Yang</last_name>
      <phone>0086-021-66301147</phone>
      <email>shsyiec@126.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Juemin Fang</last_name>
      <phone>0086-021-39590256</phone>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 28, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 30, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 3, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 30, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 30, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">August 3, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>mesothelin, PD-1, CAR T cells, solid tumor</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Antibodies</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

