<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03618771</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>B00116</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03618771</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Functional Comparison of Two TKR Designs</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Functional Outcomes and Stability of Total Knee Replacement Design Concepts</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Manchester University NHS Foundation Trust</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Medacta International SA</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Manchester University NHS Foundation Trust</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Total knee replacement (TKR) is an established treatment for knee osteoarthritis and leads to
      a satisfactory outcome in over 75% of patients. However, up to 25% of patients are not
      entirely satisfied with their TKR. Patient dissatisfaction has been associated with
      inadequate functional outcome, especially during negotiation of stairs and slopes. This
      phenomenon, known as mid-flexion instability, is believed to be caused by excessive
      anterior-posterior motion of the implant during activities of daily living. This is
      characterised as a perception that the replaced knee is unsteady during certain tasks.

      This study will compare the functional outcome of two implants that have been designed to
      provide patients with a functionally stable knee throughout its range of motion. The
      different design roles in preventing implant-related mid-flexion instability remain unknown.
      The functional outcome and stability of these implants will be tested non-invasively with 3D
      motion capture technology.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study will compare the functional outcome of two implants that have been designed to
      provide patients with a functionally stable knee throughout its range of motion. The
      different design roles in preventing implant-related mid-flexion instability remain unknown.

      The Medacta GMK-Sphere implant consists of a fully congruent medial compartment which allows
      freedom of movement in the lateral compartment. Both femoral and tibial components are also
      available in a range of 13 sizes, allowing the surgeon to find a 'best fit' for each patient.
      These design features are aimed to mimic the movement of a natural healthy knee, potentially
      preventing implant-related mid-flexion instability.

      The DePuy Synthes Attune implant design aims to provide patients with optimal functional
      outcome. The femoral component of this implant has a gradually reducing radius, and the
      tibial component an S-shaped post-cam mechanism. These features are designed to facilitate
      smooth movement and stability during flexion.

      The comparative functional outcomes and stability in gait, and other activities of daily
      living has not been established for the two different TKR design concepts. Functional
      assessments will be carried out on TKR patients pre- and post-operatively. These assessments
      will non-invasively quantify the knee's stability, range of motion, strength as well as
      walking kinematics using 3D motion capture technology. As mid-flexion instability is most
      notable during downhill walking, patients will be required to walk downhill on a treadmill as
      part of this study, to better investigate the phenomenon of mid-flexion knee instability.

      This study will not involve any invasive procedure in addition to the standard of care. As
      such, the research burden is minimal. The main ethical issue may be that patients will not be
      randomised into one of the two proposed groups.

      Patients will receive either the GMK-Sphere implant or the Attune implant according to their
      surgeon's usual practice. Surgeons who specialise in the GMK-Sphere implant will only implant
      the GMK-Sphere for this study, and surgeons who specialise in the Attune implant will only
      implant the Attune. This allows surgeons to undertake the prosthesis with which they are
      expert, and also limit potential surgical error in the case of surgeons having to randomise
      patients to different designs on the same list.

      Patients will be seen by the trial team on 3 separate occasions:

        1. Routine pre-admission clinic: Recruitment, collection of patient information and
           questionnaire data and completion of pre-operative physical tests (including gait
           analysis with 3D motion capture technology)

        2. Routine post-operation clinic: Six-weeks post-operative physical tests (including gait
           analysis with 3D motion capture technology) and questionnaire data

        3. Annual post-operation clinic: 1-year post-operative physical tests (including gait
           analysis with 3D motion capture technology) and questionnaire data

           Collection of baseline data during pre-admission clinic (standard care except physical
           tests):

             -  Descriptive: Patient demographics (sex, age, height, mass, BMI), diagnosis, pattern
                of OA, medical co-morbidity

             -  Questionnaire Data

                  -  Oxford Knee Score - A joint specific questionnaire which asks patients on the
                     level of pain and function they believe to have in their affected knee.

                  -  EQ5D - A questionnaire on patients' perception of their overall health. It
                     contains a visual analogue scale where patients have to choose on a scale of
                     0-100 how well they believe their general health to be.

                  -  SF12 - A general Quality of Life score. It has mental and physical components.

                  -  Forgotten Joint Score - This asks questions not covered in the OKS on patient
                     perception of their knee that are important to know following TKA. It focuses
                     on other aspects of outcome other than joint pain and function.

                  -  Expectation questionnaire - This asks what the patients expect from the
                     surgery. The investigators use this to gauge whether patients are expecting to
                     achieve too much or too little post-op. This is important for understanding
                     post-operative patient satisfaction.

           All questionnaires ask different questions (although there is some overlap). Together,
           they give an overall view of the patients' perception of their general health and knee
           specific problems. As such, they are all deemed necessary for this investigation.

           There are separate scoring sheets for these subjective quantitative scores. The results
           are typically presented as a Mean ± SD score for each questionnaire (provided the data
           is normally distributed). All are valid in the English language.

           • Non-invasive Physical Tests: Range of knee movement, knee muscular strength, lower
           limb kinematics during level (0°)- and downhill (7.5°)-walking

           Collection of follow-up measures by trial team between operation and post-operative
           visit (standard care):

           • Surgical complications

           Collection of data during routine follow-up clinics:

      6 weeks post-operation (standard care except physical tests):

        -  Questionnaire Data: Oxford Knee Score, SF12, EQ5D, Forgotten Joint Score

        -  Non-invasive Physical Tests: Range of knee movement, knee muscular strength, lower limb
           kinematics during level (0°)- and downhill (7.5°)-walking

           12 weeks post-operation (standard care):

        -  Descriptive: Radiographic measurement of alignment (Non-invasive)

           1 year post-operation (standard care except physical tests):

        -  Questionnaire Data: Oxford Knee Score, SF12, EQ5D, Forgotten Joint Score, Satisfaction
           questionnaire

        -  Descriptive: Late complications

        -  Non-invasive Physical Tests: Range of knee movement, knee muscular strength, lower limb
           kinematics during level (0°)- and downhill (7.5°)-walking
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 6, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline Gait Kinematics at 1-Year</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline at 1-Year</time_frame>
    <description>Gait of patients will be analysed pre-operatively, six-weeks post-operatively, and 1-year post-operatively by 3D motion capture technology. The change measured over time at 1-year will be the primary outcome.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient Satisfaction (Pain/Hospital experience/functional ability/Surgery expectations)</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year post-operatively</time_frame>
    <description>Patient satisfaction will be reported using a scale on a questionnaire which asks six questions on how happy patients were with their hospital experience/level of pain/functional ability post-operatively. The questionnaire also asks whether their expectations were met. The two satisfaction questions are answered on a scale of 'Very Satisfied/Satisfied/Unsure/Dissatisfied' by ticking the appropriate box. The four questions based on patient expectation are scored on a scale of 'Excellent/Good/Unsure/Poor' by ticking the appropriate box.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Oxford Knee Score (Patient reported outcome measure of pain and function)</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-operatively</time_frame>
    <description>A joint specific questionnaire which asks patients on the level of pain and function they believe to have in their affected knee (taking into consideration the past 4 weeks only). The questionnaire consists of 12 questions. Five of the questions are pain related, and seven are aimed at function. Each question has 5 options and is scored from 0-4, with 4 being the best and 0 being the worst pain/function. The best score is therefore 48 (no pain/good function), and the worst score is 0 (pain and poor function).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Oxford Knee Score (Patient reported outcome measure of pain and function)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks post-operatively</time_frame>
    <description>A joint specific questionnaire which asks patients on the level of pain and function they believe to have in their affected knee (taking into consideration the past 4 weeks only). The questionnaire consists of 12 questions. Five of the questions are pain related, and seven are aimed at function. Each question has 5 options and is scored from 0-4, with 4 being the best and 0 being the worst pain/function. The best score is therefore 48 (no pain/good function), and the worst score is 0 (pain and poor function).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Oxford Knee Score (Patient reported outcome measure of pain and function)</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year post-operatively</time_frame>
    <description>A joint specific questionnaire which asks patients on the level of pain and function they believe to have in their affected knee (taking into consideration the past 4 weeks only). The questionnaire consists of 12 questions. Five of the questions are pain related, and seven are aimed at function. Each question has 5 options and is scored from 0-4, with 4 being the best and 0 being the worst pain/function. The best score is therefore 48 (no pain/good function), and the worst score is 0 (pain and poor function).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>EuroQol-5 Dimensions (EQ-5D) (Patient reported outcome measure of patients' perception of their overall health)</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-operatively</time_frame>
    <description>A questionnaire on patients' perception of their overall health. The questionnaire focuses on generic health in 5 dimensions: Mobility, self-care, pain or discomfort, anxiety or depression and usual activities (including work, housework, leisure, family, and study). The questions are scored using an algorithm; the result of which relates to the health status of the patient. This score ranges between 0 (equivalent to death) to 1 (equivalent to full health). It also contains a visual analogue scale where patients have to choose on a scale of 0-100 how well they believe their general health to be on that particular day, where 0 is the worst health imaginable and 100 is the best health imaginable.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>EuroQol-5 Dimensions (EQ-5D) (Patient reported outcome measure of patients' perception of their overall health)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks post-operatively</time_frame>
    <description>A questionnaire on patients' perception of their overall health. The questionnaire focuses on generic health in 5 dimensions: Mobility, self-care, pain or discomfort, anxiety or depression and usual activities (including work, housework, leisure, family, and study). The questions are scored using an algorithm; the result of which relates to the health status of the patient. This score ranges between 0 (equivalent to death) to 1 (equivalent to full health). It also contains a visual analogue scale where patients have to choose on a scale of 0-100 how well they believe their general health to be on that particular day, where 0 is the worst health imaginable and 100 is the best health imaginable.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>EuroQol-5 Dimensions (EQ-5D) (Patient reported outcome measure of patients' perception of their overall health)</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year post-operatively</time_frame>
    <description>A questionnaire on patients' perception of their overall health. The questionnaire focuses on generic health in 5 dimensions: Mobility, self-care, pain or discomfort, anxiety or depression and usual activities (including work, housework, leisure, family, and study). The questions are scored using an algorithm; the result of which relates to the health status of the patient. This score ranges between 0 (equivalent to death) to 1 (equivalent to full health). It also contains a visual analogue scale where patients have to choose on a scale of 0-100 how well they believe their general health to be on that particular day, where 0 is the worst health imaginable and 100 is the best health imaginable.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Short Form-12 (SF-12) (Patient reported outcome measure of general quality of life)</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-operatively</time_frame>
    <description>A general Quality of Life score with 12 questions. It has mental and physical components which are scored from the same questions, using different algorithms. Each question is multiple choice, and the patient must tick one answer. Each answer corresponds to a standardised value, which is used in two algorithms to generate an overall score. One score is for the mental component and one is for the physical component. The physical standardized values are summed across all 12 items. 56.57706 is added to the sum to create the SF-12 physical score. 60.75781 is added to sum create the SF-12 mental score. Higher overall scores are better than lower scores.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Short Form-12 (SF-12) (Patient reported outcome measure of general quality of life)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks post-operatively</time_frame>
    <description>A general Quality of Life score with 12 questions. It has mental and physical components which are scored from the same questions, using different algorithms. Each question is multiple choice, and the patient must tick one answer. Each answer corresponds to a standardised value, which is used in two algorithms to generate an overall score. One score is for the mental component and one is for the physical component. The physical standardized values are summed across all 12 items. 56.57706 is added to the sum to create the SF-12 physical score. 60.75781 is added to sum create the SF-12 mental score. Higher overall scores are better than lower scores.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Short Form-12 (SF-12) (Patient reported outcome measure of general quality of life)</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year post-operatively</time_frame>
    <description>A general Quality of Life score with 12 questions. It has mental and physical components which are scored from the same questions, using different algorithms. Each question is multiple choice, and the patient must tick one answer. Each answer corresponds to a standardised value, which is used in two algorithms to generate an overall score. One score is for the mental component and one is for the physical component. The physical standardized values are summed across all 12 items. 56.57706 is added to the sum to create the SF-12 physical score. 60.75781 is added to sum create the SF-12 mental score. Higher overall scores are better than lower scores.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Forgotten Joint Score (Patient reported outcome measure of awareness of knee)</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-operatively</time_frame>
    <description>This asks questions not covered in the OKS on patient perception of their knee that are important to know following TKA. It focuses on other aspects of outcome other than joint pain and function. There are 12 questions in total, each starting with 'Are you aware of your knee joint...' followed by a daily situation such as driving/lying in bed etc. Each question has a possible of 5 answers: Never/Almost Never/Seldom/Sometimes/Mostly. Every question is scored 1 (never) to 5 (mostly) according to the selected response categories. Thus, the raw score ranges from 12 to 60. The raw score is linearly transformed to a 0-100 scale and then reversed to obtain the final score. For the final Forgotten Joint Score -12 a high score indicates good outcome.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Forgotten Joint Score (Patient reported outcome measure of awareness of knee)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks post-operatively</time_frame>
    <description>This asks questions not covered in the OKS on patient perception of their knee that are important to know following TKA. It focuses on other aspects of outcome other than joint pain and function. There are 12 questions in total, each starting with 'Are you aware of your knee joint...' followed by a daily situation such as driving/lying in bed etc. Each question has a possible of 5 answers: Never/Almost Never/Seldom/Sometimes/Mostly. Every question is scored 1 (never) to 5 (mostly) according to the selected response categories. Thus, the raw score ranges from 12 to 60. The raw score is linearly transformed to a 0-100 scale and then reversed to obtain the final score. For the final Forgotten Joint Score -12 a high score indicates good outcome.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Forgotten Joint Score (Patient reported outcome measure of awareness of knee)</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year post-operatively</time_frame>
    <description>This asks questions not covered in the OKS on patient perception of their knee that are important to know following TKA. It focuses on other aspects of outcome other than joint pain and function. There are 12 questions in total, each starting with 'Are you aware of your knee joint...' followed by a daily situation such as driving/lying in bed etc. Each question has a possible of 5 answers: Never/Almost Never/Seldom/Sometimes/Mostly. Every question is scored 1 (never) to 5 (mostly) according to the selected response categories. Thus, the raw score ranges from 12 to 60. The raw score is linearly transformed to a 0-100 scale and then reversed to obtain the final score. For the final Forgotten Joint Score -12 a high score indicates good outcome.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Knee Strength</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-operatively</time_frame>
    <description>Knee strength in Newton meters will be assessed using motion capture technology and a dynamometer</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Knee Strength</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks post-operatively</time_frame>
    <description>Knee strength in Newton meters will be assessed using a dynamometer.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Knee Strength</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year post-operatively</time_frame>
    <description>Knee strength in Newton meters will be assessed using a dynamometer.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Knee range of motion</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-operatively</time_frame>
    <description>Knee range of motion in degrees will be assessed using motion capture technology</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Knee range of motion</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks post-operatively</time_frame>
    <description>Knee range of motion in degrees will be assessed using motion capture technology</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Knee range of motion</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year post-operatively</time_frame>
    <description>Knee range of motion in degrees will be assessed using motion capture technology.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">170</enrollment>
  <condition>Knee Osteoarthritis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Medacta GMK Sphere</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Half of the patients will be implanted with the Medacta GMK Sphere total knee arthroplasty</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>DePuy Synthes Attune</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Half of the patients will be implanted with the DePuy Attune total knee arthroplasty</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Total knee arthroplasty</intervention_name>
    <description>Parts of the knee joint diseased by osteoarthritis are replaced by metal and plastic prostheses.</description>
    <arm_group_label>DePuy Synthes Attune</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Medacta GMK Sphere</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Medacta GMK Sphere Implant</other_name>
    <other_name>DePuy Synthes Attune Implant</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Clinical diagnosis of osteoarthritis of the knee which is sufficiently symptomatic to
             require knee arthroplasty as assessed by their consultant orthopaedic surgeon

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Inflammatory arthropathy

          -  Patients requiring bone augmentation

          -  Patients with collateral ligament incompetence

          -  Valgus deformity &gt;5 degrees.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>90 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Leela C Biant, FRCSEd Tr &amp; Orth</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Manchester</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Leela C Biant, FRCSEd Tr&amp;Orth</last_name>
    <phone>01612755424</phone>
    <email>leela.biant@manchester.ac.uk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Gwenllian F Tawy, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>01612755424</phone>
    <email>gwenllian.tawy@manchester.ac.uk</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Trafford General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Manchester</city>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Lynne Webster, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>01612764125</phone>
      <email>Lynne.Webster@mft.nhs.uk</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 19, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 1, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 7, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 16, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 16, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 17, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Total Knee Arthroplasty</keyword>
  <keyword>Osteoarthritis</keyword>
  <keyword>Stability</keyword>
  <keyword>Knee</keyword>
  <keyword>Functional Outcome</keyword>
  <keyword>Gait</keyword>
  <keyword>Biomechanics</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Osteoarthritis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Osteoarthritis, Knee</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

