<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03612193</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>201806182</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03612193</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Role of the Gut Microbiome in Complex Regional Pain Syndrome</brief_title>
  <official_title>Role of the Gut Microbiome in Complex Regional Pain Syndrome</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Washington University School of Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Washington University School of Medicine</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The objective of this prospective, observational study is to determine the association
      between the composition of the gut microbiota and the severity and persistence of Complex
      Regional Pain Syndrome symptoms (Study A). The objective of Study B, a longitudinal study of
      microbiota biomarkers of patients with newly diagnosed CRPS is to determine if the
      researchers can predict which patients are more likely to recover compared to those who do
      not. A secondary objective of both studies is to examine cognitive flexibility in relation to
      outcomes (study A and B).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Suspended</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Temporarily paused due to COVID-19 and expected to resume. This is not a suspension of IRB
    approval.
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date type="Actual">December 19, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with taxonomic and metabolomic differences of the gut microbiome in relation to CRPS severity score</measure>
    <time_frame>1 visit - up to one month</time_frame>
    <description>Study A</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with taxonomic and metabolomic differences of the gut microbiome in relation to recovery from CRPS</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Study B</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Score results of the Stroop Color Word Test in relation to CRPS recovery</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Study B</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Logistic regression analysis for testing the association of CRPS severity score to weight in kilograms and height in meters aggregated to BMI (kilograms/meters squared)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Study B</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Logistic regression analysis for testing the association of CRPS severity score to use of opioid analgesics</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Study B</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>5</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">140</enrollment>
  <condition>Complex Regional Pain Syndromes</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Study A: Chronic &gt;1 year</arm_group_label>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Study A: Acute &lt;1 year</arm_group_label>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Study A: Household Control</arm_group_label>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Study B: Newly Diagnosed &lt;6 months</arm_group_label>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Study B: Household Controls</arm_group_label>
  </arm_group>
  <biospec_retention>Samples Without DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Taxonomic and metabolomic biomarkers
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Pain Management Center at Washington University/Barnes-Jewish Hospital medical campus
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Study A: Cross-sectional study

        Inclusion criteria, cases:

          -  Adults over the age of 18

          -  Current (&lt; 1 year duration) or former (&gt; 1 year) diagnosis of Complex Regional Pain
             Syndrome by the Budapest criteria

          -  English as primary language

          -  able to consent

        Inclusion criteria, controls

          -  Adults over age of 18

          -  Cohabitant of person with current or former diagnosis of CRPS

        Study B: Longitudinal Study

        Inclusion criteria, cases:

          -  Adults over the age of 18

          -  Recent diagnosis (&lt;6 months) of Complex Regional Pain Syndrome by the Budapest
             criteria

          -  English as primary language

          -  able to consent

        Inclusion criteria, controls

          -  Adults over age of 18

          -  Cohabitant of person with diagnosis of CRPS

        Study A and B: Exclusion criteria, cases and controls:

          -  Unwilling to participate in the study

          -  Lives alone

          -  Current use of probiotics and unwilling to stop for 1 week prior to stool sample

          -  Pregnant or lactating

          -  Vegan diet
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Lara Crock, MD PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Washington University School of Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Washington University School of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Saint Louis</city>
        <state>Missouri</state>
        <zip>63110</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Harden RN, Bruehl S, Perez RS, Birklein F, Marinus J, Maihofner C, Lubenow T, Buvanendran A, Mackey S, Graciosa J, Mogilevski M, Ramsden C, Chont M, Vatine JJ. Validation of proposed diagnostic criteria (the &quot;Budapest Criteria&quot;) for Complex Regional Pain Syndrome. Pain. 2010 Aug;150(2):268-74. doi: 10.1016/j.pain.2010.04.030. Epub 2010 May 20.</citation>
    <PMID>20493633</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Birklein F, Dimova V. Complex regional pain syndrome-up-to-date. Pain Rep. 2017 Oct 5;2(6):e624. doi: 10.1097/PR9.0000000000000624. eCollection 2017 Nov.</citation>
    <PMID>29392238</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Birklein F, Ajit SK, Goebel A, Perez RSGM, Sommer C. Complex regional pain syndrome - phenotypic characteristics and potential biomarkers. Nat Rev Neurol. 2018 May;14(5):272-284. doi: 10.1038/nrneurol.2018.20. Epub 2018 Mar 16. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>29545626</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lenz M, Uçeyler N, Frettlöh J, Höffken O, Krumova EK, Lissek S, Reinersmann A, Sommer C, Stude P, Waaga-Gasser AM, Tegenthoff M, Maier C. Local cytokine changes in complex regional pain syndrome type I (CRPS I) resolve after 6 months. Pain. 2013 Oct;154(10):2142-9. doi: 10.1016/j.pain.2013.06.039. Epub 2013 Jun 27.</citation>
    <PMID>23811041</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ware MA, Bennett GJ. Case report: Long-standing complex regional pain syndrome relieved by a cephalosporin antibiotic. Pain. 2014 Jul;155(7):1412-5. doi: 10.1016/j.pain.2014.03.014. Epub 2014 Mar 22.</citation>
    <PMID>24667741</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Weinstock LB, Myers TL, Walters AS, Schwartz OA, Younger JW, Chopra PJ, Guarino AH. Identification and Treatment of New Inflammatory Triggers for Complex Regional Pain Syndrome: Small Intestinal Bacterial Overgrowth and Obstructive Sleep Apnea. A A Case Rep. 2016 May 1;6(9):272-6. doi: 10.1213/XAA.0000000000000292.</citation>
    <PMID>26867023</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fung TC, Olson CA, Hsiao EY. Interactions between the microbiota, immune and nervous systems in health and disease. Nat Neurosci. 2017 Feb;20(2):145-155. doi: 10.1038/nn.4476. Epub 2017 Jan 16. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>28092661</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cryan JF, Dinan TG. Mind-altering microorganisms: the impact of the gut microbiota on brain and behaviour. Nat Rev Neurosci. 2012 Oct;13(10):701-12. doi: 10.1038/nrn3346. Epub 2012 Sep 12. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22968153</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Frank DN, Robertson CE, Hamm CM, Kpadeh Z, Zhang T, Chen H, Zhu W, Sartor RB, Boedeker EC, Harpaz N, Pace NR, Li E. Disease phenotype and genotype are associated with shifts in intestinal-associated microbiota in inflammatory bowel diseases. Inflamm Bowel Dis. 2011 Jan;17(1):179-84. doi: 10.1002/ibd.21339. Epub 2010 Sep 13.</citation>
    <PMID>20839241</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bercik P, Denou E, Collins J, Jackson W, Lu J, Jury J, Deng Y, Blennerhassett P, Macri J, McCoy KD, Verdu EF, Collins SM. The intestinal microbiota affect central levels of brain-derived neurotropic factor and behavior in mice. Gastroenterology. 2011 Aug;141(2):599-609, 609.e1-3. doi: 10.1053/j.gastro.2011.04.052. Epub 2011 Apr 30.</citation>
    <PMID>21683077</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shen S, Lim G, You Z, Ding W, Huang P, Ran C, Doheny J, Caravan P, Tate S, Hu K, Kim H, McCabe M, Huang B, Xie Z, Kwon D, Chen L, Mao J. Gut microbiota is critical for the induction of chemotherapy-induced pain. Nat Neurosci. 2017 Sep;20(9):1213-1216. doi: 10.1038/nn.4606. Epub 2017 Jul 17.</citation>
    <PMID>28714953</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Amaral FA, Sachs D, Costa VV, Fagundes CT, Cisalpino D, Cunha TM, Ferreira SH, Cunha FQ, Silva TA, Nicoli JR, Vieira LQ, Souza DG, Teixeira MM. Commensal microbiota is fundamental for the development of inflammatory pain. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2008 Feb 12;105(6):2193-7. doi: 10.1073/pnas.0711891105. Epub 2008 Feb 11.</citation>
    <PMID>18268332</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nayak RR, Turnbaugh PJ. Mirror, mirror on the wall: which microbiomes will help heal them all? BMC Med. 2016 May 4;14:72. doi: 10.1186/s12916-016-0622-6.</citation>
    <PMID>27146150</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wang F, Meng J, Zhang L, Johnson T, Chen C, Roy S. Morphine induces changes in the gut microbiome and metabolome in a morphine dependence model. Sci Rep. 2018 Feb 26;8(1):3596. doi: 10.1038/s41598-018-21915-8.</citation>
    <PMID>29483538</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Basbaum AI, Bautista DM, Scherrer G, Julius D. Cellular and molecular mechanisms of pain. Cell. 2009 Oct 16;139(2):267-84. doi: 10.1016/j.cell.2009.09.028. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19837031</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ji RR, Chamessian A, Zhang YQ. Pain regulation by non-neuronal cells and inflammation. Science. 2016 Nov 4;354(6312):572-577. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>27811267</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Powell N, Walker MM, Talley NJ. The mucosal immune system: master regulator of bidirectional gut-brain communications. Nat Rev Gastroenterol Hepatol. 2017 Mar;14(3):143-159. doi: 10.1038/nrgastro.2016.191. Epub 2017 Jan 18. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>28096541</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bravo JA, Forsythe P, Chew MV, Escaravage E, Savignac HM, Dinan TG, Bienenstock J, Cryan JF. Ingestion of Lactobacillus strain regulates emotional behavior and central GABA receptor expression in a mouse via the vagus nerve. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2011 Sep 20;108(38):16050-5. doi: 10.1073/pnas.1102999108. Epub 2011 Aug 29.</citation>
    <PMID>21876150</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Neuman H, Debelius JW, Knight R, Koren O. Microbial endocrinology: the interplay between the microbiota and the endocrine system. FEMS Microbiol Rev. 2015 Jul;39(4):509-21. doi: 10.1093/femsre/fuu010. Epub 2015 Feb 19. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25701044</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lyte M. Microbial endocrinology in the microbiome-gut-brain axis: how bacterial production and utilization of neurochemicals influence behavior. PLoS Pathog. 2013;9(11):e1003726. doi: 10.1371/journal.ppat.1003726. Epub 2013 Nov 14. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24244158</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lyte M. Microbial endocrinology: Host-microbiota neuroendocrine interactions influencing brain and behavior. Gut Microbes. 2014 May-Jun;5(3):381-9. doi: 10.4161/gmic.28682. Epub 2014 Apr 1. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24690573</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nair AT, Ramachandran V, Joghee NM, Antony S, Ramalingam G. Gut Microbiota Dysfunction as Reliable Non-invasive Early Diagnostic Biomarkers in the Pathophysiology of Parkinson's Disease: A Critical Review. J Neurogastroenterol Motil. 2018 Jan 30;24(1):30-42. doi: 10.5056/jnm17105. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>29291606</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nagy-Szakal D, Williams BL, Mishra N, Che X, Lee B, Bateman L, Klimas NG, Komaroff AL, Levine S, Montoya JG, Peterson DL, Ramanan D, Jain K, Eddy ML, Hornig M, Lipkin WI. Fecal metagenomic profiles in subgroups of patients with myalgic encephalomyelitis/chronic fatigue syndrome. Microbiome. 2017 Apr 26;5(1):44. doi: 10.1186/s40168-017-0261-y.</citation>
    <PMID>28441964</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dinsdale EA, Edwards RA, Hall D, Angly F, Breitbart M, Brulc JM, Furlan M, Desnues C, Haynes M, Li L, McDaniel L, Moran MA, Nelson KE, Nilsson C, Olson R, Paul J, Brito BR, Ruan Y, Swan BK, Stevens R, Valentine DL, Thurber RV, Wegley L, White BA, Rohwer F. Functional metagenomic profiling of nine biomes. Nature. 2008 Apr 3;452(7187):629-32. doi: 10.1038/nature06810. Epub 2008 Mar 12. Erratum in: Nature. 2008 Oct 9;455(7214):830.</citation>
    <PMID>18337718</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Harden RN, Maihofner C, Abousaad E, Vatine JJ, Kirsling A, Perez RSGM, Kuroda M, Brunner F, Stanton-Hicks M, Marinus J, van Hilten JJ, Mackey S, Birklein F, Schlereth T, Mailis-Gagnon A, Graciosa J, Connoly SB, Dayanim D, Massey M, Frank H, Livshitz A, Bruehl S. A prospective, multisite, international validation of the Complex Regional Pain Syndrome Severity Score. Pain. 2017 Aug;158(8):1430-1436. doi: 10.1097/j.pain.0000000000000927.</citation>
    <PMID>28715350</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Unger MM, Spiegel J, Dillmann KU, Grundmann D, Philippeit H, Bürmann J, Faßbender K, Schwiertz A, Schäfer KH. Short chain fatty acids and gut microbiota differ between patients with Parkinson's disease and age-matched controls. Parkinsonism Relat Disord. 2016 Nov;32:66-72. doi: 10.1016/j.parkreldis.2016.08.019. Epub 2016 Aug 26.</citation>
    <PMID>27591074</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 9, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 1, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 2, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 5, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 5, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 7, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Washington University School of Medicine</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Lara Crock</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Clinical Fellow</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Complex Regional Pain Syndromes</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Reflex Sympathetic Dystrophy</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Somatoform Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

