<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03610672</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>R34DA043957</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03610672</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Mobile Intervention for Young Opioid Users</brief_title>
  <official_title>Preventing Injection: An mHealth Intervention That Leverages Social Networks to Prevent Progression to Injection Among Young Opioid Users</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Development and Research Institutes, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Development and Research Institutes, Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Opioid use disorders (OUD) are the second most common type of drug use disorder in the US,
      with nearly 2 million Americans with prescription opioid- (PO) and ~570,000 with
      heroin-related OUD. The escalation in OUD during the past two decades has been most
      pronounced among youth, many of whom demonstrate a rapid transition from nonmedical PO use
      (16-17 y/o), to heroin (19-20 y/o), with most progressing to injection drug use (IDU), within
      a year of starting heroin use (20-21 y/o). Progression to IDU is characterized by uniquely
      high levels of risk for youth, including higher rates of overdose (OD) and HIV and HCV
      incidence, compared to older peers. Addiction severity, psychosocial functioning, and social
      networks are robust predictors of transitioning to IDU; however there is virtually no
      research on how to prevent or halt this transition to IDU. Given the paucity of interventions
      targeting this large and vulnerable group of youth, we propose to adapt and evaluate an
      innovative, engaging mHealth intervention to prevent young opioid users (18-29) from
      transitioning to IDU. Aim 1: During months 1-12, we will adapt our existing mobile
      intervention for OUD that includes daily text messages plus key components of evidence-based
      CBT interventions, including Functional Analysis of Drug Use, Self-Management, and Social /
      Recreational Counseling. New components specific to youth will focus on the role of peers on
      opioid use and IDU, and OD prevention / response training. Our iterative development process
      will include focus groups with opioid-using youth (n=24), interviews with important
      stakeholders (e.g., youth treatment providers; n=6), and feedback and usability data from
      opioid-using youth (n=30). Aim 2: During months 13-31, we will conduct a small randomized,
      controlled trial of the tailored mHealth intervention with young opioid users who have not
      transitioned to regular injection (n=64) and compare (1) assessment plus in-person OD
      prevention / response training (including naloxone) versus (2) assessment plus in-person OD
      prevention / response training (including naloxone) plus our mHealth intervention.
      Feasibility and acceptability will be assessed via participant feedback, retention, and usage
      data. Diffusion will be defined as the number of participants' peers who download the
      intervention app for their own use. Preliminary effectiveness will be measured via reductions
      in opioid use (TLFB, urine / hair toxicology) and self-reported injection status at 4, 8, and
      12 weeks, and 3 and 6 month follow-up. Secondary outcomes include HIV/HCV risk behavior, OD,
      opioid-related problems (e.g., withdrawal episodes), and social network IDU-related norms and
      behaviors. If results are promising, this novel intervention will be expanded for examination
      in a large-scale efficacy / effectiveness trial.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Opioid use disorders (OUD) are the second most common type of drug use disorder in the US,
      with nearly 2 million reporting prescription opioid (PO) use and ~570,000 reporting heroin
      use consistent with an OUD. Further, drug overdose (OD) has become the leading cause of
      accidental death in the US, with opioid-involved OD driving this epidemic. The recent
      escalation in OUD has been most pronounced among youth, with nearly 1/3 of youth reporting PO
      misuse by age 21, and studies have documented the trajectory from PO misuse to injection drug
      use (IDU) in youth. An ongoing study conducted by the current investigators documented an
      alarming trajectory, wherein these youth progress from nonmedical PO use in adolescence
      (first PO use M=16.7 y/o), to oral / intranasal heroin use in young adulthood (M=19.1 y/o),
      with 64% progressing to injection drug use (IDU), within a year of heroin initiation (first
      injection M=20.1 y/o. This progression to IDU is characterized by uniquely high levels of
      risk for youth, including higher rates of injection risk behaviors and OD, and higher
      incidence of HIV and HCV within the first few years of transitioning to injection, compared
      to older peers. Thus, young opioid users are at uniquely high risk for a number of negative
      outcomes during the critical period of transitioning to injection. This rapid progression
      from PO use to IDU and the extreme risk associated with new injection status among youth
      indicate that there is a brief, but critical, period during which we may intervene to prevent
      progression to injection and its associated risk behaviors and negative health outcomes.
      Several robust predictors have been found for progression to IDU, including psychosocial
      factors (i.e., homelessness, physical abuse), OUD severity (i.e., dependence severity,
      polydrug use), and IDU norms and behaviors within one's social network. While there is some
      understanding of the mechanisms that promote IDU, there is virtually no research on
      strategies to prevent this transition. Only one intervention has been examined targeting
      intranasal heroin users in an attempt to prevent progression to IDU. This &quot;sniffers&quot;
      intervention found potent effects; half as many intervention participants progressed to
      injection (33% vs. 16%), compared to the control condition (who received HIV/AIDS education),
      indicating that direct intervention with opioid users may be an effective way to prevent
      progression to IDU and its associated harms. It is unclear why so few interventions have
      targeted this population, although young opioid users face a number of unique barriers,
      including social, economic, and motivational, that may prevent them from seeking and
      receiving treatment. Given the paucity of interventions available to the large and vulnerable
      group of opioid-using young adults, there is an urgent need to develop and evaluate
      innovative, engaging approaches to prevent young opioid users from transitioning to IDU.

      The current application is being submitted in response to PA 16-073, &quot;Behavioral and
      Integrative Treatment Development Program.&quot; The proposed project is a Stage Ib study that
      will adapt a mobile, evidence-based psychosocial intervention for opioid dependence (Check-In
      App) to prevent progression to injection in young opioid users (18-29 y/o) who have not
      progressed to regular injection.

      Aim 1: During months 1-12, we will adapt the Check-In App to target reducing opioid use and
      preventing progression to injection among young oral / intranasal opioid users. We will
      tailor our existing mHealth intervention (including daily text messages plus key components
      of evidence-based cognitive behavioral interventions, Functional Analysis of Drug Use,
      Self-Management, and Social / Recreational Counseling), for young opioid users. New
      components specific to youth will focus on the role of peers in opioid use / IDU, and OD
      prevention / response training including use of naloxone. Our iterative development process
      will include focus groups with opioid-using youth (n=24), interviews with important
      stakeholders (e.g., youth treatment providers; n=6), and feedback and usability data from
      opioid-using youth (n=30).

      Aim 2: During months 13-31, we will conduct a small randomized, controlled trial of the newly
      tailored mHealth intervention with young opioid users (18-29 y/o) who have not transitioned
      to regular injection (n=64) and compare (1) assessment plus in-person OD prevention /
      response training (including naloxone) versus (2) assessment plus in-person OD prevention /
      response training (including naloxone) plus the Preventing Injection Application. We will
      evaluate the intervention's feasibility, acceptability, diffusion, and preliminary
      effectiveness. Feasibility and acceptability will be assessed via participant feedback,
      retention, and app usage data. Diffusion will be defined as the number of participants' peers
      who download the intervention app for their own use. Preliminary effectiveness will be
      measured via reductions in opioid use (TLFB, urine and hair toxicology) and self-reported
      injection status at 4, 8, and 12 weeks, and 3 and 6 month follow-up. Secondary outcomes
      include HIV/HCV risk behavior, OD episodes, opioid-related problems (e.g., withdrawal
      episodes), and social network IDU-related norms and behaviors.

      If results are promising, this intervention will be evaluated in a large-scale efficacy /
      effectiveness trial. This intervention may have tremendous impact on improving access,
      acceptability, and potency of opioid use interventions for youth, given the extremely
      widespread use of mobile apps among young adults (98% of 18-29 y/o own mobile phones and
      spend ~3 hr/day using mobile apps).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 15, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 28, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 28, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Factorial Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>The current study is a two-armed, open randomized clinical trial design.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in opioid use</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline to 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Participant opioid use will be assessed via self-reported Timeline Followback, urine toxicology, and hair toxicology</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in self-reported injection status via Timeline Followback</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline to 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Self-reports of frequency and duration of injection drug use</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in HIV/HCV risk behavior</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline to 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>self-reported HIV/HCV risk behavior (combined injection and sexual risk behavior)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>OD</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>frequency and severity of self-reported overdose (OD) episodes</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Peer IDU norms</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline to 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Self-reported perceptions of peer injection drug use-related norms</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">64</enrollment>
  <condition>Opioid-Related Disorders</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>OD prevention/response training</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Immediately following the baseline assessment, trained research staff will conduct a brief (20 min.) OD training with each participant. Participants will be asked to view the NYC Department of Health and Mental Hygiene's 13-minute OD prevention and response training video (available online free-of-charge). Following the video, research staff will review key information, answer any questions participants may have, demonstrate assembly of the intranasal naloxone atomizer and ensure participants are able to execute this assembly procedure. A prescription for naloxone, as well as a standard naloxone kit containing two doses of the medication and atomizers for intranasal administration, will be given to participants, along with printed literature reviewing key training information.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>OD training + mobile PI intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will complete the same baseline assessment and OD training (plus naloxone) as those in the first condition. Participants also will receive mobile phones pre-loaded with the PI App and will be sent daily prompts. As part of the PI App, participants will be asked to share information about avoiding problems associated with opioid use with peers in their social network, and to encourage their peers to download the PI App for their own use.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>OD prevention/response training</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will view a 13-minute OD prevention and response training video (available online free-of-charge). This video covers NY State's recommended curriculum for Overdose Prevention: how to prevent, identify, and respond to an OD, including information on the factors that could heighten risk for overdose (mixing drugs, changes in tolerance and drug purity, and using alone), how to respond to an overdose (rescue breathing, calling 911), and specific instructions on how and when to administer naloxone to someone who is overdosing. After the video, research staff will review key information, answer any questions participants may have, demonstrate assembly of the intranasal naloxone atomizer and ensure participants are able to assemble it. A prescription for naloxone, as well as a standard naloxone kit containing two doses of the medication and atomizers for intranasal administration, will be given to participants, along with printed literature reviewing key training information.</description>
    <arm_group_label>OD prevention/response training</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>OD prevention/response training + PI mobile application</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will receive the same OD intervention as those in the first arm, as well as receiving mobile phones pre-loaded with the PI App. This intervention includes daily prompts plus key components of evidence-based cognitive behavioral interventions, including Functional Analysis of Drug Use, Self-Management, and Social/Recreational Counseling and additional content on Distress Tolerance, the relationship between Peer Networks and Drug Use, and pertinent resources.</description>
    <arm_group_label>OD training + mobile PI intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Current opioid use, defined as having used heroin and/or POs 12 or more times in the
             past 30 days (self-report verified by urine toxicology)

          -  Aged 18-29 years, verified by photo ID

          -  Able to understand and speak English

          -  Willing and available to participate in the assigned intervention.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Individuals are excluded if they report regular injection drug use (defined as
             injection 3 or more times/week in the past 30 days) for a period of more than 24
             months
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>29 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Michelle Acosta</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>NIDA/NIH</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Michelle Acosta</last_name>
    <phone>2128454535</phone>
    <email>acosta@ndri.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Honoria Guarino</last_name>
    <phone>2128454540</phone>
    <email>guarino@ndri.org</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Development and Research Institutes, Inc.</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10010</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Lisa Bernhard</last_name>
      <phone>212-845-4567</phone>
      <email>bernhard@ndri.org</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 16, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 25, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 1, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 31, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 31, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">August 2, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Opioid-Related Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

