<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03610620</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>212591</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03610620</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Confocal Microscopy Evaluation of Margin Clearance in Basal Cell Carcinomas in Mohs Surgery</brief_title>
  <acronym>FCM-P</acronym>
  <official_title>Does Ex-vivo Fluorescence Confocal Microscopy Allow Faster Evaluation of Margin Clearance in Basal Cell Carcinomas in Mohs Surgery: A Pilot Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Julie Dawson</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Mavig GmbH</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Norfolk and Norwich University Hospitals NHS Foundation Trust</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study is comparing the accuracy and speed of the Vivascope 2500 ex-vivo fluorescent
      confocal microscope with frozen section Mohs histology in evaluating clear margins in basal
      cell carcinoma in Mohs surgery.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Patients with basal cell carcinomas in the head and neck area, being considered for Mohs
      surgery with frozen sections will be invited to participate in this trial by the
      investigators when they attend for their pre-surgical consultation. They will be given
      sufficient time to review the information sheet and ask questions. When they attend for their
      Mohs surgery, they will be recruited if they wish to participate in this trial, at which
      point, the investigator, or an authorized member of their team, will obtain written informed
      consent for patients. The patient will then undergo Mohs surgery. The processing and
      interpretation with frozen sections will be conducted in the same way, the only difference
      being immediately after the BCC is excised with a Mohs bevelled edge (45o incision), the
      tissue is immersed in acridine orange (nuclear DNA stain) and placed upside down with the
      deep margin of the tissue face up. With a glass slide placed on top, we would place the FCM
      (Vivascope 2500) over this, scan the tissue and obtain mosaic images of the tissue which
      would be stitched together. The penetration of the FCM scan is approximately 0.25mm. This is
      approximately the distance between 2-3 Mohs wafers. The investigators would usually consider
      a margin of 3 Mohs wafers (300 microns) clear. When the scanning is completed (5 minutes),
      the Mohs layer would be sent for frozen section (stained with haematoxylin and eosin) for
      confirmation in the usual way. The Mohs surgeon can interpret the FCM mosaic images later.
      Acridine orange does not interfere with frozen sections or paraffin histopathological
      quality. No medicines will be used in this study. The information is collected on only 1
      patient visit. There is no follow up period. The main objectives would (1) compare the
      accuracy in detection of BCC margins with FCM compared with FSM and (2) evaluate the time
      taken for processing and interpretation of FCM (acridine orange inking and rinsing, image
      acquisition and mosaic stitching, and image interpretation) compared with the time taken for
      processing and interpretation of FSM (sample flattening, freezing and cutting with the
      cryostat, H&amp;E staining, slide cover slipping and slide interpretation).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 12, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">August 9, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">August 9, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Compare accuracy and speed of the Vivascope 2500 to frozen sections.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To compare the specificity and sensitivity of the ex-vivo fluorescence confocal microscopy against frozen section histopathology in detecting residual BCC in Mohs excisions.</measure>
    <time_frame>1 DAY</time_frame>
    <description>Compare the specificity and sensitivity of the ex-vivo fluorescence confocal microscopy against frozen section histopathology in detecting residual BCC in Mohs excisions.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To compare the time taken for processing and interpretation of the ex-vivo fluorescence confocal microscopy against frozen section histopathology in detecting residual BCC in Mohs excisions.</measure>
    <time_frame>1 DAY</time_frame>
    <description>Compare the time taken for processing and interpretation of the ex-vivo fluorescence confocal microscopy against frozen section histopathology in detecting residual BCC in Mohs excisions.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Basal Cell Carcinoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>ARM A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Vivascope 2500 ex-vivo fluorescent confocal microscope</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Vivascope 2500 ex-vivo fluorescent confocal microscope</intervention_name>
    <description>scanned with the Vivascope 2500</description>
    <arm_group_label>ARM A</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Age 18 years or older

          2. Patient with basal cell carcinoma on the head and neck undergoing Mohs surgery with
             frozen sections

          3. Patient willing and able to give informed consent

          4. Patient treated not previously or currently treated with a hedgehog inhibitor
             medication (vismodegib)

          5. Patient suitable for Mohs surgery

          6. Excised lesion suitable for scanning with FCM as determined by investigator -

        Exclusion Criteria:

        -
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Eunice Tan, Consultant</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Clinical Research and Trials Unit (Norfolk &amp; Norwich University Hospital, UK)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Norfolk &amp; Norwich University Hospitals NHS Foundation Trust</name>
      <address>
        <city>Norwich</city>
        <state>Norfolk</state>
        <zip>NR4 7UY</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 26, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 26, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 1, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 25, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 25, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 27, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Norfolk and Norwich University Hospitals NHS Foundation Trust</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Julie Dawson</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Research Services Manager</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Basal cell carcinoma</keyword>
  <keyword>Mohs surgery</keyword>
  <keyword>Vivascope 2500 ex-vivo fluorescent confocal microscope</keyword>
  <keyword>Frozen section Mohs histology</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Basal Cell</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

