<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03618004</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Kaatsu-BFR</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03618004</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Technique of Restriction of Blood Flow Associated With the Ergonomic Cycle of Upper Limbs in Women</brief_title>
  <acronym>Kaatsu-BFR</acronym>
  <official_title>Technique of Restriction of Blood Flow Associated With the Ergonomic Cycle of Upper Limbs in Women. A Randomized Pilot Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Real Fundación Victoria Eugenia</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Real Fundación Victoria Eugenia</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Finding alternatives to improve variables such as strength and anaerobic resistance is a
      subject of highly studied clinical intervention. The use of vascular occlusion associated
      with physical exercise has shown efficacy in improving these aspects.

      The objective is to analyze the effectiveness of upper limb training with vascular occlusion
      (Kaatsu training) for the improvement of isometric strength and anaerobic capacity in women
      aged 18 to 38 years.

      Study design. Randomized, prospective, single-blind, follow-up clinical study. The selected
      sample will be randomized into two groups: experimental and control. The intervention will
      consist of ergonomic exercises with and without vascular occlusion. Isometric strength will
      be assessed with a manual dynamometer, anaerobic capacity and peak power (anaerobic alactic
      system) and average power (anaerobic lactic system) with the wingate test, and subjective
      perception of effort with the Borg scale. The intervention will last 4 weeks, with 3 weekly
      sessions of 10 minutes each. A descriptive statistical analysis will be carried out among the
      dependent and independent variables of both groups. With the Kolmogórov distribution
      normality test and with the Anova and t-student tests for analysis of repeated measures.

      Expected results. The investigators intend to observe improvement of isometric biceps and
      triceps strength and the anaerobic capacity of the group treated with vascular occlusion.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The use of peripheral vascular occlusion in low intensity resistance exercises is a simple,
      safe and effective method, indicated for healthy individuals or with cardio-respiratory
      diseases, in the prevention of atrophy due to disuse, within the post rehabilitation
      approach. -surgical intervention and to improve the performance of athletes. Several studies
      evaluated the use of blood flow restriction prior to aerobic and anaerobic exercises, with
      heterogeneous results, without consensus. With this, our research proposal is a pioneer, as
      there is no other study that has investigated the use of upper limb vascular occlusion during
      anaerobic activity in an arm ergometer cycle. This could benefit individuals who need to
      maintain their anaerobic conditioning and who, for some reason, are unable to use the lower
      limbs. In addition, it could benefit in the performance and improvement of the physical
      fitness of athletes in wheelchairs of various modalities, which have their functions
      preserved in the upper limbs. Only a similar study showed the efficacy of this intervention
      model, but in lower limbs. The prevalence of men in published studies of anaerobic capacity
      with the WinGate test, with few studies recruiting women, indicates the need to perform the
      study with a female sample.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 1, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">August 2, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">April 12, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline isometric strength of biceps after treatment and at 1 month</measure>
    <time_frame>Screening visit, within the first seven days after treatment and after one month follow-up visit]</time_frame>
    <description>A Lafayette Manual Muscle Testing System force dynamometer (model 01165, USA) was used. The subject was standing with the trunk straight, the shoulders in neutral position with the arms aligned to the trunk and the elbows in 90 degrees of flexion. The evaluator requested a maximum voluntary isometric muscle contraction in elbow flexion, maintaining it for 5 seconds. Three repetitions were performed, with 5 minutes of rest between each series, the reference value being the average of the value obtained between the 3 repetitions.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline isometric strength of triceps after treatment and at 1 month</measure>
    <time_frame>Screening visit, within the first seven days after treatment and after one month follow-up visit</time_frame>
    <description>A Lafayette Manual Muscle Testing System force dynamometer (model 01165, USA) was used. The subject was standing with the trunk straight, the shoulders in neutral position with the arms aligned to the trunk and the elbows in 90 degrees of flexion. The evaluator requested a maximum voluntary isometric muscle contraction in elbow extension, maintaining it for 5 seconds. Three repetitions were performed, with 5 minutes of rest between each series, the reference value being the average of the value obtained between the 3 repetitions.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline peak power after treatment and at 1 month</measure>
    <time_frame>Screening visit, within the first seven days after treatment and after one month follow-up visit</time_frame>
    <description>The WinGate test was used. The equipment used was an ergonomic clico for upper limbs (Excite® top seat, technogyn, Brazil). Each subject was placed seated, so that the center of the glenohumeral joint was aligned with the axis of the cranks of the equipment, with 90 degrees of knee flexion, which were aligned with shoulders and feet. The horizontal distance was adjusted so that the elbows were not in maximum extension and allowing the comfort of the participants.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline relative power peak after treatment and at 1 month</measure>
    <time_frame>Screening visit, within the first seven days after treatment and after one month follow-up visit</time_frame>
    <description>The WinGate test was used. The equipment used was an ergonomic clico for upper limbs (Excite® top seat, technogyn, Brazil). Each subject was placed seated, so that the center of the glenohumeral joint was aligned with the axis of the cranks of the equipment, with 90 degrees of knee flexion, which were aligned with shoulders and feet. The horizontal distance was adjusted so that the elbows were not in maximum extension and allowing the comfort of the participants.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline medium power after treatment and at 1 month</measure>
    <time_frame>Screening visit, within the first seven days after treatment and after one month follow-up visit</time_frame>
    <description>The WinGate test was used. The equipment used was an ergonomic clico for upper limbs (Excite® top seat, technogyn, Brazil). Each subject was placed seated, so that the center of the glenohumeral joint was aligned with the axis of the cranks of the equipment, with 90 degrees of knee flexion, which were aligned with shoulders and feet. The horizontal distance was adjusted so that the elbows were not in maximum extension and allowing the comfort of the participants.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline relative medium power after treatment and at 1 month</measure>
    <time_frame>Screening visit, within the first seven days after treatment and after one month follow-up visit</time_frame>
    <description>The WinGate test was used. The equipment used was an ergonomic clico for upper limbs (Excite® top seat, technogyn, Brazil). Each subject was placed seated, so that the center of the glenohumeral joint was aligned with the axis of the cranks of the equipment, with 90 degrees of knee flexion, which were aligned with shoulders and feet. The horizontal distance was adjusted so that the elbows were not in maximum extension and allowing the comfort of the participants.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline fatigue index after treatment and at 1 month</measure>
    <time_frame>Screening visit, within the first seven days after treatment and after one month follow-up visit</time_frame>
    <description>The WinGate test was used. The equipment used was an ergonomic clico for upper limbs (Excite® top seat, technogyn, Brazil). Each subject was placed seated, so that the center of the glenohumeral joint was aligned with the axis of the cranks of the equipment, with 90 degrees of knee flexion, which were aligned with shoulders and feet. The horizontal distance was adjusted so that the elbows were not in maximum extension and allowing the comfort of the participants.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline subjective perception of effort after treatment and at 1 month</measure>
    <time_frame>Screening visit, within the first seven days after treatment and after one month follow-up visit</time_frame>
    <description>The subjective perception of effort was evaluated with the Borg CR-10 scale. One minute after the end of the evaluation, the effort perceived by the subjects was quantified from 0 to 10, with 0 the minimum perceived effort and 10 the maximum.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline heart rate after treatment and at 1 month</measure>
    <time_frame>Screening visit, within the first seven days after treatment and after one month follow-up visit</time_frame>
    <description>The heart rate was assessed through a cardiac frequency meter (model Onrhythm 310, Geonaute, France). The resting heart rates were evaluated and one minute after the intervention.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Women's Health: Female Athlete/Female Athlete Triad</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Experimental group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The intervention lasted 17 minutes each session, 2 weekly sessions were carried out, during 4 weeks. The training started with a warm-up on the hand bike without a load for 5 minutes. Later, we did a work of 3 series of 30 seconds, in maximum power, with 5 minutes of rest between them. The intensity was calculated by 0.048 kp.kg.
The subjects of the experimental group made use of the restriction of blood flow, using a pressure cuff coupled in the most proximal region of the arm, 10 cm wide. The pressure was calculated based on the initial systolic pressure of the subjects.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The intervention lasted 17 minutes each session, 2 weekly sessions were carried out, during 4 weeks. The training started with a warm-up on the hand bike without a load for 5 minutes. Later, we did a work of 3 series of 30 seconds, in maximum power, with 5 minutes of rest between them. The intensity was calculated by 0.048 kp.kg.
The subjects in the control group did not use pressure cuffs.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Experimental group</intervention_name>
    <description>The intervention lasted 17 minutes each session, 2 weekly sessions were carried out, during 4 weeks. The training started with a warm-up on the hand bike without a load for 5 minutes. Later, we did a work of 3 series of 30 seconds, in maximum power, with 5 minutes of rest between them. The intensity was calculated by 0.048 kp.kg.
The subjects of the experimental group made use of the restriction of blood flow, using a pressure cuff coupled in the most proximal region of the arm, 10 cm wide. The pressure was calculated based on the initial systolic pressure of the subjects.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Experimental group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Control group</intervention_name>
    <description>The intervention lasted 17 minutes each session, 2 weekly sessions were carried out, during 4 weeks. The training started with a warm-up on the hand bike without a load for 5 minutes. Later, we did a work of 3 series of 30 seconds, in maximum power, with 5 minutes of rest between them. The intensity was calculated by 0.048 kp.kg.
The subjects in the control group did not use pressure cuffs.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Women

          -  Between 18 and 40 years old

          -  Physically active

          -  Without orthopedic injuries that prevented them from carrying out the exercise
             protocol

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Diagnosis of chronic musculoskeletal, neurological or cardiorespiratory diseases

          -  With diagnosis of arterial hypertension, deep vein thrombosis or diabetes

          -  Pregnant

          -  Not sign the informed consent document
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>40 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Rubén Cuesta-Barriuso, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Universidad Europea de Madrid</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Royal Victoria Eugenia Foundation</name>
      <address>
        <city>Madrid</city>
        <state>Madird</state>
        <zip>28029</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Spain</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 1, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 6, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 7, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 23, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 23, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 27, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Restriction of blood flow</keyword>
  <keyword>Anaerobic capacity</keyword>
  <keyword>Subjective perception of effort</keyword>
  <keyword>Wingate</keyword>
  <keyword>Isometric strength</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Female Athlete Triad Syndrome</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <pending_results>
    <submitted>April 1, 2019</submitted>
    <returned>June 25, 2019</returned>
  </pending_results>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

