<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03610711</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>J1884</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>IRB00166032</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>CA224-053</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03610711</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>REACTION (Radiation Enhanced Assessment of Combination Therapies in Immuno-ONcology) - Nivolumab or Nivolumab in Combination With Other Immuno-oncology (IO) Agents After Targeted Systemic Radiation in Patients With Advanced Esophagogastric Cancer</brief_title>
  <acronym>REACTION</acronym>
  <official_title>REACTION (Radiation Enhanced Assessment of Combination Therapies in Immuno-ONcology) - Nivolumab or Nivolumab in Combination With Other Immuno-oncology (IO) Agents After Targeted Systemic Radiation in Patients With Advanced Esophagogastric Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Sidney Kimmel Comprehensive Cancer Center at Johns Hopkins</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Bristol-Myers Squibb</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Sidney Kimmel Comprehensive Cancer Center at Johns Hopkins</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a Phase 1B study assessing the safety of immune checkpoint inhibition after SBRT in
      patients with recurrent or metastatic gastroesophageal cancer (limited metastatic disease).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a Phase 1B study assessing the safety of immune checkpoint inhibition after SBRT in
      patients with recurrent or metastatic gastroesophageal cancer (limited metastatic disease).
      Arm A explores the safety and efficacy of nivolumab alone, and Arm B explores the safety and
      efficacy of nivolumab plus Relatlimib. Patients with recurrent or metastatic esophagogastric
      cancer are eligible for this study which will enroll patients with limited disease burden and
      who are Programmed death-1(PD-1) therapy naïve. This will allow for us to assess if systemic
      ablative radiation (SBRT to multiple metastatic sites plus PD-1/ anti-LAG3) is able to
      enhance the effectiveness of nivolumab +/- anti-LAG3 or to overcome treatment resistance
      mechanisms. Patients will be treated with targeted high dose radiation (SBRT) to metastatic
      lesions as outlined below. One of the lesions which is considered the easiest to biopsy and
      not causing symptoms will not be radiated so as to obtain tissue for correlative analysis.
      This lesion will then be re-biopsied approx. 4 weeks after the completion of radiation to the
      other metastatic sites. If a lesion is causing pain or other symptoms this site will not be
      chosen as the biopsiable site. The chosen metastatic lesion can then be irradiated at a later
      date if we do not see disease response in that region. Approximately 30 patients will be
      enrolled on study with 15 enrolled on Arm A, and 15 enrolled on Arm B.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 6, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Sequential Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in the infiltrating CD8+ T cell density units after systemic treatment with radiation plus nivolumab +/- Relatlimib</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Change in the infiltrating CD8+ T cell density units pre- and post-systemic treatment with radiation plus nivolumab +/- Relatlimib in the non-irradiated metastatic lesion.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety profile of nivolumab +/- Relatlimib plus systemic radiation as determined by number of drug-related adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Number of drug-related adverse events Grade 3 or higher as defined by CTCAE 5.0 (CTCAE v5.0).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Efficacy of PD-1 inhibition +/- Relatlimib as determined by number of participants without evidence of disease progression</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months post targeted radiation</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Gastroesophageal Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Immune Checkpoint Inhibition</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm A Nivolumab Only</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>stereotactic body radiation (SBRT) 8G x 3 followed by Nivolumab 240mg administered IV over 30 minutes every 2 weeks for one year or until evidence of disease progression or unresolved toxicity.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B Nivolumab + Relatlimab</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>stereotactic body radiation (SBRT) 8G x 3 followed by Nivolumab 240mg administered IV over 30 minutes every 2 weeks and Relatlimab (anti-LAG3) every 2 weeks for one year or until evidence of disease progression or unresolved toxicity.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Nivolumab</intervention_name>
    <description>240mg administered IV over 30 minutes every 2 weeks for one year</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm A Nivolumab Only</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B Nivolumab + Relatlimab</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Optivo</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Relatlimab</intervention_name>
    <description>every 2 weeks for one year</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B Nivolumab + Relatlimab</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>anti-LAG3</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Men and women aged ≥ 18 years old.

          -  Histologically proven (squamous cell or adenocarcinoma) esophageal or
             gastro-esophageal junction cancer or gastric cancer (core biopsy required)

          -  Either a formalin fixed paraffin block or a minimum of ten 5-micron tissue section's
             (slides) of tumor biopsy sample must be available for biomarker evaluation.

          -  Recurrent disease or Stage IV disease as per American Joint Committee on Cancer (AJCC)
             staging 8.0 - patients who decline systemic chemotherapy in the first line metastatic
             setting are eligible.

          -  (Relatlimab arm only) LVEF assessment with documented left ventricular ejection
             fraction ( LVEF) &gt;/=50% by either echocardiogram TTE or multigated acquisition scan
             (MUGA) (TTE preferred test) within 6 months from first study drug
             administration,whichever is most recent.

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status 0-1

          -  Adequate organ function as follows:

               -  Leukocytes ≥ 2,000/mm3

               -  Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) ≥ 1000/mm3

               -  Platelet count ≥ 100,000/mm3

               -  Hemoglobin ≥ 9 g/dL

               -  Creatinine ≤ 2.0 mg/dL

               -  Bilirubin (total) within normal institutional limits (except subjects with
                  Gilbert Syndrome who must have total bilirubin &lt; 3.0 mg/dL)

               -  Aspartate aminotransferase (AST) (SGOT), Alanine Aminotransferase (ALT) (SGPT),
                  and alkaline phosphatase ≤ 2.5 times the institutional upper limit of normal

               -  prothrombin time (PT) such that international normalized ratio (INR) is ≤ 1.5 (or
                  an in-range INR, usually between 2 and 3, if a patient is on a stable dose of
                  therapeutic warfarin) and a partial thromboplastin time (PTT) ≤ institutional
                  upper limit of normal

               -  Adequate cardiac function as defined by: no evidence of (PR) prolongation or
                  Atrioventricular block (AV block) on baseline electrocardiogram (ECG).

          -  The effects of nivolumab, relatlimab or BMS-986178, on the developing human fetus are
             unknown. For this reason women of child-bearing potential (WOCBP) and men must agree
             to use adequate contraception (hormonal or barrier method of birth control;
             abstinence) prior to study entry and for the duration of study participation and for 5
             months after the last dose of nivolumab +/- IO therapy. Should a woman become pregnant
             or suspect she is pregnant while she or her partner is participating in this study,
             she should inform her treating physician immediately. Sexually active fertile men must
             use effective barrier birth control if their partners are WOCBP for 7 months after the
             last dose of nivolumab +/- IO therapy. WOCBP must have a negative serum or urine
             pregnancy test (minimum sensitivity 25 IU/L or equivalent units of HCG) within two
             weeks of registration.

          -  Males who are sexually active with WOCBP must agree to follow instructions for
             method(s) of contraception (see Appendix 4) for the duration of treatment with study
             treatment(s) plus 33 weeks after the last dose of the study treatment (ie, 90 days
             [duration of sperm turnover] plus the time required for nivolumab and relatlimab to
             undergo approximately 5 half-lives). In addition, male participants must be willing to
             refrain from sperm donation during this time.

          -  Patient understands the study regimen, its requirements, risks and discomforts and is
             able and willing to sign the informed consent form. Voluntary signed and dated
             Institutional Review Board (IRB) approved written informed consent form in accordance
             with regulatory and institutional guidelines must be obtained before the performance
             of any protocol related procedures that are not part of normal patient care. Subjects
             must be competent to report Adverse Events (AEs), understand the drug dosing schedule
             and use of medications to control AEs.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Any active or history of autoimmune disease (including any history of inflammatory
             bowel disease), or history of syndrome that required systemic steroids or
             immune-suppressive medications, except for subjects with vitiligo or resolved
             childhood asthma/atopy.

          -  (Relatlimab arm only) Troponin T (TnT) or I (TnI) &gt; 2 × institutional upper limit of
             normal (ULN). Subjects with TnT or TnI levels between &gt; 1 to 2 × ULN will be permitted
             if repeat levels within 24 hours are ≤1 x ULN. If TnT or TnI levels are &gt; 1 to 2 × ULN
             within 24 hours, the subject may undergo a cardiac evaluation and be considered for
             treatment, following a discussion with the BMS Medical Monitor or designee. When
             repeat levels within 24 hours are not available, a repeat test should be conducted as
             soon as possible. If TnT or TnI repeat levels beyond 24 hours are &lt; 2 x ULN, the
             subject may undergo a cardiac evaluation and be considered for treatment, following a
             discussion with the Bristol Myers Squibb (BMS) Medical Monitor or designee.

          -  (Relatlimab arm only) Participants must not have a history of myocarditis

          -  (Relatlimab arm only) Uncontrolled or significant cardiovascular disease including,
             but not limited to, any of the following:

          -  Myocardial infarction (MI) or stroke/transient ischemic attack (TIA) within the 6
             months prior to consent

          -  Uncontrolled angina within the 3 months prior to consent

          -  Any history of clinically significant arrhythmias (such as ventricular tachycardia,
             poorly controlled atrial fibrillation, ventricular fibrillation, or torsades de
             pointes)

          -  Corrected QT interval (QTc) prolongation &gt; 480 msec

          -  History of other clinically significant cardiovascular disease (i.e., cardiomyopathy,
             congestive heart failure with New York Heart Association (NYHA) functional
             classification III-IV, pericarditis, significant pericardial effusion, significant
             coronary stent occlusion, , poorly controlled venous thrombosis etc.)

          -  Cardiovascular disease-related requirement for daily supplemental oxygen

          -  History of two or more MIs OR two or more coronary revascularization procedures

          -  (Relatlimab arm only) LVEF (Left Ventricular Ejection Fraction) assessment with
             documented LVEF ≥ 50% by either TTE or MUGA (TTE preferred test) within 6 months from
             first study drug administration.

          -  Ongoing requirement for systemic corticosteroids. However, inhalational steroids are
             allowed.

          -  Subjects with previous malignancies (except non-melanoma skin cancers, in situ
             bladder, gastric, breast, colon or cervical cancers/dysplasia) are excluded unless a
             complete remission was achieved at least 2 years prior to study entry and no
             additional therapy is required or anticipated to be required during the study period.

          -  Subjects with known brain metastasis are excluded from this study. Patients with
             suspected brain metastasis must have brain imaging (either MRI brain or CT brain with
             contrast) prior to enrollment.

          -  Subjects with a history of interstitial lung disease. Patients requiring continuous
             supplemental oxygen are excluded.

          -  Use of any vaccines against infectious diseases (e.g., influenza, varicella. etc.)
             within 4 weeks (28 days) of initiation of study therapy.

          -  Active systemic infection requiring therapy, positive tests for Hepatitis B surface
             antigen or Hepatitis C ribonucleic acid (RNA).

          -  Known positive history or positive test for Human Immunodeficiency Virus or Acquired
             ImmunoDeficiency Syndrome (AIDS).

          -  History of allergy to study drug components.

          -  Women who are pregnant or nursing.

          -  Men with female partners (WOCBP) that are not willing to use contraception

          -  Underlying medical conditions that, in the Investigator's opinion, will make the
             administration of study drug or radiation hazardous or obscure the interpretation of
             toxicity or adverse events.

          -  Prior therapy with an anti-programmed death-1 (anti-PD-1), anti-programmed death
             ligand-1 (anti-PD-L1), Anti-programmed cell death 1 ligand 2 (anti-PDL-2), or
             Anti-Cytotoxic T-lymphocyte antigen 4 (anti-CTLA-4) antibody (or any other antibody
             targeting T cell co-regulatory pathways).

          -  Prisoners or subjects who are involuntarily incarcerated or compulsorily detained for
             treatment of either a psychiatric or physical (e.g. infectious disease) illness.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>99 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Vincent Lam, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Johns Hopkins University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Vincent Lam, MD</last_name>
    <phone>410-550-5358</phone>
    <email>vklam@jhmi.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Heather Schneider, BS</last_name>
    <phone>410-502-0984</phone>
    <email>hschne12@jhmi.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Johns Hopkins University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21287</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Vincent Lam, MD</last_name>
      <phone>410-550-5358</phone>
      <email>vklam@jhmi.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Heather Schneider, BS</last_name>
      <phone>410-502-0984</phone>
      <email>hschne12@jhmi.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Russell Hales, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Rahn Voong, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Richard Battafarano, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Stephen Yang, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Josephine Feliciano, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Vincent Lam, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Alleghany Health Network</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pittsburgh</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>15212</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Blaire Job, MD</last_name>
      <email>bjobe1@wpahs.org</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Ali Zaidi, MD</last_name>
      <email>ali.zaidi@ahn.org</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Blaire Job, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>G. Scott Long, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ali Amjad, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Casey Moffa, DO</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Mohammed Islam, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Gene Finley, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Hashem Youned, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Moses Raj, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ali Zaidi, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Baylor University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dallas</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>75246</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ronan Kelly, MD</last_name>
      <phone>214-820-2881</phone>
      <email>Ronan.Kelly@BSWHealth.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Andrew S Paulson, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Andrew D McCollum, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ronan Kelly, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kang YK, Boku N, Satoh T, Ryu MH, Chao Y, Kato K, Chung HC, Chen JS, Muro K, Kang WK, Yeh KH, Yoshikawa T, Oh SC, Bai LY, Tamura T, Lee KW, Hamamoto Y, Kim JG, Chin K, Oh DY, Minashi K, Cho JY, Tsuda M, Chen LT. Nivolumab in patients with advanced gastric or gastro-oesophageal junction cancer refractory to, or intolerant of, at least two previous chemotherapy regimens (ONO-4538-12, ATTRACTION-2): a randomised, double-blind, placebo-controlled, phase 3 trial. Lancet. 2017 Dec 2;390(10111):2461-2471. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(17)31827-5. Epub 2017 Oct 6.</citation>
    <PMID>28993052</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Le DT, Uram JN, Wang H, Bartlett BR, Kemberling H, Eyring AD, Skora AD, Luber BS, Azad NS, Laheru D, Biedrzycki B, Donehower RC, Zaheer A, Fisher GA, Crocenzi TS, Lee JJ, Duffy SM, Goldberg RM, de la Chapelle A, Koshiji M, Bhaijee F, Huebner T, Hruban RH, Wood LD, Cuka N, Pardoll DM, Papadopoulos N, Kinzler KW, Zhou S, Cornish TC, Taube JM, Anders RA, Eshleman JR, Vogelstein B, Diaz LA Jr. PD-1 Blockade in Tumors with Mismatch-Repair Deficiency. N Engl J Med. 2015 Jun 25;372(26):2509-20. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa1500596. Epub 2015 May 30.</citation>
    <PMID>26028255</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cancer Genome Atlas Research Network. Comprehensive molecular characterization of gastric adenocarcinoma. Nature. 2014 Sep 11;513(7517):202-9. doi: 10.1038/nature13480. Epub 2014 Jul 23.</citation>
    <PMID>25079317</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Spranger S, Spaapen RM, Zha Y, Williams J, Meng Y, Ha TT, Gajewski TF. Up-regulation of PD-L1, IDO, and T(regs) in the melanoma tumor microenvironment is driven by CD8(+) T cells. Sci Transl Med. 2013 Aug 28;5(200):200ra116. doi: 10.1126/scitranslmed.3006504.</citation>
    <PMID>23986400</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Thompson ED, Zahurak M, Murphy A, Cornish T, Cuka N, Abdelfatah E, Yang S, Duncan M, Ahuja N, Taube JM, Anders RA, Kelly RJ. Patterns of PD-L1 expression and CD8 T cell infiltration in gastric adenocarcinomas and associated immune stroma. Gut. 2017 May;66(5):794-801. doi: 10.1136/gutjnl-2015-310839. Epub 2016 Jan 22.</citation>
    <PMID>26801886</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Derks S, Nason KS, Liao X, Stachler MD, Liu KX, Liu JB, Sicinska E, Goldberg MS, Freeman GJ, Rodig SJ, Davison JM, Bass AJ. Epithelial PD-L2 Expression Marks Barrett's Esophagus and Esophageal Adenocarcinoma. Cancer Immunol Res. 2015 Oct;3(10):1123-1129. doi: 10.1158/2326-6066.CIR-15-0046. Epub 2015 Jun 16.</citation>
    <PMID>26081225</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Muro K, Chung HC, Shankaran V, Geva R, Catenacci D, Gupta S, Eder JP, Golan T, Le DT, Burtness B, McRee AJ, Lin CC, Pathiraja K, Lunceford J, Emancipator K, Juco J, Koshiji M, Bang YJ. Pembrolizumab for patients with PD-L1-positive advanced gastric cancer (KEYNOTE-012): a multicentre, open-label, phase 1b trial. Lancet Oncol. 2016 Jun;17(6):717-726. doi: 10.1016/S1470-2045(16)00175-3. Epub 2016 May 3.</citation>
    <PMID>27157491</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Derks S, Liao X, Chiaravalli AM, Xu X, Camargo MC, Solcia E, Sessa F, Fleitas T, Freeman GJ, Rodig SJ, Rabkin CS, Bass AJ. Abundant PD-L1 expression in Epstein-Barr Virus-infected gastric cancers. Oncotarget. 2016 May 31;7(22):32925-32. doi: 10.18632/oncotarget.9076.</citation>
    <PMID>27147580</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>McGranahan N, Furness AJ, Rosenthal R, Ramskov S, Lyngaa R, Saini SK, Jamal-Hanjani M, Wilson GA, Birkbak NJ, Hiley CT, Watkins TB, Shafi S, Murugaesu N, Mitter R, Akarca AU, Linares J, Marafioti T, Henry JY, Van Allen EM, Miao D, Schilling B, Schadendorf D, Garraway LA, Makarov V, Rizvi NA, Snyder A, Hellmann MD, Merghoub T, Wolchok JD, Shukla SA, Wu CJ, Peggs KS, Chan TA, Hadrup SR, Quezada SA, Swanton C. Clonal neoantigens elicit T cell immunoreactivity and sensitivity to immune checkpoint blockade. Science. 2016 Mar 25;351(6280):1463-9. doi: 10.1126/science.aaf1490. Epub 2016 Mar 3.</citation>
    <PMID>26940869</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Attwood SE, Smyrk TC, DeMeester TR, Mirvish SS, Stein HJ, Hinder RA. Duodenoesophageal reflux and the development of esophageal adenocarcinoma in rats. Surgery. 1992 May;111(5):503-10.</citation>
    <PMID>1598670</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Llosa NJ, Cruise M, Tam A, Wicks EC, Hechenbleikner EM, Taube JM, Blosser RL, Fan H, Wang H, Luber BS, Zhang M, Papadopoulos N, Kinzler KW, Vogelstein B, Sears CL, Anders RA, Pardoll DM, Housseau F. The vigorous immune microenvironment of microsatellite instable colon cancer is balanced by multiple counter-inhibitory checkpoints. Cancer Discov. 2015 Jan;5(1):43-51. doi: 10.1158/2159-8290.CD-14-0863. Epub 2014 Oct 30.</citation>
    <PMID>25358689</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pera M, Brito MJ, Poulsom R, Riera E, Grande L, Hanby A, Wright NA. Duodenal-content reflux esophagitis induces the development of glandular metaplasia and adenosquamous carcinoma in rats. Carcinogenesis. 2000 Aug;21(8):1587-91.</citation>
    <PMID>10910963</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zaidi AH, Saldin LT, Kelly LA, Bergal L, Londono R, Kosovec JE, Komatsu Y, Kasi PM, Shetty AA, Keane TJ, Thakkar SJ, Huleihel L, Landreneau RJ, Badylak SF, Jobe BA. MicroRNA signature characterizes primary tumors that metastasize in an esophageal adenocarcinoma rat model. PLoS One. 2015 Mar 31;10(3):e0122375. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0122375. eCollection 2015.</citation>
    <PMID>25826212</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bonde P, Sui G, Dhara S, Wang J, Broor A, Kim IF, Wiley JE, Marti G, Duncan M, Jaffee E, Montgomery E, Maitra A, Harmon JW. Cytogenetic characterization and gene expression profiling in the rat reflux-induced esophageal tumor model. J Thorac Cardiovasc Surg. 2007 Mar;133(3):763-9.</citation>
    <PMID>17320581</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gibson MK, Zaidi AH, Davison JM, Sanz AF, Hough B, Komatsu Y, Kosovec JE, Bhatt A, Malhotra U, Foxwell T, Rotoloni CL, Hoppo T, Jobe BA. Prevention of Barrett esophagus and esophageal adenocarcinoma by smoothened inhibitor in a rat model of gastroesophageal reflux disease. Ann Surg. 2013 Jul;258(1):82-8. doi: 10.1097/SLA.0b013e318270500d.</citation>
    <PMID>23108119</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kosovec JE, Zaidi AH, Kelly LA, Rotoloni CL, Vytlacil C, DiCarlo C, Matsui D, Komatsu Y, Boyd NH, Omstead A, Kolano EL, Biederman RW, Finley G, Silverman JF, Landreneau RJ, Jobe BA. Preclinical Study of AUY922, a Novel Hsp90 Inhibitor, in the Treatment of Esophageal Adenocarcinoma. Ann Surg. 2016 Aug;264(2):297-304. doi: 10.1097/SLA.0000000000001467.</citation>
    <PMID>26445473</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zaidi AH, Kosovec JE, Matsui D, Omstead AN, Raj M, Rao RR, Biederman RWW, Finley GG, Landreneau RJ, Kelly RJ, Jobe BA. PI3K/mTOR Dual Inhibitor, LY3023414, Demonstrates Potent Antitumor Efficacy Against Esophageal Adenocarcinoma in a Rat Model. Ann Surg. 2017 Jul;266(1):91-98. doi: 10.1097/SLA.0000000000001908.</citation>
    <PMID>27471841</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Miyashita T, Shah FA, Marti G, Wang J, Armstrong T, Bonde P, Gibson MK, Yoshimura K, Montgomery EA, Duncan MD, Jaffee EM, Harmon JW. Vaccine impedes the development of reflux-induced esophageal cancer in a surgical rat model: efficacy of the vaccine in a Pre-Barrett's esophagus setting. J Gastrointest Surg. 2008 Jan;12(1):2-7; discussion 7-9. Epub 2007 Oct 24.</citation>
    <PMID>17957441</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kelly RJ, Zaidi AH, Smith MA, Omstead AN, Kosovec JE, Matsui D, Martin SA, DiCarlo C, Werts ED, Silverman JF, Wang DH, Jobe BA. The Dynamic and Transient Immune Microenvironment in Locally Advanced Esophageal Adenocarcinoma Post Chemoradiation. Ann Surg. 2018 Dec;268(6):992-999. doi: 10.1097/SLA.0000000000002410.</citation>
    <PMID>28806299</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Borghaei H, Paz-Ares L, Horn L, Spigel DR, Steins M, Ready NE, Chow LQ, Vokes EE, Felip E, Holgado E, Barlesi F, Kohlhäufl M, Arrieta O, Burgio MA, Fayette J, Lena H, Poddubskaya E, Gerber DE, Gettinger SN, Rudin CM, Rizvi N, Crinò L, Blumenschein GR Jr, Antonia SJ, Dorange C, Harbison CT, Graf Finckenstein F, Brahmer JR. Nivolumab versus Docetaxel in Advanced Nonsquamous Non-Small-Cell Lung Cancer. N Engl J Med. 2015 Oct 22;373(17):1627-39. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa1507643. Epub 2015 Sep 27.</citation>
    <PMID>26412456</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Brahmer J, Reckamp KL, Baas P, Crinò L, Eberhardt WE, Poddubskaya E, Antonia S, Pluzanski A, Vokes EE, Holgado E, Waterhouse D, Ready N, Gainor J, Arén Frontera O, Havel L, Steins M, Garassino MC, Aerts JG, Domine M, Paz-Ares L, Reck M, Baudelet C, Harbison CT, Lestini B, Spigel DR. Nivolumab versus Docetaxel in Advanced Squamous-Cell Non-Small-Cell Lung Cancer. N Engl J Med. 2015 Jul 9;373(2):123-35. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa1504627. Epub 2015 May 31.</citation>
    <PMID>26028407</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Herbst RS, Baas P, Kim DW, Felip E, Pérez-Gracia JL, Han JY, Molina J, Kim JH, Arvis CD, Ahn MJ, Majem M, Fidler MJ, de Castro G Jr, Garrido M, Lubiniecki GM, Shentu Y, Im E, Dolled-Filhart M, Garon EB. Pembrolizumab versus docetaxel for previously treated, PD-L1-positive, advanced non-small-cell lung cancer (KEYNOTE-010): a randomised controlled trial. Lancet. 2016 Apr 9;387(10027):1540-1550. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(15)01281-7. Epub 2015 Dec 19.</citation>
    <PMID>26712084</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rittmeyer A, Barlesi F, Waterkamp D, Park K, Ciardiello F, von Pawel J, Gadgeel SM, Hida T, Kowalski DM, Dols MC, Cortinovis DL, Leach J, Polikoff J, Barrios C, Kabbinavar F, Frontera OA, De Marinis F, Turna H, Lee JS, Ballinger M, Kowanetz M, He P, Chen DS, Sandler A, Gandara DR; OAK Study Group. Atezolizumab versus docetaxel in patients with previously treated non-small-cell lung cancer (OAK): a phase 3, open-label, multicentre randomised controlled trial. Lancet. 2017 Jan 21;389(10066):255-265. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(16)32517-X. Epub 2016 Dec 13. Erratum in: Lancet. 2017 Apr 8;389(10077):e5.</citation>
    <PMID>27979383</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Finkelstein SE, Timmerman R, McBride WH, Schaue D, Hoffe SE, Mantz CA, Wilson GD. The confluence of stereotactic ablative radiotherapy and tumor immunology. Clin Dev Immunol. 2011;2011:439752. doi: 10.1155/2011/439752. Epub 2011 Nov 15. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22162711</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wang X, Schoenhals JE, Li A, Valdecanas DR, Ye H, Zang F, Tang C, Tang M, Liu CG, Liu X, Krishnan S, Allison JP, Sharma P, Hwu P, Komaki R, Overwijk WW, Gomez DR, Chang JY, Hahn SM, Cortez MA, Welsh JW. Suppression of Type I IFN Signaling in Tumors Mediates Resistance to Anti-PD-1 Treatment That Can Be Overcome by Radiotherapy. Cancer Res. 2017 Feb 15;77(4):839-850. doi: 10.1158/0008-5472.CAN-15-3142. Epub 2016 Nov 7.</citation>
    <PMID>27821490</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gomez DR, Blumenschein GR Jr, Lee JJ, Hernandez M, Ye R, Camidge DR, Doebele RC, Skoulidis F, Gaspar LE, Gibbons DL, Karam JA, Kavanagh BD, Tang C, Komaki R, Louie AV, Palma DA, Tsao AS, Sepesi B, William WN, Zhang J, Shi Q, Wang XS, Swisher SG, Heymach JV. Local consolidative therapy versus maintenance therapy or observation for patients with oligometastatic non-small-cell lung cancer without progression after first-line systemic therapy: a multicentre, randomised, controlled, phase 2 study. Lancet Oncol. 2016 Dec;17(12):1672-1682. doi: 10.1016/S1470-2045(16)30532-0. Epub 2016 Oct 24.</citation>
    <PMID>27789196</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wong J, Armour E, Kazanzides P, Iordachita I, Tryggestad E, Deng H, Matinfar M, Kennedy C, Liu Z, Chan T, Gray O, Verhaegen F, McNutt T, Ford E, DeWeese TL. High-resolution, small animal radiation research platform with x-ray tomographic guidance capabilities. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys. 2008 Aug 1;71(5):1591-9. doi: 10.1016/j.ijrobp.2008.04.025.</citation>
    <PMID>18640502</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Demaria S, Golden EB, Formenti SC. Role of Local Radiation Therapy in Cancer Immunotherapy. JAMA Oncol. 2015 Dec;1(9):1325-32. doi: 10.1001/jamaoncol.2015.2756. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26270858</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Golden EB, Chhabra A, Chachoua A, Adams S, Donach M, Fenton-Kerimian M, Friedman K, Ponzo F, Babb JS, Goldberg J, Demaria S, Formenti SC. Local radiotherapy and granulocyte-macrophage colony-stimulating factor to generate abscopal responses in patients with metastatic solid tumours: a proof-of-principle trial. Lancet Oncol. 2015 Jul;16(7):795-803. doi: 10.1016/S1470-2045(15)00054-6. Epub 2015 Jun 18.</citation>
    <PMID>26095785</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Twyman-Saint Victor C, Rech AJ, Maity A, Rengan R, Pauken KE, Stelekati E, Benci JL, Xu B, Dada H, Odorizzi PM, Herati RS, Mansfield KD, Patsch D, Amaravadi RK, Schuchter LM, Ishwaran H, Mick R, Pryma DA, Xu X, Feldman MD, Gangadhar TC, Hahn SM, Wherry EJ, Vonderheide RH, Minn AJ. Radiation and dual checkpoint blockade activate non-redundant immune mechanisms in cancer. Nature. 2015 Apr 16;520(7547):373-7. doi: 10.1038/nature14292. Epub 2015 Mar 9.</citation>
    <PMID>25754329</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sun J, Dirden-Kramer B, Ito K, Ernst PB, Van Houten N. Antigen-specific T cell activation and proliferation during oral tolerance induction. J Immunol. 1999 May 15;162(10):5868-75.</citation>
    <PMID>10229822</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Carlson CS, Emerson RO, Sherwood AM, Desmarais C, Chung MW, Parsons JM, Steen MS, LaMadrid-Herrmannsfeldt MA, Williamson DW, Livingston RJ, Wu D, Wood BL, Rieder MJ, Robins H. Using synthetic templates to design an unbiased multiplex PCR assay. Nat Commun. 2013;4:2680. doi: 10.1038/ncomms3680.</citation>
    <PMID>24157944</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Robins HS, Campregher PV, Srivastava SK, Wacher A, Turtle CJ, Kahsai O, Riddell SR, Warren EH, Carlson CS. Comprehensive assessment of T-cell receptor beta-chain diversity in alphabeta T cells. Blood. 2009 Nov 5;114(19):4099-107. doi: 10.1182/blood-2009-04-217604. Epub 2009 Aug 25.</citation>
    <PMID>19706884</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Anagnostou V, Smith KN, Forde PM, Niknafs N, Bhattacharya R, White J, Zhang T, Adleff V, Phallen J, Wali N, Hruban C, Guthrie VB, Rodgers K, Naidoo J, Kang H, Sharfman W, Georgiades C, Verde F, Illei P, Li QK, Gabrielson E, Brock MV, Zahnow CA, Baylin SB, Scharpf RB, Brahmer JR, Karchin R, Pardoll DM, Velculescu VE. Evolution of Neoantigen Landscape during Immune Checkpoint Blockade in Non-Small Cell Lung Cancer. Cancer Discov. 2017 Mar;7(3):264-276. doi: 10.1158/2159-8290.CD-16-0828. Epub 2016 Dec 28.</citation>
    <PMID>28031159</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 26, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 26, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 1, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 1, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 1, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 4, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Nivolumab</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

