<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03617757</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>UW17-429</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03617757</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Progression From Impaired Fasting Glucose to Diabetes Mellitus Among Chinese</brief_title>
  <official_title>Determinants of Progression From Impaired Fasting Glucose to Diabetes Mellitus Among Chinese - a 3-year Follow up Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>The University of Hong Kong</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Chinese University of Hong Kong</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>The University of Hong Kong</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Impaired fasting glucose (IFG), a significant risk factor for diabetes mellitus (DM), is
      commonly encountered in the primary care setting and represents an important target for DM
      prevention. However, data on the long term risk of progression from IFG to DM among Chinese
      subjects and associated risk factors are currently lacking; appropriate DM prevention
      programme for this group cannot be yet established.

      This is a prospective cohort study that aims to estimate the incidence of progression to
      diabetes mellitus (DM) among Chinese primary care patients with impaired fasting glucose
      (IFG) over a 3-year period and evaluate putative risk factors. A prospective cohort of around
      700 non-diabetic Chinese adults who had IFG (i.e. fasting glucose level between 5.6 to
      6.9mmol/L) and received baseline assessment between May 2013 and March 2015 at 3 public
      primary care clinics across Hong Kong will be invited for a 36-month-follow-up glycaemic
      status assessment (i.e. to repeat 75-gram oral glucose tolerance test (OGTT) and HbA1c test).
      The OGTT results will be used as the gold standard for the diagnosis of DM, normoglycaemia,
      IFG and impaired glucose tolerance (IGT) state. Demographics and lifestyle of the subjects
      including age, gender, occupation, education level, socio-economic status, smoking and
      drinking history, diet, exercise, work-sleep pattern, stress, quality of life and family
      history will be collected using standardized questionnaire. Participant's medical history and
      drug history will be retrieved from the Clinical Management System (CMS) of the Hospital
      Authority. Lipid profile, blood pressure, waist circumference and body mass index will also
      be assessed.

      Logistic regression model will be performed to determine if these variables are associated
      with progression from IFG to DM. The primary outcome is the incidence of DM among the IFG
      study population. The secondary outcomes are the risks of developing DM among subjects with
      isolated IFG or combined IFG/IGT and determinants of progression to DM.

      Knowledge on the natural history of isolated IFG or combined IFG/IGT among Hong Kong Chinese
      primary care patients and the significant modifiable associated risk factors for progression
      to DM will enable primary care researchers to design optimal management programme for
      diabetes prevention among these high risk patients.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Impaired fasting glucose (IFG) represent an intermediate state of abnormal glucose regulation
      that exist between normal glucose homeostasis and diabetes mellitus (DM) and is a significant
      risk factor for DM and cardiovascular complications. IFG is defined by an elevated FG level
      between 6.1-6.9mmol/L according to the World Health Organization (WHO). The lower cutoff
      level for IFG was further lowered to 5.6mmol/L by the American Diabetes Association (ADA) in
      2003 in order to maximize sensitivity and specificity for predicting DM over a 5-year period.
      In Hong Kong, IFG individuals can be more readily identified by primary care doctors than
      subjects with impaired glucose tolerance (IGT) or elevated HbA1c - the other 2 pre-diabetic
      categories - because fasting glucose (FG) test is recommended by the Hong Kong reference
      framework for diabetes care for adults in primary care setting for DM screening. Thus, this
      group of individuals should be targeted opportunistically for DM prevention.

      On the other hand, IFG is a heterogeneous group with variable risk of progression to DM.
      Individuals with IFG may have concomitant IGT, elevated HbA1c or even DM. Thomas et al. found
      that around 20% of Hong Kong Chinese subjects with impaired glucose relation had concomitant
      IFG and IGT, whereas 49.5% had isolated IGT and 30.5% had isolated IFG. Ko et al. followed up
      55 Chinese subjects with IFG for a median period of 1.12 year and showed that 8.4% progressed
      to DM annually as defined by fasting glucose criteria (FG ≥7.0mmol.L). Lee et al. followed up
      238 Chinese women with persistent impaired glucose tolerance after gestational diabetes over
      a mean period of 52 months and found that 20% of the studied population developed diabetes
      mellitus based on OGTT criteria; the highest rate of progression to DM was noted among those
      women with concomitant postpartum impaired fasting glucose.

      A recent cross-sectional study by Yu et al on 1,200 Chinese primary care patients with IFG
      demonstrated that 20% had DM confirmed by OGTT as the gold diagnostic standard, 14.3% had
      concomitant IGT, and 16.1% would regress back to normoglycaemia upon retest within 18 months.
      However, all of these local studies had short follow-up period and used different diagnostic
      tests for confirmation of DM; the long term risk of progression to DM among Chinese subjects
      with isolated IFG or combined IFG-IGT had not been fully evaluated.

      Moreover, only few studies examined the risk factors for progression from IFG (+/- IGT) to DM
      among Asians or Chinese. Female gender, smoking, low physical activity, obesity as well as
      truncal obesity, high blood pressure, high triglyceridaemia and most importantly higher
      baseline FG level had all been reported to increase risk of progression from IFG to DM among
      Caucasians. In the only Asian study conducted in Japan, Toshihiro et al. found that stress in
      daily life, night duty and administrative position were risk factors of DM development among
      IFG subjects. To the best of our knowledge, no published data on the risk factors of
      progression from IFG to DM among Chinese is currently available. It was not certain that the
      risk factors identified among the Caucasians or Japanese were applicable to the Chinese.
      Although intensive lifestyle modifications targeting these risk factors had been reported to
      reduce progression from IFG to DM, their effects on Chinese subjects with IFG had not been
      evaluated.

      Between May 2013 and March 2015, our team have already collected a prospective cohort of
      around 700 non-diabetic adults who have underwent both 75g OGTT and HbA1c tests as rigorous
      determination of their glycemic status. We aim to conduct a 3-year follow-up study to
      estimate the incidence of progression to DM among Hong Kong Chinese primary care patients
      with IFG with or without concomitant IGT using OGTT as the gold diagnostic standard as
      recommended by the Hong Kong Reference Framework. In addition, we aim to identify
      determinants, in particular the modifiable risk factors, for the progression from IFG to DM.
      These results will provide valuable information for designing optimal follow-up plan and
      diabetes prevention programme for local IFG patients, with the ultimate goal to reduce health
      care burden of DM on our society.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 1, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">January 22, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">January 22, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Prospective and Cohort study (Compare different cohorts)</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Health Services Research</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of DM</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline</time_frame>
    <description>the incidence of DM among Chinese primary care patients with impaired fasting glucose (including isolated IFG or combined IFG / IGT)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of regression to normoglycaemia among the studied population</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Family history as risk factor associated with progression to DM</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline</time_frame>
    <description>measured by questionnaire: ask if any direct relatives have the history of DM</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Smoking habit as risk factor associated with progression to DM</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline</time_frame>
    <description>measured by questionnaire: ask if participant is non-smoker, current smoker or ex-smoker</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Drinking habit as risk factor associated with progression to DM</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline</time_frame>
    <description>measured by questionnaire: ask if participant is non-drinker, social drinker, chronic drinker or ex-drinker</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Stress level as risk factor associated with progression to DM</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline</time_frame>
    <description>measured by questionnaire: Depression Anxiety Stress Scales (DASS) - 7 Stress Scales only</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Stress level as risk factor associated with progression to DM</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline</time_frame>
    <description>measured by questionnaire: Perceived Stress Scale (PSS-10)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Eating habit as risk factor associated with progression to DM</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline</time_frame>
    <description>measured by diet questionnaire</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Sleep quality as risk factor associated with progression to DM</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline</time_frame>
    <description>measured by questionnaire Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index (PSQI)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Exercises frequency as determinant of regression to normoglycaemia</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline</time_frame>
    <description>measured by International Physical Activity Questionnaire (IPAQ) - short form</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Diet as determinant of regression to normoglycaemia</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline</time_frame>
    <description>measured by diet questionnaire</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Sleep quality as determinants of regression to normoglycaemia</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline</time_frame>
    <description>measured by Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index (PSQI)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Waist circumferences as determinants of regression to normoglycaemia</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Prevalence of depression among subjects with IFG</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline</time_frame>
    <description>measured by Patient Health Questionnaire (PHQ-2)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Health related Quality of Life of subjects with IFG</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline</time_frame>
    <description>measured by questionnaire: SF12 Health Survey version 2</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Capacity of the studied population to join intensive lifestyle intervention</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline</time_frame>
    <description>by questionnaire: history of joining exercise classes or conducting diet control with dietitians</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">386</enrollment>
  <condition>Progression From Impaired Fasting Glucose to Diabetes Mellitus</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>All recruited patients</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Blood taking procedure, oral glucose tolerance test and questionnaire will be included.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Oral Glucose Tolerance Test</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients will be invited to have oral glucose tolerance test. 2mL blood will be taken for analysis at 0 minute and 120 minutes.</description>
    <arm_group_label>All recruited patients</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>HbA1c</intervention_name>
    <description>2mL blood will be taken for analysis of HbA1c.</description>
    <arm_group_label>All recruited patients</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Aged ≥ 18 year

          2. Chinese ethnicity

          3. Diagnosis of impaired fasting glucose (i.e. FG between 5.6-6.9mmol/L) +/- impaired
             glucose tolerance (i.e. 2-hour postprandial PG between 7.8-11.0mmol/L) confirmed by
             latest OGTT results within 60 months prior to recruitment

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Confirmed diagnosis of DM or on hypoglycaemic treatment

          -  Women who are pregnant or breast-feeding at recruitment

          -  Patients taking glucocorticoid at recruitment

          -  Active and uncontrolled thyroid diseases (including subjects on thyroid replacement
             therapy or anti-thyroid drugs) or active endocrine diseases such as Cushing's syndrome
             or Acromegaly at recruitment

          -  Severe renal impairment i.e. eGFR ≤ 30 ml/min/1.73m2

          -  Clinically significant anaemia at recruitment

          -  History of blood donation or blood transfusion within 3 months prior to recruitment
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Tsan Yuk Hospital RAMP Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hong Kong</city>
        <zip>852</zip>
        <country>Hong Kong</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ap Lei Chau General Out-patient Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hong Kong</city>
        <country>Hong Kong</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Lek Yuen General Out-patient Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hong Kong</city>
        <country>Hong Kong</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Hong Kong</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>World Health Organization, Definition and diagnosis of diabetes mellitus and intermediate hyperglycaemia. 2006, World Health Organization: Geneva.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nathan DM, Davidson MB, DeFronzo RA, Heine RJ, Henry RR, Pratley R, Zinman B; American Diabetes Association. Impaired fasting glucose and impaired glucose tolerance: implications for care. Diabetes Care. 2007 Mar;30(3):753-9. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>17327355</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Genuth S, Alberti KG, Bennett P, Buse J, Defronzo R, Kahn R, Kitzmiller J, Knowler WC, Lebovitz H, Lernmark A, Nathan D, Palmer J, Rizza R, Saudek C, Shaw J, Steffes M, Stern M, Tuomilehto J, Zimmet P; Expert Committee on the Diagnosis and Classification of Diabetes Mellitus. Follow-up report on the diagnosis of diabetes mellitus. Diabetes Care. 2003 Nov;26(11):3160-7. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>14578255</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Task Force on Conceptual Model and Preventive Protocols, Hong Kong reference framework for diabetes care for adults in primary care settings. 2013: Hong Kong.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Thomas GN, Schooling CM, McGhee SM, Ho SY, Cheung BM, Wat NM, Janus ED, Lam TH; Hong Kong Cardiovascular Risk Factor Prevalence Study Steering Committee. Identification of factors differentially associated with isolated impaired fasting glucose and isolated post-load impaired glucose tolerance: the Hong Kong Cardiovascular Risk Factor Study. Eur J Endocrinol. 2006 Oct;155(4):623-32.</citation>
    <PMID>16990663</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ko GT, Chan JC, Cockram CS. Change of glycaemic status in Chinese subjects with impaired fasting glycaemia. Diabet Med. 2001 Sep;18(9):745-8.</citation>
    <PMID>11606173</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lee KF, Mak MW, Lau KO, Chung H. Risk of development of diabetes mellitus in Chinese women with persistently impaired glucose tolerance after gestational diabetes. Hong Kong Med J. 2011 Jun;17(3):195-201.</citation>
    <PMID>21636867</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yu EY, Wong CK, Ho SY, Wong SY, Lam CL. Can HbA1c replace OGTT for the diagnosis of diabetes mellitus among Chinese patients with impaired fasting glucose? Fam Pract. 2015 Dec;32(6):631-8. doi: 10.1093/fampra/cmv077. Epub 2015 Oct 14.</citation>
    <PMID>26467644</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rasmussen SS, Glümer C, Sandbaek A, Lauritzen T, Borch-Johnsen K. Determinants of progression from impaired fasting glucose and impaired glucose tolerance to diabetes in a high-risk screened population: 3 year follow-up in the ADDITION study, Denmark. Diabetologia. 2008 Feb;51(2):249-57. Epub 2007 Dec 5.</citation>
    <PMID>18060659</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Leiva E, Mujica V, Orrego R, Wehinger S, Soto A, Icaza G, Vásquez M, Díaz L, Andrews M, Arredondo M. Subjects with impaired fasting glucose: evolution in a period of 6 years. J Diabetes Res. 2014;2014:710370. doi: 10.1155/2014/710370. Epub 2014 Aug 20.</citation>
    <PMID>25215305</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nichols GA, Hillier TA, Brown JB. Progression from newly acquired impaired fasting glusose to type 2 diabetes. Diabetes Care. 2007 Feb;30(2):228-33. Erratum in: Diabetes Care. 2008 Dec;31(12):2414.</citation>
    <PMID>17259486</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sharifi F, Jaberi Y, Mirzamohammadi F, Mirzamohammadi H, Mousavinasab N. Determinants of developing diabetes mellitus and vascular complications in patients with impaired fasting glucose. Indian J Endocrinol Metab. 2013 Sep;17(5):899-905. doi: 10.4103/2230-8210.117240.</citation>
    <PMID>24083174</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Toshihiro M, Saito K, Takikawa S, Takebe N, Onoda T, Satoh J. Psychosocial factors are independent risk factors for the development of Type 2 diabetes in Japanese workers with impaired fasting glucose and/or impaired glucose tolerance. Diabet Med. 2008 Oct;25(10):1211-7. doi: 10.1111/j.1464-5491.2008.02566.x.</citation>
    <PMID>19046200</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Knowler WC, Barrett-Connor E, Fowler SE, Hamman RF, Lachin JM, Walker EA, Nathan DM; Diabetes Prevention Program Research Group. Reduction in the incidence of type 2 diabetes with lifestyle intervention or metformin. N Engl J Med. 2002 Feb 7;346(6):393-403.</citation>
    <PMID>11832527</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 26, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 3, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 6, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 3, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 3, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 6, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>The University of Hong Kong</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Dr. YU Yee Yak, Esther</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Clinical Assistant Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Chinese</keyword>
  <keyword>Diabetes Mellitus</keyword>
  <keyword>Impaired fasting glucose</keyword>
  <keyword>Incidence</keyword>
  <keyword>Progression</keyword>
  <keyword>Risk factors</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Prediabetic State</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Disease Progression</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

