<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03613454</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>R18-097</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03613454</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Embolization in Splenic Trauma</brief_title>
  <acronym>ELSA</acronym>
  <official_title>Embolization in Splenic Trauma (ELSA)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Alabama at Birmingham</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Alabama at Birmingham</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Randomized, prospective, feasibility study to begin evaluating the efficacy, safety, and cost
      of using either coils or vascular plugs (VPs) for proximal splenic artery embolization in the
      setting of traumatic splenic injury.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Splenic preservation rates are improved for participants with high-grade splenic injuries
      (defined as Grade III-V injuries by the AAST guidelines) when non-operative management is
      supplemented by image-guided, trans-catheter splenic artery embolization (SAE). SAE is
      currently the standard of care for hemodynamically stable participants with high-grade
      splenic injuries. In proximal SAE (pSAE), the mid-splenic artery is embolized between the
      origins of the dorsal pancreatic artery and pancreaticomagna artery with either VPs or coils.
      This reduces the intra-splenic arterial pressure which allows the parenchyma time to heal.
      Splenic perfusion is maintained via a collateral pathway consisting of flow from the splenic
      artery proximal to the site of embolization through the smaller dorsal pancreatic artery to
      the transverse pancreatic artery to the pancreaticomagna artery which then delivers a slower,
      smaller amount of blood to the splenic artery distal to the site of embolization.
      Additionally, collateral supply from the short gastric and gastroepiploic arteries helps to
      protect the spleen from infarction and/or abscess formation.

      pSAE is most often accomplished using either coils or VPs as the embolic agent, both of which
      are FDA-approved and clinically-available. Coils have a long history of efficacy and safety
      for embolization and are thus familiar embolic agents to most endovascular specialists.
      Further, coils large enough to embolize the mid-splenic artery can be deployed through a
      standard micro-catheter, which means they can be used in even the most tortuous splenic
      arteries. However, multiple coils may need to be deployed in the same patient to achieve
      hemostasis in the mid-splenic artery that may increase their overall cost, iodinated contrast
      use, procedural time, and the radiation exposure to the participant and medical staff.
      Additionally, given the high-flow nature of the splenic artery, even an appropriately sized
      coil may migrate distally. A typical pSAE using coils will involve the deployment of one
      helical coil followed by multiple packing coils until hemostasis is achieved. VPs attempt to
      overcome the limitations of coils. For example, the deployment of a single VP can typically
      provide hemostasis in the mid-splenic artery which theoretically reduces procedural time,
      contrast load, and radiation exposure. Despite this, VPs are more expensive than coils on a
      per unit basis and are usually less familiar devices to endovascular specialists. Another
      drawback of VPs is that they cannot be deployed through a standard micro-catheter but rather
      require the advancement of a larger, stiffer 0.035 inch system into the mid-splenic artery.
      This may limit their use in very tortuous splenic arteries. Currently, the selection of
      embolic agent for pSAE is primarily based on operator experience and preference. The embolic
      efficacy, technical success, and cost of using coils compared to VPs has been evaluated in
      other diseases; yet, to the best of our knowledge, these embolic agents have never been
      compared for their use in pSAE, much less in a randomized, prospective fashion.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 16, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Ability to enroll sufficient participants within 18 months of study initiation</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion, an average of 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>The primary outcome of the study will be enrolling 50 participants in the study within 18 months of study initiation with adequate 30 day follow-up on all participants.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Technical success of embolization</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion, an average of 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>This outcome will be measured by the ability of the operator to deploy the required embolic with resultant stasis in the splenic artery. This will be compared between the two groups.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Immediate clinical success</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion, an average of 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>This outcome will be measured by the number of intra-procedural complications and compared between the two groups</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Delayed clinical success</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion, an average of 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>This outcome will be measured by splenic salvage rate at 30 days and compared between groups.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Fluoroscopy time</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion, an average of 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>The fluoroscopy times used for each embolic will be measured and compared.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Contrast volume</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion, an average of 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>The amount of contrast used during the procedure will be measured for each group and compared.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Trauma to the Spleen</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Splenic artery embolization with vascular embolic coils</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Splenic artery embolization with vascular embolic plugs</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Splenic artery embolization with vascular embolic coils</intervention_name>
    <description>Splenic artery embolization with vascular embolic coils</description>
    <arm_group_label>Splenic artery embolization with vascular embolic coils</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Splenic artery embolization with vascular embolic plugs</intervention_name>
    <description>Splenic artery embolization with vascular embolic plugs</description>
    <arm_group_label>Splenic artery embolization with vascular embolic plugs</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients presenting to UAB emergency room requiring embolization of the splenic artery
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Andrew J. Gunn, MD</last_name>
    <phone>205-996-7115</phone>
    <email>agunn@uabmc.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Alabama at Birmingham Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Birmingham</city>
        <state>Alabama</state>
        <zip>35249</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Rebecca Lee</last_name>
      <phone>205-934-6499</phone>
      <email>rebeccalee@uabmc.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Andrew J Gunn, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jan Jansen, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Joel Raborn, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 12, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 1, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 3, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 10, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 10, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 12, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Alabama at Birmingham</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Andrew J. Gunn</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Wounds and Injuries</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

