<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03617224</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>STU 032018-018</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03617224</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Pembrolizumab and Total Skin Electron Beam Radiotherapy in Mycosis Fungoides and Sézary Syndrome</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase I Trial of Pembrolizumab and Total Skin Electron Beam Radiotherapy in Mycosis Fungoides and Sézary Syndrome</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Texas Southwestern Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Texas Southwestern Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Hypothesis: Addition of low dose TSEBT to debulk MF/SS either before or during checkpoint
      blockade with anti-PD-1 pembrolizumab monoclonal antibody therapy will be safe and well
      tolerated.

      Primary Objective:

      • To determine the maximum tolerated dose (MTD) for the combination of total skin electron
      beam therapy (TSEBT) and pembrolizumab regimen.

      Secondary Objectives:

        -  To determine the preliminary efficacy of the combination of TSEBT with pembrolizumab.

        -  To determine the impact on patient-reported health-related quality of life outcomes.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a single center phase I clinical trial assessing the safety of combination therapy of
      TSEBT and pembrolizumab for treatment of Stage IB-IV relapsed/refractory MF and SS.

      Primary Endpoint:

      • Primary endpoint will be maximum tolerated dose (MTD).

      Secondary Endpoints:

        -  Efficacy of the combination of TSEBT with pembrolizumab therapy is measured.

        -  CTCAE v4.0 toxicity beyond the 30 day period following the second therapy in the
           combination protocol treatment and up to 30 days following last dose of pembrolizumab.

        -  Skindex-29 patient-reported HRQOL survey.

      Sample Size and Accrual: 18 patients will be enrolled.

      Statistical Analysis: Time to event will be estimated using the Kaplan-Meier approach along
      with the 95% confidence interval.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Withdrawn</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Unable to enroll patients that met enrollment criteria.
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 24, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 24, 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 24, 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum Tolerated Dose (MTD)</measure>
    <time_frame>1 Year</time_frame>
    <description>The highest dose in the regimen is assessed if dose limiting toxicities do not halt escalation.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Response to therapy</measure>
    <time_frame>4 Years</time_frame>
    <description>The response to therapy is measured from overall response criteria from initiation of any therapy.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression-free survival</measure>
    <time_frame>4 Years</time_frame>
    <description>Progression-free survival is measured without the development of new metastasis.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Health-related quality of life (HRQOL)</measure>
    <time_frame>4 Years</time_frame>
    <description>HRQOL's are measured using the Skindex-29. The higher the number better the quality of life.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Dose Limiting Toxicities (DLT)</measure>
    <time_frame>4 Years</time_frame>
    <description>Severity or Toxicity will be assessed according to the National Cancer Institute (NCI) Common Toxicity Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE), version 4.0. Dose adjustments should be made according to the system showing the greatest degree of toxicity. The consequences of toxicity should all be graded 1-5 according to the Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE), version 4.0 occurring prior to 270 days from the start of protocol treatment. CTCAE V4.0 along with grades 1-5 is provided in the link for reference (https://evs.nci.nih.gov/ftp1/CTCAE/CTCAE_4.03/CTCAE_4.03_2010-06 14_QuickReference_8.5x11.pdf).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">0</enrollment>
  <condition>Cutaneous T-Cell Lymphomas</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>TSEBT and pembrolizumab</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Dose regimens are sequential therapy of TSEBT with Pembrolizumab.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Radiation: TSEBT</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The regimen includes a rule-based &quot;3+3&quot; design for escalating regimen intensity of combined TSEBT and pembrolizumab.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Radiation</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>TSEBT</intervention_name>
    <description>The regimen includes a rule-based &quot;3+3&quot; design for escalating regimen intensity of combined TSEBT and pembrolizumab.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Radiation: TSEBT</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>TSEBT and pembrolizumab</intervention_name>
    <description>Dose regimens are sequential therapy of TSEBT with Pembrolizumab.</description>
    <arm_group_label>TSEBT and pembrolizumab</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Biopsy confirmed Mycosis Fungoides or Sézary Syndrome

          -  Stage IB-IV by ISCL/EORTC 2007 Revision Staging (See Appendix Section 13.3). Maximal
             stage since diagnosis will determine eligibility.

          -  Failed or intolerant to at least one prior line of systemic therapy

          -  Life expectancy &gt; 6 months

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) Performance Status ≤ 2 and able to stand for
             TSEBT

          -  Baseline measurable disease by the mSWAT criteria

          -  Acceptable baseline laboratories:

               -  Leukocytes ≥ 2,000/mcL

               -  Absolute neutrophil count ≥ 1,500/mcL

               -  Platelets ≥ 100,000/mcl

               -  Hemoglobin ≥ 9g/dL

               -  Total bilirubin ≤ 1.5 X institutional upper limit of normal

               -  AST(SGOT)/ALT(SPGT) ≤ 2.5 X institutional upper limit of normal

               -  INR/PT ≤ 1.5 X institutional upper limit of normal (*unless on anticoagulation
                  therapy and therapeutic)

               -  Serum creatinine ≤ 1.5 X institutional upper limit normal OR ≥ 60 mL/min
                  calculated creatinine clearance ≥60 mL/min for subject

          -  Women of child-bearing potential and men must agree to use adequate contraception
             (hormonal or barrier method of birth control; abstinence) prior to study entry, for
             the duration of study participation, and for 90 days following completion of therapy.
             Should a woman become pregnant or suspect she is pregnant while participating in this
             study, she should inform her treating physician immediately.

          -  A female of child-bearing potential is any woman (regardless of sexual orientation,
             having undergone a tubal ligation, or remaining celibate by choice) who meets the
             following criteria:

               -  Has not undergone a hysterectomy or bilateral oophorectomy; or

               -  Has not been naturally postmenopausal for at least 12 consecutive months (i.e.,
                  has had menses at any time in the preceding 12 consecutive months).

          -  Ability to understand and the willingness to sign a written informed consent.

          -  Patient must provide tissue biopsy (punch) of skin at baseline (pre-study treatment),
             following 3 cycles of pembrolizumab, 1 month following end of TSEBT, at clinical event
             of progression, at end of treatment (unless at same time as progression triggered
             biopsy). Optional biopsy can be taken every 3 cycles of pembrolizumab and at time of
             initial response to pembrolizumab.

          -  Must be a candidate for TSEBT

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects who have had prior TSEBT (prior focal radiotherapy is allowed).

          -  Subjects who have had systemic cytotoxic anticancer agents or radiotherapy within 2
             weeks prior to entering the study or those who have not in the opinion of the treating
             physician recovered from adverse events due to agents administered more than 2 weeks
             earlier.

          -  Subjects who have received the following prior therapies:

          -  Alemtuzumab within the past 8 weeks

          -  Retinoids, interferons, Vorinostat, Romidepsin, oral corticosteroids (except
             physiologic replacement dose or topicals) within the past 2 weeks

          -  Phototherapy within the past 4 weeks

          -  Topical therapies including retinoids, nitrogen mustards and Imiquimod within the past
             week

          -  Patients may not have received systemic steroid therapy or other form of
             immunosuppressive therapy within 7 days prior to the first dose of pembrolizumab

          -  Subjects may not be receiving any other investigational agents during the study or for
             within 4 weeks of registration.

          -  Subjects with known brain metastases should be excluded from this clinical trial
             because of their poor prognosis and because they often develop progressive neurologic
             dysfunction that would confound the evaluation of neurologic and other adverse events.

          -  Subjects with known history of immunodeficiency or severe autoimmune disease requiring
             systemic immunosuppressive agents or severe connective tissue diseases (i.e. systemic
             scleroderma) or DNA damage repair deficiency syndromes that are known to pre-dispose
             to excess DNA damage hypersensitivity from ionizing radiation will be excluded from
             the study.

          -  Uncontrolled intercurrent illness including, but not limited to, ongoing or active
             infection, symptomatic congestive heart failure, unstable angina pectoris, cardiac
             arrhythmia, active hepatitis B or C, history of pneumonitis requiring steroids, or
             psychiatric illness/social situations that would limit compliance with study
             requirements.

          -  Subjects must not have received a recent live vaccine within 30 days of treatment.

          -  Subjects must not be pregnant or nursing due to the potential for congenital
             abnormalities and the potential of this regimen to harm nursing infants.

          -  Patients with history of hypersensitivity to monoclonal antibodies.

          -  History of prior therapy with an anti-PD-1, anti-PD-L1, or anti-PD-L2 agent

          -  History of allergic reactions attributed to compounds of similar chemical or biologic
             composition to MK-3475 (pembrolizumab)

          -  Patients may not have an additional known malignancy requiring active treatment or
             which his progressing, excluding non-melanoma skin cancer or in situ cervical cancer
             which has undergone potentially curative therapy.

          -  Known human T-lymphotropic virus type 1 (HTLV) infection

          -  History of non-infectious pneumonitis requiring steroids
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>120 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Texas Southwestern Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dallas</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>75390</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 27, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 3, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 6, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 20, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 20, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 22, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Mycosis Fungoides (MF), Sezary Syndrome (SS), Pembrolizumab, Total Skin Electron Beam Therapy (TSEBT)</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Mycoses</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Mycosis Fungoides</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sezary Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, T-Cell, Cutaneous</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pembrolizumab</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

