<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03612778</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MDRT</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03612778</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Modification of Diet in Renal Transplantation (MDRT)</brief_title>
  <acronym>MDRT</acronym>
  <official_title>Nutritional Intervention for Management of Cardiovascular Risk Factors in Kidney Transplant Patients</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University Medical Centre Ljubljana</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University Medical Centre Ljubljana</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Abnormalities in lipid metabolism are present in 50-80% of patients with a kidney transplant
      and together with concurrent comorbidities and other associated cardiovascular risk factors
      put kidney transplant recipients at a high-risk for cardiovascular disease. First line
      lipid-lowering therapy in this population is pharmacological with
      3-hydroxy-3-methyl-glutaryl-coenzyme A (HMG-CoA) reductase inhibitors (statins), however
      there is a paucity of data on the efficacy of therapeutic lifestyle modification for
      cardiovascular risk management in kidney transplant recipients. The aim of the present study
      is to assess efficacy, safety and feasibility of a nutritional intervention for lowering
      cardiovascular risk factors in kidney transplant recipients. Investigators will conduct a
      randomized controlled trial on the effects of a low-fat, unrefined, plant-based diet compared
      to the currently recommended diet according to nutrition guidelines and based on the
      Mediterranean diet pattern to lower the primary end-point LDL-cholesterol and other secondary
      end-points validated as risk factors for cardiovascular events. Length of the intervention
      will be 6 weeks, with a late follow-up after additional 3 months. Stabile kidney transplant
      recipients with LDL-cholesterol &gt;2.6 mmol/l and/or receiving lipid lowering treatment will be
      randomized in a 1:1 ratio to either interventional low-fat, unrefined, plant-based diet or to
      a control diet based on the Mediterranean dietary pattern. Both diets will be prescribed in
      the form of a weekly menu, both will be allowed to be eaten ad libitum (without prespecified
      calorie restriction) and in both groups study participants will be supported by tutor classes
      and counseling to maximise their adherence to prescribed dietary pattern.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      BACKGROUND. Abnormalities in lipid metabolism are present in 50-80% of patients with a kidney
      transplant, as a consequence of both the primary cause of end-stage renal disease, its
      complications and immunosuppressive therapy. Concurrent comorbidities and cardiovascular risk
      factors put kidney transplant recipients at high-risk for cardiovascular disease, therefore
      the target LDL-cholesterol was set to below 2.6 mmol/l (&lt; 100 mg/dl) by the guidelines. First
      line lipid-lowering therapy in this population is pharmacological, namely with HMG-CoA
      reductase inhibitors (statins), which have potential interactions with immunosuppressive
      drugs and increased risk of adverse effects. There is a paucity of data on the efficacy of
      therapeutic lifestyle modification for cardiovascular risk management in the kidney
      transplant recipient. Studies in the general population showed a significant effect of mostly
      plant-based nutrition on lowering lipid levels, achieving approximately 10-15% reduction in
      both total and LDL-cholesterol, while the effect on cardiovascular protection of such
      nutritional intervention remains hypothetical. The aim of the present study is to confirm
      efficacy, safety and feasibility of nutritional intervention for lowering cardiovascular risk
      factors in kidney transplant recipients. METHODS. Investigators will conduct a randomized
      controlled trial on the effects of a low-fat, unrefined, plant-based diet compared to the
      currently recommended diet based on the Mediterranean dietary pattern and complying with
      current nutrition guidelines for general population to lower LDL-cholesterol. Duration of
      dietary intervention will be 6 weeks with further extension of intervention and assessment of
      end-points after additional 3 months. Final follow-up is scheduled after 12 months regardless
      of continuation of the intervention as decided by subjects themselves. Subjects in the
      experimental group will receive a meal plan based on low-fat, unrefined, plant based foods
      with the goal macronutrient intake of approximately 15% protein, &lt;15 % fats and 70-75% of
      carbohydrates, and will additionally receive polyunsaturated fatty acid (PUFA n-3) supplement
      (daily dose 840 mg) to ensure daily recommended intake. Subjects in the control group will
      receive a meal plan in accordance with recommendations by the Task Force for the Management
      of Dyslipidaemias of the European Society of Cardiology and European Atherosclerosis Society
      incorporating foods according to the Mediterranean dietary pattern including the usage of
      (but not limited to) olive oil, fatty-fish and low-fat dairy products. To promote adherence
      to the meal plan, subjects will receive dietary counselling and will be invited to attend
      weekly peer-group meetings together with a next of kin. Both diets will be allowed to be
      eaten at libitum and no calorie counts will be made. A random 24-hour recall, announced
      prospective 3-day food diary analysis and analysis of a 24-hour urine collection to determine
      adherence to the prescribed meal plan will be performed. To ensure safety, periodically
      monitoring of basic serum electrolyte concentrations, body weight and composition, and
      adjustment of antihypertensive and antihyperglycemic medications will be allowed. No change
      of lipid lowering agents will be allowed for the first 6-week study period. Feasibility of
      the intervention will be assessed by adherence monitoring as described above and with the
      Kidney Disease Quality of Life Short Form questionnaire. Analysis of covariance with baseline
      parameter value used as a covariate will be used for primary statistical analysis. Based on
      expected effect of nutritional intervention on lowering LDL-cholesterol by 0.6 mmol/l (23
      mg/dl) in the study population by the end of intervention period, standard deviation of
      LDL-cholesterol of 0.6 mmol/l (23 mg/dl) in the study population with the expected drop-out
      rate of 15 %, the required sample size of 43 participants in each group to achieve a
      statistical significance p &lt; 0.05 and statistical power of 80% is defined.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">November 15, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Randomized controlled trial with two parallel groups.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Serum low density lipoprotein (LDL)-cholesterol</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks and 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Serum LDL-cholesterol concentration</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Apolipoprotein B</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks and 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Apolipoprotein B serum concentration</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Reduction in insulin resistance</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks and 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Change in insulin resistance, measured by Homeostatic Model Assessment (HOMA-IR)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Serum cholesterol</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks and 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Serum total cholesterol concentration</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Oxidized Low Density Lipoprotein (LDL)-cholesterol</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks and 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Serum concentration of oxidized LDL-cholesterol</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Inflammatory marker high sensitive C-Reactive Protein (hs-CRP)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks and 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Serum concentration of inflammatory marker high sensitive C-reactive Protein</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Total fat tissue mass</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks and 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Total body fat mass measured with bioimpedance analysis</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Lean tissue mass</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks and 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Lean tissue mass measured by bioimpedance analysis</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Blood pressure</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks and 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Office measured blood pressure</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proteinuria</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks and 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Spot urinary protein to creatinine-ratio of the second morning urine</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Serum potassium</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks and 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Serum potassium concentration (safety outcome)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Serum phosphate</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks and 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Serum phosphate concentration</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Serum bicarbonate</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks and 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Serum concentration of bicarbonate (safety outcome)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Serum uric acid</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks and 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Serum uric acid concentration (safety outcome)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Micronutrient status of Selenium (safety outcome)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks and 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Plasma Selenium concentration</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>n-3 Polyunsaturated Fatty Acid (PUFA) status</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks and 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>n-3 PUFA content of erythrocyte lipid fraction</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Urinary C-X-C motif chemokine 10 (CXCL10)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks and 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Urinary levels of C-X-C motif chemokine 10 (CXCL10) as an indicator of tubulointerstital and microvascular inflammation</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Gut produced uremic toxin p-cresyl sulphate</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks and 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Serum level of total and free p-cresyl sulphate</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Urinary iodine concentration</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks and 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Urinary level of iodine concentration in ug/L</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Plasma Zinc concentration (safety outcome)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks and 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Plasma zinc concentration</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Serum calcium concentration (safety outcome)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks and 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Serum concentration of total calcium in mmol/l</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">86</enrollment>
  <condition>Kidney Transplant; Complications</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Plant-based diet</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will receive a meal plan based on unrefined plant-based foods with the following macronutrient composition: approximately 15% of calories from vegetable protein, &lt;15% from fat, and 70-75% from carbohydrates. Additionally, to ensure adequate intake of n-3 polyunsaturated fatty acids, they will receive a supplement in the form of one 840 mg n-3 acids eicosapentaenoic acid (EPA) and docosahexaenoic acid (DHA) daily. Nutritional intervention includes dietary counselling and weekly peer-group meetings together with a next of kin.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Mediterranean diet</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will receive a meal plan, based on the recommendations by the Task Force for the Management of Dyslipidaemias of the European Society of Cardiology and European Atherosclerosis Society, based on Mediterranean diet pattern with the following macronutrient composition: approximately 15% of calories from animal and vegetable protein, up to 30% of calories from fat, 50-65% from carbohydrates. Nutritional intervention includes dietary counselling and weekly peer-group meetings together with a next of kin.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Plant-based diet</intervention_name>
    <description>Prescription of a meal plan based on unrefined plant-based foods supported by peer group meetings and dietary counselling. Change from the standard western-type nutritional pattern to a low-fat, unrefined, plant-based nutritional pattern.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Plant-based diet</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Mediterranean diet</intervention_name>
    <description>Prescription of a meal plan based on Mediterranean diet pattern supported by peer group meetings and dietary counselling. Change from the standard western-type nutritional pattern to a Mediterranean nutritional pattern.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Mediterranean diet</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  recipient of kidney transplant &gt; 12 weeks after transplantation and evaluated as
             clinically stable

          -  age 18 years or more at inclusion

          -  estimated glomerular filtration rate (GFR) &gt; 15 ml/min/1.73

          -  diagnosed dyslipidemia (LDL-cholesterol &gt; 2.6 mmol/l (&gt; 100 mg/dl) at inclusion or
             receiving lipid-lowering therapy)

          -  ability to participate in a lifestyle modification study.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  acute illness, infection or surgical intervention requiring hospitalization in 6 weeks
             before inclusion, except procedures relating to arteriovenous fistula

          -  treatment of acute rejection or citomegalovirus infection in 6 weeks before inclusion

          -  chronic illness, associated with or increasing the risk of cachexia (including
             congestive heart failure New York Heart Association III or IV, AIDS, advanced chronic
             obstructive pulmonary disease, metastatic neoplastic disease or locally active
             neoplastic disease, chemotherapy treatment in 6 weeks before inclusion)

          -  clinically evident malnutrition (BMI &lt; 18,5, reduction of body weight &gt; 5% in 3 months
             before inclusion, reduction of dietary intake &gt; 25 % from normal in 2 weeks before
             inclusion, serum albumin &lt; 30 g/l (&lt; 3 g/dl))

          -  nephrotic syndrome

          -  pregnancy

          -  treatment with vitamin K antagonists

          -  change in lipid-lowering therapy in 3 weeks before inclusion
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jernej Pajek, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University Medical Centre Ljubljana</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Jernej Pajek, MD</last_name>
    <phone>0038615222941</phone>
    <email>jernej.pajek@mf-uni-lj.si</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Ana Dovc, MD</last_name>
    <phone>0038615222941</phone>
    <email>ana.dovc@kclj.si</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Medical Centre</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ljubljana</city>
        <country>Slovenia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jernej Pajek, PhD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Slovenia</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Baigent C, Landray MJ, Reith C, Emberson J, Wheeler DC, Tomson C, Wanner C, Krane V, Cass A, Craig J, Neal B, Jiang L, Hooi LS, Levin A, Agodoa L, Gaziano M, Kasiske B, Walker R, Massy ZA, Feldt-Rasmussen B, Krairittichai U, Ophascharoensuk V, Fellström B, Holdaas H, Tesar V, Wiecek A, Grobbee D, de Zeeuw D, Grönhagen-Riska C, Dasgupta T, Lewis D, Herrington W, Mafham M, Majoni W, Wallendszus K, Grimm R, Pedersen T, Tobert J, Armitage J, Baxter A, Bray C, Chen Y, Chen Z, Hill M, Knott C, Parish S, Simpson D, Sleight P, Young A, Collins R; SHARP Investigators. The effects of lowering LDL cholesterol with simvastatin plus ezetimibe in patients with chronic kidney disease (Study of Heart and Renal Protection): a randomised placebo-controlled trial. Lancet. 2011 Jun 25;377(9784):2181-92. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(11)60739-3. Epub 2011 Jun 12.</citation>
    <PMID>21663949</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Barnard ND, Scialli AR, Turner-McGrievy G, Lanou AJ, Glass J. The effects of a low-fat, plant-based dietary intervention on body weight, metabolism, and insulin sensitivity. Am J Med. 2005 Sep;118(9):991-7.</citation>
    <PMID>16164885</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Van Breukelen GJ. ANCOVA versus change from baseline: more power in randomized studies, more bias in nonrandomized studies [corrected]. J Clin Epidemiol. 2006 Sep;59(9):920-5. Epub 2006 Jun 23. Erratum in: J Clin Epidemiol. 2006 Dec;59(12):1334.</citation>
    <PMID>16895814</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cartolano FC, Dias GD, de Freitas MCP, Figueiredo Neto AM, Damasceno NRT. Insulin Resistance Predicts Atherogenic Lipoprotein Profile in Nondiabetic Subjects. J Diabetes Res. 2017;2017:1018796. doi: 10.1155/2017/1018796. Epub 2017 Aug 22.</citation>
    <PMID>28913361</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Claesson K, Mayer AD, Squifflet JP, Grabensee B, Eigler FW, Behrend M, Vanrenterghem Y, van Hooff J, Morales JM, Johnson RW, Buchholz B, Land W, Forsythe JL, Neumayer HH, Ericzon BG, Mühlbacher F. Lipoprotein patterns in renal transplant patients: a comparison between FK 506 and cyclosporine A patients. Transplant Proc. 1998 Jun;30(4):1292-4.</citation>
    <PMID>9636524</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ferdowsian HR, Barnard ND. Effects of plant-based diets on plasma lipids. Am J Cardiol. 2009 Oct 1;104(7):947-56. doi: 10.1016/j.amjcard.2009.05.032. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19766762</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gardner CD, Coulston A, Chatterjee L, Rigby A, Spiller G, Farquhar JW. The effect of a plant-based diet on plasma lipids in hypercholesterolemic adults: a randomized trial. Ann Intern Med. 2005 May 3;142(9):725-33.</citation>
    <PMID>15867404</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Heemann U, Abramowicz D, Spasovski G, Vanholder R; European Renal Best Practice Work Group on Kidney Transplantation. Endorsement of the Kidney Disease Improving Global Outcomes (KDIGO) guidelines on kidney transplantation: a European Renal Best Practice (ERBP) position statement. Nephrol Dial Transplant. 2011 Jul;26(7):2099-106. doi: 10.1093/ndt/gfr169. Epub 2011 May 9. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21555392</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Holdaas H, Fellström B, Cole E, Nyberg G, Olsson AG, Pedersen TR, Madsen S, Grönhagen-Riska C, Neumayer HH, Maes B, Ambühl P, Hartmann A, Staffler B, Jardine AG; Assessment of LEscol in Renal Transplantation (ALERT) Study Investigators. Long-term cardiac outcomes in renal transplant recipients receiving fluvastatin: the ALERT extension study. Am J Transplant. 2005 Dec;5(12):2929-36. Erratum in: Am J Transplant. 2006 Aug;6(8):1986.</citation>
    <PMID>16303007</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Israni AK, Snyder JJ, Skeans MA, Peng Y, Maclean JR, Weinhandl ED, Kasiske BL; PORT Investigators. Predicting coronary heart disease after kidney transplantation: Patient Outcomes in Renal Transplantation (PORT) Study. Am J Transplant. 2010 Feb;10(2):338-53. doi: 10.1111/j.1600-6143.2009.02949.x.</citation>
    <PMID>20415903</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kidney Disease: Improving Global Outcomes (KDIGO) Transplant Work Group. KDIGO clinical practice guideline for the care of kidney transplant recipients. Am J Transplant. 2009 Nov;9 Suppl 3:S1-155. doi: 10.1111/j.1600-6143.2009.02834.x.</citation>
    <PMID>19845597</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wanner C, Tonelli M; Kidney Disease: Improving Global Outcomes Lipid Guideline Development Work Group Members. KDIGO Clinical Practice Guideline for Lipid Management in CKD: summary of recommendation statements and clinical approach to the patient. Kidney Int. 2014 Jun;85(6):1303-9. doi: 10.1038/ki.2014.31. Epub 2014 Feb 19. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24552851</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lopes TS, Luiz RR, Hoffman DJ, Ferriolli E, Pfrimer K, Moura AS, Sichieri R, Pereira RA. Misreport of energy intake assessed with food records and 24-h recalls compared with total energy expenditure estimated with DLW. Eur J Clin Nutr. 2016 Nov;70(11):1259-1264. doi: 10.1038/ejcn.2016.85. Epub 2016 Jun 8. Erratum in: Eur J Clin Nutr. 2017 May;71(5):680.</citation>
    <PMID>27273069</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ojo AO, Hanson JA, Wolfe RA, Leichtman AB, Agodoa LY, Port FK. Long-term survival in renal transplant recipients with graft function. Kidney Int. 2000 Jan;57(1):307-13.</citation>
    <PMID>10620213</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Palmer SC, Navaneethan SD, Craig JC, Perkovic V, Johnson DW, Nigwekar SU, Hegbrant J, Strippoli GF. HMG CoA reductase inhibitors (statins) for kidney transplant recipients. Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2014 Jan 28;(1):CD005019. doi: 10.1002/14651858.CD005019.pub4. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24470059</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Prospective Studies Collaboration, Lewington S, Whitlock G, Clarke R, Sherliker P, Emberson J, Halsey J, Qizilbash N, Peto R, Collins R. Blood cholesterol and vascular mortality by age, sex, and blood pressure: a meta-analysis of individual data from 61 prospective studies with 55,000 vascular deaths. Lancet. 2007 Dec 1;370(9602):1829-39. Review. Erratum in: Lancet. 2008 Jul 26;372(9635):292.</citation>
    <PMID>18061058</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sniderman AD, Williams K, Contois JH, Monroe HM, McQueen MJ, de Graaf J, Furberg CD. A meta-analysis of low-density lipoprotein cholesterol, non-high-density lipoprotein cholesterol, and apolipoprotein B as markers of cardiovascular risk. Circ Cardiovasc Qual Outcomes. 2011 May;4(3):337-45. doi: 10.1161/CIRCOUTCOMES.110.959247. Epub 2011 Apr 12.</citation>
    <PMID>21487090</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Authors/Task Force Members:, Catapano AL, Graham I, De Backer G, Wiklund O, Chapman MJ, Drexel H, Hoes AW, Jennings CS, Landmesser U, Pedersen TR, Reiner Ž, Riccardi G, Taskinen MR, Tokgozoglu L, Verschuren WM, Vlachopoulos C, Wood DA, Zamorano JL. 2016 ESC/EAS Guidelines for the Management of Dyslipidaemias: The Task Force for the Management of Dyslipidaemias of the European Society of Cardiology (ESC) and European Atherosclerosis Society (EAS) Developed with the special contribution of the European Assocciation for Cardiovascular Prevention &amp; Rehabilitation (EACPR). Atherosclerosis. 2016 Oct;253:281-344. doi: 10.1016/j.atherosclerosis.2016.08.018. Epub 2016 Sep 1.</citation>
    <PMID>27594540</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>October 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 28, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 1, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 2, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 18, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 18, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 22, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University Medical Centre Ljubljana</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Jernej Pajek</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor Jernej Pajek, MD, PhD</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>nutrition</keyword>
  <keyword>dyslipidemia</keyword>
  <keyword>insulin resistance</keyword>
  <keyword>inflammation</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

