<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03616210</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>61485616.0.0000.5327</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03616210</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Protective Versus Conventional Mechanical Ventilation for Peripheral Vascular Surgery.</brief_title>
  <official_title>Protective Versus Conventional Mechanical Ventilation for Peripheral Vascular Surgery.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Hospital de Clinicas de Porto Alegre</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Hospital de Clinicas de Porto Alegre</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background and goal of the study: Postoperative complications following major surgeries are
      associated with a significant increase in costs and mortality. There is increasing evidence
      that mechanical ventilation with a protective strategy using low tidal volume prevents
      postoperative pulmonary complications. Peripheral vascular surgeries include particularly
      surgeries for arterial revascularization of the lower limbs in patients with advanced
      peripheral vascular disease. These procedures are strongly associated with major
      cardiovascular morbidity postoperatively. In this specific group of patients, the presence of
      postoperative pulmonary complications (PPC) may be associated with worsening of clinical
      outcomes with a consequent significant increase in perioperative morbidity.

      Subjects and methods: In this study, the investigators aimed to compare the effects of
      controlled mechanical ventilation with the use of a protective strategy (low tidal volume
      associated with elevated PEEP) when compared to the conventional strategy (higher tidal
      volume associated with reduced PEEP levels) on the rate of PPC in patients undergoing
      peripheral vascular surgery. This study was delineated as a prospective trial, compared to
      the control group (conventional ventilation strategy). Patients and researchers were blinded
      during data collection. The investigators included adult patients, ASA status II to IV, aged
      over 18 years, scheduled to undergo lower limb arterial bypass surgery. Patients were
      randomized to treatment with conventional mechanical ventilation (tidal volume between 9 to
      10 ml.kg-1 of predicted body weight and PEEP between 3 and 5 cmH2O - Group I or control) or
      treatment with protective ventilation strategy (tidal volume of 6 to 7 ml.kg-1 of predicted
      body weight and PEEP of 6 to 8 cmH2O - Group II or treatment). The primary outcome was PPC
      and the secondary endpoint included hemodynamic and metabolic changes perioperatively.
      Statistical analysis was performed using the intention-to-treat method.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">April 15, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">April 16, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">April 15, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Postoperative pulmonary complications</measure>
    <time_frame>7 days</time_frame>
    <description>The main outcome was the presence of any pulmonary complication (composite endpoint) after surgery and until discharge. These pulmonary complications included severe hypoxemia, suspected pulmonary infection, documented atelectasis or pulmonary infiltrate, bronchospasm, pulmonary edema, pleural effusion, pneumothorax, or development of ARDS. The presence of at least one of the findings described above was considered as a positive primary outcome.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Perioperative hemodynamic complications</measure>
    <time_frame>7 days</time_frame>
    <description>Hypotension and need for continuous vasopressors (i.e., systolic arterial blood pressure &lt; 90 mmHg for more than 5 min).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">56</enrollment>
  <condition>Lung Diseases</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Protective ventilation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Protective ventilation strategy (tidal volume of 6 to 7 ml.kg-1 of predicted body weight and PEEP of 6 to 8 cmH2O)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Conventional ventilation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Conventional mechanical ventilation (tidal volume between 9 to 10 ml.kg-1 of predicted body weight and PEEP between 3 and 5 cmH2O)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Protective ventilation</intervention_name>
    <description>Protective ventilation strategy with tidal volume of 6 to 7 ml.kg-1 of predicted body weight and PEEP of 6 to 8 cmH2O.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Protective ventilation</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  This study enrolled only patients displaying peripheral occlusive arterial disease and
             scheduled to undergo an elective peripheral artery bypass surgery.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  The illiterate or who do not understand Portuguese language, those who had a body-mass
             index (BMI) higher than 35 kg/m2, had severe pulmonary comorbidities or another
             disorder that might compromise a safe trial procedure and those who refused to
             participate of the study or who had already participated in other studies.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Andre P Schmidt, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Hospital de Clinicas de Porto Alegre</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Andre P Schmidt</name>
      <address>
        <city>Porto Alegre</city>
        <state>RS</state>
        <zip>90035-903</zip>
        <country>Brazil</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Brazil</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>April 26, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 31, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 6, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 31, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 31, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">August 6, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>mechanical ventilation</keyword>
  <keyword>protective ventilation</keyword>
  <keyword>vascular surgery</keyword>
  <keyword>postoperative pulmonary complications</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lung Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

