<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03354585</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>181814</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03354585</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Mindfulness and Chronic Low Back Pain</brief_title>
  <official_title>Brain Mechanisms Supporting Mindfulness-based Chronic Pain Relief</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of California, San Diego</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of California, San Diego</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to see if mindfulness, a form of mental training, or listening
      to a book alters brain activation in response to raising your leg that may produce the
      feeling of pain. A technique called functional magnetic resonance imaging (fMRI) allows
      scientists to determine which parts of the brain are active during a particular task. This
      study will provide new information about how mindfulness affects the brain.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      You have been asked to participate in this study because you are interested in learning
      mindfulness and have been diagnosed with chronic low-back pain. Your participation is
      voluntary. We will randomly assign 40 subjects to each group for the initiation of the final
      phase of the study. Randomization means that you have a one in two chance of being assigned
      to the mindfulness meditation training or book-listening control intervention. Your
      assignment is based on chance rather than a medical decision made by the researchers.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 2, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2, 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2, 2024</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>This intervention study will utilize an unbiased randomized study design. Pain intensity and pain unpleasantness ratings will be assessed using visual analog scales (11 point) obtained before and after all sessions where low back pain is induced. Study volunteers will be randomized and subsequently participate in a twelve session mindfulness meditation or book-listening control regimen. Study volunteers will be required to complete three MRI scans over the course of the study.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>Only the study physician, research coordinator, and intervention facilitators will be aware of group assignment.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Cerebral Blood Flow (average blood perfusion; mL blood/100 grams tissue/minute)</measure>
    <time_frame>There will be up to 3 fMRI sessions (Visit 2, 9, and 16). Active enrollment provides up to 8 weeks to complete all study interventions, scans, and assessments..</time_frame>
    <description>Changes in cerebral blood flow will be assessed during pseudo continuous arterial spin labeling fMRI during their respective manipulations.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Visual Analog Scale Pain Ratings</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 3 fMRI sessions (Visit 1, 2, 9, and 16). Active enrollment provides up to 8 weeks to complete all study interventions, scans, and assessments.</time_frame>
    <description>Visual analog scale (VAS) pain ratings will be assessed in response to the straight leg raise test and lying supine in the MRI scanner.
Psychophysical Assessment of Pain: As previously in all of our previous pain studies, pain intensity and unpleasantness ratings will be assessed with a Visual Analog Scale. These scales 1) provide reliably separate assessment of experimental and clinical pain intensity and unpleasantness, 2) are internally consistent, and 3) approximate ratio scale measurement accuracy. The minimum rating (&quot;0&quot;) is designated as &quot;no pain&quot; whereas the maximum (&quot;10&quot;) is labeled as &quot;most intense imaginable&quot; or &quot;most unpleasant imaginable&quot;.
Higher numbers correspond to higher perceived pain</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Respiration Rate</measure>
    <time_frame>There will be up to 3 fMRI sessions (Visit 2, 9, and 16). Active enrollment provides up to 8 weeks to complete all study interventions, scans, and assessments.</time_frame>
    <description>Respiration rate will be collected and recorded on a Biopac respiratory transducer. Changes in respiration rate could be predictive of analgesia and health promotion.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Five Facet Mindfulness Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 3 fMRI sessions (Visit 1, 2, 9, and 16). Active enrollment provides up to 8 weeks to complete all study interventions, scans, and assessments.</time_frame>
    <description>This is a 39-item multidimensional measure of trait mindfulness and includes five subscales: non-reactivity, nonjudgment, describing, observing, and acting with awareness. A numeric value between 1 (never or very rarely true) and 5 (very often or always true) is provided in response to each statement.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Profile of Mood States Form</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 3 fMRI sessions (Visit 1, 2, 9, and 16). Active enrollment provides up to 8 weeks to complete all study interventions, scans, and assessments.</time_frame>
    <description>This is a 40-item core measure of emotional functioning and includes 6 mood states: tension-anxiety, depression-dejection, anger-hostility, vigor-activity, fatigue-inertia, and confusion-bewilderment. A numeric value between 1 (not at all) and 5 (extremely) is provided in response to each statement. Total mood disturbance scoring is calculated by summing the totals for the negative subscales and then subtracting the totals for the positive subscales.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patients' Global Impression of Change</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 3 fMRI sessions (Visit 1, 2, 9, and 16). Active enrollment provides up to 8 weeks to complete all study interventions, scans, and assessments.</time_frame>
    <description>This is a self-report assessment measured on a 7-point scaled designed to evaluate perceived improvement over trial/efficacy of treatment. Options range from &quot;no change&quot; to &quot;a great deal better, and a considerable improvement that has made all the difference.&quot; Higher ratings indicate greater impressions of change.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pain Self Efficacy Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 3 fMRI sessions (Visit 1, 2, 9, and 16). Active enrollment provides up to 8 weeks to complete all study interventions, scans, and assessments.</time_frame>
    <description>This is a 10-item questionnaire that's designed to assess the confidence in people with ongoing pain have in performing activities while in pain. The option of either &quot;not at all confident&quot; or &quot;completely confident&quot; is posed after each item. Scores on this assessment range from 0 to 60, with higher scores indicating stronger self-efficacy beliefs.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PROMIS 29-Item Profile</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 3 fMRI sessions (Visit 1, 2, 9, and 16). Active enrollment provides up to 8 weeks to complete all study interventions, scans, and assessments.</time_frame>
    <description>This is a 29-item generic health-related survey that assesses 7 domains with 4-items in each domain: depression, anxiety, physical function, pain interference, fatigue, sleep disturbance, and ability to participant in social roles/activities. Higher scores represent different outcomes based on domain. Higher scores on symptom-oriented domains represent worse symptomatology, but higher scores on function-oriented domains represent better functioning.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PROMIS Pain Behavior Measure</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 3 fMRI sessions (Visit 1, 2, 9, and 16). Active enrollment provides up to 8 weeks to complete all study interventions, scans, and assessments.</time_frame>
    <description>This is a 5-item questionnaire that measures complaints of suffering, verbal or nonverbal (i.e. such as when I am in pain I squirm) from the past 7 days. Scoring for this measure is item-content dependent.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PROMIS Pain Quality Measure</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 3 fMRI sessions (Visit 1, 2, 9, and 16). Active enrollment provides up to 8 weeks to complete all study interventions, scans, and assessments.</time_frame>
    <description>This is a 5-item questionnaire that measures sensory quality of pain experience (throbbing, aching, etc). A numeric value between 1 (not at all) and 5 (very much) is provided in response to each statement. Higher scores indicate a greater quality of pain.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Chronic Pain Acceptance Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 3 fMRI sessions (Visit 1, 2, 9, and 16). Active enrollment provides up to 8 weeks to complete all study interventions, scans, and assessments.</time_frame>
    <description>This is a 20-item assessment designed to measure acceptance of pain. Items are rated on a 7-point scale from 0 (never true) to 6 (always true). Higher scores indicate higher levels of acceptance.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>State Anxiety Inventory</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, all intervention sessions, and 3 fMRI sessions (Visit 1-16). Active enrollment provides up to 8 weeks to complete all study interventions, scans, and assessments.</time_frame>
    <description>This inventory is a 20-item assessment used to measure a subject's state of anxiety. A numeric value between 1 (Not at all) and 4 (Very Much So) is provided in response to each statement. The range of scores for this test is between 20 and 80, with higher scores reflecting higher estimates of anxiety.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Brief Pain Inventory</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 3 fMRI sessions (Visit 1, 2, 9, and 16). Active enrollment provides up to 8 weeks to complete all study interventions, scans, and assessments.</time_frame>
    <description>This is an 8-item assessment widely used to measure clinical pain. Higher scores reflect a higher severity rating of pain.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>SF 12 Health Survey</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 3 fMRI sessions (Visit 1, 2, 9, and 16). Active enrollment provides up to 8 weeks to complete all study interventions, scans, and assessments.</time_frame>
    <description>This is a 12-item version of the SF-36 item Health Survey designed to assess general mental and physical functioning, and overall health-related quality of life. Scores on this assessment range from 0 to 100, where a higher score indicates a higher level of overall health.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pain Catastrophizing Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 3 fMRI sessions (Visit 1, 2, 9, and 16). Active enrollment provides up to 8 weeks to complete all study interventions, scans, and assessments.</time_frame>
    <description>This is a 13-item questionnaire with 3 subscales assessing rumination, magnification, and helplessness in patients. A numeric value between 0 (not at all) and 4 (all the time) is provided in response to each statement. Scores on this assessment range from 0 to 52, with higher values reflecting more salient impacts of pain on one's day to day experience.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Beck Depression Inventory</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 3 fMRI sessions (Visit 1, 2, 9, and 16). Active enrollment provides up to 8 weeks to complete all study interventions, scans, and assessments.</time_frame>
    <description>This is a 21-item standard assessment used to measure clinical depression. Scores on this assessment range from 0 to 63, where higher scores indicate higher levels of depression.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Freiburg Mindfulness Inventory</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 3 fMRI sessions (Visit 1, 2, 9, and 16). Active enrollment provides up to 8 weeks to complete all study interventions, scans, and assessments.</time_frame>
    <description>This is a 14-item standard mindfulness scale to measure potential changes in mindfulness before and after intervention. A rating between &quot;rarely&quot; (0) to &quot;often&quot; (4) is provided in response to each statement.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Roland-Morris Disability Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 3 fMRI sessions (Visit 1, 2, 9, and 16). Active enrollment provides up to 8 weeks to complete all study interventions, scans, and assessments.</time_frame>
    <description>This is a critical assessment for assessing the functional impact of chronic low back pain. Scores on this assessment range from 0 to 24, where higher scores indicate greater disability and limited functioning due to pain.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 3 fMRI sessions (Visit 1, 2, 9, and 16). Active enrollment provides up to 8 weeks to complete all study interventions, scans, and assessments.</time_frame>
    <description>This is a 10-item assessment designed to measure quality of sleep. This measure is scored along a 5-point Likert scale with values ranging from 0 to 5, specific ratings associated with particular items. Scores on this assessment range from 0 to 28, with higher values reflecting greater levels of insomnia.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cohen Perceived Stress Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 3 fMRI sessions (Visit 1, 2, 9, and 16). Active enrollment provides up to 8 weeks to complete all study interventions, scans, and assessments.</time_frame>
    <description>The CPS is a series of 10 temporally constrained (i.e. in the last month) questions meant to ascertain the relative frequency of stressors in one's life, ranging from never (scored as 0) to very often (scored as 4). All positively stated questions are reversed scored and then all items are summed to yield a final estimate of stress. The higher the score the higher the level of stress.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Positive and Negative Affect Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 3 fMRI sessions (Visit 1, 2, 9, and 16). Active enrollment provides up to 8 weeks to complete all study interventions, scans, and assessments.</time_frame>
    <description>This is a 20-item self-report assessment used to assess positive and negative affect in a participant. A rating between &quot;very slightly or not at all&quot; (1) to &quot;extremely&quot; (5) is provided in response to each statement. Higher scores indicate a greater level of positive affect, and a lower score reveals a greater level of negative affect.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Perceived Intervention Effectiveness</measure>
    <time_frame>All 12 intervention sessions, MRI 2, and MRI 3 (Visit 3-16). Active enrollment provides up to 8 weeks to complete all study interventions, scans, and assessments.</time_frame>
    <description>This measure will be assessed with a VAS (&quot;0&quot; = not effective at all; &quot;10&quot;= most effective imaginable) for each intervention session's respective manipulation.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Social Connectedness Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 3 fMRI sessions (Visit 1, 2, 9, and 16). Active enrollment provides up to 8 weeks to complete all study interventions, scans, and assessments.</time_frame>
    <description>This is a 20-item assessment designed to measure social connectedness, an attribute of the self that reflects cognitions of enduring interpersonal closeness with the social world, in participants. Higher scores on the Social Connectedness Scale reflect a stronger sense of social connectedness, there are no sub-scales. The minimum score is 20 and the maximum score is 120.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">120</enrollment>
  <condition>Chronic Low Back Pain</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Meditation Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Study volunteers will participate in a twelve-session meditation training regimen. In brief, subjects will be taught that perceived sensory events are &quot;momentary&quot; and &quot;fleeting&quot; and do not require further evaluation. There will be an emphasis on breath focus and altering one's perspective of discursive sensory events. This intervention has been found to reliably attenuate the subjective experience of pain.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Meditatin Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Study volunteers will participate in a twelve-session meditation training regimen. In brief, subjects will be taught that perceived sensory events are &quot;momentary&quot; and &quot;fleeting&quot; and do not require further evaluation. There will be an emphasis on breath focus and altering one's perspective of discursive sensory events. This intervention has been found to reliably attenuate the subjective experience of pain.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Book Listening Control Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Study volunteers will listen to an audio recording of the Natural History of Selborne across each session.This 12 session intervention is meant to provide the control attention to the facilitator, room setting, social support, conditioning, and the time elapsed during the other respective interventions. We do not expect that this group will demonstrate significant cerebral blood flow changes as a function of the intervention.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Meditation training</intervention_name>
    <description>A well-validated brief mindfulness-based mental training regimen [20 min/session(s)] will be used to teach patients to independently practice mindfulness. Participants will be asked to close their eyes acknowledge distracting thoughts and feelings.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Meditation Group</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>mental training</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Meditatin training</intervention_name>
    <description>A well-validated brief meditation-based mental training regimen [20 min/session(s)] will be used to teach patients to independently practice mindfulness. Participants will be asked to close their eyes acknowledge distracting thoughts and feelings.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Meditatin Group</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>mental training</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Book Listening Control</intervention_name>
    <description>Study volunteers will listen to The Natural History and Antiquities of Selborne throughout the intervention.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Book Listening Control Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion criteria are:

          -  Participants must have a medical evaluation that demonstrates chronic low back pain
             that is evoked by lifting the legs. Existing medical records, per physician discretion
             and low back examinations will confirm diagnosis. This will be determined over the
             phone during the (pre) screening and at study session 1, and will not be contingent on
             MRI.

          -  Participants must be between the ages of 18-65 years.

          -  Participants must rate their daily chronic pain intensity at a 3 or greater on 0-10
             visual analog scale.

          -  Participants must have experienced their radicular pain for at least 3 months
             duration.

          -  Participants must be right-handed.

          -  Participants must have no prior meditative experience

        Exclusion criteria:

          -  Participants must not be participating in any new (within 2 weeks prior or anytime
             after enrollment) pain management procedures during the study period.

          -  Participants must not have had back surgery within the last year before their
             enrollment into the study.

          -  Participants must not have had any other sensory or motor deficits that precludes
             participation in this study.

          -  Participants must not have known anomalies of the central nervous system including:
             stroke, dementia, aneurysm, a personal history of psychosis.

          -  Participants must not have metal implants including ferrous arterial stints or coils,
             spinal stimulators, pacemakers, or defibrillators, permanently implanted hearing
             aides, bullets, BBs, or pellets, retinal eye implants, infusion pump for insulin or
             other medicines, ferrous surgical clips, staples, metal sutures, orthopedic hardware
             above or including the shoulders, body piercings that cannot be removed.

          -  Participants must not be claustrophobic.

          -  Participants must not produce negative straight leg test (i.e. a test is considered
             positive when the person reports reproducible pain at 40 degrees of hip flexion or
             less).

          -  Participants must not be pregnant

          -  Participants must not be over 275 pounds
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Fadel Zeidan, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Principal Investigator</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Julia Birenbaum, BA</last_name>
    <phone>(858) 246-2028</phone>
    <phone_ext>62028</phone_ext>
    <email>jbirenbaum@ucsd.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Fadel Zeidan, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>(858) 246-2391</phone>
    <email>fzeidan@ucsd.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UC San Diego Center for Functional MRI</name>
      <address>
        <city>La Jolla</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>92093</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Thomas Liu, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>858-822-0542</phone>
      <email>ttliu@ucsd.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UC San Diego Center for Mindfulness</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Diego</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>92122</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Fadel Zeidan, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>858-246-2028</phone>
      <phone_ext>62028</phone_ext>
      <email>zeidanlab@ucsd.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Apkarian AV, Krauss BR, Fredrickson BE, Szeverenyi NM. Imaging the pain of low back pain: functional magnetic resonance imaging in combination with monitoring subjective pain perception allows the study of clinical pain states. Neurosci Lett. 2001 Feb 16;299(1-2):57-60.</citation>
    <PMID>11166937</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bruno PA, Millar DP, Goertzen DA. Inter-rater agreement, sensitivity, and specificity of the prone hip extension test and active straight leg raise test. Chiropr Man Therap. 2014 Jun 16;22:23. doi: 10.1186/2045-709X-22-23. eCollection 2014.</citation>
    <PMID>24982755</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chen X, Spaeth RB, Freeman SG, Scarborough DM, Hashmi JA, Wey HY, Egorova N, Vangel M, Mao J, Wasan AD, Edwards RR, Gollub RL, Kong J. The modulation effect of longitudinal acupuncture on resting state functional connectivity in knee osteoarthritis patients. Mol Pain. 2015 Oct 29;11:67. doi: 10.1186/s12990-015-0071-9.</citation>
    <PMID>26511911</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cropley M, Ussher M, Charitou E. Acute effects of a guided relaxation routine (body scan) on tobacco withdrawal symptoms and cravings in abstinent smokers. Addiction. 2007 Jun;102(6):989-93.</citation>
    <PMID>17523994</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Eisenach JC, Rauck RL, Curry R. Intrathecal, but not intravenous adenosine reduces allodynia in patients with neuropathic pain. Pain. 2003 Sep;105(1-2):65-70.</citation>
    <PMID>14499421</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Eisenach JC, Thomas JA, Rauck RL, Curry R, Li X. Cystatin C in cerebrospinal fluid is not a diagnostic test for pain in humans. Pain. 2004 Feb;107(3):207-12.</citation>
    <PMID>14736582</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fardon DF. Nomenclature and classification of lumbar disc pathology. Spine (Phila Pa 1976). 2001 Mar 1;26(5):461-2.</citation>
    <PMID>11242371</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fardon DF, Williams AL, Dohring EJ, Murtagh FR, Gabriel Rothman SL, Sze GK. Lumbar disc nomenclature: version 2.0: Recommendations of the combined task forces of the North American Spine Society, the American Society of Spine Radiology and the American Society of Neuroradiology. Spine J. 2014 Nov 1;14(11):2525-45. doi: 10.1016/j.spinee.2014.04.022. Epub 2014 Apr 24. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24768732</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jamison RN, Ross EL, Michna E, Chen LQ, Holcomb C, Wasan AD. Substance misuse treatment for high-risk chronic pain patients on opioid therapy: a randomized trial. Pain. 2010 Sep;150(3):390-400. doi: 10.1016/j.pain.2010.02.033. Epub 2010 Mar 23.</citation>
    <PMID>20334973</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kwong EH, Virani N, Robert M, Gerry K, Harding A, Rose MS, Dukelow SP, Barton PM. Inter-rater reliability of the Active Straight-Leg Raise and One-Leg Standing tests in non-pregnant women. J Rehabil Med. 2013 Nov;45(10):1058-64. doi: 10.2340/16501977-1213.</citation>
    <PMID>23995959</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lazar N (2008) The Statistical Analysis of Functional MRI Data. New York, New York: Springer.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Loggia ML, Kim J, Gollub RL, Vangel MG, Kirsch I, Kong J, Wasan AD, Napadow V. Default mode network connectivity encodes clinical pain: an arterial spin labeling study. Pain. 2013 Jan;154(1):24-33. doi: 10.1016/j.pain.2012.07.029. Epub 2012 Oct 27.</citation>
    <PMID>23111164</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mens JM, Vleeming A, Snijders CJ, Stam HJ, Ginai AZ. The active straight leg raising test and mobility of the pelvic joints. Eur Spine J. 1999;8(6):468-73.</citation>
    <PMID>10664304</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pantano P, Mainero C, Lenzi D, Caramia F, Iannetti GD, Piattella MC, Pestalozza I, Di Legge S, Bozzao L, Pozzilli C. A longitudinal fMRI study on motor activity in patients with multiple sclerosis. Brain. 2005 Sep;128(Pt 9):2146-53. Epub 2005 May 18.</citation>
    <PMID>15901646</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Quiton RL, Keaser ML, Zhuo J, Gullapalli RP, Greenspan JD. Intersession reliability of fMRI activation for heat pain and motor tasks. Neuroimage Clin. 2014 Jul 22;5:309-21. doi: 10.1016/j.nicl.2014.07.005. eCollection 2014.</citation>
    <PMID>25161897</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rebain R, Baxter GD, McDonough S. A systematic review of the passive straight leg raising test as a diagnostic aid for low back pain (1989 to 2000). Spine (Phila Pa 1976). 2002 Sep 1;27(17):E388-95. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>12221373</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Roussel NA, Nijs J, Truijen S, Smeuninx L, Stassijns G. Low back pain: clinimetric properties of the Trendelenburg test, active straight leg raise test, and breathing pattern during active straight leg raising. J Manipulative Physiol Ther. 2007 May;30(4):270-8.</citation>
    <PMID>17509436</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Skup M. Longitudinal fMRI analysis: A review of methods. Stat Interface. 2010;3(2):232-252.</citation>
    <PMID>22655113</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Summers B, Malhan K, Cassar-Pullicino V. Low back pain on passive straight leg raising: the anterior theca as a source of pain. Spine (Phila Pa 1976). 2005 Feb 1;30(3):342-5.</citation>
    <PMID>15682017</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ussher M, Cropley M, Playle S, Mohidin R, West R. Effect of isometric exercise and body scanning on cigarette cravings and withdrawal symptoms. Addiction. 2009 Jul;104(7):1251-7. doi: 10.1111/j.1360-0443.2009.02605.x.</citation>
    <PMID>19563567</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wasan AD, Davar G, Jamison R. The association between negative affect and opioid analgesia in patients with discogenic low back pain. Pain. 2005 Oct;117(3):450-61.</citation>
    <PMID>16154274</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wasan AD, Loggia ML, Chen LQ, Napadow V, Kong J, Gollub RL. Neural correlates of chronic low back pain measured by arterial spin labeling. Anesthesiology. 2011 Aug;115(2):364-74. doi: 10.1097/ALN.0b013e318220e880.</citation>
    <PMID>21720241</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>White G (1908) Natural History and Antiquities of Selborne. London, England: Cassell and Company.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zeidan F, Johnson SK, Gordon NS, Goolkasian P. Effects of brief and sham mindfulness meditation on mood and cardiovascular variables. J Altern Complement Med. 2010 Aug;16(8):867-73. doi: 10.1089/acm.2009.0321.</citation>
    <PMID>20666590</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zeidan F, Lobanov OV, Kraft RA, Coghill RC. Brain mechanisms supporting violated expectations of pain. Pain. 2015 Sep;156(9):1772-85. doi: 10.1097/j.pain.0000000000000231.</citation>
    <PMID>26083664</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zeidan F, Johnson SK, Diamond BJ, David Z, Goolkasian P. Mindfulness meditation improves cognition: evidence of brief mental training. Conscious Cogn. 2010 Jun;19(2):597-605. doi: 10.1016/j.concog.2010.03.014. Epub 2010 Apr 3.</citation>
    <PMID>20363650</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zeidan F, Martucci KT, Kraft RA, Gordon NS, McHaffie JG, Coghill RC. Brain mechanisms supporting the modulation of pain by mindfulness meditation. J Neurosci. 2011 Apr 6;31(14):5540-8. doi: 10.1523/JNEUROSCI.5791-10.2011.</citation>
    <PMID>21471390</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zeidan F, Emerson NM, Farris SR, Ray JN, Jung Y, McHaffie JG, Coghill RC. Mindfulness Meditation-Based Pain Relief Employs Different Neural Mechanisms Than Placebo and Sham Mindfulness Meditation-Induced Analgesia. J Neurosci. 2015 Nov 18;35(46):15307-25. doi: 10.1523/JNEUROSCI.2542-15.2015.</citation>
    <PMID>26586819</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Deyo RA, Dworkin SF, Amtmann D, Andersson G, Borenstein D, Carragee E, Carrino J, Chou R, Cook K, DeLitto A, Goertz C, Khalsa P, Loeser J, Mackey S, Panagis J, Rainville J, Tosteson T, Turk D, Von Korff M, Weiner DK. Report of the NIH Task Force on Research Standards for Chronic Low Back Pain. Int J Ther Massage Bodywork. 2015 Sep 1;8(3):16-33. eCollection 2015 Sep.</citation>
    <PMID>26388962</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sharma HA, Gupta R, Olivero W. fMRI in patients with lumbar disc disease: a paradigm to study patients over time. J Pain Res. 2011;4:401-5. doi: 10.2147/JPR.S24393. Epub 2011 Dec 7.</citation>
    <PMID>22247623</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zeidan F, Gordon NS, Merchant J, Goolkasian P. The effects of brief mindfulness meditation training on experimentally induced pain. J Pain. 2010 Mar;11(3):199-209. doi: 10.1016/j.jpain.2009.07.015. Epub 2009 Oct 22.</citation>
    <PMID>19853530</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zeidan F, Adler-Neal AL, Wells RE, Stagnaro E, May LM, Eisenach JC, McHaffie JG, Coghill RC. Mindfulness-Meditation-Based Pain Relief Is Not Mediated by Endogenous Opioids. J Neurosci. 2016 Mar 16;36(11):3391-7. doi: 10.1523/JNEUROSCI.4328-15.2016.</citation>
    <PMID>26985045</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 16, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 24, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">November 28, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 15, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 15, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 18, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of California, San Diego</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Fadel Zeidan</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Mindfulness</keyword>
  <keyword>fMRI</keyword>
  <keyword>Pain</keyword>
  <keyword>Low Back</keyword>
  <keyword>Radicular</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Back Pain</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Low Back Pain</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

