<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03658759</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ECPR-062018-UAMC</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03658759</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Rapid Response VA-ECMO in Refractory Out-of-hospital Cardiac Arrest</brief_title>
  <acronym>RESuSCITATe</acronym>
  <official_title>ECPR Treatment Protocol: Rapid Response VA-ECMO in Refractory Out-of-hospital Cardiac Arrest (RESuSCITATe Registry)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Academisch Medisch Centrum - Universiteit van Amsterdam (AMC-UvA)</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Academisch Medisch Centrum - Universiteit van Amsterdam (AMC-UvA)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      A selected group of patients with refractory cardiac arrest may benefit from inhospital
      treatment and this may warrant transfer to the hospital with ongoing CPR. In patients with VF
      or ventricular tachycardia (VT) the underlying cause may be reversible and damage to other
      organs is limited at the time of the arrest. Many patients will have a coronary event that
      can be treated by angioplasty. However, up to now absence of ROSC poses a barrier for
      angioplasty, and most patients are therefore not even transported to a hospital. With the use
      of extra corporeal membrane oxygenation (ECMO) the circulation can be restored immediately,
      providing time to diagnose and treat the underlying cause of the cardiac arrest.
      International cohort studies show that a strategy of pre-hospital triage and transport to a
      cardiac arrest expertise center for &quot;rapid-response&quot; ECMO and coronary revascularization is
      feasible and improves survival.

      A clinical pathway will encompass intense cooperation and optimal logistics between several
      paramedical and medical disciplines, i.e. from prehospital ambulance service to intensive
      care. Incorporation of mechanical chest compressions devices (LUCAS™), rapid-response
      veno-arterial (VA-)ECMO (Cardiohelp, Maquet), and ECMO assisted revascularization in a
      dedicated clinical pathway will offer a potential lifesaving treatment option that is in
      accordance with the recommendations in the current Guidelines.

      The aim of the study is to investigate the feasibility of a new local clinical pathway in our
      hospital to provide ECPR for refractory OHCA patients.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Coronary heart disease is the leading cause of cardiac arrest. The incidence of cardiac
      arrest in Europe is between 0.4 and 1 per 1000 inhabitants per year, thus involving between
      350.000 and 700.000 people per year. Approximately, 275.000 of these cardiac arrests are
      treated by the emergency medical service (EMS) in Europe. (1) Survival after cardiac arrest
      varies from less than 5% to 60% according to the characteristics of the cardiac arrest event
      (e.g. cardiac etiology, witnessed arrest, initial recorded rhythm (shockable: ventricular
      fibrillation (VF), ventricular tachycardia (VT) or not shockable).(1) Cardiac arrest
      patients, who despite conventional cardiopulmonary resuscitation (CPR) do not achieve return
      of spontaneous circulation (ROSC) within 10-20 minutes of advanced life support (ALS) have
      the worst prognosis with rates of survival to hospital discharge of 2-11%.

      A selected group of patients with refractory cardiac arrest may benefit from very aggressive
      in-hospital treatment and this may warrant transfer to the hospital with ongoing CPR. In
      patients with VF or ventricular tachycardia (VT) the underlying cause may be reversible and
      damage to other organs is limited at the time of the arrest. Many patients will have a
      coronary event that can be treated by angioplasty. However, up to now absence of ROSC poses a
      barrier for angioplasty, and most patients are therefore not even transported to a hospital.

      With the use of extra corporeal membrane oxygenation (ECMO) the circulation can be restored
      immediately, providing time to diagnose and treat the underlying cause of the cardiac arrest.
      International cohort studies show that a strategy of pre-hospital triage and transport to a
      cardiac arrest expertise center for &quot;rapid-response&quot; ECMO and coronary revascularization is
      feasible and improves survival. The recent 2015 European Resuscitation Council Guidelines for
      Resuscitation position extracorporeal CPR (ECPR) as follows: &quot;ECPR should be considered as a
      rescue therapy for those patients in whom initial advanced life support (ALS) measures are
      unsuccessful and to facilitate specific interventions (e.g. coronary angiography and
      percutaneous coronary intervention (PCI) or pulmonary thrombectomy for massive pulmonary
      embolism)&quot;.(2) A recent meta-analysis performed by our group supports ECMO in this setting.
      (3)

      Currently, a strong pre-hospital and clinical pathway for acute myocardial infarction exists
      in the greater Amsterdam region / Noord-Holland region, i.e. &quot;Lifenet protocol&quot;. The Academic
      Medical Center is an international recognized center with the ARREST program to evaluate
      treatments for out-of-hospital cardiac arrest (OHCA).(4) However, a dedicated clinical
      pathway for refractory OHCA patients does not yet exist. Integration of the &quot;Lifenet
      protocol&quot; and ARREST program would provide an ideal setting to create and install a dedicated
      clinical pathway for these cardiac arrest patients.

      The existing clinical pathway for cardiac arrest patients will be optimized and upgraded to
      be able to provide ECPR for refractory cardiac arrest patients. This clinical pathway will
      encompass intense cooperation and optimal logistics between several paramedical and medical
      disciplines, i.e. from pre-hospital ambulance service to intensive care. Incorporation of
      mechanical chest compressions devices (LUCAS™), rapid-response veno-arterial (VA-)ECMO
      (Cardiohelp, Maquet), and ECMO assisted revascularization in a dedicated clinical pathway
      will offer a potential lifesaving treatment option that is in accordance with the
      recommendations in the current Guidelines.

      The aim of the study is to investigate the feasibility of a new local clinical pathway to
      provide ECPR for refractory OHCA patients.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 2, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational [Patient Registry]</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <target_duration>6 Months</target_duration>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>1-year mortality</measure>
    <time_frame>assessed through study completion: at 1-year.</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse outcomes</measure>
    <time_frame>assessed through study completion: for the time in the hospital , at 30-days and at 1-year.</time_frame>
    <description>Major adverse cardiac events (MACE) (death, myocardial infarction, revascularization, stent thrombosis, stroke, bleeding)
CPR-related complications (chest wall compartment syndrome, pneumothorax, chylothorax, pulmonary hemorrhage)
ECMO-related complications (bleeding requiring transfusion or surgery, stroke, sepsis, limb ischemia requiring intervention, system or cannula change)
Other complications (acute renal failure, ulcer bleeding, pneumonia, sepsis)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Other clinical endpoints: Mortality rate - patients not treated with ECPR in comparison to patients treated with ECPR</measure>
    <time_frame>assessed through study completion: at 30-days, at 1-year after inclusion of patient</time_frame>
    <description>Mortality rate of patients treated with ECPR in comparison to refractory OHCA patients treated outside of the hours in which ECPR can take place</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of successful cannulations</measure>
    <time_frame>assessed through study completion: at 1 year and at the end of study inclusion period (expected to be at 1.5 years)</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Neurological outcome at 6 months on the cerebral performance category scale (CPC)</measure>
    <time_frame>assessed through study completion: at 6 months after inclusion of patient.</time_frame>
    <description>measured with CPC scale: CPC 1A return to normal cerebral function and normal living CPC 2 Cerebral disability but sufficient function for independent activities of daily living CPC 3 Severe disability, limited cognition, inability to carry out independent existence CPC 4 Coma CPC 5 Brain death</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of life at 6 months assessed by Short form 36 (SF-36)</measure>
    <time_frame>assessed through study completion: at 6 months after inclusion of patient.</time_frame>
    <description>measured with quality of life assesment form Short form 36 (SF-36). The SF-36 comprises 36 items and contains eight subscales: physical functioning, social functioning, physical role functioning, emotional role functioning, mental health, vitality, bodily pain and general health. Scores are expressed on a scale of 0-100, higher values indicate better quality of life and wellbeing.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of eligible / ineligible patients treated with ECPR</measure>
    <time_frame>assessed through study completion: at 1 year and at the end of study inclusion period (expected to be at 1.5 years)</time_frame>
    <description>How many patients that were treated with ECPR were retrospectively eligible for treatment with ECPR, in comparison to how many patients were treated, but not eligible.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Noted reasons for non-adherence to the eligibility criteria ECPR</measure>
    <time_frame>assessed through study completion: at 1 year and at the end of study inclusion period (expected to be at 1.5 years)</time_frame>
    <description>If patients were treated with ECPR, but were not eligible, what were reasons to do so? (for instance: no knowledge beforehand of ineligibility, or, knowledge beforehand of ineligibility but expert decision to treat, etc.)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of patients with complete data collection</measure>
    <time_frame>assessed through study completion: at 1 year and at the end of study inclusion period (expected to be at 1.5 years)</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of eligible / ineligible patients not treated with ECPR</measure>
    <time_frame>assessed through study completion: at 1 year and at the end of study inclusion period (expected to be at 1.5 years)</time_frame>
    <description>How many patients that were not treated with ECPR were retrospectively eligible for treatment with ECPR, in comparison to how many patients were not treated, and not eligible.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>30-days mortality</measure>
    <time_frame>assessed through study completion: at 30-days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">105</enrollment>
  <condition>Out-Of-Hospital Cardiac Arrest</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Extracorporeal Cardiopulmonary Resuscitation</intervention_name>
    <description>local ECPR clinical pathway, including transport with mechanical chest compression device and rapid response VA-ECMO</description>
    <other_name>Extra Corporeal Life support</other_name>
    <other_name>Extra Corporeal Membrane Oxygenation</other_name>
    <other_name>Mechanical chest compressions</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients with refractory OHCA due to VF/VT, witnessed cardiac arrest and basic life support
        before EMS arrival.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Witnessed arrest

          -  Bystander CPR initiated before EMS arrival or EMS-witnessed arrest

          -  VF/VT as first recorded rhythm by EMS or shock delivered by AED

          -  No ROSC within 10 minutes after EMS arrival

          -  Ambulance transport with mechanical chest compression device

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Confirmation of ROSC

          -  End-tidal CO2 &lt; 10 mmHg

          -  Known terminal disease (eg. cancer)

          -  Known severe comorbidity

               -  Severe chronic pulmonary disease (GOLD classification 3 or 4)

               -  Heart failure NYHA classification 3 or 4

               -  Known history of bifemoral surgery

          -  Do Not Resuscitate (DNR) order

          -  Expected time from transport decision to start ECMO &gt;60 minute
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jose P.S. Henriques</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Academisch Medisch Centrum - Universiteit van Amsterdam (AMC-UvA)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Mina Karami</last_name>
    <phone>+31643699752</phone>
    <email>m.karami@amc.uva.nl</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Academic Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Amsterdam</city>
        <state>N-Holland</state>
        <zip>1105AZ</zip>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jose Henriques, PI</last_name>
      <phone>+31205668380</phone>
      <email>j.p.henriques@amc.nl</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jose Henriques, Prof. dr.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Netherlands</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 27, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 3, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 5, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 3, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 3, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">September 5, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Academisch Medisch Centrum - Universiteit van Amsterdam (AMC-UvA)</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>J.P.S Henriques</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Prof. dr. J.P.S. Henriques</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Extra corporeal Life support</keyword>
  <keyword>extracorporeal cardiopulmonary resuscitation</keyword>
  <keyword>refractory out-of-hospital cardiac arrest</keyword>
  <keyword>extra corporeal membrane oxygenation</keyword>
  <keyword>mechanical circulatory support</keyword>
  <keyword>mechanical chest compressions</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Heart Arrest</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Out-of-Hospital Cardiac Arrest</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

