<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03656692</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MNK61074105</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03656692</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Safety and Effectiveness of Acthar Gel for Inflammation of the Eye's Uvea (Middle Layer)</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Multicenter, Open Label Pilot Study to Explore the Efficacy and Safety of Acthar Gel in Subjects With Severe Noninfectious Intermediate Uveitis, Posterior Uveitis, or Panuveitis (NIPPU)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Mallinckrodt</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Mallinckrodt</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>Yes</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The main reason for this study is to see if Acthar Gel can reduce inflammation in the uvea.

      Also, safety information when using it for this purpose will be collected.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Logistical challenges; no safety concerns
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 5, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">July 14, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">July 14, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Score on the Nussemblatt Grading Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 36</time_frame>
    <description>The Nussemblatt grading scale uses photographic measurement of cloudy, declining vision (vitreous haze). The scale goes from 0 to 4, and lower scores are better.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Score on the Laser Flare Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 36</time_frame>
    <description>Protein that escapes from blood vessels inside the eye make a sudden burst of scattered light (flare) when a laser shines on them. This is called a laser flare. It is used to measure the amount and size of proteins in the clear fluid in the front of the eyeball (aqueous humour). The larger the flare, the more inflammation is inside the eye (intraocular inflammation) in patients with uveitis. Laser flare is scored on a scale from 0 (no visible flare when compared with the normal eye) to 3 (severe - very dense flare). Lower scores are better.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Score on the Aqueous Cell Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 36</time_frame>
    <description>The number of cells (like white blood cells) floating in the aqueous humour (aqueous cells) are measured on a scale from 0 (none) to 4 (more than 30 cells), and lower scores are better.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with an adverse event</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 36</time_frame>
    <description>Clinically significant changes in clinical and ocular measurements are considered adverse events.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Diurnal Intraocular Pressure (IOP)</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 36</time_frame>
    <description>Eye pressure is measured in millimeters of mercury (mmHg). Normal eye pressure ranges from 12-22 mmHg, and eye pressure greater than 22 mmHg is considered higher than normal. During a 24-hour period, IOP normally varies by 2 to 6 mmHg because of different amounts of secretion and drainage at different times of the day. The word diurnal means &quot;around the day,&quot; and IOP means &quot;pressure inside the eye&quot;, so diurnal IOP is the measure of pressure inside the eye during a 24-hour period. Diurnal IOP is measured in millimeters of mercury (mmHg) using Goldmann Applanation Tonometry (GAT). Lower scores are better.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">5</enrollment>
  <condition>Uveitis, Posterior</condition>
  <condition>Uveitis, Intermediate</condition>
  <condition>Panuveitis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Acthar Gel</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants receive Acthar Gel as follows: 1 mL 2x/week for 36 weeks, followed by a taper to 1 mL/week for two weeks, and then 0.5 mL/week for an additional 2 weeks</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Acthar Gel</intervention_name>
    <description>Acthar gel for subcutaneous injection 80 units per mL (40 units per 0.5 mL)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Acthar Gel</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Corticotropin</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  Has been informed, understands the nature and risks of the study, and signed and dated
             the informed consent form

          -  Has diagnosis of current severe NIPPU and active disease at the Baseline Visit as
             defined by the presence of at least 1 of the following parameters in at least one eye
             despite at least 2 weeks of current or prior history of maintenance therapy with oral
             prednisone (or oral corticosteroid equivalent):

               1. Active, inflammatory, chorioretinal and/or inflammatory retinal vascular lesion

               2. At least 2+ anterior chamber cells [Standardization of Uveitis Nomenclature (SUN)
                  criteria]

               3. At least 1.5+ vitreous haze measurements (Nussenblatt et al, 1985)

          -  If on concomitant immunosuppressive therapy at screening, has not had a dose increase
             in the 2 weeks prior to screening

          -  If currently taking corticosteroids, is willing to taper current doses of
             corticosteroid and immunomodulatory therapy to the minimum effective dose during the
             study

          -  If has solid tumor malignancy, but is not currently, and has not received therapy for
             it during the 3 years prior to Screening Visit might be eligible, after consulting
             with personal oncologist

          -  If has treated and cured basal cell carcinoma, squamous cell carcinoma of the skin, or
             carcinoma in situ of the cervix might also be eligible

          -  If has a comorbid condition and is being treated with immunosuppressants and/or
             immunomodulators, has been at a stable dose at least 2 weeks prior to screening

          -  Is of nonchildbearing potential or is nonpregnant, nonlactating and agrees to use
             protocol-defined effective contraception throughout study participation until the
             Follow-up Visit

          -  Has a mean systolic blood pressure ≤ 150 mm Hg and a diastolic blood pressure of ≤ 90
             mm Hg determined by the average of 3 seated readings taken at least 5 minutes apart at
             the Screening and Baseline Visits

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Is from a vulnerable population (per 45CFR46 and/or other local and national
             regulations), including but not limited to:

               1. Employees (temporary, part-time, full time, etc)

               2. A family member of the research staff conducting the study, or of the sponsor, of
                  the clinical research organization, or of the ethics committee (IRB/IEC)

          -  Has history of sensitivity to ACTH preparations or sensitivity to porcine protein
             products

          -  Has had (within the previous 6 months) diabetic retinopathy, age-related macular
             degeneration, intraocular surgery, ocular trauma, cataracts, or posterior capsule
             opacification

          -  Had a glucocorticosteroid implant (such as Retisert®, Iluvien®, or Yutiq™) within 3
             years prior to the Baseline Visit, complications related to the device, had one
             removed within 90 days prior to the Baseline Visit, and/or had complications related
             to removal of the device

          -  Received intraocular or periocular corticosteroids within 30 days prior to Baseline
             Visit

          -  Has proliferative or severe nonproliferative diabetic retinopathy or clinically
             significant macular edema due to diabetic retinopathy

          -  Has neovascular/wet age-related macular degeneration

          -  Has an abnormality of a vitreoretinal interface (ie, vitreomacular traction,
             epiretinal membranes, etc) with the potential for macular structural damage
             independent of the inflammatory process

          -  Has a severe vitreous haze that precludes visualization of the fundus at the Baseline
             Visit

          -  Has any known contraindication(s) to Acthar Gel including, but not limited to: known
             history of scleroderma, osteoporosis, or ocular herpes simplex. For the purposes of
             this trial, osteoporosis is defined as evidence of current vertebral or long bone
             fracture, or a bone density lumbar T-score &gt; 2.0 standard deviations (SD) below the
             mean of the reference population

          -  Has primary adrenocortical insufficiency, or adrenal cortical hyperfunction

          -  Has current congestive heart failure (as defined by New York Heart Association)

          -  Has history of chronic active hepatitis including active or chronic hepatitis B, or
             acute or chronic hepatitis C

          -  Has history of tuberculosis (TB) infection, close contact with an individual with an
             active TB infection, or signs/symptoms of TB or a positive or indeterminate interferon
             gamma release assay (IGRA) for TB at screening

          -  Has known immune compromised status (not related to disease/condition under study),
             including, but not limited to individuals who have undergone organ transplantation or
             who are known to be positive for the human immunodeficiency virus

          -  Has any of the protocol-defined laboratory abnormalities at the Screening Visit

          -  Has other clinically significant disease, disorder or laboratory abnormality (even if
             included on the package insert) which the investigator thinks might put the patient at
             risk, make them unable to complete the study, or influence the study results
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Clinical Team Lead</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Mallinckrodt</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Blue Ocean Clinical Research</name>
      <address>
        <city>Clearwater</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33761</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Midwest Eye Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Indianapolis</city>
        <state>Indiana</state>
        <zip>46290</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Massachusetts Eye Research and Surgery Institution (MERSI)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Waltham</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02451</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Metropolitan Eye Research and Surgery Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Palisades Park</city>
        <state>New Jersey</state>
        <zip>07650</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Bergstrom Eye Research, LLC</name>
      <address>
        <city>Fargo</city>
        <state>North Dakota</state>
        <zip>58103</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Valley Retina Institute, PA</name>
      <address>
        <city>McAllen</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>78503</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Foresight Studies, LLC</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Antonio</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>78240</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Virginia Eye Consultants</name>
      <address>
        <city>Norfolk</city>
        <state>Virginia</state>
        <zip>23502</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 21, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 30, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 4, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 14, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 14, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 16, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Uveitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Panuveitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Uveitis, Posterior</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Uveitis, Intermediate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pars Planitis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Adrenocorticotropic Hormone</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

