<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03652168</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>UCM2018-9</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03652168</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Stress Free UC Merced: The Effect of 8 Weeks of Mindfulness App Headspace on Stress in a Sample of University Employees</brief_title>
  <official_title>Stress Free UC Merced: The Effect of 8 Weeks of Mindfulness App Headspace on Stress in a Sample of University Employees</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of California, Merced</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Healthy Campus Network, University of California, Office of the President</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Headspace Meditation Limited</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of California, Merced</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The aim of this study is to investigate the effects of the app-based mindfulness intervention
      (i.e., the commercially available application Headspace) on overall physical and
      psychological health. Secondly, this study examines potential mindfulness mechanisms that may
      be driving these effects (i.e., decentering, attention regulation, acceptance,
      self-compassion, reactivity, exposure).

      This study will randomize UC Merced employees to 8-weeks of either a digital mindfulness
      intervention (Headspace) or a waitlist control condition. Participants assigned to the
      intervention group will be asked to download and use the Headspace mobile application for 10
      minutes per day for 8 weeks. They will be asked to fill out questionnaires at baseline, week
      4, week 8 (post intervention), 4-month, and 12-month follow up period (20-30 minutes each
      time). In addition, participants will be asked to complete surveys on their phone as a part
      of everyday life assessments (4 days per week during baseline, 2 weeks, 5 weeks, 8 weeks, up
      to 5-10 minutes a day). Participants will also wear a fitness watch, Fitbit, to assess their
      activity, sleep, and heart rate data. For the everyday life assessment part, participants
      will be asked to participate in one of our 60 minutes orientation sessions where you will
      receive training on using the mobile app and receive a fitness watch that will be collected
      upon the completion of the study.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Stress at work has shown to be an important health risk for employees. It is associated with
      poor mental and physical health including anxiety, depression, sleep disturbances,
      gastrointestinal problems, type 2 diabetes, and cardiovascular disease. Work stress also has
      major implications for employers as evidence suggests that high levels of work stress predict
      employee burnout, turnover intent, absenteeism, and poor job performance.

      Mindfulness and its positive effects on a variety of outcomes, including stress reduction,
      have been documented in many studies. The most common definition of mindfulness is as the
      state of being attentive to and aware of the present moment with an attitude of openness and
      acceptance. Several mechanisms by which mindfulness exerts its positive effects have been
      proposed in the literature including cultivating the attitude of non-judgement and
      acceptance, ability to observe one's experiences objectively without reacting to them, and
      ability to be more patient and kind toward oneself. Recent evidence suggests that teaching
      mindfulness in the workplace not only reduces stress but also improve psychological
      well-being.

      With advances in technology, technology-based delivery of many interventions has become
      popular. App-based treatments for improving psychological health are becoming increasingly
      important due to high accessibility and cost-effectiveness of smartphone technology. Despite
      a great number of app-based interventions, there has been little research evaluating their
      efficacy. Support for the use of smartphone app-based mindfulness interventions comes from a
      few small studies that found these interventions to produce benefits comparable to
      traditional delivery methods. While app-based interventions offer a convenient alternative to
      traditional delivery methods as well as promising initial empirical evidence, more research
      is needed in order to further evaluate and promote these interventions.

      The proposed study has several goals. The first goal is to investigate the effects of the
      app-based mindfulness intervention on overall physical and psychological health (e.g.,
      perceived stress, mindfulness, sleep quality, self-reported health, anxiety symptoms). The
      second goal is to examine the effect of the intervention on a variety of work-related
      outcomes (e.g., work stress, job satisfaction, work-related burnout). Further, the study will
      examine potential mindfulness mechanisms that may drive these effects (e.g., acceptance,
      reactivity, decentering).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">September 1, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 31, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 31, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>The party or parties involved in the clinical trial who are prevented from having knowledge of the interventions assigned to individual participants.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>10-Item Measure of Stress Perceptions</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from Baseline Stress Perceptions at 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Self-reported stress perceptions over the over the past month. Each item is scored using a 0 (never) and 4 (very often) scale. Items are averaged together such that scores can range from 0 to 40; higher scores indicate higher perceived stress. Total score ranging from 0-13 would be considered low stress. Score ranging from 14-26 would be considered moderate stress. Score ranging from 27-40 would be considered high perceived stress.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>9-Item Measure of Symptoms of Depression and Distress</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from Baseline Depression at 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Self-reported symptoms of depression and distress over the last two weeks. Answers range from 0 (not at all) to 4 (nearly every day). Scores are added across columns to get a total score. Scores can range from 0 to 36, the lowest score of 1- 4 indicate minimal depression; higher scores 20-27 indicating severe depression.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>7-Item Measure of Symptoms of Anxiety</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from Baseline Anxiety at 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Self-reported symptoms of anxiety over the last two weeks. Answers range from 0 (not at all) to 4 (nearly every day). Scores are added across columns to get a total score. Scores can range from 0 to 28 and scores of 5, 10, and 15 are taken as the cut-off points for mild, moderate and severe anxiety, respectively.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>15-Item Measure of Mindfulness - a receptive state of mind in which attention, informed by a sensitive awareness of what is occurring in the present</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from Baseline Mindfulness at 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Self-reported mindfulness ratings participants report on average each day. Answers are given on a 1 (almost always) to 6 (almost never) scale. Total score is calculated by computing a mean of the 15 items. Scores can range from 15 to 90 with higher scores reflect higher levels of dispositional mindfulness.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>19-Item Measure of Sleep Quality</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from Baseline Sleep Quality at 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Self-reported measure of sleep quality over the last month. The self-rated items are combined to form seven &quot;component&quot; scores, each of which has a range of 0-3 points. In all cases, a total score of &quot;0&quot; indicates no difficulty and &quot;21&quot; indicating severe difficulties in all areas.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>1-Item Measure of Leisure Physical Activity</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from Baseline Physical Activity at 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Self-reported measure of physical activity performed on average during leisure activity over the past month. Item is scored on a 0 (no physical activity) to 4 (vigorous activity at least 3 times a week) scale</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Resting Heart Rate</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from Baseline Resting Heart Rate at 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The Fitbit watch worn during the intervention will assess resting heart rate levels each day.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>12-Item Subjective Mental and Physical Well-Being Ratings</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from Baseline Self-reported health at 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Self-reported measure of views about mental and physical well-being on average. The items are scored on a 0 to 100 and averaged, where a zero score indicates the lowest level of health measured by the scales and 100 indicates the highest level of health.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>3-Item Job Satisfaction Measure</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from Job Satisfaction at 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Self-reported assessment of average levels of job satisfaction. Items are scored on a 1 (Disagree very much) to 6 (Agree very much) with an average total score across items ranging from 3 to 18.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>5-Item Work-Family Balance Measure of emotional, behavioral and time demands of both paid work and family (if relevant) or personal duties.</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from Baseline Work-family Balance at 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Self-reported measure of work-family balance on average. Items are scores on a 1 (strongly disagree) to 7 (strongly agree) scale. Items are averaged together with the total score ranging from 5 to 35.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">200</enrollment>
  <condition>Stress</condition>
  <condition>Psychological Distress</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Meditation Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Headspace application: Participants in the intervention group will use a digitally-based mindfulness intervention Headspace app (Basics + Stress packs) will be used for 10 minutes a day over the course of 8 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>No intervention, control group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Control group participants will continue their normal activities and not add any form of meditation during the study period.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Meditation</intervention_name>
    <description>10 minute a day, 8 week digital meditation</description>
    <arm_group_label>Meditation Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Have access to a smartphone or computer with internet every day

          -  Are fluent in English

          -  Are a UC Merced employee

          -  Consent: demonstrate understanding of the study and willingness to participate as
             evidenced by voluntary informed consent and has received a signed and dated copy of
             the informed consent

          -  Are at least 18 years of age

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Individuals may not join if they are experienced meditators or have participated in a
             sitting meditation practice more than twice a week (for 10 minutes or greater) over
             the last three months.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Matthew J Zawadzki, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>UC Merced</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Matthew J Zawadzki, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>(209) 228-4787</phone>
    <email>mzawadzki@ucmerced.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Larisa Gavrilova, BA</last_name>
    <email>lgavrilova@ucmerced.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of California, Merced</name>
      <address>
        <city>Merced</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>95343</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bishop, S. R., Lau, M., Shapiro, S., Carlson, L., Anderson, N. D., Carmody, J., ... &amp; Devins, G. (2004). Mindfulness: A proposed operational definition. Clinical psychology: Science and practice, 11(3), 230-241.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Brown KW, Ryan RM. The benefits of being present: mindfulness and its role in psychological well-being. J Pers Soc Psychol. 2003 Apr;84(4):822-48.</citation>
    <PMID>12703651</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ganster, D. C., &amp; Rosen, C. C. (2013). Work stress and employee health: A multidisciplinary review. Journal of Management, 39(5), 1085-1122.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Goedhard, R. G., &amp; Goedhard, W. J. (2005, June). Work ability and perceived work stress. In International Congress Series(Vol. 1280, pp. 79-83). Elsevier.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jamieson SD, Tuckey MR. Mindfulness interventions in the workplace: A critique of the current state of the literature. J Occup Health Psychol. 2017 Apr;22(2):180-193. doi: 10.1037/ocp0000048. Epub 2016 Sep 19. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>27643606</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fairburn CG, Patel V. The impact of digital technology on psychological treatments and their dissemination. Behav Res Ther. 2017 Jan;88:19-25. doi: 10.1016/j.brat.2016.08.012. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>28110672</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Howells, A., Ivtzan, I., &amp; Eiroa-Orosa, F. J. (2016). Putting the 'app'in happiness: a randomised controlled trial of a smartphone-based mindfulness intervention to enhance wellbeing. Journal of Happiness Studies, 17(1), 163-185.</citation>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>August 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 17, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 27, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 29, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 27, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 27, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">August 29, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of California, Merced</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Matthew Zawadzki</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>stress</keyword>
  <keyword>health</keyword>
  <keyword>mindfulness</keyword>
  <keyword>employees</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

