<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03653104</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>1802361245</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03653104</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Melodica Orchestra for Dyspnea: Safety and Feasibility Pilot</brief_title>
  <acronym>MELODY</acronym>
  <official_title>Melodica Orchestra for Dyspnea: Safety and Feasibility Pilot</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>VA Quality Enhancement Research Intiative</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>VA Quality Enhancement Research Intiative</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This project seeks to pilot-test the feasibility of using a melodica training program to
      teach pursed lip breathing for Veterans with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD)
      with moderate to severe dyspnea (shortness of breath). Dyspnea occurs commonly among COPD
      patients and can limit activities of daily living. Pursed lip breathing is a strategy that
      can improve dyspnea and exercise capacity among COPD patients. The melodica is a musical
      instrument that looks like a keyboard with a mouthpiece on the side. The melodica is played
      by exhaling through the mouthpiece while pressing the keys. The MELODY pilot project protocol
      has been grounded on concepts from occupational therapy; specifically, providing participants
      with a meaningful new activity that is enjoyable, that can be provided across a spectrum of
      skill levels, that can provide participants with a new sense of self, and that can improve
      health outcomes (i.e., dyspnea and exercise endurance).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      SPECIFIC AIMS:

      Primary Aim 1: Evaluate the safety of a melodica training program to teach pursed lip
      breathing among Veterans with COPD with moderate to severe dyspnea. We hypothesize that a
      melodica training program can be safely implemented among COPD patients with severe dyspnea.

      Primary Aim 2: Evaluate the feasibility of implementing a melodica training program to teach
      pursed lip breathing among Veterans with COPD with dyspnea. We hypothesize that it will be
      feasible to implement a melodica training program to teach pursed lip breathing among
      Veterans with COPD and dyspnea; specifically that enrolled participants will attend &gt;50% of
      sessions. We also hypothesize that transportation to the VA Medical Center to attend sessions
      will be identified as a significant barrier to participation.

      Secondary Aim: Collect pilot-efficacy data of a melodica training program to teach pursed lip
      breathing among Veterans with COPD and dyspnea. The objective is to understand whether
      melodica training improves dyspnea both in the short-term and in the longer-term over the
      course of the 8-week training program. We hypothesize that a melodica training program will
      reduce dyspnea by 30% in the short-term and 10% in the long-term. We also hypothesize that
      intervention participants will show gains in the secondary efficacy outcome measures of
      exercise endurance, pulmonary function, entering pulmonary rehabilitation, quality of life,
      patient global impression of change, and anxiety relative to controls.

      RANDOMIZATION AND INTERVENTION:

      Randomization:

      Participants will be randomized in a 1:1:1 ratio to the intervention group (N=50), usual care
      control group (N=50), and education control group (N=50) using a block randomization design.
      We will also seek to identify N=30 Veterans who met the COPD diagnosis and spirometry
      eligibility criteria but who chose not to participate in the intervention; these Veterans
      will be invited to participate in a brief interview to identify barriers to participation.

      Melodica Program Intervention:

      The intervention program will include: education about pursed lip breathing, instruction in
      the melodica instrument, and participation in a melodica playing group which will meet
      twice-weekly for a 8-week period. Participants will be given instructional materials for use
      in practicing the instrument in their homes and encouragement to use pursed lip breathing not
      only while playing the instrument but also in their activities of daily living. Each session
      will last one hour in duration with approximately 20 minutes for instruction, 30 minutes in
      group music-making, and 10 minutes allocated for educational information about COPD, tobacco
      cessation, and pulmonary rehabilitation.

      Education Group:

      The patients in the education control group will receive the same educational materials that
      are provided to the intervention group; however, they will receive them in a single
      educational session. As described above, the educational materials include information about
      pursed lip breathing, COPD, medications used to treat COPD, how to use an inhaler, smoking
      cessation, pulmonary rehabilitation, oxygen therapy, exercise, and travelling with COPD. The
      materials include handouts as well as links to web pages.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 12, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>This is a safety and feasibility pilot with a single intervention arm, an education control arm, a usual care control arm, and an interview only arm. The intervention arm includes participation in the melodica training program and education about pulmonary health. The education control arm includes pulmonary health education only. The interview only arm includes participation in a semi-structured interview about facilitators and barriers to participation.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
    <masking_description>No masking</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety: Adverse Events</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured at baseline and before and after each of 16 program training sessions (8 week duration).</time_frame>
    <description>We will describe the frequency with which patients reported any adverse events they experienced as a consequence of participation in the program as well as specify the types of adverse events.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety: Dyspnea Visual Analog Line</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, before and after each training session (16 sessions over 8 weeks)</time_frame>
    <description>We will measure dyspnea with a visual-analog line (100mm line with anchors at 0=no dyspnea, 100=severe dyspnea)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Feasibility: Program Participation</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured at baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Feasibility will be measured in terms of the proportion of eligible Veterans who agree to participate</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Feasibility: Attendance</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured at every intervention session (total of 16 sessions over 8 weeks)</time_frame>
    <description>Feasibility will be measured in terms of the proportion of sessions that enrolled participants attend</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Pilot-Efficacy: Dyspnea Visual Analog Line</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, before and after each intervention sessions (16 sessionis over 8 weeks).</time_frame>
    <description>We will measure dyspnea with a visual-analog line (100mm line with anchors at 0=no dyspnea, 100=severe dyspnea)</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Secondary Efficacy: Quality of Life (SF-20)</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured at baseline, 4-weeks, 8-weeks</time_frame>
    <description>We will assess quality of life based on the 20-item Short Form Health Survey (SF-20)</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Secondary Efficacy: Exercise Endurance (6-Minute Walk)</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured at baseline, 4-weeks, 8-weeks</time_frame>
    <description>We will assess exercise endurance measured by the 6-Minute Walk Test (6MWT).</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">161</enrollment>
  <condition>COPD</condition>
  <condition>Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease</condition>
  <condition>Dyspnea</condition>
  <condition>Breathlessness</condition>
  <condition>Emphysema</condition>
  <condition>Chronic Bronchitis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Melodica Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>An 8-week group intervention including twice-weekly sessions. Each session will last one hour in duration with approximately 20 minutes for instruction, 30 minutes in group music-making, and 10 minutes allocated for educational information about COPD, tobacco cessation, and pulmonary rehabilitation.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Education Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>A single 90-120 minute education session including the same educational information about COPD, tobacco cessation, and pulmonary rehabilitation provided to the melodica intervention group.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Usual Care Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Usual care at Richard L. Roudebush VA Medical Center.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Interview Only</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Semi-structured interviews will be conducted with Veterans who meet eligibility criteria, but who do not agree to participate in the intervention, to identify potential barriers to participation</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Melodica Intervention</intervention_name>
    <description>The melodica program will include education about pursed lip breathing, instruction in the melodica instrument, and participation in a melodica training group which meets twice-weekly for an 8-week period. Each session will include musical instruction, group music-making, and education about COPD and related health topics.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Melodica Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Melodica Training Program</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pulmonary Health Education</intervention_name>
    <description>A single session including education about COPD and related health topics.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Education Control</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  spirometry-confirmed COPD defined as a FEV1/FVC &lt;0.7

          -  moderate or severe dyspnea defined as a grade ≥3 on the ATS Dyspnea scale

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  visual or hearing impairments

          -  do not speak English

          -  do not have an intact airway

          -  have cognitive impairment

          -  are unable to make a seal with their mouths

          -  have a history of at least one hospital admission for congestive heart failure in the
             prior year

          -  receiving Hospital-Based Home Care (HBHC) or Telehealth care for COPD management
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Dawn M Bravata, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>VA Quality Enhancement Research Initiative</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Veteran Health Indiana, Richard L. Roudebush VA Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Indianapolis</city>
        <state>Indiana</state>
        <zip>46202</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 21, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 28, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 31, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 9, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 9, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">September 10, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>VA Quality Enhancement Research Intiative</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Dawn M. Bravata</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor of Medicine &amp; Adjunct Professor of Neurology</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Melodica</keyword>
  <keyword>pursed lip breathing</keyword>
  <keyword>breathing exercise</keyword>
  <keyword>Music</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lung Diseases, Obstructive</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pulmonary Disease, Chronic Obstructive</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dyspnea</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Bronchitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Bronchitis, Chronic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Emphysema</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

