<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03657706</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CEBD-CU-2018-06-34</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03657706</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Tunneling Technique in Treatment of Miller`s Class III Gingival Recession</brief_title>
  <official_title>Analysis of the Aesthetic Outcome After Root Coverage Using Tunneling Technique With Subepithelial Connective Tissue Graft Versus Tunneling Technique With Modified Free Gingival Graft in Miller`s Class III Recession Defect: a Randomized Clinical Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Cairo University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Cairo University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Several surgical techniques have been proposed to correct recession defect and attain root
      coverage. Though, the majority were executed on Miller Class I and II recession defects.
      Moreover, Analysis of literature revealed only a few studies that treated miller class III
      recession defects.

      In the current study, a new modification in the free gingival graft is proposed to provide
      the patient with more esthetic outcome, less pain and postoperative trauma. Likewise, the
      proposed graft modification will combined both FGG and CTG benefits, overcome the limitations
      of the FGG and enhances the advantages of CTG.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      In the current study, patients with Miller`s class III will be randomly allocated in two
      groups. In the first group, gingival recession will be treated by tunneling technique with
      subepithelial connective tissue graft (sCTG). the tunnel preparation will be performed in the
      recession site then the sCTG will be harvested from the palate and inserted in the prepared
      tunnel and sutured in a coronally advanced position.

      Equally , the second group will be treated with modified free gingival graft (mFGG).
      Initially, after tunnel preparation in the recession site and harvesting of the free gingival
      graft,the proposed modification is performed by mimicking the recession defect shape and size
      leaving the rest of the free gingival graft deepithelialized and inserted in the prepared
      tunnel. then, suturing will be performed in a coronally advanced position.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 15, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>root coverage aesthetic score (RES)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>RES evaluated five variables 6 months: gingival margin (GM), marginal tissue contour (MTC), soft tissue texture (STT), MGJ alignment, and gingival color (GC). Zero, 3, or 6 points were used for the evaluation of the position of the gingival margin, whereas a score of 0 or 1 point was used for each of the other variables.
The ideal esthetic score was 10. Zero points were assigned if the final position of the gingival margin was equal or apical to the previous recession depth (failure of root coverage procedure), irrespective of color, the presence of a scar, MTC, or MGJ. Zero points were also assigned when a partial or total loss of interproximal papilla (black triangle) occurred following the treatment</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>recession depth</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Measured from the cemento-enamel junction the most apical extension of the gingival margin.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">22</enrollment>
  <condition>Gingival Recession</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>group A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>tunnel procedure with subepithelial connective tissue graft (sCTG)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>group B</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>tunnel procedure with modified free gingival graft (mFGG)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>group A (Tunnel procedure with subepithelial connective tissue graft (sCTG)</intervention_name>
    <description>Subepithelial connective tissue graft (autogenous graft) will be harvested from the palate by Single incision technique to be used with the prepared tunnel to treating gingival recession</description>
    <arm_group_label>group A</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Tunnel procedure with subepithelial connective tissue graft (sCTG)</other_name>
    <other_name>Autogenous sCTG will be used with tunnel procedure</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>group B (Tunnel procedure with modified free gingival graft (mFGG))</intervention_name>
    <description>modified free gingival graft (autogenous graft) will be harvested from the palate and will be used with the prepared tunnel to be used in treating gingival recession</description>
    <arm_group_label>group B</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Tunnel procedure with modified free gingival graft (mFGG)</other_name>
    <other_name>Autogenous mFGG will be used with tunnel procedure</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients with healthy systemic condition.

          2. Buccal recession defects classified as Miller class III.

          3. Clinical indication and/or patient request for recession coverage.

          4. O'Leary index less than 20%.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Pregnant females.

          2. Smokers as smoking is a contraindication for any plastic periodontal surgery.

          3. Unmotivated, uncooperative patients with poor oral hygiene

          4. Patients with habits that may compromise the longevity and affect the result of the
             study as alcoholism or para-functional habits.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>60 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cairo university</name>
      <address>
        <city>Giza</city>
        <country>Egypt</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Egypt</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 26, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 4, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 5, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 4, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 4, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">September 5, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Cairo University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Nourhan Abdallah Abdelkhalek</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principle investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Gingival Recession</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>all the study records may be shared except that include participant name or personal information identifiers</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

