<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03659266</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2017-69</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03659266</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effects of Combined Treatment by Botulinum Toxin and Lokomat® on Walking Ability in Chronic Stroke</brief_title>
  <acronym>Lokomat</acronym>
  <official_title>Effects of Combined Treatment by Botulinum Toxin A and Robot-Assisted Gait Training (Lokomat®) on Walking Ability in Patients With Chronic Stroke: a Prospective, Controlled, Randomized Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Assistance Publique Hopitaux De Marseille</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Assistance Publique Hopitaux De Marseille</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      75% patients in the chronic phase of a stroke keep walking disabilities. Focal spasticity in
      the paretic lower limb frequently causes these walking disabilities, and the gold standard
      treatment is intramuscular injection of Botulinum toxin A in the spastic muscles.

      To potentiate the effects of toxin, walking rehabilitation is usually prescribed in the weeks
      following injection, but the protocols vary and few have been evaluated in the medical
      literature.

      In particular, the effect on walking ability of combined treatment by botulinum toxin A and
      robot-assisted gait training has never been evaluated.

      Tested hypothesis: Robot-assisted gait training by Lokomat® motorized exoskeleton potentiates
      botulinum toxin's effects better than conventional walking therapy.

      The aim of this study was to evaluate the effects on walking ability of the association of
      focal spasticity treatment by Botulinum toxin and Lokomat-assisted walking rehabilitation in
      patients suffering from spastic hemiparesia after stroke in the chronic phase.

      Outcome:

      -Primary: distance walked (meters) in the six-minute walk test (SMWT)

      Prospective, randomized, controlled, opened, monocentric study with a crossover design.

      Recruitment of patients over 18 years of age, in the chronic phase of stroke, who have
      already been treated by Botulinum toxin injection for focal spasticity in our PMR ward.

      Assessment at Day one (D0), Week four (W4) and Week eight (W8).

      Following a preliminary study which had the six-minute walk test as a secondary outcome, the
      expected results are a significant improvement of the distance walked in the SMWT after
      robotic rehabilitation, and a lack of significant improvement following conventional therapy.

      The study should serve to further harmonize and optimize rehabilitation protocols after toxin
      injections, and to justify the use of robotic rehabilitation for patients in the chronic
      phase of stroke.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Introduction :

      75% patients in the chronic phase of a stroke (&gt;6 months) keep walking disabilities. Focal
      spasticity in the paretic lower limb frequently causes these walking disabilities, and the
      gold standard treatment is intramuscular injection of Botulinum toxin A in the spastic
      muscles.

      To potentiate the effects of toxin, walking rehabilitation is usually prescribed in the weeks
      following injection, but the protocols vary and few have been evaluated in the medical
      literature.

      In particular, the effect on walking ability of combined treatment by botulinum toxin A and
      robot-assisted gait training has never been evaluated.

      Materials and Methods:

      Tested hypothesis:

      Robot-assisted gait training by Lokomat® motorized exoskeleton potentiates botulinum toxin's
      effects better than conventional walking therapy.

      Aims:

        -  Primary: to evaluate the effects on walking ability of the association of focal
           spasticity treatment by Botulinum toxin and Lokomat-assisted walking rehabilitation in
           patients suffering from spastic hemiparesia after stroke in the chronic phase.

        -  Secondary: to determine the optimal time between the toxin injection and the start of
           robotic rehabilitation; to evaluate the effects of the combined treatment on the balance
           and spasticity.

      Outcome:

        -  Primary: distance walked (meters) in the six-minute walk test (SMWT)

        -  Secondary: walking speed (meters/seconds), balance (Timed Up and Go Test, Berg Balance
           Scale), spasticity (score on the Modified Ashworth Scale and joint range of motion)

      Study Design:

      Prospective, randomized, controlled, opened, monocentric study with a crossover design.

      Recruitment of patients over 18 years of age, in the chronic phase of stroke, who have
      already been treated by Botulinum toxin injection for focal spasticity in our PMR ward.

      Assessment at Day one (D0), Week four (W4) and Week eight (W8).

        1. st Group D0: Injection of Botulinum toxin A in triceps surae, according to
           pre-established modalities (no influence of the experimental protocol on this stage)
           W2-W4: Robotic walking rehabilitation by Lokomat® in the functional rehabilitation
           department (conventional hospitalization) W4-W6: Return to home, &quot;wash-out&quot;period W6-W8:
           Conventional walking rehabilitation in the functional rehabilitation department
           (conventional hospitalization)

        2. nd Group: D0: Injection of Botulinum toxin A in triceps surae W2-W4: Conventional
           walking rehabilitation in the functional rehabilitation department (conventional
           hospitalization) W4-W6: Return to home, &quot;wash-out&quot;period W6-W8: Robotic walking
           rehabilitation by Lokomat® in the functional rehabilitation department (conventional
           hospitalization)

      Expected results:

      Following a preliminary study which had the six-minute walk test as a secondary outcome, the
      expected results are a significant improvement of the distance walked in the SMWT after
      robotic rehabilitation, and a lack of significant improvement following conventional therapy.

      The study should serve to further harmonize and optimize rehabilitation protocols after toxin
      injections, and to justify the use of robotic rehabilitation for patients in the chronic
      phase of stroke.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">November 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Time of Ten-meter walk test</measure>
    <time_frame>20 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>Time is measure while the individual walks the set distance (10 meters). the distance covered is divided by the time it took the individual to walk that distance</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">15</enrollment>
  <condition>Stroke</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>D0: Injection of Botulinum toxin A in triceps surae, according to pre-established modalities (no influence of the experimental protocol on this stage) W2-W4: Robotic walking rehabilitation by Lokomat® in the functional rehabilitation department (conventional hospitalization) W4-W6: Return to home, &quot;wash-out&quot;period W6-W8: Conventional walking rehabilitation in the functional rehabilitation department (conventional hospitalization)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>group 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>D0: Injection of Botulinum toxin A in triceps surae W2-W4: Conventional walking rehabilitation in the functional rehabilitation department (conventional hospitalization) W4-W6: Return to home, &quot;wash-out&quot;period W6-W8: Robotic walking rehabilitation by Lokomat® in the functional rehabilitation department (conventional hospitalization)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Robotic walking rehabilitation by Lokomat®</intervention_name>
    <description>Lokomat sessions / week for 2 weeks. Each session lasts 45 minutes including 30 minutes of effective work of the march and 15 minutes of setting up.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>group 2</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Conventional walking rehabilitation</intervention_name>
    <description>5 physiotherapy sessions / week for 2 weeks. Each session lasts 45 minutes including 30 minutes of walking and 15 minutes of stretching</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>group 2</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age between 18 and 80 years

          -  Left or right spastic hemiparesia after a single unilateral hemorrhagic or ischemic
             stroke, in chronic phase (at least 6 months after stroke)

          -  Functional hindrance in walking

          -  Spasticity of paretic triceps surae allowing for focal treatment by Botulinum toxin
             injection

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Inability to walk with or without technical aids &gt;5min

          -  Cognitive disorders disallowing informed consent

          -  Spasticity equal or superior to 4 on the triceps surae (On the Modified Ashworth
             Scale)

          -  Physical exercise not allowed: non stable cardiovascular or pulmonary disease in
             particular

          -  Lokomat® use not allowed: cutaneous lesions that could come in contact with the
             straps, non consolidated recent fracture (&lt;3months), severe disability in controlling
             trunk balance disallowing correct posture in Lokomat®, intra-abdominal cranial flap,
             weight&gt;135kg
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>EMILIE GARRIDO PRADALIE</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>APHM</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>LAURENT BENSOUSSAN, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+33491385605</phone>
    <email>Laurent.BENSOUSSAN@ap-hm.fr</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Assistance Publique Des Hopitaux de Marseille</name>
      <address>
        <city>Marseille</city>
        <state>Paca</state>
        <zip>13354</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>LAURENT BENSOUSSAN, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+33491385605</phone>
      <email>Laurent.BENSOUSSAN@ap-hm.fr</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 3, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 3, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 6, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 3, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 3, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">September 6, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Stroke</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

