<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03653728</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NTEC-2018-0106</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03653728</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Near Infra-red Spectroscopy for Detection of Intracranial Haematoma</brief_title>
  <official_title>Non-invasive Neuro-monitoring for Head Injury: Use of Near Infra-red Spectroscopy for Early Detection of Delayed Intracranial Haematoma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Chinese University of Hong Kong</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Chinese University of Hong Kong</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Fall with head injury is becoming an epidemic challenge especially with the ageing
      population. Contributing factors for mortality and poor functional outcome included
      development of cerebral contusion and delayed traumatic intracerebral haematoma. There is a
      higher prevalence especially with the increasing use of antiplatelets and anticoagulants.

      Non-invasive monitoring such as near-infrared spectroscopy (NIRS) is sensitive in detecting
      intracranial changes. The role and efficacy of this non-invasive method has not been
      specifically established in patients with head injury as an initial non-operative monitoring.
      This is particular important in the setting of a general ward in which nursing staff is
      limited. The advantages of these noninvasive monitoring might have a role of continuous
      neuro-monitoring. They can also potentially reduce the number of unnecessary repeated CT
      Brain in the context of limited radiology staff and resources. Timely detection and treatment
      of this condition accordingly is crucial. Potential options of non-invasive monitoring such
      as nearinfrared spectroscopy (NIRS) is to be investigated.

      The aim of this study is to determine the sensitivity and specificity of NIRS as a
      non-invasive monitoring in detecting delayed intracranial injuries in comparison with the
      Gold Standard CT Brain. Study design is Prospective sensitivity and specificity study of Near
      Infra-red Spectroscopy (NIRS) as a non-invasive monitoring in detecting delayed intracranial
      injuries in comparison with the Gold Standard CT Brain in Hong Kong Chinese. Consecutive
      patients admitted to Prince of Wales Hospital, Hong Kong would be recruited. Outcome measures
      including correlation of non-invasive monitoring with near-infrared spectroscopy (NIRS) to CT
      Brain findings including any increase in haematoma size, cerebral edema or mass effect.
      Secondary outcome including 30 days mortality and functional outcome at 3 months.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Introduction: Fall with head injury is becoming an epidemic challenge especially with the
      ageing population. Contributing factors for mortality and poor functional outcome included
      development of cerebral contusion and delayed traumatic intracerebral haematoma. There is a
      higher prevalence especially with the increasing use of antiplatelets and anticoagulants.

      Non-invasive monitoring such as near-infrared spectroscopy (NIRS) is sensitive in detecting
      intracranial changes. The role and efficacy of this non-invasive method has not been
      specifically established in patients with head injury as an initial non-operative monitoring.
      This is particular important in the setting of a general ward in which nursing staff is
      limited. The advantages of these non-invasive monitoring might have a role of continuous
      neuro-monitoring. They can also potentially reduce the number of unnecessary repeated CT
      Brain in the context of limited radiology staff and resources.

      Timely detection and treatment of this condition accordingly is crucial. Potential options of
      non-invasive monitoring such as near-infrared spectroscopy (NIRS) is to be investigated.

      Aims and Hypotheses to be tested:

      The aim of this study is to determine the sensitivity and specificity of near-infrared
      spectroscopy (NIRS) as a non-invasive monitoring in detecting delayed intracranial injuries
      in comparison with the Gold Standard CT Brain.

      Plan of Investigation:

      This is a prospective sensitivity and specificity correlation study of Near Infra-red
      Spectroscopy (NIRS) as a non-invasive monitoring in detecting delayed intracranial injuries
      in comparison with the Gold Standard CT Brain in Hong Kong Chinese. Consecutive patients
      admitted to Prince of Wales Hospital, Hong Kong would be recruited.

      Consecutive patients fulfilling the inclusion and exclusion criteria are treated with
      standard of care with near-infrared spectroscopy (NIRS). Criteria to proceed for repeat CT
      Brain scan 1) clinical deterioration of GCS &gt;2 points, 2) NIRS monitoring has increase in
      difference in absorbance of light at 760nm &gt;0.3, or 3) 8 hours after admission for baseline
      interval scan for all patients as part of the standard of care. Non-invasive monitoring with
      near-infrared spectroscopy (NIRS) would be applied to all patients' forehead for
      consecutively 48 hours after admission.

      Inclusion criteria

        1. Age greater than or equal to 18 years old,

        2. History of traumatic brain injury,

        3. Radiological evidence of intracranial haematoma,

        4. Glasgow Coma Scale (GCS) less than 15 upon admission,

        5. Not undergoing immediate operation,

        6. Admission to the general ward or high dependence unit of Neurosurgery, Prince of Wales
           Hospital.

      Exclusion criteria

        1. Presence of frontal scalp laceration preventing the application of non-invasive
           monitoring on the forehead,

        2. Presence of pneumocephale,

        3. Requirement of immediate surgical intervention as judged by the on-call neurosurgeon.

        4. Patients who have joined other drug trial in the last four weeks;

        5. Pregnant or on breast feeding;

        6. Any other reasons that the researchers consider unsuitable.

      Primary outcome - Correlation coefficient of near-infrared spectroscopy (NIRS) to CT Brain
      findings including any increase in haematoma size, cerebral edema or mass effect.

      Secondary outcomes

      - Secondary outcome including number of CT scan performed, correlation of NIRS reading with
      Glasgow coma scale (GCS), rate of intervention with either medical treatment such as use of
      mannitol, Transamin or blood product transfusion, or surgical treatment such as operation, 30
      days mortality and functional outcome at 3 months.

      Purpose and Potential:

      Near-infrared spectroscopy (NIRS) can offer continuous neuro-monitoring. This is particular
      important in the setting of a general ward in which nursing staff is limited. This allows
      early detection of delayed haematoma for early intervention. At the same time, the use of
      NIRS can potentially reduce the number of unnecessary repeated CT Brain in the context of
      limited radiology staff and resources.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">April 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 31, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 31, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational [Patient Registry]</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <target_duration>1 Year</target_duration>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Correlation coefficient</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week</time_frame>
    <description>Correlation coefficient of near-infrared spectroscopy (NIRS) to CT Brain findings including any increase in haematoma size, cerebral edema or mass effect.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>30 days mortality</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days</time_frame>
    <description>30 days mortality</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>modified Rankin Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>modified Rankin Scale at 3 months</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>correlation of NIRS reading with Glasgow coma scale (GCS)</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week</time_frame>
    <description>correlation of NIRS reading with Glasgow coma scale (GCS)</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Number of CT performed</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week</time_frame>
    <description>Number of CT performed</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Other intervention such as blood product transfusion or operation</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week</time_frame>
    <description>Other intervention such as blood product transfusion or operation</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">24</enrollment>
  <condition>Traumatic Brain Injury</condition>
  <condition>Intracerebral Hemorrhage</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Traumatic brain injury with cerebral contusions</arm_group_label>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Near infrared spectroscopy</intervention_name>
    <description>All patients would be receiving the same treatment including application of non-invasive monitoring with near-infrared spectroscopy (NIRS) together with the standard of care with interval CT Brain scan for all patients.
Non-invasive monitoring with near-infrared spectroscopy (NIRS) is very safe and is in current daily routine clinical use for intraoperative patients.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Traumatic brain injury with cerebral contusions</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Consecutive traumatic brain injury patients fulfilling the inclusion and exclusion criteria
        are treated with standard of care with near-infrared spectroscopy (NIRS).
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Age greater than or equal to 18 years old,

          2. History of traumatic brain injury,

          3. Radiological evidence of intracranial haematoma,

          4. Glasgow Coma Scale (GCS) less than 15 upon admission,

          5. Not undergoing immediate operation,

          6. Admission to the general ward or high dependence unit of Neurosurgery, Prince of Wales
             Hospital.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Presence of frontal scalp laceration preventing the application of non-invasive
             monitoring on the forehead,

          2. Presence of pneumocephale,

          3. Requirement of immediate surgical intervention as judged by the on-call neurosurgeon.

          4. Patients who have joined other drug trial in the last four weeks;

          5. Pregnant or on breast feeding;

          6. Any other reasons that the researchers consider unsuitable.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Division of Neurosurgery, Department of Surgery, Prince of Wales Hospital, Hong Kong</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hong Kong</city>
        <zip>852</zip>
        <country>Hong Kong</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Hong Kong</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Folkerson LE, Sloan D, Cotton BA, Holcomb JB, Tomasek JS, Wade CE. Predicting progressive hemorrhagic injury from isolated traumatic brain injury and coagulation. Surgery. 2015 Sep;158(3):655-61. doi: 10.1016/j.surg.2015.02.029. Epub 2015 Jun 9.</citation>
    <PMID>26067457</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Oertel M, Kelly DF, McArthur D, Boscardin WJ, Glenn TC, Lee JH, Gravori T, Obukhov D, McBride DQ, Martin NA. Progressive hemorrhage after head trauma: predictors and consequences of the evolving injury. J Neurosurg. 2002 Jan;96(1):109-16.</citation>
    <PMID>11794591</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Narayan RK, Maas AI, Servadei F, Skolnick BE, Tillinger MN, Marshall LF; Traumatic Intracerebral Hemorrhage Study Group. Progression of traumatic intracerebral hemorrhage: a prospective observational study. J Neurotrauma. 2008 Jun;25(6):629-39. doi: 10.1089/neu.2007.0385.</citation>
    <PMID>18491950</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Alahmadi H, Vachhrajani S, Cusimano MD. The natural history of brain contusion: an analysis of radiological and clinical progression. J Neurosurg. 2010 May;112(5):1139-45. doi: 10.3171/2009.5.JNS081369. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19575576</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Weigl W, Milej D, Janusek D, Wojtkiewicz S, Sawosz P, Kacprzak M, Gerega A, Maniewski R, Liebert A. Application of optical methods in the monitoring of traumatic brain injury: A review. J Cereb Blood Flow Metab. 2016 Nov;36(11):1825-1843. Epub 2016 Sep 7. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>27604312</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kim B, Jeong H, Kim J, Kim T, Kim K, Lee H, Ahn S, Jo YH, Lee JH, Hwang JE. Incidence and risk factors of delayed intracranial hemorrhage in the emergency department. Am J Emerg Med. 2018 Feb;36(2):271-276. doi: 10.1016/j.ajem.2017.08.009. Epub 2017 Aug 4.</citation>
    <PMID>28811212</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chieregato A, Fainardi E, Morselli-Labate AM, Antonelli V, Compagnone C, Targa L, Kraus J, Servadei F. Factors associated with neurological outcome and lesion progression in traumatic subarachnoid hemorrhage patients. Neurosurgery. 2005 Apr;56(4):671-80; discussion 671-80.</citation>
    <PMID>15792505</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chang EF, Meeker M, Holland MC. Acute traumatic intraparenchymal hemorrhage: risk factors for progression in the early post-injury period. Neurosurgery. 2006 Apr;58(4):647-56; discussion 647-56.</citation>
    <PMID>16575328</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Poon WS, Wong GK, Ng SC. The quantitative time-resolved near infrared spectroscopy (TR-NIRs) for bedside cerebrohemodynamic monitoring after aneurysmal subarachnoid hemorrhage: can we predict delayed neurological deficits? World Neurosurg. 2010 May;73(5):465-6. doi: 10.1016/j.wneu.2010.03.029.</citation>
    <PMID>20920925</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gomersall CD, Leung PL, Gin T, Joynt GM, Young RJ, Poon WS, Oh TE. A comparison of the Hamamatsu NIRO 500 and the INVOS 3100 near-infrared spectrophotometers. Anaesth Intensive Care. 1998 Oct;26(5):548-57.</citation>
    <PMID>9807611</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gomersall CD, Joynt GM, Gin T, Freebairn RC, Stewart IE. Failure of the INVOS 3100 cerebral oximeter to detect complete absence of cerebral blood flow. Crit Care Med. 1997 Jul;25(7):1252-4.</citation>
    <PMID>9233756</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>August 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 28, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 28, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 31, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 28, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 28, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">August 31, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Chinese University of Hong Kong</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>David Yuen Chung CHAN</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Neurosurgery Resident</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>non-invasive monitoring; near-infrared spectroscopy; traumatic brain injury; cerebral contusion</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Brain Injuries</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Brain Injuries, Traumatic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cerebral Hemorrhage</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hemorrhage</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hematoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

