<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03651375</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>URESARC1</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03651375</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Hypofractionated Radiotherapy With Sequential Chemotherapy in Primary Unresectable or Marginally Resectable Soft Tissue Sarcomas of Extremities or Trunk Wall</brief_title>
  <acronym>UN-RESARC</acronym>
  <official_title>Hypofractionated 5x5 Gy Radiotherapy With Sequential Doxorubicin and Ifosfamide-based Chemotherapy in Primary Unresectable or Marginally Resectable Soft Tissue Sarcomas of Extremities or Trunk Wall</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Maria Sklodowska-Curie Institute - Oncology Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Maria Sklodowska-Curie Institute - Oncology Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      After a screening, which consists of biopsy, physical examination, initial diffusion-weighted
      magnetic resonance imaging (DWI-MRI), body computed tomography (CT) scan, blood tests and
      case analysis on Multidisciplinary Team (MDT) meeting, a patient will receive the first
      course of chemotherapy - doxorubicin 75 mg/sqm and ifosfamide 10 g/sqm (AI regimen) with
      prophylactic mesna. Then a patient will be irradiated 5x5 Gy and after radiotherapy he or she
      will receive two courses of AI within 4-6 weeks, depending on the tolerance. Then the
      response analysis in DWI-MRI and toxicity assessment and will be performed. On the second MDT
      meeting, a final decision about resectability of the tumor will be made. In case of
      resectability, a patient will be referred to surgery.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      There is lack of standard treatment of unresectable and marginally resectable sarcomas.
      Results of commonly used approaches are unsatisfactory. The addition of neoadjuvant/induction
      chemotherapy before the irradiation and in the prolonged gap between the end of
      hypofractionated 5x5 Gy radiotherapy and surgery may allow to obtain the R0 resection rate,
      high pathological response rate and/or a higher rate of limb-sparing/conservative surgery as
      well as to increase patients' survival.

      Hypofractionation represents a variation of radiotherapy fractionation in which the total
      dose is divided into fewer fractions with an increased fraction dose. Such treatment may lead
      to additional biological effects when compared to conventionally fractionated radiotherapy
      (eg. vascular damage, increased immunogenicity, and antigenicity). The main advantages of
      hypofractionation are those related to the decreased overall treatment time what is more
      convenient for both patients and physicians, increased compliance and makes the treatment
      more cost-effective. Intriguing, such an approach may provide an additional benefit when
      treating non-radiosensitive tumors with a low alpha/beta ratio (eg. sarcomas).

      The basis of the study was a trial conducted by Kosela et al. in our center, which showed
      that preoperative short 5x5 Gy radiotherapy with immediate surgery is an effective and
      well-tolerated treatment of resectable sarcomas of extremities or trunk wall.

      The rationale of chemotherapy comes for the interim analysis of a multicenter, international
      EORTC study comparing neoadjuvant systemic approaches in high-risk sarcomas. It was proven
      that AI regimen, which consists of ifosfamide and anthracyclines allowed to obtain 20%
      benefit in relapse-free survival and overall survival as compared to pathologically—tailored
      chemotherapy.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 11, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 31, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>R0 resection rate</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>The rate of micro- and macroscopically radical surgeries.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Conservative/limb-sparing resection rate</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>The rate of limb-sparing or conservative resections vs amputations or no possibility to perform surgery (unresectability).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Radiological response in diffusion-weighted MRI</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Radiological assessment of tumor change, especially diffusion parameters in DWI-MRI 6 weeks after the end of irradiation, according to the EORTC criteria.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pathological response in resected tumors according to EORTC Soft Tissue and Bone Sarcoma Group criteria</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Toxicity of planned schedule of therapy according to CTCAE v.4.0 and Clavier-Dindo scale for surgical complications</measure>
    <time_frame>60 months</time_frame>
    <description>The study will be stopped prematurely if the rate of grade 3 skin toxicity &gt;30%.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>3-years overall survival</measure>
    <time_frame>60 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>3-years local control rate</measure>
    <time_frame>60 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Assessment of biomarkers in biopsy and post-operative material</measure>
    <time_frame>60 months</time_frame>
    <description>HIF-1 (hypoxia-inducible factor 1) - marker of hypoxia, predicting tumor response on radiotherapy; CD105/CD31/VEGF-A - tumor microvessel density; CD14, CD163, CD68KP i CD68 PG-M1 - tumor associated macrophages.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">46</enrollment>
  <condition>Sarcoma</condition>
  <condition>Fibrosarcoma</condition>
  <condition>Leiomyosarcoma</condition>
  <condition>Liposarcoma</condition>
  <condition>Myosarcoma</condition>
  <condition>Histiocytic Sarcoma</condition>
  <condition>Synovial Sarcoma</condition>
  <condition>Lymphangiosarcoma</condition>
  <condition>Malignant Peripheral Nerve Sheath Tumors</condition>
  <condition>Myxofibrosarcoma</condition>
  <condition>Myxoid Liposarcoma</condition>
  <condition>Undifferentiated Sarcoma</condition>
  <condition>Pleomorphic Liposarcoma</condition>
  <condition>Undifferentiated Pleomorphic Sarcoma</condition>
  <condition>Dedifferentiated Liposarcoma</condition>
  <condition>Pleomorphic Rhabdomyosarcoma</condition>
  <condition>Malignant Triton Tumor</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sequential chemoradiotherapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>1xAI (doxorubicin 75 mg/sqm and ifosfamide 10 g/sqm) + 5x5 Gy radiotherapy + 2xAI + surgery</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sequential chemotherapy - 3 courses of AI</intervention_name>
    <description>Three courses of doxorubicin and ifosfamide (AI, doxorubicin 75 mg/sqm and ifosfamide 10 g/sqm with prophylactic mesna), one before radiotherapy and two within the gap between radiotherapy and surgery.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Sequential chemoradiotherapy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Radiation</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Hypofractionated radiotherapy</intervention_name>
    <description>Preoperative hypofractionated 5x5 Gy radiotherapy (5 consecutive days) prescribed on planned target volume (tumor volume + elective margins + setup/error margin) with a daily image guidance with cone beam-CT-based position verification.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Sequential chemoradiotherapy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Able to provide informed consent

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status 0 - 2

          -  Age ≥18 years old

          -  Histologic diagnosis of soft tissue sarcoma

          -  Primary or recurrent tumor localized on extremities or trunk

          -  Grade 2 or grade 3 tumor

          -  Marginally resectable or unresectable tumor as assessed by a multidisciplinary team

          -  Adequate renal function (serum creatinine ≤ 1.5 ULN)

          -  Adequate liver function (total bilirubin, AST, ALT 3x &lt; ULN)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Radiation-induced sarcoma

          -  Second active malignancy, not including localized basal cell skin cancer, squamous
             cell skin cancer, in situ cervical cancer, ductal or lobular carcinoma in situ of the
             breast; patients with a history of other malignancies are eligible if they have been
             continuously disease-free for &gt; 10 years prior to the time of registration.

          -  History of radiation to the affected volume

          -  Histologic diagnosis of rhabdomyosarcoma (except pleomorphic subtype), angiosarcoma,
             epithelioid sarcoma, clear cell sarcoma, extraskeletal chondrosarcoma, alveolar soft
             part sarcoma, osteogenic sarcoma, Ewing's sarcoma/PPNET, aggressive fibromatosis,
             dermatofibrosarcoma protuberans

          -  Contraindications to radiotherapy, chemotherapy or surgery

          -  Metastatic disease except primary resectable isolated lung metastases
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>100 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Maria Sklodowska-Curie Institute - Oncology Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Warsaw</city>
        <state>Mazovian</state>
        <zip>02-781</zip>
        <country>Poland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Poland</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Barker HE, Paget JT, Khan AA, Harrington KJ. The tumour microenvironment after radiotherapy: mechanisms of resistance and recurrence. Nat Rev Cancer. 2015 Jul;15(7):409-25. doi: 10.1038/nrc3958. Review. Erratum in: Nat Rev Cancer. 2015 Aug;15(8):509.</citation>
    <PMID>26105538</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dumars C, Ngyuen JM, Gaultier A, Lanel R, Corradini N, Gouin F, Heymann D, Heymann MF. Dysregulation of macrophage polarization is associated with the metastatic process in osteosarcoma. Oncotarget. 2016 Nov 29;7(48):78343-78354. doi: 10.18632/oncotarget.13055.</citation>
    <PMID>27823976</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ellingsen C, Andersen LM, Galappathi K, Rofstad EK. Hypoxia biomarkers in squamous cell carcinoma of the uterine cervix. BMC Cancer. 2015 Oct 26;15:805. doi: 10.1186/s12885-015-1828-2.</citation>
    <PMID>26502718</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fujiwara T, Fukushi J, Yamamoto S, Matsumoto Y, Setsu N, Oda Y, Yamada H, Okada S, Watari K, Ono M, Kuwano M, Kamura S, Iida K, Okada Y, Koga M, Iwamoto Y. Macrophage infiltration predicts a poor prognosis for human ewing sarcoma. Am J Pathol. 2011 Sep;179(3):1157-70. doi: 10.1016/j.ajpath.2011.05.034. Epub 2011 Jul 21.</citation>
    <PMID>21771572</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ganjoo KN, Witten D, Patel M, Espinosa I, La T, Tibshirani R, van de Rijn M, Jacobs C, West RB. The prognostic value of tumor-associated macrophages in leiomyosarcoma: a single institution study. Am J Clin Oncol. 2011 Feb;34(1):82-6.</citation>
    <PMID>23781555</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gronchi A, Ferrari S, Quagliuolo, Broto M, J, Lopez-Pousa A, Grignani G, et al. Full-dose neoadjuvant anthracycline + ifosfamide chemotherapy is associated with a relapse free survival (RFS) and overall survival (OS) benefit in localized high-risk adult soft tissue sarcomas (STS) of the extremities and trunk wall: Interim analysis of a prospective randomized trial. Annals of Oncology, Volume 27, Issue suppl_6, 1 October 2016 https://academic.oup.com/annonc/article/27/suppl_6/LBA6_PR/2800561</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jiang S, Yang Y, Fang M, Li X, Yuan X, Yuan J. Co-evolution of tumor-associated macrophages and tumor neo-vessels during cervical cancer invasion. Oncol Lett. 2016 Oct;12(4):2625-2631. Epub 2016 Aug 16.</citation>
    <PMID>27698836</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kim YH, Yoo KC, Cui YH, Uddin N, Lim EJ, Kim MJ, Nam SY, Kim IG, Suh Y, Lee SJ. Radiation promotes malignant progression of glioma cells through HIF-1alpha stabilization. Cancer Lett. 2014 Nov 1;354(1):132-41. doi: 10.1016/j.canlet.2014.07.048. Epub 2014 Aug 7.</citation>
    <PMID>25109450</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Koseła-Paterczyk H, Szacht M, Morysiński T, Ługowska I, Dziewirski W, Falkowski S, Zdzienicki M, Pieńkowski A, Szamotulska K, Switaj T, Rutkowski P. Preoperative hypofractionated radiotherapy in the treatment of localized soft tissue sarcomas. Eur J Surg Oncol. 2014 Dec;40(12):1641-7. doi: 10.1016/j.ejso.2014.05.016. Epub 2014 Sep 20.</citation>
    <PMID>25282099</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lee HJ, Yoon C, Park DJ, Kim YJ, Schmidt B, Lee YJ, Tap WD, Eisinger-Mathason TS, Choy E, Kirsch DG, Simon MC, Yoon SS. Inhibition of vascular endothelial growth factor A and hypoxia-inducible factor 1α maximizes the effects of radiation in sarcoma mouse models through destruction of tumor vasculature. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys. 2015 Mar 1;91(3):621-30. doi: 10.1016/j.ijrobp.2014.10.047. Epub 2014 Dec 24.</citation>
    <PMID>25544668</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Messiou C, Bonvalot S, Gronchi A, Vanel D, Meyer M, Robinson P, Morosi C, Bloem JL, Terrier PH, Lazar A, Le Péchoux C, Wardelman E, Winfield JM, Boulet B, Bovée J, Haas RL. Evaluation of response after pre-operative radiotherapy in soft tissue sarcomas; the European Organisation for Research and Treatment of Cancer-Soft Tissue and Bone Sarcoma Group (EORTC-STBSG) and Imaging Group recommendations for radiological examination and reporting with an emphasis on magnetic resonance imaging. Eur J Cancer. 2016 Mar;56:37-44. doi: 10.1016/j.ejca.2015.12.008. Epub 2016 Jan 20.</citation>
    <PMID>26802529</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wardelmann E, Haas RL, Bovée JV, Terrier P, Lazar A, Messiou C, LePechoux C, Hartmann W, Collin F, Fisher C, Mechtersheimer G, DeiTos AP, Stacchiotti S, Jones RL, Gronchi A, Bonvalot S. Evaluation of response after neoadjuvant treatment in soft tissue sarcomas; the European Organization for Research and Treatment of Cancer-Soft Tissue and Bone Sarcoma Group (EORTC-STBSG) recommendations for pathological examination and reporting. Eur J Cancer. 2016 Jan;53:84-95. doi: 10.1016/j.ejca.2015.09.021. Epub 2015 Dec 14.</citation>
    <PMID>26700077</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yehia L, Boulos F, Jabbour M, Mahfoud Z, Fakhruddin N, El-Sabban M. Expression of HIF-1α and Markers of Angiogenesis Are Not Significantly Different in Triple Negative Breast Cancer Compared to Other Breast Cancer Molecular Subtypes: Implications for Future Therapy. PLoS One. 2015 Jun 5;10(6):e0129356. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0129356. eCollection 2015.</citation>
    <PMID>26046764</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zhang M, Qiu Q, Li Z, Sachdeva M, Min H, Cardona DM, DeLaney TF, Han T, Ma Y, Luo L, Ilkayeva OR, Lui K, Nichols AG, Newgard CB, Kastan MB, Rathmell JC, Dewhirst MW, Kirsch DG. HIF-1 Alpha Regulates the Response of Primary Sarcomas to Radiation Therapy through a Cell Autonomous Mechanism. Radiat Res. 2015 Jun;183(6):594-609. Epub 2015 May 14.</citation>
    <PMID>25973951</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>December 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 27, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 27, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 29, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 16, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 16, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 17, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Dose Hypofractionation</keyword>
  <keyword>Neoadjuvant Therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Chemoradiotherapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Sarcoma</keyword>
  <keyword>Dose Fractionation</keyword>
  <keyword>Dose-Response Relationship</keyword>
  <keyword>Antineoplastic Agents</keyword>
  <keyword>Drug Therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Antineoplastic Combined Chemotherapy Protocols</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Sarcoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Rhabdomyosarcoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leiomyosarcoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Liposarcoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sarcoma, Synovial</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Nerve Sheath Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neurofibrosarcoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fibrosarcoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Histiocytoma, Malignant Fibrous</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Liposarcoma, Myxoid</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Histiocytic Sarcoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphangiosarcoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myosarcoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

