<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03656042</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>96-0272A-ASAD-061202</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03656042</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>To Evaluate the Efficacy and Safety/Tolerability Profiles of G-CSF in Subjects With Mild to Moderate Alzheimer's Disease</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Open-label, No-treatment-controlled, Parallel, Pilot Phase Ⅱ Study to Evaluate the Efficacy and Safety/Tolerability Profiles of G-CSF in Subjects With Mild to Moderate Alzheimer's Disease</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Chang Gung Memorial Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Chang Gung Memorial Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      With the enrichment of living environment and the progress of medicine, the scale of aging
      population has increased in many countries of the world. Alzheimer's disease (AD), the
      leading cause of dementia, counts for approximately 60% to 70% in dementia in aged
      population. AD is a well-known neurodegenerative disease and characterized by the formation
      of neurofibrillary tangles and deposition of amyloid in the brain. It also affects more than
      12 million patients worldwide and puts a tremendous burden on family caregivers and causes
      high nursing home costs for society. So far, the mechanisms of AD have not been elucidated
      and currently no curable treatment exists. Thus, clinical trials concerning the treatment of
      AD are in urgent expectation.

      Granulocyte-colony stimulating factor (G-CSF) is a growth factor that presents in human body
      in small quantity and is known to promote the blood cell proliferation and differentiation.
      Previous studies showed injection of G-CSF could help release hematopoietic stem cell (HSCs)
      from bone marrow to the peripheral blood, and then migrate to repair damaged areas, e.g.
      heart tissue and ischemia brain tissue. We have found that G-CSF triggering release of stem
      cells from bone marrow shows the potential as an effective reagent for treatment of AD by
      using two AD mouse models. The one was generated by injecting the brains of normal mice with
      amyloid and another was by using a strain of transgenic mice which naturally exhibit
      Alzheimer's disease-like neuronal apoptosis and memory loss. Subcutaneous administration of
      G-CSF into mice significantly rescued their cognitive/memory functions.

      G-CSF has already been widely used in clinical practice, for example, neutropenia caused by
      chemotherapy in cancer and bone marrow transplantation. The new finding shows G-CSF can
      release HSCs from bone marrow and these cells not only can pass through the blood-brain
      barrier but can selectively migrate to the region of damaged brain to improve neurological
      recovery. Thus, we conduct this clinical trial to investigate the potential effect of G-CSF
      for the cognitive function of AD patients. If successful, G-CSF could open up a new window
      for AD treatment which is less invasive and more effective than the current therapies.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a randomized open-label Phase 2 trial with parallel design using no-treatment group
      as control. Subjects in the treatment arm will receive subcutaneous G-CSF with the dosage of
      10 microgram/kg/day, for 5 continuous days in the first week. The second dosage will be given
      in the 12 week. If subjects has received Donepezil already, the Donepezil will be
      concomitantly used in a stable dose (the same dose as pre-entering this study) during the
      study.

      Background data and general medical history will be registered on the screening visit (Visit
      1, started four weeks or less before Visit 2). Subjects fulfil the inclusion criteria 1) age
      between 50 to 85 years old; 2) those who were diagnosed as AD and the supporting evidences
      from the brain computed tomography or Magnetic Resonance Imaging scan within 12-months; 3)
      Mini-Mental State Examination scores of 10 to 26, and, 4) Clinical Dementia Rating score of 1
      or 2. Subjects with clinically significant medical or neurological disorders, other than AD,
      that may affect cognition will be excluded Additional inclusion criteria included Modified
      Hachinski Ischemic score of ≤ 4, Hamilton Psychiatric Rating Scale for Depression score of ≤
      12and a reliable caregiver who is sufficiently familiar with the subject and is willing to
      provide the accurate data.

      Participants will receive standard physical examination in all visits. Serum tests include
      complete blood count (CBC),total bilirubin, creatinine, blood urea nitrogen (BUN), uric acid,
      aspartate transaminase (AST), alanine transaminase (ALT), total protein, albumin, Vitamin
      B12, folate, T4, thyroid-stimulating hormone (TSH), HbA1c, rapid plasmin reagin
      (RPR)/Treponema pallidum haemagglutination (TPHA) will be also obtained.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 2009</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">August 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">July 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Alzheimer's Disease Assessment Scale, Cognitive subscale ─ Chinese version (ADAS-Cog-C)</measure>
    <time_frame>24 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The total score ranges from 0 to 75 and the higher the score, the greater the impairment. ADAS-Cog-C has 11 items and each has its score range:
Word Recall Task: maximum score = 10 Naming Task: maximum score = 5 Commands: maximum score = 5 Constructional Praxis: maximum score = 5 Ideational Praxis: maximum score = 5 Orientation: maximum score = 8 Word Recognition: maximum score = 12 Remembering Test Instructions: maximum score = 5 Spoken Language Ability: maximum score = 5 Word-Finding Difficulty: maximum score = 5 Comprehension: maximum score = 5 We measure the change from baseline in ADAS-Cog at 24-week visit.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mini-mental State Examination (MMSE)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 12 weeks, 24 weeks and 48 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The Mini-Mental State Examination (MMSE) is a 30-point questionnaire.
The score ranges are as follows:
Orientation to time 5 Orientation to place 5 Registration 3 Attention and calculation 5 Recall 3 Language 2 Repetition 1 Complex commands 5</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical Dementia Rating Scale (CDR)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 12 weeks, 24 weeks and 48 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The Clinical Dementia Rating Scale is a 5-point scale used to characterize six domains of cognitive and functional performance to Alzheimer disease and related dementias: Memory, Orientation, Judgment &amp; Problem Solving, Community Affairs, Home &amp; Hobbies, and Personal Care.
In each domain, the severity degree of each symptom correspond to different rating score from 0(none) to 3(severe). The total score ranges from 0 to 18</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>AD Cooperative Study - Clinical Global Impression of change (ADCS-CGIC )</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 12 weeks, 24 weeks and 48 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Interviewer scores the severity as follow:
Not impaired / not present
Borderline impairment
Mild impairment
Moderate impairment
Marked impairment
Severe impairment
very severe</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Lawton and Brody Scale for Instrumental Activities of Daily Living (IADL)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 12 weeks, 24 weeks and 48 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The test measures eight realms of function through self report, which attempt to assess everyday functional competence in the elderly. Each item is rated either dichotomously (0 = less able, 1 = more able) or trichotomously (1 = unable, 2 = needs assistance, 3 = independent) and sum the eight responses. The summary score ranges from 0 (low function, dependent) to 8 (high function, independent) for women and 0 through 5 for men.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Neuropsychiatric Inventory (NPI)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 12 weeks, 24 weeks and 48 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The NPI originally examined 12 sub-domains of behavioral functioning Each domain is scored for frequency, severity and associated caregiver distress.
Frequency:Rarely,Sometimes,Often,Very often Severity:Mild,Moderate,Severe Caregiver Distress:0(not at all),1(minimally),2(mildly),3(moderately),4(severely),5(very severely or extremely). Total score will range from Less than 20(symptoms are mild),20-50(symptoms are moderate) to 50 or over(symptoms are severe)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Ten-point clock test (TPCT)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 12 weeks, 24 weeks and 48 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>One point is given for each of the following numbers that falls in its proper eighth of the circle relative to the number 12: 1.2, 4,5,7, 8, 10, and 11. One point is given each to a short hand pointing at the number eleven, and a long hand pointing at the number two. The total score ranges from 0 to 10.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>CD34+ cell number for G-CSF treatment group</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 12 weeks, 24 weeks and 48 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>G-CSF may promote mobilizing bone marrow CD34+ stem cells. We will compare the CD34+ cell number between treatment and control group at the baseline and follow up sequential change in the treatment group.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Trail making test (TMT)(Part A))</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 12 weeks, 24 weeks and 48 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The Trail Making Test is a neuropsychological test of visual attention and task switching. Results for Trail making test A (Part A) is reported as the number of seconds required to complete the task; therefore, higher scores reveal greater impairment. The average time is 29 seconds. If the subject uses more than 78 seconds, cognitive deficient is impressed.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in whole brain volume determined by MRI</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 24 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Change from baseline in whole brain volume determined by MRI. MRI examination will be performed within 7 days before the start at the start of first cycle (Visit 2) and week-24 visit (Visit 10), to compare the change of whole brain volume.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">21</enrollment>
  <condition>Alzheimer's Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>G-CSF</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects in the treatment group will receive Filgrastim (75mcg/0.3ml, NEUPOGEN®), 10 mic/kg/day, by sc, for 5 continuous days for the first week, rest for 11 weeks. Filgrastim will be given 12-weekly ( 12 weeks/cycle ) for 2 cycles.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>No-treatment</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>No-treatment group is used to control evaluation bias and potential time effect.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Filgrastim (75mcg/0.3ml)</intervention_name>
    <description>Subjects who meet all eligible requirements for entry into the study will be randomized into one of the two treatment groups in 1:1 ratio as shown below:
10 microgram/kg/day, by sc, for 5 continuous days for the first week, rest for 11 weeks; repeat dosing regimen every 12-weekly (12 weeks / cycle) for 2 cycles
Non-treatment</description>
    <arm_group_label>G-CSF</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>NEUPOGEN®</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Subject with age of at lease 50 years old and no more than 85 years old

          2. Subject diagnosed of Alzheimer's disease; based on the criteria of The Diagnostic and
             Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders (DSM)-Ⅳ for dementia and those of National
             Institute of Neurological and Communicative Disorders and Stroke - Alzheimer's
             Dementia and Related Disorder Association (NINCDS - ADRDA) and within 12-months CT/MRI
             brain scan supporting evidences.

          3. Subject with Mini-Mental Examination (MMSE) scores of 12 to 26 (inclusive).

          4. Subject with Clinical Dementia Rating (CDR) score of 1 (mild) or 2 moderate).

          5. Subject with Modified Hachinski Ischemic score of 4.

          6. Subject with a Hamilton Psychiatric Rating Scale for Depression score of 12.

          7. Female subject with child-bearing potential agrees to take reliable contraceptive
             method during the participation of the study (Females with no child-bearing potential
             have to be surgically sterilized or at least 2 years after post-menopausal).

          8. Subject and subject's legally acceptable representative have given written informed
             consent.

          9. A reliable caregiver is sufficiently familiar with the subject (as determined by the
             investigator) and is willing to provide accurate data.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Subject has underwent any of the following treatment modalities with the respective
             time frames:

               1. Anti-epileptic agents: Within 12 weeks of the screening visit,

               2. Narcotic: within 12 weeks of the screening visit,

               3. Immunosuppressants: within 12 weeks of the screening visit,

               4. Hypnotics: within 24 hours of the screening visit or the randomization visit,

               5. Lithium: within 2 weeks of the randomization visit,

               6. Succinylcholine-type muscle relaxants: within 2 weeks of the randomization visit,

               7. Drugs or treatments known to cause major organ system toxicity: within 42 weeks
                  of the randomization visit,

               8. Tricyclic and tetracyclic anti-depressants: within 4 weeks of the screening
                  visit,

               9. Antiparkinsonian: Within12 weeks of the screening visit (Not including
                  dopaminergic agent or peripheral anticholinergic agent at stable dose for at
                  least 4 weeks of randomization visit),

              10. Any medications for cognition enhancement: Within13 weeks of the screening
                  visit(except for donepezil that has been maintained with a stable regimen for at
                  least 12 weeks).

          2. Subject is lactating, pregnant or plans to become pregnant,

          3. Subject is cared primarily by nursing home,

          4. Subject's AST or ALT is greater than 2 times of the upper limit or normal range.

          5. Subject with diabetic history and with HbA1c &gt; 8.5 %.

          6. Subject with clinically significant medical or neurological disorders, other than AD,
             that may affect cognition (e.g., abnormal thyroid function tests, Vitamin B12 or
             folate deficiency, post-traumatic conditions Huntington's disease, Parkinson's
             disease, syphilis, probable/possible vascular dementia according to NINDS-AIREN
             criteria, active/uncontrolled seizure).

          7. Subject with major psychiatric disorders.

          8. Subject with spleen related disorders.

          9. Subject with sickle cell disease.

         10. Subject with myelodysplastic syndrome.

         11. Subject with current diagnosis of acute stroke or history of acute stroke within 1
             year.

         12. Subject with allergy history to E. coli-derived proteins or G-CSF or donepezil.

         13. Subject with cancer history and has received related therapy(ies) with in 2 years of
             entering this study.

         14. Subject has participated other investigational study within 4 weeks of entering this
             study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>50 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>85 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Wen-Chuin Hsu, M.S.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Chang Gung Memorial Hospital, Linkou medical center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Chang Gung Memorial Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Taoyuan</city>
        <state>Taiwan R.o.c</state>
        <zip>333</zip>
        <country>Taiwan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Taiwan</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Alzheimer's Association. 2016 Alzheimer's disease facts and figures. Alzheimers Dement. 2016 Apr;12(4):459-509.</citation>
    <PMID>27570871</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Scheltens P, Blennow K, Breteler MM, de Strooper B, Frisoni GB, Salloway S, Van der Flier WM. Alzheimer's disease. Lancet. 2016 Jul 30;388(10043):505-17. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(15)01124-1. Epub 2016 Feb 24. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26921134</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Braak H, Del Tredici K. The preclinical phase of the pathological process underlying sporadic Alzheimer's disease. Brain. 2015 Oct;138(Pt 10):2814-33. doi: 10.1093/brain/awv236. Epub 2015 Aug 17. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26283673</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chartier-Harlin MC, Crawford F, Houlden H, Warren A, Hughes D, Fidani L, Goate A, Rossor M, Roques P, Hardy J, et al. Early-onset Alzheimer's disease caused by mutations at codon 717 of the beta-amyloid precursor protein gene. Nature. 1991 Oct 31;353(6347):844-6.</citation>
    <PMID>1944558</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tigue CC, McKoy JM, Evens AM, Trifilio SM, Tallman MS, Bennett CL. Granulocyte-colony stimulating factor administration to healthy individuals and persons with chronic neutropenia or cancer: an overview of safety considerations from the Research on Adverse Drug Events and Reports project. Bone Marrow Transplant. 2007 Aug;40(3):185-92. Epub 2007 Jun 11. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>17563736</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yanqing Z, Yu-Min L, Jian Q, Bao-Guo X, Chuan-Zhen L. Fibronectin and neuroprotective effect of granulocyte colony-stimulating factor in focal cerebral ischemia. Brain Res. 2006 Jul 7;1098(1):161-9. Epub 2006 Jul 11.</citation>
    <PMID>16814750</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schneider A, Krüger C, Steigleder T, Weber D, Pitzer C, Laage R, Aronowski J, Maurer MH, Gassler N, Mier W, Hasselblatt M, Kollmar R, Schwab S, Sommer C, Bach A, Kuhn HG, Schäbitz WR. The hematopoietic factor G-CSF is a neuronal ligand that counteracts programmed cell death and drives neurogenesis. J Clin Invest. 2005 Aug;115(8):2083-98. Epub 2005 Jul 7.</citation>
    <PMID>16007267</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tsai KJ, Tsai YC, Shen CK. G-CSF rescues the memory impairment of animal models of Alzheimer's disease. J Exp Med. 2007 Jun 11;204(6):1273-80. Epub 2007 May 21.</citation>
    <PMID>17517969</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sanchez-Ramos J, Song S, Sava V, Catlow B, Lin X, Mori T, Cao C, Arendash GW. Granulocyte colony stimulating factor decreases brain amyloid burden and reverses cognitive impairment in Alzheimer's mice. Neuroscience. 2009 Sep 29;163(1):55-72. doi: 10.1016/j.neuroscience.2009.05.071. Epub 2009 Jun 14.</citation>
    <PMID>19500657</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 2017</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 23, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 30, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 4, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 30, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 30, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">September 4, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Dementia</keyword>
  <keyword>Alzheimer's disease</keyword>
  <keyword>Granulocyte-colony stimulating factor</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Alzheimer Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lenograstim</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Individual participant data sets including IPD that underlie results in a publication have not yet decided to be shared under the consideration of patient privacy.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

