<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03651297</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IRB-FY2018-324</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03651297</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Simple Fall-Arrest Harness vs. Adjustable Harness</brief_title>
  <official_title>Testing a Simple Fall-arrest Harness vs. an Actuated and Instrumented Harness in Balance Training</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Cleveland State University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Cleveland State University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Fall risk increases with age and the fear of falling can significantly impact activity,
      mobility and future fall risk. Exercise designed specifically to help balance is effective at
      improving balance and postural control for mobility, gait, and other daily activities. The
      individual purposes of this research are to (1) effectively use a prototype of an
      instrumented and actuated harness and support system, (2) demonstrate that this system can be
      used as designed during induced falls (reactive) and in place gaming (proactive) balance
      training protocols with the ability to modulate parameters as designed, measurements of
      harness system are accurate, and resultant output of the system matches intended parameters,
      and (3) demonstrate that the use of this system can allow provision of and study of varied
      balance training protocols, including: the measurements of the system, feedback of the system
      to participants, and the impact of the support parameters of the harness system on the task
      execution, learning and transfer.

      Two separate groups of 20 participants (40 total participants) will be studied. The first
      group will include 20 individuals between the ages of 18 to 40 years old with no history of
      falls or fear of falling. The first group will complete two sessions of harnessed video
      gaming balance training. The second group will include older adults over the age of 55 with
      self-reported falls or the fear of falling. The second group of older adults will complete
      two sessions of a reactive (slip) training protocol. For both groups, the first session
      participants will be randomly assigned to use either a standard fall-arrest harness or the
      new BWS harness system. At the second session, they will switch the harness used. The
      protocol will involve slips or gaming based balance training, initially of low intensity and
      then advanced by algorithm based on their response to the trial just prior. This will allow
      comparison of postural control, perturbation responses, motor learning, and confidence with
      the system between the two harness types.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Fall risk increases with age and the fear of falling can significantly impact activity,
      mobility and future fall risk. Exercise designed specifically to help balance is effective at
      improving balance and postural control for mobility, gait, and other daily activities.
      Balance training for fall prevention can be proactive or reactive. Proactive balance training
      is the practice of anticipatory and self-initiated movement. Reactive training, on the other
      hand, involves responses to unexpected movements that cause a loss of balance. Safety harness
      systems are used for reactive balance protocols to prevent actual falls. They may also be
      used in intense proactive protocols for more vulnerable, frail, or fearful participants. In
      therapeutic settings, harnesses for gait and mobility training are either body weight
      supporting (BWS) or fall-arresting.

      The investigators have designed and built a harness system that allows better control of more
      of the support parameters than much more expensive, commercially available, and BWS systems.
      This harness system better controls aspects such as: limiting fall distance, modulation of
      how the support responds to descents, assist to return to stand, and recording of all body
      movements. This will allow the investigation of questions about the impact of harness systems
      on learning and performance of postural control and effective use of harnesses in balance
      training.

      The investigators have done extensive work with the Xbox system using Kinect, having designed
      a protocol and progression of games and surfaces that provides high intensity proactive
      balance training using Kinect. The investigators also train reactive balance through the use
      of a custom made platform called the Slip Trainer (MASS Rehab, Dayton, OH), along with a fall
      arresting harness and load measuring device. This allows the administration of repeated slip
      perturbations of a consistent and known intensity safely and efficiently.

      Questions that still need to be answered include: Will patients challenge themselves more or
      engage in more intense activities with a harness? Does the support provided by a harness
      impact or interfere with the motor learning of the balance tasks? Could balance task learning
      be more effective with some degree of support vs. just a fall-arresting &quot;backup&quot; as is
      theorized with treadmill gait training? If so, what types and parameters are most effective?
      Would this type of support allow more intense training to be extended to people who are less
      mobile, more vulnerable or frail or more fearful, those who would not be able to participate
      in effective balance training otherwise?

      This study will answer initial questions about the effectiveness and acceptance of the
      harness system by older adults in a reactive and by younger adults in a proactive protocol,
      and will provide pilot data for larger, external grants to investigate the broader questions
      among a much larger group of people. The larger impact will be translating the technology and
      understanding its impact clinically, allowing much greater intensity and more effective
      balance training for at risk populations.

      The investigators propose to build a harness system in which the support within a single
      plane can be finely controlled and measured. This harness will have the following
      capabilities: limit height/fall to a pre-set vertical limit with ability to modulate the fall
      arrest kinematics, dynamic partial body weight support - to remain constant with center of
      mass (COM) movements, modulate by pre-set thresholds how the support responds to descent,
      assist to return to stand - with preset thresholds and levels of assist,
      monitor/measure/record: vertical and horizontal components of body COM movements, and provide
      feedback to users re: the support of being provided or re: other parameters, potentially in
      various modes (haptic, visual, auditory).

      The individual purposes of this research are to (1) effectively use a prototype of an
      instrumented and actuated harness and support system, (2) demonstrate that this system can be
      used as designed during induced falls (reactive) and in place gaming (proactive) balance
      training protocols with the ability to modulate parameters as designed, measurements of
      harness system are accurate, and resultant output of the system matches intended parameters,
      and (3) demonstrate that the use of this system can allow provision of and study of varied
      balance training protocols, including: the measurements of the system, feedback of the system
      to participants, and the impact of the support parameters of the harness system on the task
      execution, learning and transfer.

      Two separate groups of 20 participants (40 total participants) will be studied. Participants
      will be recruited from students, faculty and staff, as well as community members known to the
      investigator following the procedure outlined below. The first group will include 20
      individuals between the ages of 18 to 40 years old with no history of falls or fear of
      falling. The first group will complete two sessions of harnessed video gaming balance
      training. The second group will include older adults over the age of 55 with self-reported
      falls or the fear of falling. The second group of older adults will complete two sessions of
      a reactive (slip) training protocol. For both groups, the first session participants will be
      randomly assigned to use a standard fall-arrest harness or the new BWS harness system. BWS
      harness can be set to support a predetermined portion of the person's body weight and
      maintain that support throughout the session. At the second session, they will switch the
      harness used. The protocol will involve balance training, advanced by algorithm, based on the
      participant's response to the trial just prior. This will allow comparison of postural
      control, perturbation responses, motor learning, and confidence with the system between the
      two harness types.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 20, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>The first group will complete two sessions of harnessed video gaming balance training. The second group will include older adults over the age of 50 with self-reported falls or the fear of falling. The second group of older adults will complete two sessions of a reactive (slip) training protocol. For both groups, the first session participants will be assigned randomly to use a standard fall-arrest harness or the new BWS harness system. At the second session, they will switch the harness used.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change (improvement) in response to increasingly difficult perturbations, as measured by the Rate of Perceived Stability Score (RPS).</measure>
    <time_frame>2 sessions of 60 - 90 minutes, more than 3 days but less than three weeks apart.</time_frame>
    <description>The protocols are advanced by algorithm. The reactive algorithm sets initial slip distance and force by the individual's leg length, weight, and MiniBEST (balance evaluation systems test). The result of each slip (harness loading and recovery steps) dictates the next condition as set forth in the algorithm. The proactive algorithm is a hierarchy of game and balance surface difficulty: participants begin at the same level and progress based on their Rate of Perceived Stability (RPS) score for each condition. The RPS self-rates balance task difficulty from 1 to 10 (least to most challenging). Advancing through more steps/more quickly with one harness indicates greater efficacy of that harness in balance skill acquisition. Because balance ability and the learning curve for balance tasks are highly individual, the outcome of interest is individual improvement in response to increasingly difficult perturbations, rather than standardized measure of balance ability across subjects.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Fall Accident</condition>
  <condition>Fall Injury</condition>
  <condition>Balancing Interference</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Younger Adults</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>First group will include 20 young adults with no history of falls or fear of falling. They will complete both interventions: Balance Training with Fall-Arrest Harness and Balance Training with Adjustable Harness.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Older adults</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Second group will include 20 older adults with a self-reported history of falls or fear of falling. They will complete both interventions: Balance Training with Fall-Arrest Harness and Balance Training with Adjustable Harness.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Balance training with Fall-Arrest harness</intervention_name>
    <description>This study will analyze the subjects' responses to balance training protocols with two types of harness support. The protocol will involve balance training, initially of low intensity and then advanced by an algorithm based on subjects' responses to the prior repetition of balance activity. For this intervention, the subjects will be using a standard Fall-Arrest harness for safety throughout, but no other external support. This will allow comparison of postural control, slip responses, motor learning, reliance on the harness and confidence with the system between the two harness types.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Older adults</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Younger Adults</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Balance training with Adjustable harness</intervention_name>
    <description>This study will analyze the subjects' responses to balance training protocols with two types of harness support. The protocol will involve balance training, initially of low intensity and then advanced by an algorithm based on subjects' responses to the prior repetition of balance activity. For this intervention, the subjects will be using a motorized harness in which the support provided is adjustable. This will allow comparison of postural control, slip responses, motor learning, reliance on the harness and confidence with the system between the two harness types.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Older adults</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Younger Adults</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age

          -  Completed Informed Consent

          -  Self-reported risk or fear of falling

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Medical Condition - they are not eligible if they self-identify as having any
             musculoskeletal, neuromuscular, cardiopulmonary, or other conditions that would limit
             them from participation.

          -  Allergic to adhesive tape
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Debbie Espy</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Cleveland State University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Debbie Espy, PT, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>216-687-3554</phone>
    <email>d.espy@csuohio.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Ann Reinthal, PT, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>216-687-3576</phone>
    <email>a.karas@csuohio.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cleveland State University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cleveland</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>44115</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Debbie Espy, PT, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>216-687-3554</phone>
      <email>d.espy@csuohio.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Ann Reinthal, PT, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>216-687-3576</phone>
      <email>a.karas@csuohio.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 14, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 27, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 29, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 24, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 24, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 25, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Cleveland State University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Debbie Espy</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Harness Assist</keyword>
  <keyword>Balance training</keyword>
  <keyword>Types of harness assist</keyword>
  <keyword>Fall-arrest harness</keyword>
  <keyword>Adjustable harness</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

