<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03650647</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ARibeiro</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03650647</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Comparison of Conventional Versus Conservative Caries Removal in Primary Teeth</brief_title>
  <acronym>Caries_removal</acronym>
  <official_title>Randomized Clinical Trial Comparison of Conventional Versus Conservative Caries Removal in Primary Teeth: a Two-year Evaluation</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Universidade Federal Fluminense</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Universidade Federal Fluminense</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The sample will be, at least, 90 primary molars, randomly distributed into three groups:
      Group 1: IPC; Group 2: SE; Group 3: SCR. Teeth must present deep caries lesions (at least 2/3
      of dentin depth), pulp vitality (no clinical or radiographical signs of pulp disease, such as
      abcesses, fistulae, root resorption, abnormal tooth mobility). This study received approval
      by the Ethics Committee of Fluminense Federal University (UFF; Brazil) - # CAAE:
      58812816.8.0000.5626. The study started in January, 2017; and will finish in December, 2020.
      Patients will be selected from the public schools in Nova Friburgo. The dental exams and
      treatment procedures will be done at the clinics from the

      School of Dentistry, Health Institute of Nova Friburgo (ISNF). Laboratory proceedings will be
      done at:

        -  Clinical and Microbiological Research Laboratory (LAB PECMA - ISNF) - Sample storage,
           bacterial cultivation and identification.

        -  University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

        -  Rio de Janeiro Federal University
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The aims of this Randomized Clinical Trial are:

        1. to evaluate the risk of pulpal exposure and tooth vitality maintenance of primary molars
           with deep caries lesions, treated with conservative techniques, such as Stepwise
           Excavation (SE) or Selective Caries Removal (SCR), and to compare with those teeth
           treated with Indirect Pulp Capping (IPC);

        2. to verify changes in the cultivable microbiota isolated in the deep carious dentin
           lesions of deciduous molars, before and after performing the procedures of SE;

        3. to clinically evaluate dentin reactions to the SE;

        4. to provide longitudinal monitoring of changes in the non-cultivable microbiota
           (microbiome), found in dentin carious lesions of deciduous and permanent molars,
           compared to the treatments performed;

        5. to determine, in vitro, the microbial metabolome of different strains isolated from
           dentin samples under conditions of high and low cariogenic challenge;

        6. to correlate, in vitro, the microbial metabolites with the clinical classification of
           the cavitated lesions from which these samples originated.

      The sample will be, at least, 90 primary molars, randomly distributed into three groups:
      Group 1: IPC; Group 2: SE; Group 3: SCR. Teeth must present deep caries lesions (at least 2/3
      of dentin depth), pulp vitality (no clinical or radiographical signs of pulp disease, such as
      abcesses, fistulae, root resorption, abnormal tooth mobility). This study received approval
      by the Ethics Committee of UFF (Brazil) - # CAAE: 58812816.8.0000.5626. The study started in
      January, 2017; and will finish in December, 2020. Patients will be selected from the public
      schools in Nova Friburgo. The dental exams and treatment procedures will be done at the
      clinics from the

      School of Dentistry, Health Institute of Nova Friburgo (ISNF). Laboratory proceedings will be
      done at:

      LAB PECMA - ISNF - Sample storage, bacterial cultivation and identification University of
      North Carolina at Chapel Hill Rio de Janeiro Federal University
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 15, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 5, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">January 15, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Factorial Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Tooth receive one of the two test treatments: Stepwise Excavation (conservative treatment 1), Selective caries removal (conservative treatment 2) and are evaluated in parallel against a control group (indirect pulp capping treatment).</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pulp vitality maintenance diagnosed by clinical exam</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion, up to three years.</time_frame>
    <description>Among the three treatment protocols, which one will have better prognosis in maintaining pulp vitality. The clinical parameters of pulpal failures are: pain, presence of abscess, fistulae and/or abnormal tooth mobility.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pulp vitality maintenance diagnosed by radiograph exam</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion, up to three years.</time_frame>
    <description>The prognosis of maintaining pulp vitality will be acessed by radiological signs of loss of vitality, as presence of abnormal root resorption and/or bone resorption.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">49</enrollment>
  <condition>Dental Caries Extending Into Dentin</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Indirect Pulp Capping</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Nonselective removal to hard dentine (formerly complete excavation or complete caries removal) : removal of soft dentin, only hard dentine is left on the cavity, so that demineralized dentine &quot;free&quot; of bacteria is completely removed.
Intervention: Total soft and leathery caries removal. Carious dentin removal</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Stepwise excavation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Stepwise removal is carious tissue removal in 2 stages, i.e., visits. Soft carious tissue is left over the pulp in the first step, while peripheral dentine is prepared to hard dentine to allow a complete and durable seal of the lesion. A provisional restoration is placed, which should be sufficiently durable to last up to 6 months to allow changes in the dentine and pulp to take place. After this period, a second excavation is done and, if there is hard dentin formed, the tooth is restored.
Intervention: Part of the soft caries is removed. Final restoration is placed on the second visit. Carious dentin removal</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Selective caries removal</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Selective caries removal: only part the soft dentine is removed, so soft carious tissue is left over the pulp, while peripheral enamel and dentine are prepared to hard dentine, to allow a tight seal and placement of a durable restoration.
Intervention: Part of the soft caries is removed. Final restoration is place over the soft dentin. Carious dentin removal</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Carious dentin removal</intervention_name>
    <description>Carious tissue removal and managing deep cavitated carious lesions in primary teeth.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Indirect Pulp Capping</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Selective caries removal</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Stepwise excavation</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Indirect Pulp Capping</other_name>
    <other_name>Stepwise excavation</other_name>
    <other_name>Selective caries removal</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. The child need to be healthy;

          2. This should be in the age range of 4 to 6 years of age;

          3. The primary molars to be submitted to treatment should have the following
             characteristics: deep caries lesion (greater than or equal to 2/3 of dentine
             thickness) without clinical or radiographic aspects of pulp lesion, restoration
             margins above gingival line, absence of spontaneous pain or mobility, absence of
             periodontal changes, roots compatible with pulpal maturation stage.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Children under use of controlled drugs or antibiotics.

          2. Children who presented with some neurological or motor disorder that could influence
             the treatment procedure.

          3. Molars with more than three lost walls or margins in subgingival area.

          4. Patients with allergies to the medications used.

          5. Patients in the pulpal regression stage in which the tooth is likely to be lost within
             12 months.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>4 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>6 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Apoena A Ribeiro, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <verification_date>August 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 21, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 24, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 29, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 24, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 24, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">August 29, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Universidade Federal Fluminense</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Apoena de Aguiar Ribeiro</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Dental caries</keyword>
  <keyword>Dentin</keyword>
  <keyword>Pulp exposure prevention</keyword>
  <keyword>Deep caries lesion</keyword>
  <keyword>Conservative Treatment</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Dental Caries</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

