<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03654248</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ORU 2018/191</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03654248</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>&quot;Let's Get Organized&quot; in Adult Psychiatric/Habilitation Care</brief_title>
  <official_title>Randomized Controlled Trial of &quot;Let's Get Organized&quot;; an Intervention Program for Improving Time Management Skills in Adults With Cognitive Limitations</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Örebro University, Sweden</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Region Örebro County</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Dalarna County Council, Sweden</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Uppsala University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Region Gävleborg</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>State University of New York - Downstate Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Uppsala County Council, Sweden</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Örebro University, Sweden</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This project aims to evaluate and establish evidence for a novel, group-based intervention
      that can help people with cognitive limitations due to mental or neurodevelopmental disorders
      to improve their ability to manage time and organize activities. This might provide an
      important step towards establishing healthy life habits, getting or maintaining employment,
      and managing family life. Time management is a necessary skill for maintaining healthy life
      habits and daily occupations in modern society. People with limited cognitive function due
      to, for example, mental or neurodevelopmental disorders, have documented difficulties in time
      management, which is also related to issues with self-efficacy. Common interventions for
      persons with poor time management are time-assistive devices and products, but studies show
      that these devices alone are not enough to cover these people's needs. Structured training is
      needed, but there is a lack of structured interventions to enhance time management skills.
      The intervention program &quot;Let's get organized&quot; (LGO) is a manual-based group intervention
      aiming to enhance time management, targeted to persons with mental or neurodevelopmental
      disorders. In a recent feasibility study the LGO showed promising results.

      This project aims to evaluate to what extent the LGO intervention is effective in improving
      time management, and satisfaction with daily occupations. The proposed project is a
      randomized-controlled trial carried out in ten psychiatric units in Sweden. Participants
      (n=104) will be randomly assigned to either LGO group intervention or individual Occupational
      Therapy intervention for ten weeks .The primary outcome of the study is self-reported time
      management measured by the Assessment of Time Management Skills. Secondary outcomes are
      occupational balance, self-efficacy, parental competence and cost-effectiveness.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">August 27, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Assessment of Time Management Skills-Swedish, Time management sub scale at 10 weeks after intervention start and at 24 weeks after intervention start</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline (pre-intervention), 10 weeks, 24 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>11 items, reported as 0-100 ATMS units</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Weekly Calendar Planning Activity-Swedish version No of correct appointments at 10 weeks after intervention start and at 24 weeks after intervention start</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline (pre-intervention), 10 weeks, 24 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Performance test of executive functioning. No of correctly entered appointments (range 0-17)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Weekly Calendar Planning Activity Swedish version total time at 10 weeks after intervention start and at 24 weeks after intervention start</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline (pre-intervention), 10 weeks, 24 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Performance test of executive functioning. Total time</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Weekly Calendar Planning Activity Swedish version no of strategies at 10 weeks after intervention start and at 24 weeks after intervention start</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline (pre-intervention), 10 weeks, 24 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Performance test of executive functioning. No of strategies used more strategies are better</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Weekly Calendar Planning Activity Swedish version rules followed at 10 weeks after intervention start and at 24 weeks after intervention start</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline (pre-intervention), 10 weeks, 24 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Performance test of executive functioning. No of rules followed (range 0-5) More rules followed are better</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Weekly Calendar Planning Activity Swedish version efficacy score at 10 weeks after intervention start and at 24 weeks after intervention start</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline (pre-intervention), 10 weeks, 24 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Performance test of executive functioning. Efficacy score (high score is better)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Satisfaction with daily occupations and occupational balance (SDO-OB) activity score at 10 weeks after intervention start and at 24 weeks after intervention start</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline (pre-intervention), 10 weeks, 24 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>No of activities (range 0-17, higher scores are better)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Satisfaction with daily occupations and occupational balance (SDO-OB) satisfaction score at 10 weeks after intervention start and at 24 weeks after intervention start</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline (pre-intervention), 10 weeks, 24 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Satisfaction score (range 13-91, higher scores are better)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Global satisfaction score at 10 weeks after intervention start and at 24 weeks after intervention start</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline (pre-intervention), 10 weeks, 24 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Global satisfaction score (range 1-5, lower scores are better)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Satisfaction with daily occupations and occupational balance (SDO-OB) occupational balance at 10 weeks after intervention start and at 24 weeks after intervention start</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline (pre-intervention), 10 weeks, 24 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Occupational balance (nominal data)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in General Self-Efficacy Scale at 10 weeks after intervention start and at 24 weeks after intervention start</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline (pre-intervention), 10 weeks, 24 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Self-efficacy (range 0-40, higher score is better)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Parental Sense of Competence at 10 weeks after intervention start and at 24 weeks after intervention start</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline (pre-intervention), 10 weeks, 24 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Sense of competence (range 15-90, higher score is better)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in EuroQuality of Life - 5 dimensions - 5 levels (EQ-5D-5L) item scores at 10 weeks after intervention start and at 24 weeks after intervention start</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline (pre-intervention), 10 weeks, 24 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Individual item scores on 5 items scored 1-5</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in EuroQuality of Life - 5 dimensions - 5 levels (EQ-5D-5L) global score at 10 weeks after intervention start and at 24 weeks after intervention start</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline (pre-intervention), 10 weeks, 24 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>One visual-analogue-scale answer (range 0-100)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Assessment of Time Management Skills-Swedish (ATMS-S), Organization and planning sub scale at 10 weeks after intervention start and at 24 weeks after intervention start</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline (pre-intervention), 10 weeks, 24 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>11 items, reported as 0-100 ATMS units</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Assessment of Time Management Skills-Swedish (ATMS-S), Regulation of emotions sub scale at 10 weeks after intervention start and at 24 weeks after intervention start</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline (pre-intervention), 10 weeks, 24 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>5 items, reported as 0-100 ATMS units</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders Manual-5 Self-rated level 1 Cross-Cutting Symptom Measure Adult: depression domain</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline (pre-intervention), 10 weeks, 24 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>2 items, reported as 0-8 points</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders Manual-5 Self-rated level 1 Cross-Cutting Symptom Measure Adult: anger domain</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline (pre-intervention), 10 weeks, 24 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>1 item, reported as 0-4 points</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in DSM-5 Self-rated level 1 Cross-Cutting Symptom Measure Adult: mania domain</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline (pre-intervention), 10 weeks, 24 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>2 items, reported as 0-8 points</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders Manual-5 Self-rated level 1 Cross-Cutting Symptom Measure Adult: anxiety domain</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline (pre-intervention), 10 weeks, 24 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>3 items, reported as 0-12 points</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders Manual-5 Self-rated level 1 Cross-Cutting Symptom Measure Adult: somatic symptoms domain</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline (pre-intervention), 10 weeks, 24 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>2 items, reported as 0-8 points</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in DSM-5 Self-rated level 1 Cross-Cutting Symptom Measure Adult: suicidal ideation domain</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline (pre-intervention), 10 weeks, 24 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>1 items, reported as 0-4 points</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders Manual-5 Self-rated level 1 Cross-Cutting Symptom Measure Adult: psychosis domain</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline (pre-intervention), 10 weeks, 24 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>2 items, reported as 0-8 points</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders Manual-5 Self-rated level 1 Cross-Cutting Symptom Measure Adult: sleep problems domain</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline (pre-intervention), 10 weeks, 24 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>1 items, reported as 0-4 points</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders Manual-5 Self-rated level 1 Cross-Cutting Symptom Measure Adult: memory domain</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline (pre-intervention), 10 weeks, 24 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>1 items, reported as 0-4 points</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders Manual-5 Self-rated level 1 Cross-Cutting Symptom Measure Adult: repetitive thoughts and behaviors domain</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline (pre-intervention), 10 weeks, 24 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>2 items, reported as 0-8 points</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders Manual-5 Self-rated level 1 Cross-Cutting Symptom Measure Adult: dissociation domain</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline (pre-intervention), 10 weeks, 24 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>1 items, reported as 0-4 points</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders Manual-5 Self-rated level 1 Cross-Cutting Symptom Measure Adult: personality functioning domain</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline (pre-intervention), 10 weeks, 24 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>2 items, reported as 0-8 points</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders Manual-5 Self-rated level 1 Cross-Cutting Symptom Measure Adult: substance use domain</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline (pre-intervention), 10 weeks, 24 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>3 items, reported as 0-12 points</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Autism Quotient Short</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline (pre-intervention), 10 weeks, 24 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>28 items, 28-112 points</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adult Attention Deficit Hyperactivity disorder Self-report Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline (pre-intervention), 10 weeks, 24 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>18 items, score 1-90</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">104</enrollment>
  <condition>Neurodevelopmental Disorders</condition>
  <condition>Mental Disorder</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Let's Get Organized group intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Group intervention with 10 weekly sessions, each lasting 1,5 hours</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Individual Occupational Therapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Individual intervention lasting 10 weeks</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Let's Get Organized group intervention</intervention_name>
    <description>Group intervention aiming to enhance time management, targeted to persons with mental or neurodevelopment disorders. Each group has 6-8 participants and is lead by two trained group leaders. Goal-directed and other learning strategies are used to train effective time management habits such as maintaining a calendar and wearing a watch. Group sessions are structured with PowerPoint presentation and a course manual, an information from the group leaders is intermixed with discussion among the participants and tasks to complete.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Let's Get Organized group intervention</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>LGO</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Individual Occupational Therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>Individual meetings with Occupational Therapist (standard therapy) during a 10-week period. Number of meetings and exact nature of intervention depends on the client's needs and is decided by the treating occupational therapist. Interventions will include prescription or instruction regarding time assistive devices and instructions regarding structure and planning of everyday life.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Individual Occupational Therapy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  confirmed or suspected diagnosis of a mental disorder, such as affective disorder or
             schizophrenia, or neurodevelopment disorder, such as autism spectrum disorder or
             attention deficit hyperactivity disorder/attention deficit disorder

          -  self-reported difficulties in time management in daily life to an extent that affects
             functioning in daily life negatively

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  intellectual disability
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Marie Holmefur, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Örebro University, Sweden</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Kajsa Lidström-Holmqvist, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+46703531520</phone>
    <email>kajsa.lidstrom-holmqvist@regionorebrolan.se</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Öppenvårdspsykiatrisk mottagning</name>
      <address>
        <city>Falun</city>
        <state>Dalarna</state>
        <zip>79131</zip>
        <country>Sweden</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Occupational Therapist</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Karlskoga psykiatrisk öppenvård</name>
      <address>
        <city>Karlskoga</city>
        <state>Orebro</state>
        <zip>69181</zip>
        <country>Sweden</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Occupational Therapist</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>NP Resurs och samverkan</name>
      <address>
        <city>Örebro</city>
        <zip>70116</zip>
        <country>Sweden</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Occupational Therapist</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Socialpsykiatrin i Örebro kommun</name>
      <address>
        <city>Örebro</city>
        <zip>70116</zip>
        <country>Sweden</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Occupational Therapist</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>USÖ psykiatrisk öppenvård och affektiva enhet</name>
      <address>
        <city>Örebro</city>
        <zip>70116</zip>
        <country>Sweden</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Occupational Therapist</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Vuxenhabiliteringen - Autismteamet</name>
      <address>
        <city>Örebro</city>
        <zip>70116</zip>
        <country>Sweden</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Occupational Therapist</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hallsberg psykiatrisk öppenvård</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hallsberg</city>
        <state>Örebro</state>
        <zip>69436</zip>
        <country>Sweden</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Occupational Therapist</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Lindesberg psykiatrisk öppenvård</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lindesberg</city>
        <state>Örebro</state>
        <zip>71182</zip>
        <country>Sweden</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Occupational Therapist</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Sweden</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 20, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 28, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 31, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 17, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 17, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 18, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Time management</keyword>
  <keyword>Group intervention</keyword>
  <keyword>Executive function</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Mental Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neurodevelopmental Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

