<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03655470</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>R34MH114307</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>1R34MH114307-01A1</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03655470</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Safety Planning Juvenile Justice</brief_title>
  <acronym>Safety</acronym>
  <official_title>Screening and Brief Intervention for Suicidality and Nonsuicidal Self-Injury Among Youth in the Juvenile Justice System</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Brown University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Mental Health (NIMH)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Brown University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will examine the feasibility and acceptability of a program designed to conduct
      safety planning with youth in the juvenile justice system who are at risk for a suicide
      attempt and/or self-injury and to increase the possibility of them receiving outpatient
      mental health treatment. After training staff in the intervention, the investigators will
      pilot test the safety planning intervention and gather information on how well it worked on
      reducing self-harm, getting families to follow up with referrals for mental health care, and
      how often they attend treatment.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The Juvenile Justice System (JJS) has not implemented any evidenced-based interventions that
      address suicidal behavior or nonsuicidal self-injury, hereafter referred collectively to as
      self-injury, with JJS-involved youth. This application proposes to test a scalable
      intervention, safety planning, that aims to reduce self-injury in adolescents involved in the
      JJS. Safety planning, which can be a stand-alone brief intervention, was cited as a best
      practice by the Suicide Prevention Resource Center/American Foundation for Suicide Prevention
      Best Practices Registry for Suicide Prevention. This study will have two phases. In Phase I,
      the investigators will conduct an open trial with 10 adolescents which will allow us to make
      any modifications necessary for using the protocol in a Probation Department. The
      investigators will then randomize 60 youth on Probation who screen positive for recent
      self-injury into standard care or the safety planning intervention. Counselors with community
      mental health experience embedded in Probation will conduct the intervention, consistent with
      the co-responder model found across JJS in the U.S. in which a Probation Officer works
      collaboratively with a mental health professional to coordinate care. In order to further
      conduct the study under conditions most relevant to a future implementation trial, the
      investigators will also employ a training approach that has been successfully implemented in
      a psychiatric hospital with Bachelors and Masters level staff. In Phase II, of the study, the
      investigators will: a) conduct qualitative interviews in Probation about attitudes toward the
      intervention as well as barriers to a future, larger implementation trial; and b) contract
      with the National Center for Mental Health and Juvenile Justice to conduct a Sequential
      Intercept Model (SIM) Mapping. The SIM is a conceptual framework to outline a series of
      &quot;points of interception&quot; along the JJS continuum in a state where screening and brief
      intervention may be implemented. In the Mapping, the investigators will examine the JJS
      continuum from arrest; to an initial hearing; to jail awaiting trial or adjudication;
      incarceration; to release or reentry; and finally, to community supervision. These data will
      provide a working framework to help assess current views within the statewide JJS as a
      starting point to proposing a future, larger trial. This research also has the potential to
      directly inform treatment practices in JJ settings and has significant implications for
      scalability and dissemination in order to build a stronger, more effective system of mental
      health/JJS collaboration around self-injury screening and intervention.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 31, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 1, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>2 group randomized controlled trial</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>Outcome assessors will be blind; participants will not be told to what condition they are assigned</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in suicidal ideation</measure>
    <time_frame>Past month ideation at 1 and 3 month follow-up points</time_frame>
    <description>Score on Suicidal Ideation Questionnaire; higher is worse; range 0 to180</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in suicide attempts</measure>
    <time_frame>1 and 3 month follow-up points</time_frame>
    <description>Self report of suicide attempts; higher is worse</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Suicidal Ideation</condition>
  <condition>Suicide, Attempted</condition>
  <condition>Nonsuicidal Self-injury</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Safety Planning</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>This brief intervention, consists of an in-person and follow-up phone call that are based on cognitive behavioral principles designed to help identify a concrete list of coping strategies and social supports that youth can utilize preceding or during a crisis to lower imminent risk of nonsuicidal self-injury or suicidal behavior.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Standard Care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>If a teen has a positive screen for suicide risk, the Probation Officer completes a &quot;secondary screener&quot; built into the court screening instrument to determine whether there is concern of current and/or imminent risk. If a teen endorses nonsuicidal self-injury more than once in the prior year, then the Probation Officer asks about frequency and severity. If there is ongoing concern of risk for self-injurious behavior, then the Probation Officer arranges for a crisis evaluation in the Emergency Department. If the teen is not judged to be at imminent risk, the Probation Officer makes a referral back to the current treatment provider or to a community mental health clinic. In either case, the parents and youth receive a packet with mental health resources</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Safety Planning</intervention_name>
    <description>Safety planning is an individual coping intervention to reduce suicidal risk in adolescents</description>
    <arm_group_label>Safety Planning</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Standard care</intervention_name>
    <description>Standard care entails sending an adolescent for an emergency evaluation for suicidal risk in an Emergency Department</description>
    <arm_group_label>Standard Care</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Legal guardian available to consent for juvenile's participation

          -  Juvenile and parents are English or Spanish speaking

          -  Juvenile flags in on the screening measure used in court with respect to suicidal
             ideation or nonsuicidal self-injury.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  None
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>12 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>18 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Anthony Spirito, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>401-444-1929</phone>
    <email>anthony_spirito@brown.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Kathleen Kemp, PhD</last_name>
    <email>kkemp@lifespan.org</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Rhode Island Family Court</name>
      <address>
        <city>Providence</city>
        <state>Rhode Island</state>
        <zip>02903</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Kathleen Kemp, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>401-793-8269</phone>
      <email>kkemp@lifespan.org</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Kevin Richard, BA</last_name>
      <phone>401-458-5262</phone>
      <email>KRichard@courts.ri.gov</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Brown Univerity</name>
      <address>
        <city>Providence</city>
        <state>Rhode Island</state>
        <zip>02912</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Anthony Spirito, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 30, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 30, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 31, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 4, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 4, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 5, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>suicidal behavior</keyword>
  <keyword>nonsuicidal self injury</keyword>
  <keyword>adolescents</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Suicide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Suicidal Ideation</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Suicide, Attempted</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Self-Injurious Behavior</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>The final study protocol will contain the information necessary to reproduce the findings in other populations. The protocol will include a copy of this grant application including Specific Aims and study population; recruitment and enrollment information; the measures collected and coding of the measures and subscales; the clinician intervention procedures; data analyses; syntax for data summary, and data analysis plans</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Statistical Analysis Plan (SAP)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Informed Consent Form (ICF)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>1 year after completion of all follow-up data</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>Contact PI</ipd_access_criteria>
  </patient_data>
  <provided_document_section>
    <provided_document>
      <document_type>Informed Consent Form</document_type>
      <document_has_protocol>No</document_has_protocol>
      <document_has_icf>Yes</document_has_icf>
      <document_has_sap>No</document_has_sap>
      <document_date>February 25, 2020</document_date>
      <document_url>https://ClinicalTrials.gov/ProvidedDocs/70/NCT03655470/ICF_000.pdf</document_url>
    </provided_document>
  </provided_document_section>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

