<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03652610</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>205343</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>V59_71</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>2017-003692-61</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03652610</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study to Investigate the Safety and Immunogenicity of Different Formulations of GSK Biologicals' Meningococcal ACWY Conjugate Vaccine (GSK3536820A and Menveo) Administered to Healthy Adults 18 to 40 Years of Age</brief_title>
  <official_title>Immunogenicity, Reactogenicity and Safety of Two Formulations of GSK Biologicals' Meningococcal ACWY Conjugate Vaccine (GSK3536820A and Menveo) in Healthy Adults 18 to 40 Years of Age</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>GlaxoSmithKline</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>GlaxoSmithKline</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      MenACWY (Menveo) is a GSK vaccine intended for protection against disease caused by
      meningococcal bacteria groups A, C, W and Y in infants, children and adults, licensed in more
      than 60 countries.

      The purpose of this study is to compare the immunogenicity of the currently licensed MenACWY
      vaccine with the investigational MenACWY liquid vaccine.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 7, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">June 11, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">January 17, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>Data will be collected in an observer-blind manner. By observer-blind, it is meant that during the course of the study, the vaccine recipient and those responsible for the evaluation of any study endpoint (e.g. safety, reactogenicity and immunogenicity) will all be unaware of which vaccine was administered. To do so, vaccine preparation and administration will be done by authorized medical personnel who will not participate in any of the study clinical evaluations.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Human Serum Bactericidal Activity (hSBA) Geometric Mean Titers (GMTs) against N. meningitidis serogroup A for each vaccine group and between-groups ratios.</measure>
    <time_frame>At Day 29</time_frame>
    <description>hSBA titers against N.meningitidis serogroup A are calculated in terms of GMTs.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>hSBA GMTs against each of the N.meningitidis serogroups A, C, W and Y for each vaccine group and between-groups ratios</measure>
    <time_frame>At Day 1 and Day 29</time_frame>
    <description>Geometric Mean Titers (GMTs) against each of the N. meningitidis serogroup A (except Day 29), C, W and Y</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Within-group Geometric Mean Ratios (GMRs) of GMTs against each of the N.meningitidis serogroups A, C, W and Y.</measure>
    <time_frame>At Day 29</time_frame>
    <description>Within group ratios of hSBA GMTs against each of the N.meningitidis serogroups A, C, W and Y at Day 29 compared to Day 1.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentages of subjects with ≥4 fold rise in hSBA antibody titers for each of the N.meningitidis serogroups A, C,W and Y for each vaccine group and between-groups differences.</measure>
    <time_frame>At Day 29</time_frame>
    <description>The percentages of subjects with a ≥ 4-fold rise in post-vaccination hSBA (at Day 29 compared to Day 1) and associated 2-sided 95% Clopper-Pearson CIs are computed by group and N. meningitidis serogroups A, C, W and Y. A 4-fold rise in the hSBA titers is defined as:
for individuals, whose pre-vaccination titers are &lt; the LOD (limit of detection), the post-vaccination titers must be ≥ 4-fold the LOD or ≥ the LLOQ (lower of limit of quantitation) whichever is greater;
for individuals, whose pre-vaccination titers are ≥ the LOD and ≤ the LLOQ, the post-vaccination titres must be at least four times the LLOQ;
for individuals whose pre-vaccination titers are &gt; the LLOQ, the post-vaccination titers must be at least four times the pre-vaccination titer.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentages of subjects with hSBA titers ≥8 and ≥LLOQ against each of the N. meningitidis serogroups A, C, W and Y for each vaccine group and between-groups differences</measure>
    <time_frame>At Day 1 and Day 29</time_frame>
    <description>For each vaccine group the percentages of subjects with hSBA titer ≥8 and ≥LLOQ* and associated two-sided 95% Clopper-Pearson CIs are computed by the N. meningitidis serogroups A, C, W and Y on Day 1 and Day 29 Note*: ≥ LLOQ is to be assessed for each serogroup if the pre-defined LLOQ value for that serogroup is &gt;8</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of subjects reporting any unsolicited adverse events (AEs) within 30 min after vaccination</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 30 min after vaccination at Day 1</time_frame>
    <description>An unsolicited adverse event (AE) is defined as any untoward medical occurrence in a subject or clinical investigation subject administered with a pharmaceutical product at any dose that does not necessarily have to have a causal relationship with this treatment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of subjects reporting solicited local and systemic AEs</measure>
    <time_frame>From Day 1 (6 hours) to Day 7 after vaccination</time_frame>
    <description>Number of subjects with solicited local and systemic AEs during the 7-days period (including the day of vaccination) after the vaccination.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of subjects reporting other indicators of reactogenicity</measure>
    <time_frame>From Day 1 to Day 7 after vaccination</time_frame>
    <description>Number of subjects reporting other indicators of reactogenicity such as use of analgesics/antipyretics within 7 days after vaccination</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of subjects reporting any unsolicited AEs</measure>
    <time_frame>From Day 1 to Day 29 after vaccination</time_frame>
    <description>An unsolicited adverse event (AE) is defined as any untoward medical occurrence in a subject or clinical investigation subject administered with a pharmaceutical product at any dose that does not necessarily have to have a causal relationship with this treatment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of subjects reporting serious adverse events (SAEs), AEs leading to withdrawal and medically attended AEs</measure>
    <time_frame>From Day 1 to Day 181 (during the entire study period)</time_frame>
    <description>Medically attended AEs are defined as events for which the subject received medical attention defined as hospitalization, an emergency room visit, or a visit to or from medical personnel (medical doctor) for any reason. Any medically attended AE(s) is occurrence of any medically attended AE(s) regardless of intensity grade or relation to vaccination. Serious adverse event is any congenital anomaly/birth defect in the offspring of a study subject or any untoward medical occurrence that results in death or life threatening or requires hospitalization or results in disability or incapacity</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">996</enrollment>
  <condition>Infections, Meningococcal</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>GSK3536820A ACWY_Liq Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Approximately 486 healthy adults 18 to 40 years of age, receiving at Day 1 a single dose of investigational MenACWY liquid vaccine (GSK3536820A) formulation with approximately 30% Men A FS.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>ACWY Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Approximately 486 healthy adults 18 to 40 years of age, receiving at Day 1 a single dose of licensed GSK' MenACWY vaccine formulation (Menveo).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>MenACWY liquid vaccine with approximately 30% MenA FS (GSK3536820A)</intervention_name>
    <description>Single dose administered at Day 1, by intramuscular injection in the deltoid of the non-dominant arm</description>
    <arm_group_label>GSK3536820A ACWY_Liq Group</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>GSK3536820A</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Licensed GSK MenACWY vaccine (Menveo)</intervention_name>
    <description>Single dose administered at Day 1, by intramuscular injection in the deltoid of the non-dominant arm</description>
    <arm_group_label>ACWY Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Subjects who, in the opinion of the investigator, can and will comply with the
             requirements of the protocol or subjects' parent(s)/Legally Acceptable
             Respresentative(s) [LAR(s)] who, in the opinion of the investigator, can and will
             comply, with the requirements of the protocol.

          2. Written informed consent obtained from the subject/from the parents(s)/LAR(s) of the
             subject prior to performance of any study specific procedure.

          3. Written informed assent obtained for subjects below legal age of consent, if required
             by local regulations, at the time of enrolment.

          4. A male or female between, and including, ≥18 to ≤40 YoA at the time of the first
             vaccination.

          5. Healthy subjects as established by medical history and clinical examination before
             entering into the study.

          6. Female subjects of non-childbearing potential may be enrolled in the study.

               -  Non-childbearing potential is defined as pre-menarche, current bilateral tubal
                  ligation or occlusion, hysterectomy, bilateral ovariectomy or post-menopause.

          7. Female subjects of childbearing potential may be enrolled in the study, if the
             subject:

               -  has practiced adequate contraception for 30 days prior to vaccination, and

               -  has a negative pregnancy test on the day of vaccination, and

               -  has agreed to continue adequate contraception during the entire treatment period.
                  (approximately 1 month after vaccination).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Anaphylaxis following the administration of vaccine

          2. Any (clinical) condition that in the judgment of the investigator would make
             intramuscular injection unsafe and/or represents a contraindication to intramuscular
             vaccination and blood draws.

          3. Any confirmed or suspected immunosuppressive or immunodeficient condition, including
             HIV infection.

          4. Progressive, unstable or uncontrolled clinical conditions.

          5. Hypersensitivity, including allergy, to any component of vaccines, medicinal products
             or medical equipment whose use is foreseen in this study.

          6. Hypersensitivity to the active substances or to any of the excipients of the vaccine,
             including diphtheria toxoid (CRM197), or a life-threatening reaction after previous
             administration of a vaccine containing similar components.

          7. Abnormal function of the immune system resulting from:

               -  Clinical conditions.

               -  Systemic administration of corticosteroids (Per os [PO]/ Intravenous [IV]/
                  Intramuscular [IM]) for more than 14 consecutive days within 90 days prior to
                  informed consent, and until the Day 29 blood draw.

               -  Administration of antineoplastic and immuno-modulating agents or radiotherapy
                  within 90 days prior to informed consent, and until the Day 29 blood draw.

          8. Received immunoglobulins or any blood products within 180 days prior to informed
             consent.

          9. Received an investigational or non-registered medicinal product within 30 days prior
             to informed consent.

         10. Any other clinical condition that, in the opinion of the investigator, might interfere
             with the results of the study or pose additional risk to the subject due to
             participation in the study.

         11. History of any meningococcal vaccination.

         12. Individuals who received any other vaccines within 7 days (for inactivated vaccines)
             or 14 days (for live vaccines) prior to enrolment in this study or who are planning to
             receive any vaccine within 28 days from the study vaccines*.

             * In case an emergency mass vaccination for an unforeseen public health threat (e.g.:
             a pandemic) is organised by the public health authorities, outside the routine
             immunization program, the time period described above can be reduced if necessary for
             that vaccine provided it is licensed and used according to its Summary of Product
             Characteristics (SmPC) or Prescribing Information and according to the local
             governmental recommendations and provided a written approval of the Sponsor is
             obtained.

         13. Administration of long-acting immune-modifying drugs at any time during the study
             period (e.g. infliximab).

         14. Concurrently participating in another clinical study, at any time during the study
             period, in which the subject has been or will be exposed to an investigational or a
             non-investigational vaccine/product. (pharmaceutical product or device).

         15. Current or previous, confirmed or suspected disease caused by N. meningitidis.

         16. Household contact with and/or intimate exposure to an individual with any laboratory
             confirmed N. meningitidis infection within 60 days prior to study vaccination.

         17. Acute disease and/or fever within 3 days prior to study vaccination. Note: enrolment
             may be postponed/delayed until such transient circumstances have ended.

               -  Fever is defined as body temperature ≥ 38.0°C / 100.4°F. The preferred location
                  for measuring temperature in this study will be the oral cavity.

               -  Subjects with a minor illness (such as mild diarrhoea, mild upper respiratory
                  infection) without fever may be enrolled at the discretion of the investigator.

         18. Received systemic antibiotic treatment within 3 days prior to study vaccination or
             blood draw.

         19. Study personnel as an immediate family or household member.

         20. Pregnant or lactating women.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>40 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>GSK Clinical Trials</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>GlaxoSmithKline</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Blacktown</city>
        <state>New South Wales</state>
        <zip>2148</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kanwal</city>
        <state>New South Wales</state>
        <zip>2259</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Gold Coast</city>
        <state>Queensland</state>
        <zip>4222</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sherwood</city>
        <state>Queensland</state>
        <zip>4075</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Adelaide</city>
        <state>South Australia</state>
        <zip>5000</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Melbourne</city>
        <state>Victoria</state>
        <zip>3004</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Murdoch</city>
        <state>Western Australia</state>
        <zip>6150</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Melbourne</city>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Gent</city>
        <zip>9000</zip>
        <country>Belgium</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Leuven</city>
        <zip>3000</zip>
        <country>Belgium</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Victoria</city>
        <state>British Columbia</state>
        <zip>V8V 3M9</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Halifax</city>
        <state>Nova Scotia</state>
        <zip>B3K 6R8</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Truro</city>
        <state>Nova Scotia</state>
        <zip>B2N 1L2</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Brampton</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>L6T 0G1</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>London</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>N5W 6A2</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toronto</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>M9W 4L6</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Mirabel</city>
        <state>Quebec</state>
        <zip>J7J 2K8</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pointe-Claire</city>
        <state>Quebec</state>
        <zip>H9R 4S3</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sherbrooke</city>
        <state>Quebec</state>
        <zip>J1L 0H8</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Quebec</city>
        <zip>G1W 4R4</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Wuerzburg</city>
        <state>Bayern</state>
        <zip>97070</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Essen</city>
        <state>Nordrhein-Westfalen</state>
        <zip>45355</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Goch</city>
        <state>Nordrhein-Westfalen</state>
        <zip>47574</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Mainz</city>
        <state>Rheinland-Pfalz</state>
        <zip>55116</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Berlin</city>
        <zip>10117</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hamburg</city>
        <zip>22143</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chieti</city>
        <state>Abruzzo</state>
        <zip>66013</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Genova</city>
        <state>Liguria</state>
        <zip>16132</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Conegliano - Treviso</city>
        <zip>31015</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Massafra (TA)</city>
        <zip>74016</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Australia</country>
    <country>Belgium</country>
    <country>Canada</country>
    <country>Germany</country>
    <country>Italy</country>
  </location_countries>
  <removed_countries>
    <country>Estonia</country>
  </removed_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 28, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 28, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 29, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <disposition_first_submitted>January 17, 2020</disposition_first_submitted>
  <disposition_first_submitted_qc>February 18, 2020</disposition_first_submitted_qc>
  <disposition_first_posted type="Actual">February 25, 2020</disposition_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 18, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 18, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 25, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Meningitis</keyword>
  <keyword>Liquid formulation</keyword>
  <keyword>Meningococcal disease</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Meningococcal Infections</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Vaccines</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Patient-level data for this study will be made available through www.clinicalstudydatarequest.com following the timelines and process described on this site.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted, but a results disposition has been submitted           -->
</clinical_study>

