<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03658785</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2018TNB-V01</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03658785</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Immunotherapy for the Treatment of Advanced Solid Tumor</brief_title>
  <official_title>Immunotherapy Using Precision T Cells Specific to Personalized Neo-antigen for the Treatment of Advanced Solid Tumor</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Tongji Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Tongji Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to evaluate the safety, side effects and benefits of autologous
      tumor infiltrating lymphocytes(TIL) specific to personalized Neo-antigens in the treatment of
      patients with recurrent, metastatic and advanced solid tumors.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Adoptive cell transfer therapy that utilizes an autologous TIL manufacturing progress is
      originally developed by the NCI for the treatment of patients with recurrent, metastatic
      cervical cancer. TILs specific to personalized neo-antigens will be expended in vitro and
      given back to the patients through vein. A total of 20 patients will be enrolled in the
      single-arm, open label, interventional study.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">December 10, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Objective Responce Rate</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months after cell infusion</time_frame>
    <description>The Objective Responce Rate of patients received immunotherapy are accesed by the Response Criteria in Solid Tumors (RECIST) v1.0.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse Event</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Aggregate of all adverse events, as well as their frequency and severity are accessed by the Common Terminology Criteria in Adverse Events (CTCAE v4.03).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Disease Control Rate</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Disease control rate (DCR) as measured by RECIST 1.1 criteria.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of Response</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Duration of response (DOR) as measured by RECIST 1.1 criteria .</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression-Free Survival</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>PFS will be summarized using Kaplan-Meier estimates.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall Survival</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 60 months</time_frame>
    <description>The overall survival of all patients entering the study will be monitored.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Recurrence Tumor</condition>
  <condition>Metastatic Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Solid Tumor</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>TIL,IL-2,Cyclophosphamide,Fludarabine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Biological: TIL On day 0, cells will be infused intravenously over 20 to 30 minutes (one to four days after the last dose of fludarabine).
Drug: Aldesleukin Aldesleukin 720,000 IU/kg IV (based on total body weight) over 15 minutes approximately every eight hours (+/- 1hr) beginning within 24 hours of cell infusion and continuing for up to 5 days (maximum of 15 doses.) Drug: Cyclophosphamide On day -7 and day -6: Cyclophosphamide 60 mg/kg/day X 2 days IV in 250 ml D5W over 1 hr.
Drug: Fludarabine Days -7 to -3: Fludarabine 25 mg /m2/day IVPB daily over 30 minutes for 5 days.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>TIL</intervention_name>
    <description>On day 0, cells will be infused intravenously over 20 to 30 minutes (one to four days after the last dose of fludarabine)</description>
    <arm_group_label>TIL,IL-2,Cyclophosphamide,Fludarabine</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Aldesleukin</intervention_name>
    <description>Aldesleukin 720,000 IU/kg IV (based on total body weight) over 15 minutes approximately every eight hours (+/- 1hr) beginning within 24 hours of cell infusion and continuing for up to 5 days (maximum of 15 doses.)</description>
    <arm_group_label>TIL,IL-2,Cyclophosphamide,Fludarabine</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>IL-2</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cyclophosphamide</intervention_name>
    <description>On day -7 and day -6: Cyclophosphamide 60 mg/kg/day X 2 days IV in 250 ml D5W over 1 hr.</description>
    <arm_group_label>TIL,IL-2,Cyclophosphamide,Fludarabine</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>CTX</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Fludarabine</intervention_name>
    <description>Days -7 to -3: Fludarabine 25 mg /m2/day IVPB daily over 30 minutes for 5 days</description>
    <arm_group_label>TIL,IL-2,Cyclophosphamide,Fludarabine</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        To be eligible for the study, patients must meet ALL of the following criteria prior to
        enrollment in the study:

          1. Must be ≥ 18 years of age at the time of consent.

          2. Must have recurrent, metastatic, or persistent carcinoma that is not amenable to
             curative treatment with surgery and/or radiation therapy and for which no other
             therapies are expected to have significant benefit, in the opinion of the
             Investigator.

          3. Must have at least 1 lesion that is resectable for TIL generation. The resected TIL
             generating lesion(s) should yield at least 1.5 cm in diameter post-resection of tumor
             tissue. Following resection for TIL generation, must have a remaining measurable
             target lesion as defined by RECIST v1.1.

          4. Patients must have progressive disease while receiving or after the completion of the
             most recent prior treatment.

          5. Any prior therapy directed at the malignant tumor must be discontinued at least 28
             days prior to tumor resection. Radiation therapy may have been received up to 28 days
             prior to tumor resection for lesions not expected to be used for TIL generation or
             target lesions.

          6. Have an Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status of 0 or 1.

          7. Patients must be seronegative for the human immunodeficiency virus (HIV).

          8. Patients with positive serology for hepatitis B virus surface antigen (HBsAg),
             hepatitis B core antibody (anti-HBc), or hepatitis C virus (anti-HCV) indicating acute
             or chronic infection may be enrolled if the viral load by polymerase chain reaction
             (PCR) is undetectable with/without active treatment.

          9. Hematology:

             Absolute neutrophil count greater than 1000/mm(3) without the support of
             filgrastim;White blood cell (WBC) greater than or equal to 3000/mm(3);Platelet count
             greater than or equal too 100,000/mm(3);Hemoglobin greater than 8.0 g/dl.

         10. Chemistry:

             Serum alanine aminotransferase (ALT)/aspartate aminotransferase (AST) less than or
             equal to to 2.5 times the upper limit of normal. Serum creatinine less than or equal
             to to 1.6 mg/dl.Total bilirubin less that or equal to 1.5 mg/dl, except in patients
             with Gilbert's Syndrome who must have a total bilirubin less than 3.0 mg/dl.

         11. Women of child bearing potential must have a negative pregnancy test because of the
             potentially dangerous effects of the treatment on the fetus.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients who have received an organ allograft or prior cell transfer therapy.

          2. Patients who are on a systemic steroid therapy &gt; 10 mg of prednisone daily or other
             steroid equivalent.

          3. Patients who currently have prior therapy-related toxicities greater than Grade 1
             according to NCI-CTCAE v4.03; except for peripheral neuropathy, alopecia, or vitiligo
             prior to enrollment/resection.

          4. Patients who have a contraindication to or history of hypersensitivity reaction to any
             component or excipients of the TIL therapy and the other study drugs.

          5. Patients with active systemic infections, coagulation disorders or other active major
             medical illnesses of the cardiovascular, respiratory, or immune system.

          6. Patients with symptomatic and/or untreated brain metastases (of any size and any
             number).

          7. Patients who have any form of primary or acquired immunodeficiency syndrome, such as
             severe combined immunodeficiency disease or acquired immune deficiency syndrome
             (AIDS).

          8. Patients who have a diagnosis of end-stage renal disorder requiring hemodialysis.

          9. Patients who have a left ventricular ejection fraction (LVEF) &lt; 45% or who are New
             York Heart Association (NYHA) Class 2 or higher.

             Patients who have a forced expiratory volume in 1 second (FEV1) of less than or equal
             to 60% of predicted normal.

         10. Patients who have received a live or attenuated vaccine within 28 days of the NMA-LD
             regimen.

         11. Patients whose cancer requires immediate treatment or who would otherwise suffer a
             disadvantage by participating in this study.

         12. Patients who have received prior treatment with immunotherapy (eg, anti-PD-1
             anti-PD-L1, or anti-CTLA4 antibodies)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Hui Wang, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Tongji Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Hui Wang, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+8613995688388</phone>
    <email>huit71@sohu.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Tongji Hospital, Tongji Medical College, Huazhong University of Science and Technology</name>
      <address>
        <city>Wuhan</city>
        <state>Hubei</state>
        <zip>430000</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Wang</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Stevanović S, Draper LM, Langhan MM, Campbell TE, Kwong ML, Wunderlich JR, Dudley ME, Yang JC, Sherry RM, Kammula US, Restifo NP, Rosenberg SA, Hinrichs CS. Complete regression of metastatic cervical cancer after treatment with human papillomavirus-targeted tumor-infiltrating T cells. J Clin Oncol. 2015 May 10;33(14):1543-50. doi: 10.1200/JCO.2014.58.9093. Epub 2015 Mar 30.</citation>
    <PMID>25823737</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Stevanović S, Pasetto A, Helman SR, Gartner JJ, Prickett TD, Howie B, Robins HS, Robbins PF, Klebanoff CA, Rosenberg SA, Hinrichs CS. Landscape of immunogenic tumor antigens in successful immunotherapy of virally induced epithelial cancer. Science. 2017 Apr 14;356(6334):200-205. doi: 10.1126/science.aak9510.</citation>
    <PMID>28408606</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tran E, Turcotte S, Gros A, Robbins PF, Lu YC, Dudley ME, Wunderlich JR, Somerville RP, Hogan K, Hinrichs CS, Parkhurst MR, Yang JC, Rosenberg SA. Cancer immunotherapy based on mutation-specific CD4+ T cells in a patient with epithelial cancer. Science. 2014 May 9;344(6184):641-5. doi: 10.1126/science.1251102.</citation>
    <PMID>24812403</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zacharakis N, Chinnasamy H, Black M, Xu H, Lu YC, Zheng Z, Pasetto A, Langhan M, Shelton T, Prickett T, Gartner J, Jia L, Trebska-McGowan K, Somerville RP, Robbins PF, Rosenberg SA, Goff SL, Feldman SA. Immune recognition of somatic mutations leading to complete durable regression in metastatic breast cancer. Nat Med. 2018 Jun;24(6):724-730. doi: 10.1038/s41591-018-0040-8. Epub 2018 Jun 4.</citation>
    <PMID>29867227</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>September 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 3, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 3, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 5, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 5, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 5, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">September 7, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Tongji Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Wang Hui,MD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Vice Director of Deparment of Gynecology and Obstetrics</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>TIL</keyword>
  <keyword>neo-antigen</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Recurrence</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Aldesleukin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cyclophosphamide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fludarabine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

