<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04262570</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>453_19B</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04262570</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluation of Therapeutic Response in Spinal Muscular Atrophy Using Multispectral Optoacoustic Tomography (MSOT) and Magnetic Resonance Imaging (MRI)</brief_title>
  <official_title>Evaluation of Therapeutic Response in Spinal Muscular Atrophy Using Multispectral Optoacoustic Tomography (MSOT) and Magnetic Resonance Imaging (MRI)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Erlangen-Nürnberg Medical School</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Erlangen-Nürnberg Medical School</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study aims to refine the capability of Multispectral Optoacoustic Tomography (MSOT) and
      Magnet Resonance Imaging (MRI) to characterise the molecular composition of muscle tissue
      non-invasively and to evaluate the therapeutic response in patients with spinal muscular
      atrophy (SMA) over time.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      SMA is an autosomal-recessive disorder, characterized by progressive muscle weakness and
      atrophy with an incidence of 1/10,000. The condition is caused by a homozygous deletion or
      mutation in the survival motor neuron 1 (SMN1), resulting in reduced expression of the
      survival motor neuron (SMN) protein. This leads to the degeneration of motor neurons in the
      spinal cord and brain stem. A nearby related gene, survival motor neuron 2 (SMN2), could
      partially compensate the loss of SMN1. Individuals with a higher copy number of SMN2 do in
      general have a milder phenotype. New therapeutic approaches, e.g. nusinersen (spinraza©), an
      antisense oligonucleotide medication that modulates pre-messenger RNA splicing of the
      survival motor neuron 2 (SMN2) gene, are promising to help the formerly incurable disease.
      However, most clinical trials lack primary outcomes other than clinical testing. Preliminary
      work shows that new methods such as multispectral optoacoustic tomography (MSOT) and magnetic
      resonance imaging (MRI) detect tissue changes very sensitively. Multispectral optoacoustic
      tomography (MSOT) is capable of visualizing the distribution of endogenous absorbers by
      initiating laser-induced thermoelastic expansion and detection of resulting pressure waves.
      This imaging technique enables the label-free detection and quantification of different
      endogenous chromophores. In addition to this technology, MRI imaging has advanced in the
      field of muscle diseases, with 23Na-MRI being the first example. With both methods, the
      molecular composition of muscle tissue can be determined non-invasively and quantitatively at
      the same time. In this first pilot study on patients with SMA, the investigators will now
      assess whether the differences in the muscle composition of SMA patients with or without
      therapy can be quantified and whether they can be used simultaneously as markers during
      therapy with nusinersen (spinraza©) . Ideally, both techniques can complement or validate
      each other. In the future, this could generate a completely new, non-invasive method for
      evaluating endogenous biomarkers for therapy response.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 25, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluation of muscle structure under therapy and change from baseline over time</measure>
    <time_frame>3 time points (at 0,2, and 12 months)</time_frame>
    <description>Comparison of the molecular muscle structure determined by MSOT and MRI in patients with SMA with and without treatment and evaluation of changes from baseline over time</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Muscular lipid content</measure>
    <time_frame>3 time points (at 0,2, and 12 months)</time_frame>
    <description>Quantitative lipid signal derived by transcutaneous Multispectral Optoacoustic Tomography (MSOT) in patients with SMA with and without therapy and change over time Units: arbitrary units (a.u.)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Muscular collagen content</measure>
    <time_frame>3 time points (at 0,2, and 12 months)</time_frame>
    <description>Quantitative collagen signal derived by transcutaneous Multispectral Optoacoustic Tomography (MSOT) in patients with SMA with and without therapy and change over time Units: arbitrary units (a.u.)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Muscular hemo-/myoglobin content</measure>
    <time_frame>3 time points (at 0,2, and 12 months)</time_frame>
    <description>Quantitative hemo/myoglobin signal derived by transcutaneous Multispectral Optoacoustic Tomography (MSOT) in patients with SMA with and without therapy and change over time Units: arbitrary units (a.u.)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Muscular de-/oxygenated hemo-/myoglobin content</measure>
    <time_frame>3 time points (at 0,2, and 12 months)</time_frame>
    <description>Quantitative de-/oxygenated hemo-/myoglobin signal derived by transcutaneous Multispectral Optoacoustic Tomography (MSOT) in patients with SMA with and without therapy and change over time Units: arbitrary units (a.u.)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Ratio of lipid to hemo/myoglobin signal or collagen to hemo/myoglobin signal</measure>
    <time_frame>3 time points (at 0,2, and 12 months)</time_frame>
    <description>Ratio of quantitative lipid signal to hemo/myoglobin signal or collagen signal to hemo/myoglobin signal derived by transcutaneous Multispectral Optoacoustic Tomography (MSOT) in patients with SMA with and without therapy and change over time</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>T1 relaxation time</measure>
    <time_frame>3 time points (at 0,2, and 12 months)</time_frame>
    <description>T1 relaxation time determined by Magnetic Resonance Imaging (MRI) in patients with SMA with and without therapy and change over time</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>T2 relaxation time</measure>
    <time_frame>3 time points (at 0,2, and 12 months)</time_frame>
    <description>T2 relaxation time determined by Magnetic Resonance Imaging (MRI) in patients with SMA with and without therapy and change over time</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Fat-water percentage</measure>
    <time_frame>3 time points (at 0,2, and 12 months)</time_frame>
    <description>Fat-water percentage determined by Magnetic Resonance Imaging (MRI) in patients with SMA with and without therapy and change over time</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Sodium concentration</measure>
    <time_frame>3 time points (at 0,2, and 12 months)</time_frame>
    <description>Sodium concentration determined by Magnetic Resonance Imaging (MRI) in patients with SMA with and without therapy and change over time</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Correlation of MSOT data with therapy status</measure>
    <time_frame>3 time points (at 0,2, and 12 months)</time_frame>
    <description>Correlation of the quantitative lipid/collagen/hemo/myoglobin and de-/oxygenated hemo-/myoglobin content determined by MSOT in patients with and without therapy and evaluation of change over time</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Correlation of MSOT data with clinical data (age/disease duration)</measure>
    <time_frame>3 time points (at 0,2, and 12 months)</time_frame>
    <description>Correlation of lipid/collagen/haemo/myoglobin and de-/oxygenated hemo-/myoglobin content determined by MSOT with disease duration/patient age and evaluation of change over time</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Correlation of MSOT data with physical assessment (HFMSE/RULM/6-MWT)</measure>
    <time_frame>3 time points (at 0,2, and 12 months)</time_frame>
    <description>Correlation of lipid/collagen/haemo/myoglobin and de-/oxygenated hemo-/myoglobin content determined by MSOT with HFMSE/Revised Upper Limb Module/6-MWT and evaluation of change over time</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Correlation of MRI data with therapy status</measure>
    <time_frame>3 time points (at 0,2, and 12 months)</time_frame>
    <description>Correlation of T1 relaxation time/T2 relaxation time/fat water portion/sodium concentration in patients with and without therapy and evaluation of change over time</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Correlation of MRI data with clinical data (age/disease duration)</measure>
    <time_frame>3 time points (at 0,2, and 12 months)</time_frame>
    <description>Correlation of T1 relaxation time/T2 relaxation time/fat water portion/sodium concentration with disease duration and patient age and evaluation of change over time</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Correlation of MRI data with physical assessment (HFMSE/RULM/6-MWT)</measure>
    <time_frame>3 time points (at 0,2, and 12 months)</time_frame>
    <description>Correlation of T1 relaxation time/T2 relaxation time/fat water portion/sodium concentration with HFMSE/Revised Upper Limb Module/6-MWT and evaluation of change over time</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Correlation of MSOT data and MRI data</measure>
    <time_frame>3 time points (at 0,2, and 12 months)</time_frame>
    <description>Correlation of MSOT determined lipid/collagen/haemo/myoglobin and de-/oxygenated hemo-/myoglobin content and MRI derived T1 relaxation time/T2 relaxation time/fat water portion/sodium concentration and evaluation of change over time</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Side differences</measure>
    <time_frame>3 time points (at 0,2, and 12 months)</time_frame>
    <description>Measurement of the signal differences in right / left comparison derived by Multispectral Optoacoustic Tomography (MSOT) and Magnetic Resonance Imaging (MRI) and evaluation of change over time</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">10</enrollment>
  <condition>Muscular Diseases</condition>
  <condition>Spinal Muscular Atrophy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>SMA patients (therapy arm)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Multispectral Optoacoustic Tomography (MSOT) of muscles (left and right, total 4 sites) leg proximal: Musculus quadriceps, distal: Musculus triceps surae arm proximal: Musculus biceps, distal: forearm flexors;
Magnetic Resonance Imaging (MRI) of lower leg
Physical assessment/milestones: expanded Hammersmith functional motor scale (HFMSE)/ Revised Upper Limb Module (RULM)/ 6-minute-walking-test (6-MWT)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>SMA patients (control arm)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Multispectral Optoacoustic Tomography (MSOT) of muscles (left and right, total 4 sites) leg proximal: Musculus quadriceps, distal: Musculus triceps surae arm proximal: Musculus biceps, distal: forearm flexors;
Magnetic Resonance Imaging (MRI) of lower leg
Physical assessment/milestones: expanded Hammersmith functional motor scale (HFMSE)/ Revised Upper Limb Module (RULM)/ 6-minute-walking-test (6-MWT)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Multispectral Optoacoustic Tomography (MSOT) and Magnetic Resonance Imaging (MRI)</intervention_name>
    <description>Non-invasive transcutaneous imaging of molecular muscle components</description>
    <arm_group_label>SMA patients (control arm)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>SMA patients (therapy arm)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Genetically confirmed SMA type III

          -  From age 14

          -  Willingness and ability to participate, sufficient knowledge of the german language to
             understand the declaration of consent, or if not possible, information of the patient
             in his/her mother tongue or English

          -  High probability that the patients will be able to fully participate in the study
             (defined by the ability to lie still for about 1 hour and follow any breathing
             commands) For therapy arm: • Medical indication for Spinraza® therapy; start of study
             before first administration Spinraza® administration For control arm: • No medical
             indication for Spinraza® therapy

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Pregnancy

          -  Tattoo on the skin area to be examined

          -  General contraindications for MRT examinations

          -  Electrical implants like pacemakers or perfusion pumps

          -  Pronounced claustrophobia

          -  Study participants with ferromagnetic or electrically conductive implants such as
             aneurysm clips, surgical clips, prostheses, artificial hearts, heart valves with metal
             parts, metal splinters, tattoos next to the eye, symmetrical tattoos on the
             extremities or steel implants must consult the study physician; they may not be able
             to be examined (relative contraindications for MRI).

          -  Non-approved concomitant medication: strongly sedating medication must be excluded, as
             intensive monitoring of bodily functions during ongoing imaging cannot be guaranteed
             and the active participation of the test person might be necessary.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>14 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ferdinand Knieling, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University Hospital Erlangen, Department of Pediatric and Adolescent Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Matthias Türk, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University Hospital Erlangen, Department of Neurology</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Armin Nagel, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University Hospital Erlangen, Department of Radiology</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Alexandra Wagner, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+49 9131 85 33118</phone>
    <email>alexandra.l.wagner@uk-erlangen.de</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Ferdinand Knieling, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+49 9131 85 33118</phone>
    <email>ferdinand.knieling@uk-erlangen.de</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Hospital Erlangen</name>
      <address>
        <city>Erlangen</city>
        <zip>91054</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Alexandra Wagner, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+49 9131 8533118</phone>
      <email>alexandra.l.wagner@uk-erlangen.de</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Ferdinand Knieling, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+49 9131 8533118</phone>
      <email>ferdinand.knieling@uk-erlangen.de</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Germany</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 27, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 6, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 10, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 26, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 26, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 28, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Muscular Diseases</keyword>
  <keyword>Spinal Muscular Atrophy (SMA)</keyword>
  <keyword>Multispectral Optoacoustic Tomography (MSOT)</keyword>
  <keyword>Magnetic Resonance Imaging (MRI)</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Muscular Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Muscular Atrophy</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Muscular Atrophy, Spinal</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Atrophy</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Individual participant data that underlie the results reported in the primary publication, after deidentification (text, tables, figures, and appendices)</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Statistical Analysis Plan (SAP)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>Beginning 9 months and ending 36 months following article publication.</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>The data sets generated during and/or analyzed during the current study are available from the corresponding author on reasonable request as follows:
Individual participant data will not be available
Study Protocol and Statistical Analysis Plan will be available
The data will be available beginning 9 months and ending 36 months following article publication.
The data will be available to researchers who provide a methodologically sound proposal.
The data will be available for individual participant data meta-analysis, only.
Proposals may be submitted up to 36 months following article publication. After 36 months the data will be available in our University's data warehouse but without investigator support other than deposited metadata. Information regarding submitting proposals and accessing data may be found at https://www.uk-erlangen.de.
Restrictions may apply due to patient privacy and the General Data Protection Regulation.</ipd_access_criteria>
  </patient_data>
  <provided_document_section>
    <provided_document>
      <document_type>Study Protocol</document_type>
      <document_has_protocol>Yes</document_has_protocol>
      <document_has_icf>No</document_has_icf>
      <document_has_sap>No</document_has_sap>
      <document_date>February 21, 2020</document_date>
      <document_url>https://ClinicalTrials.gov/ProvidedDocs/70/NCT04262570/Prot_001.pdf</document_url>
    </provided_document>
  </provided_document_section>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

