<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04260919</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>FRP-01</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04260919</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Chest Physiotherapy in Bronchiolitis</brief_title>
  <official_title>Chest Physiotherapy in Light and Moderate Bronchiolitis in Ambulatory Children Under Two Years of Age - a Randomised Control Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Universidade do Porto</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Universidade do Porto</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Randomized trial of chest physiotherapy in outpatients with bronchiolitis under two years of
      age, during two consecutive seasonal outbreaks.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      A randomized controlled trial was conducted (following CONSORT Statement) in the Paediatric
      Emergency Department of Centro Hospitalar Universitário São João-Porto (CHUSJ), a tertiary
      care hospital, during the period from December to March in 2011 and 2012.

      Ethical approval was obtained from the Ethics Committee of Centro Hospitalar Universitário
      São João-Porto.

      Children up to 2 years of age, both genders, with a diagnosis of acute bronchiolitis based on
      clinical findings, including wheezing or wheezing with crackles, respiratory distress and
      alteration of feeding condition, were signalized by the physician who met them at the
      emergency room.

      Then, the main investigator of the study interviewed the caregivers and informed about the
      aims and procedures of the study, after a formal written consent in accordance with the
      Declaration of Helsinki was sign by all the caregivers.

      Severity grade was established with the Kristjansson Respiratory Score which variate from
      light to severe, being the light to moderate selected to study.

      Randomization in intervention or control group was made by the method of permuted-blocks. All
      children were assessed in a calm environment, while awake and not crying, and were submitted
      to a standard assessment protocol consisting of a clinical demographic data collection by
      interview of parents and the application of the Kristjansson Respiratory Score. All children
      underwent the same medical treatment protocol at the pediatric emergency department (PED),
      consisting in nebulization with medication, during the emergency room episode, and counselled
      in the subsequent one or two weeks and were followed during two weeks after discharge from
      PED, being reassessed at the end of the two weeks.

      Children from Intervention Group (IG) underwent a standard intervention chest physiotherapy
      protocol performed by a physiotherapist, consisting on the techniques: prolonged slow
      expiration (PSE), rhinopharyngeal retrograde clearance (RRC) and provoked cough (PC).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">December 2010</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 2012</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 2011</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Randomized trial with two groups.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
    <masking_description>One control group and one intervention group, where chest physiotherapy is used.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Reduction of Kristjansson Respiratory Score</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline; after two weeks of treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Verified by changes in the Kristjansson Respiratory Score, which is a practical and simple score, that assesses the main signs and symptoms of bronchiolitis, having a good validity and inter-observer reliability.It assigns a value between 0 and 2 to each of the five variables: respiratory rate, chest recession, breath sound, skin colour and general condition. A higher Kristjansson respiratory score indicate a worse respiratory condition.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">45</enrollment>
  <condition>Bronchiolitis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>The participants just received standard medical treatment</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The participants received medical treatment and chest physiotherapy sessions</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Chest physiotherapy</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Children up to 2 years of age, both genders, with a diagnosis of acute bronchiolitis

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  presence of comorbidities, such as cystic fibrosis, neuromuscular, congenital heart
             disease, prematurity or respiratory distress and all the cases that were admitted into
             the hospital
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>24 Months</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <link>
    <url>https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC3433974/</url>
    <description>Related Info</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/23287014</url>
    <description>Related Info</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>February 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 6, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 6, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 7, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 6, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 6, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 11, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Universidade do Porto</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Frederico Ramos Pinto</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>bronchiolitis</keyword>
  <keyword>chest physiotherapy</keyword>
  <keyword>children</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Bronchiolitis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

