<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04269018</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>24</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04269018</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Effect of Mobile Text Message on Behavioral Risks of Cancer: A Randomized Controlled Trial</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Effect of Mobile Text Message on Behavioral Risks of Cancer Among College Students, Northeast Ethiopia: A Randomized Controlled Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Wollo University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Wollo University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Summary Background: Cancer is a public health problem in Ethiopia. A third of cancer deaths
      are preventable. Its effects can be significantly reduced if effective interventions are put
      in place to control risk factors. Text-messaging has been currently targeted as a simple tool
      for providing people with health information. Thus this study aimed to measure the
      effectiveness of text message in behavioral risk factors that is helpful to raise cancer
      awareness and promote cancer prevention and control in this country.

      Methods: A randomized control trial will be used to measure the effectiveness of mobile text
      message in behavioral risk factor of cancer among Governmental Collage students in Dessie
      City and utilize quantitative method of data collection. Data will be collected on a total of
      80 intervention and 80 controls using structured questionnaire. Socio-demographic, health
      belief variables and behavioral risk factor of cancer will be collected before and after
      intervention. Text message will be provided based on health belief model. Data will be
      entered using Epidata version 3.1 and will be exported to STATA version 13.0 for cleaning and
      analysis. Liner regression will be applied to identify predictors of behavioral risk factor
      of cancer. Student's paired samples t-test will be used to test changes in terms of HBM
      variables and behavioural outcomes. Analysis of Covariance will be used to test over group
      comparison.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The study will be a single blind randomized controlled trial, which utilize quantitative
      method of data collection. College students who will receive a mobile text message about the
      behavioral risks of cancer and prevention mechanism will be considered as intervention groups
      while controls will be those who receive a text message related with general health once a
      week. A total of 160 (80 interventions and 80 controls) students will be included in the
      study using simple random sampling technique. After the baseline assessment, participants
      will be randomized to either usual care (control) or the text message intervention group in a
      uniform 1:1 (control: intervention) allocation ratio, using computer-based randomization
      service.

      Self-administered questionnaire will be used to assess baseline and end line data of
      behavioral risk factors and other variables. Participants in the control group will receive
      an initial text message welcoming them to the study, but they will not receive the text
      message support program. The intervention group will receive a text message support program,
      where they will receive seven messages per week at random times and days for two months. The
      text message will be prepared and delivered based on health belief model (HBM), the items of
      this subscale will be measured on a Likert scale ranging from 1= &quot;Strongly disagree&quot; to 5 =
      &quot;Strongly agree&quot;. Tobacco use, harmful use of alcohol, unhealthy diet and physical inactivity
      with a series of items will be used to measure the behavioral outcomes the items in this
      subscale will be measured on a Likert scale.

      Validity of the items will be measured by an expert panel of specialists in health education
      and nutrition. They will judge about the necessity and relevance of the scale items. To
      control the data quality all data collectors will be trained for two days. Supervisors will
      monitor data collection process and the principal investigator will visit frequently. The
      questionnaire will be first prepared in English language and translated to Amharic and again
      re-translated in to English by another person to check for consistency. About 10% of the
      questionnaire will be pretested and internal consistency will be checked. Completeness of the
      collected data will be checked during data collection.

      The data will be checked for completeness and consistency, then categorized, coded and
      entered using Epidata version 3.1 to minimize error. Then, the clean data will be exported to
      Stata version 14 for analysis. Normality of the data will be checked through
      Kolmogorov-Smirnov test. Student's paired samples t-test will be used to test within-group
      changes in terms of health belief model (HBM) variables and behavioral outcomes. The analysis
      of Covariance will be used to make over-group comparisons. Data will be reported as mean ±
      standard deviation. The significance level for all of the results will be presented at the
      P&lt;0.05 level.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">March 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 15, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 30, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Participants will be randomly assigned to intervention and control group, the intervention group will be received daily text message while the controls will receive general health messages once a week.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
    <masking_description>To maintain blinding, randomization will occur after the baseline assessment and both groups will receive welcome message for participating in the study. Then motivational and general healthy related texts will be delivered to controls one times per week.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Physical activity level</measure>
    <time_frame>on average 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>For measuring physical activity International Physical Activity Questionnaires (IPAQ) will be used. The questions will ask the time study participants spent being physically active in the last 7 days. Then, it will be summarized as Metabolic Equivalents (METs).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Health dietary score</measure>
    <time_frame>on average 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Healthy diet score will be assessed the health diet score adapted from the WHO list of healthy diet foods, which is a Likert scale ranged from 1 to 6.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Tobacco use</measure>
    <time_frame>on average 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Tobacco smoking will be assessed using a series of questions adopted from the World Health Organization (WHO), which used to assess the duration, quantity and frequency of smoking within one month.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Alcohol intake</measure>
    <time_frame>on average 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Alcohol consumption will be assessed using a tool adopted from National Institute on Alcohol Abuse and Alcoholism (NIAAA), which used to assess participants consumption in the past 1 month.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Risk perception</measure>
    <time_frame>on average 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Risk perception will be measured using health belief model variables: perceived susceptibility towards cancer, perceived severity of cancer, perceived benefits of adopting behaviors, perceived barriers to adopting behaviors, perceived self-efficacy for adopting dietary behaviors and internal cues for adopting dietary behaviors, the items of this subscale will be measured on a Likert scale ranging from 1= &quot;Strongly disagree&quot; to 5 = &quot;Strongly agree&quot;.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">160</enrollment>
  <condition>Behavioral Risks of Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cancer specific Mobile text message</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>This arm will receive daily mobile text message related with cancer risks and prevention</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>general health messages</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>This arm will receive general health message once a week</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cancer specific Mobile text message</intervention_name>
    <description>The intervention is cancer specific lifestyle mobile text messages daily for 2 months</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cancer specific Mobile text message</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>General health messages</intervention_name>
    <description>Daily text related with general health message</description>
    <arm_group_label>general health messages</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  College students aged 18 to 35

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Mental and physical disability, those who already have diagnosed cancer
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>35 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Foziya Hussien, MPH</last_name>
    <phone>+251913714985</phone>
    <email>foziyamohammed2018@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <verification_date>February 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 9, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 11, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 13, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 19, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 19, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 21, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Wollo University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Foziya Mohammed Hussien</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>lecturer</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

