<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04263168</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>6397-19-SMC</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04263168</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Glycemic Index Variations In the Early Period Following Bariatric Surgery</brief_title>
  <official_title>Glycemic Index Variations In the Early Period Following Bariatric Surgery</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Sheba Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Weizmann Institute of Science</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Sheba Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The diverse community of gut microbes commonly referred to as the 'gut microbiome', is
      increasingly suggested to play significant roles in health and disease, and to affect even
      distant non-GI organs by metabolite signaling. Type 2 diabetes mellitus (T2DM) patients
      feature a distinct gut microbiome signature4, while modulating the gut microbiome by either
      antibiotics or fecal microbial transplantation (FMT) is suggested to impact insulin
      sensitivity. Originally designed to treat obesity, bariatric surgeries often induce a robust
      and rapid weight-independent improvement in glucose homeostasis within days. Early diabetes
      remission following bariatric surgery is hypothesized to be mediated by rapid alterations in
      the gut microbiome and bile acids composition, however, the exact mechanism is yet to be
      uncovered. Elucidating this mechanism is important as it may form the basis of a new
      therapeutic modality in diabetes. The investigators intend to deeply characterize early
      post-bariatric changes in the gut microbiome of diabetic patients, as well as their gut
      mucosal transcriptome and metabolome, by using state-of-the-art experimental and
      computational pipelines. Additionally, The investigators will utilize a unique mouse model of
      bariatric surgery under germ-free conditions, developed at the Elinav lab, that allows us to
      dissect the role of microbes in post-operative metabolic improvements.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Type 2 diabetes mellitus (T2DM) is one of the most prevalent and deadly conditions in the
      21st century. T2DM is characterized by obesity and insulin resistance that leads to chronic
      hyperglycemia, which even with best medical care is often uncontrolled, resulting in
      life-threatening micro- and macrovascular complications.

      The gut microbiota (i.e. the microbial population inhabiting the gut) has been extensively
      linked to blood glucose levels and was shown to mediate insulin response in various settings,
      including anti-diabetic pharmacotherapy. Moreover, fecal microbial transplantation (FMT) from
      lean healthy donors improved insulin resistance in humans suffering from metabolic syndrome.
      These pre-clinical and clinical evidence suggest that the gut microbiota has a mechanistic
      role in insulin-resistance.

      Bariatric surgeries were originally designed to treat obesity but were also retrospectively
      found to ameliorate T2DM among other metabolic and non-metabolic disorders. Since obesity is
      a significant risk factor for T2DM, it is not surprising that surgically-induced weight loss
      which occurs within several months after surgery also improves insulin sensitivity. However,
      a substantial share of patients experience an improvement in insulin resistance within days
      after bariatric surgery, which clinically presents as normal glycemic values despite
      decreased dosage of anti-diabetic medications in the first post-operative days. This
      phenomenon of early diabetes remission after surgery precedes any weight-loss, therefore it
      is weight-independent and it is far from being understood.

      Several explanations were suggested to explain early post-bariatric surgery diabetes
      remission, among which are acute caloric restriction, amplified incretins response, and rapid
      alterations in bile acids composition; however, none of them accounts for such a drastic
      improvement in glycemic control within such a short time frame.

      Bariatric surgery rapidly alters the gut microbiome in a conserved fashion in both humans and
      rodents. Although descriptive studies demonstrated a change in microbiome composition within
      a few months after surgery, most studies didn't analyze microbiome in the first
      post-operative weeks in which the improvement in diabetes takes place, and data so far
      remains associative at best. Two independent studies exhibited improved metabolism following
      FMT from post-bariatric surgery humans and mice donors

      into germ-free (microbiota-devoid) mice recipients, however, no mechanism was suggested and
      both studies used stool samples taken at a very late postoperative period, therefore no
      conclusions could be made regarding early diabetic remission. Caloric restriction, incretins,
      bile-acids, and the gut microbiome most probably &quot;co-evolve&quot; following surgery to exert
      surgery's beneficial metabolic effect with no single factor solely responsible for the entire
      effect.

      Despite being highly effective in ameliorating obesity and obesity-related co-morbidities in
      the short-term, bariatric surgeries are invasive, risky, and not always successful in the
      long-term. Bariatric surgeries are thus far from being a perfect solution to obese diabetic
      patients, but they do serve as an intriguing investigational-model in the context of glucose
      metabolism. Hopefully, probing the mechanisms behind surgery's metabolic effect will
      facilitate the development of safer treatments for diabetic patients.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">March 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 1, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 1, 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Bariatric surgery candidates for two types of bariatric surgery, i.e. sleeve gastrectomy (n=80) and Roux-en-Y gastric bypass (RYGB, n=80) will be recruited to the study from the bariatric surgery clinic in the Sheba medical center and will be followed pre- and postoperatively. A control group of candidates for another non-bariatric upper-GI surgery, i.e. cholecystectomy (n=80), will be recruited as well. All participants will undergo medical and metabolic profiling before surgery at baseline, and during the first two weeks following surgery. Metabolic profiling will take place during a run-in session in the Sheba medical center, that will include (A) A detailed briefing on study design, goals, samples collection and OGTT, as well as home sample-collecting kit distribution (B) Installation of a continuous glucose monitoring system (CGM, Abbott 'freeStyle Libre').</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in intestinal microbiota composition prior and following bariatric surgery</measure>
    <time_frame>two weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Changes in intestinal microbiota composition following bariatric surgery measured with RNA sequencing</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in glycemic index prior and following bariatric surgery</measure>
    <time_frame>two weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Changes in glycemic index prior and following bariatric surgery measured with continues glucose monitoring system (FreeStyle Libre)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">160</enrollment>
  <condition>Diabetes Mellitus</condition>
  <condition>Bariatric Surgery Candidate</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Bariatric Surgery Candidates</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>All participants will undergo medical and metabolic profiling before surgery at baseline, and during the first two weeks following surgery. Metabolic profiling will take place during a run-in session in the Sheba medical center, that will include (A) A detailed briefing on study design, goals, samples collection and OGTT, as well as home sample-collecting kit distribution (B) Installation of a continuous glucose monitoring system (CGM, Abbott 'freeStyle Libre').</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Laparoscopy Cholecystectomy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Sham Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>All participants will undergo medical and metabolic profiling before surgery at baseline, and during the first two weeks following surgery. Metabolic profiling will take place during a run-in session in the Sheba medical center, that will include (A) A detailed briefing on study design, goals, samples collection and OGTT, as well as home sample-collecting kit distribution (B) Installation of a continuous glucose monitoring system (CGM, Abbott 'freeStyle Libre').</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Continuous Glucose monitoring in the perioperative period</intervention_name>
    <description>All participants will undergo medical and metabolic profiling before surgery at baseline, and during the first two weeks following surgery. Metabolic profiling will take place during a run-in session in the Sheba medical center, that will include (A) A detailed briefing on study design, goals, samples collection and OGTT, as well as home sample-collecting kit distribution (B) Installation of a continuous glucose monitoring system (CGM, Abbott 'freeStyle Libre').</description>
    <arm_group_label>Bariatric Surgery Candidates</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Laparoscopy Cholecystectomy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Adult Population (&gt; 18 years old)

          -  Diabetic Patients (Type 2)

          -  Bariatric surgery candidates for two types of bariatric surgery, i.e. sleeve
             gastrectomy and Roux-en-Y gastric bypass

          -  Laparoscopic Cholecystectomy candidates

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Pregnant Women

          -  &lt; 18 years old
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>99 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Nir Horesh, MD</last_name>
    <phone>0507316266</phone>
    <email>horesh.nir@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sheba Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ramat Gan</city>
        <state>Tel Aviv (Gosh Dan)</state>
        <zip>52561</zip>
        <country>Israel</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Nir Horesh, MD</last_name>
      <phone>0507316266</phone>
      <email>Horesh.nir@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>David Goiten, MD</last_name>
      <email>david.goiten@sheba.health.gov.il</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Israel</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 19, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 7, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 10, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 7, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 7, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 10, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Sheba Medical Center</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Dr. Nir Horesh resident Department of Surgery and Transplant</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

