<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04265326</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2018-146</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04265326</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Validity and Reliability of the Turkish Version of the Head and Neck Cancer Inventory</brief_title>
  <official_title>Validity and Reliability of the Turkish Version of the Head and Neck Cancer Inventory</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Izmir Bakircay University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Gazi University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Izmir Bakircay University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The primary treatment option of many patients with head and neck cancer is surgery,
      radiotherapy and chemotherapy. In the literature, functional problems that occur after
      surgical interventions applied to head and neck cancer patients are frequently mentioned.
      Morbidities resulting from the combined application of radiotherapy and chemotherapy are
      based on more anecdotal information and critical data on long-term functional outcomes in
      this patient group are scarce. The aim of this study is to make the validity, reliability and
      cultural adaptation of the Head and Neck Cancer Inventory in Turkish.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      In the literature, there are general cancer scales developed to evaluate the quality of life
      of head and neck cancer patients and sub scales associated with head and neck cancers
      developed in addition to these scales. In addition, scales specific to head and neck cancers
      have also been developed. However, previous research shows that even general health status
      scales or cancer-specific scales cannot determine outcomes related to many head and neck
      cancer patients. In addition, items containing multiple functions and patients' attitudes
      (behaviors) cannot be analyzed separately in any of the scales specific to head and neck
      cancer. Very few surveys contain items related to patients' attitudes (behaviors), or the
      number of items related to this topic is small because most of these scales are functional
      items. Unlike its counterparts in the literature, Head and Neck Cancer Inventory evaluates
      the attitudes (behaviors) of patients associated with various functions in daily life. Head
      and Neck Cancer Inventory is the only scale in the literature that contains the basic
      features of the health conditions declared by the patient and has been developed specifically
      for head and neck cancer.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 13, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Other</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Head and Neck Cancer Inventory</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline</time_frame>
    <description>It is a scale consisting of 30 items in total, containing 4 main categories [speech (10 items), eating (10 items), aesthetics (2 items), social disorders (7 items)] evaluating the quality of life related to head and neck cancer and an additional item evaluating the overall quality of life. This inventory reflects both functionality (how functional the patient is) and attitudes (how satisfied is the patient's functional level) using a 5-point Likert-type scale. This scale does not have a summary score representing all items, the score of 4 different categories can be calculated. The higher the scores, the better the quality of life [2].</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The Functional Assessment of Cancer Therapy - Head and Neck Cancer Version 4</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline</time_frame>
    <description>In addition to the 27-item Cancer Treatment Functional Evaluation-General (FACT-G) scale, this scale consists of 9 additional items specific to head and neck cancer. FACT G consists of 4 main categories that evaluate physical (7 items), social (7 items), emotional (6 items) and functional status (7 items). Each item is scored by patients with a Likert type classification ranging from 0 (none) to 4 (too many). Points are calculated separately for each category. A summary score is also calculated for FACT-G and total FACT-H &amp; N [3]. The questionnaire is available in Turkish version [9].</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">165</enrollment>
  <condition>Quality of Life</condition>
  <condition>Head and Neck Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Head and Neck Cancer patients</arm_group_label>
    <description>Turkish patients diagnosed with Head and Neck Cancer</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Measurement of Quality of Life</intervention_name>
    <description>Quality of life will be measured using Head and Neck Cancer Inventory and The Functional Assessment of Cancer Therapy - Head and Neck Cancer Version 4</description>
    <arm_group_label>Head and Neck Cancer patients</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Turkish patients diagnosed with head and neck patients
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Voluntarily accepting to participate in the study

          -  Patients whose native language is Turkish

          -  Patients diagnosed with head and neck cancer

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients whose health conditions are too bad to fill the scale

          -  Having a serious mental disorder or dementia
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Kadirhan Ozdemir, PhD.</last_name>
    <phone>+905069439059</phone>
    <email>kadirhanozdemir@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Kadirhan Ozdemir</name>
      <address>
        <city>İzmir</city>
        <zip>06580</zip>
        <country>Turkey</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Kadirhan Ozdemir</last_name>
      <phone>05069439059</phone>
      <email>kadirhanozdemir@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Turkey</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cohen EE, LaMonte SJ, Erb NL, Beckman KL, Sadeghi N, Hutcheson KA, Stubblefield MD, Abbott DM, Fisher PS, Stein KD, Lyman GH, Pratt-Chapman ML. American Cancer Society Head and Neck Cancer Survivorship Care Guideline. CA Cancer J Clin. 2016 May;66(3):203-39. doi: 10.3322/caac.21343. Epub 2016 Mar 22. Review. Erratum in: CA Cancer J Clin. 2016 Jul;66(4):351.</citation>
    <PMID>27002678</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Funk GF, Karnell LH, Christensen AJ, Moran PJ, Ricks J. Comprehensive head and neck oncology health status assessment. Head Neck. 2003 Jul;25(7):561-75.</citation>
    <PMID>12808660</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Heutte N, Plisson L, Lange M, Prevost V, Babin E. Quality of life tools in head and neck oncology. Eur Ann Otorhinolaryngol Head Neck Dis. 2014 Feb;131(1):33-47. doi: 10.1016/j.anorl.2013.05.002. Epub 2013 Nov 28. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24291153</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gliklich RE, Goldsmith TA, Funk GF. Are head and neck specific quality of life measures necessary? Head Neck. 1997 Sep;19(6):474-80.</citation>
    <PMID>9278754</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>D'Antonio LL, Zimmerman GJ, Cella DF, Long SA. Quality of life and functional status measures in patients with head and neck cancer. Arch Otolaryngol Head Neck Surg. 1996 May;122(5):482-7.</citation>
    <PMID>8615964</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>List MA, D'Antonio LL, Cella DF, Siston A, Mumby P, Haraf D, Vokes E. The Performance Status Scale for Head and Neck Cancer Patients and the Functional Assessment of Cancer Therapy-Head and Neck Scale. A study of utility and validity. Cancer. 1996 Jun 1;77(11):2294-301.</citation>
    <PMID>8635098</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Webster K, Cella D, Yost K. The Functional Assessment of Chronic Illness Therapy (FACIT) Measurement System: properties, applications, and interpretation. Health Qual Life Outcomes. 2003 Dec 16;1:79. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>14678568</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 8, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 8, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 11, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 8, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 8, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 9, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Izmir Bakircay University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Kadirhan Ozdemir, PT, PhD.</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Head of Geriatric Rehabilitation Department</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Head and Neck Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

