<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04268446</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>turkishbriefBESTest</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04268446</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Turkish Version of the Brief-BESTest Scale</brief_title>
  <official_title>Investigation of the Turkish Version, Validity and Reliability of Brief-BESTest Scale in Stroke Patients</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Kırıkkale University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Kırıkkale University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The aim of this study is to investigate the validity and reliability of the Turkish version
      of the brief-BESTest (short BESTest) scale in stroke patients.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Brief Balance Evaluation Systems Test (Brief-BESTest) is a short version of the Balance
      evaluation systems test (BESTest). Balance assessment systems test (BESTest) The balance
      assessment systems test developed by Horak consists of 6 sub-sections that evaluate the
      systems related to balance; 1) biomechanical limitations, 2) stability limit, 3) postural
      responses, 4) intuitive postural adjustments, 5) sensory orientation and 6) walking. It
      consists of 36 tests in total. Each question is rated between 0-3. The highest score that can
      be obtained is 108. Low test scores show that the balance is disturbed. BESTest has been
      found to be reliable among raters evaluating a cohort of individuals with and without various
      neurological diagnoses. In studies conducted, it was stated that BESTest is reliable when
      compared to other scales evaluating balance.

      The necessary permissions have been obtained from the authors for Short BESTest, whose
      validity and reliability features will be tested, and the translation process to Turkish has
      been completed and the survey has been finalized. The basis for the use of special tools such
      as the scale is to prove the usability of the tool in the sample group to which it will be
      applied. The first step for this is the translation stage from the original language to the
      other language.

      At the stage of translation into Turkish, two experts who knew a good level of English
      translated the questionnaire from English into Turkish. These translations have been
      translated back into Turkish by two native speakers of English and distant medical subjects.
      In addition, these translations were re-examined by the researchers and turned into a single
      form. This form was sent to five specialists in the field, checking the content and
      compliance with Turkish was evaluated. With the opinion of experts, the scale was finalized.

      The study will include individuals over 40 years of age who have been diagnosed with an
      ischemic or hemorhagic stroke, who applied to the Kırıkkale University Faculty of Medicine
      Physical Therapy and Rehabilitation Hospital.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 29, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 31, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Other</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Cross-Sectional</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Berg Balance Test</measure>
    <time_frame>15 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>It is a 14-item scale that evaluates the tasks used in daily life activities.Standing up without support, standing without support, sitting without support, standing up, transfers, standing with feet, standing with legs while standing, reaching out while standing, picking up from the ground, looking back, 360 degree rotation, firm side standing on the stool, one foot standstill and standstill functions are evaluated.Each item is planned between 0-4; 0 is unable to fulfill the task, 4 is to fulfill the task successfully. The total score of the test is between 0-56.0-20 points: wheelchair dependent, 21-40: assisted walking, 41-56: means independent ambulation.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Functional Reach Test</measure>
    <time_frame>5 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>Subjects will asked to stand comfortably, to make a fist, and to raise their arm until it was parallel to the yardstick (position 1). The placement of the end of the third metacarpal along the yardstick will recorded. Subjects will then asked to reach as far forward as they could without losing their balance (position 2), and the position of the end of the third metacarpal along the yardstick will again recorded. No attempt will make to control the subject's method of reach, but if he will touch the wall or took a step during the maneuver, that trial will consider invalid and repeated.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Time Up and Go Test</measure>
    <time_frame>5 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>This test is applied to assess the risk of falling and mobility.This test starts with the individual leaving the chair without receiving arm support by giving the go command while sitting in a chair.The distance of 3 meters is asked to return and sit again in the chair.The elapsed time is recorded in seconds.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>10 Meter Walk Tests</measure>
    <time_frame>3 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>Walking speed are measure by timing subjects over 10 meters with a stopwatch. To avoid the effects of acceleration and deceleration, measurements take over the middle 10 meters of a 14-meter walkway. It is repeated 2 times.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Falls Efficacy Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>5 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>FES is a 10-item scale and these items are; To enter and get out of bed, to sit and stand on the chair, to take a bath or shower, to dress and undress, to lie on the shelves, to walk in the house, to answer the door or phone, to prepare food without lifting heavy objects and to do simple shopping. Individuals score between 0 (not safe) and 10 (very safe) for each question, and when all scores are summed, a total score between 0 and 100 is obtained.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Stroke Patients</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients who are able to walk 10 m independently with or without a device over 40 years old
        with a diagnosis of stroke.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Being 40 years old or older,

          -  Diagnosis of stroke,

          -  No cooperation and communication problems

          -  To be able to walk 10 m independently with or without an auxiliary device

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Another neurological or orthopedic problem other than stroke that will affect
             functionality and balance

          -  Individuals with advanced contraindications for cardiovascular disease and
             mobilization will not be included in the study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>40 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Saniye Aydoğan Arslan</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Kırıkkale University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Kübra Uğurlu</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Kırıkkale University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Cevher Demirci</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Balikesir University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Zekiye İpek Katırcı Kırmacı</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Sanko University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Saniye Aydoğan Arslan</last_name>
    <phone>+905053333457</phone>
    <email>fztsaniye1982@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Kübra Uğurlu</last_name>
    <phone>+0905077295353</phone>
    <email>kubraozdamar@hotmail.com.tr</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Kırıkkale University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kırıkkale</city>
        <zip>71000</zip>
        <country>Turkey</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Saniye Aydoğan Arslan</last_name>
      <phone>+905053333457</phone>
      <email>fztsaniye1982@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Kübra Uğurlu</last_name>
      <phone>+905077295353</phone>
      <email>kubraozdamar@hotmail.com.tr</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Turkey</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Padgett PK, Jacobs JV, Kasser SL. Is the BESTest at its best? A suggested brief version based on interrater reliability, validity, internal consistency, and theoretical construct. Phys Ther. 2012 Sep;92(9):1197-207. doi: 10.2522/ptj.20120056. Epub 2012 Jun 7.</citation>
    <PMID>22677295</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Smith PS, Hembree JA, Thompson ME. Berg Balance Scale and Functional Reach: determining the best clinical tool for individuals post acute stroke. Clin Rehabil. 2004 Nov;18(7):811-8.</citation>
    <PMID>15573838</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schmidt S, Bullinger M. Current issues in cross-cultural quality of life instrument development. Arch Phys Med Rehabil. 2003 Apr;84(4 Suppl 2):S29-34. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>12692769</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chinsongkram B, Chaikeeree N, Saengsirisuwan V, Viriyatharakij N, Horak FB, Boonsinsukh R. Reliability and validity of the Balance Evaluation Systems Test (BESTest) in people with subacute stroke. Phys Ther. 2014 Nov;94(11):1632-43. doi: 10.2522/ptj.20130558. Epub 2014 Jun 12.</citation>
    <PMID>24925073</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bergström M, Lenholm E, Franzén E. Translation and validation of the Swedish version of the mini-BESTest in subjects with Parkinson's disease or stroke: a pilot study. Physiother Theory Pract. 2012 Oct;28(7):509-14. doi: 10.3109/09593985.2011.653707. Epub 2012 Jan 30.</citation>
    <PMID>22288658</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>O'Hoski S, Sibley KM, Brooks D, Beauchamp MK. Construct validity of the BESTest, mini-BESTest and briefBESTest in adults aged 50 years and older. Gait Posture. 2015 Sep;42(3):301-5. doi: 10.1016/j.gaitpost.2015.06.006. Epub 2015 Jun 25.</citation>
    <PMID>26183191</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Franchignoni F, Horak F, Godi M, Nardone A, Giordano A. Using psychometric techniques to improve the Balance Evaluation Systems Test: the mini-BESTest. J Rehabil Med. 2010 Apr;42(4):323-31. doi: 10.2340/16501977-0537.</citation>
    <PMID>20461334</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Horak FB, Wrisley DM, Frank J. The Balance Evaluation Systems Test (BESTest) to differentiate balance deficits. Phys Ther. 2009 May;89(5):484-98. doi: 10.2522/ptj.20080071. Epub 2009 Mar 27.</citation>
    <PMID>19329772</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 11, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 11, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 13, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 11, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 11, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 13, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Kırıkkale University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Kübra Uğurlu</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Research Assistant</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>brief BESTest</keyword>
  <keyword>stroke patients</keyword>
  <keyword>Turkish version</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Stroke</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

