<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04265053</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2020-0336</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>A176000</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>EDUC/KINESIOLOGY/KINESIOLOG</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04265053</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Human Cerebral Blood Flow Regulation</brief_title>
  <acronym>Gas Challenge</acronym>
  <official_title>Human Cerebral Blood Flow Regulation: Sex, Mechanism, and Stress Differences</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Wisconsin, Madison</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Wisconsin, Madison</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study tests basic differences in how men and women control brain (cerebral) blood flow
      (CBF), at rest and under stress. The stress is low oxygen or high carbon dioxide. The
      investigators hypothesize that sex differences per se, plus sex hormone differences, drive
      different signals in blood vessels that change the way CBF is regulated. The investigators
      will test these mechanisms with medicine infusions during stress, and measure CBF using
      state-of-the-art MRI approaches. Research confounding variables like aging and disease will
      be mitigated by comparing younger adults (18-40 years old).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Cerebrovascular disease is the third leading killer in the U.S., and contributes to decreased
      quality of life and increased long-term care spending. The risk of cerebrovascular disease is
      inversely associated with resting cerebral blood flow (CBF). Men exhibit a lower resting CBF
      and have twice the risk of cerebrovascular disease when compared to premenopausal women. The
      ability of cerebral vessels to respond to challenges is also inversely related to disease
      risk, and may be useful in identifying at-risk patients pre-clinically. However, these
      studies are often confounded by aging and/or comorbidities, and the associations provide
      little insight into physiologic mechanisms responsible for sexually dimorphic cerebrovascular
      disease risk. Conversely, animal studies use supraphysiologic levels of hormone treatment in
      primarily young animals, which limits the translational relevance of animal CBF mechanisms.
      While there is general agreement that estrogen is protective in healthy adults, the basic
      impact of sex, and physiologic fluctuations in sex hormones, on mechanisms of CBF control
      remains unclear.

      The overall goal of this research program is to investigate the mechanisms which actively
      control cerebral blood flow (CBF) in humans, particularly how men and women differ in control
      mechanisms on a regional basis throughout the brain circulation. The investigators propose to
      study CBF control mechanisms in healthy younger (18-40 yrs) adult men and women. The overall
      hypothesis is that female sex and sex hormones contribute to larger stress-induced increases
      in CBF, due to greater prostanoid (COX) and nitric oxide (NOS) dilation.

      A key technological innovation of this proposal derives from multi-mode, high-resolution,
      flow sensitive MRI to quantify CBF at macro- and microvascular levels, at rest, and in
      response to environmental challenges. Additionally, the research design allows the
      quantification of sex differences in two vascular control mechanisms across all brain
      regions. Preliminary data demonstrate: hypoxic cerebral vasodilation is 60-100% higher in
      women compared to men, COX inhibition reduces dilation in women but not men, NOS inhibition
      reduces vasodilation more in women, and hypoxic vasodilation is increased in women during
      early luteal cycle, in part to greater COX-mediated vasodilation. Sex hormone suppression,
      followed by single hormone addition, will be used to systematically study the impacts on CBF
      control in both sexes.

      Substantial preliminary findings support these hypotheses, and integrated physiologic,
      pharmacologic, and MRI approaches are available to test them. This state-of-the-art approach
      will yield previously unattainable insight into not only maintaining CBF, but actively
      controlling it during physiologic demands for increased flow. These novel, high resolution,
      regionally-specific, sex-specific, and mechanism-specific findings will serve as a knowledge
      platform, for designing sex-specific CBF studies in high risk disease populations (e.g.
      diabetes, hypertension, Alzheimer's) which exhibit strong sex-specific etiology and important
      vascular contributions.

      Three Specific Aims will be addressed in this study:

      Aim 1: Test the hypothesis that healthy males exhibit reduced cerebral vasodilation compared
      to healthy females despite exhibiting similar vasodilation to hypercapnia.

        -  Aim 1A: Vasodilation to hypoxia will be markedly lower in males, more so in anterior
           brain regions.

        -  Aim 1B: Vasodilation to hypercapnia will be similar between sexes.

      Aim 2: Test the hypothesis that acute inhibition of COX or NOS will reduce sex differences in
      hypoxia-mediated cerebral vasodilation.

        -  Aim 2A: COX-mediates vasodilation primarily in females.

        -  Aim 2B: NOS mediates vasodilation more in females than males.

      Aim 3: Test the hypothesis that manipulating sex steroids can abolish or magnify sex
      differences in vasodilation.

        -  Aim 3A: Short-term suppression of sex steroids will abolish sex differences in resting
           and hypoxic CBF via greater losses of COX- and NOS-mediated vasodilation in females than
           males.

        -  Aim 3B: Short-term supplementation of unopposed testosterone in males will magnify sex
           differences by driving COX vasoconstriction (TXA2) and uncoupled NOS vasoconstriction.

        -  Aim 3C: Short-term supplementation of unopposed estradiol in females will magnify sex
           differences via increased NOS and COX vasodilation.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">August 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2026</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2025</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Early Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Aims 1-2: Both male (n=48) and female (n=48) groups. Participants complete both aims in 2 visits. Participants assigned to one of 2 drug treatments in Aim 2 (n=24/sex/drug). These drugs are mechanistic studies, not treatment studies. Drugs inhibit NOS or COX signaling in blood vessels and are given intravenously during one MRI visit.
Aim 3: Both male (n=20) and female (n=20) groups (a subset of participants enrolled in Aims 1-2) enroll for ~14 days. All 14 days participants suppress endogenous sex hormones with a GnRH agonist/antagonist, and repeat Aim 1-2 visits around days 5-7. Subsequently, males start taking exogenous testosterone, and females take exogenous estrogen for the remaining 7-9 days. On days 12-14 (depending on MRI and participant schedule), participants repeat visits like Aim 1-2. During half those MRI visits, participants will receive one of the two FDA drugs (same as in original Aim 1-2 visit).</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Cerebrovascular Conductance (CVC) in response to Hypoxia</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 75 minutes for entire visit, but hypoxia lasts about 20 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>CVC is the ratio between Cerebral Blood Flow (CBF) and blood pressure (BP). Change in CVC in response to hypoxia between male and female groups, where baseline CVC is subtracted from hypoxia CVC. Hypoxia typically lasts about 20 minutes. The hypothesis is that women will exhibit 50-60% more vasodilation in response to hypoxia [Aim 1].</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>CVC in response to Hypercapnia</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 75 minutes for entire visit, but hypercapnia lasts about 10-15 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>CVC is the ratio between Cerebral Blood Flow (CBF) and blood pressure (BP). Change in CVC in response to hypercapnia between male and female groups, where CBF is normalized for BP. Baseline CVC will be subtracted from hypercapnia CVC. Hypercapnia typically lasts about 10-15 minutes.The hypothesis is that hypercapnic vasodilation will be similar between groups [Aim 1B].</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>CVC change in response to Drug Infusion</measure>
    <time_frame>approximately 10 minutes in the middle of 75 minute study visit</time_frame>
    <description>CVC is the ratio between Cerebral Blood Flow (CBF) and blood pressure (BP). Change in CVC in response to drug infusion between male [NOS or COX] and female [NOS or COX] groups. The hypothesis is that acute inhibition of COX or NOS will reduce sex differences in hypoxia-mediated cerebral vasodilation [Aim 2].</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in hypoxia CVC in response to Ganirelix compared to no ganirelix Baseline (Aim 3a)</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and up to 7 days during ganirelix treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Change in hypoxia CVC response to ganirelix compared to baseline within male and female groups, where CVC is CBF is normalized for BP. The hypothesis is that GnRH suppression will abolish hypoxic CBF differences, indicating sex steroids play a vital role in CBF control [Aim 3].</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in hypoxia CVC response to sex hormone suppression with single sex hormone add-back</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and up to 14 days</time_frame>
    <description>Change in hypoxia CVC response to ganirelix+testosterone (in males Aim 3B) or ganirelix+estradiol (in females, Aim 3C) compared to baseline within male and female groups, where CVC is CBF is normalized for BP. The hypothesis is that adding a sex steroid will magnify hypoxic CVC differences, indicating sex steroids play a vital role in CBF control [Aim 3].</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in hypoxia CVC response to NOS or COX inhibition during ganirelix+single sex hormone add-back</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and up to 14 days</time_frame>
    <description>Change in hypoxia CVC drug response to NOS or COX inhibition during ganirelix+testosterone (in males Aim 3B) or ganirelix+estradiol (in females, Aim 3C) compared to baseline hypoxia studies from Aim 2. The hypothesis is that adding a sex steroid will magnify hypoxic CVC differences in drug effects, indicating sex steroids play a vital role in CBF control [Aim 3].</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">144</enrollment>
  <condition>Cerebral Arterial Diseases</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Male NOS</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Males visit MRI twice. Once for hypercapnia visit (no drugs), and once for hypoxia visit (IV and drug infusion to inhibit NOS). CBF measured via MRI sequences, and hemodynamics monitored for safety/research.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Male COX</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Males visit MRI twice. Once for hypercapnia visit (no drugs), and once for hypoxia visit (IV and drug infusion to inhibit COX). CBF measured via MRI sequences, and hemodynamics monitored for safety/research.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Female NOS</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Females visit MRI twice. Once for hypercapnia visit (no drugs), and once for hypoxia visit (IV and drug infusion to inhibit NOS). CBF measured via MRI sequences, and hemodynamics monitored for safety/research.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Female COX</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Females visit MRI twice. Once for hypercapnia visit (no drugs), and once for hypoxia visit (IV and drug infusion to inhibit COX). CBF measured via MRI sequences, and hemodynamics monitored for safety/research.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>L-NMMA</intervention_name>
    <description>L-NMMA is a modified amino acid which competitively inhibits Nitric Oxide Synthase (NOS). It is infused acutely (~5 min) via IV catheter. Metabolized via normal metabolic (amino acid) pathways in ~24 hours.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Female NOS</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Male NOS</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ketorolac Tromethamine</intervention_name>
    <description>Ketorolac is an NSAID which competitively inhibits Cyclooxygenase (COX). It is infused acutely (~5 min) via IV catheter. Metabolized in &lt;24 hours.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Female COX</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Male COX</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ganirelix Acetate</intervention_name>
    <description>Gonadotropin-Releasing Hormone (GnRH) antagonist ganirelix acetate as a model to isolate estrogen and testosterone effects on the cerebrovascular system. Participants receive daily injections of ganirelix for 12-14 days for Aim 3 studies only. This will be overseen by clinical endocrinologists.
Both males and females receive this treatment in Aim 3.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Female COX</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Female NOS</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Male COX</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Male NOS</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Testosterone Transdermal Product</intervention_name>
    <description>In Aim 3, males receive this for 7-9 days of the ganirelix treatment.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Male COX</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Male NOS</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Estradiol Topical</intervention_name>
    <description>In Aim 3, females receive this for 7-9 days of the ganirelix treatment.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Female COX</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Female NOS</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  All participants will be healthy adults between 18-40 years old, matched for age and
             aerobic fitness

          -  Participants will be non-hypertensive (&lt;125/80mm Hg)

          -  Participants will be non-obese (BMI 19-25 kg/m2)

          -  Participants will have normal blood glucose (&lt;100 g/dl)

          -  Participants will have normal lipids (LDL cholesterol &lt;130 mg/dl, triglycerides &lt;150
             mg/dl)

          -  Women must have a natural regular menstrual cycle

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Participants with a history of:

               -  peripheral vascular disease

               -  hepatic disease

               -  renal disease

               -  hematologic disease

               -  stroke

               -  obesity

               -  prediabetes

               -  diabetes

               -  sleep apnea

          -  Participants with current BP&gt;130/85 mmHg

          -  Regular smokers

          -  Taking cardiovascular medications

          -  Women who take hormonal birth control

          -  Women who are pregnant or have polycystic ovarian syndrome [Hormonal birth control
             will not be allowed in women]
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>40 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>William Schrage, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Wisconsin, Madison</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Shawn E Bolin, MS</last_name>
    <phone>608-263-6308</phone>
    <email>sbolin@wisc.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Wisconsin, Madison</name>
      <address>
        <city>Madison</city>
        <state>Wisconsin</state>
        <zip>53706</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 7, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 7, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 11, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 4, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 4, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 9, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cerebral Arterial Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Ketorolac</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ketorolac Tromethamine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Estradiol</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Testosterone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ganirelix</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

