<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04262544</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2019-0790</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>1R21NR018281-01A1</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04262544</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>An Innovative Mobile Health Intervention to Improve Self-care in Patients With Heart Failure</brief_title>
  <official_title>An Innovative Mobile Health Intervention to Improve Self-care in Patients With Heart Failure</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Illinois at Chicago</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Nursing Research (NINR)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Indiana University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Rush University Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Illinois at Chicago</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Heart failure (HF) is associated with high mortality and hospitalization rates. Prior studies
      show that adherence to routine HF self-care behaviors reduces the risk of all-cause mortality
      and HF-related hospitalizations, and improves health related quality of life. However,
      self-care has generally been found to be poor among HF patients. This study aims to assess
      the feasibility, acceptance, and efficacy of an innovative, patient-centered intervention
      (iCardia4HF) that aims to promote adherence to HF self-care and improve patient outcomes
      through the use of commercially available mobile health technologies.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      More than 6.5 million people have heart failure (HF) in the United States and 960,000 new
      cases are reported annually. HF is associated with high mortality and hospitalization rates,
      high costs, and poor health-related quality of life (HRQL). Despite major improvements in
      outcomes with medical and surgical therapy, admission rates following a HF-related
      hospitalization remain high with 25% of patients readmitted to the hospital within 30-days
      and up to 50% readmitted within 6 months. Previous research shows that adherence to routine
      HF self-care behaviors reduces the risk of all-cause mortality and HF-related
      hospitalization, and improves HRQL. However, self-care has generally been found to be poor
      among HF patients, particularly minority populations. Nonadherence to HF symptom monitoring
      and medication use is remarkably high even among recently discharged patients hospitalized
      due to a HF exacerbation. Recent advances in consumer-based mobile health (mHealth)
      technologies, such as smartphones, mobile health apps, wearable sensors, and other smart and
      connected health devices, offer scalable and affordable solutions for promoting better HF
      self-care and expanding delivery of care services to communities that are difficult to reach.
      However, no prior studies have assessed the impact of these technologies on HF self-care and
      patient outcomes.

      This study aims to conduct a pilot randomized controlled trial (RCT) of a patient-centered
      intervention named iCardia4HF that promotes adherence to HF self-care through the use of
      commercial mHealth devices and app tools. iCardia4HF consists of: (1) a patient-centered
      mHealth app, developed in partnership with the Heart Failure Society of America, that
      interfaces with multiple connected health devices and comprises a number of self- monitoring,
      patient education, and adherence reminder tools for improving self-care; and (2) individually
      tailored text-messages (TMs) targeting health beliefs, self-care efficacy, and HF-knowledge.
      Study participants (n=92) diagnosed with HF will be randomly assigned to iCardia4HF or the
      control group for 12 weeks. Specific aims are to: 1) assess the feasibility and acceptance of
      iCardia4HF; 2) examine the preliminary efficacy of iCardia4HF on objectively assessed
      measures of HF self-care using real- time data from the connected health devices and app, as
      well as self-reported Self-Care and HRQL; track the number of hospitalizations and emergency
      room (ER) visits over 12 weeks; and 3) examine the mediating effect of intervention target
      variables (health beliefs, self-care efficacy, and HF-knowledge) and impact of independent
      patient factors on HF self-care.

      This study represents an important step in identifying an affordable and scalable mHealth
      intervention that has the potential to bring about a new paradigm in self-care management of
      HF.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 20, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 30, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 30, 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Care Provider, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>Care providers (doctors and nurses) providing usual care to study participants will be blinded to the allocation of participants.
Data collectors and assessors of subjective outcomes (e.g. health beliefs, self-efficacy, self-care) will be blinded to the allocation. Study participants will be asked not to reveal to their provider and assessor which group they are assigned to. Data collectors/assessors will have restricted access to patient data in REDCap and will not share the same space with other study investigators.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Medication adherence (dose count)</measure>
    <time_frame>Weeks 1 to 12</time_frame>
    <description>Percent of prescribed number of doses taken</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Medication adherence (dose time)</measure>
    <time_frame>Weeks 1 to 12</time_frame>
    <description>Percent of doses taken on schedule within 25% of the expected time interval</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Adherence to daily self-monitoring of weight</measure>
    <time_frame>Weeks 1 to 12</time_frame>
    <description>Number of days patients completed at least one measurement between 12 am and 11:59pm</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adherence to daily self-monitoring of blood pressure</measure>
    <time_frame>Weeks 1 to 12</time_frame>
    <description>Number of days patients completed at least one BP measurement between 12 am and 11:59pm</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adherence to self-monitoring of HF symptoms</measure>
    <time_frame>Weeks 1 to 12</time_frame>
    <description>Number of days intervention patients used the mobile app to record their HF symptoms</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Physical activity - Steps</measure>
    <time_frame>Weeks 1 to 12</time_frame>
    <description>Number of daily steps (measured with a Fitbit device)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Moderate-to-Vigorous Physical Activity</measure>
    <time_frame>Weeks 1 to 12</time_frame>
    <description>Number of moderate-to-vigorous physical activity minutes per day (measured with a Fitbit device)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adherence to low-sodium diet</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 12 Weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Sodium intake will be assessed with a urinary sample test</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Self-reported Self-care</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 30 days, and 12 Weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Measured with the Self-Care Heart Failure Index (SCHFI) v.7.2. Each scale score ranges from 0 to 100. Higher scores indicate better self-care.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Health Beliefs about Medication Compliance</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 30 days, and 12 Weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Beliefs about Medication Compliance Scale (12-items)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Health Beliefs about Dietary Compliance</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 30 days, and 12 Weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Beliefs about Dietary Compliance Scale (12 items)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Health Beliefs about Self-Monitoring Compliance</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 30 days, and 12 Weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Beliefs about Self-Monitoring Scale (18 items)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>HF-knowledge</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 30 days, and 12 Weeks</time_frame>
    <description>HF-specific knowledge will be assessed with the Dutch Heart Failure Knowledge Scale (DHFK), a 15-item questionnaire measuring general knowledge about HF, symptom recognition, and treatment (e.g. diet and fluid restriction)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Health-related Quality of life (HRQoL)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 30 days, and 12 Weeks</time_frame>
    <description>HRQoL will be measured with the Kansas City Cardiomyopathy Questionnaire, which contains 23-items that can be quantified into five subscales: physical limitations, symptoms (frequency, severity, and change over time), quality of life (QoL), social interference, and self-efficacy. Lower scores indicate worse HRQoL.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>HF-related hospitalizations</measure>
    <time_frame>Weeks 1 to 12</time_frame>
    <description>Number of patients with an event</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>HF-related hospitalization rate</measure>
    <time_frame>Weeks 1 to 12</time_frame>
    <description>Number of hospitalizations per person</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>All-cause hospitalizations</measure>
    <time_frame>Weeks 1 to 12</time_frame>
    <description>Number of patients with an event</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>All-cause hospitalization rate</measure>
    <time_frame>Weeks 1 to 12</time_frame>
    <description>Number of all-cause hospitalizations per person</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Emergency room visits</measure>
    <time_frame>Weeks 1 to 12</time_frame>
    <description>Number of patients with an event</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Emergency room visit rate</measure>
    <time_frame>Weeks 1 to 12</time_frame>
    <description>Number of emergency room visits per person</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">92</enrollment>
  <condition>Heart Failure</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>mHealth</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Intervention group</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Usual Care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Control group</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>iCardia4HF</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants in the intervention group will receive the following main components in addition to usual care: 1) the Heart Failure Health Storylines mobile app which supports daily self-monitoring and management of vital signs and symptoms; 2) three connected health devices (Fitbit activity tracker, Withings Cardio Body weight scale and blood pressure monitor), and 3) a program of tailored text-messages targeting health beliefs, self-efficacy, and HF-knowledge.</description>
    <arm_group_label>mHealth</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Usual Care</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants assigned to the control group will receive usual care and the same connected health devices (Fitbit activity tracker, Withings weight scale and blood pressure monitor) as patients in the intervention group, but without the heart failure health storylines mobile app and text-messaging program. Usual care includes patient education before hospital discharge, and follow-up visits at the outpatient HF clinic a week after discharge and monthly thereafter depending on the patient's condition. Patient education includes literacy-sensitive, education material about HF self-care developed by the Sheps Center for Health Services Research,and a 40-minute education session with an APN and a dietician to review and discuss the education material provided to the patient.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Usual Care</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Inpatients admitted to the hospital with a primary or secondary diagnosis of HF as
             defined by the International Classification of Diseases (ICD-10) codes or outpatients
             with a hospitalization due to HF in the last 12 months

          -  ≥ 18 years of age

          -  Stage C, NYHA I, II or III, IV

          -  Left Ventricular Ejection Fraction ≤40%

          -  Being treated with at least one cardiovascular medication for heart failure

          -  Ability to speak and read English

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Planned coronary revascularization, Transcatheter Aortic Valve Implantation (TAVI),
             Cardiac Resynchronization Therapy (CRT) - implantation, and/or heart transplantation
             (HTx) within the next 3 months.

          -  Coronary revascularization and/or CRT-implantation within the last 30 days

          -  Advanced renal disease (stage IV CKD, GFR&lt;30, or hemodialysis)

          -  Known alcohol or drug use

          -  End-stage HF (hospice candidate)

          -  Active cancer

          -  Pregnancy

          -  Not able to take care of self (eat, dress, walk, bath, take medications, or use the
             toilet)

          -  Discharged to or already living in a nursing home or other care facility other than
             home

          -  Cognitive impairment (MoCA score &lt; 22).

          -  Prior use of study devices for self-care or participation in a similar trial
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Spyros Kitsiou</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Illinois at Chicago</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Spyros Kitsiou, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>312-355-3519</phone>
    <email>skitsiou@uic.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Illinois Hospital &amp; Health Sciences System</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chicago</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60612</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 6, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 7, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 10, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 11, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 11, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 13, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Illinois at Chicago</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Spyros Kitsiou</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>mHealth</keyword>
  <keyword>text messaging</keyword>
  <keyword>smartphone</keyword>
  <keyword>mobile apps</keyword>
  <keyword>wearables</keyword>
  <keyword>heart failure</keyword>
  <keyword>self-management</keyword>
  <keyword>telehealth</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Heart Failure</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Final research data along with metadata and descriptors will be shared to make sharing meaningful and usable by other researchers. More specifically, we will share both de-identified individual-level data and aggregate data in the form of summary statistics and tables. For the individual-level data, we will develop a data dictionary and documentation guide to maximize the utility of the data and to help qualified researchers understand and properly use the data as needed.</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Clinical Study Report (CSR)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>Within 2 years after the final data collection is completed or within one year after the publication of the main outcomes manuscript (whichever comes first), we will share the final, completely de-identified dataset with the research community.</ipd_time_frame>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

