<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04267913</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>S1900D</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2020-00171</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>S1900D</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>S1900D</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>U10CA180888</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04267913</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Testing of TAK228 (MLN0128, Sapanisertib) Plus Docetaxel to the Usual Standard of Care for Advanced Squamous Cell Lung Cancer (A Lung-MAP Treatment Trial)</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized Phase II Study of TAK228 (MLN0128, Sapanisertib) Plus Docetaxel Versus Standard of Care in Patients With Previously - Treated NFE2L2 or KEAP1-Positive Stage IV or Recurrent Squamous Cell Lung Cancer (ECOG-ACRIN LUNG-MAP Sub-Study)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Southwest Oncology Group</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Southwest Oncology Group</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This phase II LUNG-MAP treatment trial studies how well sapanisertib and docetaxel work for
      the treatment for squamous cell lung cancer that is stage IV or has come back (recurrent).
      Sapanisertib may stop the growth of tumor cells by blocking some of the enzymes needed for
      cell growth. Drugs used in chemotherapy, such as docetaxel, work in different ways to stop
      the growth of tumor cells, either by killing the cells, by stopping them from dividing, or by
      stopping them from spreading. Giving sapanisertib and docetaxel may work better in treating
      patients with squamous cell lung cancer compared to standard chemotherapy.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PRIMARY OBJECTIVE:

      I. To compare the investigator-assessed progression-free survival (IA-PFS) between patients
      with NFE2L2 or KEAP1-positive stage IV or recurrent squamous cell lung cancer (SQCLC)
      randomized to TAK228 (MLN0128, sapanisertib) + docetaxel versus standard of care therapy.

      SECONDARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To compare overall response rate (ORR) by Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors
      (RECIST) 1.1 between the treatment arms.

      II. To compare overall survival (OS) between the treatment arms. III. To evaluate duration of
      response (DOR) among responders within each treatment arm.

      IV. To evaluate and compare the frequency and severity of toxicities associated within each
      treatment arm.

      V. To evaluate outcomes of IA-PFS, OS, and response in the subsets of patients eligible based
      on the presence of NFE2L2 versus KEAP1 alterations.

      TRANSLATIONAL MEDICINE OBJECTIVES:

      I. To collect, process, and bank cell-free deoxyribonucleic acid (DNA) (cfDNA) at baseline,
      cycle 2 day 1, and end of treatment for future development of a proposal to evaluate
      comprehensive next-generation sequencing of circulating tumor DNA (ctDNA).

      II. To establish a tissue/blood repository from patients with refractory non-small cell lung
      cancer (NSCLC).

      OUTLINE: Patients are randomized to 1 of 2 arms.

      ARM A: Patients receive docetaxel intravenously (IV) and dexamethasone IV over 30 minutes on
      days 1 and 8 and sapanisertib orally (PO) once daily (QD) on days 2-4, 9-11, and 16-18.
      Cycles repeat every 21 days in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.
      If docetaxel is discontinued, patients receive sapanisertib PO QD on days 1-21. Cycles repeat
      every 21 days in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.

      ARM B: Patients receive standard of care treatment comprising either docetaxel IV and
      dexamethasone IV over 30 minutes on day 1 or docetaxel IV, dexamethasone IV over 30 minutes,
      and ramucirumab IV over 60 minutes on day 1. Cycles repeat every 21 days in the absence of
      disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.

      After completion of study treatment, patients are followed up every 6 months for 2 years and
      then at 3 years.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">September 5, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 31, 2026</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 31, 2025</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Investigator-assessed progression-free survival (IA-PFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 3 years</time_frame>
    <description>IA-PFS will be compared between the arms using a stratified log-rank test.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall response rate (ORR)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Will be assessed by Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors (RECIST) 1.1.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of response</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Will be estimated using the Kaplan-Meier method. The Brookmeyer-Crowley method will be used to estimate 95% confidence intervals for the median. For point estimates at landmark times, the associated 95% confidence interval (CI) will be calculated using Greenwood's formula and based on a log-log transformation applied on the survival function. Hazard ratios for these outcomes will be estimated using a Cox Proportional Hazards regression model adjusting for the stratification factors.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression free survival</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Will be estimated using the Kaplan-Meier method. The Brookmeyer-Crowley method will be used to estimate 95% confidence intervals for the median. For point estimates at landmark times, the associated 95% CI will be calculated using Greenwood's formula and based on a log-log transformation applied on the survival function. Hazard ratios for these outcomes will be estimated using a Cox Proportional Hazards regression model adjusting for the stratification factors.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Will be estimated using the Kaplan-Meier method. The Brookmeyer-Crowley method will be used to estimate 95% confidence intervals for the median. For point estimates at landmark times, the associated 95% CI will be calculated using Greenwood's formula and based on a log-log transformation applied on the survival function. Hazard ratios for these outcomes will be estimated using a Cox Proportional Hazards regression model adjusting for the stratification factors.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">94</enrollment>
  <condition>Lung Squamous Cell Carcinoma</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Lung Carcinoma</condition>
  <condition>Stage IV Lung Cancer AJCC v8</condition>
  <condition>Stage IVA Lung Cancer AJCC v8</condition>
  <condition>Stage IVB Lung Cancer AJCC v8</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm A (docetaxel, dexamethasone, sapanisertib)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive docetaxel IV and dexamethasone IV over 30 minutes on days 1 and 8 and sapanisertib PO QD on days 2-4, 9-11, and 16-18. Cycles repeat every 21 days in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity. If docetaxel is discontinued, patients receive sapanisertib PO QD on days 1-21. Cycles repeat every 21 days in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B (standard of care treatment)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive standard of care treatment comprising either docetaxel IV and dexamethasone IV over 30 minutes on day 1 or docetaxel IV, dexamethasone IV over 30 minutes, and ramucirumab IV over 60 minutes on day 1. Cycles repeat every 21 days in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Dexamethasone</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm A (docetaxel, dexamethasone, sapanisertib)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B (standard of care treatment)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Aacidexam</other_name>
    <other_name>Adexone</other_name>
    <other_name>Aknichthol Dexa</other_name>
    <other_name>Alba-Dex</other_name>
    <other_name>Alin</other_name>
    <other_name>Alin Depot</other_name>
    <other_name>Alin Oftalmico</other_name>
    <other_name>Amplidermis</other_name>
    <other_name>Anemul mono</other_name>
    <other_name>Auricularum</other_name>
    <other_name>Auxiloson</other_name>
    <other_name>Baycadron</other_name>
    <other_name>Baycuten</other_name>
    <other_name>Baycuten N</other_name>
    <other_name>Cortidexason</other_name>
    <other_name>Cortisumman</other_name>
    <other_name>Decacort</other_name>
    <other_name>Decadrol</other_name>
    <other_name>Decadron</other_name>
    <other_name>Decadron DP</other_name>
    <other_name>Decalix</other_name>
    <other_name>Decameth</other_name>
    <other_name>Decasone R.p.</other_name>
    <other_name>Dectancyl</other_name>
    <other_name>Dekacort</other_name>
    <other_name>Deltafluorene</other_name>
    <other_name>Deronil</other_name>
    <other_name>Desamethasone</other_name>
    <other_name>Desameton</other_name>
    <other_name>Dexa-Mamallet</other_name>
    <other_name>Dexa-Rhinosan</other_name>
    <other_name>Dexa-Scheroson</other_name>
    <other_name>Dexa-sine</other_name>
    <other_name>Dexacortal</other_name>
    <other_name>Dexacortin</other_name>
    <other_name>Dexafarma</other_name>
    <other_name>Dexafluorene</other_name>
    <other_name>Dexalocal</other_name>
    <other_name>Dexamecortin</other_name>
    <other_name>Dexameth</other_name>
    <other_name>Dexamethasone Intensol</other_name>
    <other_name>Dexamethasonum</other_name>
    <other_name>Dexamonozon</other_name>
    <other_name>Dexapos</other_name>
    <other_name>Dexinoral</other_name>
    <other_name>Dexone</other_name>
    <other_name>Dinormon</other_name>
    <other_name>Fluorodelta</other_name>
    <other_name>Fortecortin</other_name>
    <other_name>Gammacorten</other_name>
    <other_name>Hexadecadrol</other_name>
    <other_name>Hexadrol</other_name>
    <other_name>Lokalison-F</other_name>
    <other_name>Loverine</other_name>
    <other_name>Methylfluorprednisolone</other_name>
    <other_name>Millicorten</other_name>
    <other_name>Mymethasone</other_name>
    <other_name>Orgadrone</other_name>
    <other_name>Spersadex</other_name>
    <other_name>TaperDex</other_name>
    <other_name>Visumetazone</other_name>
    <other_name>ZoDex</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Docetaxel</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm A (docetaxel, dexamethasone, sapanisertib)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B (standard of care treatment)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Docecad</other_name>
    <other_name>RP56976</other_name>
    <other_name>Taxotere</other_name>
    <other_name>Taxotere Injection Concentrate</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ramucirumab</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B (standard of care treatment)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Anti-VEGFR-2 Fully Human Monoclonal Antibody IMC-1121B</other_name>
    <other_name>Cyramza</other_name>
    <other_name>IMC-1121B</other_name>
    <other_name>LY3009806</other_name>
    <other_name>Monoclonal Antibody HGS-ETR2</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sapanisertib</intervention_name>
    <description>Given PO</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm A (docetaxel, dexamethasone, sapanisertib)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B (standard of care treatment)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>INK-128</other_name>
    <other_name>INK128</other_name>
    <other_name>MLN-0128</other_name>
    <other_name>MLN0128</other_name>
    <other_name>TAK-228</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients must be assigned to S1900D. Assignment to S1900D is determined by the S1400
             or LUNGMAP protocol genomic profiling using the FoundationOne assay. Biomarker
             eligibility for S1900D is based on the identification of an NFE2L2 mutation or KEAP1
             alteration

          -  Patients must have a histologically or cytologically confirmed stage IV or recurrent
             pure squamous cell lung cancer

          -  Patients must have measurable disease documented by computed tomography (CT) or
             magnetic resonance imaging (MRI). The CT from a combined positron emission tomography
             (PET)/CT may be used to document only non-measurable disease unless it is of
             diagnostic quality. Measurable disease must be assessed within 28 days prior to
             sub-study randomization. Pleural effusions, ascites and laboratory parameters are not
             acceptable as the only evidence of disease. Non-measurable disease must be assessed
             within 42 days prior to sub-study randomization. All disease must be assessed and
             documented on the Baseline Tumor Assessment Form. Patients whose only measurable
             disease is within a previous radiation therapy port must demonstrate clearly
             progressive disease (in the opinion of the treating investigator) prior to
             randomization. CT and MRI scans must be submitted for central review via transfer of
             images and data (TRIAD)

          -  Patients must have a CT or MRI scan of the brain to evaluate for central nervous
             system (CNS) disease within 42 days prior to sub-study randomization

          -  Patients with evidence of chronic hepatitis B virus (HBV) infection must have
             undetectable HBV viral load on suppressive therapy within 28 days prior to sub-study
             randomization

          -  Patients with a history of hepatitis C virus (HCV) infection must have been treated
             and cured. Patients with HCV infection who are currently on treatment must have an
             undetectable HCV viral load within 28 days prior to sub-study randomization

          -  Patients with a known history of human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) seropositivity:

               -  Must have undetectable viral load using standard HIV assays in clinical practice

               -  Must have CD4 count &gt;= 400/mcL

               -  Must not require prophylaxis for any opportunistic infections (i.e., fungal,
                  mycobacterium avium complex [MAC], or pneumocystis pneumonia [PCP] prophylaxis)

               -  Must not be newly diagnosed within 12 months prior to sub-study randomization

          -  Patients must be able to swallow oral medications. Patients must not have any
             impairment of gastrointestinal function or gastrointestinal disease that may
             significantly alter the absorption of TAK228 (MLN0128, sapanisertib) (e.g. ulcerative
             disease, uncontrolled nausea, vomiting, diarrhea, malabsorption syndrome or small
             bowel resection, or enteric stomata)

          -  Patients must be able to safely receive at least one of the investigator's choice of
             standard of care regimens

          -  Patients must have progressed (in the opinion of the treating physician) following the
             most recent line of therapy

          -  Patients must have recovered (=&lt; grade 1) from any side effects of prior therapy

          -  Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) &gt;= 1,500/mcl (obtained within 28 days prior to
             sub-study randomization)

          -  Platelet count &gt;= 100,000 mcl (obtained within 28 days prior to sub-study
             randomization)

          -  Hemoglobin &gt;= 9 g/dL (obtained within 28 days prior to sub-study randomization).
             Transfusion to obtain a hemoglobin (Hb) of &gt;= 9 g/dl is acceptable

          -  Patients must have fasting triglycerides =&lt; 300 mg/dL within 28 days prior to
             sub-study randomization

          -  Serum bilirubin =&lt; Institutional upper limit of normal (IULN) (within 28 days prior to
             sub-study randomization. For patients with liver metastases, serum bilirubin must be
             =&lt; 2 x IULN

          -  Alanine aminotransferase (ALT) or aspartate aminotransferase (AST) =&lt; 2 x IULN (within
             28 days prior to sub-study randomization) (if both ALT and AST are done, both must be
             &lt; 2 IULN). For patients with liver metastases, ALT or AST must be =&lt; 5 x IULN (if both
             ALT and AST are done, both must be =&lt; 5 x IULN)

          -  Patients must have a serum creatinine =&lt; the IULN or calculated creatinine clearance
             &gt;= 40 mL/min using the following Cockcroft-Gault formula. This specimen must have been
             drawn and processed within 28 days prior to sub-study randomization

          -  Patients must have Zubrod performance status 0-1 documented within 28 days prior to
             sub-study randomization

          -  Pre-study history and physical exam must be obtained within 28 days prior to
             randomization

          -  No other prior malignancy is allowed except for the following: adequately treated
             basal cell or squamous cell skin cancer, in situ cervical cancer, adequately treated
             stage I or II cancer from which the patient is currently in complete remission, or any
             other cancer from which the patient has been disease free for two years. In addition,
             indolent or low-grade malignancies which are not expected to interfere with assessment
             of the primary or toxicity endpoints are permissible (e.g. localized well
             differentiated prostate cancer). These cases should be discussed with a study chair
             prior to enrollment

          -  Patients must agree to have blood specimens submitted for circulating tumor DNA
             (ctDNA)

          -  Patients must also be offered participation in banking and in the correlative studies
             for collection and future use of specimens

          -  Patients must be informed of the investigational nature of this study and must sign
             and give written informed consent in accordance with institutional and federal
             guidelines

          -  As a part of the OPEN registration process the treating institution's identity is
             provided in order to ensure that the current (within 365 days) date of institutional
             review board approval for this study has been entered in the system

          -  Patients with impaired decision-making capacity are eligible as long as their
             neurological or psychological condition does not preclude their safe participation in
             the study (e.g., tracking pill consumption and reporting adverse events to the
             investigator)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients must not have EGFR sensitizing mutations, EGFR T790M mutation, ALK gene
             fusion, ROS 1 gene rearrangement, and BRAF V600E mutation unless they have progressed
             following all standard of care targeted therapy

          -  Patient must not have leptomeningeal disease, spinal cord compression or brain
             metastases unless: (1) metastases have been locally treated and have remained
             clinically controlled and asymptomatic for at least 14 days following treatment, and
             prior to sub-study randomization, AND (2) patient has no residual neurological
             dysfunction and has been off corticosteroids for at least 14 days prior to sub-study
             randomization. Patients with brain metastases that have not been treated may be
             registered if the metastases are:

               -  &lt; 2 mm OR deemed clinically equivocal, AND

               -  No evidence of shift, AND

               -  No focal or other neurologic deficits, AND

               -  No requirement for steroids, anti-seizure medications

          -  Patients must not have uncontrolled illnesses within 28 days prior to sub-study
             randomization including:

               -  Uncontrolled asthma is defined as: oxygen (O2) saturation &lt; 90% by arterial blood
                  gas analysis or pulse oximetry on room air

               -  Medically significant (symptomatic) bradycardia

               -  History of arrhythmia requiring an implantable cardiac defibrillator

               -  Symptomatic pulmonary hypertension

               -  Uncontrolled hypertension (use of anti-hypertensive agents to control
                  hypertension before cycle 1 day 1 [C1D1] is allowed)

               -  Clinically significant valvular disease

          -  Patients must not have received any radiation therapy within 14 days prior to
             randomization

          -  Patients must not be planning to receive any concurrent chemotherapy, immunotherapy,
             biologic or hormonal therapy for cancer treatment while receiving treatment on this
             study. Concurrent use of hormones for non-cancer-related conditions (e.g. insulin for
             diabetes and hormone replacement therapy) is acceptable

          -  Patient must not have had a major surgery within 14 days prior to sub-study
             randomization. Patient must have fully recovered from the effects of prior surgery in
             the opinion of the treating investigator

          -  Patients must not have previously received treatment with PI3K, AKT, PI3K/mTOR
             inhibitors, TORC1/2 inhibitors or TORC1 inhibitors

          -  Patients must not have uncontrolled diabetes within 28 days prior to sub-study
             randomization

               -  Definition of uncontrolled diabetes: Glycosylated hemoglobin (HbA1c) &gt;= 8.0% and
                  fasting serum glucose (&gt; 130 mg/dL) within 28 days prior to sub-study
                  randomization

          -  Patients must not have any grade III/IV cardiac disease as defined by the New York
             Heart Association Criteria (i.e., patients with cardiac disease resulting in marked
             limitation of physical activity or resulting in inability to carry on any physical
             activity without discomfort), unstable angina pectoris, myocardial infarction within 6
             months, or serious uncontrolled cardiac arrhythmia

          -  Patients must not have had an ischemic cerebrovascular event or pulmonary embolism
             within 6 months

          -  Patients must not have a rate-corrected QT interval &gt; 480 msec based on the 12-lead
             electrocardiography (ECG) within 28 days prior to sub-study randomization (i.e.,
             repeated demonstration of corrected QT [QTc] interval &gt; 480 milliseconds, or history
             of congenital long QT syndrome, or torsades de pointes). It is suggested that a local
             cardiologist review the QTc intervals

          -  Patients must not have received any live attenuated vaccinations or been in close
             contact with those who have received live vaccines within 28 days prior to sub-study
             registration and throughout protocol treatment

          -  Patients must not be planning to use proton pump inhibitors (PPIs) at least one week
             prior to sub-study randomization and throughout protocol treatment

          -  Patients must not be pregnant or nursing. Women of reproductive potential must have
             agreed to use an effective contraceptive method and must not donate eggs during
             protocol treatment and for 90 days after the last protocol treatment. Men of
             reproductive potential must have agreed to use an effective contraceptive method and
             must not donate sperm during protocol treatment and for 120 days after the last
             protocol treatment. A woman is considered to be of &quot;reproductive potential&quot; if she has
             had menses at any time in the preceding 12 consecutive months. In addition to routine
             contraceptive methods, &quot;effective contraception&quot; also includes heterosexual celibacy
             and surgery intended to prevent pregnancy (or with a side-effect of pregnancy
             prevention) defined as a hysterectomy, bilateral oophorectomy or bilateral tubal
             ligation. However, if at any point a previously celibate patient chooses to become
             heterosexually active during the time period for use of contraceptive measures
             outlined in the protocol, he/she is responsible for beginning contraceptive measures
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Paul K Paik</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Southwest Oncology Group</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <verification_date>February 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 11, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 11, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 13, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 11, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 11, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 13, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lung Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Dexamethasone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dexamethasone acetate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Docetaxel</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ramucirumab</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Antineoplastic Agents, Immunological</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ichthammol</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>BB 1101</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Antibodies</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Immunoglobulins</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Antibodies, Monoclonal</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

