<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04262882</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>1R21HD098523-01A1</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>1R21HD098523-01A1</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04262882</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Multilevel Family Planning Intervention</brief_title>
  <official_title>Development, Testing and Health Effects of a Multilevel Family Planning Intervention</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>The University of Texas at San Antonio</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Makerere University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>San Diego State University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Yale University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Eunice Kennedy Shriver National Institute of Child Health and Human Development (NICHD)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>The University of Texas at San Antonio</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study seeks to develop and evaluate a multi-level intervention to satisfy couples' unmet
      need for family planning in rural Uganda. The study will evaluate the acceptability,
      feasibility, and preliminary efficacy of the intervention at increasing contraceptive uptake
      and continuation and improving intermediate outcomes of knowledge, attitudes, perceived
      community norms, partner communication and equity among couples in rural Uganda.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      In 2018, 32.6% of women of reproductive age had an unmet need for family planning in Uganda,
      meaning they wanted to avoid pregnancy but were not using a modern contraceptive method.
      Filling the unmet need for family planning has important public health implications,
      including reductions in pregnancy-related health risks and deaths, and infant mortality.
      While Uganda is scaling up efforts to reduce supply-side barriers in rural areas, such as
      community distribution of contraceptives, couples are still faced with multi-level
      demand-side barriers to contraceptive use. In addition to misinformation and fear of
      contraceptive side-effects, relationship dynamics, peer and family influence, and broader
      community norms promoting large family size and traditional gender roles influence family
      planning. This study will pilot test a multi-level, community-based intervention, which
      employs transformative community dialogues to alter individual attitudes and the perception
      of community norms that discourage family planning. Community dialogues are delivered to
      groups of couples enhanced to simultaneously address individual and interpersonal-level
      determinants of family planning and link couples to family planning services. The aims of
      this project are to conduct a pilot quasi-experimental controlled trial to: 1) assess
      acceptability and feasibility of the trial procedures and intervention content; 2) the
      intervention's potential efficacy on contraceptive uptake and continuation and intermediate
      outcomes (knowledge, attitudes, perceived community norms, partner communication and equity)
      through 6-month follow up.

      One village will be randomized to the multi-level intervention and one village to the control
      condition (attention-matched control intervention). Participation in the full study will last
      6 months. Participants will first complete a questionnaire after enrollment, and female
      participants will take a pregnancy test at baseline. Participants in both study arms will
      participate in interviewer administered questionnaires at 3 months and 6 months follow-up,
      pregnancy testing at 6-months follow-up for women, and will permit the research team to
      access their medical records to extract information about their contraceptive use and use of
      family planning services. Participants in the intervention arm will participate in a series
      of group sessions with other couples from the community. Group sessions will last
      approximately 90 minutes, including community dialogues to reconstruct group norms that
      discourage contraceptive use enhanced with activities to improve knowledge, motivation,
      couple dynamics, and link couples to services.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">September 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in modern contraceptive from baseline to 3- and 6-months follow-up</measure>
    <time_frame>3 and 6 months follow-up</time_frame>
    <description>Uptake of any modern contraceptive method (pills, injection, condoms [self-report, ≥90% of sex acts], intrauterine device, implant, tubal ligation, vasectomy); measured through women's clinic records (men's for vasectomy), and triangulated by women and men's self-report</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Contraceptive continuation</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months follow-up</time_frame>
    <description>For participants reporting contraceptive uptake at 3-months, continued use of modern method of contraceptive reported at 6 months follow-up. Modern contraceptive methods include pills, injection, condoms [self-report, ≥90% of sex acts], intrauterine device, implant, tubal ligation, vasectomy); measured through women's clinic records (men's for vasectomy), and triangulated by women and men's self-report</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pregnancy</measure>
    <time_frame>6 month follow-up</time_frame>
    <description>Biological measure; pregnancy test</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in knowledge of contraceptives from baseline to 3- and 6-months follow-up</measure>
    <time_frame>3 and 6 months follow-up</time_frame>
    <description>Scale from the Uganda Demographic and Health Survey (DHS) aimed to assess knowledge of modern contraceptive methods; collected through interviewer-administered questionnaire</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in family planning attitudes from baseline to 3- and 6-months follow-up</measure>
    <time_frame>3 and 6 months follow-up</time_frame>
    <description>Scale developed for use in Uganda to assess how participants would feel about using contraceptive methods; collected through interviewer-administered questionnaire</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in family planning norms from baseline to 3- and 6-months follow-up</measure>
    <time_frame>3 and 6 months follow-up</time_frame>
    <description>Scale adapted from the Family Planning Approval Index to assess the perceived acceptance of family planning and contraceptive use among partner, family, peers, and broader community; collected through interviewer-administered questionnaire</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in family planning intentions from baseline to 3- and 6-months follow-up</measure>
    <time_frame>3 and 6 months follow-up</time_frame>
    <description>Scale developed for use in Uganda to assess participants' plans to use contraceptives and family planning services in the future; collected through interviewer-administered questionnaire</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in fertility desire from baseline to 3- and 6-months follow-up</measure>
    <time_frame>3 and 6 months follow-up</time_frame>
    <description>Scale from the Uganda Demographic and Health Survey (DHS) on the participants' fertility desires (i.e., desired number of children); collected through interviewer-administered questionnaire</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in fertility concordance between partners from baseline to 3- and 6-months follow-up</measure>
    <time_frame>3 and 6 months follow-up</time_frame>
    <description>Concordance between partners in a couple's fertility desires (i.e., desired number of children); Scale from the Uganda Demographic and Health Survey (DHS) on the participants' fertility desires (i.e., desired number of children); collected through interviewer-administered questionnaire</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in pregnancy intentions from baseline to 3- and 6-months follow-up</measure>
    <time_frame>3 and 6 months follow-up</time_frame>
    <description>Items from the Uganda Demographic and Health Survey (DHS) to assess desire and time frame for future pregnancy; collected through interviewer-administered questionnaire</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in partner communication about family planning from baseline to 3- and 6-months follow-up</measure>
    <time_frame>3 and 6 months follow-up</time_frame>
    <description>Scale developed for use in Uganda to assess the frequency of communication with partner about family planning and contraceptive use; collected through interviewer-administered questionnaire</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in gender equitable attitudes from baseline to 3- and 6-months follow-up</measure>
    <time_frame>3 and 6 months follow-up</time_frame>
    <description>Gender Equitable Men Scale to assess participants' endorsement of traditional gender norms and attitudes on gender equity; collected through interviewer-administered questionnaire</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">140</enrollment>
  <condition>Contraceptive Usage</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Multilevel Family Planning Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>A multi-level, community-based intervention delivered in groups of couples to increase contraceptive uptake, reduce discontinuation, and reduce the incidence of unintended pregnancy, and improve intermediate outcomes (knowledge, attitudes, norms, communication, equity).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Time and attention-matched control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>A community sanitation intervention delivered in groups of couples to increase at-home and community hygiene practices.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Multilevel Family Planning Intervention</intervention_name>
    <description>The intervention is comprised of community dialogues, or facilitated discussions, aimed to reshape community norms around gender roles, equity, and family size, and critically analyze the social and community influences of &quot;family-wealth&quot; and poverty with the overall goal of reconstructing individual attitudes and group norms on paths to/definitions of a &quot;successful family&quot; inclusive of family planning. Dialogues are enhanced to address knowledge, motivation, self-efficacy, and relationship dynamics, tailored to men and women. Sessions include both gender segregated and integrated groups with couples in the community.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Multilevel Family Planning Intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Time and attention matched control</intervention_name>
    <description>This intervention serves as the attention-matched control. The format and delivery will mirror that of the &quot;Family Health = Family Wealth&quot; intervention (i.e., number, timing, and duration of sessions). The focus of the intervention is on community sanitation and at-home hygiene (hand-washing, food preparation) following an intervention manual that was developed for community groups in Uganda.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Time and attention-matched control</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Being in a relationship and both partners providing written informed consent; women:
             age 18-40 (or emancipated minor); men: age 18-50; not currently using modern
             contraceptives and having never used a non-reversible method; one or both partners
             wanting to prevent pregnancy for at least the next year; living within the selected
             villages; Luganda speaking.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Pregnant; Breastfeeding; Using a modern contraceptive method
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>50 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Katelyn M Sileo, PhD, MPH</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Texas at San Antonio</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Susan M Kiene, PhD, MPH</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>San Diego State University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Christine Muhumuza, MHSR</last_name>
    <phone>+256772658876</phone>
    <email>cmuhumuza@musph.ac.ug</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <verification_date>February 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 4, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 6, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 10, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 6, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 6, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 10, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Quantitative data collected in this trial (baseline, follow-up assessments) will be made available, under the following provisions: (1)The data will be fully de-identified; (2) Access to the data will be made available first to researchers and their students at the four collaborating institutions (within 3 years of study completion): The University of Texas at San Antonio, San Diego State University, the Makerere University School of Public Health (MakSPH), and Yale University; 4) 5 years after study completion, data will be made available to those requesting access outside of the four requesting institutions. Qualitative data collected as part of this trial will not be made available, as it is difficult to fully de-identify and to interpret without knowledge of the context.</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Statistical Analysis Plan (SAP)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Informed Consent Form (ICF)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>3 years after study completion for researchers and students within the collaborating institutions and 5 years after study completion for those outside of the collaborating institutions upon request</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>Upon request from the PI</ipd_access_criteria>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

