<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04260282</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IIBSP-ANE-2020-04</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04260282</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Microbiome and Exacerbations in Neutrophilic Asthma</brief_title>
  <acronym>AsmaEx</acronym>
  <official_title>Exacerbations in Neutrophilic Asthma: Influence of Bronchial Microbiome</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Fundació Institut de Recerca de l'Hospital de la Santa Creu i Sant Pau</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Sociedad Española de Neumología y Cirugía Torácica</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>GlaxoSmithKline</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Fundació Institut de Recerca de l'Hospital de la Santa Creu i Sant Pau</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Neutrophilic asthma (NA) is the least known severe asthma phenotype. It is associated with
      more exacerbations, worse control and impaired lung function. One of its possible etiologies
      is bronchial infections. The study of bronchial microbiology and its relationship with
      exacerbations is a new line of research.

      Objectives: 1) To analyze bronchial microbiome in patients with AN and non-neutrophilic
      (ANN), with frequent exacerbations and without exacerbations. 2) To relate the presence of
      bronchial infections with differences in the microbiome. 3) Correlate the characteristics of
      the microbiome with other evidence used in exacerbations.

      Methods: Prospective study involving 40 non-smoking asthmatics without bronchiectasis (20
      with AN and 20 with ANN). Of these, 10 in each group will have frequent exacerbations (&gt;2
      rounds of systemic steroids in the last year, of &gt;3 days each) and 10 non- frequent
      exacerbations. AN will be defined as &gt;65% neutrophils in stable phase sputum. All patients
      will have two stable visits in which clinical variables, asthma control, lung function and
      induced sputum samples will be collected (for analysis of bronchial inflammatory cell count
      and for the study of the microbiome by 16S rRNA). Specific Immunoglobulin Afor Chlamydia
      Pneumoniae will be determined. In exacerbations, sputum samples will be collected for culture
      and nasopharyngeal smears for the study of major respiratory viruses and bacteria by multiple
      polymerase chain reaction.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">February 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 1, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Qualitative and quantitative analysis of bronchial microbiome</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Qualitative and quantitative analysis of bronchial microbiome in patients with neutrophilic and non-neutrophilic asthma, with frequent exacerbations and without exacerbations.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Influence of bronchial infections in changes of lung microbiome</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Influence of bronchial infections in qualitative and quantitative characteristics of lung microbiome</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes of lung microbiome characteristics over time</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Qualitative and quantitative changes of lung microbiome</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Relationship between qualitative and quantitative characteristics of lung microbiome with levels of specific IgA C. pneumoniae, PCR, IgG aspergillus</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Relationship between qualitative and quantitative characteristics of lung microbiome with levels of specific IgA C. pneumoniae, PCR, IgG aspergillus</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Asthma</condition>
  <condition>Microbiome</condition>
  <condition>Exacerbation</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Neutrophilic asthma</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients with asthma diagnosed according to guidelines, with eosinophils &lt;300/mm3 in blood and &lt;3% in induced sputum</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Eosinophilic asthma</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients with asthma diagnosed according to guidelines, with eosinophils &gt;300/mm3 in blood and/or &gt;3% in induced sputum</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Polymerase Chain Reaction (PCR) for viruses and bacteria in nasal swab</intervention_name>
    <description>PCR for viruses and bacteria in nasal swab</description>
    <arm_group_label>Eosinophilic asthma</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Neutrophilic asthma</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Induced sputum microbiome</intervention_name>
    <description>Microbiome in induced sputum</description>
    <arm_group_label>Eosinophilic asthma</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Neutrophilic asthma</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <biospec_retention>Samples Without DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Induced sputum Nasal swab
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Severe asthma according to guidelines, 18-80 years
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age between 18 -80

          -  Confirmed diagnose of asthma

          -  Severe persistent asthma

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Respiratory infection during the previous month

          -  Other significant lung disease
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital de la Santa Creu i Sant Pau. Carrer Mas Casanovas 90.</name>
      <address>
        <city>Barcelona</city>
        <zip>08041</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Astrid Crespo, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+34-935565972</phone>
      <email>acrespo@santpau.cat</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Spain</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Reddel HK, FitzGerald JM, Bateman ED, Bacharier LB, Becker A, Brusselle G, Buhl R, Cruz AA, Fleming L, Inoue H, Ko FW, Krishnan JA, Levy ML, Lin J, Pedersen SE, Sheikh A, Yorgancioglu A, Boulet LP. GINA 2019: a fundamental change in asthma management: Treatment of asthma with short-acting bronchodilators alone is no longer recommended for adults and adolescents. Eur Respir J. 2019 Jun 27;53(6). pii: 1901046. doi: 10.1183/13993003.01046-2019. Print 2019 Jun.</citation>
    <PMID>31249014</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Plaza Moral V; Comité Ejecutivo de GEMA. [GEMA(4.0). Guidelines for Asthma Management]. Arch Bronconeumol. 2015 Jan;51 Suppl 1:2-54. doi: 10.1016/S0300-2896(15)32812-X. Epub 2015 Nov 30. Spanish.</citation>
    <PMID>26707419</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nair P, Aziz-Ur-Rehman A, Radford K. Therapeutic implications of 'neutrophilic asthma'. Curr Opin Pulm Med. 2015 Jan;21(1):33-8. doi: 10.1097/MCP.0000000000000120. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25415406</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wenzel SE, Szefler SJ, Leung DY, Sloan SI, Rex MD, Martin RJ. Bronchoscopic evaluation of severe asthma. Persistent inflammation associated with high dose glucocorticoids. Am J Respir Crit Care Med. 1997 Sep;156(3 Pt 1):737-43.</citation>
    <PMID>9309987</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shaw DE, Berry MA, Hargadon B, McKenna S, Shelley MJ, Green RH, Brightling CE, Wardlaw AJ, Pavord ID. Association between neutrophilic airway inflammation and airflow limitation in adults with asthma. Chest. 2007 Dec;132(6):1871-5. Epub 2007 Oct 9.</citation>
    <PMID>17925424</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Brusselle GG, Vanderstichele C, Jordens P, Deman R, Slabbynck H, Ringoet V, Verleden G, Demedts IK, Verhamme K, Delporte A, Demeyere B, Claeys G, Boelens J, Padalko E, Verschakelen J, Van Maele G, Deschepper E, Joos GF. Azithromycin for prevention of exacerbations in severe asthma (AZISAST): a multicentre randomised double-blind placebo-controlled trial. Thorax. 2013 Apr;68(4):322-9. doi: 10.1136/thoraxjnl-2012-202698. Epub 2013 Jan 3.</citation>
    <PMID>23291349</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Polosa R, Thomson NC. Smoking and asthma: dangerous liaisons. Eur Respir J. 2013 Mar;41(3):716-26. doi: 10.1183/09031936.00073312. Epub 2012 Aug 16. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22903959</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sutherland ER, Martin RJ. Asthma and atypical bacterial infection. Chest. 2007 Dec;132(6):1962-6. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18079229</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Uddin M, Nong G, Ward J, Seumois G, Prince LR, Wilson SJ, Cornelius V, Dent G, Djukanovic R. Prosurvival activity for airway neutrophils in severe asthma. Thorax. 2010 Aug;65(8):684-9. doi: 10.1136/thx.2009.120741.</citation>
    <PMID>20685741</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Simpson JL, Baines KJ, Ryan N, Gibson PG. Neutrophilic asthma is characterised by increased rhinosinusitis with sleep disturbance and GERD. Asian Pac J Allergy Immunol. 2014 Mar;32(1):66-74. doi: 10.12932/AP0322.32.1.2014.</citation>
    <PMID>24641293</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Green BJ, Wiriyachaiporn S, Grainge C, Rogers GB, Kehagia V, Lau L, Carroll MP, Bruce KD, Howarth PH. Potentially pathogenic airway bacteria and neutrophilic inflammation in treatment resistant severe asthma. PLoS One. 2014 Jun 23;9(6):e100645. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0100645. eCollection 2014.</citation>
    <PMID>24955983</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Huang YJ, Nariya S, Harris JM, Lynch SV, Choy DF, Arron JR, Boushey H. The airway microbiome in patients with severe asthma: Associations with disease features and severity. J Allergy Clin Immunol. 2015 Oct;136(4):874-84. doi: 10.1016/j.jaci.2015.05.044. Epub 2015 Jul 26.</citation>
    <PMID>26220531</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Blasi F. Atypical pathogens and respiratory tract infections. Eur Respir J. 2004 Jul;24(1):171-81. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>15293621</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Frehn L, Jansen A, Bennek E, Mandic AD, Temizel I, Tischendorf S, Verdier J, Tacke F, Streetz K, Trautwein C, Sellge G. Distinct patterns of IgG and IgA against food and microbial antigens in serum and feces of patients with inflammatory bowel diseases. PLoS One. 2014 Sep 12;9(9):e106750. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0106750. eCollection 2014.</citation>
    <PMID>25215528</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rogers GB, Carroll MP, Serisier DJ, Hockey PM, Jones G, Bruce KD. characterization of bacterial community diversity in cystic fibrosis lung infections by use of 16s ribosomal DNA terminal restriction fragment length polymorphism profiling. J Clin Microbiol. 2004 Nov;42(11):5176-83.</citation>
    <PMID>15528712</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 23, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 5, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 7, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 5, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 5, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 7, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Asthma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

