<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04263233</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>SIH124_Optional Transition</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04263233</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluation of the Optimal Transition Program</brief_title>
  <official_title>Evaluation of the Optimal Transition Program</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Satellite Healthcare</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Satellite Healthcare</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is an evaluation of a program developed by a team of nephrologists, operations experts
      and researchers. The goal is to provide CKD patients with a better way to transition to life
      on dialysis - one that emphasizes even more individual clinical, psychosocial and lifestyle
      needs. On top of high-quality clinical care, the 4-week Optimal Transition program supports
      patients as they adjust to treatment and learn to live the best life possible. This is done
      through a robust education curriculum and a trust-building approach.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      In this program evaluation the investigators will be reporting on the following program
      outcomes:

        1. Clinical and psychosocial stabilization: to include lab values, clinical dialysis
           parameters, patient-reported symptoms, quality of life, hospitalization and mortality
           rates.

        2. Dialysis modality choice with satisfaction with the modality education and continued
           modality use over 24 months.

        3. Patient knowledge, activation, and satisfaction.

        4. Program parameters such as time, costs, referral rate, admissions and length of stay
           within the program.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 29, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 28, 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Other</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Other</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluation of clinical stabilization through standard clinical dialysis labs</measure>
    <time_frame>On admission, week 4 and day 90</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluation of changes in the Standard of care monthly dialysis labs</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluation of clinical stabilization through standard clinical dialysis blood pressure measurements</measure>
    <time_frame>At week one and week 4.</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluation of any changes in the Pre and post dialysis blood pressures for each patient which are collected as part of the patient's dialysis flow sheet.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluation of clinical stabilization through standard clinical dialysis measurements of Intradialytic blood pressures</measure>
    <time_frame>At week one and week 4.</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluation of any changes in the incidence of Intradialytic hypotension as assessed by review of the patient's dialysis flow sheet.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluation of clinical stabilization through standard clinical dialysis measurements of ultrafiltration</measure>
    <time_frame>At week one, week 4, day 90, day 180 and day 360.</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluation of interval changes in the patient's ultrafiltration rates as measured by the dialysis machine and reported on the patient's dialysis flow sheets.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluation of clinical stabilization through standard clinical dialysis measurements of weight</measure>
    <time_frame>At week one and week 4, and changes between week one and week 4.</time_frame>
    <description>Target weight defined and achieved as measured by standard of care at the unit</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluation of clinical stabilization through standard clinical dialysis measurements</measure>
    <time_frame>At week one and day 90</time_frame>
    <description>Dialysis access type as reported in the dialysis treatment sheets</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluation of clinical stabilization through standard clinical dialysis collection of patient hospitalizations.</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 30, day 90, 6 months and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Hospitalization rates as reported in the standard dialysis record for all patients</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluation of clinical stabilization through standard clinical dialysis records.</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 30, day 90, 6 months and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Mortality rates as reported in the standard dialysis record for all patients</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluation of clinical and psychological stabilization through a quality of life measurement.</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 4</time_frame>
    <description>The EQ-5D tool will be used</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluation of clinical and psychological stabilization through assessment of patient symptoms.</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 1 and Week 4</time_frame>
    <description>The ESAS-r:Renal tool will be used</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Satisfaction with the modality options education</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 1 and Week 4</time_frame>
    <description>Survey of patient experience</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Type of Dialysis Modality chosen by the patient</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 1 and Week 4</time_frame>
    <description>Dialysis modality choice as reported by the patient</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Actual Type of Dialysis Modality used by the patient</measure>
    <time_frame>week 4, month 3, 6, 12, 18 and 24</time_frame>
    <description>Dialysis modality as reported on the standard dialysis treatment sheets</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluation of patient knowledge of dialysis and modalities</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 1, 2, 3, 4</time_frame>
    <description>Weekly focused one on one discussion where the patient is questioned about his/her understanding of dialysis, his/her progress, questions, concerns using a questionnaire developed by the investigator</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluation of patient activation</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 3 and month 3</time_frame>
    <description>Survey measuring patient activation (PAM-13) survey</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluation of patient satisfaction</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 4 or discharge from the program whichever comes first</time_frame>
    <description>Survey of satisfaction with the program</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluation of the program process for time utilization</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 1 through week 4</time_frame>
    <description>Time per patient for visits from program start to completion for each patient</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluation of the program process for cost utilization</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 1 through week 4</time_frame>
    <description>Time, and thus cost, for personnel to complete the program with each patient from entrance to completion or early termination.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluation of the feasibility of the program</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 1 through week 4</time_frame>
    <description>Number of referrals to the program and subsequent number of admissions to the program.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluation of the program efficiency</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 1 through week 4</time_frame>
    <description>Average length of stay for each patient in the program.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">20</enrollment>
  <condition>ESRD</condition>
  <condition>Hemodialysis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Other</arm_group_label>
    <description>This program, which is provided for all patients new to dialysis at the participating units, will be evaluated by assessing patient clinical outcomes and the results of surveys measuring patient-reported symptoms, quality of life, knowledge and activation. In addition, satisfaction with the program will be assessed.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Analysis using descriptive statistics of patient clinical outcomes.</intervention_name>
    <description>Evaluation of the following:
Laboratory values at admission, week 4, and day 90.
Pre and post blood pressure at week one and week 4.
Intradialytic hypotension at week one and week 4.
Ultrafiltration rates at week one, week 4, day 90, day 180, and day 360.
Target weight defined and achievement in week one and week 4 and changes between week one and week 4.
Dialysis access type at week one and day 90.
Hospitalization and mortality rates.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Other</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Surveys with participants using validated survey tools.</intervention_name>
    <description>Surveys will assess participants' Symptom index, Quality of Life, Patient Activation as well as satisfaction with the program.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Other</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Evaluation of the program process including time, costs, referral rates, admission to the program and length of stay.</intervention_name>
    <description>Data will be collected using tracking tools throughout the program.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Other</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        All patients referred by their treating nephrologist to one of the two Satellite Healthcare
        (SHC) participating centers who are new to dialysis and meet the inclusion/exclusion
        criteria.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Referred for incenter hemodialysis at one of two Satellite Healthcare (SHC)
             participating dialysis units

          -  Without significant cognitive impairment;

          -  Able to meaningfully interact with staff; and

          -  Fluent in English (due to education material being limited to English at this time).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Unable to meaningfully interact with staff;

          -  Unable to read and understand English; or

          -  Has significant cognitive impairment per the nephrologist or Principal Investigator
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Wael F Hussein, MBBS</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Satellite Healthcare, Inc.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Jug Atwal</last_name>
    <phone>650-404-3606</phone>
    <email>atwalJ@satellitehealth.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Legg Veronica, M.S.</last_name>
    <phone>650-404-3736</phone>
    <email>leggv@satellitehealth.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Satellite Healthcare Oakland</name>
      <address>
        <city>Oakland</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94609</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Satellite Healthcare Chickasaw Gardens</name>
      <address>
        <city>Memphis</city>
        <state>Tennessee</state>
        <zip>38111</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 5, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 6, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 10, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 7, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 7, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 11, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>ESRD</keyword>
  <keyword>Hemodialysis</keyword>
  <keyword>Education</keyword>
  <keyword>Evaluation</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

