<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04263311</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>19-01192</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04263311</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Scaling Community-Clinical Linage Models to Address Diabetes and Hypertension Disparities in the Southeast United States</brief_title>
  <official_title>Scaling Community-Clinical Linage Models to Address Diabetes and Hypertension Disparities in the Southeast United States</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>NYU Langone Health</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>NYU Langone Health</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to work with primary care physicians and their staff, and with
      community health workers (CHWs) to improve diabetes and hypertension management, health
      behaviors and improve blood pressure for South Asian patients with uncontrolled diabetes and
      hypertension in primary care clinics in Atlanta, Georgia. The CHWs are community members who
      are trained to work with patients to address health needs holistically by providing
      information on wellness, nutrition, stress relief, and blood pressure management in a
      culturally-appropriate and language-appropriate manner.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The study will provide research training, technical assistance, and capacity-building to
      community and clinical sites in Georgia for implementation of culturally tailored,
      evidenced-based CHW programs to improve HTN and diabetes management for South Asians. In
      addition, the use a multi-theoretical framework to test the effectiveness of a CHW-led
      intervention compared to usual care among South Asian individuals with diabetes and
      uncontrolled HTN in Atlanta. The primary outcome is blood pressure control, defined as 130/80
      mmHg. It is hypothesized that, compared to usual care, individuals receiving the CHW
      intervention will be 20% more likely to achieve blood pressure control at 6 months.

      And to apply RE-AIM and CFIR frameworks to delineate factors influencing appropriateness,
      fidelity, adoption, and maintenance of the intervention within clinical and community
      settings to optimize intervention replication.

      In addition, this study will serve as a national information and dissemination resource in
      the adaptation of evidence-based strategies to reduce geographic disparities in HTN and
      diabetes across Asian American groups.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">March 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in BP control</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline Visit, 6 months visits</time_frame>
    <description>The primary outcome will be the proportion of eligible patients at a practice site to achieve BP control (130/80 mmHg) six months following the index office visit. Individuals receiving care during the implementation of the intervention will be more likely achieve BP control six months following the index office visit than individuals receiving care as usual. The primary outcome of interest is the proportion of patients who achieve BP control. this will be measured by the treatment participants and providers surveys.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Hemoglobin A1c (HbA1c)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Change in HbA1c will be measured in participants of CHW intervention versus the control participants. Clinical data will be retrieved from EHR.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in systolic blood pressure (SBP)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Change in SBP will be measured in participants of CHW intervention versus the control participants. Clinical data will be retrieved from EHR.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in diastolic blood pressure (DBP)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Change in DBP will be measured in participants of CHW intervention versus the control participants. Clinical data will be retrieved from EHR.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in body mass index (BMI)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Change in BMI will be measured in participants of CHW intervention versus the control participants. Clinical data will be retrieved from EHR.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Physicians Attitudes Regarding the Integrated Intervention</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline Visit, 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Physician attitudes will be primarily assessed with data from brief surveys collected from the participating clinicians. Survey items with response scales will be designed to capture data on each of the research questions above. For instance, participants may be asked to respond on a five-point scale (from 1=strongly agree to 5=strongly disagree) to the following statement: &quot;CHWs are helpful tome&quot;. The survey data come from a small sample (n=approximately 10) and are only intended to quantify descriptive information and not for extensive statistical analyses. The data will be tabulated and summarized descriptively to assess change in attitudes from baseline to 6 months.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Barriers and Facilitators to Implementation Adoption and Implications for Scalability</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline Visit, 6 months visit, 12 month visit</time_frame>
    <description>At baseline, qualitative interviews of key informants will assess current satisfaction and usage of CHWs and organizational workflows. At follow-up the interviews will assess barriers and facilitators to the implementation and adoption process of the integrated intervention appropriates, fidelity to the interventions and the solicit recommendations for the replication and scalability of the intervention to other sites. Satisfaction and outcomes from the partnership and capacity building process will also be assessed. Audio-recordings and interview transcripts will be stripped of all identifying data. Using a qualitative approach, interview data will be transcribed and analysis will follow &quot;constant comparison&quot; analytic approach. Using &quot;thematic&quot; coding, initial set of codes will be created which will be reviewed by the CAB to ensure they are relevant and complete. The coded transcripts will be analyzed with ATLAS.ti, a qualitative data analysis software.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">162</enrollment>
  <condition>Hypertension</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Community Health Workers (CHW) treatment group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>There will be 81 treatment participants who will receive the Community Health Workers (CHW) intervention. Once recruited and consented, surveys will be administered and collected at baseline and 6 months in person or by a study coordinator within two weeks of completion of the CHW coaching component of the intervention. Participants enrolled in the intervention will receive monthly text and phone call reminders. in addition, multiple sessions will be hosted at varying times/days of the week to accommodate schedules of both working individuals and at-home caretakers. Finally, small incentives will be provided at each session to encourage ongoing attendance, and a cash raffle prize will be distributed at program completion for individuals who attend all five sessions.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>There will be 81 control participants who will be offered the health education sessions as a point of service and not for research purposes</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>CHW</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will undergo 5 group-based health education sessions on hypertension and diabetes management and provide culturally and linguistically tailored health information and resources There will be 2 one-on-one in-person meetings and up to 7 follow-up calls/meetings to engage in goal-setting activities regarding changes to health behaviors, medication adherence, or other issues related to diabetes prevention as identified jointly by patient and CHW. Participants will develop with the CHW and receive a copy of their long-term and short-term Participant Action Plan. Referrals to other services available in the community (i.e. exercise classes, social services, mental health, tobacco cessation, etc.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Community Health Workers (CHW) treatment group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        CHW intervention:

        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  identified as of South Asian ethnicity

          -  are at least 21 years of age and younger than age 75

          -  had an appointment with a physician or mid-level clinician for routine non-emergent
             primary care in the last 12 months

          -  a diagnosis of diabetes

          -  a diagnosis of hypertension

          -  an uncontrolled BP reading (&gt;130/80mmHg) in the last 6 months

        Provider Surveys Inclusion criteria

          -  clinicians employed by the clinic

          -  have enrolled into the study.

        Key Informant Interviews Inclusion criteria

          -  must be a provider, clinic manager, or community health worker.

        CHW intervention

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  under the age of 21 and older than 75

          -  pregnant

          -  Type 1 diabetes or diabetes secondary to other conditions

          -  malignancy or life threatening illness with life expectancy of &lt;5 years

          -  inability to perform unsupervised physical activity

          -  diagnosed cognitive deficits or limited decision-making capacity

        Provider Surveys Inclusion criteria

          -  clinicians who are unable to complete the survey in the English language.

        Key Informant Interviews Inclusion criteria

          -  who are unable to participate in the interview conducted in the English language.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>21 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Nadia Islam</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>NYU Langone</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Jennifer Zanowiak</last_name>
    <phone>(646) 501-3502</phone>
    <email>Jennifer.Zanowiak@nyulangone.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <verification_date>February 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 31, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 7, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 10, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 7, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 7, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 10, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hypertension</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Individual participant data that underlie the results reported in this article, after deidentification (text, tables, figures, and appendices).</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Statistical Analysis Plan (SAP)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>Beginning 9 months and ending 36 months following article publication or as required by a condition of awards and agreements supporting the research.</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>The investigator who proposed to use the data. Researchers who provide a methodologically sound proposal. Upon reasonable request Requests should be directed to laura.wyatt@nyulangone.org. To gain access, data requestors will need to sign a data access agreement.</ipd_access_criteria>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

