<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04261985</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>1R21HD096298-01A1</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>1R21HD096298-01A1</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04261985</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Mobile Phone Based Pilot Intervention to Prevent Obesity in Latino Preschool Children</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Mobile Phone Based Pilot Intervention to Prevent Obesity in Latino Preschool Children</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of California, Los Angeles</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Eunice Kennedy Shriver National Institute of Child Health and Human Development (NICHD)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of California, Los Angeles</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To pilot a stand-alone mobile phone intervention with Latino caregivers of 2- to 5-year olds,
      using a prospective control group design, to assess feasibility and preliminary effect sizes
      on children's BMI changes (primary outcome) and dietary and physical activity changes
      (secondary outcomes) at 6 months post-baseline, in preparation for a larger randomized trial
      to evaluate the intervention's efficacy.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The investigators will pilot an mHealth intervention using a prospective control group design
      with 66 caregiver-child dyads (33 intervention and 33 comparison) recruited from two
      community based agencies in East Los Angeles. Fidelity and feasibility will be assessed. Pre-
      and post- intervention data (child dietary, physical activity, and media viewing behaviors
      and BMI z-scores) will be collected to estimate preliminary effect sizes and standard
      deviations. The mHealth intervention has been informed by a previous feasibility study and
      focus groups with Latino caregivers of 2- to 5-year old children. This mHealth childhood
      obesity intervention specifically targets Latino mothers, fathers, and grandmothers of 2- to
      5-year olds. The intervention focuses on parenting skills, dietary, physical activity, and
      media-viewing behaviors consistent with American Academy of Pediatrics guidelines.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">March 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 1, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 1, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>a prospective control group design</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Health Services Research</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>A research assistant not working on any other aspect of the study, and therefore having no knowledge of whether participants are in the control or intervention group, will measure child and caregiver height and weight. A 2nd research assistant, who is not blinded to participants, will be responsible for making appointments with participants for height and weight measures.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Child BMI (BMI=kg/m2)</measure>
    <time_frame>6-months post intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Child BMI will be calculated using participant weight in Kilograms measured on a digital scale (calibrated with 5kg weight before each measurement) to the nearest 100 grams and height measured to the nearest 0.1cm using a stadiometer</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>caregiver BMI (BMI=kg/m2)</measure>
    <time_frame>6-months post-intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Caregiver BMI will be calculated using participant weight in Kilograms measured on a digital scale (calibrated with 5kg weight before each measurement) to the nearest 100 grams and height measured to the nearest 0.1cm using a stadiometer</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Children's Dietary Behaviors</measure>
    <time_frame>6-months post intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Children's Dietary Questionnaire (29-item instrument) measures a child's average consumption of 4 categories of foods or beverages. The 4 categories are further divided into 4 separate scores: a fruits and vegetables score, a fat from dairy products score, a sweetened beverage score, and a noncore food. Items are measured by participants responding to frequency/counts or using a likert scale. There are cutoffs provided for each score of the 4 categories. Overall, the higher the score in the fruits and vegetable sections the healthier the dietary behavior and the higher the score on dairy from fat and noncore foods the unhealthier the diet.
score</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Child media-viewing behaviors</measure>
    <time_frame>6-months post intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Home Environment Inventory Survey: measures hours of watching TV, DVDs or Computer using two questions with responses including hours spent from three time categories throughout the day. The higher the number of hours reported the unhealthier the media-viewing behavior.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Child physical activity behaviors</measure>
    <time_frame>6-months post intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Outdoor Playtime Checklist : the items on the scale ask two questions with responses from five time interval categories that are coded 0 through 4. The ordered categorical responses and summing the responses across both questions gives a maximum score of 24. The higher the score the more time spent playing outdoors.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">132</enrollment>
  <condition>Childhood Obesity</condition>
  <condition>Parenting</condition>
  <condition>Mobile Phone Use</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Mobile Phone Obesity Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Caregiver-child dyads will be recruited from two early childhood education centers in East Los Angeles. Approximately 30 caregiver-child dyads will be randomized into the intervention arm. Every week for 4 weeks, caregivers will receive 4 interactive multi-media phone prompts to support the intervention's targeted topics. Each mobile phone prompt starts with a 140-character text with an embedded link. Clicking on the link navigates caregivers to a web-based application with interactive content that includes images, text, videos, and prompts. Each week, caregivers will share their goal/s, perceived barriers, questions, tips and strategies that may be helpful to other participants. Each week, caregivers will also receive strategies, and individual and group feedback on changing unhealthy behaviors. The content shared by caregivers are summarized by a team research assistant and sent back to participants at the end of every week.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Caregiver-child dyads will be recruited from two early childhood education centers in East Los Angeles. Approximately 30 caregiver-child dyads will be randomized into the control (no intervention) arm. Every week for 4 weeks, these caregivers will receive 4 interactive multi-media phone prompts around managing common illness in young children (i.e. fever, vomiting, constipation, etc.) Each mobile phone prompt will start with a 140-character text with an embedded link. Clicking on the link navigates caregivers to a web-based application with interactive content that includes images, text, videos, and prompts. Each week, caregivers will share questions and strategies that may be helpful to other participants. Each week, caregivers will also receive tips and group feedback based on group questions. The content shared by caregivers will be summarized by a team research assistant and sent back to participants at the end of every week.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>healthy weight behaviors supported by web-based mobile phone application</intervention_name>
    <description>Chorus is a mobile phone platform that provides texting, a web application, and an online community for mHealth interventions.Content is created using existing templates to insert text, images, pictures, audio, video clips, or any combination of these. Users interface with Chorus by clicking a hyperlink embedded in a text message sent to their phone to then access web-based interactions via prompts and clicks. Content is available in English and Spanish.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Mobile Phone Obesity Intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  adult male or female caregiver

          -  self-identifies as an individual of Latino descent

          -  has a child or grandchild 2-5 years of age (relationship does not have to be
             biological but caregiver is a legal guardian)

          -  lives with or cares for child/grandchild at least 20 hours/week

          -  is fluent in English or Spanish

          -  has the ability to participate in the mHealth intervention (ability determined by
             using a Subject Comprehension and Participation Assessment Tool)

          -  agrees to complete baseline, 1-, and 6-month post-baseline surveys and have adult and
             child height and weight measured.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  child has a failure to thrive diagnosis

          -  medical complications associated with their weight status such as Prader-Willi
             Syndrome
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Alma Guerrero, MD, MPH</last_name>
    <phone>310-267-2789</phone>
    <email>aguerrero@mednet.ucla.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <verification_date>February 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 3, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 5, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 10, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 10, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 10, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 12, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of California, Los Angeles</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Alma Guerrero, MD, MPH</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Clinical Professor of Pediatrics</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Obesity</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pediatric Obesity</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

