<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04268940</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>19-5121</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04268940</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Thrombo-Elastography Guided Management of ECMO</brief_title>
  <acronym>TEGMO</acronym>
  <official_title>Thrombo-Elastography Guided Management of ECMO</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Damian Ratano</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>The PSI Foundation, Ontario</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University Health Network, Toronto</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Anticoagulation and coagulation management during ECMO is a challenge. Bleeding and clotting
      are major sources of morbidity and mortality. The currently used strategies are of poor
      evidence. This observational study wants to evaluate the use of automated thromboelastography
      (TEG 6s) to guide the management of coagulation and anticoagulation in patients supported by
      ECMO
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      ECMO induces both a risk of clotting and bleeding. Therapeutic anticoagulation is recommended
      during ECMO. While preventing clotting, anticoagulation triggers a higher risk of bleeding.
      However, anticoagulation does not completely avoid clotting due to complex interactions
      between the circuit, the patients' blood and the anticoagulant. Unfractionated heparin (UFH)
      is the most commonly used anticoagulant and requires monitoring. No clear recommendation
      exists. The activated partial thromboplastin time (aPTT) as well as the anti-factor Xa
      activity (anti-Xa) are plasma-based tests used to monitor UFH. The evidence for their use is
      poor and they do no correlate well. Moreover, these two tests do not take into account all
      the elements of blood and do not reflect the entire coagulation process.

      Thromboelastography is a whole-blood point-of-care test that describes each phases of the
      clotting process from the activation of coagulation factors to the later lysis to the
      thrombus. TEG is also sensitive to UFH and can be used to quantify its effect. The use of
      heparinase during TEG also permits to evaluate the coagulation process during the use of
      heparin. This could give an important understanding of the effect of the ECMO itself on the
      circuit and help to develop a strategy to prevent bleeding and clotting as well as monitor
      heparin treatment.

      The hypothesis for this study is that the use of thromboelastography will identify situations
      with high risk of bleeding and allow interventions to reduce hemorrhagic events and blood
      products transfusions. It is also hypothesized that the monitoring of unfractionated heparin
      (UFH) with TEG is feasible and could lead to the use of less UFH during the course of ECMO.

      The objectives of this study are 1) to determine and calibrate the TEG R-time values
      corresponding to aPTT therapeutic range for patients under therapeutic UFH during ECMO
      course, 2) to determine the level of correlation of TEG parameters with other anticoagulation
      tests [Prothrombin Time (PT), anti-Xa, activated clotting time (ACT)], fibrinogen level,
      platelets count and d-dimers, 3) to determine the TEG values that are associated with the
      administration of blood-derived coagulation products in clinical practice 4) to identify TEG
      cutoff points that are associated with an increased risk of bleeding/clotting in ECMO
      patients 5) use these observational data to develop a TEG-based algorithm for anticoagulation
      management and blood products replacement that could be tested in a future study.

      This study will you the last version of TEG, TEG-6s which is a fully automated point-of-care
      device.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 3, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 1, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 1, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Correlation between TEG (R-time K-TEG) and aPTT</measure>
    <time_frame>0-10 days</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Correlation of TEG parameters with &quot;classical&quot; coagulation tests</measure>
    <time_frame>0-10 days</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Ability of TEG data to identify patients at higher risk of bleeding (or clotting) during the course of ECMO</measure>
    <time_frame>0-10 days</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Extracorporeal Circulation of Blood; Thrombocytopenia</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Thromboelastography</intervention_name>
    <description>Thromboelastography (TEG 6s, global hemostasis cartridge) will be performed before ECMO insertion and at different time-points during the course of ECMO. In parallel a full coagulation work-up (aPTT, prothrombin time [PT], anti-Xa, activated clotting time[ACT], platelets count, d-dimers, von Willebrand panel and fibrinogen) will be measured simultaneously with each TEG.</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Adult patients suffering from cardiorespiratory failure and needing Extracorporeal Membrane
        Oxygenation
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Consecutive patients admitted in Toronto General Hospital Medical Surgical ICU (MSICU)
             supported with ECMO. Patients cannulated before admission (ECMO retrieval) can also be
             included

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Refusal of consent, unavailability or impossibility to process blood samples before
             ECMO cannulation
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Damian Ratano, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University Health Network, Toronto</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Eddy Fan, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University Health Network, Toronto</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Damian Ratano, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+1416 340 3601</phone>
    <email>damian.ratano@uhn.ca</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Eddy Fan, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+1416 340 3601</phone>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Health Network</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toronto</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>M5G2N2</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Eddy Fan, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+1 416 340 3601</phone>
      <email>eddy.fan@uhn.ca</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Damian Ratano, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+ 416 340 3601</phone>
      <email>damian.ratano@uhn.ca</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://www.elso.org/Portals/0/Files/elsoanticoagulationguideline8-2014-table-contents.pdf</url>
    <description>Extracorporeal life support organisation (ELSO) anticoagulation guidelines</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>https://teg.haemonetics.com/en-gb/teg-6s-hemostasis-analyzer</url>
    <description>TEG 6s description</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sauer CM, Yuh DD, Bonde P. Extracorporeal membrane oxygenation use has increased by 433% in adults in the United States from 2006 to 2011. ASAIO J. 2015 Jan-Feb;61(1):31-6. doi: 10.1097/MAT.0000000000000160.</citation>
    <PMID>25303799</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gorbet MB, Sefton MV. Biomaterial-associated thrombosis: roles of coagulation factors, complement, platelets and leukocytes. Biomaterials. 2004 Nov;25(26):5681-703. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>15147815</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Annich GM. Extracorporeal life support: the precarious balance of hemostasis. J Thromb Haemost. 2015 Jun;13 Suppl 1:S336-42. doi: 10.1111/jth.12963. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26149045</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zangrillo A, Landoni G, Biondi-Zoccai G, Greco M, Greco T, Frati G, Patroniti N, Antonelli M, Pesenti A, Pappalardo F. A meta-analysis of complications and mortality of extracorporeal membrane oxygenation. Crit Care Resusc. 2013 Sep;15(3):172-8. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23944202</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Garcia DA, Baglin TP, Weitz JI, Samama MM. Parenteral anticoagulants: Antithrombotic Therapy and Prevention of Thrombosis, 9th ed: American College of Chest Physicians Evidence-Based Clinical Practice Guidelines. Chest. 2012 Feb;141(2 Suppl):e24S-e43S. doi: 10.1378/chest.11-2291. Review. Erratum in: Chest. 2012 May;141(5):1369. Dosage error in article text. Chest. 2013 Aug;144(2):721. Dosage error in article text.</citation>
    <PMID>22315264</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kreyer S, Muders T, Theuerkauf N, Spitzhüttl J, Schellhaas T, Schewe JC, Guenther U, Wrigge H, Putensen C. Hemorrhage under veno-venous extracorporeal membrane oxygenation in acute respiratory distress syndrome patients: a retrospective data analysis. J Thorac Dis. 2017 Dec;9(12):5017-5029. doi: 10.21037/jtd.2017.11.05.</citation>
    <PMID>29312706</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ratano D, Alberio L, Delodder F, Faouzi M, Berger MM. Agreement between activated partial thromboplastin time and anti-Xa activity in critically ill patients receiving therapeutic unfractionated heparin. Thromb Res. 2019 Mar;175:53-58. doi: 10.1016/j.thromres.2019.01.002. Epub 2019 Jan 7.</citation>
    <PMID>30708169</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Basu D, Gallus A, Hirsh J, Cade J. A prospective study of the value of monitoring heparin treatment with the activated partial thromboplastin time. N Engl J Med. 1972 Aug 17;287(7):324-7.</citation>
    <PMID>5041701</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Levine MN, Hirsh J, Gent M, Turpie AG, Cruickshank M, Weitz J, Anderson D, Johnson M. A randomized trial comparing activated thromboplastin time with heparin assay in patients with acute venous thromboembolism requiring large daily doses of heparin. Arch Intern Med. 1994 Jan 10;154(1):49-56.</citation>
    <PMID>8267489</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Atallah S, Liebl M, Fitousis K, Bostan F, Masud F. Evaluation of the activated clotting time and activated partial thromboplastin time for the monitoring of heparin in adult extracorporeal membrane oxygenation patients. Perfusion. 2014 Sep;29(5):456-61. doi: 10.1177/0267659114524264. Epub 2014 Feb 25.</citation>
    <PMID>24570077</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Panigada M, E Iapichino G, Brioni M, Panarello G, Protti A, Grasselli G, Occhipinti G, Novembrino C, Consonni D, Arcadipane A, Gattinoni L, Pesenti A. Thromboelastography-based anticoagulation management during extracorporeal membrane oxygenation: a safety and feasibility pilot study. Ann Intensive Care. 2018 Jan 16;8(1):7. doi: 10.1186/s13613-017-0352-8.</citation>
    <PMID>29340875</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Henderson N, Sullivan JE, Myers J, Wells T, Calhoun A, Berkenbosch J, Tzanetos DT. Use of Thromboelastography to Predict Thrombotic Complications in Pediatric and Neonatal Extracorporeal Membranous Oxygenation. J Extra Corpor Technol. 2018 Sep;50(3):149-154.</citation>
    <PMID>30250340</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Riley JB, Schears GJ, Nuttall GA, Oliver WC Jr, Ereth MH, Dearani JA. Coagulation Parameter Thresholds Associated with Non-Bleeding in the Eighth Hour of Adult Cardiac Surgical Post-Cardiotomy Extracorporeal Membrane Oxygenation. J Extra Corpor Technol. 2016 Jun;48(2):71-8.</citation>
    <PMID>27578897</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gurbel PA, Bliden KP, Tantry US, Monroe AL, Muresan AA, Brunner NE, Lopez-Espina CG, Delmenico PR, Cohen E, Raviv G, Haugen DL, Ereth MH. First report of the point-of-care TEG: A technical validation study of the TEG-6S system. Platelets. 2016 Nov;27(7):642-649. Epub 2016 Apr 11.</citation>
    <PMID>27809712</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Delmas C, Jacquemin A, Vardon-Bounes F, Georges B, Guerrero F, Hernandez N, Marcheix B, Seguin T, Minville V, Conil JM, Silva S. Anticoagulation Monitoring Under ECMO Support: A Comparative Study Between the Activated Coagulation Time and the Anti-Xa Activity Assay. J Intensive Care Med. 2020 Jul;35(7):679-686. doi: 10.1177/0885066618776937. Epub 2018 May 16.</citation>
    <PMID>29768983</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 11, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 11, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 13, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 3, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 3, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 5, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University Health Network, Toronto</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Damian Ratano</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Unfractionated heparin</keyword>
  <keyword>Extracorporeal Membrane Oxygenation (ECMO)</keyword>
  <keyword>Thromboelastography</keyword>
  <keyword>Anticoagulation monitoring</keyword>
  <keyword>aPTT</keyword>
  <keyword>Anti-factor Xa</keyword>
  <keyword>Point-of-care</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Thrombocytopenia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

