<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04264052</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>19IC5362</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04264052</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Characterisation of Large Airway Collapse During Exercise (LACE)</brief_title>
  <acronym>LACE</acronym>
  <official_title>The Feasibility of Continuous Bronchoscopy During Exercise in Healthy Adults in Assessing Large Airways Collapse</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Imperial College London</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Royal Brompton &amp; Harefield NHS Foundation Trust</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Imperial College London</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The large central airways (i.e. trachea and bronchi) act as a conduit to enable lower airway
      ventilation but also facilitate airway clearance during dynamic manoeuvres, such as coughing.
      It is becoming increasingly well recognised however, that in a significant proportion of
      individuals with chronic airway disease (e.g. chronic obstructive pulmonary disease-COPD or
      chronic asthma) and in those with an elevated body mass index (BMI), that the large airways
      may exhibit a tendency to excessive closure or narrowing. This large airway collapse (LAC)
      can be associated with exertional breathlessness and difficulty clearing airway secretions. A
      variety of terms have been used to describe LAC including excessive dynamic airway collapse
      (EDAC) or if the cartilaginous structures are involved then tracheobronchomalacia (TBM).

      One clear limitation of the current approach to diagnosis is the fact that many of the
      'diagnostic' tests employed, utilise static, supine measures +/- forced manoeuvres. These are
      somewhat physiologically flawed and differ markedly from the reality of the heightened state
      of airflow that develops during exertion. i.e. forced manoeuvres likely induce very different
      turbulent and thoracic pressure changes, in contrast to the hyperpnoea of real-life physical
      activity (i.e. walking or cycling). A current unanswered question is therefore, what happens
      to the large airway dynamic movement of healthy individuals (and ultimately patients) during
      real-life exercise and how does this compare with the measures taken during a forced
      manoeuvre, either during a bronchoscopy or during an imaging study such as CT or MRI scan.

      The key aim of this study is therefore to evaluate and characterise large airway movement in
      a cohort of healthy adults during a real-life exercise challenge and to compare this with
      findings from a dynamic expiratory MRI and MRI during exercise. In order to achieve this, the
      investigators proposes to develop and test the feasibility of an exercise-bronchoscopy
      protocol.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The large central airways (i.e. trachea and bronchi) act as a conduit to enable lower airway
      ventilation but also facilitate airway clearance during dynamic manoeuvres, such as coughing.
      It is becoming increasingly well recognised however, that in a significant proportion of
      individuals with chronic airway disease (e.g. chronic obstructive pulmonary disease or
      chronic asthma) and in those with an elevated body mass index (BMI), that the large airways
      may exhibit a tendency to excessive closure or narrowing. This large airway collapse (LAC)
      can be associated with exertional breathlessness and difficulty clearing airway secretions. A
      variety of terms have been used to describe LAC including excessive dynamic airway collapse
      (EDAC) or if the cartilaginous structures are involved then tracheobronchomalacia (TBM).

      At the current time, there is considerable debate regarding the definition of LAC. Typically
      the 'excessive' collapse underpinning a 'diagnosis' of EDAC is defined as excessive bulging
      of the posterior tracheal membrane into the airway lumen during expiration without associated
      collapse of the cartilaginous rings, however the degree to which the trachea closes, to
      constitute EDAC is debated, with literature varying from &gt;50% to &gt;90%. Moreover, partial
      expiratory airways collapse (up to 50% reduction in airways cross-sectional area) can be
      identified in 70-80% of healthy individuals during dynamic computed tomography (CT).

      One clear limitation of the current approach to diagnosis is the fact that many of the
      'diagnostic' tests employed, utilise static, supine measures +/- forced manoeuvres. These are
      somewhat physiologically flawed and differ markedly from the reality of the heightened state
      of airflow that develops during exertion. i.e. forced manoeuvres likely induce very different
      turbulent and thoracic pressure changes, in contrast to the hyperpnoea of real-life physical
      activity (i.e. walking or cycling). A current unanswered question is therefore, what happens
      to the large airway dynamic movement of healthy individuals (and ultimately patients) during
      real-life exercise and how does this compare with the measures taken during a forced
      manoeuvre, either during a bronchoscopy or during an imaging study such as CT or MRI scan.

      The key aim of this study is therefore to evaluate and characterize large airway movement in
      a cohort of healthy adults during a real-life exercise challenge and to compare this with
      findings from a dynamic expiratory MRI and MRI during exercise. In order to achieve this, the
      investigators propose to develop and test the feasibility of an exercise-bronchoscopy
      protocol.

      As a clinical service, the investigators have extensive experience of evaluating movement of
      the upper airway and larynx during strenuous exercise. The Principal Investigator currently
      performs over 100 continuous laryngoscopy during exercise (CLE) tests per year, whereby a
      small laryngoscope is placed in the upper airway and is secured on a headgear to allow
      visualisation of the laryngeal and subglottic movement during exercise. i.e. whilst a subject
      performs running exercise. This test has an established role in patient evaluation and a
      proven safety record in the assessment of laryngeal closure during exercise. The research
      team has performed approximately 500 CLE tests in the Royal Brompton Hospital, with no
      serious adverse outcome.

      The investigators thus now propose to utilise a similar exercise technique but to advance the
      scope (using a bronchoscope because this is needed to evaluate the lower airways) slightly
      more distally to allow visualisation of the large airways during an exercise challenge.
      Others have also utilised a similar approach. Specifically, a study evaluated military
      personal with symptoms of exertional dyspnoea. As part of this study the research team
      performed dynamic bronchoscopy with real-time observation on a bicycle ergometer.

      Therefore, the investigators recommend the application of a similar approach, termed
      continuous bronchoscopy during exercise (CBE) to evaluate large airway movement during
      exercise and to report the feasibility and tolerability of the technique and to compare
      findings with imaging techniques (i.e. as is often used to diagnose EDAC) using MRI. In this
      initial study however, the investigators propose to study only healthy subjects to assess
      feasibility and provide comparator data for later work. i.e. to use this data to provide
      pilot feasibility work and thus to utilise results to inform and power later work, as
      indicated.

      Study Rationale The investigators hypothesise that exercise bronchoscopy is feasible to
      perform for the investigation of EDAC. It is also hypothesised that findings on dynamic
      static manoeuvres (i.e. when subjects are asked to perform a forced dynamic breath out) with
      both a bronchoscope in situ and also during MRI will exaggerate a tendency to closure and not
      relate to the real-life physiological airway stress encountered during exercise.

      STUDY OBJECTIVES

      The primary objective of this study is to investigate the feasibility and safety of
      continuous bronchoscopy during exercise.

      The following hypothesis will be tested:

        1. Continuous bronchoscopy during exercise is feasible

        2. Continuous bronchoscopy during exercise is well-tolerated

        3. Continuous bronchoscopy during exercise provides stable large airway images; to enable
           reliable assessment of any propensity to large airway collapse.

      Secondary objectives include:

        1. To evaluate the degree of LAC apparent in normal subjects during exercise and to compare
           this with static forced expiratory manoeuvres in MRI and MRI during exercise.

        2. To evaluate the degree of LAC from MRI in normal subjects during forced expiratory
           manoeuvres and during supine MRI cycling.

      To compare findings between modalities (treadmill vs supine cycling) and to compare all
      findings with simple baseline physiological measures, such as lung function.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">February 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Feasibility of continuous bronchoscopy during exercise (CBE): questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Primary outcome will be the feasibility of continuous bronchoscopy during continuous exercise in healthy adults. Feasibility will be assessed via a post CBE tolerability questionnaire.
The post exercise tolerability questionnaire aims to evaluate the upper airways function during exercise and the discomfort that the participant might experience during the test. It consists of 5 questions (Part A) where the score ranges from 1 (strongly disagree) to 5 (strongly agree), and 2 questions (Part B) where the score ranges from 1 (None at all) to 10 (Unbearable amount).
The total score that will confirm the feasibility of CBE should be &lt; 3 or &lt; 5, for Part A and B, respectively.
The questions relate to the tolerability of the CBE test (e.g., Exercise with the camera in place cause discomfort, 1 (strongly agree) to 5 (strongly disagree).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Diagnostic capacity of CBE and MRIE</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>To evaluate the degree of large airway collapse (LAC) apparent in normal subjects via continuous bronchoscopy during exercise (CBE) and to compare this with static forced expiratory manoeuvres in magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) and MRI during exercise (MRIE).
Flexible bronchoscopy and MRI at rest will be performed using dynamic inspiratory and expiratory manoeuvres.
CBE will be performed on a treadmill utilising a linear individualised ramp protocol. Heart rate and electrocardiogram will be monitored throughout the test.
MRIE will be performed on the MRI with and feet will be placed on a cycle ergometer fitted on the MRI (MR Pedal, Lode, Netherlands).
The degree of LAC will be estimated in percentage reduction of the airway lumen in several sites of the trachea and main bronchi. In bronchoscopy the reduction will be classified as 0 to 50% / 50 to 75% / 75 to 100% / 100% airway closure. In MRI LAC will be diagnosed as &gt;50% airway closure.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Comparing dynamic versus physical exertion large airway collapse in CBE and MRIE</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>To estimate the percentage of LAC from MRI in normal subjects during forced expiratory manoeuvres at rest and during exercise for both modalities.
More specifically, the reduction (%) of LAC will be estimated in bronchoscopy at rest and will be compared with CBE to evaluate whether physical exertion can induce the similar response to dynamic expiratory manoeuvres. Similarly, percentage of LAC will be estimated in MRI at rest and compared with MRIE.
Comparisons will be performed using statistical tests (e.g., Paired sample T-tests).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Exploring the diagnostic capacity of different exercise modalities to assess LAC</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>To compare findings between modalities (treadmill vs supine cycling).
The percentages of LAC between CBE and MRIE will be compared (via statistical tests such as t-tests and Pearson's correlation tests.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Airway Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>CBE &amp; MRIE</arm_group_label>
    <description>Forty healthy volunteers split in different age ranges (20-30 years n=10, 30-40 years n=10, 40-50 years n=10 and 50-60 years n=10) will undergo two airway assessments at rest and during exercise. The exercise assessments will be a continuous bronchoscopy during exercise (CBE-1st visit) and magnetic resonance imaging during exercise (MRIE-2nd visit) separated by at least three days to ensure for a sufficient cardiorespiratory and musculoskeletal recovery.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>CBE &amp; MRIE</intervention_name>
    <description>The diagnostic tests will be consisted by two visits.
In the first visit participants will undergo a medical history assessment and they will complete questionnaires related to the lung function (MRC Dyspnoea score, Dyspnoea-12 questionnaire, and Visual Analogue Scale). A spirometry will be performed to assess the lung function. Bronchoscopy will be performed at rest in a semi-supine position (on a reclined bed) and then during exercise on a treadmill.
In the second visit, spirometry and questionnaires will be performed prior to resting and during exercise measurements on a magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) scan.
Rest: Structural imaging of the neck and chest will be performed followed by dynamic imaging of the airways during several inspiratory and expiratory manoeuvres. No IV contrast media will be used.
Exercise: After obtaining the baseline images, the participants will be asked to cycle using a programmable supine ergometer placed on the MRI.</description>
    <arm_group_label>CBE &amp; MRIE</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Subjects will be healthy and ≥ 20 to 60 years old.

        The total sample size will be 40 subjects. 10 for each age group (20-30; 30-40; 40-50;
        50-60 years).
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects will need to be within the age range of 20-60 years old

          -  have no known respiratory disease and normal spirometry

          -  be able to exercise without medical reason for limitation.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects who have a significant comorbidity that prohibit exercise

          -  have had a respiratory infection within the last month

          -  known respiratory disease

          -  current smokers or are pregnant.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>20 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>60 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>James Hull, Dr</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Royal Brompton Hospital-Imperial College London</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>James Hull, Dr</last_name>
    <phone>02073528121</phone>
    <email>j.hull@rbht.nhs.uk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Alexandros Mitropoulos, Dr</last_name>
    <phone>07704440653</phone>
    <email>a.mitropoulos@rbht.nhs.uk</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <verification_date>November 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 19, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 10, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 11, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 10, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 10, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 11, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>excessive dynamic airway collapse</keyword>
  <keyword>tracheobronchomalacia</keyword>
  <keyword>large airways collapse</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Shock</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

