<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04267172</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>270167</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04267172</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Total Hip Replacement Performance &amp; Assessment</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Prospective Randomised Controlled Study Assessing the Impact of Simulation Training in Primary Total Hip Replacement (THR).</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Oxford</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Buckinghamshire Healthcare NHS Trust</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Oxford University Hospitals NHS Trust</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Oxford</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This research study is focused upon assessing and optimising surgeon's performance during,
      and patient outcomes following, primary total hip replacement (THR) surgery. The primary
      research question is to determine if additional simulation training can improve the
      intra-operative performance of surgical trainees (Residents) during a THR, or the outcome of
      patients after their THR. The investigators will aim to define an 'expert' standard in
      performing a primary elective THR, which may be used as a benchmark when assessing surgical
      trainee performance; and also determine if operative surgeon performance metrics during a THR
      are correlated with surgical experience, or patient outcomes.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The surgeon participants in this study will be divided into 2 groups depending upon their
      position and seniority. The 'Expert' group will be composed of Consultant Orthopaedic
      Surgeons and Senior Fellows, and the 'Trainee' group will be composed of Trauma &amp; Orthopaedic
      Specialty Registrars (Residents) on clinical placements in Adult Arthroplasty.

      The intervention to be tested is the simulation-based training and cognitive learning
      package. This will be delivered for 1-2 hours per week over a 4-week period in a supervised
      non-clinical setting to a randomised sub-group of 50% of the Surgical Trainees enrolled into
      this study. Surgeon participants within the Expert/Fellow comparator group will not undergo
      any interventions.

      The outcome measures will be surgeon-specific and patient-specific. These outcome measures
      for the 'Trainee' group will commence following completion of the simulation training (if
      applicable), whereas they can commence immediately following study approval for the 'Expert'
      group. The surgeon-specific outcome measures will be the objective motion-analysis metrics
      generated by validated and extensively used wireless sensors placed on the elbows of surgeons
      under their sterile gowns during the operation; and subjective assessments of surgical
      trainee performance using validated and reliable forms of structured human grading.
      Patient-specific outcome measures will be collected for a pre-determined number of patients
      who have undergone a primary elective THR by any of the surgeon participants in this study.
      All patient participants will be asked to provide their written informed consent for the use
      of their data in this study. The patient-specific outcome measures include: pre- and
      post-operative blood tests and radiograph (X-ray) analysis; the incidence of blood
      transfusions and any other peri-operative complications; the in-patient length of stay; and
      two patient-reported outcome measure (PROMs) questionnaires, namely the Oxford Hip Score
      (OHS) and EQ-5D.

      Statistical analysis will be performed on the data collected, specifically aiming to identify
      any significant differences in either surgeon performance metrics, or patient outcome
      measures between:

        1. The Surgical Trainees who have undertaken additional simulation training versus those
           who have routine training.

        2. The 'Trainee' group and the 'Expert' group. A sub-group analysis may be performed within
           the 'Expert' group also to determine any differences between the Consultants and
           Fellows.

      In summary, this novel research will use validated methodology and routinely collected
      patient outcome measures in order to determine the impact of simulation training on surgical
      trainee performance and patient outcomes following a primary elective THR, and also help to
      benchmark an expert level of performance in this commonly performed and highly effective
      operation. The results of this study will hopefully help in shaping the future of orthopaedic
      surgical training and assessment.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 26, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>The intervention to be tested is the simulation-based training and cognitive learning package. This will be delivered for 1-2 hours per week over a 4-week period in a supervised non-clinical setting to a randomised sub-group of 50% of the Surgical Residents enrolled into this study.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>Consultant assessors will be blinded to the grouping of the Surgical Residents (additional simulation training group, or control group).</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Surgeon participant intra-operative motion analysis</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Total number of surgeon hand movements obtained from elbow worn wireless motion sensors.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Surgeon participant intra-operative timings</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Total time taken by each surgeon participant per step of the total hip replacement.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Surgical Trainee Global Rating Scale (GRS)</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>A subjective human grading assessment of surgical performance rated on a scale of 7-35 with a higher score indicating a better surgical performance.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Objective Structured Assessment of Technical Skills (OSATS)</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>A subjective human grading assessment of surgical performance. Rated on a 5 point scale, with a higher score indicating a more competently performed procedure.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Post-operative patient X-ray</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Post-operative X-ray analysis for component positioning, orientation, and quality of cementing for each patient recruited into this study.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient blood loss.</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Pre- and post-operative full blood counts from each patient participant.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient blood transfusion requirements.</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>The number of units of packed red blood cells transfused for each patient participant (if applicable).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient Hospital length of stay</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Length of stay (total days) for each patient recruited into this study.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Oxford Hip Score</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>A joint-specific patient-reported outcome measure (PROM) to be assessed pre- and post-operatively. This is a 12 item questionnaire scored on a scale of 0-48, with a higher score representing better joint function.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>EQ-5D</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>A general patient-reported outcome measure (PROM) to be assessed pre- and post-operatively. The EQ-5D is comprised of 5 short questions each rated on a scale of 1-5 (25 points in total), with a higher score indicating a higher quality of life, and a visual analogue scale (EQ VAS) from 0-100, with a higher score indicating better health.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Hip Osteoarthritis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Surgical Residents with additional simulation training</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Surgeon participant Group 1a: Interventional group ('StR's'): Trauma &amp; Orthopaedic Specialty Registrars (Surgical Residents) on Arthroplasty clinical placements (n=6-8) receiving additional simulation training.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Surgical Residents with routine training</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Surgeon participant Group 1b: control group (StR's): Trauma &amp; Orthopaedic Specialty Registrars (Surgical Residents) on Arthroplasty clinical placements (n=6-8) receiving routine and normal training.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Orthopaedic Surgeon 'Experts &amp; Fellows'</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Consultant Orthopaedic Surgeons (n=5), and nationally appointed Arthroplasty Fellows (n=8). Surgeon participants within this group will not undergo any interventions.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Surgical simulation training in primary Total Hip Arthroplasty</intervention_name>
    <description>The simulation-based and cognitive learning package will be delivered to a randomised sub-group of 50% of the Surgical Residents recruited into this study. This will be delivered in a supervised non-clinical setting within a dedicated University-owned simulation laboratory over a 4-week period for between 1 to 2 hours per week, over 3 to 4 consecutive but separate six-month placements.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Surgical Residents with additional simulation training</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>No intervention: Surgical Resident Control Group</intervention_name>
    <description>Control Group</description>
    <arm_group_label>Surgical Residents with routine training</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>No Intervention: Consultant and Fellow Comparator Group</intervention_name>
    <description>Comparator Group</description>
    <arm_group_label>Orthopaedic Surgeon 'Experts &amp; Fellows'</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Adult patients diagnosed with primary hip osteoarthritis who have been listed for
             elective primary Total Hip Replacement within the United Kingdoms National Health
             Service.

          -  Total Hip Replacement performed by a surgeon participant as lead surgeon.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with complex hip pathology (e.g. previous trauma, hip dysplasia, infection).

          -  Patients who have had previous surgery on their affected hip.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Botnar Research Centre</name>
      <address>
        <city>Oxford</city>
        <state>Oxfordshire</state>
        <zip>OX3 7HE</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jonathan Rees, MB.BS</last_name>
      <phone>01865737540</phone>
      <email>jjonathan.rees@ndorms.ox.ac.uk</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Daniel Howgate, MBChB</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 7, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 10, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 12, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 23, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 23, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 24, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Osteoarthritis, Hip</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

