<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04261361</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HMRFCBTAD</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04261361</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Cognitive Behavioural Therapy for Adherence and Sub-clinical Depression for Type 2 Diabetes</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized Controlled Trial of Cognitive Behavioural Therapy for Adherence and Sub-clinical Depression (CBT-AD) for Type 2 Diabetes in Hong Kong</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>The Hong Kong Polytechnic University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>The Hong Kong Polytechnic University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Objectives: The aim of the study is evaluate the efficacy of a telephone assisted cognitive
      behavioral therapy for adherence (CBT-AD) in type 2 diabetes.

      Hypothesis: CBT-AD will primarily reduce depressive symptoms and improve glycemic control and
      secondarily, improve adherence and self-care and reduce diabetes-specific distress.

      Design and subjects: This is a prospective randomized two-armed intervention study. One
      hundred sixty eight participants will be recruited from five sites covering the following
      clusters: New Territories East, Kowloon East and Hong Kong West.

      Intervention: The CBT-AC protocol (Safren et al., 2013) will be used in the intervention.
      Specific components include: 1) introducing CBT-AD for behavior change, 2) increasing
      pleasurable activities and mood monitoring, 3) cognitive restructuring, 4) problem-solving in
      self-care and 5) relaxation training. To maximize accessibility, eight sessions will be
      delivered face-to-face in group setting and the other four sessions will be delivered by
      telephone. Three monthly follow-up telephone calls will be made to consolidate treatment
      gains.

      Main outcome measures: Primary outcomes include the Beck Depression Inventory-II (BDI-II) and
      glycemic control. Secondary outcomes include adherence by the Morisky Medication Adherence
      Scale, self-care and diabetes-specific distress,

      Data analysis: Treatment outcomes will be assessed by Repeated Measures ANOVA and also
      Intention to Treat Analysis. Regression models will be used to estimate effect sizes and
      associations among variables.

      Expected results: CBT-AD would significantly reduce depressive symptoms and improve glycemic
      control. With secondary outcomes, CBT-AD will improve adherence and self-care and reduce
      diabetes-specific distress.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      A program based on CBT-AD is tested for patients living with diabetes(DM) and subclinical
      depression. The program includes both face-to-face group sessions and individual telephone
      sessions. The aim of the current study is to evaluate the efficacy of a mixed mode CBT-AD in
      reducing depressive symptoms and enhancing adherence among adults with DM and subclinical
      depression. The intervention program consists of three components: 1) eight weekly sessions
      of face-to-face interventions, 2) four weekly consolidation individual telephone calls and 3)
      three monthly individual follow-up phone calls.

      This is a prospective randomized two-armed intervention study. The CBT-AD intervention will
      be compared with enhanced treatments usual (ETAU) using a single blinded randomized design.
      The intervention will be delivered by qualified health care professional (e.g. clinical
      psychology/ social worker/ nurse counsellor) who have had some training in CBT in the initial
      training.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">December 12, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 1, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 1, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Depressive symptoms</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline through study completion, an average of 24 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The full 21-item version of the Beck Depression Inventory (BDI-II) assesses cognitive, behavioral and somatic symptoms of depression.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Glycemic control</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline through study completion, an average of 24 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Glycated haemoglobin (HbA1c) is used to measure glycemic control</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Medication Adherence: 4-item Morisky Medication Adherence (MMAS-4)</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline through study completion, an average of 24 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The Morisky Medication Adherence Scale consists of 4 &quot;yes/no&quot; questions (MMAS-4), scored 0 and 1 respectively.Total score ranges from 0 to 4, with &quot;4&quot; indicating high adherence; &quot;2-3&quot;, intermediate adherence and &quot;0-1&quot; low adherence to medication use.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The Summary of DM Self-care Activities Questionnaire (SDSCA)</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline through study completion, an average of 24 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The revised 11-item SDSCA assess aspects of diabetes self-management that includes diet, exercise, self-monitoring of blood-glucose, foot care, and smoking in the past 7 days (0-7 points) by self-reported frequency.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>DM-specific distress</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline through study completion, an average of 24 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The DM Distress Scale (DDS) is a 17-item self-administered questionnaire identifying four domains of DM-related distress: emotional burden, physician-related distress, regimen related distress, and interpersonal distress</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">168</enrollment>
  <condition>Type 2 Diabetes</condition>
  <condition>Depression</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>CBT-AD intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Adherence counseling
Psycho-education package
The intervention program consists of three components: 1) eight weekly sessions of face-to-face interventions, 2) four weekly consolidation individual telephone calls and 3) three monthly individual follow-up phone calls.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>enhanced treatments usual (ETAU)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Adherence counseling;
Psycho-education package;
To maintain some control over the contact time, we will give them 4 bi-weekly individual phone calls of about 10 minutes each while the CBT-AD intervention group is having their 8 weeks of face-to-face group sessions.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>CBT-AD intervention</intervention_name>
    <description>8 group CBT-AD sessions and 4 weekly follow-up calls</description>
    <arm_group_label>CBT-AD intervention</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>CBT</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Adherence counseling</intervention_name>
    <description>All participants in both CBT-AD and ETAU groups will have one session of Life-Steps, a stand-alone CBT intervention designed to improve adherence to medical recommendations and individualized DM self-management goals.</description>
    <arm_group_label>CBT-AD intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>enhanced treatments usual (ETAU)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Psycho-education package</intervention_name>
    <description>Printed materials of a DM self-management education program will be delivered to both the CBT-AD and ETAU groups.</description>
    <arm_group_label>CBT-AD intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>enhanced treatments usual (ETAU)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients have to meet the following criteria: 1) aged between 25 to 60 years; 2)
             living with Type 2 DM, 3) community dwelling, 4) independent in their activities of
             daily living as indicated on the Barthel Index and 5) obtained on screening a score of
             5 to 9 on the Patient Health Questionnaire Depression Scale (PHQ-9).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients will be excluded by a clinician/ investigator for major depression within the
             past 6 months, lifetime history of other psychiatric disorder including psychosis,
             schizophrenia ad bipolar affective disorder, serious suicidal risk, alcohol or
             substance abuse and medical illnesses with prognosis of less than 12 months to live
             (as identified by reviewing their medical history), already taking medication or
             receiving psychological intervention for depressive disorders or related symptom,
             bedridden, having memory loss, not being able to understand or communicate in Chinese
             language, or refusing to give consent.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>25 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>60 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Alma Au, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Applied Social Sciences, Hong Kong Polytechnic University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Ceci Chan, Masters</last_name>
    <phone>852 3400 8379</phone>
    <email>wing-sze.cc.chan@polyu.edu.hk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Applied Social Sciences, Hong Kong Polytechnic University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hong Kong</city>
        <country>Hong Kong</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Alma Au, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>85227665504</phone>
      <email>ssalma@polyu.edu.hk</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Institute of Active Ageing</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kowloon</city>
        <country>Hong Kong</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Alma Au, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>852-2766-7746</phone>
      <phone_ext>7746</phone_ext>
      <email>alma.au@polyu.edu.hk</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Hong Kong</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Goldney RD, Phillips PJ, Fisher LJ, Wilson DH. Diabetes, depression, and quality of life: a population study. Diabetes Care. 2004 May;27(5):1066-70.</citation>
    <PMID>15111522</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ali S, Stone MA, Peters JL, Davies MJ, Khunti K. The prevalence of co-morbid depression in adults with Type 2 diabetes: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Diabet Med. 2006 Nov;23(11):1165-73. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>17054590</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gonzalez JS, Shreck E, Psaros C, Safren SA. Distress and type 2 diabetes-treatment adherence: A mediating role for perceived control. Health Psychol. 2015 May;34(5):505-13. doi: 10.1037/hea0000131. Epub 2014 Aug 11.</citation>
    <PMID>25110840</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cully JA, Breland JY, Robertson S, Utech AE, Hundt N, Kunik ME, Petersen NJ, Masozera N, Rao R, Naik AD. Behavioral health coaching for rural veterans with diabetes and depression: a patient randomized effectiveness implementation trial. BMC Health Serv Res. 2014 Apr 28;14:191. doi: 10.1186/1472-6963-14-191.</citation>
    <PMID>24774351</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Glasgow RE, Nelson CC, Strycker LA, King DK. Using RE-AIM metrics to evaluate diabetes self-management support interventions. Am J Prev Med. 2006 Jan;30(1):67-73.</citation>
    <PMID>16414426</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nan H, Au A, Sum R, et al. Effect of family support intervention in diabetic retinopathy with depressive symptoms: a randomized clinical trial in Hong Kong. The 10th International Diabetes Federation-Western Pacific Congress. Suntec Singapore: International Diabetes Federation-Western Pacific Congress, 2014:ABS-1807.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zhang Y, Ting R, Lam M, Lam J, Nan H, Yeung R, Yang W, Ji L, Weng J, Wing YK, Sartorius N, Chan JC. Measuring depressive symptoms using the Patient Health Questionnaire-9 in Hong Kong Chinese subjects with type 2 diabetes. J Affect Disord. 2013 Nov;151(2):660-6. doi: 10.1016/j.jad.2013.07.014. Epub 2013 Jul 31.</citation>
    <PMID>23938133</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ting RZ, Nan H, Yu MW, Kong AP, Ma RC, Wong RY, Loo K, So WY, Chow CC, Ko GT, Wing YK, Chan JC. Diabetes-related distress and physical and psychological health in chinese type 2 diabetic patients. Diabetes Care. 2011 May;34(5):1094-6. doi: 10.2337/dc10-1612. Epub 2011 Mar 11.</citation>
    <PMID>21398526</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Au A, Gallagher-Thompson D, Wong MK, Leung J, Chan WC, Chan CC, Lu HJ, Lai MK, Chan K. Behavioral activation for dementia caregivers: scheduling pleasant events and enhancing communications. Clin Interv Aging. 2015 Mar 26;10:611-9. doi: 10.2147/CIA.S72348. eCollection 2015.</citation>
    <PMID>25848237</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Au, Alma. Developing Volunteer-Assisted Behavioral Activation Teleprograms to Meet the Needs of Chinese Dementia Caregivers. Clinical Gerontologist 38(3): 190-202, 2015.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Katon W, Unützer J, Fan MY, Williams JW Jr, Schoenbaum M, Lin EH, Hunkeler EM. Cost-effectiveness and net benefit of enhanced treatment of depression for older adults with diabetes and depression. Diabetes Care. 2006 Feb;29(2):265-70.</citation>
    <PMID>16443871</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chan BS, Tsang MW, Lee VW, Lee KK. Cost of Type 2 Diabetes mellitus in Hong Kong Chinese. Int J Clin Pharmacol Ther. 2007 Aug;45(8):455-68.</citation>
    <PMID>17725179</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hermanns N, Caputo S, Dzida G, Khunti K, Meneghini LF, Snoek F. Screening, evaluation and management of depression in people with diabetes in primary care. Prim Care Diabetes. 2013 Apr;7(1):1-10. doi: 10.1016/j.pcd.2012.11.002. Epub 2012 Dec 30. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23280258</PMID>
  </reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Safren SA, Gonzalez JS, Wexler DJ, Psaros C, Delahanty LM, Blashill AJ, Margolina AI, Cagliero E. A randomized controlled trial of cognitive behavioral therapy for adherence and depression (CBT-AD) in patients with uncontrolled type 2 diabetes. Diabetes Care. 2014;37(3):625-33. doi: 10.2337/dc13-0816. Epub 2013 Oct 29. Erratum in: Diabetes Care. 2016 Jun;39(6):1065.</citation>
    <PMID>24170758</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>February 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 22, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 6, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 7, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 6, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 6, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 7, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>The Hong Kong Polytechnic University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Dr. Au May-lan Alma</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>telephone follow-up</keyword>
  <keyword>sustainability</keyword>
  <keyword>cognitive behavioural therapy</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus, Type 2</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depression</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

