<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04262219</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>18-1068</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>1R03CA235238-01</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04262219</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Clinician Communication About Sexual Health</brief_title>
  <official_title>Enhancing Clinician Communication About Sexual Health in Breast Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Fox Chase Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Fox Chase Cancer Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The objective of this study is to adapt a previously tested brief intervention aimed at
      enhancing clinicians communication about sexual health (iSHARE) to a mobile web-based
      platform showcasing a two-part podcast and to assess the feasibility, acceptability, and
      preliminary effects of the intervention in breast cancer clinicians.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Specific aims are: 1) To assess the feasibility and acceptability of iSHARE in a mobile
      learning (mLearning) format and 2) To assess the preliminary effects of iSHARE in a mLearning
      format.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 7, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 1, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 1, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Feasibility of the Intervention Trial - Enrollment</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Enrollment will be measured through measures of participant enrollment defined as the percent of eligible candidates approached who enroll in the pilot trial.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Feasibility of the Intervention Trial - Retention</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Study retention will defined as percentage of enrolled participants who complete all study surveys.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Feasibility of the Intervention Trial - Intervention Completion</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month</time_frame>
    <description>Intervention completion will defined as percentage of enrolled participants who complete participation in the podcast intervention.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Acceptability</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week up to 1 month</time_frame>
    <description>Acceptability will be measured through the proportion of the sample endorsing 6 primary acceptability items favorably at two time points (1 week and 1 month; (satisfaction, informativeness, relevance, ease of listening, likelihood to recommend, likelihood to impact practice).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Clinician Knowledge about Sexual Health and Related Communication</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline up to 1 month</time_frame>
    <description>Clinician knowledge about sexual health and communication will be measured using a 10-item scale asking about common sexual problems experienced by breast cancer patients and the most effective ways to communicate with patients about these issues. Knowledge will be reported as the percentage of items answered correctly. Positive mean change scores indicate an increase in knowledge over time.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Clinician Self-Efficacy about Sexual Health Communication</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline up to 1 month</time_frame>
    <description>Clinician self-efficacy about sexual health communication will be measured using a 3-item scale asking about confidence in discussing sexual concerns with patients. Mean scores range from 0-10, with higher scores indicating higher self-efficacy. Positive mean change scores indicate an increase in self-efficacy over time.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Clinician Outcome Expectancies for Sexual Health Communication</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline up to 1 month</time_frame>
    <description>Clinician outcome expectancies for sexual health communication will be measured using a 7-item scale asking about expected positive results in discussing sexual concerns with patients. Mean scores range from 0-10, with higher scores indicating better expected outcomes. Positive mean change scores indicate an increase in outcome expectancies over time.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Clinician Comfort with Communicating about Sexual Health</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline up to 1 month</time_frame>
    <description>Clinician comfort with sexual health communication will be measured using a 7-item scale asking about comfort level in discussing sexual concerns with patients. Mean scores range from 0-10, with higher scores indicating a higher level of comfort. Positive mean change scores indicate an increase in comfort level over time.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Clinician Communication about Sexual Health</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline up to 1 month</time_frame>
    <description>Clinician communication about sexual health will be measured using a 3-item scale asking about recent communication practices around sexual health (initiating conversations, offering information, giving referrals). Mean scores range from 1-5, with higher scores indicating higher amounts of communication. Positive mean change scores indicate an increase in communication behaviors over time.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Breast Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>iShare</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will be asked to listen to a podcast intervention.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>iShare</intervention_name>
    <description>The iShare intervention consists of a two-episode educational podcast series containing information about breast cancer patients' sexual problems, approaches for addressing sexual concerns, and information about discussing sexual concerns with patients, such as initiating a conversation about sexual health and asking questions to assess sexual concern. Both episodes feature expert guests and relevant discussions or case studies.</description>
    <arm_group_label>iShare</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Clinician is a medical oncologist or medical oncology advanced practice clinician
             (Nurse Practitioner, Physician Assistant) who treats breast cancer patients

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Clinician has participated in previous pilot study of the intervention
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Jennifer Reese, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>215-214-3223</phone>
    <email>jennifer.reese@fccc.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Kristen Sorice, BA</last_name>
    <phone>215-214-1433</phone>
    <email>kristen.sorice@fccc.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Fox Chase Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19111</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jennifer B Reese, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>215-214-3223</phone>
      <email>jennifer.reese@fccc.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Kristen Sorice</last_name>
      <phone>215-214-1433</phone>
      <email>kristen.sorice@fccc.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 7, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 7, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 10, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 13, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 13, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 17, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

