<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04268355</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CambridgeHA</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>UH3AT009145</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04268355</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>MINDFUL-PC for Portuguese Speakers Pilot Study 2020</brief_title>
  <official_title>MINDFUL-PC for Portuguese Speakers Pilot #2 Study 2020 (Integrating Mindfulness Into the Patient-Centered Medical Home)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Cambridge Health Alliance</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Center for Complementary and Integrative Health (NCCIH)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Cambridge Health Alliance</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The study evaluates the effects of the Mindfulness Training for Primary Care (MTPC)
      Portuguese-adapted version on heart rate variability during a demanding cognitive task. The
      study also evaluates the effects on mental health, quality of life, self-regulation and
      behavior outcomes. The study will also complete the MTPC cultural adaptation process for
      Brazilian culture.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This single-arm, pre-post, non-randomized, unblinded, pilot trial evaluates the effects of
      Mindfulness Training for Primary Care (MTPC) Portuguese-adapted version on heart rate
      variability during a demanding cognitive task, i.e., Sustained Attention to Response Task
      (SART). Secondary aims are the following: 1) to measure pre/post outcomes for a) mental
      health (anxiety, depression, stress); b) quality of life; c) self-regulation
      (self-compassion, mindfulness, interoceptive awareness, difficulties in emotion regulation);
      and to determine the rate of d) chronic disease self-management action plan initiation; and
      2) to complete the MTPC cultural adaptation for Brazilian culture through a) Satisfaction and
      Suggestions Survey; and b) Interviews of MTPC Group Leaders about their experience teaching
      the program Portuguese-adapted version.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 21, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 30, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 30, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Single-arm, pre-post, non-randomized, unblinded pilot trial including up to 36 participants over 2 MTPC group cohorts</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>High-Frequency power (HF) - Heart Rate Variability (HRV) during Sustained Attention to Response Task (SART) last 5 minutes</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 9</time_frame>
    <description>High-Frequency power (HF) - Heart Rate Variability (HRV) during Sustained Attention to Response Task (SART) last 5 minutes will be measured using Biostamp nPoint速 medical device. During SART participants complete a computerized test measuring sustained attention and response inhibition. They are asked to press a key in response to rapidly displayed integers (1-9) and withhold a response to a designated &quot;no-go&quot; integer.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Root Mean Square of the Successive Differences (RMSSD) - Heart Rate Variability (HRV) during Sustained Attention to Response Task (SART) last 5 minutes</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 9</time_frame>
    <description>Root Mean Square of the Successive Differences (RMSSD) - Heart Rate Variability (HRV) during Sustained Attention to Response Task (SART) last 5 minutes will be measured using Biostamp nPoint速 medical device. During SART participants complete a computerized test measuring sustained attention and response inhibition. They are asked to press a key in response to rapidly displayed integers (1-9) and withhold a response to a designated &quot;no-go&quot; integer.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Perceived Stress Scale (PSS-14)</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 8</time_frame>
    <description>The Perceived Stress Scale (PSS-14) (14 items) measures the degree to which situations in life are stressful. Items are designed to evaluate how overloaded, unpredictable, and uncontrollable one finds one's life. Each item is scored on a 5 point Likert scale from 0 (Never) to 4 (Very often).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient Reported Outcomes Measurement Information System - Anxiety Short Form (PROMIS-ASF)</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 8</time_frame>
    <description>The Patient Reported Outcomes Measurement Information System - Anxiety Short Form 8a (PROMIS-ASF) is an 8-item scale used to assess patient-reported health status for anxiety. PROMIS instruments are funded by the National Institutes of Health (NIH) and used to reliably and validly measure patient-reported outcomes for clinical research and practice. Participants are asked to rate their experience of the item in the past seven days on a 5-point scale from 1 (Never) to 5 (Always).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient Reported Outcomes Measurement Information System - Depression Short Form (PROMIS-DSF)</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 8</time_frame>
    <description>The Patient Reported Outcomes Measurement Information System - Depression Short Form 8a (PROMIS-DSF) is an 8-item scale used to assess patient-reported health status for depression. PROMIS instruments are funded by the National Institutes of Health (NIH) and used to reliably and validly measure patient-reported outcomes for clinical research and practice. Participants are asked to rate their experience of the item in the past seven days on a 5-point scale from 1 (Never) to 5 (Always).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>High-Frequency power (HF) - Heart Rate Variability (HRV) during four 5-minute Sustained Attention to Response Task (SART) time blocks</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 9</time_frame>
    <description>High-Frequency power (HF) - Heart Rate Variability (HRV) during four 5-minute Sustained Attention to Response Task (SART) time blocks will be measured using Biostamp nPoint速 medical device. During SART participants complete a computerized test measuring sustained attention and response inhibition. They are asked to press a key in response to rapidly displayed integers (1-9) and withhold a response to a designated &quot;no-go&quot; integer. Relationship between HF-HRV and SART performance will be evaluated and the effect of over time during the demanding SART task will also be evaluated.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Root Mean Square of the Successive Differences (RMSSD) - Heart Rate Variability (HRV) during four 5-minute Sustained Attention to Response Task (SART) time blocks</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 9</time_frame>
    <description>Root Mean Square of the Successive Differences (RMSSD) - Heart Rate Variability (HRV) during four 5-minute Sustained Attention to Response Task (SART) time blocks will be measured using Biostamp nPoint速 medical device. During SART participants complete a computerized test measuring sustained attention and response inhibition. They are asked to press a key in response to rapidly displayed integers (1-9) and withhold a response to a designated &quot;no-go&quot; integer. Relationship between RMSSD and SART performance will be evaluated and the effect of over time during the demanding SART task will also be evaluated.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Action Plan Initiation Survey (APIS-5)</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 9</time_frame>
    <description>Patient self-reported Action Plan Initiation is based on two-item in the APIS-5 self-report survey in which patients are asked to list their action plan SMART goal, if they met the goal and how much control they had over meeting the goal. The main outcome is a single-item response determining whether they met or did not meet the goal using a 7-point Likert scale (ranging from 1-7) with scores &gt;=5 representing self-reported initiation of the goal.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>World Health Organization Quality of Life- BREF (WHOQOL-BREF)</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 8</time_frame>
    <description>The World Health Organization has developed a quality of life instrument, the WHOQOL, which captures many subjective aspects of quality of life. The WHOQOL-BREF is a WHOQOL shorter version, comprises 26 items that produces scores for four domains related to quality of life: physical health, psychological, social relationships and environment. It also includes one facet on overall quality of life and general health.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Multidimensional Assessment of Interoceptive Awareness (MAIA)</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 8</time_frame>
    <description>The Multidimensional Assessment of Interoceptive Awareness (MAIA) is a 32-item self-report scale designed to assess multiple aspects of interoception and interoceptive awareness. The 6 point Likert scale (ranging from 0-6) assesses 8 aspects of interoceptive awareness: noticing, not-distracting, not-worrying, attention regulation, emotional awareness, self-regulation, body listening, and trusting. Subscales are averaged, and a higher total score represents a better outcome.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Difficulty in Emotion Regulation Scale (DERS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 8</time_frame>
    <description>The Difficulties in Emotion Regulation (DERS) Scale is a 36-item self-report scale designed to assess emotional dysregulation using a 5 point Likert scale. The scale assesses 6 aspects of emotional dysregulation: non-acceptance of emotional responses, difficulties engaging in goal directed behavior, impulse control difficulties, lack of emotional awareness, limited access to emotion regulation strategies, and lack of emotional clarity. Subscales are summed and a lower total score represents a better outcome.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Five Facet Mindfulness Questionnaire (FFMQ)</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 8</time_frame>
    <description>The Five Facet Mindfulness Questionnaire (FFMQ) is a 39-item scale that examines five factors that represent aspects of the current empirical conception of mindfulness. These five facets include: &quot;observing, describing, acting with awareness, non-judging of inner experience, and non-reactivity to inner experience.&quot; Participants rate their degree of agreement with each of the items on a Likert-type scale ranging from 1 (Never or very rarely true) to 5 (Very often or always true), with higher scores indicating higher experience of mindfulness.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Self-Compassion Scale (SCS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 8</time_frame>
    <description>The Self-Compassion Scale is composed by 26 items measuring six components of self-compassion: self-kindness, self-judgment, common humanity, isolation, mindfulness and over-identification.The items are rated on a five-point response scale ranging from 1 (almost never) to 5 (almost always).</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Satisfaction Survey</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 8</time_frame>
    <description>Satisfaction Survey is an 18-item survey contains two parts. First is a series of 12 questions scored on a 5-point Likert scale from 1 (Strongly Disagree/Poor) to 5 (Strongly Agree/Excellent), with statements such as &quot;I found this program helpful.&quot; Next is a series of six open-ended questions in which patients enter a written response to statements including &quot;The most important thing I learned during this program.&quot;</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Suggestions Survey</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 8</time_frame>
    <description>The Suggestions Survey consist of 4 questions focusing on the intervention cultural aspects.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">36</enrollment>
  <condition>Depression</condition>
  <condition>Anxiety Disorders</condition>
  <condition>Stress Related Disorder</condition>
  <condition>Adjustment Disorders</condition>
  <condition>Chronic Illness</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Mindfulness Training for Primary Care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Mindfulness Training for Primary Care (MTPC) is a primary care adaptation that includes core common Mindfulness-Based Intervention (MBI) elements integrated with novel mindfulness-oriented behavior change elements into a format that is adaptable to delivery in primary care health centers</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Mindfulness Training for Primary Care</intervention_name>
    <description>MTPC is a referral-based, insurance-reimbursable 8-week program delivered as group psychotherapy by Patient-Centered Medical Home-integrated behavioral clinicians or as an 8-week primary care group visit delivered by a primary care provider. MTPC groups are 2 hours for 8 weeks with a 7-hour weekend day of silent practice. MTPC emphasizes mindfulness-oriented skills for self-regulation, self-management of chronic illness, and health behavior change. All participants complete an action plan during Week 7. Participants are called every two weeks for the first eight weeks for 5-10 minute engagement calls which focus helping participants cultivate a relationship with study staff, giving participants a place to ask questions, and supporting participants in completing study visits.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Mindfulness Training for Primary Care</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Current CHA patient with an enrolled CHA primary care doctor.

          -  CHA patients 18 years of age and older.

          -  Able to tolerate and participate in interviews and engage in all procedures.

          -  Diagnosis eligible to be covered by insurance for group visits (e.g., anxiety
             disorder, depression, stress disorders including adjustment disorder related to
             chronic illness, pain, insomnia, etc.).

          -  Must be able to fill out the study questionnaires on a computer or compatible mobile
             device.

          -  Must be willing to attend the two computer task sessions.

          -  Able to give written consent in Portuguese

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Any cognitive impairment that precludes informed consent.

          -  Patients who, in the opinion of the Principal Investigator, pose an imminent risk of
             suicide or danger to self or others.

          -  Likelihood of potential incarceration such as a conviction or pending charges that may
             potentially result in imprisonment.

          -  Behaviors that may cause disruption to a mindfulness group.

          -  Patients with symptoms of psychosis, thought disorder, and/or severe mental illness,
             including schizophrenia, schizoaffective, bipolar disorder, or a current severe
             episode of major depressive disorder.

          -  Refusal of insurance to cover group psychotherapy treatment may lead to exclusion from
             participation in groups.

          -  Patients in their third trimester of pregnancy who foresee conflicts that preclude
             their commitment to completing all activities.

          -  Patients with highly unstable medical problems that put them at a high risk of
             hospitalization.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Zev Schuman-Olivier, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Cambridge Health Alliance</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Marcelo Trombka, MD</last_name>
    <phone>617-806-8732</phone>
    <email>mtrombka@challiance.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cambridge Health Alliance</name>
      <address>
        <city>Somerville</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02143</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Marcelo Trombka, MD</last_name>
      <phone>617-806-8732</phone>
      <email>mtrombka@challiance.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Zev Schuman-Olivier, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gawande R, To MN, Pine E, Griswold T, Creedon TB, Brunel A, Lozada A, Loucks EB, Schuman-Olivier Z. Mindfulness Training Enhances Self-Regulation and Facilitates Health Behavior Change for Primary Care Patients: a Randomized Controlled Trial. J Gen Intern Med. 2019 Feb;34(2):293-302. doi: 10.1007/s11606-018-4739-5. Epub 2018 Dec 3.</citation>
    <PMID>30511291</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gawande R, Pine E, Griswold T, Creedon T, Vallejo Z, Rosenbaum E, Lozada A, Schuman-Olivier Z. Insurance-Reimbursable Mindfulness for Safety-Net Primary Care Patients: A Pilot Randomized Controlled Trial. Mindfulness (N Y). 2019 Sep;10(9):1744-1759. doi: 10.1007/s12671-019-01116-8. Epub 2019 Mar 18.</citation>
    <PMID>32042349</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 11, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 11, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 13, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 11, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 11, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 13, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Chronic Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Anxiety Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Adjustment Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

