<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02151682</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>KF5503-66</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2012-004360-22</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>U1111-1154-4572</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02151682</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study to Look at Tapentadol Tablets in Children and Adolescents in Pain</brief_title>
  <official_title>An Open-label Trial, Enrolling Subjects Aged 6 Years to Less Than 18 Years Suffering From Pain Requiring Prolonged Release Opioid Treatment, to Evaluate the Safety and Efficacy of Tapentadol PR Versus Morphine PR, Followed by an Open-label Extension</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Grünenthal GmbH</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Grünenthal GmbH</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Tapentadol has already been studied in adults. This study is needed to find out if tapentadol
      works and is safe to use in children and adolescents with long-term pain.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      During the first 2 weeks of the study (Part 1), participants were given either tapentadol or
      morphine prolonged-release (PR) tablets. Assignment was done randomly (like tossing a coin).
      The participant and the caregiver knew which medication the child was taking. The primary
      endpoint was based on data collected in Part 1 of this study.

      If eligible and willing, participants from Part 1 could enter a 12 month follow-up period
      (Part 2). In Part 2 of this study, participants were either treated with tapentadol PR
      tablets or entered observations arms where they were not treated at all or with standard of
      care.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">April 29, 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">October 15, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">October 18, 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2/Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>There were 2 arms in Part 1: Randomization was carried out in blocks and in a 2:1 ratio (tapentadol PR to morphine PR). Participants were stratified using interactive response technology: by age group (6 years to less than 12 years and 12 years to less than 18 years, at the second visit [Allocation Visit]) so that at least 25% of participants were in the younger age group, and by underlying pain condition (cancer/non-cancer-related pain).
There were 4 arms in Part 2: The investigators/participants decided if participants from Part 1 switched to or continued on tapentadol PR (tapentadol arm) or if they received no treatment/standard of care treatment if needed (2 direct observation arms following treatment in Part 1 and 1 observation arm after initial treatment with tapentadol in Part 2).</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants Classified as Responder (Part 1)</measure>
    <time_frame>From Day 1 up to Day 14 (End of Part 1)</time_frame>
    <description>The proportion of participants classified as responders was assessed and compared between the treatment groups.
A participant was defined as responder if both of the following criteria were met:
Completion of the 14-day Treatment Period (Part 1).
One of the following calculated from the scheduled pain assessments (&quot;pain right now&quot;) documented during the last 3 days of the Treatment Period:
Average pain less than 50 on a visual analog scale (VAS, range 0 [no pain] to 100 [pain as bad as it could be]) for participants aged 12 years to less than 18 years; or less than 5 on the Faces Pain Scale-revised (FPS-R, range 0 [no pain] and 10 [very much pain]) for participants aged 6 years to less than 12 years.
Average reduction from baseline of pain greater than or equal to 20 on a VAS for participants aged 12 years to less than 18 years; or greater than or equal to 2 on the FPS-R for participants aged 6 years to less than 12 years.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Extent of Constipation (Part 1)</measure>
    <time_frame>From Day 1 to Day 14 (End of Part 1)</time_frame>
    <description>Constipation was assessed using the modified constipation assessment scale (mCAS). This is an 8-item questionnaire where the observer has scored constipation on a nominal scale (no Problem [score 0], some problem [score 1] or severe Problem [score 2]). The response to an item could also be scored as &quot;unable to assess&quot;.
The Total Score can vary from 0-16; the higher the Total Score the higher the extent of constipation. A positive change from Day 1 to Day 14 indicates a worsening, a negative change an improvement.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Tolerability Over the Complete Trial Period</measure>
    <time_frame>Part 1: Day 1 (Start of Part 1) to Day 14; Part 2: Day 15 to Day 379 (End of Part 2)</time_frame>
    <description>Tolerability was assessed by the number of participants with exactly 1 to more than 5 treatment emergent adverse events (TEAE) by treatment group during the different trial periods, on a participant level.
In addition, tolerability was assessed by the number of participants with TEAEs which were considered by the investigator to be at least possibly related to the treatment the participant received.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Pain Intensity in the Open-label, Active-controlled Treatment Period (Part 1)</measure>
    <time_frame>From Baseline up to Day 14 (End of Part 1) or early discontinuation</time_frame>
    <description>Pain intensity was assessed by scoring &quot;Pain right now&quot; twice daily up to Day 14 by every participant using the Visual Analog Scale (VAS) as well as the Faces Pain Scale-Revised (FPS-R) in an electronic diary. Pain intensity was first documented using the VAS and directly thereafter the FPS-R. If required, pain intensity diary entry could be assisted by the legal guardian or a health care provider.
The VAS is scored from 0, equivalent to &quot;no pain&quot;, to 100, equivalent to &quot;pain as bad as it could be&quot;.
The FPS-R is a validated self-reported 6-point scale with 0 representing &quot;no pain&quot; and 10 representing &quot;very much pain&quot;. Facial representations were used to indicate how much the pain hurts.
The &quot;pain right now&quot; scores at baseline (last evaluation before starting IMP) and the mean of last 6 assessments collected up to the time point of last IMP intake in Part 1 (i.e., Day 14 or the day of early discontinuation) were used for the calculation of the change in pain intensity from baseline.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Pain Intensity in the Tapentadol Open-label Extension Period (Part 2)</measure>
    <time_frame>From Day 15 to Day 379 (End of Part 2)</time_frame>
    <description>Pain intensity was assessed by scoring &quot;Pain right now&quot; using the Visual Analog Scale (VAS) as well as the Faces Pain Scale-Revised (FPS-R) at each visit. The pain intensity was first documented using the VAS and directly thereafter the FPS-R. If required, pain intensity assessments could be assisted by the legal guardian or a health care provider.
The VAS is scored from 0, equivalent to &quot;no pain&quot;, to 100, equivalent to &quot;pain as bad as it could be&quot;. The FPS-R is a validated self-reported 6-point scale with 0 representing &quot;no pain&quot; and 10 representing &quot;very much pain&quot;. Facial representations were used to indicate how much the pain hurts.
The &quot;pain right now&quot; score at the tapentadol baseline (last evaluation before or at Day 15) and at the last assessment for those subjects who completed the 12 months treatment of Part 2 were used for the calculation of the change in pain intensity from the tapentadol baseline.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Use of Rescue Medication in the Open-Label, Active-controlled Treatment Period (Part 1)</measure>
    <time_frame>From Day 1 up to Day 14 (End of Part 1)</time_frame>
    <description>Due to an overall low intake of rescue medication, it was not appropriate to present the number of doses of oral morphine solution used at different dose levels of investigational medicinal product (IMP) but the average daily dose (milligrams per kilogram body weight) for the treatment period and a modified average daily dose. Average daily dose and modified average daily dose were both calculated based on drug accountability.
For the modified average daily doses, implausible values were excluded from the analysis, i.e., the amount of rescue medication that was lost due to a broken bottle was excluded from the analysis and negative amounts of rescue medication intakes due to measurement inaccuracies for bottle weights were considered as no intake.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Serum Concentrations of Tapentadol (Part 1)</measure>
    <time_frame>From Day 1 to Day 14 (End of Part 1)</time_frame>
    <description>Tapentadol serum concentrations were measured in participants in the tapentadol treatment arm (Part 1).
All participants who had quantifiable serum concentrations during the Treatment Period were included in the descriptive pharmacokinetic analysis. Data from participants who vomited within 6 hours of administration of IMP during the Treatment Period were carefully assessed to decide if the data should be included in the pharmacokinetic analysis.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Serum Concentrations of Tapentadol-O-glucuronide (Part 1)</measure>
    <time_frame>From Day 1 to Day 14 (End of Part1)</time_frame>
    <description>Tapentadol-O-glucuronide is a metabolite of tapentadol. The body transforms tapentadol into its metabolites so that it can be more easily/quickly removed from the body. Tapentadol-O-glucuronide serum concentrations were measured in participants who received tapentadol PR in Part 1.
All participants who had quantifiable serum concentrations were included in the descriptive pharmacokinetic analysis. Data from participants who vomited within 6 hours of administration of IMP during Part 1 were carefully assessed to decide if they should be included in the pharmacokinetic analysis.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Palatability of Study Medication (Part 1, Day 8)</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 8 (Part 1)</time_frame>
    <description>Palatability was determined in Part 1 by asking the participant &quot;How does the medication taste&quot;. The participant was requested to give a score on a 5-point hedonic faces rating scale in combination with a verbal rating. The response can range from really bad to really good.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Palatability of Study Medication (Part 1, Day 14)</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 14 (Part 1)</time_frame>
    <description>Palatability was determined in Part 1 by asking the participant &quot;How does the medication taste&quot;. The participant was requested to give a score on a 5-point hedonic faces rating scale in combination with a verbal rating. The response can range from really bad to really good.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Acceptability of Study Medication (Part 1, Day 8)</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 8 (Part 1)</time_frame>
    <description>Acceptability of the study medication was determined in Part 1 by asking the participant &quot;Swallowing the medication is...&quot;. The participant was requested to give a score on a 5-point hedonic faces rating scale in combination with a verbal rating. The response can range from really difficult to really easy.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Acceptability of Study Medication (Part 1, Day 14)</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 14 (End of Part 1)</time_frame>
    <description>Acceptability of the study medication was determined in Part 1 by asking the participant &quot;Swallowing the medication is...&quot;. The participant was requested to give a score on a 5-point hedonic faces rating scale in combination with a verbal rating. The response can range from really difficult to really easy.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Extent of Constipation (Part 2)</measure>
    <time_frame>From baseline (Day 15 or switch) to last assessment (up to Day 379 of Part 2)</time_frame>
    <description>Constipation was assessed using the modified constipation assessment scale (mCAS). This is an 8-item questionnaire where the observer has scored constipation on a nominal scale (no problem [score 0], some problem [score 1] or severe problem [score 2]). The response to an item could also be scored as &quot;unable to assess&quot;.
The Total Score can vary from 0-16; the higher the Total Score the higher the extent of constipation. A positive change from baseline to last assessment indicates a worsening, a negative change an improvement.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Change From Baseline in Subjective Opiate Withdrawal Scale (SOWS)</measure>
    <time_frame>From Day 1 to Day 386 (End of Part 2 + 7 days)</time_frame>
    <description>Opiate withdrawal symptoms were assessed using the Subjective Opiate Withdrawal Scale (SOWS) questionnaire. The SOWS is designed to reflect common motoric, autonomic, musculoskeletal, and psychic signs and symptoms of opiate withdrawal. Each participant was requested to rate the first 15 items of the 16-item questionnaire for 7 days after last IMP intake. Participants rated the intensity of specific signs and symptoms on a scale of 0 (not at all) to 4 (extremely). The minimum overall score is 0, the maximum score is 64.
SOWS Total Score at baseline (i.e., for Part 1 = Day 14-17, for Part 2 = Day 352-380, or the day after an early termination visit (Part 1/2)), and changes from baseline 2-7 days after last intake of IMP in Part 1 (= up to Day 23) and in Part 2 (= up to Day 386) are presented.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Time to Discontinuation (Lack of Efficacy) in Part 1</measure>
    <time_frame>From first day in Part 1 (Day 1) to last day in Part 1</time_frame>
    <description>The time to discontinuation from IMP due to lack of efficacy was planned to be analyzed for both treatment arms (tapentadol PR and morphine PR) in Part 1 of the trial. However, no participant was reported with early discontinuation from IMP due to lack of efficacy. Consequently, no time to discontinuation can be reported.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Time to Discontinuation (Lack of Efficacy) in Part 2</measure>
    <time_frame>From first day in Part 2 (Day 15) to last day in Part 2 (Day 379)</time_frame>
    <description>The time to discontinuation from IMP due to lack of efficacy was analyzed for tapentadol PR treatment in Part 2 of the trial.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Time to Discontinuation (Treatment Emergent Adverse Events) in Part 1</measure>
    <time_frame>From first day in Part 1 (Day 1) to last day in Part 1 (Day 14)</time_frame>
    <description>The time to discontinuation from IMP due to treatment emergent adverse events (TEAEs) was analyzed for both treatment arms (tapentadol PR and morphine PR) in Part 1 of the study.
Note that no participant discontinued due to a TEAE in the morphine PR arm, and 2 participants in the tapentadol PR arm.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Time to Discontinuation (Treatment Emergent Adverse Events) in Part 2</measure>
    <time_frame>From first day in Part 2 (Day 15) to last day in Part 2 (Day 379)</time_frame>
    <description>The time to discontinuation from IMP due to treatment emergent adverse events (TEAEs) was analyzed for tapentadol PR treatment in Part 2 of the study.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Time to First Intake of Rescue Medication in the Open-label, Active-controlled Treatment Period (Part 1)</measure>
    <time_frame>From Day 1 up to Day 14 (End of Part 1)</time_frame>
    <description>Morphine oral solution could be given during Part 1 as rescue medication in both treatment groups. The dose per rescue medication intake was 1/6 of the total daily dose of the scheduled tapentadol or morphine PR intakes. Rescue medication administration times and doses were recorded.
18 Participants in the morphine PR group and 27 participants in the tapentadol PR group had no documented intake of rescue medication between Day 1 and Day 14.
Summary statistics were calculated based on participants with any intake, i.e., those that took at least 1 dose of rescue medication. The mean (standard deviation) time (hours) to first dose of rescue medication following the first dose of the IMP (on Day 1) is presented.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>6</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">73</enrollment>
  <condition>Pain</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Morphine prolonged-release (Part 1)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>10 milligram (mg) or 30 mg tablets were taken orally twice daily. Starting doses varied from 10 to 40 mg morphine PR twice daily depending on participant's weight; if necessary, doses were gradually increased up to a maximum dose defined per weight group.
The highest dose defined for participants weighing 55 kg and more was 200 mg per day.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Tapentadol prolonged-release (Part 1)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>25 mg or 100 mg tablets were taken orally twice daily. Starting doses varied from 25 to 100 mg tapentadol PR twice daily depending on participant's weight. If necessary, doses were gradually increased up to a maximum dose defined per weight group.
The highest dose defined for participants weighing 55 kg and more was 500 mg per day.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Tapentadol in Part 2 after Tapentadol or Morphine in Part 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants on tapentadol PR in Part 1 of the study continued on the current dose of tapentadol PR in Part 2 and if necessary could modify their tapentadol PR dosage. Participants who were randomized to morphine PR in Part 1 of the study were rotated to tapentadol PR in Part 2 with 70 percent of their current morphine equivalent dose or lower. The dosage could be increased gradually up to approximately 4.5 mg/kg body weight tapentadol PR twice daily.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Observation Period after Tapentadol in Part 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants who completed tapentadol PR in Part 1 of the study or discontinued tapentadol treatment early in Part 1 could continue directly in the observation period in Part 2 for up to 12 months (with standard-of-care treatment if needed).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Observation Period after Morphine in Part 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants who completed morphine PR treatment in Part 1 of the study or discontinued early from morphine treatment in Part 1 could continue directly in the observation period in Part 2 (with standard-of-care treatment if needed).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Observation Period after Tapentadol in Part 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants who completed tapentadol PR or morphine PR treatment in Part 1 of the study could enter the Observation Period for up to 12 months (with standard-of-care treatment if needed) after they had discontinued from tapentadol PR treatment in Part 2.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Tapentadol prolonged release</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Tapentadol in Part 2 after Tapentadol or Morphine in Part 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Tapentadol prolonged-release (Part 1)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Palexia®</other_name>
    <other_name>Nucynta®</other_name>
    <other_name>Yantil®</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Morphine prolonged release</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Morphine prolonged-release (Part 1)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Part 1 - Randomized to open-label, active comparator controlled treatment

        Participants were eligible for the study at enrollment if all the following applied:

          -  Informed consent (if applicable assent) obtained.

          -  Male or female participant at least 6 years of age at the Enrollment Visit and less
             than 18 years of age on Day 14.

          -  Participant has an underlying long-term pain condition (e.g., cancer, chronic disease,
             planned or performed surgery) that is, according to the judgment of the investigator,
             expected to require a twice-daily prolonged release opioid treatment until at least
             the end of the 14-day Treatment Period.

          -  Participant can swallow tablets of appropriate size.

          -  Participant is able to participate in the study as planned and willing to comply with
             the requirements of the protocol including refraining from drinking beverages
             containing alcohol and recreational intake of drugs while on study medication.

        Participants had to satisfy the following criteria before allocation to treatment:

          -  Less than 18 years of age.

          -  No opioid intake or last calculated morphine equivalent dose of less than 3.5 mg/kg
             per day.

          -  Participant has a body weight of at least 17.5 kg.

          -  If a female of childbearing potential (post menarchal and not surgically incapable of
             childbearing) and sexually active, must practice an effective method of birth control
             (e.g., prescription oral contraceptives, contraceptive injections, intrauterine
             device, double barrier method, contraceptive patch) before allocation to study
             medication until the end of intake of study medication.

          -  If a female and post menarchal or older than 12 years, has a negative urine pregnancy
             test on the day before or on the day of allocation to study medication.

        Part 2

        Inclusion criteria for the Tapentadol Open-label extension period:

          -  Participant has completed the 14-day Treatment Period.

          -  Participant is still in need of prolonged release opioid treatment.

          -  Participant does not meet any of the compulsory discontinuation criteria.

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Participants were not eligible for the study if any of the following applied.

        The following was checked at enrollment:

          -  Has been previously enrolled in this study or a previous study with tapentadol.

          -  Has a clinically relevant history of hypersensitivity, allergy, or contraindication to
             morphine or tapentadol or any ingredient, including galactose intolerance (see
             investigator's brochure for tapentadol prolonged-release [PR] and summary of product
             characteristics for morphine PR), or naloxone.

          -  History or current condition of any one of the following:

               -  Seizure disorder or epilepsy.

               -  Serotonin syndrome.

               -  Traumatic or hypoxic brain injury, brain contusion, stroke, transient ischemic
                  attack, intracranial hematoma, posttraumatic amnesia, brain neoplasm, or
                  episode(s) of more than 24 hours duration of unconsciousness.

          -  History or current condition of any one of the following:

               -  Moderate to severe renal or hepatic impairment.

               -  Abnormal pulmonary function or clinically relevant respiratory disease (e.g.,
                  acute or severe bronchial asthma, hypercapnia)

               -  Complex regional pain syndrome.

               -  A pain indication with a strong psycho-somatic component that, in the judgment of
                  the investigator, is unlikely to respond to opioids.

          -  History of alcohol or drug abuse in the investigator's judgment, based on history and
             physical examination. Drugs of abuse detected in urine screen unless explained by
             allowed concomitant medication

          -  Participant has:

               -  A clinically relevant abnormal electrocardiogram.

               -  Signs of pre-excitation syndrome.

               -  Brugada's syndrome.

               -  QT or corrected QT (QTcF, Fridericia) interval greater than 470 ms.

          -  Any surgery scheduled during the first 14 days of the study that is expected to
             require post-surgical intensive care unit (ICU) treatment, or that requires
             post-surgical parenteral pain-treatment, or may, affect the safety of the participant.

          -  Participant is not able to understand and comply with the protocol as appropriate for
             the age of the participant or participant is cognitively impaired in the
             investigator's judgment such that they cannot comply with the protocol.

          -  Participant, parent or the legal representative is an employee of the investigator or
             study site, with direct involvement in the proposed study or other studies under the
             direction of that investigator or study site, or family member of the employees or the
             investigator.

        The following was checked at the enrollment and the allocation visits:

          -  Has a concomitant disease or disorder (e.g., endocrine, metabolic, neurological,
             psychiatric, infection) that in the opinion of the investigator may affect or
             compromise participant safety during the study participation.

          -  Pancreatic/biliary tract disease (e.g., pancreatitis) or paralytic ileus.

          -  Intake of forbidden concomitant medication/use of forbidden therapies (see synopsis
             section Concomitant medications/therapies).

          -  Female participant is breastfeeding a child.

        The following was checked at the allocation to treatment visit:

          -  Has received a drug or used a medical device not approved for human use within 30 days
             prior to visit.

          -  Based on data from the local laboratory, one or more of:

               -  Total serum bilirubin greater than 2.0 mg/dL.

               -  Serum albumin less than 2.8 g/dL.

               -  Aspartate transaminase or alanine transaminase greater than 5 times upper limit
                  of normal.

          -  Based on data from the local laboratory, creatinine clearance less than 30 mL/min per
             1.73 m2 (calculated according to a formula that is appropriate for the respective age
             group).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>6 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>17 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Director Clinical Trials</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Grünenthal GmbH</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>BE001</name>
      <address>
        <city>Leuven</city>
        <zip>3000</zip>
        <country>Belgium</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>BG005</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pleven</city>
        <zip>5800</zip>
        <country>Bulgaria</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>BG004</name>
      <address>
        <city>Plovdiv</city>
        <zip>4001</zip>
        <country>Bulgaria</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>BG001</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sofia</city>
        <zip>1606</zip>
        <country>Bulgaria</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>BG006</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sofia</city>
        <zip>1606</zip>
        <country>Bulgaria</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CL004</name>
      <address>
        <city>Santiago</city>
        <zip>7500996</zip>
        <country>Chile</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CL001</name>
      <address>
        <city>Valparaíso</city>
        <zip>2341131</zip>
        <country>Chile</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>FR008</name>
      <address>
        <city>Amiens</city>
        <zip>80054</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>FR004</name>
      <address>
        <city>Brest</city>
        <zip>29609</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>FR002</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lille</city>
        <zip>59020</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>FR006</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lyon</city>
        <zip>69008</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>FR005</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nice</city>
        <zip>06200</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>FR001</name>
      <address>
        <city>Vandoeuvre les Nancy</city>
        <zip>54500</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>FR003</name>
      <address>
        <city>Villejuif Cedex</city>
        <zip>94805</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>DE001</name>
      <address>
        <city>Homburg</city>
        <zip>66421</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>HU001</name>
      <address>
        <city>Budapest</city>
        <zip>1094</zip>
        <country>Hungary</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>IT003</name>
      <address>
        <city>Turin</city>
        <zip>10126</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>PT001</name>
      <address>
        <city>Braga</city>
        <zip>4710-243</zip>
        <country>Portugal</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>PT002</name>
      <address>
        <city>Porto</city>
        <zip>4200-319</zip>
        <country>Portugal</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>ES003</name>
      <address>
        <city>Valladolid</city>
        <zip>47005</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GB005</name>
      <address>
        <city>Leeds</city>
        <zip>LS1 3EX</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GB003</name>
      <address>
        <city>Manchester</city>
        <zip>M13 9WL</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GB006</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sheffield</city>
        <zip>S10 2TH</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Belgium</country>
    <country>Bulgaria</country>
    <country>Chile</country>
    <country>France</country>
    <country>Germany</country>
    <country>Hungary</country>
    <country>Italy</country>
    <country>Portugal</country>
    <country>Spain</country>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <removed_countries>
    <country>Croatia</country>
    <country>Mexico</country>
    <country>Slovakia</country>
    <country>Slovenia</country>
    <country>Switzerland</country>
  </removed_countries>
  <verification_date>August 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 28, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 29, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 30, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <results_first_submitted>August 23, 2018</results_first_submitted>
  <results_first_submitted_qc>August 1, 2019</results_first_submitted_qc>
  <results_first_posted type="Actual">September 12, 2019</results_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 1, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 1, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">September 12, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>chronic pain</keyword>
  <keyword>opioid</keyword>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Morphine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Tapentadol</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Information available on the Grünenthal Web Site (see URL below for details)</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Statistical Analysis Plan (SAP)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Clinical Study Report (CSR)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_url>http://www.grunenthal.com/r-d-vision-mission/clinical-trials/data-sharing-clinical-trials</ipd_url>
  </patient_data>
  <provided_document_section>
    <provided_document>
      <document_type>Study Protocol</document_type>
      <document_has_protocol>Yes</document_has_protocol>
      <document_has_icf>No</document_has_icf>
      <document_has_sap>No</document_has_sap>
      <document_date>July 27, 2017</document_date>
      <document_url>https://ClinicalTrials.gov/ProvidedDocs/82/NCT02151682/Prot_000.pdf</document_url>
    </provided_document>
    <provided_document>
      <document_type>Statistical Analysis Plan</document_type>
      <document_has_protocol>No</document_has_protocol>
      <document_has_icf>No</document_has_icf>
      <document_has_sap>Yes</document_has_sap>
      <document_date>February 13, 2018</document_date>
      <document_url>https://ClinicalTrials.gov/ProvidedDocs/82/NCT02151682/SAP_001.pdf</document_url>
    </provided_document>
  </provided_document_section>

  <clinical_results>

    <participant_flow>
      <recruitment_details>The first participant was enrolled for Part 1 on 29 April 2015.</recruitment_details>
      <pre_assignment_details>73 participants signed an informed consent form (assented). 1 participant withdrew consent and 2 did not meet in-/exclusion criteria. 70 participants were allocated to investigational medicinal product (IMP). 1 of the allocated participants was not treated, resulting in 69 participants who were dosed in Part 1.</pre_assignment_details>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="P1">
          <title>Morphine Prolonged-release (Part 1)</title>
          <description>10 milligram (mg) or 30 mg tablets were taken orally twice daily. Starting doses varied from 10 to 40 mg morphine PR twice daily depending on participant's weight; if necessary, doses were gradually increased up to a maximum dose defined per weight group.
The highest dose defined for participants weighing 55 kg and more was 200 mg per day.</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="P2">
          <title>Tapentadol Prolonged-release (Part 1)</title>
          <description>25 mg or 100 mg tablets were taken orally twice daily. Starting doses varied from 25 to 100 mg tapentadol PR twice daily depending on participant's weight. If necessary, doses were gradually increased up to a maximum dose defined per weight group.
The highest dose defined for participants weighing 55 kg and more was 500 mg per day.</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="P3">
          <title>Tapentadol in Part 2 After Tapentadol or Morphine in Part 1</title>
          <description>26 Participants on tapentadol PR in Part 1 continued on the current dose of tapentadol PR in Part 2 and if necessary could modify their tapentadol PR dosage. 10 Participants on morphine PR in Part 1 were rotated to tapentadol PR in Part 2 with 70 percent of their current morphine equivalent dose or lower. The dosage could be increased gradually up to approximately 4.5 mg/kg body weight tapentadol PR twice daily.
Treatment with tapentadol was up to 12 months in Part 2.</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="P4">
          <title>Observation Period After Tapentadol in Part 1</title>
          <description>14 Participants who completed tapentadol PR in Part 1 of the study and 4 of 5 participants who discontinued tapentadol treatment early in Part 1 continued directly in the observation period in Part 2 for up to 12 months (with standard-of-care treatment if needed).
One subject who withdrew consent in Part 1 did not enter the observation period.</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="P5">
          <title>Observation Period After Morphine in Part 1</title>
          <description>12 Participants who completed morphine PR treatment in Part 1 of the study and 2 participants who discontinued early from morphine treatment in Part 1 continued directly in the observation period in Part 2 (with standard-of-care treatment if needed).</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="P6">
          <title>Observation Period After Tapentadol in Part 2</title>
          <description>19 Participants who completed tapentadol treatment in Part 1 and discontinued from tapentadol treatment in Part 2 and 7 participants who completed morphine treatment in Part 1 and discontinued from tapentadol in Part 2 entered the Observation Period for up to 12 months (with standard-of-care treatment if needed).</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <period_list>
        <period>
          <title>Part 1: 14 Days Morphine or Tapentadol</title>
          <milestone_list>
            <milestone>
              <title>STARTED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="24"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="45"/>
                <participants group_id="P3" count="0">Group not defined for Part 1.</participants>
                <participants group_id="P4" count="0">Group not defined for Part 1.</participants>
                <participants group_id="P5" count="0">Group not defined for Part 1.</participants>
                <participants group_id="P6" count="0">Group not defined for Part 1.</participants>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>COMPLETED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="22">14-Day treatment and final post-treatment visit completed or tapentadol treatment in Part 2 entered.</participants>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="40">14-Day treatment and final post-treatment visit completed or tapentadol treatment in Part 2 entered.</participants>
                <participants group_id="P3" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P4" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P5" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P6" count="0"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>NOT COMPLETED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="2"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="5"/>
                <participants group_id="P3" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P4" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P5" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P6" count="0"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
          </milestone_list>
          <drop_withdraw_reason_list>
            <drop_withdraw_reason>
              <title>Adverse Event</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="2"/>
                <participants group_id="P3" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P4" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P5" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P6" count="0"/>
              </participants_list>
            </drop_withdraw_reason>
            <drop_withdraw_reason>
              <title>Withdrawal by Subject</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="1"/>
                <participants group_id="P3" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P4" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P5" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P6" count="0"/>
              </participants_list>
            </drop_withdraw_reason>
            <drop_withdraw_reason>
              <title>Technical problems</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="1"/>
                <participants group_id="P3" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P4" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P5" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P6" count="0"/>
              </participants_list>
            </drop_withdraw_reason>
            <drop_withdraw_reason>
              <title>No need for opioid</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="1"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="1"/>
                <participants group_id="P3" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P4" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P5" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P6" count="0"/>
              </participants_list>
            </drop_withdraw_reason>
            <drop_withdraw_reason>
              <title>Missing</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="1"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P3" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P4" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P5" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P6" count="0"/>
              </participants_list>
            </drop_withdraw_reason>
          </drop_withdraw_reason_list>
        </period>
        <period>
          <title>Part 2: Tapent. Extension or Observation</title>
          <milestone_list>
            <milestone>
              <title>STARTED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="0">Group not defined for Part 2.</participants>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="0">Group not defined for Part 2.</participants>
                <participants group_id="P3" count="36">26 Completers on tapentadol PR and 10 completers on morphine PR from Part 1.</participants>
                <participants group_id="P4" count="18">14 Completers and 4 of 5 non-completers on tapentadol in Part 1.</participants>
                <participants group_id="P5" count="14">12 Completers and 2 non-completers from morphine treatment in Part 1.</participants>
                <participants group_id="P6" count="0"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>COMPLETED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P3" count="8">12 Month of tapentadol treatment completed and final visit of Part 2 performed.</participants>
                <participants group_id="P4" count="14"/>
                <participants group_id="P5" count="14"/>
                <participants group_id="P6" count="0"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>NOT COMPLETED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P3" count="28"/>
                <participants group_id="P4" count="4"/>
                <participants group_id="P5" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P6" count="0"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
          </milestone_list>
          <drop_withdraw_reason_list>
            <drop_withdraw_reason>
              <title>Adverse Event</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P3" count="3"/>
                <participants group_id="P4" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P5" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P6" count="0"/>
              </participants_list>
            </drop_withdraw_reason>
            <drop_withdraw_reason>
              <title>Death</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P3" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P4" count="2"/>
                <participants group_id="P5" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P6" count="0"/>
              </participants_list>
            </drop_withdraw_reason>
            <drop_withdraw_reason>
              <title>Withdrawal by Subject</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P3" count="1"/>
                <participants group_id="P4" count="1"/>
                <participants group_id="P5" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P6" count="0"/>
              </participants_list>
            </drop_withdraw_reason>
            <drop_withdraw_reason>
              <title>Lack of Efficacy</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P3" count="3"/>
                <participants group_id="P4" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P5" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P6" count="0"/>
              </participants_list>
            </drop_withdraw_reason>
            <drop_withdraw_reason>
              <title>Protocol Violation</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P3" count="1"/>
                <participants group_id="P4" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P5" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P6" count="0"/>
              </participants_list>
            </drop_withdraw_reason>
            <drop_withdraw_reason>
              <title>No need for opioid</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P3" count="13"/>
                <participants group_id="P4" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P5" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P6" count="0"/>
              </participants_list>
            </drop_withdraw_reason>
            <drop_withdraw_reason>
              <title>Missing</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P3" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P4" count="1"/>
                <participants group_id="P5" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P6" count="0"/>
              </participants_list>
            </drop_withdraw_reason>
            <drop_withdraw_reason>
              <title>Various other</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P3" count="6"/>
                <participants group_id="P4" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P5" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P6" count="0"/>
              </participants_list>
            </drop_withdraw_reason>
            <drop_withdraw_reason>
              <title>Final post-treatment visit not performed</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P3" count="1"/>
                <participants group_id="P4" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P5" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P6" count="0"/>
              </participants_list>
            </drop_withdraw_reason>
          </drop_withdraw_reason_list>
        </period>
        <period>
          <title>Part 2: Observ. Aft. Tapent. Extension</title>
          <milestone_list>
            <milestone>
              <title>STARTED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="0">Group not defined for Part 2.</participants>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="0">Group not defined for Part 2.</participants>
                <participants group_id="P3" count="0">Not applicable for this period.</participants>
                <participants group_id="P4" count="0">Not applicable for this period.</participants>
                <participants group_id="P5" count="0">Not applicable for this period.</participants>
                <participants group_id="P6" count="26">19 tapentadol and 7 morphine completers (Part 1) who discontinued from tapentadol treatm. in Part 2.</participants>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>COMPLETED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P3" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P4" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P5" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P6" count="19"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>NOT COMPLETED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P3" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P4" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P5" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P6" count="7"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
          </milestone_list>
          <drop_withdraw_reason_list>
            <drop_withdraw_reason>
              <title>Withdrawal by Subject</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P3" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P4" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P5" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P6" count="1"/>
              </participants_list>
            </drop_withdraw_reason>
            <drop_withdraw_reason>
              <title>Death</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P3" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P4" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P5" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P6" count="1"/>
              </participants_list>
            </drop_withdraw_reason>
            <drop_withdraw_reason>
              <title>Missing</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P3" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P4" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P5" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P6" count="3"/>
              </participants_list>
            </drop_withdraw_reason>
            <drop_withdraw_reason>
              <title>Various other</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P3" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P4" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P5" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P6" count="2"/>
              </participants_list>
            </drop_withdraw_reason>
          </drop_withdraw_reason_list>
        </period>
      </period_list>
    </participant_flow>

    <baseline>
      <population>Safety Set</population>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="B1">
          <title>Morphine Prolonged-release (Part 1)</title>
          <description>The treatment group comprised 7 participants aged 6 years to less than 12 years and 17 participants aged 12 years to less than 18 years.
Starting doses varied from 10 to 40 milligrams (mg) morphine PR twice daily depending on participant’s weight; if necessary, doses were gradually increased up to a maximum dose defined per weight group.
The highest dose defined for participants weighing 55 kg and more was 200 mg per day.</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="B2">
          <title>Tapentadol Prolonged-release (Part 1)</title>
          <description>The treatment group comprised 12 participants aged 6 years to less than 12 years and 33 participants aged 12 years to less than 18 years.
Starting doses varied from 25 to 100 mg tapentadol PR twice daily depending on participant’s weight. If necessary, doses were gradually increased up to a maximum dose defined per weight group.
The highest dose defined for participants weighing 55 kg and more was 500 mg per day.</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="B3">
          <title>Total</title>
          <description>Total of all reporting groups</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <analyzed_list>
        <analyzed>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <scope>Overall</scope>
          <count_list>
            <count group_id="B1" value="24"/>
            <count group_id="B2" value="45"/>
            <count group_id="B3" value="69"/>
          </count_list>
        </analyzed>
      </analyzed_list>
      <measure_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Age</title>
          <units>years</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>Standard Deviation</dispersion>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>All participants</title>
              <analyzed_list>
                <analyzed>
                  <units>Participants</units>
                  <scope>Class</scope>
                  <count_list>
                    <count group_id="B1" value="24"/>
                    <count group_id="B2" value="45"/>
                    <count group_id="B3" value="69"/>
                  </count_list>
                </analyzed>
              </analyzed_list>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="13.2" spread="2.8"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="13.2" spread="2.8"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="13.2" spread="2.8"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Sex: Female, Male</title>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <param>Count of Participants</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <analyzed_list>
                <analyzed>
                  <units>Participants</units>
                  <scope>Class</scope>
                  <count_list>
                    <count group_id="B1" value="24"/>
                    <count group_id="B2" value="45"/>
                    <count group_id="B3" value="69"/>
                  </count_list>
                </analyzed>
              </analyzed_list>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <title>Female</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="10"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="22"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="32"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Male</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="14"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="23"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="37"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Ethnicity (NIH/OMB)</title>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <param>Count of Participants</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <analyzed_list>
                <analyzed>
                  <units>Participants</units>
                  <scope>Class</scope>
                  <count_list>
                    <count group_id="B1" value="24"/>
                    <count group_id="B2" value="45"/>
                    <count group_id="B3" value="69"/>
                  </count_list>
                </analyzed>
              </analyzed_list>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <title>Hispanic or Latino</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="4"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="7"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="11"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Not Hispanic or Latino</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="20"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="36"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="56"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Unknown or Not Reported</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="2"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="2"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Race (NIH/OMB)</title>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <param>Count of Participants</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <analyzed_list>
                <analyzed>
                  <units>Participants</units>
                  <scope>Class</scope>
                  <count_list>
                    <count group_id="B1" value="24"/>
                    <count group_id="B2" value="45"/>
                    <count group_id="B3" value="69"/>
                  </count_list>
                </analyzed>
              </analyzed_list>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <title>American Indian or Alaska Native</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Asian</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Native Hawaiian or Other Pacific Islander</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="1"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="1"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Black or African American</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>White</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="24"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="44"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="68"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>More than one race</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Unknown or Not Reported</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Age, customized</title>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <param>Count of Participants</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <analyzed_list>
                <analyzed>
                  <units>Participants</units>
                  <scope>Class</scope>
                  <count_list>
                    <count group_id="B1" value="24"/>
                    <count group_id="B2" value="45"/>
                    <count group_id="B3" value="69"/>
                  </count_list>
                </analyzed>
              </analyzed_list>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <title>6 years to less than 12 years</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="7"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="12"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="19"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>12 years to less than 18 years</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="17"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="33"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="50"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Height</title>
          <population>Height is presented by age group.</population>
          <units>centimeters</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>Standard Deviation</dispersion>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>6 years to less than 12 years</title>
              <analyzed_list>
                <analyzed>
                  <units>Participants</units>
                  <scope>Class</scope>
                  <count_list>
                    <count group_id="B1" value="7"/>
                    <count group_id="B2" value="12"/>
                    <count group_id="B3" value="19"/>
                  </count_list>
                </analyzed>
              </analyzed_list>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="138.9" spread="13.4"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="136.0" spread="12.5"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="137.1" spread="12.5"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>12 years to less than 18 years</title>
              <analyzed_list>
                <analyzed>
                  <units>Participants</units>
                  <scope>Class</scope>
                  <count_list>
                    <count group_id="B1" value="17"/>
                    <count group_id="B2" value="33"/>
                    <count group_id="B3" value="50"/>
                  </count_list>
                </analyzed>
              </analyzed_list>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="165.8" spread="11.2"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="162.9" spread="11.3"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="163.9" spread="11.2"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Weight</title>
          <population>Weight is presented by age group.</population>
          <units>kilograms</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>Standard Deviation</dispersion>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>6 years to less than 12 years</title>
              <analyzed_list>
                <analyzed>
                  <units>Participants</units>
                  <scope>Class</scope>
                  <count_list>
                    <count group_id="B1" value="7"/>
                    <count group_id="B2" value="12"/>
                    <count group_id="B3" value="19"/>
                  </count_list>
                </analyzed>
              </analyzed_list>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="34.17" spread="14.08"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="32.37" spread="11.39"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="33.03" spread="12.09"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>12 years to less than 18 years</title>
              <analyzed_list>
                <analyzed>
                  <units>Participants</units>
                  <scope>Class</scope>
                  <count_list>
                    <count group_id="B1" value="17"/>
                    <count group_id="B2" value="33"/>
                    <count group_id="B3" value="50"/>
                  </count_list>
                </analyzed>
              </analyzed_list>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="56.69" spread="9.52"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="56.35" spread="13.92"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="56.47" spread="12.50"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Body Mass Index</title>
          <population>Body Mass Index is presented by age group.</population>
          <units>kg/m^2</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>Standard Deviation</dispersion>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>6 years to less than 12 years</title>
              <analyzed_list>
                <analyzed>
                  <units>Participants</units>
                  <scope>Class</scope>
                  <count_list>
                    <count group_id="B1" value="7"/>
                    <count group_id="B2" value="12"/>
                    <count group_id="B3" value="19"/>
                  </count_list>
                </analyzed>
              </analyzed_list>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="17.28" spread="5.69"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="17.08" spread="3.38"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="17.16" spread="4.22"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>12 years to less than 18 years</title>
              <analyzed_list>
                <analyzed>
                  <units>Participants</units>
                  <scope>Class</scope>
                  <count_list>
                    <count group_id="B1" value="17"/>
                    <count group_id="B2" value="33"/>
                    <count group_id="B3" value="50"/>
                  </count_list>
                </analyzed>
              </analyzed_list>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="20.59" spread="2.98"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="21.15" spread="4.66"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="20.96" spread="4.14"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Pain cause</title>
          <population>As a parameter of special interest, pain cause (cancer-related pain, non-cancer-related pain) was presented by age group.</population>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <param>Count of Participants</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>Cancer-related pain</title>
              <analyzed_list>
                <analyzed>
                  <units>Participants</units>
                  <scope>Class</scope>
                  <count_list>
                    <count group_id="B1" value="5"/>
                    <count group_id="B2" value="9"/>
                    <count group_id="B3" value="14"/>
                  </count_list>
                </analyzed>
              </analyzed_list>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <title>6 years to less than 12 years</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="1"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="1"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>12 years to less than 18 years</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="4"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="9"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="13"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Non-cancer-related pain</title>
              <analyzed_list>
                <analyzed>
                  <units>Participants</units>
                  <scope>Class</scope>
                  <count_list>
                    <count group_id="B1" value="19"/>
                    <count group_id="B2" value="36"/>
                    <count group_id="B3" value="55"/>
                  </count_list>
                </analyzed>
              </analyzed_list>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <title>6 years to less than 12 years</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="6"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="12"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="18"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>12 years to less than 18 years</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="13"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="24"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="37"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Type of pain</title>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <param>Count of Participants</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>Neuropathic</title>
              <analyzed_list>
                <analyzed>
                  <units>Participants</units>
                  <scope>Class</scope>
                  <count_list>
                    <count group_id="B1" value="24"/>
                    <count group_id="B2" value="45"/>
                    <count group_id="B3" value="69"/>
                  </count_list>
                </analyzed>
              </analyzed_list>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="4"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="9"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="13"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Nociceptive/somatic</title>
              <analyzed_list>
                <analyzed>
                  <units>Participants</units>
                  <scope>Class</scope>
                  <count_list>
                    <count group_id="B1" value="24"/>
                    <count group_id="B2" value="45"/>
                    <count group_id="B3" value="69"/>
                  </count_list>
                </analyzed>
              </analyzed_list>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="13"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="28"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="41"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Nociceptive/visceral</title>
              <analyzed_list>
                <analyzed>
                  <units>Participants</units>
                  <scope>Class</scope>
                  <count_list>
                    <count group_id="B1" value="24"/>
                    <count group_id="B2" value="45"/>
                    <count group_id="B3" value="69"/>
                  </count_list>
                </analyzed>
              </analyzed_list>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Neuropathic and nociceptive/somatic</title>
              <analyzed_list>
                <analyzed>
                  <units>Participants</units>
                  <scope>Class</scope>
                  <count_list>
                    <count group_id="B1" value="24"/>
                    <count group_id="B2" value="45"/>
                    <count group_id="B3" value="69"/>
                  </count_list>
                </analyzed>
              </analyzed_list>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="6"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="6"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="12"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Neuropathic and nociceptive/visceral</title>
              <analyzed_list>
                <analyzed>
                  <units>Participants</units>
                  <scope>Class</scope>
                  <count_list>
                    <count group_id="B1" value="24"/>
                    <count group_id="B2" value="45"/>
                    <count group_id="B3" value="69"/>
                  </count_list>
                </analyzed>
              </analyzed_list>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Nociceptive/somatic and nociceptive/visceral</title>
              <analyzed_list>
                <analyzed>
                  <units>Participants</units>
                  <scope>Class</scope>
                  <count_list>
                    <count group_id="B1" value="24"/>
                    <count group_id="B2" value="45"/>
                    <count group_id="B3" value="69"/>
                  </count_list>
                </analyzed>
              </analyzed_list>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="1"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="1"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="2"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>All of the pain types</title>
              <analyzed_list>
                <analyzed>
                  <units>Participants</units>
                  <scope>Class</scope>
                  <count_list>
                    <count group_id="B1" value="24"/>
                    <count group_id="B2" value="45"/>
                    <count group_id="B3" value="69"/>
                  </count_list>
                </analyzed>
              </analyzed_list>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="1"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="1"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Pain intensity (FPS-R)</title>
          <description>Pain intensity was assessed on a revised Faces Pain Scale (FPS-R). The FPS-R is a validated self-reported 6 point scale with 0 representing “no pain” and 10 representing “very much pain”. Facial representations are used to indicate how much the pain hurts.</description>
          <population>FPS-R data at baseline were available for 32 participants on tapentadol PR and for 19 participants on morphine PR (51 of 69 participants overall).</population>
          <units>units on a scale</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>Standard Deviation</dispersion>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>6 years to less than 12 years</title>
              <analyzed_list>
                <analyzed>
                  <units>Participants</units>
                  <scope>Class</scope>
                  <count_list>
                    <count group_id="B1" value="6"/>
                    <count group_id="B2" value="10"/>
                    <count group_id="B3" value="16"/>
                  </count_list>
                </analyzed>
              </analyzed_list>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="6.7" spread="2.1"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="5.8" spread="3.6"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="6.1" spread="3.1"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>12 years to less than 18 years</title>
              <analyzed_list>
                <analyzed>
                  <units>Participants</units>
                  <scope>Class</scope>
                  <count_list>
                    <count group_id="B1" value="13"/>
                    <count group_id="B2" value="22"/>
                    <count group_id="B3" value="35"/>
                  </count_list>
                </analyzed>
              </analyzed_list>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="3.1" spread="2.7"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="4.0" spread="3.1"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="3.7" spread="2.9"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Pain intensity (VAS)</title>
          <description>Participants were asked to indicate the current level of pain intensity at the time of assessment on a validated vertical Visual Analog Scale (VAS). It was scored such that a score of 0 was equivalent to “no pain” and a score of 100 was equivalent to “pain as bad as it could be”.</description>
          <population>VAS data at baseline were available for 32 participants on tapentadol PR and for 19 participants on morphine PR (51 of 69 participants overall).</population>
          <units>units on a scale</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>Standard Deviation</dispersion>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>6 years to less than 12 years</title>
              <analyzed_list>
                <analyzed>
                  <units>Participants</units>
                  <scope>Class</scope>
                  <count_list>
                    <count group_id="B1" value="6"/>
                    <count group_id="B2" value="10"/>
                    <count group_id="B3" value="16"/>
                  </count_list>
                </analyzed>
              </analyzed_list>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="75.3" spread="14.6"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="59.1" spread="32.8"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="65.2" spread="28.0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>12 years to less than 18 years</title>
              <analyzed_list>
                <analyzed>
                  <units>Participants</units>
                  <scope>Class</scope>
                  <count_list>
                    <count group_id="B1" value="13"/>
                    <count group_id="B2" value="22"/>
                    <count group_id="B3" value="35"/>
                  </count_list>
                </analyzed>
              </analyzed_list>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="39.5" spread="32.4"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="42.7" spread="31.6"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="41.5" spread="31.5"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Region of Enrollment</title>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <param>Count of Participants</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>Hungary</title>
              <analyzed_list>
                <analyzed>
                  <units>Participants</units>
                  <scope>Class</scope>
                  <count_list>
                    <count group_id="B1" value="24"/>
                    <count group_id="B2" value="45"/>
                    <count group_id="B3" value="69"/>
                  </count_list>
                </analyzed>
              </analyzed_list>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="1"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="1"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Italy</title>
              <analyzed_list>
                <analyzed>
                  <units>Participants</units>
                  <scope>Class</scope>
                  <count_list>
                    <count group_id="B1" value="24"/>
                    <count group_id="B2" value="45"/>
                    <count group_id="B3" value="69"/>
                  </count_list>
                </analyzed>
              </analyzed_list>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="3"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="3"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Portugal</title>
              <analyzed_list>
                <analyzed>
                  <units>Participants</units>
                  <scope>Class</scope>
                  <count_list>
                    <count group_id="B1" value="24"/>
                    <count group_id="B2" value="45"/>
                    <count group_id="B3" value="69"/>
                  </count_list>
                </analyzed>
              </analyzed_list>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="4"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="3"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="7"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Spain</title>
              <analyzed_list>
                <analyzed>
                  <units>Participants</units>
                  <scope>Class</scope>
                  <count_list>
                    <count group_id="B1" value="24"/>
                    <count group_id="B2" value="45"/>
                    <count group_id="B3" value="69"/>
                  </count_list>
                </analyzed>
              </analyzed_list>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="1"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="1"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="2"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>United Kingdom</title>
              <analyzed_list>
                <analyzed>
                  <units>Participants</units>
                  <scope>Class</scope>
                  <count_list>
                    <count group_id="B1" value="24"/>
                    <count group_id="B2" value="45"/>
                    <count group_id="B3" value="69"/>
                  </count_list>
                </analyzed>
              </analyzed_list>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="1"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="7"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="8"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Chile</title>
              <analyzed_list>
                <analyzed>
                  <units>Participants</units>
                  <scope>Class</scope>
                  <count_list>
                    <count group_id="B1" value="24"/>
                    <count group_id="B2" value="45"/>
                    <count group_id="B3" value="69"/>
                  </count_list>
                </analyzed>
              </analyzed_list>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="3"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="4"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="7"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>France</title>
              <analyzed_list>
                <analyzed>
                  <units>Participants</units>
                  <scope>Class</scope>
                  <count_list>
                    <count group_id="B1" value="24"/>
                    <count group_id="B2" value="45"/>
                    <count group_id="B3" value="69"/>
                  </count_list>
                </analyzed>
              </analyzed_list>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="5"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="9"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="14"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Germany</title>
              <analyzed_list>
                <analyzed>
                  <units>Participants</units>
                  <scope>Class</scope>
                  <count_list>
                    <count group_id="B1" value="24"/>
                    <count group_id="B2" value="45"/>
                    <count group_id="B3" value="69"/>
                  </count_list>
                </analyzed>
              </analyzed_list>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="4"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="5"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="9"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Belgium</title>
              <analyzed_list>
                <analyzed>
                  <units>Participants</units>
                  <scope>Class</scope>
                  <count_list>
                    <count group_id="B1" value="24"/>
                    <count group_id="B2" value="45"/>
                    <count group_id="B3" value="69"/>
                  </count_list>
                </analyzed>
              </analyzed_list>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="1"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="1"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Bulgaria</title>
              <analyzed_list>
                <analyzed>
                  <units>Participants</units>
                  <scope>Class</scope>
                  <count_list>
                    <count group_id="B1" value="24"/>
                    <count group_id="B2" value="45"/>
                    <count group_id="B3" value="69"/>
                  </count_list>
                </analyzed>
              </analyzed_list>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="6"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="11"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="17"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </measure_list>
    </baseline>

    <outcome_list>
      <outcome>
        <type>Primary</type>
        <title>Number of Participants Classified as Responder (Part 1)</title>
        <description>The proportion of participants classified as responders was assessed and compared between the treatment groups.
A participant was defined as responder if both of the following criteria were met:
Completion of the 14-day Treatment Period (Part 1).
One of the following calculated from the scheduled pain assessments (&quot;pain right now&quot;) documented during the last 3 days of the Treatment Period:
Average pain less than 50 on a visual analog scale (VAS, range 0 [no pain] to 100 [pain as bad as it could be]) for participants aged 12 years to less than 18 years; or less than 5 on the Faces Pain Scale-revised (FPS-R, range 0 [no pain] and 10 [very much pain]) for participants aged 6 years to less than 12 years.
Average reduction from baseline of pain greater than or equal to 20 on a VAS for participants aged 12 years to less than 18 years; or greater than or equal to 2 on the FPS-R for participants aged 6 years to less than 12 years.</description>
        <time_frame>From Day 1 up to Day 14 (End of Part 1)</time_frame>
        <population>Full Analysis Set; missing pain assessments (last 3 days) were imputed using multiple imputation.</population>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Morphine Prolonged-release (Part 1)</title>
            <description>The treatment group comprised 7 participants aged 6 years to less than 12 years and 17 participants aged 12 years to less than 18 years. Starting doses varied from 10 to 40 milligrams (mg) morphine PR twice daily depending on participant’s weight; if necessary, doses were gradually increased up to a maximum dose defined per weight group.
The highest dose defined for participants weighing 55 kg and more was 200 mg per day.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>Tapentadol Prolonged-release (Part 1)</title>
            <description>The treatment group comprised 12 participants aged 6 years to less than 12 years and 33 participants aged 12 years to less than 18 years. Participants starting doses varied from 25 to 100 mg tapentadol PR twice daily depending on participant’s weight. If necessary, doses were gradually increased up to a maximum dose defined per weight group.
The highest dose defined for participants weighing 55 kg and more was 500 mg per day.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Number of Participants Classified as Responder (Part 1)</title>
          <description>The proportion of participants classified as responders was assessed and compared between the treatment groups.
A participant was defined as responder if both of the following criteria were met:
Completion of the 14-day Treatment Period (Part 1).
One of the following calculated from the scheduled pain assessments (&quot;pain right now&quot;) documented during the last 3 days of the Treatment Period:
Average pain less than 50 on a visual analog scale (VAS, range 0 [no pain] to 100 [pain as bad as it could be]) for participants aged 12 years to less than 18 years; or less than 5 on the Faces Pain Scale-revised (FPS-R, range 0 [no pain] and 10 [very much pain]) for participants aged 6 years to less than 12 years.
Average reduction from baseline of pain greater than or equal to 20 on a VAS for participants aged 12 years to less than 18 years; or greater than or equal to 2 on the FPS-R for participants aged 6 years to less than 12 years.</description>
          <population>Full Analysis Set; missing pain assessments (last 3 days) were imputed using multiple imputation.</population>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <param>Count of Participants</param>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="24"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="45"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="19"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="32"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <analysis_list>
          <analysis>
            <group_id_list>
              <group_id>O1</group_id>
              <group_id>O2</group_id>
            </group_id_list>
            <non_inferiority_type>Non-Inferiority</non_inferiority_type>
            <non_inferiority_desc>A logistic regression model was fitted to the response using baseline pain, age group, treatment, and underlying pain condition as explanatory variables, followed by a Farrington-Manning test for non-inferiority, based on Full Analysis Set.</non_inferiority_desc>
            <p_value>0.0790</p_value>
            <p_value_desc>The p-value is based on Farrington-Manning variance estimator using a pre-specified non-inferiority margin of -0.2. A 1-sided alpha of 0.1 was used. A p-value &lt;0.1 represents non-inferiority.</p_value_desc>
            <method>Farrington-Manning test</method>
            <method_desc>Non-inferiority of tapentadol prolonged-release versus morphine prolonged-release has been demonstrated.</method_desc>
            <param_type>Risk Difference (RD)</param_type>
            <param_value>-0.06</param_value>
            <ci_percent>80</ci_percent>
            <ci_n_sides>2-Sided</ci_n_sides>
            <ci_lower_limit>-0.19</ci_lower_limit>
            <ci_upper_limit>0.06</ci_upper_limit>
            <estimate_desc>A confidence interval for the risk difference (RD) completely above the pre-specified non-inferiority margin of -0.2 represents non-inferiority of tapentadol prolonged-release versus morphine prolonged-release.</estimate_desc>
          </analysis>
        </analysis_list>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Secondary</type>
        <title>Extent of Constipation (Part 1)</title>
        <description>Constipation was assessed using the modified constipation assessment scale (mCAS). This is an 8-item questionnaire where the observer has scored constipation on a nominal scale (no Problem [score 0], some problem [score 1] or severe Problem [score 2]). The response to an item could also be scored as &quot;unable to assess&quot;.
The Total Score can vary from 0-16; the higher the Total Score the higher the extent of constipation. A positive change from Day 1 to Day 14 indicates a worsening, a negative change an improvement.</description>
        <time_frame>From Day 1 to Day 14 (End of Part 1)</time_frame>
        <population>Safety Set</population>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Morphine Prolonged-release (Part 1)</title>
            <description>The treatment group comprised 7 participants aged 6 years to less than 12 years and 17 participants aged 12 years to less than 18 years. Starting doses varied from 10 to 40 milligrams (mg) morphine PR twice daily depending on participant's weight; if necessary, doses were gradually increased up to a maximum dose defined per weight group.
The highest dose defined for participants weighing 55 kg and more was 200 mg per day.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>Tapentadol Prolonged-release (Part 1)</title>
            <description>The treatment group comprised 12 participants aged 6 years to less than 12 years and 33 participants aged 12 years to less than 18 years. Participants starting doses varied from 25 to 100 mg tapentadol PR twice daily depending on participant's weight. If necessary, doses were gradually increased up to a maximum dose defined per weight group.
The highest dose defined for participants weighing 55 kg and more was 500 mg per day.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Extent of Constipation (Part 1)</title>
          <description>Constipation was assessed using the modified constipation assessment scale (mCAS). This is an 8-item questionnaire where the observer has scored constipation on a nominal scale (no Problem [score 0], some problem [score 1] or severe Problem [score 2]). The response to an item could also be scored as &quot;unable to assess&quot;.
The Total Score can vary from 0-16; the higher the Total Score the higher the extent of constipation. A positive change from Day 1 to Day 14 indicates a worsening, a negative change an improvement.</description>
          <population>Safety Set</population>
          <units>score on a scale</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>Standard Deviation</dispersion>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="24"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="45"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>Day 1</title>
              <analyzed_list>
                <analyzed>
                  <units>Participants</units>
                  <scope>Class</scope>
                  <count_list>
                    <count group_id="O1" value="23"/>
                    <count group_id="O2" value="40"/>
                  </count_list>
                </analyzed>
              </analyzed_list>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="2.7" spread="3.0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="1.5" spread="1.4"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Day 14</title>
              <analyzed_list>
                <analyzed>
                  <units>Participants</units>
                  <scope>Class</scope>
                  <count_list>
                    <count group_id="O1" value="24"/>
                    <count group_id="O2" value="41"/>
                  </count_list>
                </analyzed>
              </analyzed_list>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="2.7" spread="2.4"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="1.8" spread="2.0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Change from Day 1</title>
              <analyzed_list>
                <analyzed>
                  <units>Participants</units>
                  <scope>Class</scope>
                  <count_list>
                    <count group_id="O1" value="23"/>
                    <count group_id="O2" value="39"/>
                  </count_list>
                </analyzed>
              </analyzed_list>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="-0.1" spread="1.6"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="0.4" spread="2.4"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Secondary</type>
        <title>Tolerability Over the Complete Trial Period</title>
        <description>Tolerability was assessed by the number of participants with exactly 1 to more than 5 treatment emergent adverse events (TEAE) by treatment group during the different trial periods, on a participant level.
In addition, tolerability was assessed by the number of participants with TEAEs which were considered by the investigator to be at least possibly related to the treatment the participant received.</description>
        <time_frame>Part 1: Day 1 (Start of Part 1) to Day 14; Part 2: Day 15 to Day 379 (End of Part 2)</time_frame>
        <population>Safety Set</population>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Morphine Prolonged-release (Part 1)</title>
            <description>The treatment group comprised 7 participants aged 6 years to less than 12 years and 17 participants aged 12 years to less than 18 years. Starting doses varied from 10 to 40 milligrams (mg) morphine PR twice daily depending on participant's weight; if necessary, doses were gradually increased up to a maximum dose defined per weight group.
The highest dose defined for participants weighing 55 kg and more was 200 mg per day.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>Tapentadol Prolonged-release (Part 1)</title>
            <description>The treatment group comprised 12 participants aged 6 years to less than 12 years and 33 participants aged 12 years to less than 18 years. Participants starting doses varied from 25 to 100 mg tapentadol PR twice daily depending on participant's weight. If necessary, doses were gradually increased up to a maximum dose defined per weight group.
The highest dose defined for participants weighing 55 kg and more was 500 mg per day.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O3">
            <title>Tapentadol Prolonged-release (Part 2)</title>
            <description>36 Participants who completed Part 1 of the trial (26 on tapentadol PR and 10 participants on morphine PR) continued treatment or switched to treatment with tapentadol PR for up to 12 months in Part 2.
Participants on tapentadol PR in Part 1 continued on the current dose of tapentadol PR in Part 2 and if necessary could modify their tapentadol PR dosage. Participants on morphine PR in Part 1 were rotated to tapentadol PR in Part 2 with 70 percent of their current morphine equivalent dose or lower. The dosage could be increased gradually up to approximately 4.5 mg/kg body weight tapentadol PR twice daily.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Tolerability Over the Complete Trial Period</title>
          <description>Tolerability was assessed by the number of participants with exactly 1 to more than 5 treatment emergent adverse events (TEAE) by treatment group during the different trial periods, on a participant level.
In addition, tolerability was assessed by the number of participants with TEAEs which were considered by the investigator to be at least possibly related to the treatment the participant received.</description>
          <population>Safety Set</population>
          <units>participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="24"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="45"/>
                <count group_id="O3" value="36"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>Participants without any TEAE</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="12"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="19"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O3" value="6"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Participants with at least 1 TEAE</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="12"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="26"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O3" value="30"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Participants with exactly 1 TEAE</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="1"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="7"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O3" value="5"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Participants with exactly 2 TEAEs</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="2"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="5"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O3" value="2"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Participants with exactly 3 TEAEs</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="2"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="4"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O3" value="2"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Participants with exactly 4 TEAEs</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="2"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="1"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O3" value="4"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Participants with exactly 5 TEAEs</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="1"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="3"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O3" value="3"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Participants with more than 5 TEAEs</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="4"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="6"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O3" value="14"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Participants with related TEAEs</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="6"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="12"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O3" value="13"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Other Pre-specified</type>
        <title>Change in Pain Intensity in the Open-label, Active-controlled Treatment Period (Part 1)</title>
        <description>Pain intensity was assessed by scoring &quot;Pain right now&quot; twice daily up to Day 14 by every participant using the Visual Analog Scale (VAS) as well as the Faces Pain Scale-Revised (FPS-R) in an electronic diary. Pain intensity was first documented using the VAS and directly thereafter the FPS-R. If required, pain intensity diary entry could be assisted by the legal guardian or a health care provider.
The VAS is scored from 0, equivalent to &quot;no pain&quot;, to 100, equivalent to &quot;pain as bad as it could be&quot;.
The FPS-R is a validated self-reported 6-point scale with 0 representing &quot;no pain&quot; and 10 representing &quot;very much pain&quot;. Facial representations were used to indicate how much the pain hurts.
The &quot;pain right now&quot; scores at baseline (last evaluation before starting IMP) and the mean of last 6 assessments collected up to the time point of last IMP intake in Part 1 (i.e., Day 14 or the day of early discontinuation) were used for the calculation of the change in pain intensity from baseline.</description>
        <time_frame>From Baseline up to Day 14 (End of Part 1) or early discontinuation</time_frame>
        <population>Full Analysis Set</population>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Morphine Prolonged-release (Part 1)</title>
            <description>The treatment group comprised 7 participants aged 6 years to less than 12 years and 17 participants aged 12 years to less than 18 years. Starting doses varied from 10 to 40 milligrams (mg) morphine PR twice daily depending on participant's weight; if necessary, doses were gradually increased up to a maximum dose defined per weight group.
The highest dose defined for participants weighing 55 kg and more was 200 mg per day.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>Tapentadol Prolonged-release (Part 1)</title>
            <description>The treatment group comprised 12 participants aged 6 years to less than 12 years and 33 participants aged 12 years to less than 18 years. Participants starting doses varied from 25 to 100 mg tapentadol PR twice daily depending on participant's weight. If necessary, doses were gradually increased up to a maximum dose defined per weight group.
The highest dose defined for participants weighing 55 kg and more was 500 mg per day.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Change in Pain Intensity in the Open-label, Active-controlled Treatment Period (Part 1)</title>
          <description>Pain intensity was assessed by scoring &quot;Pain right now&quot; twice daily up to Day 14 by every participant using the Visual Analog Scale (VAS) as well as the Faces Pain Scale-Revised (FPS-R) in an electronic diary. Pain intensity was first documented using the VAS and directly thereafter the FPS-R. If required, pain intensity diary entry could be assisted by the legal guardian or a health care provider.
The VAS is scored from 0, equivalent to &quot;no pain&quot;, to 100, equivalent to &quot;pain as bad as it could be&quot;.
The FPS-R is a validated self-reported 6-point scale with 0 representing &quot;no pain&quot; and 10 representing &quot;very much pain&quot;. Facial representations were used to indicate how much the pain hurts.
The &quot;pain right now&quot; scores at baseline (last evaluation before starting IMP) and the mean of last 6 assessments collected up to the time point of last IMP intake in Part 1 (i.e., Day 14 or the day of early discontinuation) were used for the calculation of the change in pain intensity from baseline.</description>
          <population>Full Analysis Set</population>
          <units>units on a scale</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>Standard Deviation</dispersion>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="24"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="45"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>Pain intensity change from Baseline (FPS-R)</title>
              <analyzed_list>
                <analyzed>
                  <units>Participants</units>
                  <scope>Class</scope>
                  <count_list>
                    <count group_id="O1" value="17"/>
                    <count group_id="O2" value="29"/>
                  </count_list>
                </analyzed>
              </analyzed_list>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="-2.0" spread="3.5"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="-1.9" spread="3.4"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Pain intensity change from Baseline (VAS)</title>
              <analyzed_list>
                <analyzed>
                  <units>Participants</units>
                  <scope>Class</scope>
                  <count_list>
                    <count group_id="O1" value="17"/>
                    <count group_id="O2" value="29"/>
                  </count_list>
                </analyzed>
              </analyzed_list>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="-23.4" spread="36.9"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="-18.8" spread="33.5"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Other Pre-specified</type>
        <title>Change in Pain Intensity in the Tapentadol Open-label Extension Period (Part 2)</title>
        <description>Pain intensity was assessed by scoring &quot;Pain right now&quot; using the Visual Analog Scale (VAS) as well as the Faces Pain Scale-Revised (FPS-R) at each visit. The pain intensity was first documented using the VAS and directly thereafter the FPS-R. If required, pain intensity assessments could be assisted by the legal guardian or a health care provider.
The VAS is scored from 0, equivalent to &quot;no pain&quot;, to 100, equivalent to &quot;pain as bad as it could be&quot;. The FPS-R is a validated self-reported 6-point scale with 0 representing &quot;no pain&quot; and 10 representing &quot;very much pain&quot;. Facial representations were used to indicate how much the pain hurts.
The &quot;pain right now&quot; score at the tapentadol baseline (last evaluation before or at Day 15) and at the last assessment for those subjects who completed the 12 months treatment of Part 2 were used for the calculation of the change in pain intensity from the tapentadol baseline.</description>
        <time_frame>From Day 15 to Day 379 (End of Part 2)</time_frame>
        <population>Full Analysis Set; data from 9 subjects who completed the visit 12 months after start of Part 2 were analyzed.</population>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Tapentadol Prolonged-release (Part 2)</title>
            <description>36 participants who completed Part 1 of the trial (26 on tapentadol PR and 10 participants on morphine PR) continued treatment or switched to treatment with tapentadol PR for up to 12 months in Part 2.
Participants on tapentadol PR in Part 1 continued on the current dose of tapentadol PR in Part 2 and if necessary could modify their tapentadol PR dosage. Participants on morphine PR in Part 1 were rotated to tapentadol PR in Part 2 with 70 percent of their current morphine equivalent dose or lower. The dosage could be increased gradually up to approximately 4.5 mg/kg body weight tapentadol PR twice daily.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Change in Pain Intensity in the Tapentadol Open-label Extension Period (Part 2)</title>
          <description>Pain intensity was assessed by scoring &quot;Pain right now&quot; using the Visual Analog Scale (VAS) as well as the Faces Pain Scale-Revised (FPS-R) at each visit. The pain intensity was first documented using the VAS and directly thereafter the FPS-R. If required, pain intensity assessments could be assisted by the legal guardian or a health care provider.
The VAS is scored from 0, equivalent to &quot;no pain&quot;, to 100, equivalent to &quot;pain as bad as it could be&quot;. The FPS-R is a validated self-reported 6-point scale with 0 representing &quot;no pain&quot; and 10 representing &quot;very much pain&quot;. Facial representations were used to indicate how much the pain hurts.
The &quot;pain right now&quot; score at the tapentadol baseline (last evaluation before or at Day 15) and at the last assessment for those subjects who completed the 12 months treatment of Part 2 were used for the calculation of the change in pain intensity from the tapentadol baseline.</description>
          <population>Full Analysis Set; data from 9 subjects who completed the visit 12 months after start of Part 2 were analyzed.</population>
          <units>units on a scale</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>Standard Deviation</dispersion>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="9"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>Pain intensity change (FPR-S) from Day 15</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="0" spread="2.8"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Pain intensity change (VAS) from Day 15</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="-11.7" spread="29.0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Other Pre-specified</type>
        <title>Use of Rescue Medication in the Open-Label, Active-controlled Treatment Period (Part 1)</title>
        <description>Due to an overall low intake of rescue medication, it was not appropriate to present the number of doses of oral morphine solution used at different dose levels of investigational medicinal product (IMP) but the average daily dose (milligrams per kilogram body weight) for the treatment period and a modified average daily dose. Average daily dose and modified average daily dose were both calculated based on drug accountability.
For the modified average daily doses, implausible values were excluded from the analysis, i.e., the amount of rescue medication that was lost due to a broken bottle was excluded from the analysis and negative amounts of rescue medication intakes due to measurement inaccuracies for bottle weights were considered as no intake.</description>
        <time_frame>From Day 1 up to Day 14 (End of Part 1)</time_frame>
        <population>Full Analysis Set</population>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Morphine Prolonged-release (Part 1)</title>
            <description>The treatment group comprised 7 participants aged 6 years to less than 12 years and 17 participants aged 12 years to less than 18 years. Starting doses varied from 10 to 40 milligrams (mg) morphine PR twice daily depending on participant's weight; if necessary, doses were gradually increased up to a maximum dose defined per weight group.
The highest dose defined for participants weighing 55 kg and more was 200 mg per day.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>Tapentadol Prolonged-release (Part 1)</title>
            <description>The treatment group comprised 12 participants aged 6 years to less than 12 years and 33 participants aged 12 years to less than 18 years. Participants starting doses varied from 25 to 100 mg tapentadol PR twice daily depending on participant's weight. If necessary, doses were gradually increased up to a maximum dose defined per weight group.
The highest dose defined for participants weighing 55 kg and more was 500 mg per day.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Use of Rescue Medication in the Open-Label, Active-controlled Treatment Period (Part 1)</title>
          <description>Due to an overall low intake of rescue medication, it was not appropriate to present the number of doses of oral morphine solution used at different dose levels of investigational medicinal product (IMP) but the average daily dose (milligrams per kilogram body weight) for the treatment period and a modified average daily dose. Average daily dose and modified average daily dose were both calculated based on drug accountability.
For the modified average daily doses, implausible values were excluded from the analysis, i.e., the amount of rescue medication that was lost due to a broken bottle was excluded from the analysis and negative amounts of rescue medication intakes due to measurement inaccuracies for bottle weights were considered as no intake.</description>
          <population>Full Analysis Set</population>
          <units>milligrams per kilogram per day</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>Standard Deviation</dispersion>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="24"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="45"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>Average daily dose</title>
              <analyzed_list>
                <analyzed>
                  <units>Participants</units>
                  <scope>Class</scope>
                  <count_list>
                    <count group_id="O1" value="24"/>
                    <count group_id="O2" value="44"/>
                  </count_list>
                </analyzed>
              </analyzed_list>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="0.07" spread="0.154"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="0.46" spread="2.426"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Modified average daily dose</title>
              <analyzed_list>
                <analyzed>
                  <units>Participants</units>
                  <scope>Class</scope>
                  <count_list>
                    <count group_id="O1" value="24"/>
                    <count group_id="O2" value="44"/>
                  </count_list>
                </analyzed>
              </analyzed_list>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="0.08" spread="0.160"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="0.11" spread="0.201"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Other Pre-specified</type>
        <title>Serum Concentrations of Tapentadol (Part 1)</title>
        <description>Tapentadol serum concentrations were measured in participants in the tapentadol treatment arm (Part 1).
All participants who had quantifiable serum concentrations during the Treatment Period were included in the descriptive pharmacokinetic analysis. Data from participants who vomited within 6 hours of administration of IMP during the Treatment Period were carefully assessed to decide if the data should be included in the pharmacokinetic analysis.</description>
        <time_frame>From Day 1 to Day 14 (End of Part 1)</time_frame>
        <population>Pharmacokinetic Analysis Set</population>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Tapentadol Prolonged-release (All Participants)</title>
            <description>The treatment group comprised 12 participants aged 6 years to less than 12 years and 33 participants aged 12 years to less than 18 years. Participants starting doses varied from 25 to 100 mg tapentadol PR twice daily depending on participant's weight. If necessary, doses were gradually increased up to a maximum dose defined per weight group.
The highest dose defined for participants weighing 55 kg and more was 500 mg per day.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>Tapentadol Prolonged-release (6 Years to Less Than 12 Years)</title>
            <description>The treatment group comprised 12 participants aged 6 years to less than 12 years. Participants starting doses varied from 25 to 100 mg tapentadol PR twice daily depending on participant's weight. If necessary, doses were gradually increased up to a maximum dose defined per weight group.
The highest dose defined for participants weighing 55 kg and more was 500 mg per day.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O3">
            <title>Tapentadol Prolonged-release (12 Years to Less Than 18 Years)</title>
            <description>The treatment group comprised 33 participants aged 12 years to less than 18 years. Participants starting doses varied from 25 to 100 mg tapentadol PR twice daily depending on participant's weight. If necessary, doses were gradually increased up to a maximum dose defined per weight group.
The highest dose defined for participants weighing 55 kg and more was 500 mg per day.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Serum Concentrations of Tapentadol (Part 1)</title>
          <description>Tapentadol serum concentrations were measured in participants in the tapentadol treatment arm (Part 1).
All participants who had quantifiable serum concentrations during the Treatment Period were included in the descriptive pharmacokinetic analysis. Data from participants who vomited within 6 hours of administration of IMP during the Treatment Period were carefully assessed to decide if the data should be included in the pharmacokinetic analysis.</description>
          <population>Pharmacokinetic Analysis Set</population>
          <units>nanograms per milliliter</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>Standard Deviation</dispersion>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="44"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="12"/>
                <count group_id="O3" value="32"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>Day 1</title>
              <analyzed_list>
                <analyzed>
                  <units>Participants</units>
                  <scope>Class</scope>
                  <count_list>
                    <count group_id="O1" value="40"/>
                    <count group_id="O2" value="12"/>
                    <count group_id="O3" value="28"/>
                  </count_list>
                </analyzed>
              </analyzed_list>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="19.1" spread="19.57"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="17.2" spread="7.40"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O3" value="19.9" spread="22.99"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Day 14</title>
              <analyzed_list>
                <analyzed>
                  <units>Participants</units>
                  <scope>Class</scope>
                  <count_list>
                    <count group_id="O1" value="41"/>
                    <count group_id="O2" value="12"/>
                    <count group_id="O3" value="29"/>
                  </count_list>
                </analyzed>
              </analyzed_list>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="44.7" spread="34.17"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="35.6" spread="18.14"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O3" value="48.5" spread="38.59"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Other Pre-specified</type>
        <title>Serum Concentrations of Tapentadol-O-glucuronide (Part 1)</title>
        <description>Tapentadol-O-glucuronide is a metabolite of tapentadol. The body transforms tapentadol into its metabolites so that it can be more easily/quickly removed from the body. Tapentadol-O-glucuronide serum concentrations were measured in participants who received tapentadol PR in Part 1.
All participants who had quantifiable serum concentrations were included in the descriptive pharmacokinetic analysis. Data from participants who vomited within 6 hours of administration of IMP during Part 1 were carefully assessed to decide if they should be included in the pharmacokinetic analysis.</description>
        <time_frame>From Day 1 to Day 14 (End of Part1)</time_frame>
        <population>Pharmacokinetic Analysis Set</population>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Tapentadol Prolonged-release (All Participants)</title>
            <description>The treatment group comprised 12 participants aged 6 years to less than 12 years and 33 participants aged 12 years to less than 18 years. Participants starting doses varied from 25 to 100 mg tapentadol PR twice daily depending on participant's weight. If necessary, doses were gradually increased up to a maximum dose defined per weight group.
The highest dose defined for participants weighing 55 kg and more was 500 mg per day.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>Tapentadol Prolonged-release (6 Years to Less Than 12 Years)</title>
            <description>The treatment group comprised 12 participants aged 6 years to less than 12 years. Participants starting doses varied from 25 to 100 mg tapentadol PR twice daily depending on participant's weight. If necessary, doses were gradually increased up to a maximum dose defined per weight group.
The highest dose defined for participants weighing 55 kg and more was 500 mg per day.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O3">
            <title>Tapentadol Prolonged-release (12 Years to Less Than 18 Years)</title>
            <description>The treatment group comprised 33 participants aged 12 years to less than 18 years. Participants starting doses varied from 25 to 100 mg tapentadol PR twice daily depending on participant's weight. If necessary, doses were gradually increased up to a maximum dose defined per weight group.
The highest dose defined for participants weighing 55 kg and more was 500 mg per day.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Serum Concentrations of Tapentadol-O-glucuronide (Part 1)</title>
          <description>Tapentadol-O-glucuronide is a metabolite of tapentadol. The body transforms tapentadol into its metabolites so that it can be more easily/quickly removed from the body. Tapentadol-O-glucuronide serum concentrations were measured in participants who received tapentadol PR in Part 1.
All participants who had quantifiable serum concentrations were included in the descriptive pharmacokinetic analysis. Data from participants who vomited within 6 hours of administration of IMP during Part 1 were carefully assessed to decide if they should be included in the pharmacokinetic analysis.</description>
          <population>Pharmacokinetic Analysis Set</population>
          <units>nanograms per milliliter</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>Standard Deviation</dispersion>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="44"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="12"/>
                <count group_id="O3" value="32"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>Day 1</title>
              <analyzed_list>
                <analyzed>
                  <units>Participants</units>
                  <scope>Class</scope>
                  <count_list>
                    <count group_id="O1" value="40"/>
                    <count group_id="O2" value="12"/>
                    <count group_id="O3" value="28"/>
                  </count_list>
                </analyzed>
              </analyzed_list>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="731.7" spread="840.02"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="603.2" spread="312.11"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O3" value="786.7" spread="984.42"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Day 14</title>
              <analyzed_list>
                <analyzed>
                  <units>Participants</units>
                  <scope>Class</scope>
                  <count_list>
                    <count group_id="O1" value="40"/>
                    <count group_id="O2" value="12"/>
                    <count group_id="O3" value="28"/>
                  </count_list>
                </analyzed>
              </analyzed_list>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="1557.3" spread="1187.24"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="1223.8" spread="511.27"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O3" value="1700.3" spread="1363.41"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Other Pre-specified</type>
        <title>Palatability of Study Medication (Part 1, Day 8)</title>
        <description>Palatability was determined in Part 1 by asking the participant &quot;How does the medication taste&quot;. The participant was requested to give a score on a 5-point hedonic faces rating scale in combination with a verbal rating. The response can range from really bad to really good.</description>
        <time_frame>Day 8 (Part 1)</time_frame>
        <population>Full Analysis Set</population>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Morphine Prolonged-release (Part 1)</title>
            <description>The treatment group comprised 7 participants aged 6 years to less than 12 years and 17 participants aged 12 years to less than 18 years. Starting doses varied from 10 to 40 milligrams (mg) morphine PR twice daily depending on participant's weight; if necessary, doses were gradually increased up to a maximum dose defined per weight group.
The highest dose defined for participants weighing 55 kg and more was 200 mg per day.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>Tapentadol Prolonged-release (Part 1)</title>
            <description>The treatment group comprised 12 participants aged 6 years to less than 12 years and 33 participants aged 12 years to less than 18 years. Participants starting doses varied from 25 to 100 mg tapentadol PR twice daily depending on participant's weight. If necessary, doses were gradually increased up to a maximum dose defined per weight group.
The highest dose defined for participants weighing 55 kg and more was 500 mg per day.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Palatability of Study Medication (Part 1, Day 8)</title>
          <description>Palatability was determined in Part 1 by asking the participant &quot;How does the medication taste&quot;. The participant was requested to give a score on a 5-point hedonic faces rating scale in combination with a verbal rating. The response can range from really bad to really good.</description>
          <population>Full Analysis Set</population>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <param>Count of Participants</param>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="24"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="45"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <title>Really bad</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Bad</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="2"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>A bit bad/a bit good</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="13"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="21"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Good</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="7"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="12"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Really good</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="3"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="6"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Missing</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="1"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="4"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Other Pre-specified</type>
        <title>Palatability of Study Medication (Part 1, Day 14)</title>
        <description>Palatability was determined in Part 1 by asking the participant &quot;How does the medication taste&quot;. The participant was requested to give a score on a 5-point hedonic faces rating scale in combination with a verbal rating. The response can range from really bad to really good.</description>
        <time_frame>Day 14 (Part 1)</time_frame>
        <population>Full Analysis Set</population>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Morphine Prolonged-release (Part 1)</title>
            <description>The treatment group comprised 7 participants aged 6 years to less than 12 years and 17 participants aged 12 years to less than 18 years. Starting doses varied from 10 to 40 milligrams (mg) morphine PR twice daily depending on participant's weight; if necessary, doses were gradually increased up to a maximum dose defined per weight group.
The highest dose defined for participants weighing 55 kg and more was 200 mg per day.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>Tapentadol Prolonged-release (Part 1)</title>
            <description>The treatment group comprised 12 participants aged 6 years to less than 12 years and 33 participants aged 12 years to less than 18 years. Participants starting doses varied from 25 to 100 mg tapentadol PR twice daily depending on participant's weight. If necessary, doses were gradually increased up to a maximum dose defined per weight group.
The highest dose defined for participants weighing 55 kg and more was 500 mg per day.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Palatability of Study Medication (Part 1, Day 14)</title>
          <description>Palatability was determined in Part 1 by asking the participant &quot;How does the medication taste&quot;. The participant was requested to give a score on a 5-point hedonic faces rating scale in combination with a verbal rating. The response can range from really bad to really good.</description>
          <population>Full Analysis Set</population>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <param>Count of Participants</param>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="24"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="45"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <title>Really bad</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Bad</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="1"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>A bit bad/a bit good</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="9"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="23"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Good</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="9"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="11"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Really good</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="6"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="9"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Missing</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="1"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Other Pre-specified</type>
        <title>Acceptability of Study Medication (Part 1, Day 8)</title>
        <description>Acceptability of the study medication was determined in Part 1 by asking the participant &quot;Swallowing the medication is...&quot;. The participant was requested to give a score on a 5-point hedonic faces rating scale in combination with a verbal rating. The response can range from really difficult to really easy.</description>
        <time_frame>Day 8 (Part 1)</time_frame>
        <population>Full Analysis Set</population>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Morphine Prolonged-release (Part 1)</title>
            <description>The treatment group comprised 7 participants aged 6 years to less than 12 years and 17 participants aged 12 years to less than 18 years. Starting doses varied from 10 to 40 milligrams (mg) morphine PR twice daily depending on participant's weight; if necessary, doses were gradually increased up to a maximum dose defined per weight group.
The highest dose defined for participants weighing 55 kg and more was 200 mg per day.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>Tapentadol Prolonged-release (Part 1)</title>
            <description>The treatment group comprised 12 participants aged 6 years to less than 12 years and 33 participants aged 12 years to less than 18 years. Participants starting doses varied from 25 to 100 mg tapentadol PR twice daily depending on participant's weight. If necessary, doses were gradually increased up to a maximum dose defined per weight group.
The highest dose defined for participants weighing 55 kg and more was 500 mg per day.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Acceptability of Study Medication (Part 1, Day 8)</title>
          <description>Acceptability of the study medication was determined in Part 1 by asking the participant &quot;Swallowing the medication is...&quot;. The participant was requested to give a score on a 5-point hedonic faces rating scale in combination with a verbal rating. The response can range from really difficult to really easy.</description>
          <population>Full Analysis Set</population>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <param>Count of Participants</param>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="24"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="45"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <title>Really difficult</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Difficult</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="3"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>A bit difficult/a bit easy</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="3"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="5"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Easy</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="8"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="9"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Really easy</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="12"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="24"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Missing</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="1"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="4"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Other Pre-specified</type>
        <title>Acceptability of Study Medication (Part 1, Day 14)</title>
        <description>Acceptability of the study medication was determined in Part 1 by asking the participant &quot;Swallowing the medication is...&quot;. The participant was requested to give a score on a 5-point hedonic faces rating scale in combination with a verbal rating. The response can range from really difficult to really easy.</description>
        <time_frame>Day 14 (End of Part 1)</time_frame>
        <population>Full Analysis Set</population>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Morphine Prolonged-release (Part 1)</title>
            <description>The treatment group comprised 7 participants aged 6 years to less than 12 years and 17 participants aged 12 years to less than 18 years. Starting doses varied from 10 to 40 milligrams (mg) morphine PR twice daily depending on participant's weight; if necessary, doses were gradually increased up to a maximum dose defined per weight group.
The highest dose defined for participants weighing 55 kg and more was 200 mg per day.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>Tapentadol Prolonged-release (Part 1)</title>
            <description>The treatment group comprised 12 participants aged 6 years to less than 12 years and 33 participants aged 12 years to less than 18 years. Participants starting doses varied from 25 to 100 mg tapentadol PR twice daily depending on participant's weight. If necessary, doses were gradually increased up to a maximum dose defined per weight group.
The highest dose defined for participants weighing 55 kg and more was 500 mg per day.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Acceptability of Study Medication (Part 1, Day 14)</title>
          <description>Acceptability of the study medication was determined in Part 1 by asking the participant &quot;Swallowing the medication is...&quot;. The participant was requested to give a score on a 5-point hedonic faces rating scale in combination with a verbal rating. The response can range from really difficult to really easy.</description>
          <population>Full Analysis Set</population>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <param>Count of Participants</param>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="24"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="45"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <title>Really difficult</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="1"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="1"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Difficult</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="1"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>A bit difficult/a bit easy</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="2"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="7"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Easy</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="8"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="16"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Really easy</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="13"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="19"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Missing</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="1"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Other Pre-specified</type>
        <title>Extent of Constipation (Part 2)</title>
        <description>Constipation was assessed using the modified constipation assessment scale (mCAS). This is an 8-item questionnaire where the observer has scored constipation on a nominal scale (no problem [score 0], some problem [score 1] or severe problem [score 2]). The response to an item could also be scored as &quot;unable to assess&quot;.
The Total Score can vary from 0-16; the higher the Total Score the higher the extent of constipation. A positive change from baseline to last assessment indicates a worsening, a negative change an improvement.</description>
        <time_frame>From baseline (Day 15 or switch) to last assessment (up to Day 379 of Part 2)</time_frame>
        <population>Safety Set</population>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Tapentadol in Part 2 After Tapentadol or Morphine in Part 1</title>
            <description>Participants on tapentadol PR in Part 1 of the study continued on the current dose of tapentadol PR in Part 2 and if necessary could modify their tapentadol PR dosage. Participants who were randomized to morphine PR in Part 1 of the study were rotated to tapentadol PR in Part 2 with 70 percent of their current morphine equivalent dose or lower.The dosage could be increased gradually up to approximately 4.5 mg/kg body weight tapentadol PR twice daily.
Tapentadol prolonged release</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>Observation Period After Tapentadol in Part 1</title>
            <description>Participants who completed tapentadol PR in Part 1 of the study or discontinued tapentadol treatment early in Part 1 could continue directly in the observation period in Part 2 for up to 12 months (with standard-of-care treatment if needed).</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O3">
            <title>Observation Period After Morphine in Part 1</title>
            <description>Participants who completed morphine PR treatment in Part 1 of the study or discontinued early from morphine treatment in Part 1 could continue directly in the observation period in Part 2 (with standard-of-care treatment if needed).</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O4">
            <title>Observation Period After Tapentadol in Part 2</title>
            <description>Participants who completed tapentadol PR or morphine PR treatment in Part 1 of the study could enter the Observation Period for up to 12 months (with standard-of-care treatment if needed) after they had discontinued from tapentadol PR treatment in Part 2.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Extent of Constipation (Part 2)</title>
          <description>Constipation was assessed using the modified constipation assessment scale (mCAS). This is an 8-item questionnaire where the observer has scored constipation on a nominal scale (no problem [score 0], some problem [score 1] or severe problem [score 2]). The response to an item could also be scored as &quot;unable to assess&quot;.
The Total Score can vary from 0-16; the higher the Total Score the higher the extent of constipation. A positive change from baseline to last assessment indicates a worsening, a negative change an improvement.</description>
          <population>Safety Set</population>
          <units>units on a scale</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>Standard Deviation</dispersion>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="36"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="18"/>
                <count group_id="O3" value="14"/>
                <count group_id="O4" value="26"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>Baseline</title>
              <analyzed_list>
                <analyzed>
                  <units>Participants</units>
                  <scope>Class</scope>
                  <count_list>
                    <count group_id="O1" value="35"/>
                    <count group_id="O2" value="17"/>
                    <count group_id="O3" value="14"/>
                    <count group_id="O4" value="25"/>
                  </count_list>
                </analyzed>
              </analyzed_list>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="2.3" spread="2.4"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="1.8" spread="2.3"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O3" value="2.5" spread="2.5"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O4" value="1.5" spread="2.5"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Last assessment</title>
              <analyzed_list>
                <analyzed>
                  <units>Participants</units>
                  <scope>Class</scope>
                  <count_list>
                    <count group_id="O1" value="32"/>
                    <count group_id="O2" value="10"/>
                    <count group_id="O3" value="12"/>
                    <count group_id="O4" value="16"/>
                  </count_list>
                </analyzed>
              </analyzed_list>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="1.8" spread="2.7"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="0.4" spread="0.8"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O3" value="0.4" spread="1.2"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O4" value="0.8" spread="1.7"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Change from baseline</title>
              <analyzed_list>
                <analyzed>
                  <units>Participants</units>
                  <scope>Class</scope>
                  <count_list>
                    <count group_id="O1" value="32"/>
                    <count group_id="O2" value="9"/>
                    <count group_id="O3" value="12"/>
                    <count group_id="O4" value="15"/>
                  </count_list>
                </analyzed>
              </analyzed_list>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="-0.7" spread="3.3"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="-1.4" spread="2.1"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O3" value="-1.6" spread="1.7"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O4" value="-1.4" spread="2.7"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Other Pre-specified</type>
        <title>Change From Baseline in Subjective Opiate Withdrawal Scale (SOWS)</title>
        <description>Opiate withdrawal symptoms were assessed using the Subjective Opiate Withdrawal Scale (SOWS) questionnaire. The SOWS is designed to reflect common motoric, autonomic, musculoskeletal, and psychic signs and symptoms of opiate withdrawal. Each participant was requested to rate the first 15 items of the 16-item questionnaire for 7 days after last IMP intake. Participants rated the intensity of specific signs and symptoms on a scale of 0 (not at all) to 4 (extremely). The minimum overall score is 0, the maximum score is 64.
SOWS Total Score at baseline (i.e., for Part 1 = Day 14-17, for Part 2 = Day 352-380, or the day after an early termination visit (Part 1/2)), and changes from baseline 2-7 days after last intake of IMP in Part 1 (= up to Day 23) and in Part 2 (= up to Day 386) are presented.</description>
        <time_frame>From Day 1 to Day 386 (End of Part 2 + 7 days)</time_frame>
        <population>Safety Set</population>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Morphine Prolonged-release (Part 1)</title>
            <description>The treatment group comprised 7 participants aged 6 years to less than 12 years and 17 participants aged 12 years to less than 18 years. Starting doses varied from 10 to 40 milligrams (mg) morphine PR twice daily depending on participant's weight; if necessary, doses were gradually increased up to a maximum dose defined per weight group.
The highest dose defined for participants weighing 55 kg and more was 200 mg per day.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>Tapentadol Prolonged-release (Part 1)</title>
            <description>The treatment group comprised 12 participants aged 6 years to less than 12 years and 33 participants aged 12 years to less than 18 years. Participants starting doses varied from 25 to 100 mg tapentadol PR twice daily depending on participant's weight. If necessary, doses were gradually increased up to a maximum dose defined per weight group.
The highest dose defined for participants weighing 55 kg and more was 500 mg per day.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O3">
            <title>Tapentadol Prolonged-release (Part 2)</title>
            <description>36 participants who completed Part 1 of the trial (26 on tapentadol PR and 10 participants on morphine PR) continued treatment or switched to treatment with tapentadol PR for up to 12 months in Part 2.
Participants on tapentadol PR in Part 1 continued on the current dose of tapentadol PR in Part 2 and if necessary could modify their tapentadol PR dosage. Participants on morphine PR in Part 1 were rotated to tapentadol PR in Part 2 with 70 percent of their current morphine equivalent dose or lower. The dosage could be increased gradually up to approximately 4.5 mg/kg body weight tapentadol PR twice daily.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Change From Baseline in Subjective Opiate Withdrawal Scale (SOWS)</title>
          <description>Opiate withdrawal symptoms were assessed using the Subjective Opiate Withdrawal Scale (SOWS) questionnaire. The SOWS is designed to reflect common motoric, autonomic, musculoskeletal, and psychic signs and symptoms of opiate withdrawal. Each participant was requested to rate the first 15 items of the 16-item questionnaire for 7 days after last IMP intake. Participants rated the intensity of specific signs and symptoms on a scale of 0 (not at all) to 4 (extremely). The minimum overall score is 0, the maximum score is 64.
SOWS Total Score at baseline (i.e., for Part 1 = Day 14-17, for Part 2 = Day 352-380, or the day after an early termination visit (Part 1/2)), and changes from baseline 2-7 days after last intake of IMP in Part 1 (= up to Day 23) and in Part 2 (= up to Day 386) are presented.</description>
          <population>Safety Set</population>
          <units>units on a scale</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>Standard Deviation</dispersion>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="24"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="45"/>
                <count group_id="O3" value="36"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>Total score at baseline</title>
              <analyzed_list>
                <analyzed>
                  <units>Participants</units>
                  <scope>Class</scope>
                  <count_list>
                    <count group_id="O1" value="9"/>
                    <count group_id="O2" value="9"/>
                    <count group_id="O3" value="23"/>
                  </count_list>
                </analyzed>
              </analyzed_list>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="4.0" spread="3.8"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="6.9" spread="7.6"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O3" value="6.1" spread="6.0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Change Day 2 after last IMP intake</title>
              <analyzed_list>
                <analyzed>
                  <units>Participants</units>
                  <scope>Class</scope>
                  <count_list>
                    <count group_id="O1" value="10"/>
                    <count group_id="O2" value="10"/>
                    <count group_id="O3" value="25"/>
                  </count_list>
                </analyzed>
              </analyzed_list>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="-0.4" spread="2.0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="-1.7" spread="2.5"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O3" value="-0.7" spread="2.8"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Change Day 3 after last IMP intake</title>
              <analyzed_list>
                <analyzed>
                  <units>Participants</units>
                  <scope>Class</scope>
                  <count_list>
                    <count group_id="O1" value="10"/>
                    <count group_id="O2" value="11"/>
                    <count group_id="O3" value="25"/>
                  </count_list>
                </analyzed>
              </analyzed_list>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="-1.6" spread="2.7"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="-2.3" spread="4.9"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O3" value="-0.3" spread="3.1"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Change Day 4 after last IMP intake</title>
              <analyzed_list>
                <analyzed>
                  <units>Participants</units>
                  <scope>Class</scope>
                  <count_list>
                    <count group_id="O1" value="10"/>
                    <count group_id="O2" value="12"/>
                    <count group_id="O3" value="27"/>
                  </count_list>
                </analyzed>
              </analyzed_list>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="-1.7" spread="4.4"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="-3.9" spread="4.7"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O3" value="-0.1" spread="3.6"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Change Day 5 after last IMP intake</title>
              <analyzed_list>
                <analyzed>
                  <units>Participants</units>
                  <scope>Class</scope>
                  <count_list>
                    <count group_id="O1" value="10"/>
                    <count group_id="O2" value="12"/>
                    <count group_id="O3" value="26"/>
                  </count_list>
                </analyzed>
              </analyzed_list>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="-1.6" spread="3.6"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="-3.8" spread="5.1"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O3" value="0" spread="5.0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Change Day 6 after last IMP intake</title>
              <analyzed_list>
                <analyzed>
                  <units>Participants</units>
                  <scope>Class</scope>
                  <count_list>
                    <count group_id="O1" value="9"/>
                    <count group_id="O2" value="12"/>
                    <count group_id="O3" value="25"/>
                  </count_list>
                </analyzed>
              </analyzed_list>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="-2.3" spread="3.6"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="-3.6" spread="4.6"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O3" value="-0.6" spread="3.1"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Change Day 7 after last IMP intake</title>
              <analyzed_list>
                <analyzed>
                  <units>Participants</units>
                  <scope>Class</scope>
                  <count_list>
                    <count group_id="O1" value="7"/>
                    <count group_id="O2" value="12"/>
                    <count group_id="O3" value="18"/>
                  </count_list>
                </analyzed>
              </analyzed_list>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="-2.7" spread="3.9"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="-5.1" spread="6.3"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O3" value="-1.4" spread="2.8"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Other Pre-specified</type>
        <title>Time to Discontinuation (Lack of Efficacy) in Part 1</title>
        <description>The time to discontinuation from IMP due to lack of efficacy was planned to be analyzed for both treatment arms (tapentadol PR and morphine PR) in Part 1 of the trial. However, no participant was reported with early discontinuation from IMP due to lack of efficacy. Consequently, no time to discontinuation can be reported.</description>
        <time_frame>From first day in Part 1 (Day 1) to last day in Part 1</time_frame>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Other Pre-specified</type>
        <title>Time to Discontinuation (Lack of Efficacy) in Part 2</title>
        <description>The time to discontinuation from IMP due to lack of efficacy was analyzed for tapentadol PR treatment in Part 2 of the trial.</description>
        <time_frame>From first day in Part 2 (Day 15) to last day in Part 2 (Day 379)</time_frame>
        <population>Safety Set; 3 participants with early discontinuation from IMP due to lack of efficacy</population>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Tapentadol Prolonged-release (Part 2)</title>
            <description>36 participants who completed Part 1 of the trial (26 on tapentadol PR and 10 participants on morphine PR) continued treatment or switched to treatment with tapentadol PR for up to 12 months in Part 2.
Participants on tapentadol PR in Part 1 continued on the current dose of tapentadol PR in Part 2 and if necessary could modify their tapentadol PR dosage. Participants on morphine PR in Part 1 were rotated to tapentadol PR in Part 2 with 70 percent of their current morphine equivalent dose or lower. The dosage could be increased gradually up to approximately 4.5 mg/kg body weight tapentadol PR twice daily.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Time to Discontinuation (Lack of Efficacy) in Part 2</title>
          <description>The time to discontinuation from IMP due to lack of efficacy was analyzed for tapentadol PR treatment in Part 2 of the trial.</description>
          <population>Safety Set; 3 participants with early discontinuation from IMP due to lack of efficacy</population>
          <units>weeks</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>Full Range</dispersion>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="3"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="30.9" lower_limit="9" upper_limit="36"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Other Pre-specified</type>
        <title>Time to Discontinuation (Treatment Emergent Adverse Events) in Part 1</title>
        <description>The time to discontinuation from IMP due to treatment emergent adverse events (TEAEs) was analyzed for both treatment arms (tapentadol PR and morphine PR) in Part 1 of the study.
Note that no participant discontinued due to a TEAE in the morphine PR arm, and 2 participants in the tapentadol PR arm.</description>
        <time_frame>From first day in Part 1 (Day 1) to last day in Part 1 (Day 14)</time_frame>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Morphine Prolonged-release (Part 1)</title>
            <description>The treatment group comprised 7 participants aged 6 years to less than 12 years and 17 participants aged 12 years to less than 18 years. Starting doses varied from 10 to 40 milligrams (mg) morphine PR twice daily depending on participant’s weight; if necessary, doses were gradually increased up to a maximum dose defined per weight group.
The highest dose defined for participants weighing 55 kg and more was 200 mg per day.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>Tapentadol Prolonged-release (Part 1)</title>
            <description>The treatment group comprised 12 participants aged 6 years to less than 12 years and 33 participants aged 12 years to less than 18 years. Participants starting doses varied from 25 to 100 mg tapentadol PR twice daily depending on participant’s weight. If necessary, doses were gradually increased up to a maximum dose defined per weight group.
The highest dose defined for participants weighing 55 kg and more was 500 mg per day.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Time to Discontinuation (Treatment Emergent Adverse Events) in Part 1</title>
          <description>The time to discontinuation from IMP due to treatment emergent adverse events (TEAEs) was analyzed for both treatment arms (tapentadol PR and morphine PR) in Part 1 of the study.
Note that no participant discontinued due to a TEAE in the morphine PR arm, and 2 participants in the tapentadol PR arm.</description>
          <units>days</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>Full Range</dispersion>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="24"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="45"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="NA" lower_limit="NA" upper_limit="NA">No participant discontinued due to a TEAE in the morphine PR arm.</measurement>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="3.0" lower_limit="2" upper_limit="4"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Other Pre-specified</type>
        <title>Time to Discontinuation (Treatment Emergent Adverse Events) in Part 2</title>
        <description>The time to discontinuation from IMP due to treatment emergent adverse events (TEAEs) was analyzed for tapentadol PR treatment in Part 2 of the study.</description>
        <time_frame>From first day in Part 2 (Day 15) to last day in Part 2 (Day 379)</time_frame>
        <population>Safety Set; 3 participants discontinued due to treatment emergent adverse events.</population>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Tapentadol Prolonged-release (Part 2)</title>
            <description>36 participants who completed Part 1 of the trial (26 on tapentadol PR and 10 participants on morphine PR) continued treatment or switched to treatment with tapentadol PR for up to 12 months in Part 2.
Participants on tapentadol PR in Part 1 continued on the current dose of tapentadol PR in Part 2 and if necessary could modify their tapentadol PR dosage. Participants on morphine PR in Part 1 were rotated to tapentadol PR in Part 2 with 70 percent of their current morphine equivalent dose or lower. The dosage could be increased gradually up to approximately 4.5 mg/kg body weight tapentadol PR twice daily.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Time to Discontinuation (Treatment Emergent Adverse Events) in Part 2</title>
          <description>The time to discontinuation from IMP due to treatment emergent adverse events (TEAEs) was analyzed for tapentadol PR treatment in Part 2 of the study.</description>
          <population>Safety Set; 3 participants discontinued due to treatment emergent adverse events.</population>
          <units>weeks</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>Full Range</dispersion>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="36"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="5.3" lower_limit="3" upper_limit="24"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Other Pre-specified</type>
        <title>Time to First Intake of Rescue Medication in the Open-label, Active-controlled Treatment Period (Part 1)</title>
        <description>Morphine oral solution could be given during Part 1 as rescue medication in both treatment groups. The dose per rescue medication intake was 1/6 of the total daily dose of the scheduled tapentadol or morphine PR intakes. Rescue medication administration times and doses were recorded.
18 Participants in the morphine PR group and 27 participants in the tapentadol PR group had no documented intake of rescue medication between Day 1 and Day 14.
Summary statistics were calculated based on participants with any intake, i.e., those that took at least 1 dose of rescue medication. The mean (standard deviation) time (hours) to first dose of rescue medication following the first dose of the IMP (on Day 1) is presented.</description>
        <time_frame>From Day 1 up to Day 14 (End of Part 1)</time_frame>
        <population>Full Analysis Set</population>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Morphine Prolonged-release (Part 1)</title>
            <description>The treatment group comprised 7 participants aged 6 years to less than 12 years and 17 participants aged 12 years to less than 18 years. Starting doses varied from 10 to 40 milligrams (mg) morphine PR twice daily depending on participant's weight; if necessary, doses were gradually increased up to a maximum dose defined per weight group.
The highest dose defined for participants weighing 55 kg and more was 200 mg per day.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>Tapentadol Prolonged-release (Part 1)</title>
            <description>The treatment group comprised 12 participants aged 6 years to less than 12 years and 33 participants aged 12 years to less than 18 years. Participants starting doses varied from 25 to 100 mg tapentadol PR twice daily depending on participant's weight. If necessary, doses were gradually increased up to a maximum dose defined per weight group.
The highest dose defined for participants weighing 55 kg and more was 500 mg per day.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Time to First Intake of Rescue Medication in the Open-label, Active-controlled Treatment Period (Part 1)</title>
          <description>Morphine oral solution could be given during Part 1 as rescue medication in both treatment groups. The dose per rescue medication intake was 1/6 of the total daily dose of the scheduled tapentadol or morphine PR intakes. Rescue medication administration times and doses were recorded.
18 Participants in the morphine PR group and 27 participants in the tapentadol PR group had no documented intake of rescue medication between Day 1 and Day 14.
Summary statistics were calculated based on participants with any intake, i.e., those that took at least 1 dose of rescue medication. The mean (standard deviation) time (hours) to first dose of rescue medication following the first dose of the IMP (on Day 1) is presented.</description>
          <population>Full Analysis Set</population>
          <units>hours</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>Standard Deviation</dispersion>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="24"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="45"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>Participants with rescue medication intake</title>
              <analyzed_list>
                <analyzed>
                  <units>Participants</units>
                  <scope>Class</scope>
                  <count_list>
                    <count group_id="O1" value="6"/>
                    <count group_id="O2" value="18"/>
                  </count_list>
                </analyzed>
              </analyzed_list>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="39.7" spread="63.75"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="74.6" spread="94.45"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Participants with no rescue medication intake</title>
              <analyzed_list>
                <analyzed>
                  <units>Participants</units>
                  <scope>Class</scope>
                  <count_list>
                    <count group_id="O1" value="18"/>
                    <count group_id="O2" value="27"/>
                  </count_list>
                </analyzed>
              </analyzed_list>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="NA" spread="NA">No documented intake of rescue medication between Day 1 and Day 14.</measurement>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="NA" spread="NA">No documented intake of rescue medication between Day 1 and Day 14.</measurement>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
    </outcome_list>

    <reported_events>
      <time_frame>Adverse events were regularly assessed by the investigator using a standard set of questions. Treatment emergent adverse events (TEAEs) were collected from first dose (on Day 1) to last intake of IMP plus 72 hours (therapeutic reach).</time_frame>
      <desc>Part 1: TEAEs from first to last dose in Part 1 if participant continued on tapentadol PR in Part 2; from first to last dose in Part 1 + 72 hours (therapeutic reach) if participant did not continue on tapentadol PR in Part 2.
Part 2: TEAEs from start of Part 2 to the last IMP intake in Part 2 + 72 hours (therapeutic reach).</desc>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="E1">
          <title>Morphine Prolonged-release (Part 1)</title>
          <description>The treatment group comprised 7 participants aged 6 years to less than 12 years and 17 participants aged 12 years to less than 18 years.
Starting doses varied from 10 to 40 milligrams (mg) morphine PR twice daily depending on participant’s weight; if necessary, doses were gradually increased up to a maximum dose defined per weight group.
The highest dose defined for participants weighing 55 kg and more was 200 mg per day.</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="E2">
          <title>Tapentadol Prolonged-release (Part 1)</title>
          <description>The treatment group comprised 12 participants aged 6 years to less than 12 years and 33 participants aged 12 years to less than 18 years.
Starting doses varied from 25 to 100 mg tapentadol PR twice daily depending on participant’s weight. If necessary, doses were gradually increased up to a maximum dose defined per weight group.
The highest dose defined for participants weighing 55 kg and more was 500 mg per day.</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="E3">
          <title>Overall (Part 1)</title>
          <description>Overall (Part 1) includes all participants with a 2-week treatment with tapentadol PR or morphine PR tablets.
One participant who completed the tapentadol PR treatment in Part 1 died in the Observation Period (Part 2; standard-of-care treatment, no IMP) due to progression of Ewing’s sarcoma, which started progressing in Part 1. A second participant died in the Observation Period after Tapentadol in Part 1 due to serious progression of osteosarcoma with fatal outcome. The progression started in the Observation Period.</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="E4">
          <title>Tapentadol Prolonged-release in Part 2</title>
          <description>Tapentadol prolonged release in Part 2 comprises all participants who completed Part 1 (on tapentadol PR or morphine PR) and continued on or switched to an extended treatment with tapentadol PR for up to 12 months.
No deaths were reported during treatment with tapentadol PR in Part 2. Following tapentadol PR treatment in Part 2, 1 participant died during the Observation Period (under standard-of-care treatment, no IMP) due to malignant neoplasm progression (sarcoma). The progression started in the Observation Period.</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <serious_events>
        <default_vocab>MedDRA 20.1</default_vocab>
        <default_assessment>Systematic Assessment</default_assessment>
        <category_list>
          <category>
            <title>Total</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, all-cause mortality</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="24"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="45"/>
                <counts group_id="E3" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="69"/>
                <counts group_id="E4" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="36"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, serious adverse events</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="24"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="3" subjects_at_risk="45"/>
                <counts group_id="E3" subjects_affected="4" subjects_at_risk="69"/>
                <counts group_id="E4" subjects_affected="13" subjects_at_risk="36"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Blood and lymphatic system disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Lymphopenia</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="24"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="45"/>
                <counts group_id="E3" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="69"/>
                <counts group_id="E4" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="36"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Sickle cell anaemia with crisis</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="24"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="45"/>
                <counts group_id="E3" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="69"/>
                <counts group_id="E4" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="36"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Gastrointestinal disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Diarrhoea</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="24"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="45"/>
                <counts group_id="E3" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="69"/>
                <counts group_id="E4" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="36"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Vomiting</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="24"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="45"/>
                <counts group_id="E3" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="69"/>
                <counts group_id="E4" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="36"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>General disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Breakthrough pain</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="24"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="45"/>
                <counts group_id="E3" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="69"/>
                <counts group_id="E4" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="36"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Malaise</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="24"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="45"/>
                <counts group_id="E3" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="69"/>
                <counts group_id="E4" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="36"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Mucosal inflammation</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="24"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="45"/>
                <counts group_id="E3" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="69"/>
                <counts group_id="E4" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="36"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Pain</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="24"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="45"/>
                <counts group_id="E3" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="69"/>
                <counts group_id="E4" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="36"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Pyrexia</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="24"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="45"/>
                <counts group_id="E3" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="69"/>
                <counts group_id="E4" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="36"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Infections and infestations</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Appendicitis</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="24"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="45"/>
                <counts group_id="E3" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="69"/>
                <counts group_id="E4" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="36"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Application site infection</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="24"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="45"/>
                <counts group_id="E3" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="69"/>
                <counts group_id="E4" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="36"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Clostridium difficile infection</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="24"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="45"/>
                <counts group_id="E3" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="69"/>
                <counts group_id="E4" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="36"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Cystitis</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="24"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="45"/>
                <counts group_id="E3" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="69"/>
                <counts group_id="E4" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="36"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Herpes zoster</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="24"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="45"/>
                <counts group_id="E3" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="69"/>
                <counts group_id="E4" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="36"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Infection</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="24"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="45"/>
                <counts group_id="E3" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="69"/>
                <counts group_id="E4" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="36"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Injury, poisoning and procedural complications</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Fall</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="24"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="45"/>
                <counts group_id="E3" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="69"/>
                <counts group_id="E4" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="36"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Investigations</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>White blood cell count decreased</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="24"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="45"/>
                <counts group_id="E3" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="69"/>
                <counts group_id="E4" events="3" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="36"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Neoplasms benign, malignant and unspecified (incl cysts and polyps)</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Malignant neoplasm progression</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="24"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="45"/>
                <counts group_id="E3" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="69"/>
                <counts group_id="E4" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="36"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Nervous system disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Movement disorder</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="24"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="45"/>
                <counts group_id="E3" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="69"/>
                <counts group_id="E4" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="36"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Neuralgia</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="24"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="45"/>
                <counts group_id="E3" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="69"/>
                <counts group_id="E4" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="36"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Somnolence</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="24"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="45"/>
                <counts group_id="E3" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="69"/>
                <counts group_id="E4" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="36"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Psychiatric disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Dissociation</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="24"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="45"/>
                <counts group_id="E3" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="69"/>
                <counts group_id="E4" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="36"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Renal and urinary disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Acute kidney injury</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="24"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="45"/>
                <counts group_id="E3" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="69"/>
                <counts group_id="E4" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="36"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Cutaneous lupus erythematosus</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="24"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="45"/>
                <counts group_id="E3" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="69"/>
                <counts group_id="E4" events="2" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="36"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Surgical and medical procedures</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Limb operation</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="24"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="45"/>
                <counts group_id="E3" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="69"/>
                <counts group_id="E4" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="36"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Vascular disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Thrombophlebitis superficial</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="24"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="45"/>
                <counts group_id="E3" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="69"/>
                <counts group_id="E4" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="36"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
        </category_list>
      </serious_events>
      <other_events>
        <frequency_threshold>5</frequency_threshold>
        <default_vocab>MedDRA 20.1</default_vocab>
        <default_assessment>Systematic Assessment</default_assessment>
        <category_list>
          <category>
            <title>Total</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, other adverse events</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="11" subjects_at_risk="24"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="26" subjects_at_risk="45"/>
                <counts group_id="E3" subjects_affected="37" subjects_at_risk="69"/>
                <counts group_id="E4" subjects_affected="30" subjects_at_risk="36"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Blood and lymphatic system disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Anaemia</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="24"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="45"/>
                <counts group_id="E3" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="69"/>
                <counts group_id="E4" events="3" subjects_affected="3" subjects_at_risk="36"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Neutropenia</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="24"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="45"/>
                <counts group_id="E3" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="69"/>
                <counts group_id="E4" events="2" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="36"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Thrombocytopenia</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="24"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="45"/>
                <counts group_id="E3" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="69"/>
                <counts group_id="E4" events="4" subjects_affected="3" subjects_at_risk="36"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Gastrointestinal disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Abdominal pain</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="24"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="7" subjects_affected="6" subjects_at_risk="45"/>
                <counts group_id="E3" events="7" subjects_affected="6" subjects_at_risk="69"/>
                <counts group_id="E4" events="6" subjects_affected="3" subjects_at_risk="36"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Abdominal pain upper</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="2" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="24"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="45"/>
                <counts group_id="E3" events="2" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="69"/>
                <counts group_id="E4" events="3" subjects_affected="3" subjects_at_risk="36"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Constipation</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="4" subjects_affected="4" subjects_at_risk="24"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="7" subjects_affected="7" subjects_at_risk="45"/>
                <counts group_id="E3" events="11" subjects_affected="11" subjects_at_risk="69"/>
                <counts group_id="E4" events="6" subjects_affected="5" subjects_at_risk="36"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Diarrhoea</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="24"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="3" subjects_affected="3" subjects_at_risk="45"/>
                <counts group_id="E3" events="4" subjects_affected="4" subjects_at_risk="69"/>
                <counts group_id="E4" events="3" subjects_affected="3" subjects_at_risk="36"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Nausea</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="5" subjects_affected="4" subjects_at_risk="24"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="10" subjects_affected="10" subjects_at_risk="45"/>
                <counts group_id="E3" events="15" subjects_affected="14" subjects_at_risk="69"/>
                <counts group_id="E4" events="18" subjects_affected="11" subjects_at_risk="36"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Toothache</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="24"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="45"/>
                <counts group_id="E3" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="69"/>
                <counts group_id="E4" events="3" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="36"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Vomiting</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="9" subjects_affected="7" subjects_at_risk="24"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="6" subjects_affected="6" subjects_at_risk="45"/>
                <counts group_id="E3" events="16" subjects_affected="14" subjects_at_risk="69"/>
                <counts group_id="E4" events="5" subjects_affected="5" subjects_at_risk="36"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>General disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Fatigue</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="3" subjects_affected="3" subjects_at_risk="24"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="2" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="45"/>
                <counts group_id="E3" events="5" subjects_affected="5" subjects_at_risk="69"/>
                <counts group_id="E4" events="3" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="36"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Pyrexia</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="24"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="5" subjects_affected="3" subjects_at_risk="45"/>
                <counts group_id="E3" events="6" subjects_affected="4" subjects_at_risk="69"/>
                <counts group_id="E4" events="4" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="36"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Infections and infestations</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Nasopharyngitis</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="24"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="45"/>
                <counts group_id="E3" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="69"/>
                <counts group_id="E4" events="7" subjects_affected="5" subjects_at_risk="36"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Metabolism and nutrition disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Hypokalaemia</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="24"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="45"/>
                <counts group_id="E3" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="69"/>
                <counts group_id="E4" events="2" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="36"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Musculoskeletal and connective tissue disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Back pain</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="24"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="3" subjects_affected="3" subjects_at_risk="45"/>
                <counts group_id="E3" events="3" subjects_affected="3" subjects_at_risk="69"/>
                <counts group_id="E4" events="5" subjects_affected="5" subjects_at_risk="36"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Pain in extremity</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="24"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="2" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="45"/>
                <counts group_id="E3" events="2" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="69"/>
                <counts group_id="E4" events="9" subjects_affected="3" subjects_at_risk="36"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Nervous system disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Dizziness</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="24"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="4" subjects_affected="4" subjects_at_risk="45"/>
                <counts group_id="E3" events="4" subjects_affected="4" subjects_at_risk="69"/>
                <counts group_id="E4" events="2" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="36"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Dysarthria</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="2" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="24"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="45"/>
                <counts group_id="E3" events="2" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="69"/>
                <counts group_id="E4" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="36"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Headache</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="3" subjects_affected="3" subjects_at_risk="24"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="9" subjects_affected="6" subjects_at_risk="45"/>
                <counts group_id="E3" events="12" subjects_affected="9" subjects_at_risk="69"/>
                <counts group_id="E4" events="24" subjects_affected="10" subjects_at_risk="36"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Paraesthesia</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="24"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="45"/>
                <counts group_id="E3" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="69"/>
                <counts group_id="E4" events="2" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="36"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Somnolence</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="2" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="24"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="45"/>
                <counts group_id="E3" events="2" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="69"/>
                <counts group_id="E4" events="2" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="36"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Psychiatric disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Nightmare</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="24"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="45"/>
                <counts group_id="E3" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="69"/>
                <counts group_id="E4" events="3" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="36"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Sleep disorder</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="24"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="45"/>
                <counts group_id="E3" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="69"/>
                <counts group_id="E4" events="2" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="36"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Renal and urinary disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Dysuria</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="2" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="24"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="45"/>
                <counts group_id="E3" events="2" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="69"/>
                <counts group_id="E4" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="36"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Respiratory, thoracic and mediastinal disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Cough</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="24"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="45"/>
                <counts group_id="E3" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="69"/>
                <counts group_id="E4" events="2" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="36"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Oropharyngeal pain</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="24"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="45"/>
                <counts group_id="E3" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="69"/>
                <counts group_id="E4" events="4" subjects_affected="4" subjects_at_risk="36"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Pruritus</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="3" subjects_affected="3" subjects_at_risk="24"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="45"/>
                <counts group_id="E3" events="4" subjects_affected="4" subjects_at_risk="69"/>
                <counts group_id="E4" events="2" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="36"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
        </category_list>
      </other_events>
    </reported_events>

    <certain_agreements>
      <pi_employee>Principal Investigators are NOT employed by the organization sponsoring the study.</pi_employee>
      <restrictive_agreement>The sponsor reserves the right to review any proposed presentation of the results of this trial before they are submitted for publication or public disclosure. Neither party (e.g., the sponsor, the coordinating investigator) has the right to prohibit publication or public disclosure unless it can be shown to affect possible patent rights.</restrictive_agreement>
    </certain_agreements>
    <point_of_contact>
      <name_or_title>Clinical Trial Helpdesk</name_or_title>
      <organization>Grünenthal GmbH</organization>
      <phone>+49-(0)241-569 ext 3223</phone>
      <email>clinical-trials@grunenthal.com</email>
    </point_of_contact>
  </clinical_results>
</clinical_study>

