<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03912753</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>R01MH116829</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03912753</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Building Mobile HIV Prevention and Mental Health Support in Low-resource Settings</brief_title>
  <official_title>Building Mobile HIV Prevention and Mental Health Support in Low-resource Settings</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Rutgers University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Yale University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Rutgers University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This project is designed to remedy unaddressed and interlocking HIV-prevention and mental
      health needs among gay and bisexual men (GBM) in the Central Eastern European country of
      Romania, and their underpinning stigma-related mechanisms. Rampant stigma contributes to the
      increasing prevalence of HIV among Romanian GBM (from under 10% in 2009 to close to 20% in
      2014, by best available estimates) and keeps GBM out-of-reach of HIV-prevention services. An
      mHealth pilot intervention (titled &quot;Despre Mine. Despre Noi.&quot; [DMDN] translated as &quot;About Me.
      About Us.&quot;), which reduced Romanian GBM's risk for HIV infection while also reducing
      depression and alcohol abuse in an initial pre-post trial, is now ready for testing in a
      randomized controlled trial with a large national sample in the current study, entitled
      Comunică (translation: Communicate). The Comunică intervention entails eight 60-minute live
      chat sessions delivered by trained counselors on a mobile study platform using motivational
      interviewing (MI) and cognitive-behavioral skills training (CBST). First, during pre-trial
      (mos 1-5), in collaboration with a community advisory board consisting of GBM community
      members, GBM-affirmative physical and mental health providers, and a technical developer, the
      investigators will fine-tune the Comunică intervention based on the investigators' pilot
      findings and evaluation interviews, and expand the original DMDN education materials for an
      education attention condition (EAC) that will serve as control. Second, during the
      intervention phase (mos 6-45), the investigators will recruit, screen, assess, and randomize
      GBM at risk for HIV infection and alcohol abuse to either the Comunică intervention (n=163)
      or EAC (n=163). The conditions are content matched, and both are hosted on the study
      platform. While Comunică will consist of eight weekly mHealth live chat sessions, EAC will
      consist of eight self-administered educational modules. Third, during the follow-up phase
      (mos 8-55), the investigators will assess at 4, 8, and 12 months post-baseline, in a mobile
      fashion identical to the baseline, the primary outcome of condomless anal sex with male
      partners and secondary outcomes of alcohol abuse, depression, biologic HIV/STI infection,
      HIV/STI testing, and psychosocial mechanisms rooted in the Information-Motivation-Behavioral
      Skills (IMB) model (e.g., HIV/STI knowledge, condom use self-efficacy) and minority stress
      theory (e.g., identity concealment, internalized homophobia).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Recruitment. Cities. 326 GBM living in or 40-miles within 10 cities (i.e., București, Brașov,
      Timișoara, Cluj-Napoca, Iași, Constanța, Suceava, Craiova, Galați, Satu Mare) will be
      recruited and screened for the trial. In selecting these cities, the investigators sought to
      cover all regions of the country and capture areas of increasing HIV risk.

      Numbers. The investigators set the study total sample at 326 based on power calculations (136
      participants will finish per arm accounting for a conservative 20% attrition).

      Venues. The investigators will post study ads on local collaborators' websites, subscriber
      lists, and key virtual venues (e.g., Grindr, Facebook), as in the pilot successful pilot,
      where 45% of participants were recruited on Grindr and 41% on Facebook. The investigators
      will also recruit using word-of-mouth. Trained recruitment staff will approach men in
      GBM-prevalent venues (bars; known public cruising areas, such as central train stations)
      across 10 cities. Recruitment staff will conduct quarterly recruitment trips to 9 cities (as
      they reside in Bucharest) following a rotating schedule. Furthermore, pilot participants who
      agreed to be contacted for the very purpose of recruiting within their GBM networks will
      advertise the study within these networks. Finally, enrolled participants will be encouraged
      to spread the word.

      Screening. Potential participants will complete an eligibility screener on Qualtrics.com, a
      research-designated secure online software. Eligible GBM will have the option to provide
      contact information at the end of the screener, in a separate survey, in order for research
      staff to later contact them for consent.

      Consent. Eligible participants will be contacted within days of screening for consent by
      affiliated project staff with whom the investigators collaborated on the pilot. Participants
      will be assigned a numeric identification and undergo the phone consent process used in the
      pilot. Research staff and participants will read through the entire electronic consent
      document (10 min). Points of confusion will be clarified and those still interested in
      participating will submit an electronic consent.

      Baseline assessment. After consent, participants will be sent their unique study ID and an
      electronic link to their Qualtrics-based baseline (BL) assessment (45 min).

      Randomization. After BL, participants will be block randomized to the Comunică (n=163) or EAC
      (n=163) condition. Qualtrics will stratify participants into randomly chosen blocks of 4 and
      6 according to: baseline # CAS acts and # past-3-mo alcohol abuse days. After HIV/STI testing
      (below), Comunică participants will be randomly assigned to counselors so that all counselors
      always have an equal case load. Counselors will contact their assigned participants via
      preferred contact method to schedule the first session, when they will both log onto the
      mHealth platform. Comunică sessions and EAC modules span 3 months. Participants can use any
      mobile device (smartphone, tablet, laptop).

      Comunică Intervention. The intervention aims to support GBM in reducing their CAS and alcohol
      abuse and improving their mental health. Comunică is delivered over eight 60-min live chat
      sessions on an mHealth study platform compatible with any mobile device (laptops,
      smartphones). Comunică is based on the Information-Motivation-Behavioral Skills (IMB) model
      of health behavior change, which postulates that individuals must possess the requisite
      information for enacting sexual health, motivation to change their HIV risk and alcohol use,
      and behavioral skills necessary for reducing their risk. Therefore, Comunică includes MI to
      provide accurate information about HIV transmission, alcohol abuse, and local GBM-affirmative
      health resources (e.g., HIV-testing sites) and build motivation to improve behavioral skills
      (via CBST). MI is an evidence-based form of person-centered therapeutic communication that
      privileges client values and preferences for change to help individuals resolve ambivalence
      and move toward their valued goals. Skills-building is often a natural outcome of MI,
      especially for individuals who attain a high degree of motivation for change. CBST is a
      therapeutic approach used in the treatment of various behavioral problems, such as alcohol
      abuse and depression and more recently HIV risk. CBST can help modify cognitions driving
      unhealthy behaviors, promote awareness of contextual triggers and unhealthy behavioral
      patterns, and teach coping skills to improve health. Comunică also draws upon minority stress
      theory recognizing that stigmatizing societal contexts compromise health behavior. GBM in
      highly stigmatizing contexts such as Romania experience a lack of structural protections
      (e.g., national policies), institutional support (e.g., GBM-affirmative healthcare), and
      coping resources (e.g., social support). Thus, the CBST skills in Comunică are presented in a
      manner that acknowledges the barriers that social stigma poses to GBM's health, while
      empowering them to circumvent these barriers by building self-efficacy, effective
      communication, and planful problem-solving. All participants will receive referrals to
      GBM-affirmative psychologists trained by the investigators. DMDN Safety. Protocols include
      instructions for protecting participants' identities, data, and safety. Comunică is unable to
      address pre-exposure prophylaxis (PrEP). PrEP is not available in Romania and it would be
      unhelpful and likely unethical to discuss this inaccessible prevention tool. However, the
      investigators' long-term agenda includes working with NGOs to promote PrEP in Romania.

      The EAC Condition. The EAC condition consists of eight modularized topics (Appendix 1),
      content-matched with the Comunică sessions, which the investigators have generated based on
      HIV-prevention education with GBM in the US and Romania. Topics include 1) GBM identity, 2)
      &quot;HIV 101,&quot; 3) HIV/STI testing, 4) alcohol and the body, 5) the role of alcohol in HIV risk,
      6) HIV-status disclosure and sexual health communication, 7) IPV and finding social supports,
      and 8) summary. The content is preliminary and will be refined with the CAB. To maintain
      uniformity of information exposure across participants and maximize learning, each screen
      will be timed at a comfortable speed and participants will be unable to advance to the next
      screen prior to the set time limit. EAC participants will receive five quiz questions after
      each module, with correct answers in a following screen.

      Retention. The investigators will utilize retention strategies that yielded a 93% retention
      rate from BL to 26-month follow-up in the pilot. The investigators will: 1) build strong
      rapport, 2) update contact information often, 3) use all means of communication permitted by
      participants, and 4) send frequent reminders.

      HIV/STI Testing, Counseling, and Linkage to Services. All study participants will be tested
      for HIV, gonorrhea, and chlamydia at BL and 12-month follow-up, and, if positive, will be
      linked to care. The investigators have developed the HIV/STI protocol with ARAS (translated
      as the Romanian Association against AIDS), which contributes a 25-year experience in HIV/STI
      testing and care and demonstrates unusually high GBM-sensitive testing expertise for Romania.
      The investigators will convene with ARAS testing counselors to review protocols and set up
      all communication systems (i.e., with participants, IDPs) and results reporting. Procedures.
      After consent, the Project Coordinator will provide ARAS with the participant's information.
      An assigned ARAS testing counselor will contact the participant to provide two options: 1)
      mail an HIV/STI test kit to their home or 2) have the participant pick up the test at the
      study's infectious disease physician's (IDP) office in the region where the participant
      lives. The investigators provide these options based on the feedback they received from
      Romanian GBM, some of whom prefer not to receive such a package at home due to privacy
      concerns. Testing. Participants will receive a self-testing kit containing an HIV and
      syphilis test by drawing one drop of blood from their finger, and swabs and urine collection
      container for pharyngeal, rectal and urethral testing of chlamydia and gonorrhea (Cobas®
      Taqman® CT/NG PCR, Roche Molecular Diagnostics) to be performed by SH24, a UK-based partner
      for HIV/STI testing service. The kits will contain instructions in Romanian, and the ARAS
      testing counselors will conduct phone-based VCT and walk participants through testing steps.
      After self-testing, participants will mail the specimens in a prepaid discrete envelope to
      ARAS, who will then mail those to SH24 for analysis. SH24 will report results to ARAS within
      3-5 days, at which time ARAS counselors will call participants to discuss results.
      Confidentiality of results will be stressed during consent and contact with ARAS staff, and
      on the kit instructions. Counseling. The investigators base their testing protocols on the
      CDC's voluntary counseling and testing (VCT) guidelines and WHO guidelines for self-testing.
      VCT will consist of one 45-min phone session. By phone, ARAS HIV-test counselors will conduct
      pre-test counseling for all participants and post-testing counseling for positive or
      inconclusive results, with linkage to care to local study-affiliated IDPs. Home testing has
      proven to be highly acceptable globally Only participants who receive an HIV-negative test
      result are eligible to participate in the study. Test result reporting. SH24 will report STI
      results to participants and ARAS. Negative results. Participants will be encouraged by the
      ARAS counselor to re-test every three months with the IDP in their area. IDP information will
      be provided on the online study platforms of all participants. Positive or inconclusive
      results. Instructions about steps to follow for reactive tests will be included in the
      testing kit and will be repeated by the ARAS counselor on the phone. The participant will
      receive the name and contact information of the study-affiliated IDP in their area.

      Baseline (BL), 4-, 8-, and 12-month assessments. The project coordinator will send a link to
      the BL survey to all HIV-negative participants, and tell them that they will be contacted by
      their counselor after submitting the survey. The quarterly self-administered mobile
      assessments are identical, take 45 min. to complete, have been validated by the Romanian
      pilot gay and bisexual men participants, and assess: 1) sexual behavior (e.g., # condomless
      anal sex acts; number and types of partners; sex under the influence) and 2) past-3-mo
      alcohol use; 3) depressive symptoms; 4) HIV/STI testing and other healthcare access (e.g.,
      annual exams; mental health) patterns; 5) hypothesized mediators of intervention efficacy,
      including IMB model components (e.g., HIV-risk-related information, motivation, behavioral
      skills) and minority stress or (e.g., outness, internalized homonegativity, collective
      self-worth); 6) demographics and psychosocial risk contexts. During the follow-up phase (mos
      8-55), the investigators will assess at 4, 8, and 12-mos post-baseline, in the same mobile
      fashion as the baseline, the primary outcome of condomless anal sex (CAS) with male partners,
      and secondary outcomes of alcohol abuse, depression, biologic HIV/STI infection, HIV/STI
      testing, and psychosocial mechanisms rooted in the Information-Motivation-Behavioral Skills
      (IMB) model (e.g., HIV/STI knowledge, condom use self-efficacy) and minority stress theory
      (e.g., identity concealment, stigma consciousness).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 13, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>We will recruit, screen, assess, and randomize gay and bisexual men at risk for HIV infection and alcohol abuse to either the Comunică intervention (n=163) or EAC (n=163). The conditions are content matched, and both are hosted on our study platform. While Comunică will consist of eight weekly mHealth live chat sessions, EAC will consist of eight self-administered educational modules. We we will assess at baseline, and 4, 8, and 12 months post-baseline, in a mobile fashion identical to the baseline, the primary outcome of condomless anal sex with male partners and secondary outcomes of alcohol abuse, depression, biologic HIV/STI infection, HIV/STI testing, and psychosocial mechanisms rooted in the Information-Motivation-Behavioral Skills (IMB) model (e.g., HIV/STI knowledge, condom use self-efficacy) and minority stress theory (e.g., identity concealment, internalized homophobia).</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Timeline Followback for Online Use: (Sexual behavior)</measure>
    <time_frame>From change baseline to each follow-up assessment point (4, 8, and 12 months post-training)</time_frame>
    <description>TLFB assesses sexual behavior in the past three months. It collects retrospective day-level data and has been validated for online self-administration. The TLFB has good test-retest reliability, convergent validity, and agreement with collateral reports for sexand alcohol use. Participants will report on daily partner type (e.g. primary), type of sexual behavior (e.g. insertive anal), and condom use. Median cronbach's alpha is 0.96.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Timeline Followback for Online Use: (Alcohol use)</measure>
    <time_frame>From change baseline to each follow-up assessment point (4, 8, and 12 months post-training)</time_frame>
    <description>The TLFB tool will also ask participants to report on alcohol heavy use alone, and before/during sex, in the previous 90 days.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Alcohol Use Disorders Identification Test (AUDIT)</measure>
    <time_frame>From change baseline to each follow-up assessment point (4, 8, and 12 months post-training)</time_frame>
    <description>AUDIT is a 10-item screening tool use to assess alcohol consumption, drinking behaviors, and alcohol-related problems. Participants will report on standard drinks. A score of 8 or more is considered to indicate hazardous or harmful alcohol use. Cronbach's alpha is 0.82.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Center for Epidemiologic Studies Depression Scale (CES-D)</measure>
    <time_frame>From change baseline to each follow-up assessment point (4, 8, and 12 months post-training)</time_frame>
    <description>CES-D is a self-report, standardized measure for depressive symptoms. It consists of 20-items in which respondents rate how frequently each item applied to them over the course of the past week. Ratings are based on a 4-point Likert scale ranging from 0 (rarely or none of the time [less than 1 day]) to 3 (most or all of the time [5-7 days]). Cronbach's alpha coefficients ranging from .85 to .90 across studies.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Beck's Anxiety Inventory (BAI)</measure>
    <time_frame>From change baseline to each follow-up assessment point (4, 8, and 12 months post-training)</time_frame>
    <description>BAI is a brief self-report measure of anxiety with a focus on somatic symptoms of anxiety that was developed as a measure adept at discriminating between anxiety and depression. It consists of 21 items and respondents indicate how much they have been bothered by each symptom over the past week. Responses are rated on a 4‐point Likert scale and range from 0 (not at all) to 3 (severely). Cronbach's alpha is 0.94</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>HIV Knowledge Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>From change baseline to each follow-up assessment point (4, 8, and 12 months post-training)</time_frame>
    <description>It is a 18-item, brief self-report measure of HIV-related knowledge. Respondents read each statements about HIV and indicate whether they think the statement is true or false, or they indicate that they &quot;don't know.&quot; Cronbach's alpha ranges from 0.75-0.89.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Alcohol Effects Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>From change baseline to each follow-up assessment point (4, 8, and 12 months post-training)</time_frame>
    <description>This is a 10-item scale asking about alcohol use-related knowledge (e.g., &quot;Beer usually contains from 2-12% alcohol by volume&quot;) with responses being 0=I don't know, 1=True and 2=False. Cronbach's alpha is 0.86.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>SOCRATES Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>From change baseline to each follow-up assessment point (4, 8, and 12 months post-training)</time_frame>
    <description>The SOCRATES is a 19-item, self-administered instrument designed to assess client motivation to change drinking-related behavior. It is made up of three scales: Problem Recognition, Ambivalence, and Taking Steps. Respondents rate their agreement with each item on a 5-point Likert-type scale (from strongly disagree to strongly agree). Cronbach's alpha ranges from 0.88-0.0.96 across three subscales.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Decisional Balance (motivation to use condoms)</measure>
    <time_frame>From change baseline to each follow-up assessment point (4, 8, and 12 months post-training)</time_frame>
    <description>This 18-item scale measures one's motivation to increase condom use (e.g., &quot;I would feel bad if my friends found out I had sex without a condom&quot;), with response options ranging between 1=not at all to 5=extremely. Cronbach's alpha is 0.88.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Safer-Sex Self-Efficacy Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>From change baseline to each follow-up assessment point (4, 8, and 12 months post-training)</time_frame>
    <description>It is a 13-item scale that measures behavioral self-efficacy skills to increase condom use. Cronbach's alpha is 0.88.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Confidence in Reducing Alcohol Use Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>From change baseline to each follow-up assessment point (4, 8, and 12 months post-training)</time_frame>
    <description>It is a 15-item scale that measures behavioral self-efficacy skills to reduce alcohol use. . Cronbach's alpha ranges from 0.79 - 0.95.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Rejection Sensitivity Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>From change baseline to each follow-up assessment point (4, 8, and 12 months post-training)</time_frame>
    <description>It is a 14 items gay-related rejection sensitivity measure. Participants first indicated how concerned or anxious they would be that the situation occurred because of their sexual orientation. They then indicated the likelihood that the situation occurred because of their sexual orientation. Cronbach's alpha is .91.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Sexual Orientation Concealment Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>From change baseline to each follow-up assessment point (4, 8, and 12 months post-training)</time_frame>
    <description>It is a 6-item measure designed to assess lesbian, gay, and bisexual (LGB) individual's active concealment of their sexual minority status. Items were derived from literature on sexual orientation identity management and include items reflecting use of avoidance strategies (i.e., evading circumstances that would implicate one as LGB) and counterfeiting strategies (i.e., constructing a false guise of heterosexuality). Respondents were asked to &quot;rate each item to complete the following phrase: In the last 2 weeks, I have . . .&quot; using a fully anchored rating scale (1 not at all, 2 a little bit, 3 somewhat, 4 very much, 5 all the time).</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Assertiveness Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>From change baseline to each follow-up assessment point (4, 8, and 12 months post-training)</time_frame>
    <description>A 30-item self-report which measure assertive behaviors. The items include statamenst like &quot;Most people seem to be more aggressive and assertive than I am&quot;, &quot;When I am asked to do something, I insist upon knowing why&quot; etc. The responses ranges from 3, very much like me to -3 very much unlike me. Scores on the assertiveness schedule can vary from +90 to -90.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Multidimensional Measure of Sexual Minority Identity</measure>
    <time_frame>From change baseline to each follow-up assessment point (4, 8, and 12 months post-training)</time_frame>
    <description>It is a 27 items self-report that measure acceptance, concealment motivation, identity affirmation, etc.of sexual minority populations.Cronbach's alpha ranges from 0.78-0.86.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>LGBT Victimization Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>From baseline to each follow-up assessment point (4, 8, and 12 months post-training)</time_frame>
    <description>A 10-item measure that assesses the frequency of experiences of victimization in the previous 6 months &quot;because you are, or were thought to be, gay, lesbian, bisexual, or transgender.&quot; Items addressed verbal threats and insults, being chased, having property damaged, and being physically or sexually assaulted. Cronbach alpha is .86.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Multidimensional Scale of Perceived Social Support</measure>
    <time_frame>From change baseline to each follow-up assessment point (4, 8, and 12 months post-training)</time_frame>
    <description>MSPSS is a 12-item scale designed to measure perceived social support from three sources: Family, Friends, and a Significant Other. It is rated on a seven-point Likert-type scale with scores ranging from 'very strongly disagree' (1) to 'very strongly agree' (7). The MSPSS has proven to be psychometrically sound in diverse samples and to have good internal reliability and test-retest reliability, and robust factorial validity.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">326</enrollment>
  <condition>Human Immunodeficiency Virus</condition>
  <condition>Risk Reduction</condition>
  <condition>Alcohol Abuse</condition>
  <condition>Depression, Anxiety</condition>
  <condition>Behavior, Sex</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Comunică</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Comunică is delivered over eight 60-min live chat sessions, delivered by trained psychologists, on our mHealth study platform compatible with any mobile device (laptops, smartphones).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Education Attention Control (EAC)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The EAC condition consists of eight self-administered modularized topics, content-matched with the Comunică sessions, which we have generated based on our HIV-prevention education with GBM in the US and Romania.Topics include 1) GBM identity, 2) &quot;HIV 101,&quot; 3) HIV/STI testing, 4) alcohol and the body, 5) the role of alcohol in HIV risk, 6) HIV-status disclosure and sexual health communication, 7) finding social supports, and 8) summary. EAC participants will receive five quiz questions after each module, with correct answers in a following screen.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Comunică</intervention_name>
    <description>Comunică is based on the Information-Motivation-Behavioral Skills (IMB) model of health behavior change, which postulates that individuals must possess the requisite information for enacting sexual health, motivation to change their HIV risk and alcohol use, and behavioral skills necessary for reducing their risk. Therefore, Comunică includes MI to provide accurate information about HIV transmission, alcohol abuse, and local GBM-affirmative health resources and build motivation to improve behavioral skills (via CBST). CBST is a therapeutic approach used in the treatment of various behavioral problems, such as alcohol abuse and depression and more recently HIV risk. CBST can help modify cognitions driving unhealthy behaviors, promote awareness of contextual triggers and unhealthy behavioral patterns, and teach coping skills to improve health. Comunică also draws upon minority stress theory recognizing that stigmatizing societal contexts compromise health behavior.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Comunică</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Education Attention Control</intervention_name>
    <description>The EAC condition consists of eight self-administered modularized topics, content-matched with the Comunică sessions, which we have generated based on our HIV-prevention education with GBM in the US and Romania.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Education Attention Control (EAC)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Gay and bisexual men will be eligible if they report: 1) male sex at birth and current
             male identity; 2) ≥ age 16; 3) ≥ 3 acts of condomless anal sex with an HIV-positive or
             status-unknown male partner in the prior 3 months; 4) ≥ 15 heavy drinking days in the
             prior 3 months, (e.g., binge drinking as defined by SAMHSA: ≥ 5 standard alcoholic
             drinks on five occasions per month); 5) own a mobile device (smartphone, tablet,
             laptop); and 6) are confirmed to be HIV-negative upon testing at study baseline.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  As severe mental illness poses barriers to participation, GMB will be excluded if they
             report past-year: (a) psychiatric hospitalization, (b) psychotic and manic symptoms,
             or (c) current mood-stabilizing or anti-psychotic medication prescription. Lastly, we
             will exclude participants based on any condition that, in the principal investigators'
             judgment, interferes with safe study participation.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <gender_based>Yes</gender_based>
    <gender_description>Biological males at birth who currently identify as male</gender_description>
    <minimum_age>16 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Corina Lelutiu-Weinberger, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Rutgers University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>John E Pachankis, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Yale University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Corina Lelutiu-Weinberger, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>973-972-2093</phone>
    <email>cl1148@sn.rutgers.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>John E Pachankis, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>203-785-3710</phone>
    <email>john.pachankis@yale.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Romanian Association against AIDS (ARAS)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bucharest</city>
        <state>Ilfov</state>
        <country>Romania</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Mihai Lixandru</last_name>
      <phone>+40213190771</phone>
      <email>mihai.lixandru@arasnet.ro</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Romania</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>April 2, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 10, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 11, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 31, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 31, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 5, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Rutgers University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Corina Lelutiu-Weinberger</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Acquired Immunodeficiency Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>HIV Infections</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Alcoholism</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

