<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03914482</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>6186</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03914482</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Fatty Liver Imaging Project ( FLIP ) Patient Pilot Study</brief_title>
  <acronym>FLIP</acronym>
  <official_title>Feasibility Study to Estimate Fat Concentration of Liver in Adults Through RF Imaging</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Aaron Fenster</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Endra Life Sciences</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Western University, Canada</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study is being done to test the FLIP device, a novel device developed and manufactured
      by Endra Life Sciences, located in Ann Arbor, Michigan. The purpose of the device is to
      measure the fat content of liver tissue to assist in the diagnosis of fatty liver disease.
      This feasibility study will involve 50 patients having their liver imaged by traditional
      ultrasound and MRI methods as well as using the FLIP device. The data obtained by the FLIP
      will be compared with the data obtained by ultrasound and MRI in order to determine the
      effectiveness of the device. This is a preliminary study to see if the investigational device
      could eventually be used to image the liver alongside traditional ultrasound for discerning
      fat concentration.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      It has been demonstrated that thermoacoustic imaging can be used to identify water and fat
      concentrations [Bauer, 2012]. In addition, the group led by Dr. Kruger have demonstrated that
      conventional computed tomography shows similar features to thermoacoustic imaging in small
      animal studies [Kruger, 2003]. These concepts have led Endra Life Sciences to develop the
      FLIP device with the purpose of imaging fat concentration in liver tissue with indications
      for fatty liver disease. Non-alcoholic fatty liver disease (NAFLD) was first reported in 1980
      by pathologists at the Mayo clinic in obese, or overweight, patients with no history of
      alcohol abuse. This represented the first time that fatty livers were observed with no
      history of alcohol abuse. Since that first report of NAFLD, increased rates of obesity and
      general increased caloric intake has dramatically increased rates of fatty liver disease.
      Estimates of NAFLD range from 25 - 40% of the adult population globally. NAFLD is a
      multi-system disease. Fatty liver disease is highly correlated with obesity and alcohol
      abuse, and is an important biomarker of insulin resistance and metabolic disease. Endra's
      technology offers a non-invasive, cost effective point of care solution to monitoring liver
      fat content that will be enormously helpful in surveilling patients with metabolic disease,
      insulin resistance, and those at risk for later stage liver disease. This study will provide
      additional information that will guide the further development of the FLIP device with the
      end goal of commercializing the product. Fibroscan is a device that is currently on the
      market that is also indicated for fatty liver disease. Fibroscan is a shear wave elastography
      device that measures the stiffness of liver tissue by mechanically deforming tissue (by
      utilizing a plunger that vibrates the surface of the skin) and measures the resulting shear
      wave speed within the liver by ultrasound. The shear wave speed is related to the mechanical
      stiffness of the tissue. Fibroscan aims to assess the progression of infiltration of collagen
      into normal liver tissue that results in scarring, characteristic of fibrotic liver disease.
      Liver fibrosis progresses from fatty liver disease, not all fatty liver disease patients
      develop fibrotic liver disease. The Fibroscan device has an optional software module that
      attempts to quantify the attenuation of the shear wave as it travels away from the plane of
      deformation. Fibroscan refers to this measurement as CAP (Calculated Attenuation Parameter).
      The attenuation of the shear wave is thought to be related to the degree of liver steatosis
      (fat content).

      To date, the technique has demonstrated poor sensitivity, and is poorly correlated with
      quantitative MRI measures of liver fat. Furthermore, CAP measurements in obese patients are
      difficult to obtain and unreliable. Endra's technology aims to provide much more sensitive
      measurements of liver fat content at the point of care. The Endra device has the potential to
      quantify fat content as low as 5% (by volume). The system is interoperable with ultrasound
      and leverages B-mode ultrasound imaging to guide measurement location. Compared to
      Fibroscan's CAP, Endra's fatty liver measures are expected to be much more sensitive and
      reproducible based on anatomical guidance by ultrasound imaging.

      A healthy volunteer study was conducted to test the overall feasibility of the device in use
      in humans. The median liver fat percentage was in the normal range, less than six percent,
      which helped gauge the accuracy of using the device in detecting low levels of liver fat. In
      addition, the operator was able to optimize the use of the device on human scanning. Of the
      25 study subject datasets analyzed, only 4 subjects had above normal liver fat by MRI fat
      fraction (normal is &lt; 6% fat fraction). All 4 study subjects with &gt;6% liver fat fraction,
      fell into 'mild liver fat' grade that spans 6% - 26% fat fraction, with the maximum value of
      22%.

      Using all 25 study subject datasets the TAEUS investigational device measurement has an R^2
      correlation value of 0.61 with MRI measurements of fat fraction. This is particularly
      interesting as BMI and abdominal fat thickness were found to have R^2 correlation values with
      MRI measures of liver fat of 0.19 and 0.31, respectively.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">September 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Fat concentration estimate</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 1 month following data collection</time_frame>
    <description>The purpose of the device is to measure the fat content of liver tissue to assist in the diagnosis of fatty liver disease</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Fatty Liver</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Patients at risk of FLD</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients who choose to participate in the study that meet the inclusion criteria</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>MRI</intervention_name>
    <description>The device will acquire thermoacoustic data while the ultrasound probe acquires ultrasound images, and an MR of the liver is acquired as a comparative modality</description>
    <arm_group_label>Patients at risk of FLD</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Liver Imaging</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients which have had at least 1 appointment with a clinician for liver function,
             diabetes, or obesity in the past year.

          -  Must be over the age of 18.

          -  Mild (6-26%), moderate (26-37%), or high (&gt;37%) level of fat in the liver that is
             estimated by ultrasound imaging.

          -  Must be proficient in English (reading/writing).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Any metal or electronic implants including but not limited to pacemakers, metal clips,
             hips.

          -  Pregnancy
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Aaron Fenster</last_name>
    <phone>5199315777</phone>
    <email>afenster@uwo.ca</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>April 10, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 11, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 16, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 11, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 11, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 13, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Western University, Canada</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Aaron Fenster</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Scientist</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Fatty Liver</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

