<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03911323</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>20190401</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03911323</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Real-world Diagnostic Effectiveness of Artificial Intelligence Algorithm in Diabetic Retinopathy Screening</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Prospective Clinical Study on the Real-world Diagnostic Effectiveness of Artificial Intelligence Algorithm in Diabetic Retinopathy Screening</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Shenzhen Second People's Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Shenzhen Second People's Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Recently, artificial intelligence algorithm has made great progress in the prediction of
      diabetic retinopathy based on fundus images，showing very high sensitivity and specificity.
      However，the real-world diagnosis effectiveness of deep learning model is still unclear.

      This study is designed to evaluate the clinical efficacy of such an algorithm in detecting
      referable diabetic retinopathy.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This prospective clinical study is designed to evaluate the real-world diagnostic performance
      of an AI model in detecting referable diabetic retinopathy (RDR, defined as more than mild
      NPDR), by evaluating its sensitivity and specificity compared to the clinical reference
      standard- seven-field stereoscopic photography.

      The subjects enrolled in this study are patients with T1DM or T2DM. Qualified color fundus
      images and seven-field stereoscopic photography images of each eyes of the subject are taken.
      The fundus images are graded for RDR by the algorithm under test, and seven-field
      stereoscopic photography images of the same eye are graded by ophthalmologist, which serving
      as the gold standard to compare the algorithm performance against.

      The trial plans to enroll 1000 subjects. With a 95% confidence interval, the sensitivity is
      expected to be at least 87% whereas the specificity at 89% or above.

      The quality of fundus images are assessed according to the National DR Screening Imaging and
      Grading Guideline published by Chinese Ophthalmological Society and Chinese Medical Doctor
      Association in 2017.

      The grading of RDR is based on the National DR Clinical Diagnosis and Treatment Guideline
      published by Chinese Ophthalmological Society in 2014.

      A brief overview of the clinical protocol is as follows:

      Candidate recruiting phase: recruiting qualified participants; Clinical phase: imaging and
      diagnosing by AI and ophthalmologist ; Statistical analysis phase: comparing two outputs;
      Closing phase: final report and archiving
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 1, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 1, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 1, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Only</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Sensitivity and specificity</measure>
    <time_frame>No more than 1 day for each subject</time_frame>
    <description>To evaluate the sensitivity and specificity of the model in detecting referable DR (more than mild NPDR)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">1000</enrollment>
  <condition>Diabetic Retinopathy</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>diabetic retinopathy</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients with diabetes enrolled will undergo nonmydriatic fundus imaging and seven-field stereoscopic photography. The images will be run on an artificial intelligence (AI) algorithm. The diagnosis of the AI algorithm will be compared to the diagnosis of seven-field stereoscopic photography by ophthalmologist. Sensitivity and specificity will be calculated to evaluate the performance of AI algorithm.</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Diabetic patients who meet the eligibility criteria.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Subject must understand the study, participate voluntarily, and has signed informed
             consent

          2. Age 18 or older, no limitations on gender identity

          3. Patients with type 1 or type 2 diabetes.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Subjects diagnosed with eye diseases other than diabetic retinopathy

          2. Subjects diagnosed with macular edema, severe non-proliferative retinopathy,
             proliferative retinopathy, radioactive retinopathy or retinal vein obstruction.

          3. Pregnant woman, subjects with mydriatic allergy, unclear refractive medium, family
             history of glaucoma, or diagnosed as narrow angle

          4. Subjects with a history of laser therapy, retinal surgery or anti-vascular endothelial
             growth factor injection

          5. Subjects currently participating in another ophthalmic research, receiving ophthalmic
             research products.

          6. Subject who is photo-sensitivity or taking medication that causes photosensitivity

          7. Subjects received photodynamic therapy recently
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Lisha Mou, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Shenzhen Second People's Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Jiying Hu, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+86-1808-6481-821</phone>
    <email>18086481821@163.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Shenzhen second peoples's hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Shenzhen</city>
        <state>Guangdong</state>
        <zip>518000</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Lisha Mou, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>+86-1589-9876-015</phone>
      <email>lishamou@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>April 9, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 9, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 11, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 9, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 9, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 11, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Retinal Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diabetic Retinopathy</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

