<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03919019</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>RET 04 2017</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03919019</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Morpho-functional Changes After Oral Supplementation of Antioxidants and Anti-inflammatory Treatment in Age-Related Macular Degeneration.</brief_title>
  <acronym>MACUPREV</acronym>
  <official_title>Evaluation of Macular Function and Related Changes in Visual Perception and Retinal Morphology After 6 Months of Use of Oral Supplementation Called MACUPREV, in Patients With Dry Age-related Macular Degeneration (AMD)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Fondazione G.B. Bietti, IRCCS</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Fondazione G.B. Bietti, IRCCS</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      In patients with AMD a deterioration of the antioxidant mechanisms of the retina is observed
      and therefore an increase in the production of free radicals responsible for tissue damage.

      The Age-Related Eye Disease Study (AREDS) found that the intake of antioxidants reduces the
      risk of progression of the disease to an advanced stage (choroidal neovascularization or
      geographic atrophy ) and reduces the loss of visual acuity.

      In this study the investigators want to analyze the functional retinal changes (mfERG) of the
      macular region, in patients with dry age-related macular degeneration, after the use for 6
      months of an oral supplementation based on Ganoderma lucidum (Reishi), Calendula Officinalis,
      Lutepure-Marigold ( 5% Lutein and 1% Zeaxanthin) Blueberry, Rutin, Alpha-lipoic acid,
      Bromelain, NAC, Vtiamine C, B9, B12, D3, Selenium, Zinc and Copper.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 18, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">November 20, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">October 19, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>monocentric, prospective, double blind randomized six months study</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of Multifocal electroretinogram (mfERG) in patients with dry age-related macular degeneration after 6 months follow up</measure>
    <time_frame>Functional retinal changes after 6 months follow up</time_frame>
    <description>To evaluate functional retinal changes of the macular region by multifocal electroretinogram in patients with dry age-related macular degeneration after the use for 6 months of an oral supplementation in tablets based on Ganoderma lucidum (Reishi), Calendula Officinalis, Lutepure-Marigold ( 5% Lutein and 1% Zeaxanthin) Blueberry, Rutin, Alpha-lipoic acid, Bromelain, NAC, Vtiamine C, B9, B12, D3, Selenium, Zinc and Copper.
The researchers analyzed the average response amplitude densities (RAD: nanoV/ degree 2) between the first negative peak, N1 and the first positive peak, P1</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To evaluate correlation between mfERG changes (functional activity) and morphological retinal changes (CRT: central retinal thickness and VD: vessel density at the superficial and deep capillary plexa) after 6 months follow up</measure>
    <time_frame>Morpho-functional retinal relationships after 6 months follow up</time_frame>
    <description>The researchers evaluated the linear relationships between the mfERG (Response Amplitude Density (RAD nanoV/degree2) and OCT/OCTA values (CRT in micron and vessel density in mm3) by Pearson's Test after administration of a oral supplementation (Macuprev)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Dry AMD</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Macuprev Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>patients taking oral supplementation (Macuprev) 2 capsules per day for 6 months</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>patients taking oral placebo 2 capsules per day for 6 months</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Macuprev Group</intervention_name>
    <description>oral supplementation (Macuprev) 2 capsules per day for 6 months</description>
    <arm_group_label>Macuprev Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo Group</intervention_name>
    <description>oral placebo 2 capsules per day for 6 months</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  age&gt; 50;

          -  dry AMD not in therapy with oral supplements or antioxidants

          -  visual acuity ≥ 20/40

          -  ability to provide written informed consent and to follow the procedures of the study;

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  spherical refractive error greater than ±6 diopters

          -  cylindrical refractive error greater than ±3 dioptres

          -  opacity of diopter means

          -  any active or past retinal pathology other than AMD

          -  history of ocular surgery (&lt;6 months)

          -  Pregnancy
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>50 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Fondazione G.B.Bietti</name>
      <address>
        <city>Roma</city>
        <zip>00135</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Italy</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Age-Related Eye Disease Study Research Group, SanGiovanni JP, Chew EY, Clemons TE, Ferris FL 3rd, Gensler G, Lindblad AS, Milton RC, Seddon JM, Sperduto RD. The relationship of dietary carotenoid and vitamin A, E, and C intake with age-related macular degeneration in a case-control study: AREDS Report No. 22. Arch Ophthalmol. 2007 Sep;125(9):1225-32.</citation>
    <PMID>17846363</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Parisi V, Tedeschi M, Gallinaro G, Varano M, Saviano S, Piermarocchi S; CARMIS Study Group. Carotenoids and antioxidants in age-related maculopathy italian study: multifocal electroretinogram modifications after 1 year. Ophthalmology. 2008 Feb;115(2):324-333.e2. Epub 2007 Aug 22.</citation>
    <PMID>17716735</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Piermarocchi S, Saviano S, Parisi V, Tedeschi M, Panozzo G, Scarpa G, Boschi G, Lo Giudice G; Carmis Study Group. Carotenoids in Age-related Maculopathy Italian Study (CARMIS): two-year results of a randomized study. Eur J Ophthalmol. 2012 Mar-Apr;22(2):216-25. doi: 10.5301/ejo.5000069.</citation>
    <PMID>22009916</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 14, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 16, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 18, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 7, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 7, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 9, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Fondazione G.B. Bietti, IRCCS</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Mariacristina Parravano</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Head Retina Unit</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>oral supplementation</keyword>
  <keyword>mfERG</keyword>
  <keyword>OCT</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Macular Degeneration</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

