<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03911999</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CRE-2018.063</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03911999</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Exosomal microRNA in Predicting the Aggressiveness of Prostate Cancer in Chinese Patients</brief_title>
  <official_title>To Investigate the Diagnostic Accuracy of Exosomal microRNA in Predicting the Aggressiveness of Prostate Cancer in Chinese Patients</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Chinese University of Hong Kong</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Chinese University of Hong Kong</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The prostate gland is a clinically important male accessory sex gland and vital for its
      production of semen. Prostate cancer (PCa) is now ranked 3th in annual incidence of male
      cancer and ranked 5th for cancer-related death in men in Hong Kong which accounts for about
      10.9 deaths per 100,000 persons. Its incidence is rising rapidly, almost tripled in the past
      10 years. Fortunately, with the improvement in awareness of the disease and also increasing
      use of serum prostate specific antigen for early case identification, many patients are
      diagnosed at an earlier stage. However, unlike other malignancy, PCa is characterized by its
      slow progression nature. Therefore, some patients with low grade low volume disease might
      never suffered from PCa related complications or mortality. As a result, recent year, there
      is an increase use a more conservative approach, active surveillance (AS), for management of
      early prostate cancer. The principle of AS is selecting patients with low risk of disease and
      offered them regular monitoring, instead of radical local therapy, unless patient's cancer
      was noticed to progressing. By using this approach, patients might avoid possible
      complications related to treatment. Currently, people could use some clinical parameters,
      imaging and repeated prostate biopsy to assess and monitor the aggressiveness/ progression of
      PCa. However, these parameters suffered from defects, such as low correlation to the final
      PCa pathology or not readily repeatable for patients. Therefore, there is a need to identify
      more easy, safe and repeatable monitoring of the aggressiveness of prostate cancer.

      Exosome is genetic materials secreted by cells and could be measured in various body fluid.
      There are some studies suggested it is a potential marker for PCa diagnosis and monitoring.
      The aim of this study is to investigate the relationship of urinary exosome and the
      aggressiveness of prostate cancer.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Prostate cancer (PCa) is the third most common male cancer in Hong Kong. While the use of
      serum PSA has greatly improved the proportion of patients diagnosed at localized /early
      stage, there are also problems of overdiagnosis and overtreatment. Unfortunately, there was
      still no ideal markers that could help to predict the aggressiveness of PCa, especially in
      Chinese population. Exosome is an important media for cell-cell interaction. The content of
      exomsomes, including microRNAs, are believed to have important roles in PCa development and
      progression, and might also serve as potential markers in PCa management. Therefore,
      investigators would like to explore the role of exosomal microRNA in the prediction of tumour
      aggressiveness in local Chinese PCa patients. This is a prospective study divided into two
      parts. Subjects will be recruited consecutively from two hospitals.

      In Part I of the study (Candidate exosomal microRNA discovery and selection), a total of 60
      patients from three groups (non-cancer, pathologically insignificant cancer and significant
      cancer patients) will be recruited. First portion of urine will be collected from them. For
      Group 2&amp;3 patients, they are patients with clinically localized prostate cancer and planned
      for radical prostatectomy, urine will be collected before surgery for these two groups.
      Exosomal RNA will be extracted from urine and microRNAs expression profiles will be
      determined by next-generation sequencing. Candidate exosomal microRNAs that could
      differentiate pathological insignificant and significant PCa will be identified for Part II
      study.

      In Part II study (Candidate exosomal microRNAs validation), 180 patients with localized
      prostate cancer, planned for radical prostatectomy will be recruited. Urine will be again
      collected before surgery and the level of candidate exosomal microRNAs for each patient will
      be assessed. The diagnostic accuracy of these candidate exosomal microRNAs on predicting
      pathological insignificant cancer and also correlation with the final pathology will be
      assessed.

      The primary tasks for Part I study is the identification of potential exosomal microRNAs that
      could differentiate pathologically insignificant and significant PCa.

      The primary task for Part II study is the validation of the ability of those candidate
      exosomal microRNAs in differentiating pathological insignificant and significant PCa.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 3, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 30, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 30, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To compare the differences in microRNA expression between non-prostate cancer subjects, pathologically insignificant and significant prostate cancer patients.</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, one-time point</time_frame>
    <description>Urine will be collected prior to surgery. The urine sample will then be handled immediately for exosomal RNA extraction (refer to specific methodology). The extracted exosomal RNA would then be stored for next generation sequencing (NGS). Results of the 3 groups will then be compared, with reference to literatures findings. Candidate microRNAs that can differentiate between pathologically significant and insignificant cancer will be selected for Part II study.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To assess the accuracy of selected microRNAs for the differentiation of patients with pathologically insignificant and significant prostate cancer after radical prostatectomy</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, one-time point</time_frame>
    <description>Urine will be collected prior to surgery. The urine sample will then be handled immediately for exosomal RNA extraction (refer to specific methodology). The extracted exosomal RNA would then be stored for next generation sequencing (NGS). Results of the 3 groups will then be compared, with reference to literatures findings. Candidate microRNAs that can differentiate betten pathologically significant and insignificant cancer will be selected for Part II study.The preoperative patients and disease parameters, including age, clinical staging, serum PSA level, prostatic biopsy results, MRI findings, together with the prostatectomy pathology will be collected for subsequent data analysis.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>3</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">240</enrollment>
  <condition>Prostate Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Non-prostate cancer subjects</arm_group_label>
    <description>No clinical evidence of prostate cancer</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Subjects with pathologically insignificant prostate cancer</arm_group_label>
    <description>Insignificant prostate cancers were organ confined with tumor volumes less than 0.5 cc and Gleason score &lt; 7.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Subjects with pathologically significant prostate cancer</arm_group_label>
    <description>Significant cancers are those with either Gleason score &gt; 7, evidences of extra-prostatic extension with positive margins, or seminal vesicles / lymph nodes involvement.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        For non prostate cancer group, there is no specific time limit for urine collection. For
        prostate cancer group, urine will be collected prior to prostatectomy.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. For non prostate cancer group

               -  Male subject with age 45 or above

               -  No clinical evidence of PCa, serum PSA &lt;4 ng/dl and normal digital rectal
                  examination.

          2. For prostate cancer group

               -  Male subject with age 45 or above

               -  Clinically diagnosed to have localized PCa and planned for radical prostatectomy

               -  No prior systemic therapy for PCa used, including hormonal or chemotherapy.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  History of medications usage that can affect serum PSA levels within 6 months of study
             enrolment.

          -  History of active urinary tract infection within 1 month of study enrolment.

          -  History of invasive prostate / bladder treatments within 6 months of study enrolment.

          -  History of concurrent renal/bladder cancer within 6 months of study enrolment.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>45 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Chi Fai Ng, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Chinese University of Hong Kong</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Chi Fai Ng, MD</last_name>
    <phone>852-3505-1663</phone>
    <email>ngcf@surgery.cuhk.edu.hk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Prince of Wales Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hong Kong</city>
        <country>Hong Kong</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Chi Fai Ng, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Hong Kong</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Strope SA, Andriole GL. Prostate cancer screening: current status and future perspectives. Nat Rev Urol. 2010 Sep;7(9):487-93. doi: 10.1038/nrurol.2010.120. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20818326</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Epstein JI, Walsh PC, Carmichael M, Brendler CB. Pathologic and clinical findings to predict tumor extent of nonpalpable (stage T1c) prostate cancer. JAMA. 1994 Feb 2;271(5):368-74.</citation>
    <PMID>7506797</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ploussard G, Epstein JI, Montironi R, Carroll PR, Wirth M, Grimm MO, Bjartell AS, Montorsi F, Freedland SJ, Erbersdobler A, van der Kwast TH. The contemporary concept of significant versus insignificant prostate cancer. Eur Urol. 2011 Aug;60(2):291-303. doi: 10.1016/j.eururo.2011.05.006. Epub 2011 May 17. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21601982</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>McKiernan J, Donovan MJ, O'Neill V, Bentink S, Noerholm M, Belzer S, Skog J, Kattan MW, Partin A, Andriole G, Brown G, Wei JT, Thompson IM Jr, Carroll P. A Novel Urine Exosome Gene Expression Assay to Predict High-grade Prostate Cancer at Initial Biopsy. JAMA Oncol. 2016 Jul 1;2(7):882-9. doi: 10.1001/jamaoncol.2016.0097.</citation>
    <PMID>27032035</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dinh KT, Mahal BA, Ziehr DR, Muralidhar V, Chen YW, Viswanathan VB, Nezolosky MD, Beard CJ, Choueiri TK, Martin NE, Orio PF, Sweeney CJ, Trinh QD, Nguyen PL. Incidence and Predictors of Upgrading and Up Staging among 10,000 Contemporary Patients with Low Risk Prostate Cancer. J Urol. 2015 Aug;194(2):343-9. doi: 10.1016/j.juro.2015.02.015. Epub 2015 Feb 11.</citation>
    <PMID>25681290</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chiu PK, Lai FM, Teoh JY, Lee WM, Yee CH, Chan ES, Hou SM, Ng CF. Prostate Health Index and %p2PSA Predict Aggressive Prostate Cancer Pathology in Chinese Patients Undergoing Radical Prostatectomy. Ann Surg Oncol. 2016 Aug;23(8):2707-14. doi: 10.1245/s10434-016-5183-6. Epub 2016 Mar 10.</citation>
    <PMID>26965697</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schiffer E. Biomarkers for prostate cancer. World J Urol. 2007 Dec;25(6):557-62. Epub 2007 Aug 10. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>17690889</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ng CF, Yeung R, Chiu PK, Lam NY, Chow J, Chan B. The role of urine prostate cancer antigen 3 mRNA levels in the diagnosis of prostate cancer among Hong Kong Chinese patients. Hong Kong Med J. 2012 Dec;18(6):459-65.</citation>
    <PMID>23223645</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Laxman B, Tomlins SA, Mehra R, Morris DS, Wang L, Helgeson BE, Shah RB, Rubin MA, Wei JT, Chinnaiyan AM. Noninvasive detection of TMPRSS2:ERG fusion transcripts in the urine of men with prostate cancer. Neoplasia. 2006 Oct;8(10):885-8.</citation>
    <PMID>17059688</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ren S, Peng Z, Mao JH, Yu Y, Yin C, Gao X, Cui Z, Zhang J, Yi K, Xu W, Chen C, Wang F, Guo X, Lu J, Yang J, Wei M, Tian Z, Guan Y, Tang L, Xu C, Wang L, Gao X, Tian W, Wang J, Yang H, Wang J, Sun Y. RNA-seq analysis of prostate cancer in the Chinese population identifies recurrent gene fusions, cancer-associated long noncoding RNAs and aberrant alternative splicings. Cell Res. 2012 May;22(5):806-21. doi: 10.1038/cr.2012.30. Epub 2012 Feb 21.</citation>
    <PMID>22349460</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gudmundsson J, Sulem P, Gudbjartsson DF, Masson G, Agnarsson BA, Benediktsdottir KR, Sigurdsson A, Magnusson OT, Gudjonsson SA, Magnusdottir DN, Johannsdottir H, Helgadottir HT, Stacey SN, Jonasdottir A, Olafsdottir SB, Thorleifsson G, Jonasson JG, Tryggvadottir L, Navarrete S, Fuertes F, Helfand BT, Hu Q, Csiki IE, Mates IN, Jinga V, Aben KK, van Oort IM, Vermeulen SH, Donovan JL, Hamdy FC, Ng CF, Chiu PK, Lau KM, Ng MC, Gulcher JR, Kong A, Catalona WJ, Mayordomo JI, Einarsson GV, Barkardottir RB, Jonsson E, Mates D, Neal DE, Kiemeney LA, Thorsteinsdottir U, Rafnar T, Stefansson K. A study based on whole-genome sequencing yields a rare variant at 8q24 associated with prostate cancer. Nat Genet. 2012 Dec;44(12):1326-9. doi: 10.1038/ng.2437. Epub 2012 Oct 28.</citation>
    <PMID>23104005</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wang G, Chan ES, Kwan BC, Li PK, Yip SK, Szeto CC, Ng CF. Expression of microRNAs in the urine of patients with bladder cancer. Clin Genitourin Cancer. 2012 Jun;10(2):106-13. doi: 10.1016/j.clgc.2012.01.001. Epub 2012 Mar 3.</citation>
    <PMID>22386240</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kumar B, Lupold SE. MicroRNA expression and function in prostate cancer: a review of current knowledge and opportunities for discovery. Asian J Androl. 2016 Jul-Aug;18(4):559-67. doi: 10.4103/1008-682X.177839. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>27056344</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Endzeliņš E, Melne V, Kalniņa Z, Lietuvietis V, Riekstiņa U, Llorente A, Linē A. Diagnostic, prognostic and predictive value of cell-free miRNAs in prostate cancer: a systematic review. Mol Cancer. 2016 May 18;15(1):41. doi: 10.1186/s12943-016-0523-5. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>27189160</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yu S, Wang X, Ng CF, Chen S, Chan FL. ERRgamma suppresses cell proliferation and tumor growth of androgen-sensitive and androgen-insensitive prostate cancer cells and its implication as a therapeutic target for prostate cancer. Cancer Res. 2007 May 15;67(10):4904-14.</citation>
    <PMID>17510420</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tsoi TH, Chan CF, Chan WL, Chiu KF, Wong WT, Ng CF, Wong KL. Urinary Polyamines: A Pilot Study on Their Roles as Prostate Cancer Detection Biomarkers. PLoS One. 2016 Sep 6;11(9):e0162217. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0162217. eCollection 2016.</citation>
    <PMID>27598335</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zhang DZ, Lau KM, Chan ES, Wang G, Szeto CC, Wong K, Choy RK, Ng CF. Cell-free urinary microRNA-99a and microRNA-125b are diagnostic markers for the non-invasive screening of bladder cancer. PLoS One. 2014 Jul 11;9(7):e100793. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0100793. eCollection 2014.</citation>
    <PMID>25014919</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Leung YK, Chan QK, Ng CF, Ma FM, Tse HM, To KF, Maranchie J, Ho SM, Lau KM. Hsa-miRNA-765 as a key mediator for inhibiting growth, migration and invasion in fulvestrant-treated prostate cancer. PLoS One. 2014 May 16;9(5):e98037. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0098037. eCollection 2014. Erratum in: PLoS One. 2019 Mar 18;14(3):e0214184.</citation>
    <PMID>24837491</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>April 10, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 10, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 11, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 16, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 16, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 20, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Chinese University of Hong Kong</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Chi Fai NG</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Prostatic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Aggression</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

