<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03918785</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>1114/06072014</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03918785</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Rice Germ Supplementation on Swimmers</brief_title>
  <acronym>RGS swimmers</acronym>
  <official_title>Rice Germ Supplementation on Moderately Trained Swimmers: a Randomized Pilot Clinical Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Azienda di Servizi alla Persona di Pavia</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Azienda di Servizi alla Persona di Pavia</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      In order to enhance the effects of training and improve performance, athletes often turn to
      nutritional supplements. According to the American College of Sports Medicine (ACSM),
      adequate selection of nutrients and supplements, adjusting intake according to the exercise
      performed, is necessary for optimal performance in athletes. The most recent consensus from
      the International Society for Sport Nutrition (ISSN), The American Dietetic Association (ADA)
      and ACSM on sport nutrition have been reviewed by Potgieter, stating that a single guideline
      is not sufficient to elaborate an individualized and focused nutritional management of
      athletes. Moreover, apart from the abovementioned guidelines, sport-specific nutritional
      strategies, including quantity, structure and timing of food (or supplement) intake should
      also be followed in order to maximize sports performance and recovery. The importance of
      dietary supplementation is of particular interest in swimming, where athletes usually
      undertake a training approach characterized by a high volume of training during aerobic
      development and high intensity training during the competition phase, coupled with strength
      training.

      The size and market value of the sports supplement industry is continuing to grow, with
      health, safety and contamination concerns becoming more pressing. Therefore, it is important
      to identify dietary supplements that are safe and effective in supporting swimmers. Rice germ
      could be a safe and effective dietary supplement for swimmers. In the last few years,
      scientific research is trying to use waste rice products in the pharmaceutical and
      nutraceutical fields, considering the potential value of nutrients they contain. In
      particular, rice germ has a high protein and essential amino acids, such as lysine, histidine
      and valine content, a good lipid content (with prevalence of mono- unsaturated and
      polyunsaturated fatty acids - in particular linoleic and linolenic essential fatty acids and
      oleic acid), an high fiber presence; regarding water-soluble vitamins, rice germ has high
      content if thiamine (B1) and pyridoxine (B6), while vitamin E prevails for liposoluble
      vitamins. About minerals, are most present iron and magnesium. All these nutrients play
      important roles in maintaining the health of athletes. Currently, despite these
      characteristics, no study has evaluated the potential beneficial effect of RG supplementation
      on athletes. Given this background, the purpose of this investigation was to ascertain
      whether performance in swimmers could be improved by a 5-weeks of RG supplementation.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">April 1, 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 31, 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 30, 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Performance change</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline and after 5 weeks of supplementation</time_frame>
    <description>Whether the performance in 50m, 200m, is improved in a 25m swimming pool in front crawl at maximal speed. Performance measured in seconds.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Lactic acid production change</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline and after 5 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Capillary blood samples were collected from the fingertip before and after each swimming (at the 1st and 3rdmin of recovery) to access the higher values of blood lactate concentration (AccutrendLactate®Roche, Germany).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Antropometric measures change (skinfolds)</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline and after 5 weeks of supplementation</time_frame>
    <description>skinfolds thicknesses (mm) (biceps, triceps, suprailiac, subscapular), measured twice using a Harpenden skinfold caliper at 5 min intervals at each site</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Body weight change (kg)</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline and after 5 weeks of supplementation</time_frame>
    <description>Change in body weight (kg).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Antropometric measures change (circumferences)</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline and after 5 weeks of supplementation</time_frame>
    <description>Waist circumference (cm), hip circumference (cm), mid-arm circumference (cm).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Total fat mass, total free fat mass and visceral adipose tissue (DXA)</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline and after 5-weeks of supplementation</time_frame>
    <description>Body composition by dual-energy X-ray absorptiometry (DXA). Body composition was measured at baseline by DXA, using a Lunar Prodigy DEXA (GE Medical Systems, Waukesha, WI). Free Fat mass, Fat mass and visceral fat (kg) data were derived from DXA using the DXA Prodigy enCORE software (version 17; GE Healthcare).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Body composition parameters change (BIVA)</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline and after 5-weeks of supplementation</time_frame>
    <description>Body composition analyzed with BIVA: free fat mass, fat mass, body cellular mass change (kg).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hydration parameters change (BIVA)</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline and after 5-weeks of supplementation</time_frame>
    <description>Hydration analyzed with BIVA: total body water, extracellular water, intracellular water change (L)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Registration of adverse effects</measure>
    <time_frame>After 7 days, 14 days, 21 days, 28 days from baseline and after 5 weeks.</time_frame>
    <description>Adverse effects recorded, through phone call</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Muscle function change</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseine and after 5 weeks.</time_frame>
    <description>The JAMAR Hand Dynamometer (Jamar 5030J1; Sammons Preston Rolyan; accuracy 0.6 N) was used to assess muscle function with the use of a standardized procedure(Spijkerman, Dorine C., Snijders, Chris J., Stijnen, Theo, &amp; Lankhorst 1991). Handgrip measured in kilograms.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">27</enrollment>
  <condition>Athletes</condition>
  <condition>Sports</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Rice Germ</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The Rice Germ was supplied in vacuum jars of a weight of 130 grams. These jars once opened, were stored in the refrigerator (-3-4°C). Together with cans, small containers were provided to act as dosers and served to determine the correct dose to be taken (25 grams, twice a day). The rice germ or placebo were continually taken every day twice a day (25 grams in the morning with breakfast and 25 grams in the afternoon as snacks) for 5 weeks. The rice germ was supplied by the company &quot;Acquerello&quot; (TenutaColombara, Livorno Ferraris, Vercelli, Italy).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Active comparator, which consisted of an isocaloric wheat germ-based supplement. Characteristics of supplementation are the same of experimental group.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Rice germ</intervention_name>
    <description>25 g twice a day.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Rice Germ</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Wheat-based supplement</intervention_name>
    <description>25g twice a day.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  moderately trained athletes

          -  regularly involved in regional and national competitions

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  No history of cardiac or respiratory disease

          -  no medication at the time of the study

          -  no abnormalities on physical examination or on resting electrocardiogram
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mariangela Rondanelli, MD, PhD, Professor</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Mariangela Rondanelli, IRCCS Mondino Foundation, Pavia</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <verification_date>April 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 27, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 14, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 18, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 18, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 18, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 22, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Azienda di Servizi alla Persona di Pavia</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Mariangela Rondanelli</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>rice germ</keyword>
  <keyword>swimmers</keyword>
  <keyword>nutritional supplement</keyword>
  <keyword>lactic acid</keyword>
  <keyword>fat free mass</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

