<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03913286</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>17D.459</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03913286</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Neuromotor Prosthetic to Treat Stroke-Related Paresis</brief_title>
  <acronym>Cortimo</acronym>
  <official_title>Neuromotor Prosthetic to Treat Stroke-Related Paresis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Thomas Jefferson University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Thomas Jefferson University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of the research is to develop a new medical device prototype to restore
      functional movement of an arm made weak due to a chronic stroke
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Microelectrode arrays implanted into the brain will decode signals to drive motors on the
      powered brace worn on the arm so that the patient can &quot;power steer&quot; his or her own arm. The
      ultimate goal is to create a fully implantable medical device that will restore movement in
      all parts of the body affected by a stroke. Independent movement will have functional
      benefits (e.g., being able to lift a fork to eat) and health benefits (e.g., decreasing the
      frequency of skin infections and preventing the formation of painful joint contractures).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 1, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 1, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Device Feasibility</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline Fugl-Meyer Motor Impairment Score at 4 months</measure>
    <time_frame>4 months</time_frame>
    <description>The Fugl-Meyer assessment is a stroke specific index for estimating the performance of motor function. Total scores of FMA-Upper limb range from 0-66.
From: Fugl-Meyer et al. The post-stroke hemiplegic patient: a method for evaluation of physical performance. Scand. J. Rehabil. Med., 1975.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline Action Research Arm Test (ARAT) score at 4 months</measure>
    <time_frame>4 months</time_frame>
    <description>The Action Research Arm Test (ARAT) measures specific changes in the arm function in people who sustained cerebral damage resulting in arm weakness. The ARAT consists of 19 items grouped into four subscales: grasp, grip, pinch and gross movements. Each sub scale has items ordered according to ascending difficulty: 0- can not perform any part of the test, 1- performs the test partialy, 2- completes the test, but takes abnormally long time, 3- performs the test normally. The sum of all subscales are added to compute the total score. The total score ranges between 0 to 57. The higher score is considered to be better outcome.
From: Yozbatiran et al. A standardized approach to performing the action research arm test. Neurorehabil. Neural Repair, 2008.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline Motricity Index score at 4 months</measure>
    <time_frame>4 months</time_frame>
    <description>The Motricity Index measures strength in the arms and legs after stroke. The weighted score is based on the ordinal 6 point scale of Medical Research Council to measure maximal isometric muscle strength.
From: Collin and Wade. Assessing motor impairment after stroke: A pilot reliability study. J. Neurol. Neurosurg. Psychiatry, 1990.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline ADL, Hand and Recovery Scales within Stroke Impact Scale, at 4 months</measure>
    <time_frame>4 months</time_frame>
    <description>The Stroke Impact Scales assess how having a stroke impacts a person's life. The scale has 8 subscales which ask questions regarding a person's physical limitations, memory and thinking, emotions and mood, ability to communicate, daily activities, mobility at home and in the community, use of hand most affected by stroke, and ability to participate in meaningful life activities. Each subscale item is rated on a scale from 5-1 (5= None of the time, 4=a little of the time, 3=Some of the time, 2=Most of the time, 1=All of the time).
From: Duncan et al. The Stroke Impact Scale Version 2.0 : Evaluation of Reliability, Validity, and Sensitivity to Change. Stroke, 1999.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline &quot;Giving Them A Hand&quot; ADL at 4 months</measure>
    <time_frame>4 months</time_frame>
    <description>The &quot;Giving Them A Hand&quot; ADL scale measures a person's ability to perform four functional tasks emphasizing proximal movement of the weak arm and some limited movement of the distal areas given a myoelectric elbow-wrist-hand orthosis' capabilities to assist with flexion and extension of the first two fingers. The tasks are: (1) turning on a light switch,(2) lifting a laundry basket bilaterally, (3) bringing a spoon to the mouth, and (4) drinking from a cup. Quality of movement for both grasp and elbow components of each of these is individually rated using a 3-point ordinal scale (where 0 is performs no part of task and 3 is performs normally), and performance of each component is timed with a 120-second limit
From Peters, et al. Giving Them a Hand: Wearing a Myoelectric Elbow-Wrist-Hand Orthosis Reduces Upper Extremity Impairment in Chronic Stroke. Arch. Phys. Med. Rehabil. 2017.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline Braden skin health score at 4 months</measure>
    <time_frame>4 months</time_frame>
    <description>The Braden scale predicts pressure sore risk. The Braden score consists of 6 categories: sensory perception, moisture, activity, mobility, nutrition and friction. The score ranges from 6-23 with lower scores indicating a higher risk.
From: Bergstrom et al. The Braden Scale for Predicting Pressure Sore Risk. Nurs. Res. 36(4): 205-210. 1987.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">1</enrollment>
  <condition>Stroke, Complication</condition>
  <condition>Stroke</condition>
  <condition>Stroke Sequelae</condition>
  <condition>Hemiparesis</condition>
  <condition>Arm Paralysis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The participant will be implanted with the Blackrock Microsystems MultiPort system.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cortimo</intervention_name>
    <description>The Cortimo comprises an implanted brain activity sensor and a wearable powered arm orthosis.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>MyoPro powered orthotic brace</other_name>
    <other_name>Blackrock Microsystems MultiPort</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Must be 18 years or older.

          -  Clinical diagnosis of stroke (hemorrhagic or ischemic, cortical or subcortical),
             confirmed by brain computer tomography or magnetic resonance imaging, that occurred
             six or more months prior to enrollment

          -  Must have arm weakness due to stroke.

          -  Participant is willing to comply with all follow-up evaluations at the specified
             times.

          -  Participant is able to provide informed consent prior to enrollment in the study.

          -  The participant is fluent in English.

          -  &gt; 24 on the Mini Mental Status Examination

          -  Medically stable.

          -  Passive flexion of shoulder in weakened upper extremity with range of &gt; 30 degrees or
             more

          -  Passive abduction of shoulder in weakened upper extremity with range of &gt; 20 degrees
             or more

          -  Participant must have a caregiver willing to participate in the study who will help
             provide care for the surgical site.

          -  Must be willing to live at hospital or at nearby hotel for 90-day duration when
             implantable components were present.

          -  Plateaued post-stroke recovery with complete or incomplete hemiplegia due to stroke in
             one upper limb, as measured on two serial occasions (at least one month apart) without
             improvement, by the following standardized functional assessments of the weaker upper
             extremity:

               -  Manual Muscle Testing scores of 0/5 (no movement) or 1/5 (palpable contraction in
                  muscle, without movement) in the biceps (elbow flexion), triceps (elbow
                  extension), wrist flexors, wrist extensors or intrinsic hand muscles

               -  Mild to plegia according to Medical Research Council Scale for Muscle Strength

               -  Fugl-Meyer Motor Impairment Score of 38 or lower

               -  Action Research Arm Test (ARAT) score of 35 or lower

               -  Motricity Index score of 55 or lower

          -  No joint contracture or severe spasticity in affected upper limb precluding the
             operation of the MyoPro orthotic device.

          -  Sufficient sitting balance to participate with robotic brace activities.

          -  No condition (e.g., severe arthritis, central pain) that would interfere with
             administration of motor function tests, ability to understand verbal commands and
             cooperate with test procedures.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  No medical condition requiring active anti-coagulation with a medication such as
             heparin, warfarin or rivaroxaban (note that anti-platelet agents such as aspirin or
             clopidogrel are acceptable)

          -  No active wound healing or skin breakdown issues.

          -  No history of poorly controlled autonomic dysreflexia.

          -  Visual impairment such that extended viewing of a computer monitor would be
             challenging even with ordinary corrective lenses

          -  Chronic oral or intravenous steroids or immunosuppressive therapy

          -  A score of 23 or lower on Folstein's Mini-Mental Status Examination

          -  Orthopedic conditions of either arm that would affect performance on study

          -  Untreated psychiatric disturbances that would affect motivation and trial
             participation

          -  Medical contraindications for general anesthesia, craniotomy, or surgery.

          -  Diagnosis of acute myocardial infarction or cardiac arrest within previous 6 months.

          -  Dementia

          -  Other implantable devices such as heart/brain pacemakers

          -  Participants who rely on ventilators

          -  Co-morbid conditions that would interfere with study activities or response to
             treatment, which may include:

               -  Life expectancy &lt; 3 years

               -  Severe chronic pulmonary disease

               -  Seizure within three months prior to enrollment

               -  History of uncontrolled seizures

               -  Local, systemic acute or chronic infectious illness

               -  Life threatening cardiac arrhythmias

               -  Severe collagen vascular disorder

          -  Kidney failure or other major organ system failures History of a neurological ablation
             procedure.

          -  Labeled contraindication for MRI.

          -  History of HIV infection or ongoing chronic infection (such as tuberculosis).

          -  Pregnant or of child-bearing potential and are not taking acceptable methods of
             contraception.

          -  Participation in another investigational device or medication trial

          -  Excessive pain in the paretic upper extremity (&gt; 5 on a 10-point visual analog scale)

          -  Excessive spasticity at the paretic elbow, wrist, or digits as defined as a score of &gt;
             2 on the Modified Ashworth Spasticity Scale

          -  Participating in any experimental rehabilitation or drug studies

          -  Moderate to severe apraxia (&lt; 2.5 on the Alexander scale)

          -  Received phenol injections to any portion of the paretic upper extremity within the
             past 12 months

          -  Other conditions or circumstances that, in the opinion of the investigators, would
             preclude safe and/or effective participation, including severe skin conditions, and/or
             other sequelae that may be contraindicated for arm orthosis use as well as personal
             circumstance
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mijail Serruya, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Dr.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Mijail Serruya, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>215-955-8922</phone>
    <email>Mijail.Serruya@jefferson.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Erica Jones</last_name>
    <phone>215-955-8922</phone>
    <email>Erica.Jones@jefferson.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Thomas Jefferson University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19107</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Mijail D Serruya, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>215-955-8922</phone>
      <email>Mijail.Serruya@jefferson.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 7, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 11, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 12, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 16, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 16, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 20, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>neuroprosthetic</keyword>
  <keyword>neuroprosthesis</keyword>
  <keyword>brain-computer</keyword>
  <keyword>brain-machine</keyword>
  <keyword>microelectrode</keyword>
  <keyword>Utah array</keyword>
  <keyword>orthosis</keyword>
  <keyword>brain computer interface</keyword>
  <keyword>assistive device</keyword>
  <keyword>Neurorehabilitation</keyword>
  <keyword>neurotechnology</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Stroke</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Paralysis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Paresis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

