<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03911596</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IRB # 114415</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>5U01EB023048</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03911596</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Smart Autofocusing Eyeglasses</brief_title>
  <official_title>Cyber Physical System for Smart Corrective Eyeglasses</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Utah</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute for Biomedical Imaging and Bioengineering (NIBIB)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Utah</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      A high-performance smart eyeglasses system with integrated sensing, actuation, control and
      data collection is being developed at the University of Utah. These smart eyeglasses use
      tunable lenses and integrated sensor technologies to correct blurred vision caused due to a
      major age-related condition called presbyopia.The objective of this study is to test this
      smart system on patients suffering from presbyopia aged 45 and above. The researchers intend
      to study the effect of these smart eyeglasses by qualitatively investigating the patient's
      visual acuity with this smart system. The results of this study and subsequent research have
      the potential to lead to major lifestyle improvements and better treatment for millions of
      presbyopic patients that are constrained by the limitation of current corrective eyeglass
      technologies. There are two main sources of fairly well understood problems that lead to
      presbyopia and loss of the eye focusing function. The adaptive eyeglasses used in these tests
      do not fix any of the internal eye problems. They just compensate externally for the loss of
      the eye focusing function caused by presbyopia. As such, the investigators intend to evaluate
      our system's effectiveness in terms of the sharpness of the perceived images.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Eye defects occur when the eye cannot focus images from the outside world. This results in
      blurred vision, which sometimes is so severe that it causes visual impairment. Among the many
      vision defects, presbyopia is an inevitable, irreversible, universal age-related condition
      where the crystalline lens in the eye loses its accomodation orthe ability to change the
      optical power. This defect occurs as a natural result of aging and will ultimately affect any
      person reaching advanced enough age. It was estimated in 2005 that over 1 billion people
      worldwide suffered from presbyopia, with approximately 400 million suffering from near vision
      loss due to the lack of correction technologies.

      The most inexpensive and commonly used tools to correct vision errors are fixed power
      eyeglasses, which haven't seen any improvement since the mid-1800s. Conventional eyeglasses
      are an ancient piece of technology which originated in Europe's middle ages. A major drawback
      of such eyeglasses is that they can only correct the lack of accomodation at a particular
      object distance, since they use fixed power lenses. As a result, conventional eyeglasses can
      produce sharp images for objects located either far away or near the observer but not both.
      Bifocal, multifocal and progressive lenses can partially alleviate vision defects, but at the
      expense of reduced and fragmented field of view. As an example, multifocal lenses have
      different lens powers in different regions of the lens. With such lenses, it is not possible
      to see objects clearly over the entire visual field. Further, the effectiveness of
      conventional eyeglasses is not monitored outside the optometrist's office.

      The proposed smart eyeglasses system uses a combination of large-aperture fluidic lenses,
      ultra-light actuators, object distance sensors and embedded control, communications and
      computing electronics to continuously produce sharp and focused images at any object range.
      They can also collect the behaviour and characteristics of the observer's eyes to gauge the
      effectiveness of the technology and adapt to observer's visual degradation over age.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 1, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 1, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Only</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Accommodation response of the natural lens of the eye with smart eyeglasses technology</measure>
    <time_frame>60 minutes</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Presbyopia</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Smart Autofocusing Eyeglasses</intervention_name>
    <description>The smart eyeglasses system is meant to be a next generation alternative technology which replaces the generic eyeglasses used for correction of refractory defects in human vision. These smart eyeglasses do not fix any internal eye problems. They just externally compensate for the loss of eye focusing functions caused by presbyopia. This system is a medical assistive device which is meant to improve the quality of life of presbyopic patients.</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Any individual above 45 years of age with symptoms of presbyopia.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Presbyopic

          -  Less than 1.0 diopter astigmatism

          -  Eyeglass prescription between -2.5 and +2.5, correctable to 20/20

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Artificial intraocular lens

          -  Any ocular pathology that would inhibit accommodation of the natural lens
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>45 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Carlos H Mastrangelo, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Utah</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Carlos H Mastrangelo, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>801-587-7587</phone>
    <email>carlos.mastrangelo@utah.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Mohit U Karkhanis</last_name>
    <email>mohit.karkhanis@utah.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Moran Eye Center, University of Utah</name>
      <address>
        <city>Salt Lake City</city>
        <state>Utah</state>
        <zip>84112</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Kelliann Farnsworth, Certified Ophthalmic Assistant</last_name>
      <phone>801-581-2352</phone>
      <email>kellian.farnsworth@hsc.utah.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Mohit U Karkhanis</last_name>
      <email>mohit.karkhanis@utah.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Mohit U Karkhanis</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hasan N, Banerjee A, Kim H, Mastrangelo CH. Tunable-focus lens for adaptive eyeglasses. Opt Express. 2017 Jan 23;25(2):1221-1233. doi: 10.1364/OE.25.001221.</citation>
    <PMID>28158006</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>N. Hasan, M. Karkhanis, C. Ghosh, F. Khan, T. Ghosh, H. Kim, and C. H. Mastrangelo. Lightweight smart autofocusing eyeglasses. Proc. SPIE 10545, MOEMS and Miniaturized Systems XVII, 1054507 (22 February 2018); doi: 10.1117/12.2300737; https://doi.org/10.1117/12.2300737</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>N. Hasan, M. Karkhanis, F. Khan, T. Ghosh, H. Kim, and C. H. Mastrangelo. Adaptive Optics for Autofocusing Eyeglasses. Imaging and Applied Optics 2017 (3D, AIO, COSI, IS, MATH, pcAOP), OSA Technical Digest (online) (Optical Society of America, 2017), paper AM3A.1.</citation>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>April 9, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 9, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 11, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 13, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 13, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 14, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Utah</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Carlos Mastrangelo</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Presbyopia, accommodation, smart eyeglasses</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Presbyopia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

