<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03912272</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>RF-9835-NAFLD-001</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03912272</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>12-Month Once-a-week HIIT Improves Body Adiposity and Liver Fat</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effectiveness of Long-term Low-frequency High-Intensity Interval Training (HIIT) to Improve Body Adiposity and Liver Fat in Adults With Central Obesity: A Randomized Controlled Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>The University of Hong Kong</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>The University of Hong Kong</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Obesity and non-alcoholic fatty liver disease (NAFLD) are two related growing epidemics that
      are becoming pressing public health concerns. High-intensity interval training (HIIT) is a
      promising cost-effective and time-efficient exercise modality for managing obesity and NAFLD.
      However, patients with obesity and NAFLD are generally inactive and unfit, and might feel
      intimidated by the frequency of the prescribed HIIT (conventionally three times weekly).
      Previous HIIT studies, mostly over 2-4 month periods, showed that the participants could
      accomplish this exercise frequency under a controlled laboratory environment, but the
      long-term adherence and sustainability, especially in a field setting, remains uncertain. The
      situation is more unclear if we also consider those individuals who refused to participate
      possibly because of their overwhelming perceptions or low self-efficacy toward HIIT. Thus,
      logically, HIIT at a lower frequency would be practical and more suitable for patients with
      obesity and NAFLD, but the minimum exercise frequency required to improve health, especially
      in the long-term, is unknown. This proposed study aims to examine the effectiveness of
      long-term low-frequency HIIT for improving body adiposity and liver fat in centrally obese
      adults. The premise of this proposal is supported by recent findings that HIIT performed once
      a week could improve cardiorespiratory fitness, blood pressure, cardiac morphology, metabolic
      capacity, muscle power, and lean mass. This study will provide evidence for the benefits of
      long-term low-frequency HIIT with a follow-up period to assess its effectiveness, safety,
      adherence, and sustainability. We expect this intervention will enhance the practical
      suitability of HIIT in inactive obese adults and will provide evidence for low-frequency HIIT
      as a new exercise option in the management of obesity and NAFLD.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 1, 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 1, 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Liver Fat</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline amount of intrahepatic triglycerides content at 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Intrahepatic triglycerides will be examined by 1H-MR spectroscopy in a 3×3×3 cm voxel using a Philips Achieva 3.0T system housed at the MR imaging unit of HKU core facility. A trained MRI radiographer will operate the machine, position the subjects and analyze the results. NAFLD will be defined as &gt;5% intrahepatic triglycerides assessed by 1H-MR spectroscopy.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Body Adiposity</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline amount of body fat mass triglycerides at 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Total body fat mass will be determined using a full body dual-energy X-ray absorptiometry (DXA) scanner (Explorer S/N 91075, Hologic Inc., Waltham, USA). A trained technician will operate the DXA machine, position the subjects and analyze the results. The typical coefficients of variation of the DXA scanner for each body compartment from duplicate analyses are 0.4% for lean mass, 1.4% for fat mass and 1.0% for bone mass</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Visceral Adiposity</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline measurement (2019.01.01); All assessments will be repeated at 12 months post-intervention (2020.01.01) and at 24 months at the follow-up(2022.01.01)</time_frame>
    <description>Abdominal visceral fat will be measured at the L4-L5 junction using a three-point Dixon sequence using a Philips Achieva 3.0T system housed at the MR imaging unit of HKU core facility. A trained MRI radiographer will operate the machine, position the subjects and analyze the results.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Body Mass Index</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline measurement (2019.01.01); All assessments will be repeated at 12 months post-intervention (2020.01.01) and at 24 months at the follow-up(2022.01.01)</time_frame>
    <description>A calibrated electronic digital weighing scale (BC418, Tanita, Japan) with a 200 kg capacity and ± 0.05 kg accuracy will be used to weigh the subjects. A stadiometer (Holtain Ltd., UK) with 200 cm limit and ± 0.01 cm accuracy will be used to measure body height. Then BMI will be calculated from the body weight and height.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Waist Circumference</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline measurement (2019.01.01); All assessments will be repeated at 12 months post-intervention (2020.01.01) and at 24 months at the follow-up(2022.01.01)</time_frame>
    <description>Waist circumference will be measured on bare skin midway between the lowest rib and the superior border of the iliac crest using an inelastic measuring tape to the nearest 0.1 cm. Measurement will be performed at the end of normal expiration.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>VO2max</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline measurement (2019.01.01); All assessments will be repeated at 12 months post-intervention (2020.01.01) and at 24 months at the follow-up(2022.01.01)</time_frame>
    <description>VO2max test will be conducted using a calibrated motor-driven treadmill (LE500C, Jaeger, Germany) by continuous metabolic VO2 measurement using a Cosmed K5 portable telemetric gas analysis system. The test will be performed using a ramp protocol where the speed will be constant and the incline will be increased by 2% every second minute until VO2max is reached. Capillary blood will be obtained before and immediately after the test for the blood lactate analysis. The highest value of VO2 which meets one of the following criteria will be considered as the VO2max: 1) plateau of VO2 with increasing intensity, 2) respiratory exchange ratio (RER) ≥1.05, and 3) post-exercise blood lactate exceeding 8 mmol/L.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>VO2</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline measurement (2019.01.01); All assessments will be repeated at 12 months post-intervention (2020.01.01) and at 24 months at the follow-up(2022.01.01)</time_frame>
    <description>VO2 will be continuously recorded during the VO2max test.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Borg Rate of Perceived exertion (RPE)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline measurement (2019.01.01); All assessments will be repeated at 12 months post-intervention (2020.01.01) and at 24 months at the follow-up(2022.01.01)</time_frame>
    <description>RPE will be continuously recorded during the VO2max test</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Heart Rate</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline measurement (2019.01.01); All assessments will be repeated at 12 months post-intervention (2020.01.01) and at 24 months at the follow-up(2022.01.01)</time_frame>
    <description>Heart rate will be continuously recorded during the VO2max test.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Blood Pressure</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline measurement (2019.01.01); All assessments will be repeated at 12 months post-intervention (2020.01.01) and at 24 months at the follow-up(2022.01.01)</time_frame>
    <description>Subjects will abstain from consuming caffeine and alcohol at least 10 hours prior to the assessment. After 10 minutes rest in the seated position, blood pressure will be measured on the right arm using a blood pressure monitor (M3 Vital Signs Monitor, EDAN). Systolic and diastolic blood pressure and mean arterial pressure will be obtained over the brachial artery region with the arm supported at the heart level using an appropriately sized cuff. Measurements will be repeated after 10 minutes and the average of two separate measurements will be recorded for the analysis.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Lean Mass</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline measurement (2019.01.01); All assessments will be repeated at 12 months post-intervention (2020.01.01) and at 24 months at the follow-up(2022.01.01)</time_frame>
    <description>Total body lean mass will be determined by using DXA scan.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Bone Mineral Density</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline measurement (2019.01.01); All assessments will be repeated at 12 months post-intervention (2020.01.01) and at 24 months at the follow-up(2022.01.01)</time_frame>
    <description>Bone mineral density will be determined by using DXA scan.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Fasting glucose</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline measurement (2019.01.01); All assessments will be repeated at 12 months post-intervention (2020.01.01) and at 24 months at the follow-up(2022.01.01)</time_frame>
    <description>Subjects will fast overnight for 10 hours. Subjects will sit in a quiet environment for 15 minutes prior to blood collection. Venous blood will be drawn from an antecubital vein in the forearm by a certified phlebotomist and sent to an accredited medical laboratory to measure the level of fasting glucose.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Insulin</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline measurement (2019.01.01); All assessments will be repeated at 12 months post-intervention (2020.01.01) and at 24 months at the follow-up(2022.01.01)</time_frame>
    <description>Subjects will fast overnight for 10 hours. Subjects will sit in a quiet environment for 15 minutes prior to blood collection. Venous blood will be drawn from an antecubital vein in the forearm by a certified phlebotomist and sent to an accredited medical laboratory to measure the level of insulin.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>HbA1c</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline measurement (2019.01.01); All assessments will be repeated at 12 months post-intervention (2020.01.01) and at 24 months at the follow-up(2022.01.01)</time_frame>
    <description>Subjects will fast overnight for 10 hours. Subjects will sit in a quiet environment for 15 minutes prior to blood collection. Venous blood will be drawn from an antecubital vein in the forearm by a certified phlebotomist and sent to an accredited medical laboratory to measure the level of HbA1c.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Alanine aminotransferase ALT</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline measurement (2019.01.01); All assessments will be repeated at 12 months post-intervention (2020.01.01) and at 24 months at the follow-up(2022.01.01)</time_frame>
    <description>Subjects will fast overnight for 10 hours. Subjects will sit in a quiet environment for 15 minutes prior to blood collection. Venous blood will be drawn from an antecubital vein in the forearm by a certified phlebotomist and sent to an accredited medical laboratory to measure the level of ALT.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Aspartate aminotransferase AST</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline measurement (2019.01.01); All assessments will be repeated at 12 months post-intervention (2020.01.01) and at 24 months at the follow-up(2022.01.01)</time_frame>
    <description>Subjects will fast overnight for 10 hours. Subjects will sit in a quiet environment for 15 minutes prior to blood collection. Venous blood will be drawn from an antecubital vein in the forearm by a certified phlebotomist and sent to an accredited medical laboratory to measure the level of AST.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>LDL cholesterol</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline measurement (2019.01.01); All assessments will be repeated at 12 months post-intervention (2020.01.01) and at 24 months at the follow-up(2022.01.01)</time_frame>
    <description>Subjects will fast overnight for 10 hours. Subjects will sit in a quiet environment for 15 minutes prior to blood collection. Venous blood will be drawn from an antecubital vein in the forearm by a certified phlebotomist and sent to an accredited medical laboratory to measure the level of LDL cholesterol.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>HDL cholesterol</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline measurement (2019.01.01); All assessments will be repeated at 12 months post-intervention (2020.01.01) and at 24 months at the follow-up(2022.01.01)</time_frame>
    <description>Subjects will fast overnight for 10 hours. Subjects will sit in a quiet environment for 15 minutes prior to blood collection. Venous blood will be drawn from an antecubital vein in the forearm by a certified phlebotomist and sent to an accredited medical laboratory to measure the level of HDL cholesterol.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Total cholesterol</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline measurement (2019.01.01); All assessments will be repeated at 12 months post-intervention (2020.01.01) and at 24 months at the follow-up(2022.01.01)</time_frame>
    <description>Subjects will fast overnight for 10 hours. Subjects will sit in a quiet environment for 15 minutes prior to blood collection. Venous blood will be drawn from an antecubital vein in the forearm by a certified phlebotomist and sent to an accredited medical laboratory to measure the level of total cholesterol.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">120</enrollment>
  <condition>Non-Alcoholic Fatty Liver Disease</condition>
  <condition>Central Obesity</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Usual Care Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects in the usual care control group will receive a health education programme. This programme includes 12-month twice-a-month sessions (70 minutes each session) for obesity-related health briefing, dietary caloric restriction advice, and lifestyle counseling/consultation. The same health information will be delivered to the subjects in the HIIT group throughout the 12-month intervention period. Subjects will be asked to attend &gt;70% of the classes.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>High-intensity Interval Training Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>HIIT will be prescribed once weekly under the supervision of certified athletics coaches for 12 months. HIIT training will be performed in a small group (~10) in an open field setting. In each session, subjects will run for four 4-minute intervals at 85%-95% of the peak heart rate (HRpeak) with a 3-minute active recovery at 50%-70% of the HRpeak between each interval. A 5-minute jog at an intensity of 70% of the HRpeak will be included for warm-up and cool-down before and after, respectively. Subjects will be asked to attend &gt;70% of the classes.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>High-intensity Interval Training</intervention_name>
    <description>In the high-intensity interval training group, subjects will receive respective prescribed exercise once a week.</description>
    <arm_group_label>High-intensity Interval Training Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Usual Care Control</intervention_name>
    <description>In the usual care control group, obesity-related health briefing, dietary caloric restriction advice, and lifestyle counseling/consultation will be provided.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Usual Care Control</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Cantonese, Mandarin or English speaking,

          2. Aged 18-60,

          3. Central obesity, defined as BMI ≥25 (obesity classification adopted by the Hong Kong
             Government) with waist circumference of ≥90 cm for men and ≥80 cm for women (abdominal
             obesity according to the International Diabetes Federation's Chinese ethnic-specific
             criterion),

          4. Willing to initiate lifestyle modification but not pharmacologic or surgical means for
             treating obesity.

        Exclusion criteria:

          1. ≥150 minutes moderate-intensity exercise or ≥75 minutes vigorous exercise weekly,

          2. Regular HIIT (≥1 weekly) in the past six months,

          3. Medical history of cardiovascular disease, chronic pulmonary or kidney disease, heart
             failure, cancer, and liver disease except for NAFLD,

          4. Somatic conditions that limit exercise participation (e.g., limb loss),

          5. Impaired mobility due to chronic diseases (e.g., chronic arthritis/osteoarthritis,
             neurological, musculoskeletal and autoimmune diseases),

          6. Daily smoking habit,

          7. Excess alcohol consumption (daily ≥30 g of alcohol for men and ≥20 g for women) in the
             past six months

          8. Surgery, therapy or medication for obesity or weight loss in the past 6 months (e.g.,
             gastric bypass, gastric band, sleeve gastrectomy, gastric reduction duodenal switch,
             and dietitian-prescribed dietary program).

          9. During the study period, subjects identified with major physical changes that would
             considerably affect their body composition and weight (e.g., anorexia nervosa, bulimia
             nervosa, and prolonged gastrointestinal and digestive disorders) will be excluded.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>60 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>PARCO,MING FAI SIU, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>The University of Hong Kong</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>JUCHENG YU</last_name>
    <phone>97561053</phone>
    <email>dannyu@connect.hku.hk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>PARCO,MING FAI SIU, PhD</last_name>
    <email>pmsiu@hku.hk</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Li Ka Shing Faculty of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hong Kong</city>
        <country>Hong Kong</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>JUCHENG YU, PhD Student</last_name>
      <phone>28315291</phone>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <phone>97561053</phone>
      <email>dannyu@connect.hku.hk</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Hong Kong</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chan AW, Tetzlaff JM, Gøtzsche PC, Altman DG, Mann H, Berlin JA, Dickersin K, Hróbjartsson A, Schulz KF, Parulekar WR, Krleza-Jeric K, Laupacis A, Moher D. SPIRIT 2013 explanation and elaboration: guidance for protocols of clinical trials. BMJ. 2013 Jan 8;346:e7586. doi: 10.1136/bmj.e7586.</citation>
    <PMID>23303884</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Siu PM, Yu AP, Benzie IF, Woo J. Effects of 1-year yoga on cardiovascular risk factors in middle-aged and older adults with metabolic syndrome: a randomized trial. Diabetol Metab Syndr. 2015 Apr 30;7:40. doi: 10.1186/s13098-015-0034-3. eCollection 2015.</citation>
    <PMID>26000038</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Siu PM. Efficacy of Tai Chi training to alleviate insomnia in older adults. Proceeding of The 6th International Conference on Nutrition and Physical Activity (NAPA 2015), Taipei, Taiwan 2015;p.59</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Siu PM, Yu AP, Yu DS, Hui SS, Woo J. Effectiveness of Tai Chi training to alleviate metabolic syndrome in abdominal obese older adults: A randomized controlled trial.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Siu PM, Yu AP, Yu DS, Hui SS, Woo J. Effects of Tai Chi Exercise on Cardiometabolic Health and Muscle Content. Proceeding of the 3rd Asian Conference for Frailty and Sarcopenia, Seoul, Korea 2017</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ramos JS, Dalleck LC, Borrani F, Beetham KS, Mielke GI, Dias KA, Wallen MP, Keating SE, Fassett RG, Coombes JS. High-intensity interval training and cardiac autonomic control in individuals with metabolic syndrome: A randomised trial. Int J Cardiol. 2017 Oct 15;245:245-252. doi: 10.1016/j.ijcard.2017.07.063. Epub 2017 Jul 21.</citation>
    <PMID>28747269</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ramos JS, Dalleck LC, Borrani F, Beetham KS, Wallen MP, Mallard AR, Clark B, Gomersall S, Keating SE, Fassett RG, Coombes JS. Low-Volume High-Intensity Interval Training Is Sufficient to Ameliorate the Severity of Metabolic Syndrome. Metab Syndr Relat Disord. 2017 Sep;15(7):319-328. doi: 10.1089/met.2017.0042. Epub 2017 Jun 22.</citation>
    <PMID>28846513</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ramos JS, Dalleck LC, Borrani F, Mallard AR, Clark B, Keating SE, Fassett RG, Coombes JS. The effect of different volumes of high-intensity interval training on proinsulin in participants with the metabolic syndrome: a randomised trial. Diabetologia. 2016 Nov;59(11):2308-2320. doi: 10.1007/s00125-016-4064-7. Epub 2016 Aug 1.</citation>
    <PMID>27480182</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ramos JS, Dalleck LC, Ramos MV, Borrani F, Roberts L, Gomersall S, Beetham KS, Dias KA, Keating SE, Fassett RG, Sharman JE, Coombes JS. 12 min/week of high-intensity interval training reduces aortic reservoir pressure in individuals with metabolic syndrome: a randomized trial. J Hypertens. 2016 Oct;34(10):1977-87. doi: 10.1097/HJH.0000000000001034.</citation>
    <PMID>27467767</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Siu PM, Chin EC, Wong SH, Fong DY, Chan DK, Ngai HH, Lee CH, Yung PS. Low-frequency high-intensity interval training (HIIT) improves cardiorespiratory fitness and body composition in overweight adults. Med Sci Sports Exerc 2018:abstract submitted to the 65th American College of Sports Medicine (ACSM) Annual Meeting.</citation>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>April 9, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 9, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 11, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 14, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 14, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 18, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>The University of Hong Kong</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Parco M. Siu, PhD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor and Division Head, Division of Kinesiology, School of Public Health, Li Ka Shing Faculty of Medicine</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Long-Term Low-Frequency High-Intensity Interval Training</keyword>
  <keyword>Non-Alcoholic Fatty Liver Disease</keyword>
  <keyword>Central Obesity</keyword>
  <keyword>Body Adiposity</keyword>
  <keyword>Liver Fat</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Liver Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fatty Liver</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Non-alcoholic Fatty Liver Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Obesity</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Obesity, Abdominal</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Patient data can be shared upon request. Personal data such as name, and phone number will be blinded.</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Clinical Study Report (CSR)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>Data will be available for a year after the study is finished and published.</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>Only for Academic use with proof of need.</ipd_access_criteria>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

