<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03913910</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>AOUPisana_1</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03913910</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Perianal Fistula Treatment With Autologous Adipose Tissue Injection</brief_title>
  <official_title>Treatment of Perianal Fistulas Through Injection of Autologous and Micro-fragmented Adipose Tissue: a Prospective Multicentre Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Azienda Ospedaliero, Universitaria Pisana</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Azienda Ospedaliero, Universitaria Pisana</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The study aims to evaluate the efficacy of the local injection of autologous micro-fragmented
      adipose tissue obtained with the Lipogems®system in patients with trans-sphincteric fistulas
      untreatable with fistulotomy.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      STUDY BACKGROUND

      Perianal fistulas are diseases that, by their nature, do not tend to heal spontaneously and
      are very rarely cured with medical treatment. Their healing is usually pursued through
      surgery, which often needs to be repeated due to the natural tendency of the fistulas to
      recur. A surgical treatment that is currently able to provide a high chance of healing is
      fistulotomy which, however, can injure the anal sphincter and may result in degrading scars
      and possible fecal incontinence. One possible strategy could be the lipofilling, i.e.,
      autologous adipose tissue transplant containing, among the many, pericytes and progenitor
      cells, including adult mesenchymal stem cells.

      STUDY DESIGN

      This is a no profit interventional prospective multicenter study without drugs where 100
      patients (10 each participant centre) with a diagnosis of trans-sphincteric anal fistula that
      is not suitable to be laid open will be enrolled.

      After the enrolment, medical history and clinical data will be collected and pre-operatory
      exams will be performed.

      METHODS

      - Harvesting of the adipose tissue

      The lower/lateral abdomen or, eventually, the inner/outer thigh will be chosen as donor site
      for adipose tissue harvesting under general or spinal anaesthesia. Before the harvesting, the
      donor site will be injected with 100 cc of Klein Solution (500 cc saline, 1 cc epinephrine
      1/1000 IU, and 40 cc lidocaine 2%) using a disposable 17 gauge blunt cannula connected to a
      60-cc luer-lock syringe. The fat will be then harvested (50-100 cc) using a 13 gauge blunt
      cannula connected to a 20-ml VacLok® syringe.

      - Processing of the adipose tissue with the Lipogems® device

      The harvested fat will be immediately processed in the Lipogems® processing kit (Lipogems
      International Spa, Milan, Italy). Lipogems® is a disposable device that mechanically reduces
      the size of the adipose tissue clusters while eliminating oily substances and blood residues
      with pro-inflammatory properties. The entire process is carried out in one surgical step in
      complete immersion in physiological solution minimizing any traumatic action on the cells and
      microarchitecture. The processed micro-fragmented fat will be collected in a 60-cc syringe
      and positioned to decant the excess of saline solution. At the end, the product will be
      transferred in several 5-cc syringes to be re-injected in the patient.

      - Surgical procedure and micro-fragmented adipose tissue (Lipogems®) injection

      The micro-fragmented autologous adipose tissue will be injected with wheals of no more than
      1cc in the internal orifice, mucosal, submucosal and muscular layer, then in the fistula
      tract and external orifice.

      - Follow-up visits and outcome measures

      All patients will be assessed at 7 days, 1, 3, 6 and 12 months after the procedure.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Control</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Healing</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Closing of the fistula tract (internal and external orifice)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety collecting all types of adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>All types of adverse events intra-, peri-, or post-operative will be collected</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pain assessed using the Visual Analogue Scale (VAS) for pain</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Pain will be assessed using the Visual Analogue Scale for pain (VAS 0-10), where 0 is no pain and 10 is the maximum pain.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Continence</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Continence will be assessed with the Wexner Continence Grading Scale. The score takes into account the type and frequency of incontinence and the extent to which it alters the patient's life.
This scoring system cross-tabulates frequencies and different anal incontinence presentations (Gas/Liquid/Solid/Pad use/Need for lifestyle alterations) and sums the returned score to a total of 0-20 (where 0 = perfect continence and 20 = complete incontinence).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient's satisfaction</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Patient's satisfaction will be evaluated using a visual analogue scale 0-5, where 0 is no satisfaction and 5 is maximum satisfaction.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Non inferiority compared with the Advancement flap technique</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Non-inferiority will be determined comparing healing rate of Lipogems with retrospective data on the advancement flap.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Perianal Fistula</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Lipogems</arm_group_label>
    <description>Lipogems injection in the internal orifice, mucosal, submucosal and muscular layer, in the fistula tract and external orifice.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Lipogems</intervention_name>
    <description>Autologous micro-fragmented adipose tissue is injected in the internal orifice, mucosal, submucosal and muscular layer, then in the fistula tract and external orifice in addition to anal flap.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Lipogems</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients with a diagnosis of transphincteric anal fistula that is not suitable to be laid
        open.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients of both sexes, aged over 18 and under 80 years old.

          -  Diagnosis, confirmed by standard methods (magnetic resonance and/or trans anal
             ultrasound), of complex fistula (trans-sphincteric unsuitable for treatment lay-open)
             without any secondary tracts and no active septic processes, performed 2-4 weeks after
             the first perianal access drainage procedure and fistulectomy, with positioning of a
             drainage seton.

          -  Seton placed at least 4-6 weeks previously

          -  No previous sphincter saving procedures for the anal fistula

          -  No limitations to a periodic follow-up lasting for a total of 12 months

          -  Informed consent form signed

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with multiple fistulas

          -  Active septic process

          -  Patients unable to follow the pathway required by the protocol

          -  Patients with active Human Immunodeficiency Virus, Hepatitis B Virus or Hepatitis C
             Virus infections

          -  Patients with Irritable Bowel Syndrome

          -  Patients with rectal-vaginal fistulas

          -  Patients with a history of cancer lasting less than 5 years

          -  Patients undergoing cortisone and/or immunosuppressive and/or anticoagulant therapy

          -  Patients with a history rectal or pelvic radiotherapy

          -  Pregnant women

          -  Patients with connective tissue diseases and/or coagulation diseases and/or
             uncompensated diabetes mellitus

          -  Failure to sign the informed consent form
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Gabriele Naldini, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+39050997802</phone>
    <email>gabrielenaldini65@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Alessandro Sturiale, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+39050997814</phone>
    <email>alexstur@yahoo.it</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>AOU Pisana - Cisanello</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pisa</city>
        <state>Toscana</state>
        <zip>56124</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Gabriele Naldini, MD</last_name>
      <email>gabrielenaldini65@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Alessandro Sturiale</last_name>
      <phone>0039 3311372249</phone>
      <email>alexstur@yahoo.it</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Italy</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Naldini G, Sturiale A, Fabiani B, Giani I, Menconi C. Micro-fragmented adipose tissue injection for the treatment of complex anal fistula: a pilot study accessing safety and feasibility. Tech Coloproctol. 2018 Feb;22(2):107-113. doi: 10.1007/s10151-018-1755-8. Epub 2018 Feb 16.</citation>
    <PMID>29453515</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tremolada C, Colombo V, Ventura C. Adipose Tissue and Mesenchymal Stem Cells: State of the Art and Lipogems® Technology Development. Curr Stem Cell Rep. 2016;2:304-312. Epub 2016 Jul 13. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>27547712</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ceserani V, Ferri A, Berenzi A, Benetti A, Ciusani E, Pascucci L, Bazzucchi C, Coccè V, Bonomi A, Pessina A, Ghezzi E, Zeira O, Ceccarelli P, Versari S, Tremolada C, Alessandri G. Angiogenic and anti-inflammatory properties of micro-fragmented fat tissue and its derived mesenchymal stromal cells. Vasc Cell. 2016 Aug 18;8:3. doi: 10.1186/s13221-016-0037-3. eCollection 2016.</citation>
    <PMID>27547374</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tremolada C, Ricordi C, Caplan AI, Ventura C. Mesenchymal Stem Cells in Lipogems, a Reverse Story: from Clinical Practice to Basic Science. Methods Mol Biol. 2016;1416:109-22. doi: 10.1007/978-1-4939-3584-0_6.</citation>
    <PMID>27236668</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Vezzani B, Shaw I, Lesme H, Yong L, Khan N, Tremolada C, Péault B. Higher Pericyte Content and Secretory Activity of Microfragmented Human Adipose Tissue Compared to Enzymatically Derived Stromal Vascular Fraction. Stem Cells Transl Med. 2018 Dec;7(12):876-886. doi: 10.1002/sctm.18-0051. Epub 2018 Sep 26.</citation>
    <PMID>30255987</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Garcia-Contreras M, Messaggio F, Mendez AJ, Ricordi C. Metabolomic changes in human adipose tissue derived products following non-enzymatic microfacturing. Eur Rev Med Pharmacol Sci. 2018 May;22(10):3249-3260. doi: 10.26355/eurrev_201805_15088.</citation>
    <PMID>29863273</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cestaro G, De Rosa M, Massa S, Amato B, Gentile M. Intersphincteric anal lipofilling with micro-fragmented fat tissue for the treatment of faecal incontinence: preliminary results of three patients. Wideochir Inne Tech Maloinwazyjne. 2015 Jul;10(2):337-41. doi: 10.5114/wiitm.2014.47435. Epub 2014 Dec 4.</citation>
    <PMID>26240640</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bianchi F, Maioli M, Leonardi E, Olivi E, Pasquinelli G, Valente S, Mendez AJ, Ricordi C, Raffaini M, Tremolada C, Ventura C. A new nonenzymatic method and device to obtain a fat tissue derivative highly enriched in pericyte-like elements by mild mechanical forces from human lipoaspirates. Cell Transplant. 2013;22(11):2063-77. doi: 10.3727/096368912X657855. Epub 2012 Oct 8.</citation>
    <PMID>23051701</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Paolella F, Manferdini C, Gabusi E, Gambari L, Filardo G, Kon E, Mariani E, Lisignoli G. Effect of microfragmented adipose tissue on osteoarthritic synovial macrophage factors. J Cell Physiol. 2019 Apr;234(4):5044-5055. doi: 10.1002/jcp.27307. Epub 2018 Sep 6.</citation>
    <PMID>30187478</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>April 11, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 11, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 12, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 10, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 10, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 14, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Azienda Ospedaliero, Universitaria Pisana</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Gabriele Naldini</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Autologous micro-fragmented adipose tissue</keyword>
  <keyword>Perianal fistula</keyword>
  <keyword>Lipogems</keyword>
  <keyword>Mesenchymal Stem Cells</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Rectal Fistula</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fistula</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

