<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03914391</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CRE-2018.376</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03914391</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>To Identify Potential New Urine Markers for the Screening of Prostate Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>To Identify Potential New Urine Markers for the Screening of Prostate Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Chinese University of Hong Kong</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Chinese University of Hong Kong</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Prostate gland is a clinically important male sexual organ and its main function is for the
      production of semen. Globally, it is the second most common cancer in men globally and is
      also the fifth cancer cause for death in male. Despite the improvement in the understanding
      of prostate cancer, the current usage of serum prostate specific antigen (PSA) as a
      diagnostic marker is still not ideal. Many patients with elevated PSA and then subjected to
      prostate biopsy were found to have no prostate cancer. Therefore, there is a need to discover
      new biological markers to improve the current situation in diagnosis and also management of
      prostate cancer.

      From the earlier small-scale studies, urinary spermine levels have been shown to correlate
      well with prostate cancer diagnosis and cancer aggressiveness. Due to its nature, it could
      provide a more convenient and non-invasive method for detecting prostate cancer. The purpose
      of this study was to collect urine samples to study the role of potential new urine
      diagnostic markers (including Spermine and others) for prostate cancer diagnosis.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Prostate cancer (PC) is highly prevalent worldwide and is the second most commonly diagnosed
      cancer in men globally and is the 5th leading cause of cancer death in men. 1 In some Asian
      areas, even n with widely used serum Prostate Specific Antigen (PSA) diagnostic testing, more
      than 50% men with newly diagnosed PC are deemed to have high risk disease. 2 However, the
      current use of serum PSA as a diagnostic marker is unsatisfactory. Many patients has elevated
      serum PSA is actually due to other causes and also the level of serum PSA do not correlate
      with the staging and grading of prostate cancer. 3 Moreover, the use of serum PSA required
      blood taking which is invasive and non-convenience for large scale screening. Therefore,
      newer markers is needed for more simple and accurate diagnosis of prostate cancer.

      One example of such cancer biomarkers are natural polyamines. Interests on these analytes
      have been starting in 1971 when Russell reported a considerable increase of urinary
      polyamines such as putrescine (Put), spermidine (Spd) and spermine (Spm) in patients with
      various types of solid tumors and leukaemias. 4 Afterwards, polyamine studies focusing on
      specific cancers continued, like cervical cancer, 5 colorectal cancer 6 and breast cancer, 7
      etc. In investigators' recent study, investigators have explored the potential roles of
      urinary polyamines as prostate cancer biomarkers were evaluated. Patients with prostate
      cancer (PCa), benign prostatic hyperplasia (BPH) patients and healthy controls (HC) showing
      PSA&gt;4.0ng/ml were enrolled in the study.8 Their urine samples were obtained, and the urinary
      levels of Put, Spd, Spm were determined by ultra-high-performance liquid chromatography
      coupled with triple quadrupole mass spectrometer (UPLC-MS/MS). Receiver operating
      characteristics (ROC) curve and Student's t- test were used to evaluate their diagnostic
      accuracies. Among the three biogenic polyamines, Spm had demonstrated a good diagnostic
      performance when comparing their levels in PCa patients with BPH patients (1.47 in PCa vs
      5.87 in BPH; p&lt;0.0001). The results were in accordance with transrectal ultrasound prostatic
      biopsy (TRUSPB) results, with an area under curve (AUC) value of 0.83±0.03. Therefore,
      urinary Spm could have a potential to serve as a novel PCa diagnostic biomarker, which in
      turn could help to address the limited sensitivity and specificity problem of serum PSA test.

      Therefore, investigators would like to have a larger scale study, with inclusion of subjects
      from different geographic locations, to further assess the correlation spermine and other
      potential newer urine markers with diagnosis of prostate cancer and investigate their role as
      a potential non-invasive marker for prostate cancer risk stratification and prognosis
      prediction.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 16, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To investigate the role of urine spermine in the diagnosis of prostate cancer</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline (one-time point)</time_frame>
    <description>Fresh urine will be collected for liquid chromatography and mass spectrometry to detect the concentration of spermine in urine. Then the The correlation between the concentration of urine spermine and serum PSA level and pathological result will be assessed.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To investigate the role of urine spermine in prognostic prediction of prostate cancer</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline (one-time point)</time_frame>
    <description>Fresh urine will be collected for liquid chromatography and mass spectrometry to detect the concentration of spermine in urine. Then the The correlation between the concentration of urine spermine and pathological result and serum PSA level will be assessed.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">10000</enrollment>
  <condition>Prostate Cancer</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients who has elevated serum PSA, i.e. &gt; 4ng/ml, and planned for prostatic biopsy.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Adult male patients with age &gt; 18 years old

          2. Subject has elevated serum PSA level above 4ng/ml

          3. Clinical planned for prostatic biopsy.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Patient with recent urinary tract infection within 6 weeks prior to PSA testing and
             urine collection.

          2. Patient with recent urethral instrumentation, such as Foley catheter insertion,
             cystoscopy etc, within 6 weeks prior to PSA testing and urine collection.

          3. Patient with consumption of 5 alpha reductase inhibitors in past 6 months.

          4. Patient did not receive any surgery for prostatic pathology

          5. Patient refused or unable to provide consent for the study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <gender_based>Yes</gender_based>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Chi Fai Ng, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>The Chinese University if Hong Kong</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Chi Fai Ng, MD</last_name>
    <phone>852-3505-2625</phone>
    <email>ngcf@surgery.cuhk.edu.hk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Prince of Wales Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Shatin</city>
        <country>Hong Kong</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Chi Fai NG, MD</last_name>
      <phone>3505 3953</phone>
      <email>ngcf@surgery.cuhk.edu.hk</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Pui Tak LAI, BN</last_name>
      <phone>3505 1663</phone>
      <email>francolai@surgery.cuhk.edu.hk</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Hong Kong</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>April 9, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 11, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 16, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 16, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 16, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 20, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Chinese University of Hong Kong</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Chi Fai NG</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Prostatic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

