<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03583840</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>RP041A-15HTM</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03583840</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effectiveness of a Web-based Intervention to Promote Health Screening in Men</brief_title>
  <acronym>ScreenMen</acronym>
  <official_title>Effectiveness of a Web-based Intervention to Promote Health Screening in Men: A Community-based Randomised Controlled Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Malaya</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Leeds Beckett University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Sheffield</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>The University of New South Wales</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Malaya</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Health screening is proven to be effective in reducing morbidity, death and healthcare cost.
      However, the uptake of health screening is low particularly in men. In the earlier phase of
      this project, a web-based intervention (ScreenMen) to increase health screening uptake in men
      was developed based on theories, evidence and user needs. It was tested with experts and
      users for its utility and usability.

      In this phase, a randomised controlled trial (RCT) will be conducted to evaluate the
      effectiveness of ScreenMen in improving health screening knowledge &amp; uptake in men. Healthy
      men, who have not gone for screening in the past 1 year will be recruited via Facebook to
      participate in this RCT. The participants will be randomised to receive or not to receive
      ScreenMen. Knowledge and intention to screen will be measured immediately post-intervention.
      All participants will be followed up at 1 month and 3 months to measure knowledge, intention
      and actual uptake of screening.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The uptake of health screening is low in Malaysia, particularly in men. There is a need to
      increase health screening uptake in men as this will not just save healthcare cost and
      increase national productivity in the long run but also improve the quality of life of men
      and their family.

      There were many interventions to increase health screening uptake in men which have been
      identified in the systematic review conducted in the earlier phase of this study. However,
      there is a lack of ICT-based intervention promoting health screening. The few existing ICT
      based interventions only focus on screening on a specific disease such as HIV or prostate
      cancer.(1-3) There was no ICT-based intervention which aimed to increase the uptake of
      comprehensive health screening.

      Studies have shown that ICT-based interventions are effective in improving health
      behaviour.(4) On top of that, there is a high number of internet accessibility and smartphone
      ownership in Malaysia, which provides a good platform to promote health screening in men.
      Thus, ScreenMen, a web-based intervention was developed based on theories, evidence and
      users' needs. It was tested with experts and users in terms of its utility and usability.
      (5-7)

      To the best of our knowledge, ScreenMen is the first mobile-responsive web-based intervention
      that promotes comprehensive evidence-based health screening in men. It aims to educate men
      about screening and empowers them to take charge of their health including undergoing regular
      health screening. Apart from encouraging health screening, ScreenMen provides advice to men
      about the recommended health screening they should undergo based on their health risks and
      educates them to avoid non-evidence-based screening.

      Before being launched to the public, a randomised controlled trial (RCT) will be conducted to
      evaluate the effectiveness of ScreenMen in improving knowledge on screening, intention to
      screen and the actual uptake of screening. Process evaluation will also be conducted to
      identify the components that work in improving health screening uptake and resolve any
      implementation issues of ScreenMen.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 27, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Screening</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
    <masking_description>It is not possible to blind the participants as the intervention is a website. Participants in the intervention arm will need to go through the website and will know its contents while participants in the control arm will not.
There is no care provider in this study as the intervention is delivered via a website.
The assignment of intervention or control arm to the participants will be done automatically by the website. After signing the consent form, participants will enter a website which will randomise them to either intervention or control arm. The investigators do not play a role in this.
The outcome assessment only involves the participants answering a questionnaire themselves. No Outcome Assessor is required to assess any outcome from the participants.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants who have undergone health screening</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month post-intervention</time_frame>
    <description>A questionnaire will be sent to the participants 1 month after using the intervention (ScreenMen web) to assess whether they have undergone health screening.
The number of participants who have undergone health screening will be divided over the total number of participants in this study to obtain the proportion and according to study arm.
Uptake at 1 month Intervention: %= n / N *100%; Control: %= n / N *100%</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants who have undergone health screening</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months post-intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Participants who reported that they have not undergone health screening during the 1-month follow up will be followed up at 3-month. They will be asked whether they have undergone health screening up to this stage.
The number of participants who have undergone health screening (including those from 1-month follow up) will be divided over the total number of participants in this study to obtain the proportion and according to study arm.
Uptake at 3 month (including those reported yes in 1-month follow up) Intervention: %= n / N *100%; Control: %= n / N *100%</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in intention (months) to undergo health screening</measure>
    <time_frame>Immediately post-intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Immediately after using the ScreenMen web, participants will be asked when do they intend to undergo health screening. They will be asked in terms of 'in the next __ month(s)'.
The same question has been asked pre-intervention. The change in the 'month(s)' will be calculated. This will be averaged and compared between the intervention and control group.
Change in intention to screen (months) immediately post-intervention = pre-intervention intention to screen (months) - post-intervention intention to screen (months)
Comparison between the change in intention to screen (months) [immediate] for intervention arm and change in intention to screen (months) [immediate] for control arm will be done.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in intention (months) to undergo health screening</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month post-intervention</time_frame>
    <description>One month after using the ScreenMen web, participants will be followed up and asked if they have undergone health screening. If not, they will be asked when do they intend to undergo health screening. They will be asked in terms of 'in the next __ month(s)'.
Change in intention to screen will be calculated based on their immediate intention to screen after intervention
Comparison between the change in intention to screen (months) [1-month] for intervention arm and change in intention to screen (months) [1-month] for control arm will be done.
The aim of this is to evaluate the long-term effect of the intervention, whether it is sustained or diminished.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in intention (months) to undergo health screening</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months post-intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Participants who have not undergone screening will be followed up again at 3-month and asked if they have undergone health screening. If not, they will be asked when do they intend to undergo health screening. They will be asked in terms of 'in the next __ month(s)'.
Change in intention to screen will be calculated based on their immediate intention to screen after intervention
Comparison between the change in intention to screen (months) [3-month] for intervention arm and change in intention to screen (months) [3-month] for control arm will be done.
The aim of this is to evaluate the long-term effect of the intervention, whether it is sustained or diminished.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in knowledge on health screening</measure>
    <time_frame>Immediately post-intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Immediately after using the ScreenMen web, participants will be asked to answer a validated questionnaire on health screening. The score will be calculated by calculating the number of correctly answered questions over the total number of questions. Knowledge Score (post-intervention - immediate) = n/N
The participants have filled the same questionnaire pre-intervention. Change of knowledge score will be calculated as shown below:
Change in Knowledge Score = Knowledge Score (post-intervention - immediate) - Knowledge Score (pre-intervention)
The Change in Knowledge Score will be compared between intervention and control group.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in knowledge on health screening</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month post-intervention</time_frame>
    <description>One month after using the ScreenMen web, participants will be followed up and asked to fill up the same health screening questionnaire. The score will be calculated by calculating the number of correctly answered questions over the total number of questions. Knowledge Score (post-intervention - immediate) = n/N
Change of knowledge score from immediate to 1 month post-intervention will be calculated as shown below:
Change in Knowledge Score = Knowledge Score (1 month post-intervention) - Knowledge Score (immediately post-intervention)
The Change in Knowledge Score from immediate to 1 month post-intervention will be compared between intervention and control group.
The aim of this is to evaluate the long-term effect of the intervention, whether the participants' knowledge on health screening is sustained or diminished.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in knowledge on health screening</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months post-intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Three months after using the ScreenMen web, participants will be followed up and asked to fill up the same health screening questionnaire. The score will be calculated by calculating the number of correctly answered questions over the total number of questions. Knowledge Score (post-intervention - immediate) = n/N
Change of knowledge score from immediate to 3 months post-intervention will be calculated as shown below:
Change in Knowledge Score = Knowledge Score (3 months post-intervention) - Knowledge Score (immediately post-intervention)
The Change in Knowledge Score from immediate to 1 months post-intervention will be compared between intervention and control group.
The aim of this is to evaluate the long-term effect of the intervention, whether the participants' knowledge on health screening is sustained or diminished.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">220</enrollment>
  <condition>Mass Screening</condition>
  <condition>Preventive Health Services</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants who will not be directed to the ScreenMen website</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants who will be directed to the ScreenMen website</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ScreenMen website</intervention_name>
    <description>An educational website that aims to improve evidence-based health screening uptake in men</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion criteria:

          -  Male

          -  18 year old and above

          -  Own a smart phone

        Exclusion criteria:

          -  Undergone health screening within the past 1 year

          -  Diagnosed with any of the following diseases (Hypertension, Diabetes, High
             cholesterol, Colorectal cancer, Lung cancer, Hepatitis B, Hepatitis C, HIV
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Chirk Jenn Ng, MMed,PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Malaya</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Malaya</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kuala Lumpur</city>
        <country>Malaysia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Malaysia</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bauermeister JA, Pingel ES, Jadwin-Cakmak L, Harper GW, Horvath K, Weiss G, Dittus P. Acceptability and preliminary efficacy of a tailored online HIV/STI testing intervention for young men who have sex with men: the Get Connected! program. AIDS Behav. 2015 Oct;19(10):1860-74. doi: 10.1007/s10461-015-1009-y.</citation>
    <PMID>25638038</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Evans R, Joseph-Williams N, Edwards A, Newcombe RG, Wright P, Kinnersley P, Griffiths J, Jones M, Williams J, Grol R, Elwyn G. Supporting informed decision making for prostate specific antigen (PSA) testing on the web: an online randomized controlled trial. J Med Internet Res. 2010 Aug 6;12(3):e27. doi: 10.2196/jmir.1305.</citation>
    <PMID>20693148</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hirshfield S, Chiasson MA, Joseph H, Scheinmann R, Johnson WD, Remien RH, Shaw FS, Emmons R, Yu G, Margolis AD. An online randomized controlled trial evaluating HIV prevention digital media interventions for men who have sex with men. PLoS One. 2012;7(10):e46252. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0046252. Epub 2012 Oct 2.</citation>
    <PMID>23071551</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wantland DJ, Portillo CJ, Holzemer WL, Slaughter R, McGhee EM. The effectiveness of Web-based vs. non-Web-based interventions: a meta-analysis of behavioral change outcomes. J Med Internet Res. 2004 Nov 10;6(4):e40. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>15631964</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schnall R, Rojas M, Bakken S, Brown W, Carballo-Dieguez A, Carry M, Gelaude D, Mosley JP, Travers J. A user-centered model for designing consumer mobile health (mHealth) applications (apps). J Biomed Inform. 2016 Apr;60:243-51. doi: 10.1016/j.jbi.2016.02.002. Epub 2016 Feb 20.</citation>
    <PMID>26903153</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Uhler LM, Pérez Figueroa RE, Dickson M, McCullagh L, Kushniruk A, Monkman H, Witteman HO, Hajizadeh N. InformedTogether: Usability Evaluation of a Web-Based Decision Aid to Facilitate Shared Advance Care Planning for Severe Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease. JMIR Hum Factors. 2015 Feb 25;2(1):e2. doi: 10.2196/humanfactors.3842.</citation>
    <PMID>27025896</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Verkuyl M, Atack L, Mastrilli P, Romaniuk D. Virtual gaming to develop students' pediatric nursing skills: A usability test. Nurse Educ Today. 2016 Nov;46:81-85. doi: 10.1016/j.nedt.2016.08.024. Epub 2016 Aug 25.</citation>
    <PMID>27614548</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Young SD, Cumberland WG, Lee SJ, Jaganath D, Szekeres G, Coates T. Social networking technologies as an emerging tool for HIV prevention: a cluster randomized trial. Ann Intern Med. 2013 Sep 3;159(5):318-24. doi: 10.7326/0003-4819-159-5-201309030-00005.</citation>
    <PMID>24026317</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>July 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 18, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 28, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 11, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 21, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 21, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 23, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Malaya</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Professor Ng Chirk Jenn</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor Dr</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>men's health</keyword>
  <keyword>internet</keyword>
  <keyword>telemedicine</keyword>
  <keyword>mass screening</keyword>
  <keyword>health behavior</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

