<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03581747</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>EB/EIS</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03581747</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Detection of Skin Epithelial Barrier in Patients With Allergic Skin Disorders</brief_title>
  <official_title>Assessment of Skin Epithelial Barrier Defects in Patients With Allergic Skin Disorders by Electrical Impedance Spectroscopy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Swiss Institute of Allergy and Asthma Research</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>CK-CARE (Christine Kühne – Center for Allergy Research and Education)</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>SciBase AB</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Swiss Institute of Allergy and Asthma Research</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The primary function of epithelial tissues is to form a barrier between the body and the
      external environment, in order to protect the internal tissues from environmental stresses,
      by minimizing water loss and preventing the entry of pathogens, pollutants and allergens.
      Allergic disorders, such as atopic dermatitis, have been associated to an impaired epithelial
      barrier function. Indeed, defects in the epithelial barriers allow tissue-damaging factors to
      enter the tissue and thus activate the immune response. This study aims to establish a method
      to assess the epithelial barrier function in vivo by electrical impedance (EI) spectroscopy,
      a new technique for the characterisation of epithelial tissue. By this technique, a harmless
      electrical signal is sent through the skin and the response of the tissue is analysed, which
      is influenced by several cellular properties, such as shape, orientation and size. In order
      to validate this technique, skin of mice was treated with some molecules able to destroy the
      epithelial barrier. The investigators observed that, after damaging the barrier, a decrease
      of the EI can be detected, consistent with the type and degree of the damage.

      Based on this result, the investigators believe that this technique is a good candidate as an
      in vivo method to determine skin barrier defects, which might be used in the future as an
      early diagnostic tool for the prediction of the risk to develop atopic dermatitis in young
      subjects, allowing the possibility to apply in time possible preventive measures. In
      addition, this technique might be suitable for the evaluation of a given therapy during the
      hospitalisation. To confirm this hypothesis, in the present study patients with atopic
      dermatitis will be recruited. EI measurements will be performed in both lesional and
      non-lesional skin and values will be compared in order to detect any difference in the
      electrical response due to the inflammatory state. In addition, in order to evaluate whether
      these patients have an appreciable defect in their skin electrical behaviour, the
      investigators will compare non-lesional and lesional skin of patients with skin of healthy
      volunteers. Peripheral venous blood and skin biopsies will be collected, in oder to
      characterise several immune cell populations, to detect specific skin barrier mutations and
      to measure serum cytokines and immunoglobulins. These and some other parameters and will be
      analysed in order to identify a possible correlation with the EI.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">August 1, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Control</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Comparison of electrical impedance values between lesional and non-lesional skin in patients with atopic dermatitis</measure>
    <time_frame>At Day 0 on hospital admission</time_frame>
    <description>In patients with atopic dermatitis electrical impedance will be measured. Measurements will be performed in both lesional skin and non-lesional skin and values will be compared in order to detect any difference in skin permeability and electrical response due to the inflammatory state.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Comparison of electrical impedance values in healthy controls and patients with atopic dermatitis</measure>
    <time_frame>At Day 0 on hospital admission</time_frame>
    <description>In order to evaluate whether patients have an appreciable defect in their skin electrical behaviour, we will compare the skin of patients with the skin of healthy volunteers.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Correlation between electrical impedance measurements and innate and adaptive immune responses</measure>
    <time_frame>At Day 0 on hospital admission; at Day 10; at Day 20 on completion of treatment.</time_frame>
    <description>50 ml of peripheral venous blood will be taken in lithium heparin 7 ml tubes and one 7 ml tube without anticoagulant for serum collection. Peripheral blood mononuclear cells (PBMC) will be purified by ficoll density gradient from venous blood and then analysed by multicolor flow cytometry, to characterize T cells, B cells, Natural Killer cells and other immune cell populations. Possible correlations between EI values and these cell subsets will be described.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Correlation between electrical impedance measurements and genes associated with epidermal barrier defects</measure>
    <time_frame>At Day 0 on hospital admission; at Day 10; at Day 20 on completion of treatment.</time_frame>
    <description>From venous blood, DNA will be isolated to detect specific skin barrier mutations, such as filaggrin defects. Possible correlations between EI values and these defects will be identified.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Correlation between electrical impedance measurements and immune biomarkers in serum</measure>
    <time_frame>At Day 0 on hospital admission; at Day 10; at Day 20 on completion of treatment.</time_frame>
    <description>From serum, cytokines and immunoglobulins will be measured, by using protein analysis methods (immunoblotting, ELISA), in order to identify a possible correlation between EI values and specific serum biomarkers.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Correlation between electrical impedance measurements and the expression profile of relevant proteins at skin tissue level</measure>
    <time_frame>At Day 0 on hospital admission; at Day 10; at Day 20 on completion of treatment.</time_frame>
    <description>Skin biopsies will be collected, Real Time Polymerase Chain Reaction (PCR) and immunohistochemistry will be performed to analyse relevant skin molecules, such epidermal barrier proteins and tight junction proteins. Possible correlations between EI values and the expression of these proteins will be described.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">1000</enrollment>
  <condition>Atopic Dermatitis</condition>
  <condition>Skin Inflammation</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Subjects with atopic dermatitis</arm_group_label>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Controls</arm_group_label>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Nevisense</intervention_name>
    <description>Measurement of electrical impedance</description>
    <arm_group_label>Controls</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Subjects with atopic dermatitis</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients will be recruited from the Hochgebirgsklinik in Davos Wolfgang. Healthy controls
        will be recruited within the heathy population. All individuals will be sampled for skin,
        blood and other samples after informal consent.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        The inclusion criteria for patients in this study are as follows:

          1. Age 0 - 85 years

          2. Diagnosis of atopic dermatitis and/or another disease of the atopic group

          3. The inclusion of patients in this study is independent from the current therapy.
             During the study all patients will be kept on a therapy that is medically indicated

        The inclusion criteria for healthy controls in this study are as follows:

          1. Age 0 - 85 years

          2. No diagnosis or history of allergic disease

          3. The inclusion of patients in this study is independent from the current therapy.
             During the study all patients will be kept on a therapy that is medically indicated
             Written consent will be obtained after detailed information of the study was given to
             the participant.

        Exclusion criteria:

        Unable to give consent or refusal to participate in the study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>85 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Arturo O Rinaldi</last_name>
    <phone>+41814100842</phone>
    <email>arturo.rinaldi@siaf.uzh.ch</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Swiss Institute of Allergy and Asthma Research (SIAF)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Davos Platz</city>
        <state>Grisons</state>
        <zip>7270</zip>
        <country>Switzerland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Arturo O Rinaldi, MSc</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Cezmi A Akdis, Prof., M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Arturo O Rinaldi, MSc</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Switzerland</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>April 25, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 9, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 10, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 7, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 7, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">September 10, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Atopic dermatis</keyword>
  <keyword>Epithelial barrier</keyword>
  <keyword>Electrical impedance spectroscopy</keyword>
  <keyword>Allergy</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Dermatitis, Atopic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dermatitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Skin Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Inflammation</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

