<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03582774</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>18-000484</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NUC MED 18-000484</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-02018-01518</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03582774</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Trial of 68Ga-PSMA-11 PET/CT Molecular Imaging for Prostate Cancer Salvage Radiotherapy Planning [PSMA-SRT]</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase III Randomized Trial of 68Ga-PSMA-11 PET/CT Molecular Imaging for Prostate Cancer Salvage Radiotherapy Planning [PSMA-SRT]</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Jonsson Comprehensive Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Jonsson Comprehensive Cancer Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To evaluate the success rate of salvage radiation therapy (SRT) for recurrence of prostate
      cancer after prostatectomy with and without planning based on 68Ga-PSMA-11 PET/CT.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      For men with a recurrence following radical prostatectomy, salvage external beam radiation
      therapy (SRT) can provide long-term disease control if the recurrence is encompassed within
      the treatment field and a sufficient radiation dose can be delivered to eradicate the
      residual/recurrent cancer. SRT offers long-term biochemical control in about 60% of patients.
      Target volume delineations for prostate cancer SRT after radical prostatectomy are usually
      drawn in the absence of visibly recurrent disease.

      68Ga-PSMA-11 PET/CT detects recurrent prostate cancer with sensitivity superior to standard
      of care imaging at serum prostate specific antigen (PSA) values low enough to impact routine
      SRT planning (i.e. &lt;1.0 ng/ml). 68Ga-PSMA-11 PET/CT imaging can improve patient selection for
      successful SRT by excluding patients with M1 disease where SRT would be futile (extra-pelvic
      disease is seen in at least 13% of patients with PSA &lt;1.0 ng/ml) and by improving the
      coverage of the recurrent lesions by the pelvic radiation fields (out-of-field pelvic disease
      is seen in at least 7% of patients).

      This phase III randomized trial aims at showing that 68Ga-PSMA-11 PET/CT improve the success
      rate of SRT after radical prostatectomy.

      Routine care SRT involves either radiotherapy directed to the prostate bed alone, or the
      prostate bed and pelvic lymph nodes. In addition, the radiotherapy can be delivered either
      with or without concurrent ADT (typically for 6 months duration of ADT). The choice of
      treating the prostate bed alone vs prostate bed and pelvic lymph nodes, with or without ADT,
      is based upon clinico-pathologic features and practice patterns of the treating physician.
      The treating physician will be asked to describe their general treatment plan prior to
      randomization.

      The treating physician will be encouraged to pursue their general treatment plan after
      randomization regardless of what arm the patient is randomized into. In some cases, due to
      specific anatomical features of the patient (for example, location of small bowel), or
      patient's preference (for example, patient may decline ADT), the general treatment plan may
      be modified during the radiotherapy planning process. However, the treating physician is
      encouraged not to use the results of the PSMA PET/CT, if patient receives this scan, to
      de-escalate therapy. For example, a negative PSMA PET/CT does not mean that the patient has
      no recurrent prostate cancer. Furthermore, a PSMA PET/CT showing PSMA positive disease in one
      or more pelvic nodes does not exclude the possibility of additional disease in the prostate
      bed, and vice versa.

      Patients will be followed until either one of the following conditions occur: 5 years after
      the date of initiation of SRT, Biochemical progression, Diagnostic of metastatic disease,
      Initiation of any additional, salvage therapy, Death.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 12, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of biochemical progression-free survival</measure>
    <time_frame>Time Frame: From date of initiation of salvage radiation therapy until the date of first documented progression or date of death from any cause, whichever came first, assessed up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Success rate of SRT measured as biochemical progression-free survival after initiation of SRT. Biochemical progression is defined by PSA ≥ 0.2 ng/mL and rising after completion of SRT</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>5-year progression-free survival rate</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <description>5-year biochemical progression-free survival rate (from date of initiation of SRT)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Metastasis free-survival</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Diagnostic of extra-pelvic metastatic (M1) disease can be obtained by any imaging or biopsy</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of additional prostate cancer therapy initiation-free survival</measure>
    <time_frame>assessed up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <description>From the initiation of salvage radiation therapy until the first documented initiation of any additional prostate cancer treatment</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">193</enrollment>
  <condition>Recurrent Prostate Carcinoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patient does not undergo 68Ga-PSMA-11 PET/CT for SRT planning.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patient undergoes 68Ga-PSMA-11 PET/CT for SRT planning.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>68Ga-PSMA-11</intervention_name>
    <description>If 68Ga-PSMA-11 PET/CT scan detects PSMA-positive lesions in the pelvis: SRT will be performed per discretion of the treating radiation oncologist. SRT can be performed as routinely planned in accordance with the initial general treatment plan. SRT can also be performed with adapted/extended target volumes to include all pelvic PSMA-positive lesions within the radiation fields. SRT also may be performed with focal dose escalation on the PSMA-positive lesions if feasible. If 68Ga-PSMA-11 PET/CT scan detects PSMA-positive lesions outside the pelvis: treatment management will be performed as per discretion of the treating radiation oncologist. However, the patient will not be included in analysis of the primary endpoint. We assume that approximately 13% of subjects randomized to Arm 2 will be found to be ineligible for SRT and will not be included for further analysis.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 2</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Histopathology proven prostate cancer

          2. Planned SRT for recurrence after primary prostatectomy

          3. PSA ≥ 0.1ng/ml at time of enrollment

          4. Willingness to undergo radiotherapy.

          5. Treating radiation oncologist intends to incorporate 68Ga-PSMA-11 PET/CT findings into
             the radiotherapy plan if patient undergoes 68Ga-PSMA-11 PET/CT -

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Extra-pelvic metastasis on any imaging or biopsy

          2. Prior PSMA PET/CT

          3. Prior pelvic external beam radiation therapy (RT)

          4. Androgen deprivation therapy (ADT) within 3 months before 68Ga-PSMA-11 PET/CT

          5. Contraindications to radiotherapy (including active inflammatory bowel disease)

          6. Concurrent systemic therapy for prostate cancer with investigational agents. -
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <gender_based>Yes</gender_based>
    <gender_description>Prostate Cancer only occurs in male subjects</gender_description>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jeremie Calais, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of California, Los Angeles</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Kiara Booker Adame</last_name>
    <phone>310-206-7372</phone>
    <email>KMBooker@mednet.ucla.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Stephanie Lira</last_name>
    <phone>310 206 7372</phone>
    <email>StephanieLira@mednet.ucla.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UCLA</name>
      <address>
        <city>Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90095</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>J Gartman</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 19, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 27, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 11, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 22, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 22, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 23, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Prostatic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

