<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03580291</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2017001</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03580291</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Human Umbilical Cord Mesenchymal Stem Cells Treatment for Lupus Nephritis (LN)</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized, Double-Blind, Parallel-Controlled, Multi-Center Study to Evaluate the Safety and Efficacy of Human Umbilical Cord Mesenchymal Stem Cells in Patients With Lupus Nephritis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Lingyun Sun</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>The Affiliated Nanjing Drum Tower Hospital of Nanjing University Medical School</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Lupus nephritis (LN) is one of the most serious complications and the main cause of death in
      patients with systemic lupus erythematosus (SLE).The investigators have investigated the
      usefulness, and confirmed the efficacy and safety of mesenchymal stem cells (MSC) treatment
      of LN in animal models, in vitro experiments and phase I clinical trial. In this study, a
      randomized, placebo-controlled, parallel group, non-inferiority, prospective, multicenter
      clinical trial is performed to investigate the efficacy and safety of MSC transplantation in
      the treatment of LN compared to mycophenolate mofetil (MMF).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Lupus nephritis (LN) is one of the most serious complications and the main cause of death in
      patients with systemic lupus erythematosus (SLE). Type III, type IV and type V LN are severe
      clinical entities with poor prognosis, and its treatment remains challenging. Currently, type
      III, type IV, type V, type III plus V and type IV plus V LN are treated mainly according to
      the guidelines developed by KDIGO and the European Association for Anti-Rheumatism and
      European League Against Rheumatism/European Renal Association-European Dialysis and
      Transplant Association (EULAR/ERAEDTA). The main therapeutic regimens recommended by these
      guidelines include glucocorticoid combined with immunosuppressants such as cyclophosphamide
      (CTX), mycophenolate mofetil (MMF), etc. These medications can significantly induce disease
      remission and improve the long-term survival. However, some patients do not adequately
      response to the treatment of the combination of steroids and immunosuppressants, and the
      disease activity cannot be well-controlled. The high prevalence of steroids and
      immunosuppressants related adverse effects, such as steroid-related diabetes, bone necrosis,
      hypertension, peptic ulcer, CTX-related bone marrow and gonadal suppression, MMF-related
      infection risk and so on, have been found in long-term follow-up study. In addition, to date,
      there is insufficient data to support the use of new biologics, such as rituximab and
      abatacept in the induction therapy in patients with LN.

      Mesenchymal stem cells (MSCs) can be obtained from several tissues and possess multiple
      differentiation potencies and immunomodulatory effects. The investigators have investigated
      the usefulness, and confirmed the efficacy and safety of MSC treatment of LN in animal
      models, in vitro experiments and phase I clinical trial. The studies also for the first time
      found that the MSC abnormalities are involved in the onset and development of lupus both in
      the lupus mice model and in SLE patients. The investigators found that the efficacy of
      allogeneic (xenogeneic) MSC transplantation is superior to autologous MSC transplantation in
      LN mice model. Thus, in current opinion, SLE is not only a hematopoietic stem cell disease,
      but also a mesenchymal stem cell disease. The investigators treated the refractory LN
      patients with allogenic MSC treatment, the outcomes revealed that the total response rate was
      60%, the mortality rate of 2 to 5 years decreased from 35% - 45% to 6%. These results
      strongly support the use of allogenic MSC transplantation in the refractory LN patients. The
      mechanisms of MSC treatment include correcting the immune unbalance, inducing immune
      tolerance, tissue repair and the improvement of organ function. Allogeneic MSC
      transplantation for the treatment of SLE and other refractory autoimmune diseases have shown
      significant efficacy and excellent safety. However, these studies have limitations due to the
      lack of large-scale, multi-center, randomized, controlled, prospective study to further
      confirm the efficacy of allogeneic MSC transplantation, as well as the guideline for MSC
      treatment in SLE needs to be developed. Therefore, a randomized, placebo-controlled, parallel
      group, non-inferiority, prospective, multicenter clinical trial is urgent needed to promote
      the application of MSC transplantation in SLE treatment, to bring the benefit of the patients
      with SLE.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">August 1, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 1, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 1, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Total remission rate</measure>
    <time_frame>weeks 24</time_frame>
    <description>Complete remission rate (CR) and partial remission rate (PR)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The time for subjects of the two groups to achieve PR and CR</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to weeks 24</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Levels of 24-hour urinary protein</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, weeks 4, 8, 12, 16, 20, 24</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Ratio of Urinary Protein / Creatinine</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, weeks 4, 8, 12, 16, 20, 24</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Levels of serum albumin</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, weeks 4, 8, 12, 16, 20, 24</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Levels of serum creatinine</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, weeks 4, 8, 12, 16, 20, 24</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The estimated glomerular filtration rate ( eGFR )</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, weeks 4, 8, 12, 16, 20, 24</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Levels of Complement component 3 (C3)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, weeks 4, 8, 12, 16, 20, 24</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Levels of Complement component 4 (C4)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, weeks 4, 8, 12, 16, 20, 24</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The antinuclear antibody (ANA) levels</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, weeks 4, 8, 12, 16, 20, 24</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The anti-double stranded DNA antibody (dsDNA) levels</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, weeks 4, 8, 12, 16, 20, 24</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient Health Assessment Questionnaire (HAQ) score</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, weeks 4, 8, 12, 16, 20, 24</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Physician Global Assessment (PhGA) score</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, weeks 4, 8, 12, 16, 20, 24</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The (Systemic lupus Erythematosis Disease Activity index) SLEDAI score</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, weeks 4, 8, 12, 16, 20, 24</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The (British Isles lupus assessment group ) BILAG score</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, weeks 4, 8, 12, 16, 20, 24</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The SLE reaction index</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, weeks 4, 8, 12, 16, 20, 24</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Total remission rate</measure>
    <time_frame>weeks 12</time_frame>
    <description>Complete remission rate (CR) and partial remission rate (PR)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with treatment-related adverse events as assessed by CTCAE v4.0</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to weeks 24</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">230</enrollment>
  <condition>Lupus Nephritis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Mesenchymal stem cells</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The group receive pulse infusion of MSCs and placebo of oral Mycophenolate Mofetil (MMF). The cells of 2 x 10^6/kg body weight are suspended in 100ml saline and infused intravenously.
Dexamethasone of 10mg is intravenously injected before 30 minutes of cells infusion.
A sterile blood transfusion device is used during the venous transfusion, and it is washed with saline before infusion. Take a slow infusion of about 20 drops per minute in the first 15 minutes. Increase to about 60 drops per minute if the patient had no complaints of discomfort.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Mycophenolate Mofetil</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The group receive placebo of MSCs and oral Mycophenolate Mofetil of 2.0g/d. .</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Mesenchymal stem cells</intervention_name>
    <description>The group receive pulse infusion of MSCs once of 2 x 10^6/kg body weight</description>
    <arm_group_label>Mesenchymal stem cells</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Mycophenolate Mofetil</intervention_name>
    <description>This group receive oral MMF of 2.0 g / d.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Mycophenolate Mofetil</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo of Mesenchymal stem cells</intervention_name>
    <description>The group receive placebo of Mesenchymal stem cells.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Mycophenolate Mofetil</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo of Mycophenolate Mofetil</intervention_name>
    <description>The group receive placebo of oral mycophenolate mofetil.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Mesenchymal stem cells</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Subjects who met the American college of Rheumatology (ACR, 1997) classification
             criteria for SLE;

          2. Ages: 18-60 years old (including);

          3. Presence of class III, IV, V, III+V or IV+V LN as determined by renal biopsy within 12
             weeks of randomization(2003 ISN/RPS LN classification criteria);

          4. Morning proteinuria /creatinine ratio &gt;1.0 or 24 hours Proteinuria &gt;1.0g, with or
             without microscopic hematuria(&gt;5 red blood cells/high-power field);

          5. Women of childbearing age agreed to adopt effective contraception measures during the
             trial period;

          6. Urine pregnancy tests were negative in women of childbearing age;

          7. Subject signed the informed consent form voluntarily and complied with the
             requirements of the research program.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Received MMF, CTX, other potent immunosuppressive agents (including cyclosporine,
             tacrolimus, Tripterygium wilfordii and leflunomide) or biologics (Rituximab or others)
             within the past 12 weeks.

          2. Previous failure to respond to MMF.

          3. Known intolerance to MMF.

          4. Renal biopsy showing ≥50% glomerulus sclerosis.

          5. Renal biopsy showing capillary loops necrosis, microthrombus formation in capillary
             loops, or cellular crescent in ≥50% of glomeruli.

          6. Patients diagnosed with other autoimmune diseases apart from SLE:
             dermatomyositis/polymyositis, mixed connective tissue disease, scleroderma, rheumatoid
             arthritis, etc. However, participants with secondary Sjogren's syndrome are allowed to
             take part in the study.

          7. Patients suffering from severe liver or kidney dysfunction (total bilirubin more than
             14mg/L, aspartate aminotransferase (AST) or alanine aminotransferase (ALT) more than
             1.5 times the upper limit of normal lab value; creatinine clearance rate (Ccr) &lt;
             30ml/min or serum creatinine (Scr) ≥265.2umol/L).

          8. Patients with hematological abnormalities (white blood cell &lt;3000/uL, hemoglobin
             &lt;8g/dL, and/or platelets &lt;50000/uL).

          9. Patients diagnosed with severe or uncontrolled cardiovascular, neurological, pulmonary
             (including obstructive pulmonary disease and interstitial lung disease), hepatic,
             endocrine (including uncontrolled diabetes mellitus), and gastrointestinal disorders.

         10. Known active or history of recurrent bacterial, viral, fungal, mycobacterial or other
             infections (including but not limited to tuberculosis, atypical mycobacterial
             infection, granulomatous disease showed by chest X-ray, hepatitis B, hepatitis C, HIV
             infection and herpes zoster, whereas not including onychomycosis). Any infection
             requiring hospitalization within 4 weeks prior to enrollment or intravenous
             antimicrobial treatment within 2 weeks prior to randomization.

         11. History of malignancy, including solid tumor and hematologic malignancies (except
             basal cell carcinoma which has been excised or successfully treated).

         12. Women who are pregnant or breastfeeding.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>60 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Lingyun Sun, Ph.D M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>+86(025)83106666</phone>
    <phone_ext>61421</phone_ext>
    <email>lingyunsun@nju.edu.cn</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The Affiliated Drum Tower Hospital of Nanjing University Medical School</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nanjing</city>
        <state>Jiangsu</state>
        <zip>210008</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Lingyun Sun, M.D.</last_name>
      <phone>+86(25)83106666</phone>
      <phone_ext>61421</phone_ext>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 12, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 25, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 9, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 9, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 9, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 10, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>The Affiliated Nanjing Drum Tower Hospital of Nanjing University Medical School</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Lingyun Sun</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Director of Department of Rheumatology and Immunology</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Lupus Nephritis</keyword>
  <keyword>Mesenchymal stem cell</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Nephritis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lupus Nephritis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Mycophenolic Acid</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

