<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03587077</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Pain during IUD insertion</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03587077</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Pain Relief During IUD Insertion in Women Delivered Only by Elective Cesarean Section</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effect of Adding Vaginal Isosorbide Mononitrate to Misoprostol Prior to Intrauterine Device Insertion in Women Delivered Only by Elective Cesarean Section: a Randomized Double-blind Controlled Clinical Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Assiut University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Assiut University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The aim of the work is to assess the effect of combined misoprostol 200 mcg and isosorbide
      mononitrate 40 mg versus misoprostol 200 mcg and placebo as local vaginal tablet on the
      successful IUD insertion.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Fear of pain during insertion of an IUD may deter women from choosing the IUD as a method of
      contraception. According to Hubacher et al. predictors of increased pain during IUD insertion
      include nulliparity, age greater than 30 years, lengthier time since last pregnancy or last
      menses, and not currently breastfeeding. Allen et al. predicted pain to be greater based on
      history of no previous vaginal delivery, and difficulty of the procedure. Pharmacological
      interventions for pain control during IUD insertion include analgesics, local anesthetics,
      and the use of prostaglandins to soften the cervix; however, there is wide variation in the
      use of these methods . Misoprostol has also been proposed as an agent to ease IUD insertion
      and decrease procedure-associated pain .

      Nitrous oxide has been used for years for procedural analgesia in outpatient settings and has
      recently been investigated as an approach to pain management in the context of IUD insertion
      .

      Sewell and Vincent have been offering nitrous oxide for reducing the pain of IUD insertion
      and have had a positive response.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Not yet recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">September 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>rate of successful IUD insertion</measure>
    <time_frame>10 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>Defined by a distance from the IUD to the endometrial end of less than 25 mm</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">113</enrollment>
  <condition>IUD Insertion Complication</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>study group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Women will receive vaginally one tablet misoprostol 200 mcg(Misotac; Sigma Pharma, SAE, EGYPT) plus one tablet isosorbide mononitrate 40 mg(Effox 40 mg; Minapharm). A trained clinical nurse will introduce the tablets, digitally without using speculum, 3 hours before IUD insertion into the posterior vaginal fornix of the woman while lying in the lithotomy position.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>control group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Women will receive vaginally one tablet misoprostol 200 mcg Plus one tablet placebo.A trained clinical nurse will introduce the tablets, digitally without using speculum, 3 hours before IUD insertion into the posterior vaginal fornix of the woman while lying in the lithotomy position.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Misoprostol</intervention_name>
    <description>vaginal application</description>
    <arm_group_label>control group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>study group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebos</intervention_name>
    <description>vaginal application</description>
    <arm_group_label>control group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>isosorbide mononitrate</intervention_name>
    <description>vaginal application</description>
    <arm_group_label>study group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:We will include

          -  Nonpregnant women,

          -  aged 18-45 years, .delivered before only by elective CS and did not receive any
             analgesics in the 24 h prior to IUD insertion.

        Exclusion Criteria:We will exclude

          -  Women with any uterine abnormalities as congenital anomalies,

          -  Women with endometrial lesions,

          -  Women with adenomyosis,

          -  Women with fibroids,

          -  Women with intrauterine adhesions,

          -  Women with chronic pelvic pain,

          -  Women with spasmodic dysmenorrhea,

          -  Women with abnormal uterine bleeding,

          -  Women with history of cervical surgery, .Women with allergy to misoprostol or
             isosorbide mononitrate or any medical disease that contraindicates its use and those
             who refused to participate in the study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <gender_based>Yes</gender_based>
    <gender_description>All eligible participants included in the study signed a written informed consent before participation after explaining the nature of the study.</gender_description>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>45 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mohamad S. Abdellah, Prof.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Supervisor</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ihab M. El-Nashar, Prof.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Supervisor</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Eman I. Ramadan, BSc</last_name>
    <phone>00201063959596</phone>
    <email>emanelmelwany@yahoo.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <link>
    <url>http://goo.gl/R5m3to</url>
    <description>SFP guideline 89: 75-84</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Akintomide H, Sewell RD, Stephenson JM. The use of local anaesthesia for intrauterine device insertion by health professionals in the UK. J Fam Plann Reprod Health Care. 2013 Oct;39(4):276-80. doi: 10.1136/jfprhc-2012-100486. Epub 2013 Feb 5.</citation>
    <PMID>23385310</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Allen RH, Bartz D, Grimes DA, Hubacher D, O'Brien P. Interventions for pain with intrauterine device insertion. Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2009 Jul 8;(3):CD007373. doi: 10.1002/14651858.CD007373.pub2. Review. Update in: Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2015;7:CD007373.</citation>
    <PMID>19588429</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Allen RH, Carey MS, Raker C, Goyal V, Matteson K. A prospective cohort study of pain with intrauterine device insertion among women with and without vaginal deliveries. J Obstet Gynaecol. 2014 Apr;34(3):263-7. doi: 10.3109/01443615.2013.868424. Epub 2014 Jan 31.</citation>
    <PMID>24483244</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Allen RH, Raker C, Goyal V. Higher dose cervical 2% lidocaine gel for IUD insertion: a randomized controlled trial. Contraception. 2013 Dec;88(6):730-6. doi: 10.1016/j.contraception.2013.07.009. Epub 2013 Aug 1.</citation>
    <PMID>24012096</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Asker C, Stokes-Lampard H, Beavan J, Wilson S. What is it about intrauterine devices that women find unacceptable? Factors that make women non-users: a qualitative study. J Fam Plann Reprod Health Care. 2006 Apr;32(2):89-94.</citation>
    <PMID>16824298</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bahamondes L, Mansour D, Fiala C, Kaunitz AM, Gemzell-Danielsson K. Practical advice for avoidance of pain associated with insertion of intrauterine contraceptives. J Fam Plann Reprod Health Care. 2014 Jan;40(1):54-60. doi: 10.1136/jfprhc-2013-100636. Epub 2013 Sep 27. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24076534</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Barber EL, Lundsberg LS, Belanger K, Pettker CM, Funai EF, Illuzzi JL. Indications contributing to the increasing cesarean delivery rate. Obstet Gynecol. 2011 Jul;118(1):29-38. doi: 10.1097/AOG.0b013e31821e5f65.</citation>
    <PMID>21646928</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Carusi, D. A., &amp; Goldberg, A. B. (2015). Intrauterine contraceptive device: insertion and removal. In: M. Zieman (Ed), UpToDate. Retrieved from http://www.uptodate.com/home .</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Division of Reproductive Health, National Center for Chronic Disease Prevention and Health Promotion, Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC). U.S. Selected Practice Recommendations for Contraceptive Use, 2013: adapted from the World Health Organization selected practice recommendations for contraceptive use, 2nd edition. MMWR Recomm Rep. 2013 Jun 21;62(RR-05):1-60.</citation>
    <PMID>23784109</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>d'Arcangues C. Worldwide use of intrauterine devices for contraception. Contraception. 2007 Jun;75(6 Suppl):S2-7. Epub 2007 Apr 19. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>17531612</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Edmunds, M. W., &amp; Mayhew, M. S. (2014). Pharmacology for the primary care provider (4th ed.). St. Louis, MI: Elsevier Mosby.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Finer LB, Jerman J, Kavanaugh ML. Changes in use of long-acting contraceptive methods in the United States, 2007-2009. Fertil Steril. 2012 Oct;98(4):893-7. doi: 10.1016/j.fertnstert.2012.06.027. Epub 2012 Jul 13.</citation>
    <PMID>22795639</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fox MC, Krajewski CM. Cervical preparation for second-trimester surgical abortion prior to 20 weeks' gestation: SFP Guideline #2013-4. Contraception. 2014 Feb;89(2):75-84. doi: 10.1016/j.contraception.2013.11.001. Epub 2013 Nov 11.</citation>
    <PMID>24331860</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Heikinheimo O, Inki P, Kunz M, Parmhed S, Anttila AM, Olsson SE, Hurskainen R, Gemzell-Danielsson K. Double-blind, randomized, placebo-controlled study on the effect of misoprostol on ease of consecutive insertion of the levonorgestrel-releasing intrauterine system. Contraception. 2010 Jun;81(6):481-6. doi: 10.1016/j.contraception.2010.01.020. Epub 2010 Mar 1.</citation>
    <PMID>20472114</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hubacher D, Reyes V, Lillo S, Zepeda A, Chen PL, Croxatto H. Pain from copper intrauterine device insertion: randomized trial of prophylactic ibuprofen. Am J Obstet Gynecol. 2006 Nov;195(5):1272-7.</citation>
    <PMID>17074548</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kass-Wolff JH, Fisher JE. Evidence-based pain management for endometrial biopsies and IUD insertions. Nurse Pract. 2014 Mar 13;39(3):43-50. doi: 10.1097/01.NPR.0000434094.19101.d1. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24535311</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lopez LM, Bernholc A, Zeng Y, Allen RH, Bartz D, O'Brien PA, Hubacher D. Interventions for pain with intrauterine device insertion. Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2015 Jul 29;(7):CD007373. doi: 10.1002/14651858.CD007373.pub3. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26222246</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Maguire K, Morrell K, Westhoff C, Davis A. Accuracy of providers' assessment of pain during intrauterine device insertion. Contraception. 2014 Jan;89(1):22-4. doi: 10.1016/j.contraception.2013.09.008. Epub 2013 Sep 21.</citation>
    <PMID>24134898</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Singh RH, Thaxton L, Carr S, Leeman L, Schneider E, Espey E. A randomized controlled trial of nitrous oxide for intrauterine device insertion in nulliparous women. Int J Gynaecol Obstet. 2016 Nov;135(2):145-148. doi: 10.1016/j.ijgo.2016.04.014. Epub 2016 Jul 16.</citation>
    <PMID>27481016</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Winner B, Peipert JF, Zhao Q, Buckel C, Madden T, Allsworth JE, Secura GM. Effectiveness of long-acting reversible contraception. N Engl J Med. 2012 May 24;366(21):1998-2007. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa1110855.</citation>
    <PMID>22621627</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>World Health Organization. Medical eligibility criteria for contraceptive use. Geneva (Switzerland): WHO; 2010.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zhuo Z, Yu H, Jiang X. A systematic review and meta-analysis of randomized controlled trials on the effectiveness of cervical ripening with misoprostol administration before hysteroscopy. Int J Gynaecol Obstet. 2016 Mar;132(3):272-7. doi: 10.1016/j.ijgo.2015.07.039. Epub 2015 Dec 11. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26797202</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>April 9, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 13, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 16, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 13, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 13, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 16, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Assiut University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Eman Ibrahim Ramadan Abdelrahman</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Isosorbide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Isosorbide Dinitrate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Isosorbide-5-mononitrate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Misoprostol</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

