<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03582384</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IRB-P00026926</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03582384</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Use of Tocofersolan (Vedrop®) to Prevent or Treat Refractive Vitamin E Deficiency in Infants and Children</brief_title>
  <official_title>Use of Tocofersolan (Vedrop®) to Prevent or Treat Refractive Vitamin E Deficiency in Infants and Children</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Boston Children’s Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Boston Children’s Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Patients with short bowel syndrome or other forms of intestinal failure/fat malabsorption are
      unable to tolerate adequate oral or enteral feedings. They require that nutrition be given as
      enteral nutrition that is delivered by feeding tube. Often these children take supplements
      such as vitamins to help improve their nutritional status but, due to their condition, they
      have difficulty absorbing the supplement sufficiently and most of it is lost in the stool.
      The drug that will be studied, Tocofersolan (Vedrop®) is a form of vitamin E, a type of the
      fat soluble vitamin needed in the human diet. It has been formulated in such a way that it
      may be more easily absorbed by patients with this condition. The main purpose of the study is
      to learn about the safety and tolerability of this form of vitamin E. Before receiving the
      study drug, the severity of the child's vitamin E deficiency will be determined by a blood
      sample, followed by giving them a daily dose of tocofersolan (Vedrop®) either orally or
      through their feeding tube. After a 4 weeks of therapy, a second blood sample will be checked
      and the child will continue either same dose of tocoferssolan or it will be adjusted in
      response to the blood levels. If the study drug works as it is designed to do, there should
      be an increase in the concentration of the vitamin E in the child's blood, suggesting that
      the drug was absorbed. At each visit, a sample of blood will be obtained to assess the
      child's vitamin E status and general health.

      Patients will remain on tocofersolan for approximately one year or as long as the study
      remains open. Based on the European pediatric experience, patients should be expected be on
      tocofersolan a minimum of 3 months, ideally 6 months to see optimal clinical response.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Withdrawn</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Study never started
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">December 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Vitamin E Level</measure>
    <time_frame>1 Year</time_frame>
    <description>Primary outcomes measured will include whether the vitamin E level increased to &gt; 5 mg/L</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">0</enrollment>
  <condition>Short Bowel Syndrome</condition>
  <condition>Vitamin E Deficiency</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Tocofersolan</intervention_name>
    <description>After baseline labs are obtained, therapy with tocofersolan will be initiated at an initial dose of 17 mg/kg of d-alpha-tocopherol in the form of tocofersolan (0.34 ml/kg/day) and titrated based on blood levels.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        1. Patients with intestinal failure or fat malabsorption who have refractory vitamin E
        deficiency (defined as vitamin E level &lt; 5 mg/L) despite receiving vitamin E
        supplementation with currently available enteral vitamin E products for at least 6 months
        or requiring the provision of vitamin parenterally as part of a multivitamin infusion.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Pregnancy

          2. Use of warfarin or any related vitamin K antagonist.

          3. Enrollment in any other clinical trial involving an investigational agent (unless
             approved by the principal investigators of the other trial)

          4. The parent or guardian or child unwilling to provide consent or assent
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>17 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <reference>
    <citation>Westergren T, Kalikstad B. Dosage and formulation issues: oral vitamin E therapy in children. Eur J Clin Pharmacol. 2010 Feb;66(2):109-18. doi: 10.1007/s00228-009-0729-1. Epub 2009 Oct 13. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19823814</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>European Medicines Agency Evaluation of Medicines for Human Use, CHMP Assessment Report for Vedrop, London, 29 May 2009 Doc.Ref.: EMEA/485798/2009.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sokol RJ. A New Old Treatment for Vitamin E Deficiency in Cholestasis. J Pediatr Gastroenterol Nutr. 2016 Dec;63(6):577-578.</citation>
    <PMID>27429361</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Thébaut A, Nemeth A, Le Mouhaër J, Scheenstra R, Baumann U, Koot B, Gottrand F, Houwen R, Monard L, de Micheaux SL, Habes D, Jacquemin E. Oral Tocofersolan Corrects or Prevents Vitamin E Deficiency in Children With Chronic Cholestasis. J Pediatr Gastroenterol Nutr. 2016 Dec;63(6):610-615.</citation>
    <PMID>27429423</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ubesie AC, Kocoshis SA, Mezoff AG, Henderson CJ, Helmrath MA, Cole CR. Multiple micronutrient deficiencies among patients with intestinal failure during and after transition to enteral nutrition. J Pediatr. 2013 Dec;163(6):1692-6. doi: 10.1016/j.jpeds.2013.07.015. Epub 2013 Aug 24.</citation>
    <PMID>23978355</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zondlo Fiume M. Final report on the safety assessment of Tocopherol, Tocopheryl Acetate, Tocopheryl Linoleate, Tocopheryl Linoleate/Oleate, Tocopheryl Nicotinate, Tocopheryl Succinate, Dioleyl Tocopheryl Methylsilanol, Potassium Ascorbyl Tocopheryl Phosphate, and Tocophersolan. Int J Toxicol. 2002;21 Suppl 3:51-116. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>12537931</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ash, M. (2004). Handbook of green chemicals (2nd ed.). Endicott, N.Y.: Synapse Information Resources.</citation>
  </reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Yang CF, Duro D, Zurakowski D, Lee M, Jaksic T, Duggan C. High prevalence of multiple micronutrient deficiencies in children with intestinal failure: a longitudinal study. J Pediatr. 2011 Jul;159(1):39-44.e1. doi: 10.1016/j.jpeds.2010.12.049. Epub 2011 Feb 16.</citation>
    <PMID>21324480</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>May 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 26, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 9, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 11, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 11, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 11, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 13, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Boston Children’s Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Daniel Elman</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Clinical Research Specialist</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Short Bowel Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vitamin E Deficiency</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

