<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03585062</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2017KY007</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03585062</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Trial of Neoadjuvant Chemotherapy With S1 Plus Paclitaxel-albumin on Pancreatic Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>Clinical Trial of Neoadjuvant Chemotherapy With S1 Plus Paclitaxel-albumin in Patients With Unresectable Locally Advanced Pancreatic Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Zhejiang Provincial People’s Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Zhejiang Provincial People’s Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The study is to evaluate the R0 resection rate of patients with unresectable locally advanced
      pancreatic cancer ,after treated with S-1 plus Paclitaxel-albumin as neoadjuvant chemotherapy
      protocols
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      BACKGROUND:

        1. The incidence of pancreatic cancer in China has been increasing rapidly in recent
           years，but most of the pancreatic cancer patients are unresectable, whose median survival
           time were only 6~9 months.

        2. Studies have shown that neoadjuvant therapy improves the quality of surgery in patients
           with pancreatic cancer，and prolong their life.

        3. S-1 is a new generation of oral fluorouracil derivatives ,S-1 single drug as an adjuvant
           therapy for resectable pancreatic cancer is better than gemcitabine, and has less side
           effects than gemcitabine. Protein bound paclitaxel is a novel paclitaxel combined of
           paclitaxel and albumin by nanotechnology , which can extend free survival in patients
           with advanced pancreatic cancer with less side effects than gemcitabine. So S-1 combined
           with Paclitaxel-albumin is expected to play an important role in neoadjuvant
           chemotherapy in Pancreatic cancer, and may improve the rate of R0 resection in patients
           with unresectable locally advanced pancreatic.

      STUDY DESIGN:

      S-1 combined with Paclitaxel-albumin

        1. S-1:40~60mg bid, day 1~14 (S-1: BSA (Body surface area)&lt;1.25m2, 40mg bid , 1.25m2 ≤ BSA
           ≤1.5m2, 50mg bid, BSA&gt;1.5m2, 60mg bid),2 weeks and rest for 1 weeks.

        2. Paclitaxel-albumin: 125 mg/m2, intravenous infusion for 30 minutes, Day1 and Day 8.

      Repeat every three weeks. for 6 cycles.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 20, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>R0 resection rate</measure>
    <time_frame>one week After the operation</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluate the R0 resection rate of S-1 combined with Paclitaxel-albumin as neoadjuvant chemotherapy in patients with unresectable locally advanced pancreatic cancer</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The objective remission rate (ORR)</measure>
    <time_frame>at the end of cycle 6 of the neoadjuvant chemotherapy((each cycle is 21 days)</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluate the objective remission rate (ORR) of S-1 combined with Paclitaxel-albumin as neoadjuvant chemotherapy in patients with unresectable locally advanced pancreatic cancer</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The disease free survival (DFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of randomization until the date of first documented progression or date of death from any cause, whichever came first,assessed up to 60 months. Progressing should be confirmed by imaging examination or histology / cytology examination.</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluate the disease free survival (DFS) of S-1 combined with Paclitaxel-albumin as neoadjuvant chemotherapy in patients with unresectable locally advanced pancreatic cancer</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The 2 year and 5 year survival rate</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years and 5 years after treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluate the 2 year and 5 year survival rate of S-1 combined with Paclitaxel-albumin as neoadjuvant chemotherapy in patients with unresectable locally advanced pancreatic cancer</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The quality of life</measure>
    <time_frame>Questionnaire at baseline, and then 1-2 days before each cycle of treatment(each cycle is 21 days, for a total of 6 cycles.). During follow-up period after treatment, questionnaire every 6 months, up to 2 years.</time_frame>
    <description>Assess the quality of life in pancreatic cancer according to EORTC QLQ-PAN26(European Organization for Research and Treatment of Cancer Quality of Life Questionnaire - Pancreas 26).For each assessment item, there are four options, scores are as 1,2,3,4. Each score corresponds to a physical condition. Then have the total score for each patient. The total score range from 26-104, the higher the score, the poorer the quality of life is.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Pancreatic Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Neoadjuvant Chemotherapy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>S-1 combined with Paclitaxel-albumin</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>S-1 combined with Paclitaxel-albumin S-1:40~60mg bid, day 1~14 (S-1: BSA &lt;1.25m2, 40mg bid , 1.25m2 ≤ BSA ≤1.5m2, 50mg bid, BSA&gt;1.5m2, 60mg bid， for 2 weeks, rest a week) Paclitaxel-albumin: 125 mg/m2, intravenous infusion for 30 minutes, Day1 and Day 8.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>S1,</intervention_name>
    <description>S-1 is a combination of tegafur, gimeracil and oteracil at a molar ratio of 1:0.4:1, and is a new oral fluoropyrimidine anticancer agent shown to be effective for pancreatic cancer. cancer</description>
    <arm_group_label>S-1 combined with Paclitaxel-albumin</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Gimeracil and Oteracil Porassium Capsules</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Paclitaxel-albumin</intervention_name>
    <description>Paclitaxel-albumin is a drug which showed a survival benefit in Pancreatic Cancer when combined with S1</description>
    <arm_group_label>S-1 combined with Paclitaxel-albumin</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Confirmed invasive ductal adenocarcinoma of pancreas by histology

          2. Evaluated as CT4N0M0 pancreatic cancer patients by Image testing

          3. Adults age from 18-80 years old

          4. No history of pancreatic resection or pancreatic cancer

          5. ECOG score 0-1; can be orally administered

          6. No distant metastasis or malignant ascites

          7. Relatively good liver、 kidney、heart、hematology function. Baseline blood routine and
             biochemical indexes of the subjects meet the following criteria: hemoglobin
             ≥90g/L;absolute neutrophil count(ANC)≥3.5×109/L；Platelet≥100×109/L;prothrombin time
             ≤1.8;partial thromboplastin time ≤1.8; ALT≤102U/L、AST≤95U/L; ALP≤2.5 times the upper
             limits of normal; Serum total bilirubin≤2.5 g/dL(total bilirubin ≤1.5 times the upper
             limit of normal (ULN)；Serum creatinine≤2.0 mg/dL； creatinine clearance rate &gt;50 ml/min

          8. Sign the Informed consent -

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Woman in pregnant or lactation period

          2. Woman of childbearing age who was positive at baseline pregnancy test or did not have
             pregnancy tests.Menopausal women must have menopause for at least 12 months before
             they think they are free of pregnancy.

          3. Men and women who had sexual life (Fertility possibility) were reluctant to have
             contraception during the study period.

          4. Patients with the history of other malignant diseases in the past 5 years, except for
             cured skin cancer and cervical carcinoma in situ.

          5. Patients of uncontrolled epilepsy, central nervous system diseases or history of
             mental disorders, should be judged by the researchers whether their clinical severity
             hinder the signature of the informed consent or influenced patients'compliance with
             oral medications

          6. Clinically serious (i.e. activity) heart disease, such as symptomatic coronary heart
             disease , New York Heart Association (NYHA) class II or more serious congestive heart
             failure or serious arrhythmia which need drug intervention, or have a history of MI
             within the last 12 months.

          7. Patients with upper gastrointestinal obstruction or Abnormal physiological function or
             Malabsorption syndrome, which may affect the absorption of S-1.

          8. Organ transplant patients who need immunosuppressive therapy

          9. Patients with Serious uncontrolled repeated infection or other serious uncontrolled
             Concomitant disease.

         10. Patient that is lack of dihydropyrimidine dehydrogenase (DPD)

         11. Allergic to any of the drug ingredients in this study

         12. participate in other clinical trials within 4 weeks before randomization -
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Liu Yang, Doctor</last_name>
    <phone>13666601475</phone>
    <email>yangliuqq2003@163.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Zhejiang procincial people's hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hanzhou</city>
        <state>Zhejiang</state>
        <zip>310014</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Liu Yang</last_name>
      <phone>13666601475</phone>
      <email>yangliuqq2003@163.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Siegel R, Naishadham D, Jemal A. Cancer statistics, 2013. CA Cancer J Clin. 2013 Jan;63(1):11-30. doi: 10.3322/caac.21166. Epub 2013 Jan 17.</citation>
    <PMID>23335087</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jemal A, Bray F, Center MM, Ferlay J, Ward E, Forman D. Global cancer statistics. CA Cancer J Clin. 2011 Mar-Apr;61(2):69-90. doi: 10.3322/caac.20107. Epub 2011 Feb 4. Erratum in: CA Cancer J Clin. 2011 Mar-Apr;61(2):134.</citation>
    <PMID>21296855</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Witkowski ER, Smith JK, Tseng JF. Outcomes following resection of pancreatic cancer. J Surg Oncol. 2013 Jan;107(1):97-103. doi: 10.1002/jso.23267. Epub 2012 Sep 18. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22991309</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Neoptolemos JP, Stocken DD, Friess H, Bassi C, Dunn JA, Hickey H, Beger H, Fernandez-Cruz L, Dervenis C, Lacaine F, Falconi M, Pederzoli P, Pap A, Spooner D, Kerr DJ, Büchler MW; European Study Group for Pancreatic Cancer. A randomized trial of chemoradiotherapy and chemotherapy after resection of pancreatic cancer. N Engl J Med. 2004 Mar 18;350(12):1200-10. Erratum in: N Engl J Med. 2004 Aug 12;351(7):726.</citation>
    <PMID>15028824</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>July 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 8, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 1, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 12, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 1, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 1, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">August 3, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Zhejiang Provincial People’s Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Yi-Ping Mou</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Vice Present of Zhejiang Provincial People's Hospital</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>S-1</keyword>
  <keyword>Paclitaxel-albumin</keyword>
  <keyword>Unresectable Pancreatic Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Neoadjuvant chemotherapy</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pancreatic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Paclitaxel</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

