<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03581253</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2017-44</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03581253</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Validation of a French-language Version of Quality of Life Questionnaires in Patients With Peripheral Facial Palsy</brief_title>
  <acronym>PFQDV</acronym>
  <official_title>Validation of a French-language Version of Specific Quality of Life Questionnaires in Patients With Peripheral Facial Palsy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Assistance Publique Hopitaux De Marseille</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Assistance Publique Hopitaux De Marseille</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Facial palsy is a serious and disabling disease whose drudgery and sensation are probably
      underestimated. Psychological, social and economic issues have major impacts although vital
      prognosis is not engaged in this pathology. Facial palsy remains a personal drama for
      patient. Consequences may take the form of: aesthetic deformation, modification of body
      image, with socio-professional consequences. Beside unsightly facial aspects, weakness of
      facial muscles can cause troubles in eating, drinking, talking, communicating personal
      emotions and communication. Facial palsy impacts patients' quality of life (QOL) and affects
      mental health. This wide multidimensional concept usually includes self-measures of physical
      and mental health. QOL is evaluated with general and specific scales. General scales allow to
      compare QOL of different diseases, when specific scales focus on one disease and consider all
      aspects related to this disease and therefore are more appropriate and sensitive in
      dimensions related to patient disease and health.

      &quot;Facial disability Index&quot; (FDi) and &quot;Facial Clinimetric Evaluation&quot; (FaCE) are the most used
      validated questionnaires to assess QOL of patients suffering from peripheral facial palsy
      (PFP). There is no existing validated questionnaire or scale in French version despite many
      French studies on PFP available. Using these questionnaires in French language requires
      translation and strict approval of the new language version. The aim of the study is to
      translate and validate French versions of specific scales of QOL in peripheral facial palsy
      patients: FDI and FaCE. Secondary objective is to evaluate QOL of patients depending on PFP
      etiology. Translation process will be done respecting internationally recognized rules. A
      pilot study will be performed on 5 physicians and 5 patients in order to validate the
      questionnaires translations. French versions obtained will be used for their validation on 80
      patients suffering from PFP.

      Cronbach's alpha will be estimated to check internal consistency of FDI and FaCE scales. Test
      re-test reliability will be calculated with inter-class correlation, reiterating
      questionnaires one week later. Scores of FDI and FaCE scales will be compared to other
      clinical evaluation scales, estimating correlation coefficient. Social function of FDI and
      FaCE scales will be compared with general scale SF-36 scores, estimating a correlation
      coefficient.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Facial palsy is a serious and disabling disease whose drudgery and sensation are probably
      underestimated. Psychological, social and economic issues have major impacts although vital
      prognosis is not engaged in this pathology. Facial palsy remains a personal drama for
      patient. Consequences may take the form of: aesthetic deformation, modification of body
      image, with socio-professional consequences. Beside unsightly facial aspects, weakness of
      facial muscles can cause troubles in eating, drinking, talking, and communicating personal
      emotions. Physical as well as psychological repercussions limit daily verbal and non-verbal
      communication.

      Facial palsy impacts patients' quality of life (QOL) and affects mental health. Consequently,
      QOL impacts and directs the patient's care and the healthcare professionals widely take
      account of QOL.

      This wide multidimensional concept usually includes self-measures of physical and mental
      health. QOL is evaluated with general and specific scales. General scales allow to compare
      QOL of different diseases, when specific scales focus on one disease and consider all aspects
      related to this disease and therefore are more appropriate and sensitive in dimensions
      related to patient disease and health.

      &quot;Facial disability Index&quot; (FDi) and &quot;Facial Clinimetric Evaluation&quot; (FaCE) are the two most
      used validated questionnaires to assess QOL of patients suffering from peripheral facial
      palsy (PFP).

      There is no existing validated questionnaire or scale in French version evaluating QOL of
      patients with PFP despite many French studies on PFP available. Using these questionnaires in
      French language requires translation and strict approval of the new language version.

      The aim of the study is to translate and validate French versions of specific scales of QOL
      in peripheral facial palsy patients: FDI and FaCE. Secondary objective is to evaluate QOL of
      patients depending on PFP etiology.

      Translation process will be done respecting internationally recognized rules. A pilot study
      will be performed on 5 physicians and 5 patients in order to validate the questionnaires
      translations. French versions obtained for these 2 questionnaires will be used for their
      validation on 80 patients suffering from PFP in our hospital.

      Cronbach's alpha will be estimated to check internal consistency of FDI and FaCE scales. Test
      re-test reliability will be calculated with inter-class correlation, reiterating
      questionnaires one week later. Scores of FDI and FaCE scales will be compared to
      House-Brackmann and Sunnybrook clinical evaluation scales, estimating correlation
      coefficient. Social function of FDI and FaCE scales will also be compared with general scale
      SF-36 scores, estimating a correlation coefficient.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">December 15, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 15, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>&quot;Facial disability Index&quot; (FDi)</measure>
    <time_frame>one week</time_frame>
    <description>questionnaire to assess the oral, ocular and the influence of facial impairment on emotions and daily activity</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Facial Clinimetric Evaluation&quot; (FaCE)</measure>
    <time_frame>one week</time_frame>
    <description>questionnaire to asses facial deficit and disability relating to 6 areas: facial movement, facial comfort, oral function, ocular comfort, tear control and social function</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>House-Brackmann score</measure>
    <time_frame>one week</time_frame>
    <description>The House-Brackmann score is a score to grade the degree of nerve damage in a facial nerve palsy. The measurement is determined by measuring the upwards (superior) movement of the mid-portion of the top of the eyebrow, and the outwards (lateral) movement of the angle of the mouth. Each reference point scores 1 point for each 0.25 cm movement, up to a maximum of 1 cm. The scores are then added together, to give a number out of 8</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Sunnybrook index</measure>
    <time_frame>one week</time_frame>
    <description>clinical evaluation calculating a score depending of Resting Symmetry, Symmetry of Voluntary Movement and Synkinesis</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>SF-36 score</measure>
    <time_frame>one week</time_frame>
    <description>The Short Form (36) Health Survey is a 36-item.
It consists of eight scaled scores, which are the weighted sums of the questions in their section. Each scale is directly transformed into a 0-100 scale on the assumption that each question carries equal weight. The lower the score the more disability. The higher the score the less disability i.e., a score of zero is equivalent to maximum disability and a score of 100 is equivalent to no disability. To calculate the scores it is necessary to purchase special software. Pricing depends on the number of scores that the researcher needs to calculate.
The eight sections are: vitality, physical functioning, bodily pain, general health perceptions, physical role functioning, emotional role functioning, social role functioning and mental health</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">80</enrollment>
  <condition>Peripheral Facial Paralysis</condition>
  <condition>Quality of Life</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>peripheral facial palsy patients</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>peripheral facial palsy patients will performed questionnaires of quality of life (&quot;Facial disability Index&quot; (FDi) and &quot;Facial Clinimetric Evaluation&quot; (FaCE)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Facial disability Index&quot; (FDi)</intervention_name>
    <description>questionnaires regarding to quality of life</description>
    <arm_group_label>peripheral facial palsy patients</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>&quot;Facial Clinimetric Evaluation&quot; (FaCE)</intervention_name>
    <description>questionnaires regarding to quality of life</description>
    <arm_group_label>peripheral facial palsy patients</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patient with peripheral facial palsy

          -  Age over 18 years old.

          -  Subject wishing and able to give informed consent and to respect the requirements of
             the protocol

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patient not being French.

          -  Patient who can not read French.

          -  Facial graduation.

          -  Facial dysfunction other than PFP such as facial trauma.

          -  Major medical or psychiatric illness that, in the opinion of the investigator, would
             pose a risk to the subject or could compromise compliance with the study protocol.

          -  Participation in other studies in the 30 days prior to inclusion in this study.

          -  Legal incapacity or limited legal capacity.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>EMILIE GARRIDO PRADALIE</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>ASSISTANCE PUBLIQUE DES HOPITAUX DE MARSEILLE</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>MARION MONTAVA, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+33491435618</phone>
    <email>Marion.MONTAVA@ap-hm.fr</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>CECILE LAVOUTE, PHD</last_name>
    <phone>+33491381878</phone>
    <email>cecile.lavoute@ap-hm.fr</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Assistance Publique Des Hopitaux de Marseille</name>
      <address>
        <city>Marseille</city>
        <state>Paca</state>
        <zip>13005</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>CECILE LAVOUTE, PHD</last_name>
      <phone>+33491381878</phone>
      <email>cecile.lavoute@ap-hm.fr</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>MARION MONTAVA, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 26, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 26, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 10, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 11, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 11, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 12, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Bell Palsy</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Facial Paralysis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Paralysis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Facies</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

