<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03581955</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2016-A00153-48</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03581955</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Identification of New Biomarkers of Banana and Tomato Intake</brief_title>
  <acronym>BioBanaTom</acronym>
  <official_title>Identification of New Biomarkers of Banana and Tomato Intake</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Claudine MANACH</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Research Agency, France</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Institut National de la Recherche Agronomique</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The intake of fruits and vegetables has been associated to a lower risk of developing
      metabolic diseases and cancer. The intake of tomato has been proposed to decrease the risk of
      prostate cancer while the high content of pro-vitamine A carotenes in banana have shown to
      alleviate Vitamin A deficiency in different countries. Interestingly in spite of their
      popularity, there are no biomarkers of banana intake reported in the literature while
      lycopene is the most frequently used metabolite to indicate tomato consumption however, its
      limited specificity and between-subjects variation sets doubt of its accuracy. Therefore, the
      identification of novel biomarkers for both banana and tomato is of great value. Untargeted
      metabolomics, allows a holistic analysis of the food metabolome allowing a deeper inquiry in
      the metabolism of different compounds and the recognition of patterns and individual
      differences that may lead to new hypothesis and further research. Therefore, the aim of the
      present study is to identify biomarkers of acute intake of banana and tomato using an
      untargeted approach on urine serum of 12 volunteers that participated in a crossover,
      randomized, controlled study. Volunteers consumed three different test foods: 1) 240g of
      banana, 2) 300g of tomato and 3) Fresubin 2kcal as control. Serum and urine samples were
      collected in kinetics over 24h and processed to be analyzed using LC-QTof analysis. The
      metabolomics profiles are compared using univariate (ANOVA) and multivariate statistical
      methods (PCA, PLSDA). The identification of discriminant compounds was performed by tandem
      mass fragmentation with a high-resolution LTQ-Orbitrab Mass spectrometer and by an extensive
      inquiry of different online databases.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The rise of metabolomics along with different platforms such as liquid chromatography mass
      spectrometers (LC-MS) have allowed the assessment of thousands of metabolites simultaneously
      in biological samples and the recognition of patterns that may constitute a fingerprint of
      the intake of different foods. Recent studies demonstrated the great potential of
      metabolomics to discover new biomarkers of intake in intervention and cohort studies.The
      diversity of compounds found in food metabolomics represents a major challenge and so in an
      international effort to improve dietary biomarkers identification and validation, the Food
      Biomarkers Alliance (FOODBALL) has been created. In this project, 22 institutions from 11
      different countries will collaborate in three main tasks: 1) Discovery of new dietary
      biomarker using a metabolomic approach, 2) systemic validation of existing and newly
      discovered biomarker to achieve a good coverage of food intake in different European
      populations and 3) exploring biological effects using biomarkers of intake
      (http://foodmetabolome.org/). With the latter, the necessity of building a chemical library
      that allows the use of standards for further identification arises. Along with FOODBALL, The
      Food Compound Exchange (FoodComEx) aims to improve the availability of analytical standards
      of biological compounds to achieve a better and easier biomarker identification
      (http://foodcomex.org/).

      As part of INRA collaboration to FOODBALL and FoodComEx, the present project attempts to
      identify biomarkers of banana and tomato intake, through the exploration of the serum and
      urine metabolome of 12 subjects who consumed these foods following a randomized, controlled,
      crossover design. The present study was comprised of 3 different intervention periods and a
      minimum of 3 days washout between interventions. The intervention periods were comprised of 2
      run in days, 1 intervention day and 1 post intervention day. In the first day of the run in
      period, subjects were instructed to avoid the intake of banana or tomato or any of their
      products; the day prior to the intervention volunteers were asked to avoid the intake of
      phytochemical rich foods and beverages such as wine, coffee, chocolate, tea, and other plant
      based foods including banana and tomato.In the morning of the intervention, day subjects
      arrived in fasting state to the research center at 7.30 am. Volunteers were randomly assigned
      to one of the three interventions, Fresubin ® 2kcal fiber, 240g of banana plus control drink,
      or 300g of tomato plus control drink plus 12g of refined sunflower oil. Throughout the
      intervention, subjects had free access to water, maximum 250ml of water per hour until 6
      hours after the intake of the test food.

      A trained phlebotomist placed a catheter on the subject's arm before the intake of the test
      foods to collect the baseline sample. Then four other samples were collected postprandially
      after 1h, 2h, 4h, and 6h. A total of 7 urine samples were collected. The first void of urine
      was collected by the subjects at home upon the morning of Day 3 and the rest of the samples
      after the intake of the test foods as follows: 0-1h, 1h-2h, 2h-4h, 4h-6h. The urine samples
      corresponding to 6h-12h and 12-24h interval were collected by volunteers at home until the
      morning after the intake of the food.

      After the 6h collection of blood, the peripheral catheter was removed and subjects had lunch
      composed of white bread and cooked pasta, then subjects were allowed to go home. Before
      leaving the Investigation center, participants were instructed to prepare a standardized
      dinner based on pan fried chicken with butter and boiled rice with salt. Volunteers were not
      allowed to eat or drink anything except water and the standardized dinner.

      On the morning of the post intervention day, subjects arrived in fasting state to the
      research center to give the 24h blood sample and deliver the 06-12h and 12-24h urine
      collection. Afterward, subjects were served breakfast at the research center and resumed
      their normal diet until the next run in days of the next intervention period.

      Urine samples and serum samples were aliquoted and stored at -80° C until analysis.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 26, 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">June 16, 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 19, 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>The present project is a randomized, controlled, crossover study with 12 subjects. A cross-over design has been selected as each subject can serve as his/her own control thereby minimizing variations. The intervention order was randomized. The study design does not allow blinding as intervention is the ingestion of different foods.In this study, we assessed the metabolomic profiles of human biofluids after consumption of two different foods: banana (240g peeled fruit) and tomato (300g fresh fruit) in order to identify novel biomarkers for each food. As a control diet, a high energy high protein drink, Fresubin ® 2kcal fiber (Fresinius kabi) was used. The study comprised three dietary interventions of 4 days each and a wash-out period no shorter than 3 days.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in metabolite profiles present in blood serum and urine before the dietary intervention (t=0) and in kinetics over 24 hours.</measure>
    <time_frame>0-24 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Metabolite profiles analyzed using a non-targeted metabolomics approach with a UPLC-MS platform. Blood serum samples collected at time 0, 1 hour, 2 hours, 4 hours, 6 hours and 24 hours. Urine fractions collected at 0-1 hours, 1-2 hours, 2-4 hours, 4-6 hours, 6-12 hours, 12-24 hours. Identification of biomarkers of acute intake of the foods of interest through the comparison of metabolomes after either single dose of tomato, banana or control drink.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Collection of pools of urine and serum samples after acute intake of tomato or banana to be used as analytical standards or for the identification of specific metabolites of banana or tomato components.</measure>
    <time_frame>0-24 hours</time_frame>
    <description>The collection of pools of biofluids that result from this study may be shared with the scientific community through the FoodComEx library in order to be used as an analytical standard or for the identification of metabolites that are specific of banana or tomato intake.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">12</enrollment>
  <condition>Biomarkers</condition>
  <condition>Food Intake</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Banana Cavendish</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>240g of fruit plus 150ml of Fresubin ® 2kcal fiber neutral flavor</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control drink</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>250ml of Fresubin ® 2kcal fiber neutral flavor</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Tomato</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>300g of tomato plus of Fresubin ® 2kcal fiber neutral flavor plus 12g of refined sunflower oil.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Banana Cavendish</intervention_name>
    <description>240g of fruit plus 150ml of control drink (Fresubin ® 2kcal fiber neutral flavor)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Banana Cavendish</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Test Food</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Tomato</intervention_name>
    <description>300g of raw tomato (&quot;coeur de boeuf&quot;) with refined sunflower oil (12g) and 150ml of control drink (Fresubin ® 2kcal fiber neutral flavor).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Tomato</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Test Food</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Fresubin ® 2kcal fiber neutral flavor</intervention_name>
    <description>250 ml Fresubin ® 2kcal fiber neutral flavor</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control drink</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Control</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Healthy males and females

          -  Aged 18- 40 years

          -  BMI &gt;18.5 and &lt; 30 kg/m2

          -  Willing/able to consume all test foods (tomato, banana, Fresubin drink) and the
             standardized meals (rice and chicken)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Smokers

          -  Diagnosed health condition (chronic or infectious disease)

          -  Taking nutritional supplements (e.g. vitamins, minerals) several times a week.

          -  Taking medication (oral contraceptive pill is allowed).

          -  Pregnant, lactating.

          -  Antibiotics treatment within 3 months prior to intervention.

          -  Vegetarians, as standardized meals will contain meat.

          -  Not willing to follow nutritional restrictions, including drinking alcohol during
             study days

          -  Not willing/able to give informed consent or to sign informed consent.

          -  Not affiliated to National Health Insurance.

          -  Being in exclusion on the National Volunteers Data file or refusing to be registered
             on the National Volunteers Data file.

          -  Currently participating or who having got 4500€ in this year to have participated in
             another clinical trial.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>40 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Claudine Manach, Researcher</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Institut National de la Recherche Agronomique</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>INRA</name>
      <address>
        <city>Clermont-Ferrand</city>
        <state>Rhône-Alpes-Auvergne</state>
        <zip>63122</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Andersen MB, Kristensen M, Manach C, Pujos-Guillot E, Poulsen SK, Larsen TM, Astrup A, Dragsted L. Discovery and validation of urinary exposure markers for different plant foods by untargeted metabolomics. Anal Bioanal Chem. 2014 Mar;406(7):1829-44. doi: 10.1007/s00216-013-7498-5. Epub 2014 Jan 4.</citation>
    <PMID>24390407</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Manach C, Hubert J, Llorach R, Scalbert A. The complex links between dietary phytochemicals and human health deciphered by metabolomics. Mol Nutr Food Res. 2009 Oct;53(10):1303-15. doi: 10.1002/mnfr.200800516. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19764066</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Scalbert A, Brennan L, Manach C, Andres-Lacueva C, Dragsted LO, Draper J, Rappaport SM, van der Hooft JJ, Wishart DS. The food metabolome: a window over dietary exposure. Am J Clin Nutr. 2014 Jun;99(6):1286-308. doi: 10.3945/ajcn.113.076133. Epub 2014 Apr 23. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24760973</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Re R, Bramley PM, Rice-Evans C. Effects of food processing on flavonoids and lycopene status in a Mediterranean tomato variety. Free Radic Res. 2002 Jul;36(7):803-10.</citation>
    <PMID>12180131</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Giovannucci E. Tomatoes, tomato-based products, lycopene, and cancer: review of the epidemiologic literature. J Natl Cancer Inst. 1999 Feb 17;91(4):317-31. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>10050865</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pereira A, Maraschin M. Banana (Musa spp) from peel to pulp: ethnopharmacology, source of bioactive compounds and its relevance for human health. J Ethnopharmacol. 2015 Feb 3;160:149-63. doi: 10.1016/j.jep.2014.11.008. Epub 2014 Nov 13. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25449450</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pujos-Guillot E, Hubert J, Martin JF, Lyan B, Quintana M, Claude S, Chabanas B, Rothwell JA, Bennetau-Pelissero C, Scalbert A, Comte B, Hercberg S, Morand C, Galan P, Manach C. Mass spectrometry-based metabolomics for the discovery of biomarkers of fruit and vegetable intake: citrus fruit as a case study. J Proteome Res. 2013 Apr 5;12(4):1645-59. doi: 10.1021/pr300997c. Epub 2013 Mar 5.</citation>
    <PMID>23425595</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Peralta I, Spooner DM. Genetic Improvement of Solanaceous Crops Volume 2: Tomato. CRC Press; 2006. https://books.google.com/books?hl=en&amp;lr=&amp;id=1m7RBQAAQBAJ&amp;pgis=1. Accessed December 18, 2015</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Manach C., Brennan L, Drasgted L.O. Metabolomics to evaluate food intake and utilization in nutritional epidemiology. In: Metabolomics as a Tool in Nutritional Research, Woodhead publishing 2015. pp.167-196</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kesse-Guyot E, Castetbon K, Touvier M, Hercberg S, Galan P. Relative validity and reproducibility of a food frequency questionnaire designed for French adults. Ann Nutr Metab. 2010;57(3-4):153-62. doi: 10.1159/000321680. Epub 2010 Nov 16.</citation>
    <PMID>21079389</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>July 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 31, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 26, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 10, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 12, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 12, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 16, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Institut National de la Recherche Agronomique</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Claudine MANACH</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>biomarkers</keyword>
  <keyword>diet</keyword>
  <keyword>banana</keyword>
  <keyword>tomato</keyword>
  <keyword>urine</keyword>
  <keyword>plasma</keyword>
  <keyword>intake</keyword>
  <keyword>exposure</keyword>
  <keyword>metabolomics</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <provided_document_section>
    <provided_document>
      <document_type>Study Protocol</document_type>
      <document_has_protocol>Yes</document_has_protocol>
      <document_has_icf>No</document_has_icf>
      <document_has_sap>No</document_has_sap>
      <document_date>June 25, 2018</document_date>
      <document_url>https://ClinicalTrials.gov/ProvidedDocs/55/NCT03581955/Prot_000.pdf</document_url>
    </provided_document>
    <provided_document>
      <document_type>Statistical Analysis Plan</document_type>
      <document_has_protocol>No</document_has_protocol>
      <document_has_icf>No</document_has_icf>
      <document_has_sap>Yes</document_has_sap>
      <document_date>June 25, 2018</document_date>
      <document_url>https://ClinicalTrials.gov/ProvidedDocs/55/NCT03581955/SAP_001.pdf</document_url>
    </provided_document>
  </provided_document_section>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

