<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03585699</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NMRR-16-690-30761</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03585699</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Percutaneous Fluoroscopic vs CT Guided Core Needle Biopsy for Spinal Infection and Tumor</brief_title>
  <official_title>Accuracy, Safety and Diagnostic Outcome of Percutaneous Fluoroscopic vs. CT Guided Transpedicular Core Needle Biopsy for Spinal Infections and Tumors. A Prospective Randomized Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Malaya</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Malaya</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Spinal biopsy is important to obtain culture and histopathological diagnosis in spine
      infection and tumors. To date, there is no prospective randomized study comparing both
      techniques. Therefore, the aim of this prospective randomized trial was to evaluate the
      accuracy, safety and diagnostic outcome of both these techniques.A prospective randomized
      trial was performed in 60 patients divided equally into fluoroscopic and CT guided spinal
      biopsy groups. Transpedicular approach was done with 8G core biopsy needle. Specimens were
      sent for histopathological examinations and cultures. Diagnosis were made based on biopsy
      results, clinical criteria and disease progression during 6 months follow up. Radiation
      expose to patients and doctors were measured with optically stimulated luminescence
      dosimeters (OSLDs).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This prospective randomized study was carried out in a single institution from November 2016
      to June 2018.

      Patients were recruited by three spine surgeons from the same institution after eligibility
      assessment. Sixty consecutive patients were randomized equally into fluoroscopic and CT
      guided spinal biopsy groups. Randomization procedure was performed using a computer generated
      random number sequence on www.random.org. Separate individuals completed the random
      allocation sequence, patient enrollment and outcome assessment. Outcome assessors were
      blinded to group assignment.

      Data collection Clinical data collected were: patient demographics, comorbidities, infective
      parameters, tumor markers, Magnetic Resonance Imaging (MRI) findings and pre-biopsy pain
      score at rest using visual analogue scale (VAS). Intraoperative data included radiation
      exposure dosage, biopsy duration and complications encountered. Following biopsy, we recorded
      the biopsy result, 6-hourly pain score (VAS) at for 48 hours, additional analgesia
      requirement and complications.

      Radiation measurement Commercial optically stimulated luminescence dosimeters, OSLDs
      (NanoDotTM Dosimeter, Landauer Inc, Glenwood, IL) were used to measure radiation dose. Ten
      OSLDs were placed on patients and doctors prior to all biopsies over selective areas
      representing radiosensitive organs. Placements of the OSLDs were done by a single observer.
      OSLDs were processed using MicroStar OSLD reader system (Landauer, Inc. Glenwood, IL). Each
      OSLD was processed 3 times during each reading to obtain a mean value to minimize error. The
      absorbed doses were measured in centigrays (cGy). Bleaching/zeroing of the OSLDs were done
      using optical annealing system containing fluorescent lamps (Osram lumilux, 24 W, 280 ~780
      nm) in between each use of OSLDs.

      Biopsy technique Transpedicular approach with an 8-gauge T-Lok™ bone marrow biopsy needle
      (Argon Medical Devices, Athens, TX, USA) was used in both arms. 10cc 2% lignocaine was
      infiltrated prior to biopsy. Biopsy needle was tapped gently with mallet through the pedicle
      and into the lesion under imaging guidance. Trocar was then withdrawn once it reached the
      affected area. The cannula was rotated several times to disengage sample from surrounding
      tissue. Then, aspiration of samples was done using 10-ml syringe prior to retraction of the
      cannula. Tissue samples were retrieved from the cannula with the use of stylet.

      Samples collected were sent to laboratories for histopathological examination (HPE), culture
      and sensitivity (bacteriology, mycology and acid-fast bacilli), staining (Gram and
      Ziehl-Neelsen) and polymerase chain reaction (PCR) test for Mycobacterium tuberculosis.

        1. Fluoroscopy Guided Spinal Biopsy Arm: Fluoroscopy guided spinal biopsies were done by
           spine surgeons in the operation theatre using C-Arm fluoroscopy device
           (OECFluorostar7900Compact - GE®). C-arm image intensiﬁer was positioned until
           fluoroscopic beam was collinear with the corresponding vertebral body on AP view prior
           to insertion of biopsy needle.

        2. CT guided Spinal Biopsy Arm: CT guided spinal biopsies were done by radiologist under
           guidance of 128-slice CT scanner (SOMATOM Definition AS+, Siemens Medical Solutions USA,
           Inc.). Preliminary axial CT scanning was done in bone window (window width, WW:2500;
           window level, WL:500) at the pre-selected levels decided from previous imaging to plan
           the needle access. Biopsy was then performed under sequential CT-fluoroscopy scan.

      Post biopsy care Antimicrobials were commenced upon completion of biopsy for patients who
      were diagnosed to have spine infection. Disease progression was assessed based on clinical
      symptoms, ESR, CRP and/or MRI repeated during 6 months follow up for patients who were not
      treated for spinal infection.

      For suspected spinal tumor cases, negative biopsies that were reported to have inadequate
      sample, were repeated with the other method or other investigation modalities will be
      resorted accordingly. Patients with negative biopsy that was reported to have adequate sample
      were follow up for 6 months for disease progression.

      Sample size Sample size was determined based on accuracy of biopsy as outcome variable, in
      which the accuracy rate was 0.89. It was estimated using G*Power software (version 3.1.9.2)
      based on 2 proportions formula (Fisher's exact test). With alpha level of 0.05, 95%
      confidence interval and power of study 0.8, a minimum number of 52 patients (26 patients for
      each arm) was required for this study.

      Statistical analysis Data were analyzed with SPSS Inc., Chicago, IL (SPSS v 23). Continuous
      data were reported as mean ± standard deviation and compared using t test. Chi-squared
      testing was used for between-groups comparisons. Fisher-exact test was used for the
      comparison of diagnostic accuracy between fluoroscopic and CT guided spinal biopsy. A p-value
      of &lt;0.05 was considered significant.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 1, 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">June 2, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 2, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>Separate individuals completed the random allocation sequence, patient enrollment and outcome assessment. Outcome assessors were blinded to group assignment.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Diagnostic accuracy of fluoroscopic and CT guided spinal biopsy</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Diagnostic accuracy were determined based on true positive, true negative, false positive and false negative biopsy findings</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Radiation expose to patients and doctors</measure>
    <time_frame>During biopsy</time_frame>
    <description>Total of 10 commercial optically stimulated luminescence dosimeters (OSLDs) were placed on patients and doctors at different body areas prior to biopsy to measure radiation dose</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pre biopsy and post biopsy pain score assessed by visual analogue scale (VAS)</measure>
    <time_frame>48 hours post biopsy</time_frame>
    <description>Pre biopsy pain score and post biopsy pain score (6-hourly for 48 hours) were assessed base on visual analogue scale (VAS) and recorded. Pain score will be aggregated by mean and standard deviation and compared between both groups. Additional analgesia requirement was documented.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Complications of spinal biopsy</measure>
    <time_frame>During and 48 hours after spinal biopsy</time_frame>
    <description>Complications of spinal biopsy were observed such as neurovascular injury and iatrogenic fracture.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Spondylodiskitis</condition>
  <condition>Spinal Tumor</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Fluoroscopy Guided Spinal Biopsy Arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Fluoroscopy guided spinal biopsies were done by spine surgeons in the operation theatre using C-Arm fluoroscopy device (OECFluorostar7900Compact - GE®). C-arm image intensiﬁer was positioned until fluoroscopic beam was collinear with the corresponding vertebral body on AP view prior to insertion of biopsy needle</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>CT guided Spinal Biopsy Arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>CT guided spinal biopsies were done by radiologist under guidance of 128-slice CT scanner (SOMATOM Definition AS+, Siemens Medical Solutions USA, Inc.). Preliminary axial CT scanning was done in bone window (window width, WW:2500; window level, WL:500) at the pre-selected levels decided from previous imaging to plan the needle access. Biopsy was then performed under sequential CT-fluoroscopy scan.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Fluoroscopy Guided Spinal Biopsy</intervention_name>
    <description>Spinal biopsy done via Transpedicular approach with an 8-gauge T-Lok™ bone marrow biopsy needle under fluoroscopic guidance.
Samples collected were sent to laboratories for histopathological examination (HPE), culture and sensitivity (bacteriology, mycology and acid-fast bacilli), staining (Gram and Ziehl-Neelsen) and polymerase chain reaction (PCR) test for Mycobacterium tuberculosis.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Fluoroscopy Guided Spinal Biopsy Arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>CT guided Spinal Biopsy</intervention_name>
    <description>Spinal biopsy done via Transpedicular approach with an 8-gauge T-Lok™ bone marrow biopsy needle under CT guidance.
Samples collected were sent to laboratories for histopathological examination (HPE), culture and sensitivity (bacteriology, mycology and acid-fast bacilli), staining (Gram and Ziehl-Neelsen) and polymerase chain reaction (PCR) test for Mycobacterium tuberculosis.</description>
    <arm_group_label>CT guided Spinal Biopsy Arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Age more than 18;

          2. Patients who presented with clinical symptoms and radiological features suggestive of
             infection or malignancy;

          3. MRI reported as probable infection or tumour.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Cervical spine lesion;

          2. Significant neurological deficit that required urgent surgery;

          3. Partially treated spinal infections;

          4. Vascular tumour;

          5. Infection over skin puncture site;

          6. Pregnancy;

          7. Bleeding diathesis;

          8. Medically unfit for spinal biopsy.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Chris Yin Wei Chan</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>University of Malaya</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Malaya Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kuala Lumpur</city>
        <zip>59100</zip>
        <country>Malaysia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Malaysia</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 29, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 11, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 13, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 17, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 17, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 19, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Malaya</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Dr Lee She Ann</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Orthopedic Registra</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>spinal biopsy</keyword>
  <keyword>prospective randomizd trial</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Discitis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

