<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03581006</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>17-00127</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03581006</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Metabolomics of World Trade Center-Lung Injury: Biomarker Validation, Longitudinal Assessment, and Dietary Intervention</brief_title>
  <official_title>Metabolomics of World Trade Center-Lung Injury: Biomarker Validation, Longitudinal Assessment, and Dietary Intervention</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>NYU Langone Health</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>NYU Langone Health</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a randomized-controlled unblinded clinical trial to investigate dietary intervention
      on metabolic biomarker assessment in World Trade Center (WTC) Lung Injury (LI) in
      firefighters. The purpose of this study is to evaluate biomarkers of metabolic dysregulation
      that have previously been found to predict WTC-LI in a case cohort study selected from the
      entire exposed firefighter cohort, and attempt to alter these metabolites using dietary
      intervention and a technology-supported behavioral modification program. Investigators will
      measure Pre/Post global metabolic expression in WTC-exposed, symptomatic firefighter serum
      sampled after 6-month intervention, as well as clinical outcomes of WTC-LI in the study group
      vs controls.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Investigators propose to measure metabolites on this expanded cohort with serum sampled
      before and after 6-month intervention with calorie restricted Mediterranean diet to: 1)
      determine the effects of a technology assisted calorie restricted diet on metabolic risk and
      lung function; 2) determine differences between usual care and intervention group using
      genomics and metabolomics that may be targetable markers for further evaluation; 3) quantify
      the metabolome and evaluate pre/post changes in BMI, FEV1, FeNo, vascular stiffness, and
      overall quality of life; and 4) explore dietary modification as treatment of WTC-LI. The
      biomarker profile of the cohort control will be useful for discovering biomarker associations
      with other disease manifestations such as: bronchial wall thickening on CT, obstruction on
      FEV1 /FVC ratio, bronchodilator response, methacholine reactivity, and other definitions of
      loss of FEV 1 . This cohort control will be an asset to future studies.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 12, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational [Patient Registry]</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <target_duration>6 Months</target_duration>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pulmonary Function using FEV Measure</measure>
    <time_frame>4 Years</time_frame>
    <description>Forced expiratory volume (FEV) at timed intervals of 0.5, 1.0 (FEV1), 2.0, and 3.0 seconds using spirometer that measures the amount (volume) and/or speed (flow) of air that can be inhaled and exhaled.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Body mass index (BMI)</measure>
    <time_frame>4 Years</time_frame>
    <description>Body mass (weight in kg) divided by square of the body height (measured in meters), expressed in units kg/m^2</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>St. George's Respiratory Questionnaire (SGRQ)</measure>
    <time_frame>4 Years</time_frame>
    <description>Airways-disease specific paper questionnaire assessing symptoms, effect on activity level, and impact on quality of life.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Electrocardiogram (EKG)</measure>
    <time_frame>4 years</time_frame>
    <description>Non-invasive brief electrical recording of heart rate and rhythm using electrodes placed on the chest</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Fraction of exhaled nitrous oxide (FENO)</measure>
    <time_frame>4 years</time_frame>
    <description>Simple breathing test to measure airway inflammation as often seen in asthma or particulate matter lung injury, measured in ppb.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pulse Wave Velocity (PWV)</measure>
    <time_frame>4 years</time_frame>
    <description>Non-invasive measurement to ascertain vascular stiffness, by measuring the velocity at which the blood pressure pulse propogates through the circulatory system. This is done using a simple non-invasive blood pressure cuff assessment at the carotid and femoral arteries. It is measured as a velocity, in meters/per second.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>6-minute walk test (6MWT)</measure>
    <time_frame>4 years</time_frame>
    <description>Simple exercise capacity assessment measuring distance walked over 6 minutes, measured in meters.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Individual metabolomic profile - blood sample</measure>
    <time_frame>4 years</time_frame>
    <description>Routine blood testing via sterile phlebotomy to assess metabolic biomarkers that may or may not predict lung injury. These metabolites are generated in all individuals based on their dietary and exercise habits, underlying comorbidities, and unique metabolism. Measured in routine blood samples, and quantified based on unique chemical composition of that molecule. There is no additional risk to the human subject aside that of venipuncture.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Individual genomic profile - saliva sample</measure>
    <time_frame>4 years</time_frame>
    <description>Simple home collection of sputum/saliva sample using a buccal swab kit, provided to the human subject. Saliva will be used to generate a genetic profile unique to that individual, reported as chromosomes, genes, and proteins that may predict lung injury. There is no risk to the human subject aside that of providing a sputum sample. All individual information is de-identified for personal protection.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Individual microbiome profile - stool sample</measure>
    <time_frame>4 years</time_frame>
    <description>Simple home collection of a stool sample using a sterile collection kit, provided to the human subject. Stool will be used to generate a microbiome profile unique to that individual, reported as bacterial species found in the gut flora, that may predict lung injury. There is no risk to the human subject aside that of providing a stool sample. All individual information is de-identified for personal protection.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Short-form-36 (SF-36) questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>4 years</time_frame>
    <description>Generalized paper questionnaire for self-assessment of mental health, general health perception, and overall quality of life</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Routine vital signs - Heart Rate</measure>
    <time_frame>4 years</time_frame>
    <description>Brief assessment of heart rate (pulse) measured in beats/per minute</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Routine vital signs - Blood Pressure</measure>
    <time_frame>4 years</time_frame>
    <description>Subjects who have spirometry available within the last 36 months, and at their post-9/11 visits at the FDNY.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Routine vital signs - Body temperature</measure>
    <time_frame>4 years</time_frame>
    <description>Brief assessment of body temperature using a basic thermometer under the tongue, measured in degrees Fahrenheit</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Neck circumference</measure>
    <time_frame>4 years</time_frame>
    <description>Assessment of neck circumference using basic measuring tape, recorded in centimeters</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Waist circumference</measure>
    <time_frame>4 years</time_frame>
    <description>Assessment of waist circumference using basic measuring tape, recorded in centimeters</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Bioelectrical impedance analysis (BIA)</measure>
    <time_frame>4 years</time_frame>
    <description>Assessment of lean body mass and total body fat percentage using an InBody bioelectrical impedance analysis scale.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Food Frequency Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>4 years</time_frame>
    <description>Paper assessment of typical dietary intake over previous one month, multiple choice answers</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">140</enrollment>
  <condition>Lung Injury</condition>
  <condition>Particulate Matter Inhalation Injury</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention Group</arm_group_label>
    <description>This observational cohort study will follow firefighters enrolled in Monitoring and Treatment Program. Investigators will include firefighters in the validation cohort who were present at the WTC site within 3 days of 9/11, have consent, and have abnormal post-9/11 lung function.
This intervention group will undergo technology based monitoring and behavioral participation in a dietary and exercise program with the intent of weight loss and compliance with a low-calorie Mediterranean diet.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control (Usual care) Group</arm_group_label>
    <description>This observational cohort study will follow firefighters enrolled in Monitoring and Treatment Program. Investigators will include firefighters in the validation cohort who were present at the WTC site within 3 days of 9/11, have consent, and have abnormal post-9/11 lung function.
This group will receive no dietary or behavioral intervention. They will continue usual care with their home physicians.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Low-Calorie Mediterranean Diet</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants in the intervention group will receive 6 months of education and behavioral counseling with self-monitoring to help them adopt a Mediterranean-style, calorie-restricted diet, and engage in physical activity</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention Group</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>LoCalMed</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Combination Product</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Technology based monitoring and behavioral participation</intervention_name>
    <description>Intervention participants will use smart phones to connect to intervention applications, WebEx, MyNetDiary</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention Group</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>LoCalMed</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Usual care group</intervention_name>
    <description>Control group, who will receive no dietary or behavioral intervention during the trial</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control (Usual care) Group</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Control group</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      -FEV1&lt;LLN to define WTC-LI; resistant subjects had the highest FEV1(FEV1≥107% predicted and
      within one-standard deviation(SD) of the highest FEV1% predicted of the study cohort).
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        FDNY rescue and recovery worker with 9/11 exposure with documented WTC-LI by spirometry
        criteria.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Age 21-90.

          2. Born male sex and currently identify as genetic male

          3. FDNY rescue and recovery worker.

          4. Documented WTC exposure.

          5. Enrolled in the FDNY WTC Health Program

          6. Subjects are willing and able to consent for themselves to study enrollment

          7. Subjects are willing and able to participate in study procedures

          8. Are able to perform their activities of daily living independently

          9. Are either light duty or retired FDNY Firefighters

         10. Have an FEV1 less than the LLN of predicted for age/sex/weight documented at any time
             after 9/11/2001.

         11. Have a BMI&gt;27 kg/m2 and &lt;50kg/m2

         12. Willing and able to modify their diet and activity level.

         13. Subjects who have a spirometry available within the last 36 months, and at their
             post-9/11 visits at the FDNY

         14. Demonstrate minimal proficiency using a smart phone

         15. Have means to accommodate transportation to/from in-person visits

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Have pre-existing and documented conditions or concurrent diagnoses, including (and
             not necessarily limited to) active cancer, severe heart disease, significant cognitive
             impairment, eating disorders, significant psychiatric illness, end-stage COPD, severe
             pulmonary hypertension, or organ transplant.

          2. Concomitant use of interfering medication(s) or devices currently or within the month
             prior to enrollment, including anti-retrovirals, human monoclonal antibodies,
             supplemental daytime oxygen, and insulin pumps.

          3. Severe gastrointestinal issues or illnesses that would prevent adherence to the
             proposed diets.

          4. Severe kidney disease requiring dialysis

          5. Severe liver disease requiring frequent medical intervention

          6. Participating in other diet modification studies.

          7. High dose steroid (&gt;20mg prednisone or equivalent) or other hormonal
             treatments/chemotherapy use in the last month, including testosterone supplementation.

          8. Life-expectancy &lt; 6 months

          9. BMI ≥50 kg/m2 or ≤27 kg/m2

         10. Recent significant intentional or unintentional weight loss, defined as over 5%
             reduction in total body weight over the last month. (Blackburn Criteria).

         11. Significant or severe alcohol abuse disorder
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <gender_based>Yes</gender_based>
    <gender_description>Male only</gender_description>
    <minimum_age>21 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>90 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Anna Nolan, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>NYU Langone Health</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Jessica Riggs, MD</last_name>
    <phone>646-501-6783</phone>
    <email>jessica.riggs@nyumc.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Rachel Lam</last_name>
    <phone>646-501-6783</phone>
    <email>rachel.lam@nyumc.org</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>New York University School of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10016</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jessica Riggs, MD</last_name>
      <phone>646-501-6783</phone>
      <email>jessica.riggs@nyumc.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Anna Nolan</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 15, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 6, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 10, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 27, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 27, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 28, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>World Trade Center</keyword>
  <keyword>Firefighters</keyword>
  <keyword>FDNY</keyword>
  <keyword>9/11</keyword>
  <keyword>Metabolomics</keyword>
  <keyword>FIREHOUSE</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lung Injury</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Wounds and Injuries</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

