<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03587870</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>EKNZ 2018-00259</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03587870</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Protein Delivery in Intermittent and Continuous Enteral Nutrition in ICU Patients</brief_title>
  <acronym>ProBoNo</acronym>
  <official_title>Protein Delivery in Intermittent and Continuous Enteral Nutrition in ICU Patients A Prospective, Randomised Controlled Pilot Study in Critical Ill Patients With a Protein-rich Formula</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University Hospital, Basel, Switzerland</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University Hospital, Basel, Switzerland</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Acute skeletal muscle wasting in ICU patients is associated with functional impairment and
      with increased risk of death. Of what we know today, physical disability can persist up to 5
      years. Adequate nutrition is the basis for an optimal recovery for ICU patients and for
      prevention of muscle wasting. Today, continuous feeding is still the standard enteral
      nutrition form for patients in the ICU to limit the incidence of aspiration. A study of Serpa
      et al. and Georgia et al. compared the continuous feeding versus a bolus nutrition with a
      feeding time of 30 - 60 minutes every 4 hours. They showed no statistical differences in
      complications between both groups.

      ProBoNo is a prospective, randomized, controlled pilot study of critically ill patients with
      a protein- rich formula to explore the impact of continuous or intermittent bolus nutrition
      on muscle breakdown in ICU patients. The investigators would like to recruit 68 patients
      during the first 24 hours after surgical intensive care unit admission. Prior beginning of
      nutrition administration, and on the 7th day thereafter the investigators will perform a
      muscle biopsy and an ultrasound from the vastus lateralis muscle in both groups.

      The primary outcome is the time from 6.00 am of the following day after admission until the
      patient reaches his daily protein's target quantity. Secondary outcomes include the diameter
      and densitiy of the hamstrings assessed by ultrasound and histology, the process of gastric
      residual volume, number of diarrhoea events and laboratory findings like glucose, urea and
      insulin like growth factor (IGF)-1, all compared between the two time points.

      Intermittent feeding is not only more natural and could help to limit the muscle wasting in
      ICU patients, it is also easier to handle for the ICU caring medical team. A trial from
      Georgia et al. in 2007 compared continuous to intermittent enteral nutrition. They found that
      the intermittently fed patients reached their nutrition goal faster than those being
      continuously nourished. This might in part be explained by feeding interruptions in the
      continuous feeding regimen. Presumably, preoperative holding of tube feedings in the
      continuous nutrition group most commonly caused interruptions. Thus, independently from
      prevention of muscle breakdown, a bolus nutrition would be more attractive.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The relevance of early continuous or intermittent enteral feeding of critically ill patients
      has been discussed controversially in the last years. Today, continuous feeding is still the
      standard for enteral nutrition in the ICU. The continuous nutrition can prevent abdominal
      intolerance like vomiting, diarrhoea and aspiration. Pulmonary aspiration is the most
      dramatic consequence of enteral nutrition and can be limited by a continuous feeding as shown
      by a study in 2003. However, nutrition was started with a bolus of 125ml as baseline by force
      of gravity over 15 minutes. Compared to the continuous nutrition, this is considered much
      volume in a short time. Naturally, risk of gastric intolerance in this scenario is very high.

      In other studies, a similar amount of nutrition was given over a longer period of time (30 -
      60 minutes) every 4 hours. In each cohort (continuous and bolus), only one case of pulmonary
      aspiration or tube obstruction was detected. After this study, other trials with a similar
      result followed. In 2007 a trial of Georgia et al. showed no statistical differences in
      complications regarding tube feeding, no differences of diarrhoea, emesis or pneumonias
      between continuous and bolus nutrition. The feeding time for bolus nutrition is also a
      critical influential factor. When an intermittent feeding is given over a longer period of
      time (20-40 minutes), the incidence of nausea and vomiting has not increased.

      Intermittent feeding is not only a good alternative to continuous feeding, but also more
      natural, as long-term intake of nutrition over 20 hours is not common in any mammal. The
      alimentary tract and metabolic pathways of humans seem designed for intermittent ingestion of
      essential nutrients reduced to a few times a day. Different hormones of the endocrine cells
      affect complex roles of gastrointestinal motility, gall bladder contraction and nutrient
      absorption. The level of these hormones depends on the amount of nutrient ingestion. This
      response of the hormones is almost completely abolished in continuous feeding. But in
      intermittent nutrition, hormones like incretin, glucose-dependent insulinotropic polypeptide
      (GLP-1) and glucose-dependent insulinotropic polypeptide (GIP) boost the level of insulin and
      the resulting carbohydrate load and therefore influence the muscle protein synthesis and
      breakdown.

      In healthy individuals, the anabolic effects of feeding occur due to an increase on the
      synthetic rate of muscle protein synthesis of approximately 300% with a simultaneous 50%
      decrease in the rate of protein breakdown. Two studies of 2009 and 2011 compared the
      intermittent bolus and continuous feeding and the effect of protein synthesis in skeletal
      muscle in neonatal pigs. They analysed the fractional rates of protein synthesis in muscle
      samples of continuous and intermittent bolus feeding groups. They could show that although
      both groups, continuous and intermittent bolus feeding, stimulate muscle protein synthesis,
      but in the bolus-fed, in the fractional rates of protein synthesis called K's was greater
      after a meal.

      An ongoing study wants to show the effect of bolus vs. continuous feeding in ICU patients
      related to muscle wasting by measurements of ultrasound and blood samples. In this trial, the
      investigators would like to have a similar approach but with different measurements. Using
      ultrasound and muscle biopsies, the investigators aim to determine whether intermittent
      enteral feeding could preserve muscle mass better or more than standard continuous enteral
      feeding in the critically ill patients. In addition, the investigators would like to assess
      if intermittent bolus feeding optimizes protein intake in the first 7 days of critical
      illness since the intermittent route is less affected by interruptions following treatment
      and diagnostic procedures.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 25, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>A prospective, randomised controlled pilot study in critical ill patients with a protein-rich formula</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Daily protein target quantity</measure>
    <time_frame>During ICU stay for the duration of 7 days after study inclusion</time_frame>
    <description>Is the time from 6.00 am of the following day after admission until the patient reaches his daily protein target quantity (1.2 g/ kg Biologische Wertigkeit (BW)/ biological value protein in the control group, to 1.5 g/kg BW protein in the experimental group).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Diameter of the hamstrings</measure>
    <time_frame>During ICU stay, exactly 7 days after study inclusion</time_frame>
    <description>Diameter of the hamstrings assessed by ultrasound and histology</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Gastric residual content</measure>
    <time_frame>Every day during ICU stay for the duration of 7 days after study inclusion</time_frame>
    <description>Amount of gastric residual volume (ml)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Diarrhoea</measure>
    <time_frame>Every day during ICU stay for the duration of 7 days after study inclusion</time_frame>
    <description>Number of diarrhoea events</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Glucose (mmol/l) measurement</measure>
    <time_frame>Every day during ICU stay for the duration of 7 days after study inclusion</time_frame>
    <description>Laboratory parameters relevant to assess under enteral Nutrition (Glucose (mmol/l))</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>BUN (mg/dl) measurement</measure>
    <time_frame>Every day during ICU stay for the duration of 7 days after study inclusion</time_frame>
    <description>Laboratory parameters relevant to assess under enteral Nutrition (BUN (mg/dl))</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>IGF-1 (mmol/l) measurement</measure>
    <time_frame>Every day during ICU stay for the duration of 7 days after study inclusion</time_frame>
    <description>Laboratory parameters relevant to assess under enteral Nutrition (IGF-1 (mmol/l))</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">68</enrollment>
  <condition>Muscle Wasting in Critically Ill</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Bolus enteral nutrition with Fresubin Intensive</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Bolus nutrition over 30-40 minutes every 4 hours with Fresubin Intensive</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Continuous enteral nutrition with Fresubin Intensive</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Continuous nutrition over 20 hours per day with Fresubin Intensive (standard)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Enteral nutrition with Fresubin Intensive</intervention_name>
    <description>Comparison of intermittent (experimental) vs continuous (standard, active comparator) enteral nutrition on muscle wasting in critically ill patients</description>
    <arm_group_label>Bolus enteral nutrition with Fresubin Intensive</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Continuous enteral nutrition with Fresubin Intensive</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Informed Consent as documented by signature

          -  Adult patients (age 18 years or older)

          -  Expected ICU stay of five days or longer

          -  Expected enteral feeding during at least five days

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Pregnancy or breast feeding (women of childbearing age are tested for high beta-human
             chorionic gonadotropin (hCG) in urine or serum upon ICU admission)

          -  Clinically significant chronic or acute kidney insufficiency with a glomerular
             filtration rate (GFR) &lt;15.

          -  BMI ≤ 18 and ≥ 35.

          -  Intestinal perforation, peritonitis, intestinal fistula, necrosis or other
             contraindication to enteral diet

          -  Death or discharge before 48 hours of observation

          -  Noradrenaline ≥ 0.5 µg/kg bodyweight /min

          -  Inherited and chronic skeletal muscle disease (e.g. Morbus Duchenne or other
             motoneuron disease)

          -  Paralysis (e.g. hemiplegia, tetraplegia and paraplegia)

          -  Immunosuppression

          -  Haematologic malignancy
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Alexa Hollinger, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University Hospital Basel, Basel Switzerland</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Alexa Hollinger, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+41786747130</phone>
    <email>alexa.hollinger@usb.ch</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Désirée Yeginsoy, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+41774261353</phone>
    <email>desi.y@bluewin.ch</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Hospital Basel, operative ICU</name>
      <address>
        <city>Basel</city>
        <state>Basel-Stadt</state>
        <zip>4031</zip>
        <country>Switzerland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Alexa Hollinger, Dr. MD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Switzerland</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 4, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 3, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 16, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 16, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 16, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 17, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>intensive care unit</keyword>
  <keyword>intermittent enteral nutrition</keyword>
  <keyword>continuous enteral nutrition</keyword>
  <keyword>muscle wasting</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Muscular Atrophy</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Wasting Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Critical Illness</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cachexia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

