<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03587792</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>38RC17.325</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2017-A02900-53</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03587792</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study of Binaural Squelch Effect in Unilateral Otosclerosis</brief_title>
  <acronym>CBOU</acronym>
  <official_title>Study of Binaural Squelch Effect Among Patients Undergoing Unilateral Otosclerosis Surgery: Comparison of Understanding in Noise Before-after Surgery</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University Hospital, Grenoble</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University Hospital, Grenoble</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Patients with unilateral transmission hypoacusis due to otosclerosis undergoing stapedectomy
      surgery will be prospectively included.

      They will be undergoing a free field vocal audiometry using the Oldenburg MATRIX software to
      evaluated the squelch effect gain between audiometry before and after 9months after surgery.

      Our hypothesis is to show a squelch effect with the rehabilitation of the binaural audition.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Otosclerosis is one of the main causes of transmission hypoacusis. It can be treated with
      stapedectomy surgery.

      But the understanding ability in noise has not been really studied. The Oldenburg MATRIX test
      is a well know test in audiology and allow to study the understanding in noise.

      This study included all the patients coming in our center for stapedectomy for otosclerosis
      with controlateral audition under 30 decibels (dB) loss.

      They will all undergo the MATRIX test in three situations: vocal material and noise from the
      front of the patient (S0N0 situation); vocal material from the front and noise from the
      bad-earing side (S0N-90 situation); vocal material from the front and noise from the
      good-earing side (S0N90 situation).

      This might give three informations:

      -Squelch effect which is the difference between Speech Reception Threshold (SRT) in S0N90
      situation at 9month after surgery and before surgery.

      The squelch effect is the ability of cortical discrimination to extract spatial cues and
      information providing from two different sources. So we considered the situation before
      surgery as a unilateral condition and the surgery rehabilitation as a bilateral condition.

        -  Head Shadow effect which is the difference between S0N90 and S0N-90 audiometry
           situations. The head shadow effect is the difference in the Speech Reception Threshold
           (SRT) due to diffraction effect of the physical sound wave.

        -  Binaural benefit which is the difference between S0N0 situation after and before
           surgery.

      The binaural benefit is the SRT gain of both ear with same threshold comparing to a gap of
      threshold between the two ears.

      The patients will also filled two questionnaires of quality of life: Abbreviated Profile of
      Hearing Aid Benefit (APHAB) and Speech and Spatial Questionnaire (SSQ).

      The aim is to show the benefit of the surgery in otosclerosis for comprehension in noise.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 6, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 11, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 11, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational [Patient Registry]</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <target_duration>9 Months</target_duration>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Measure of squelch effect 9 months after surgery</measure>
    <time_frame>9 months</time_frame>
    <description>Speech reception threshold between S0N90 situation after and before surgery</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Measure of shadow effect 9 months after surgery</measure>
    <time_frame>9 months</time_frame>
    <description>Comparison of Speech reception threshold between (S0N90) - (S0N-90) between 9months after surgery and before surgery</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Measure of binaural benefit 9 months after surgery</measure>
    <time_frame>9 months</time_frame>
    <description>Comparison of Speech reception threshold S0N0 between 9months after surgery and before surgery</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>improving quality of life : Abbreviated Profile of Hearing Aid Benefit</measure>
    <time_frame>9 months</time_frame>
    <description>comparison of the global score and the four sub-scales: &quot;aversiveness&quot;; &quot;reverberation&quot;; &quot;background noise&quot;; &quot;ease of communication&quot; between 3 months after surgery and before surgery</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Improving quality of life : Speech and Spatial Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>9 months</time_frame>
    <description>comparison of the global score and the three sub-scale: &quot;speech hearing&quot;; &quot;spatial hearing&quot;; &quot;qualities of hearing&quot;</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Measure of squelch effect 3 months after surgery</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Speech reception threshold between S0N90 situation after and before surgery</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Measure of binaural benefit 3 months after surgery</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Comparison of Speech reception threshold S0N0 between 3 months after surgery and before surgery</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Measure of shadow effect 3 months after surgery</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Comparison of Speech reception threshold between (S0N90) - (S0N-90) between 3 months after surgery and before surgery</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>improving quality of life : Abbreviated Profile of Hearing Aid Benefit</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>comparison of the global score and the four sub-scale: &quot;aversiveness&quot;; &quot;reverberation&quot;; &quot;background noise&quot;; &quot;ease of communication&quot; between 3 months after surgery and before surgery</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Improving quality of life : Speech and Spatial Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>comparison of the global score and the three sub-scale: &quot;speech hearing&quot;; &quot;spatial hearing&quot;; &quot;qualities of hearing&quot; between 3 months after surgery and before surgery</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">25</enrollment>
  <condition>Otosclerosis of Middle Ear</condition>
  <condition>Unilateral Hearing Loss</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>stapedectomy</intervention_name>
    <description>Stapedectomy as described in literature with stapes removal, Carbon Dioxide (CO2) laser platinectomy and placement of a prothesis(piston) between the incus long process and the stapes footplate</description>
    <other_name>platinectomy</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        All the patients undergoing a stapedectomy for unilateral disabled ear due to otosclerosis
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  diagnosis of otosclerosis

          -  controlateral audiometry under 30dB loss

          -  the ear to be operated with a transmission over 30dB

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  otosclerosis which has already operated on the ear studied

          -  other cause of transmission hypoacusis

          -  transmission after surgery other 30dB
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Hospital Grenoble</name>
      <address>
        <city>Grenoble</city>
        <state>Rhone Alpes Auvergne</state>
        <zip>38000</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rudic M, Keogh I, Wagner R, Wilkinson E, Kiros N, Ferrary E, Sterkers O, Bozorg Grayeli A, Zarkovic K, Zarkovic N. The pathophysiology of otosclerosis: Review of current research. Hear Res. 2015 Dec;330(Pt A):51-6. doi: 10.1016/j.heares.2015.07.014. Epub 2015 Aug 12. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26276418</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Vasama JP, Linthicum FH Jr. Temporal bone histopathology case of the month: otosclerosis. Am J Otol. 1998 May;19(3):398-9.</citation>
    <PMID>9596194</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Veillon F, Riehm S, Emachescu B, Haba D, Roedlich MN, Greget M, Tongio J. Imaging of the windows of the temporal bone. Semin Ultrasound CT MR. 2001 Jun;22(3):271-80. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>11451100</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chole RA, McKenna M. Pathophysiology of otosclerosis. Otol Neurotol. 2001 Mar;22(2):249-57. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>11300278</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wegner I, van Waes AM, Bittermann AJ, Buitinck SH, Dekker CF, Kurk SA, Rados M, Grolman W. A Systematic Review of the Diagnostic Value of CT Imaging in Diagnosing Otosclerosis. Otol Neurotol. 2016 Jan;37(1):9-15. doi: 10.1097/MAO.0000000000000924. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26649602</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gros A, Vatovec J, Sereg-Bahar M. Histologic changes on stapedial footplate in otosclerosis. Correlations between histologic activity and clinical findings. Otol Neurotol. 2003 Jan;24(1):43-7.</citation>
    <PMID>12544027</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Husain Q, Lin KF, Selesnick SH. Stapes prosthesis length and hearing outcomes. Laryngoscope. 2018 Mar;128(3):722-726. doi: 10.1002/lary.26700. Epub 2017 May 31.</citation>
    <PMID>28561306</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fayad JN, Semaan MT, Meier JC, House JW. Hearing results using the SMart piston prosthesis. Otol Neurotol. 2009 Dec;30(8):1122-7. doi: 10.1097/MAO.0b013e3181be645d.</citation>
    <PMID>19816231</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Avan P, Giraudet F, Büki B. Importance of binaural hearing. Audiol Neurootol. 2015;20 Suppl 1:3-6. doi: 10.1159/000380741. Epub 2015 May 19. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25998698</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Weiss R, Leinung M, Baumann U, Weißgerber T, Rader T, Stöver T. Improvement of speech perception in quiet and in noise without decreasing localization abilities with the bone conduction device Bonebridge. Eur Arch Otorhinolaryngol. 2017 May;274(5):2107-2115. doi: 10.1007/s00405-016-4434-2. Epub 2016 Dec 28.</citation>
    <PMID>28032241</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gartrell BC, Jones HG, Kan A, Buhr-Lawler M, Gubbels SP, Litovsky RY. Investigating long-term effects of cochlear implantation in single-sided deafness: a best practice model for longitudinal assessment of spatial hearing abilities and tinnitus handicap. Otol Neurotol. 2014 Oct;35(9):1525-32. doi: 10.1097/MAO.0000000000000437.</citation>
    <PMID>25158615</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schleich P, Nopp P, D'Haese P. Head shadow, squelch, and summation effects in bilateral users of the MED-EL COMBI 40/40+ cochlear implant. Ear Hear. 2004 Jun;25(3):197-204.</citation>
    <PMID>15179111</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jansen S, Luts H, Wagener KC, Kollmeier B, Del Rio M, Dauman R, James C, Fraysse B, Vormès E, Frachet B, Wouters J, van Wieringen A. Comparison of three types of French speech-in-noise tests: a multi-center study. Int J Audiol. 2012 Mar;51(3):164-73. doi: 10.3109/14992027.2011.633568. Epub 2011 Nov 28.</citation>
    <PMID>22122354</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>De Seta E, Rispoli G, Balsamo G, Covelli E, De Seta D, Filipo R. Indication for surgery in otosclerotic patients with unilateral hearing loss. Otol Neurotol. 2009 Dec;30(8):1116-21. doi: 10.1097/MAO.0b013e3181bc3c22.</citation>
    <PMID>19752765</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 4, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 3, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 16, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 24, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 24, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 25, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hearing Loss</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Otosclerosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hearing Loss, Unilateral</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

