<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03581136</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>STU 042018-083</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03581136</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Phase II Multi-center Trial Evaluating 5 Fraction Stereotactic Partial Breast Irradiation Using Gammapod</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase II Multi-center Trial Evaluating 5 Fraction S-PBI (Stereotactic Partial Breast Irradiation) for Early Stage Breast Cancer Using the GammaPod</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Texas Southwestern Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Texas Southwestern Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>Yes</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Stereotactic radiation has been implemented more than 3 decades ago, initially to radiate
      benign and later malignant tumors within the brain. Doses up to 24 Gy in one session have
      been used. Hundreds of thousands of patients have been treated worldwide with very good
      outcomes . Over the last decade, the stereotactic radiation techniques have been implemented
      to treat extra-cranial tumors. The challenges of extra cranial tumors were in part target
      motion during the radiation session, but also accurate re positioning of the patient and of
      the target volume at time of radiation treatment. Specific immobilization devices are now
      available to improve accuracy of target localization. Stereotactic radiation therapy is
      widely available, non-invasive for the patient and less operator dependent as the planning
      process (from target volume to dose calculation) can be done and verified by different
      operators through a quality assessment procedure. Stereotactic radiation is a complex type of
      3D CRT that is a very attractive technique making the 3D CRT more conformal and more accurate
      delivery of the prescription dose within the target volume with a very good sparing of
      surrounding normal tissue. The principles of stereotactic radiation are the following:
      precise image definition of target volume and OARs, very conformal radiation treatment.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The GammaPod is a new external beam radiotherapy device dedicated for stereotactic
      radiotherapy of breast cancer (Xcision Medical Systems, LLC, Columbia, Maryland). The design
      goal of the GammaPod has been the ability to deliver ablative doses with sharp gradients
      under stereotactic image guidance. Highly focused radiation is achieved at the isocenter due
      to the cross-firing from 36 radiation arcs generated by rotating 36 individual Cobalt-60
      beams.In order to immobilize the breast during imaging and treatment and in order to get a
      stereotactic localization of the breast target volume, a vacuum-assisted breast
      immobilization cup with built-in stereotactic frame is used. The patient can be imaged on a
      CT or MRI wearing the vacuum-assisted breast cup and then be transferred to the GammaPod for
      treatment. Then, the planner is required to delineate the gross tumor volume (GTV) and its
      subclinical extensions. Multiple targets within a breast are allowed.Different doses can be
      prescribed to different targets.One benefit of using the GammaPod over the cyberknife for
      breast SBRT, is elimination of the need for internal gold fiducial markers, which are
      required for the cyberknife treatment.

      Using a stereotactic technique for APBI allows smaller margins in comparison to a 3DCRT
      technique. The total expansions on the RAPID trial (3DCRT APBI) were 1.0 cm CTV expansion on
      the lumpectomy cavity and an additional 1.0 cm for PTV, for a total expansion of 2.0 cm. As a
      3DCRT technique was used on the RAPID trial limited number of radiation beams were employed,
      no Intensity Modulated Radiation Techniques allowed, and the margins used to create a PTV
      were relatively large (total margin 2 cm).

      As the GammaPod will allow us to minimize the volume of normal breast being irradiated, and
      decrease the PTV volume we hypothesize that a stereotactic technique with the GammaPod will
      allow us to improve on the 3 year global cosmesis rates (physician and patient) reported in
      the RAPID trial (3DCRT) by 40% despite 5 daily fractions of SBRT (in contrast to 38.5Gy/10
      fractions 3DCRT BID on the RAPID trial) The GammaPod was FDA approved 12-2017.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">April 22, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 28, 2030</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 25, 2028</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Health-Related Quality of Life (HRQOL) Analysis</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <description>The quality of life questionnaire will be used as a standardized instrument to measure the health outcome.Its provides a simple descriptive profile and a single index value for health status. The US version of the EQ-5D will be used, to enable mapping of general HR-QOL scores from EQ-5D scores into health state utility scores (ranging from 0 to 100) for the US population.Analyses will be performed for all subjects having received at least one fraction of radiation.The study will use the CTCAE version 4.0 for reporting of acute and late adverse events related to breast will be reported by the physician through exam/assessment during research visit, encompassing events since last research visit. Research will collect and log breast related events for up to 5 years.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluation of Cosmesis</measure>
    <time_frame>3Years</time_frame>
    <description>Photographs of both breasts will be taken and cosmesis will be graded by the patient, and the radiation oncologist using the EORTC scale at baseline, and twelve months from the start of therapy and at yearly intervals thereafter up to 3 years after treatment. Digital Photographs will be evaluated using the BCCT.core proprietary software developed by INESC Porto Breast Research Group (50-51) and an independent panel. Cosmesis forms using the EORTC scale will be completed by both physician and patient</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Breast Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Prescription Isodose Surface Coverage</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The dose fractionation to the CTV (1cm expansion on cavity) will be 40Gy/ 5 fractions and the PTV (3 mm expansion of CTV) will be a minimum dose of 30Gy/5 fractions.
Isodose value to which treatment dose is prescribed is usually between 65-85%, but should be greater than 50%.Optional and up to investigator -If PTV &gt;125cc can prescribe CTV (1.0cm) to 35Gy/5 fractions and PTV (3mm) to 30Gy/5 fractions. This is to potentially reduce risk of fat necrosis</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Dose Fractionation</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients will receive 5 fractions of radiation. These should not be on consecutive days. At least 40 hours between each fraction and a maximum of 15 days to complete, i.e.: Tuesday, Thursday, Monday, Wednesday, Friday.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Prescription Isodose Surface Coverage</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Women who satisfy all of the following conditions will be eligible for this study.

        1 DCIS or invasive ductal, medullary, papillary, mucinous (colloid), or tubular histologies
        2. Age ≥ 18 years. 3. ECOG Performance status 0-2 4. Women of child-bearing potential must
        agree to use adequate contraception (barrier method of birth control- condom or diaphragm
        and spermicidal foam; intrauterine device, prescription birth control pills, or abstinence)
        prior to study entry, for the duration of study participation, and for 90 days following
        completion of therapy. Should a woman become pregnant or suspect she is pregnant while
        participating in this study, she should inform her treating physician immediately.

        5. A female of child-bearing potential is any woman (regardless of sexual orientation,
        having undergone a tubal ligation, or remaining celibate by choice) who meets the following
        criteria:

          -  Has not undergone a hysterectomy or bilateral oophorectomy; or

          -  Has not been naturally postmenopausal for at least 12 consecutive months (i.e., has
             had menses at any time in the preceding 12 consecutive months).

             6. Appropriate staging studies identifying as AJCC stage Tis, or T1-T2, N0 (N0i+). The
             tumor size must be 3 cm or less.

             7. Surgical treatment of the breast with lumpectomy with histologically confirmed
             margins free of tumor (no ink on margin) for invasive disease, and at least 2mm for
             Ductal Carcinoma In Situ.. (Re-excision of margins is permitted).

             8. Gross disease within the breast must be unifocal. (Patients with microscopic
             multifocality are eligible as long as the total extent of tumor, gross and
             microscopic, occupies a volume with greatest dimension 3 cm or less).

             9. Patients with invasive disease are required to have axillary staging including:
             sentinel node biopsy or axillary dissection. Patients with DCIS are not required to
             have axillary staging.

             10. The target lumpectomy cavity must be clearly delineated or clips can be placed at
             time of surgery to delineate cavity.

             11. If adjuvant chemotherapy is planned after SPBI, it must begin no earlier than two
             weeks following completion of radiation. Delivery of SPBI can be done prior to
             adjuvant chemotherapy or after adjuvant chemotherapy. If SPBI radiation planned after
             chemotherapy, a minimum of three weeks after chemotherapy, prior to start of radiation
             is recommended.

             12. Ability to understand and the willingness to sign a written informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Men are not eligible for this study.

          2. T2(&gt;3.0 cm), T3, N1, stage III, or stage IV breast cancer

          3. Positive non-axillary sentinel lymph nodes or evidence of suspicious supraclavicular,
             infraclavicular, or internal mammary lymph nodes by imaging or physical exam, unless
             biopsied and found to be negative for tumor.

          4. Evidence by physical examination or mammography of other suspicious masses, densities,
             or microcalcifications in either breast, unless biopsied and found to be benign.

          5. Patients with non-epithelial breast malignancies such as sarcoma or lymphoma are
             excluded.

          6. Multicentric gross breast carcinoma (either DCIS or invasive cancer) or microscopic
             breast carcinoma occupying a volume with maximum dimensions of more than 3
             centimeters.

          7. Paget's disease of the nipple.

          8. Previous thoracic or breast radiation on ipsilateral side. Contralateral breast
             radiation is not excluded.

          9. Treatment plan that includes ipsilateral whole breast or ipsilateral regional nodal
             irradiation.

         10. Any prior treatment with radiation, endocrine therapy, or chemotherapy (in the
             neoadjuvant setting) for currently diagnosed breast cancer prior to GammaPod
             treatment- adjuvant chemotherapy is acceptable.

         11. Patients with active collagen vascular disease, specifically dermatomyositis with a
             CPK level above normal or active skin rash, systemic lupus erythematosis, or
             scleroderma

         12. Uncontrolled intercurrent illness including, but not limited to, ongoing or active
             infection, symptomatic congestive heart failure, unstable angina pectoris, cardiac
             arrhythmia, immunosuppressed patients or psychiatric illness/social situations that
             would limit compliance with study requirements.

         13. Subjects must not be pregnant or nursing due to the potential for congenital
             abnormalities and the potential of this regimen to harm nursing infants.

         14. If the lumpectomy cavity is completely outside of the vacuum assisted breast cup, then
             patient should not be treated on the GammaPod secondary to concerns of
             reproducibility.

         15. Transplant patients or any patients on immunosuppressive therapy
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <gender_based>Yes</gender_based>
    <gender_description>Men are not eligible for this study.</gender_description>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>99 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Asal Rahimi, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>UT Southwestern Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Asal Rahimi, MD</last_name>
    <phone>214-645-8525</phone>
    <email>Asal.rahimi@utsouthwestern.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Sarmistha Sen, MS</last_name>
    <phone>214-645-1477</phone>
    <email>Sarmistha.Sen@UTSouthwestern.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Maryland Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21201</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Elizabeth, Nichols, MD</last_name>
      <phone>410-328-6080</phone>
      <email>enichols1@umm.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UT Southwestern Medical Centre</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dallas</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>75390</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Asal Rahimi, MD</last_name>
      <phone>214-645-8556</phone>
      <email>Asal.Rahimi@UTSouthwestern.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 6, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 6, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 10, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 17, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 17, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 21, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

