<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03580538</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>44443915.5.0000.5515</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03580538</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Training With Elastic Tubing in Cardiopaths: Clinical Trial</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Short-term Effects of a Resistive Training Program Using Elastic Tubing in Cardiac Patients: Clinical Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Universidade Estadual Paulista Júlio de Mesquita Filho</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Universidade Estadual Paulista Júlio de Mesquita Filho</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background: Resistance training is effective in cardiac rehabilitation; however, other types
      of training, such as elastic tubing, are rarely used and may present good therapeutic
      alternatives. Due to its practicality and cost effectiveness, training using elastic tubing
      may become an important tool in cardiovascular rehabilitation. Objective: To evaluate
      muscular strength, functional capacity, aerobic capacity and quality of life in patients with
      cardiovascular diseases in phase II of rehabilitation, after resistance training with elastic
      tubing. Methods: patients with cardiovascular diseases performed training with elastic tubing
      for six weeks, twice a week and the load was progressively increased every 15 days. The
      following muscle groups were evaluated and trained: shoulder abductors and flexors, elbow
      flexors, and knee flexors and extensors. Muscular strength was evaluated using a dynamometer;
      functional capacity with a 6-minute walk test and ergospirometric test; and quality of life
      using the SF-36 questionnaire. Data normality was assessed using the Shapiro Wilk test.
      Comparisons before and after training were performed using the paired Student's t test or the
      Wilcoxon test (p &lt;5%).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 5, 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">July 30, 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 20, 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline Muscular Strength at 6 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>The evaluation of muscular strength was performed at the start of the intervention protocol and after 6 weeks.</time_frame>
    <description>The evaluation of muscular strength was performed at the start of the intervention protocol and after 6 weeks, using a digital force gauge, brand Force Gauge®, model FG-100kg - United States, and all results were expressed in Newtons (N). The evaluation was performed with the dominant member of each patient, using a steel cord coated with rigid plastic attached to a dynamometer, with one end attached to a fixed bar and the other end to the distal portion of the dominant member of the patient</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline Functional Capacity at 6 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>was performed at the start of the intervention protocol and after 6 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The evaluation of functional capacity was carried out through the 6-minute walk test (6MWT). The 6MWT followed the criteria established by the American Thoracic Society15. The test was performed in a gym hall at Oeste Paulista University, Presidente Prudente/SP-Brazil, and was repeated twice with an interval of 30 minutes between attempts and the highest value was taken into account, during the test Standardized verbal performance incentives were given every minute. During the 6MWT was measured blood pressure, oximetry, perception subjective of effort, heart and respiratory rate.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline Evaluation of maximal aerobic capacity at 6 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>was performed at the start of the intervention protocol and after 6 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The patients underwent a cardiopulmonary test performed by a cardiologist. All tests were performed on a treadmill (Inbrasport ATL 2000). The modified Bruce protocol16 was used and the test performed until voluntary exhaustion. No patient presented alterations in the electrocardiogram that prevented the realization and completion of the test.
Cardiovascular parameters were monitored continuously: heart rate through the Polar S810i, Finland, arterial oxygen saturation using the Mindray PM 50 pulse oximeter, Brazil, and the subjective perception of effort.17 The ventilatory variables were obtained through the VO2000 gas analyzer (Medical Graphics, USA) calibrated before each test according to the manufacturer's instructions. The average air flow was used in all tests and obtained every 10 seconds, Aerograph®, Michigan, USA.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline Evaluation of quality of life at 6 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>was performed at the start of the intervention protocol and after 6 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The quality of life of these patients was assessed using the generic quality of life evaluation questionnaire SF-36, validated in Brazil, which has eight dimensions that are scored from 0 to 100. For each dimension, values greater than 50 are positive in relation to a good perception of quality of life</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">13</enrollment>
  <condition>Resistance Training</condition>
  <condition>Muscular Strength</condition>
  <condition>Cardiovascular Diseases</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>elastic tube group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>resistive exercise with elastic tube</intervention_name>
    <description>performed training with elastic tubing for six weeks, twice a week and the load was progressively increased every 15 days.</description>
    <arm_group_label>elastic tube group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients of both sexes

          -  Aged between 45-79 years

          -  Clinical diagnosis of heart disease (coronary artery disease, postoperative myocardial
             revascularization, acute myocardial infarction)

          -  In phase II of CRP for at least three months

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients hemodynamically unstable

          -  Patients with changes in medication for a minimum of 30 days

          -  Patients who presented arteriopathies, neurological, muscular or orthopedic disorders,
             such as rheumatism and unstable heart disease that could be detected by
             electrocardiogram, and lung diseases.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <verification_date>June 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 14, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 6, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 9, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 6, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 6, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 9, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Universidade Estadual Paulista Júlio de Mesquita Filho</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Mayara Moura Alves da Cruz</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>physiotherapist</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cardiovascular Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

