<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03586687</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>00008490</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03586687</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Osteoarthritis Shoulder Injection Study</brief_title>
  <official_title>Clinical Outcomes Following Randomization of Steroid Concentration in Patients With Glenohumeral Osteoarthritis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Milton S. Hershey Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Milton S. Hershey Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to determine the most effective intraarticular steroid dose for
      the treatment of glenohumeral osteoarthritis. The investigators aim to randomize patients
      into low, medium, and high dose groups of injectable corticosteroids as these doses are
      typically used in the standard of care for our patients. To date there has been no study to
      evaluate which dose is most efficient with the fewest side effects for glenohumeral
      osteoarthritis. The investigators objective will be to provide ultrasound guided
      intraarticular glenohumeral injections of these randomized concentrations and to evaluate
      pain and function before and following injection with the Shoulder Pain and Disability Index
      (SPADI). The investigators hypothesize that the low dose steroid will provide equivalent
      improvement of the pain and function to the medium and high doses, while minimizing side
      effects.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Osteoarthritis (OA) affects 54.4 million US adults and 23.7 million (43.5%) have
      arthritis-attributable activity limitation. As the condition progresses, pain and functional
      disability increase. Patients usually begin treatment with conservative measures including
      physical therapy and administration of nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs before obtaining
      a corticosteroid injection. Corticosteroid injections have a patient-specific duration that
      often provide relief for a month before the effects begin to taper with most individuals
      returning to baseline by 2-3 months post injection.

      Unfortunately, data on intraarticular injections is not robust and primarily focused on hip,
      knee, and disease processes rather than the glenohumeral joint. For example, steroid
      concentrations have been studied in adhesive capsulitis, where 20 and 40mg of triamcinolone
      acenotide were used with no statistical significance between the two. When a placebo was
      added, both doses were better than the placebo, but once again no difference was seen between
      the two steroid concentrations. Another study, looking at knee osteoarthritis, found that
      high dose steroids had a larger effect on duration, but other studies have shown no
      difference in duration between the 40mg and 80mg concentration of triamcinolone acetonide.

      Intraarticular injections do have adverse effects. Similar to steroids taken orally or
      intravenously, intraarticular injections have a similar side effect profile. Fortunately,
      intraarticular injections are localized, by the nature of the procedure, and the chances of
      experiencing a significant side effect is rare. The most common side effects are steroid
      flare, allergic reaction, facial erythema, hypo-pigmentation, fat pad necrosis, cutaneous
      atrophy, and a transient increase in blood glucose. Some of the rare side effects have been
      seen in case reports include idiopathic central serous chorioretinopathy, decrease in breast
      milk production, sepsis, tendon rupture, and cataracts. In addition, the administration of
      steroid injections are limited to being done every three months due to risk of weakening
      tendons, and acceleration of cartilage loss.

      There is a void of literature for understating the ideal injectable steroid concentrations in
      glenohumeral osteoarthritis. Because of this, providers who perform intraarticular injections
      tend to perform them based on prior training experience or anecdotal evidence. We aim to
      evaluate the ideal steroid concentration that will maximize treatment effect for glenohumeral
      osteoarthritis, but at the same time minimize side effects, and better train our future
      providers.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 13, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 30, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 30, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Overall SPADI scores at baseline compared to 2,4, and 6 months.</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 2, 4, and 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>The Shoulder Pain and Disability Index (SPADI) measures current shoulder pain and disability using a 13 item assessment. Scores range from 0-100 with higher scores indicating greater impairment or disability</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Assess reactions to the steroid</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 2, 4, and 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Adverse events will only include those that are determined to be related to steroid</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of Shoulder Arthroplasty following injection</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Shoulder arthroplasty is defined as total shoulder replacement</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in overall SPADI scores for those receiving Shoulder Arthroplasty at 1 year</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>The Shoulder Pain and Disability Index (SPADI) measures current shoulder pain and disability using a 13 item assessment. Scores range from 0-100 with higher scores indicating greater impairment or disability</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">171</enrollment>
  <condition>Glenohumeral Osteoarthritis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>20 mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>20mg Triamcinolone with 3cc of 1% Lidocaine</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>40 mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>40mg Triamcinolone with 3cc of 1% Lidocaine</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>80 mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>80mg Triamcinolone with 3cc of 1% Lidocaine</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Triamcinolone</intervention_name>
    <description>Ultrasound guided glenohumeral shoulder joint injection</description>
    <arm_group_label>20 mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>40 mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>80 mg</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  An X-ray within a year with Radiographic evidence of OA

          -  18 years of age or older

          -  Clinical diagnosis established due to symptoms that will include pain attributed to
             glenohumeral osteoarthritis, pain with range of motion, and/or functional limitations
             longer than 3 months.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Previous guided steroid injection of the glenohumeral joint within 3 months

          -  Previous diagnosis of inflammatory arthritis, rotator cuff tear, or immunocompromised

          -  Previous shoulder surgery

          -  Allergy to steroid or lidocaine

          -  A Kellgren and Lawrence classification of 1 or less on radiograph

          -  Non-English Speaking

          -  Inability to provide informed consent
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Cayce Onks, DO</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Penn State Hershey Medical Cen</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Milton S. Hershey Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hershey</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>17033</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Barbour KE, Helmick CG, Boring M, Brady TJ. Vital Signs: Prevalence of Doctor-Diagnosed Arthritis and Arthritis-Attributable Activity Limitation - United States, 2013-2015. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep. 2017 Mar 10;66(9):246-253. doi: 10.15585/mmwr.mm6609e1.</citation>
    <PMID>28278145</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>McAlindon TE, Bannuru RR, Sullivan MC, Arden NK, Berenbaum F, Bierma-Zeinstra SM, Hawker GA, Henrotin Y, Hunter DJ, Kawaguchi H, Kwoh K, Lohmander S, Rannou F, Roos EM, Underwood M. OARSI guidelines for the non-surgical management of knee osteoarthritis. Osteoarthritis Cartilage. 2014 Mar;22(3):363-88. doi: 10.1016/j.joca.2014.01.003. Epub 2014 Jan 24.</citation>
    <PMID>24462672</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Godwin M, Dawes M. Intra-articular steroid injections for painful knees. Systematic review with meta-analysis. Can Fam Physician. 2004 Feb;50:241-8. Review. Erratum in: Can Fam Physician. 2009 Jun;55(6):590.</citation>
    <PMID>15000335</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Arroll B, Goodyear-Smith F. Corticosteroid injections for osteoarthritis of the knee: meta-analysis. BMJ. 2004 Apr 10;328(7444):869. Epub 2004 Mar 23.</citation>
    <PMID>15039276</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gaujoux-Viala C, Dougados M, Gossec L. Efficacy and safety of steroid injections for shoulder and elbow tendonitis: a meta-analysis of randomised controlled trials. Ann Rheum Dis. 2009 Dec;68(12):1843-9. doi: 10.1136/ard.2008.099572. Epub 2008 Dec 3. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19054817</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kim YS, Lee HJ, Lee DH, Choi KY. Comparison of high- and low-dose intra-articular triamcinolone acetonide injection for treatment of primary shoulder stiffness: a prospective randomized trial. J Shoulder Elbow Surg. 2017 Feb;26(2):209-215. doi: 10.1016/j.jse.2016.09.034. Epub 2016 Nov 30.</citation>
    <PMID>27914846</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yoon SH, Lee HY, Lee HJ, Kwack KS. Optimal dose of intra-articular corticosteroids for adhesive capsulitis: a randomized, triple-blind, placebo-controlled trial. Am J Sports Med. 2013 May;41(5):1133-9. doi: 10.1177/0363546513480475. Epub 2013 Mar 18.</citation>
    <PMID>23507791</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Popma JW, Snel FW, Haagsma CJ, Brummelhuis-Visser P, Oldenhof HG, van der Palen J, van de Laar MA. Comparison of 2 Dosages of Intraarticular Triamcinolone for the Treatment of Knee Arthritis: Results of a 12-week Randomized Controlled Clinical Trial. J Rheumatol. 2015 Oct;42(10):1865-8. doi: 10.3899/jrheum.141630. Epub 2015 Aug 1.</citation>
    <PMID>26233499</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Intra-articular injections for osteoarthritis of the knee. Med Lett Drugs Ther. 2006 Mar 27;48(1231):25-7.</citation>
    <PMID>16554699</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Smuin DM, Seidenberg PH, Sirlin EA, Phillips SF, Silvis ML. Rare Adverse Events Associated with Corticosteroid Injections: A Case Series and Literature Review. Curr Sports Med Rep. 2016 May-Jun;15(3):171-6. doi: 10.1249/JSR.0000000000000259. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>27172081</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>McAlindon TE, LaValley MP, Harvey WF, Price LL, Driban JB, Zhang M, Ward RJ. Effect of Intra-articular Triamcinolone vs Saline on Knee Cartilage Volume and Pain in Patients With Knee Osteoarthritis: A Randomized Clinical Trial. JAMA. 2017 May 16;317(19):1967-1975. doi: 10.1001/jama.2017.5283.</citation>
    <PMID>28510679</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kegel G, Marshall A, Barron OA, Catalano LW, Glickel SZ, Kuhn M. Steroid injections in the upper extremity: experienced clinical opinion versus evidence-based practices. Orthopedics. 2013 Sep;36(9):e1141-8. doi: 10.3928/01477447-20130821-15.</citation>
    <PMID>24025004</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 21, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 2, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 13, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 10, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 10, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 13, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Milton S. Hershey Medical Center</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Cayce Onks</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor of Family and Community Medicine and Orthopedics and Rehabilitation</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Ultrasound guided injection</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Osteoarthritis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Triamcinolone</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

