<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03582475</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>18-000435</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2018-01120</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>18-000435</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03582475</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Pembrolizumab With Combination Chemotherapy in Treating Participants With Locally Advanced or Metastatic Small Cell/Neuroendocrine Cancers of Urothelium or Prostate</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase Ib Trial of Pembrolizumab (MK-3475) With Platinum-Based Chemotherapy in Small Cell/Neuroendocrine Cancers of Urothelium and Prostate</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Jonsson Comprehensive Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Merck Sharp &amp; Dohme Corp.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Jonsson Comprehensive Cancer Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>Yes</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This phase Ib trial studies how well pembrolizumab works with combination chemotherapy in
      treating participants with small cell/neuroendocrine cancers of the urothelium or prostate
      that has spread to nearby tissue or lymph nodes or that has spread to other places in the
      body. Monoclonal antibodies, such as pembrolizumab, may interfere with the ability of tumor
      cells to grow and spread. Drugs used in chemotherapy, such as etoposide, docetaxel,
      cisplatin, and carboplatin, work in different ways to stop the growth of tumor cells, either
      by killing the cells, by stopping them from dividing, or by stopping them from spreading.
      Giving pembrolizumab with platinum-based chemotherapy may work better in treating
      participants with small cell/neuroendocrine cancers of the urothelium or prostate.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PRIMARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To evaluate the preliminary efficacy of pembrolizumab (MK-3475) in combination with
      standard-of-care cisplatin-based chemotherapy by assessing the durable response rate (DRR),
      overall response rate (ORR), duration of response (DOR), and progression free survival (PFS)
      by Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors (RECIST) 1.1 and overall survival (OS) in
      Cohorts 1 and 2, and radiographic PFS (rPFS) by Prostate Cancer Working Group 3 (PCWG3) and
      prostate-specific antigen (PSA) response in Cohort 2.

      SECONDARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To determine the safety and tolerability of pembrolizumab in combination with etoposide
      and cisplatin/carboplatin or docetaxel and carboplatin assessed by parameters of adverse
      events (AEs).

      EXPLORATORY OBJECTIVES:

      I. Determine correlation of biomarkers including PD-L1 expression (PD-L1 positive &gt;= 1% by
      immunohistochemistry [IHC] using 22C3 antibody), and serum and tissue molecular (including
      genomic, proteomic) biomarkers that may be indicative of clinic response or safety.

      OUTLINE:

      Participants receive pembrolizumab intravenously (IV) over 30 minutes on day 1. Courses
      repeat every 3 weeks for 2 years in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable
      toxicity. Participants also receive standard of care chemotherapy comprising either etoposide
      IV on days 1-3 and cisplatin IV or carboplatin IV on day 1 (Cohort 1), or etoposide IV on
      days 1-3, carboplatin IV on day 1, and docetaxel IV on day 1 (Cohort 2). Treatment repeats
      every 3 weeks for up to 6 courses in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable
      toxicity.

      After completion of study treatment, participants are followed up at 30 days, every 9-12
      weeks for up to 2 years, and then every 12 weeks thereafter.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">December 20, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 1, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 1, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Durable response rate (DRR) (Cohorts 1 and 2)</measure>
    <time_frame>At 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>The statistical analyses will be primarily descriptive and exploratory. The proportional data (DRR) will be summarized using 95% 2-sided exact binomial confidence intervals (CIs).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall response rate (ORR) per Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors (RECIST) 1.1 (Cohorts 1 and 2)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 3 years</time_frame>
    <description>ORR will be determined as the proportion of subjects who have a complete response (CR) or partial response (PR).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of response (DOR) per RECIST 1.1 (Cohorts 1 and 2)</measure>
    <time_frame>From the first documented CR or PR up to 3 years</time_frame>
    <description>DOR will be defined as the time from the first documented CR or PR until radiograph disease progression or PSA progression. PSA progression will be defined as the date that an increase of 25% or more and an absolute increase of &gt;= 2 ng/ml above nadir occurs. Time-to-event data (DOR) will be summarized by cohort using the Kaplan-Meier method. Kaplan-Meier estimates of event rates at landmark time points (e.g., 3-,6-, and 12-months) and median time to the event will be presented with the corresponding 95% CIs.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression-free survival per Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors (RECIST) 1.1 (Cohorts 1 and 2)</measure>
    <time_frame>Time from the first day of study treatment up to 3 years</time_frame>
    <description>PFS will be defined as the time from the first day of study treatment to first documented disease progression or PSA progression. Time-to-event data (PFS) will be summarized by cohort using the Kaplan-Meier method. Kaplan-Meier estimates of event rates at landmark time points (e.g., 3-,6-, and 12-months) and median time to the event will be presented with the corresponding 95% CIs.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival (OS) (Cohorts 1 and 2)</measure>
    <time_frame>From the first day of study treatment up to 3 years</time_frame>
    <description>OS is defined as the time from the first day of study treatment to the time of death from any cause. Time-to-event data (OS) will be summarized by cohort using the Kaplan-Meier method. Kaplan-Meier estimates of event rates at landmark time points (e.g., 3-,6-, and 12-months) and median time to the event will be presented with the corresponding 95% CIs.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Radiographic PFS (rPFS) by Prostate Cancer Working Group 3 (PCWG3) (Cohort 2)</measure>
    <time_frame>Time from the first day of study treatment up to 3 years</time_frame>
    <description>rPFS will be defined as the time from the first day of study treatment to first documented disease progression.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of adverse events per Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE) Version 4.0 (Cohorts 1 and 2)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2 years</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>PD-L1 expression biomarkers</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2 years</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Bladder Small Cell Neuroendocrine Carcinoma</condition>
  <condition>Castration-Resistant Prostate Carcinoma</condition>
  <condition>Metastatic Bladder Urothelial Carcinoma</condition>
  <condition>Metastatic Urethral Urothelial Carcinoma</condition>
  <condition>Prostate Carcinoma Metastatic in the Bone</condition>
  <condition>Prostate Neuroendocrine Neoplasm</condition>
  <condition>Prostate Small Cell Carcinoma</condition>
  <condition>Stage III Bladder Cancer AJCC v8</condition>
  <condition>Stage III Prostate Cancer AJCC v8</condition>
  <condition>Stage III Urethral Cancer AJCC v8</condition>
  <condition>Stage IV Bladder Cancer AJCC v8</condition>
  <condition>Stage IV Prostate Cancer AJCC v8</condition>
  <condition>Stage IV Urethral Cancer AJCC v8</condition>
  <condition>Stage IVA Bladder Cancer AJCC v8</condition>
  <condition>Stage IVB Bladder Cancer AJCC v8</condition>
  <condition>Ureter Small Cell Carcinoma</condition>
  <condition>Urothelial Carcinoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (pembrolizumab, platinum-based chemotherapy)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants receive pembrolizumab IV over 30 minutes on day 1. Courses repeat every 3 weeks for 2 years in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity. Participants also receive standard of care chemotherapy comprising either etoposide IV on days 1-3 and cisplatin IV or carboplatin IV on day 1 (Cohort 1), or etoposide IV on days 1-3, carboplatin IV on day 1, and docetaxel IV on day 1 (Cohort 2). Treatment repeats every 3 weeks for up to 6 courses in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Carboplatin</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (pembrolizumab, platinum-based chemotherapy)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Blastocarb</other_name>
    <other_name>Carboplat</other_name>
    <other_name>Carboplatin Hexal</other_name>
    <other_name>Carboplatino</other_name>
    <other_name>Carbosin</other_name>
    <other_name>Carbosol</other_name>
    <other_name>Carbotec</other_name>
    <other_name>CBDCA</other_name>
    <other_name>Displata</other_name>
    <other_name>Ercar</other_name>
    <other_name>JM-8</other_name>
    <other_name>Nealorin</other_name>
    <other_name>Novoplatinum</other_name>
    <other_name>Paraplatin</other_name>
    <other_name>Paraplatin AQ</other_name>
    <other_name>Paraplatine</other_name>
    <other_name>Platinwas</other_name>
    <other_name>Ribocarbo</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cisplatin</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (pembrolizumab, platinum-based chemotherapy)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Abiplatin</other_name>
    <other_name>Blastolem</other_name>
    <other_name>Briplatin</other_name>
    <other_name>CDDP</other_name>
    <other_name>Cis-diammine-dichloroplatinum</other_name>
    <other_name>Cis-diamminedichloridoplatinum</other_name>
    <other_name>Cis-diamminedichloro Platinum (II)</other_name>
    <other_name>Cis-diamminedichloroplatinum</other_name>
    <other_name>Cis-dichloroammine Platinum (II)</other_name>
    <other_name>Cis-platinous Diamine Dichloride</other_name>
    <other_name>Cis-platinum</other_name>
    <other_name>Cis-platinum II</other_name>
    <other_name>Cis-platinum II Diamine Dichloride</other_name>
    <other_name>Cismaplat</other_name>
    <other_name>Cisplatina</other_name>
    <other_name>Cisplatinum</other_name>
    <other_name>Cisplatyl</other_name>
    <other_name>Citoplatino</other_name>
    <other_name>Citosin</other_name>
    <other_name>Cysplatyna</other_name>
    <other_name>DDP</other_name>
    <other_name>Lederplatin</other_name>
    <other_name>Metaplatin</other_name>
    <other_name>Neoplatin</other_name>
    <other_name>Peyrone's Chloride</other_name>
    <other_name>Peyrone's Salt</other_name>
    <other_name>Placis</other_name>
    <other_name>Plastistil</other_name>
    <other_name>Platamine</other_name>
    <other_name>Platiblastin</other_name>
    <other_name>Platiblastin-S</other_name>
    <other_name>Platinex</other_name>
    <other_name>Platinol</other_name>
    <other_name>Platinol- AQ</other_name>
    <other_name>Platinol-AQ</other_name>
    <other_name>Platinol-AQ VHA Plus</other_name>
    <other_name>Platinoxan</other_name>
    <other_name>Platinum</other_name>
    <other_name>Platinum Diamminodichloride</other_name>
    <other_name>Platiran</other_name>
    <other_name>Platistin</other_name>
    <other_name>Platosin</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Docetaxel</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (pembrolizumab, platinum-based chemotherapy)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Docecad</other_name>
    <other_name>RP56976</other_name>
    <other_name>Taxotere</other_name>
    <other_name>Taxotere Injection Concentrate</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Etoposide</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (pembrolizumab, platinum-based chemotherapy)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Demethyl Epipodophyllotoxin Ethylidine Glucoside</other_name>
    <other_name>EPEG</other_name>
    <other_name>Lastet</other_name>
    <other_name>Toposar</other_name>
    <other_name>Vepesid</other_name>
    <other_name>VP 16-213</other_name>
    <other_name>VP-16</other_name>
    <other_name>VP-16-213</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pembrolizumab</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (pembrolizumab, platinum-based chemotherapy)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Keytruda</other_name>
    <other_name>Lambrolizumab</other_name>
    <other_name>MK-3475</other_name>
    <other_name>SCH 900475</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Histologically confirmed diagnosis of locally advanced or metastatic 1) naive small
             cell cancer of the bladder, urethra, or upper urinary tract, or 2) primary small cell
             or neuroendocrine prostate cancer will be enrolled in this study.

          -  Histological diagnosis of pure or mixed small cell or neuroendocrine cancer by a
             genitourinary pathologist is sufficient and confirmatory immunohistochemistry is not
             required.

          -  Cohort 1 will include subjects with no prior systemic chemotherapy for locally
             advanced or metastatic urothelial carcinoma, with the following exception(s):

               -  Platinum-based chemotherapy with recurrence &gt; 12 months from completion of
                  therapy is permitted.

          -  Cohort 2 will include subjects with no prior systemic chemotherapy for primary small
             cell prostate cancer, with the following exception(s):

               -  Platinum-based chemotherapy with recurrence &gt; 12 months from completion of
                  therapy is permitted.

          -  Cohort 2 will include subjects with prior treatments for metastatic
             castration-resistant prostate cancer (mCRPC) including:

               -  Prior chemotherapy with 2 other agents is allowed if &gt; 6 months elapsed from last
                  dose (if docetaxel chemotherapy is used more than once for hormone-sensitive and
                  for mCRPC it will be considered 1 therapy).

               -  Ongoing androgen deprivation therapy with up to 2 second-generation hormonal
                  manipulations (e.g. including but not limited to abiraterone acetate and/or
                  enzalutamide).

               -  Ongoing treatment with for bone metastasis (e.g. denosumab or zoledronic acid) is
                  permitted.

               -  Prior immunotherapy with sipuleucel-T is allowed if completed &gt; 4 weeks prior to
                  trial enrollment.

          -  A male participant must agree to use contraception during the treatment period and for
             at least 120 days after the last dose of pembrolizumab or 180 days after chemotherapy
             and refrain from donating sperm during this period.

          -  A female participant is eligible to participate if she is not pregnant, not
             breastfeeding, and at least one of the following conditions applies:

               -  Not a woman of childbearing potential (WOCBP) or

               -  A WOCBP who agrees to follow the contraceptive guidance during the treatment
                  period and for at least 120 days after the last dose of pembrolizumab or 180 days
                  after chemotherapy.

          -  The participant (or legally acceptable representative if applicable) provides written
             informed consent for the trial.

          -  Have measurable disease based on RECIST 1.1. Lesions situated in a previously
             irradiated area are considered measurable if progression has been demonstrated in such
             lesions.

          -  Have provided archival tumor tissue sample or newly obtained core or excisional biopsy
             of a tumor lesion not previously irradiated within 6 months of screening.
             Formalin-fixed, paraffin embedded (FFPE) tissue blocks are preferred to slides. In
             addition, the availability of fresh frozen tissue is encouraged. Newly obtained
             biopsies are preferred to archival tissue.

          -  Have an Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status of 0 to 1.
             Evaluation of ECOG is to be performed within 7 days prior to the date of allocation.

          -  Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) &gt;= 1500/uL within 10 days prior to the start of study
             treatment.

          -  Platelets &gt;= 100 000/uL within 10 days prior to the start of study treatment.

          -  Hemoglobin &gt;= 9.0 g/dL or &gt;= 5.6 mmol/L within 10 days prior to the start of study
             treatment.

               -  Criteria must be met without erythropoietin dependency and without packed red
                  blood cell (pRBC) transfusion within last 2 weeks.

          -  Creatinine =&lt; 1.5 x upper limit of normal (ULN) OR measured or calculated creatinine
             clearance (glomerular filtration rate [GFR] can also be used in place of creatinine or
             creatinine clearance [CrCl]) &gt;= 30 mL/min for participant with creatinine levels &gt;1.5
             x institutional ULN within 10 days prior to the start of study treatment.

               -  Creatinine clearance (CrCl) should be calculated per institutional standard.

          -  Total bilirubin =&lt; 1.5 ?ULN or direct bilirubin =&lt; ULN for participants with total
             bilirubin levels &gt; 1.5 ? ULN within 10 days prior to the start of study treatment.

          -  Aspartate aminotransferase (AST) (serum glutamic oxaloacetic transaminase [SGOT]) and
             alanine aminotransferase (ALT) (serum glutamate pyruvate transaminase [SGPT]) =&lt; 2.5 ?
             ULN (=&lt; 5 ? ULN for participants with liver metastases) within 10 days prior to the
             start of study treatment.

          -  International normalized ratio (INR) or prothrombin time (PT) =&lt; 1.5 ? ULN unless
             participant is receiving anticoagulant therapy as long as PT or activated partial
             thromboplastin time (aPTT) is within therapeutic range of intended use of
             anticoagulants within 10 days prior to the start of study treatment.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Has disease suitable for local treatment with curative intent.

          -  A WOCBP who has a positive urine pregnancy test within 72 hours prior to receiving the
             first dose of trial medication. If the urine test is positive or cannot be confirmed
             as negative, a serum pregnancy test will be required.

          -  Has received prior therapy with an anti-PD-1, anti-PD-L1, or anti-PD-L2 agent or with
             an agent directed to another stimulatory or co-inhibitory T-cell receptor (e.g.
             CTLA-4, OX-40, CD137).

          -  Has received prior systemic anti-cancer therapy including investigational agents
             within 4 weeks prior to first dose of trial treatment.

               -  Note: Participants must have recovered from all AEs due to previous therapies to
                  =&lt; grade 1 or baseline. Participants with =&lt; grade 2 neuropathy may be eligible.

               -  Note: If participant received major surgery, they must have recovered adequately
                  from the toxicity and/or complications from the intervention prior to starting
                  study treatment.

          -  Has received prior radiotherapy within 2 weeks of start of study treatment.
             Participants must have recovered from all radiation-related toxicities, not require
             corticosteroids, and not have had radiation pneumonitis. A 1-week washout is permitted
             for palliative radiation (=&lt; 2 weeks of radiotherapy) to non-central nervous system
             (CNS) disease.

          -  Has received a live vaccine within 30 days prior to the first dose of study drug.
             Examples of live vaccines include, but are not limited to, the following: measles,
             mumps, rubella, varicella/zoster (chicken pox), yellow fever, rabies, Bacillus
             Calmette?Guerin (BCG), and typhoid vaccine. Seasonal influenza vaccines for injection
             are generally killed virus vaccines and are allowed; however, intranasal influenza
             vaccines (eg, FluMist) are live attenuated vaccines and are not allowed.

          -  Is currently participating in or has participated in a study of an investigational
             agent or has used an investigational device within 4 weeks prior to the first dose of
             study treatment.

               -  Note: Participants who have entered the follow-up phase of an investigational
                  study may participate as long as it has been 4 weeks after the last dose of the
                  previous investigational agent.

          -  Has a diagnosis of immunodeficiency or is receiving chronic systemic steroid therapy
             (in dosing exceeding 10 mg daily of prednisone equivalent) or any other form of
             immunosuppressive therapy within 7 days prior to the first dose of study drug.

          -  Has a known additional malignancy that is progressing or has required active treatment
             within the past 3 years. Note: Participants with basal cell carcinoma of the skin,
             squamous cell carcinoma of the skin, or carcinoma in situ (e.g. breast carcinoma,
             cervical cancer in situ) that have undergone potentially curative therapy are not
             excluded.

               -  For Cohort 1, a history of prostate cancer that was identified incidentally
                  following cystoprostatectomy for bladder cancer is acceptable provided that the
                  PSA is &lt; 0.2.

          -  Has known active CNS metastases and/or carcinomatous meningitis. Participants with
             previously treated brain metastases may participate provided they are radiologically
             stable, i.e. without evidence of progression for at least 4 weeks by repeat imaging
             (note that the repeat imaging should be performed during study screening), clinically
             stable and without requirement of steroid treatment for at least 14 days prior to
             first dose of study treatment.

          -  Has severe hypersensitivity (&gt;= grade 3) to pembrolizumab and/or any of its
             excipients.

          -  Has active autoimmune disease that has required systemic treatment in the past 2 years
             (i.e. with use of disease modifying agents, corticosteroids or immunosuppressive
             drugs). Replacement therapy (eg., thyroxine, insulin, or physiologic corticosteroid
             replacement therapy for adrenal or pituitary insufficiency, etc.) is not considered a
             form of systemic treatment.

          -  Has a history of (non-infectious) pneumonitis that required steroids or has current
             pneumonitis.

          -  Has an active infection requiring systemic therapy.

          -  Has a known history of human immunodeficiency virus (HIV).

          -  Has a known history of hepatitis B (defined as hepatitis B surface antigen [HBsAg]
             reactive) or known active hepatitis C virus (defined as HCV ribonucleic acid [RNA]
             [qualitative] is detected) infection. Note: no testing for hepatitis B and hepatitis C
             is required unless mandated by local health authority.

          -  Has a known history of active TB (bacillus tuberculosis).

          -  Has a history or current evidence of any condition, therapy, or laboratory abnormality
             that might confound the results of the study, interfere with the subject?s
             participation for the full duration of the study, or is not in the best interest of
             the subject to participate, in the opinion of the treating investigator.

          -  Has known psychiatric or substance abuse disorders that would interfere with
             cooperation with the requirements of the trial.

          -  Is pregnant or breastfeeding, or expecting to conceive or father children within the
             projected duration of the study, starting with the screening visit through 120 days
             after the last dose of trial treatment.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Arnold Chin</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>UCLA / Jonsson Comprehensive Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Sara Rodriguez</last_name>
    <phone>310 794-2877</phone>
    <email>sararodriguez@mednet.ucla.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UCLA / Jonsson Comprehensive Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90095</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Arnold Chin</last_name>
      <phone>310-206-6453</phone>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Arnold Chin</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 13, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 9, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 11, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 22, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 22, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 24, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Prostatic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Urinary Bladder Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Transitional Cell</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Neuroendocrine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Urethral Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Small Cell</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Small Cell Lung Carcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neuroendocrine Tumors</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cisplatin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carboplatin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Docetaxel</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Etoposide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pembrolizumab</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Etoposide phosphate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Podophyllotoxin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

