<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04049045</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ZKSJ0109</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04049045</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effects of Empagliflozin on Diuresis and Renal Function in Patients With Acute Decompensated Heart Failure</brief_title>
  <acronym>EMPAG-HF</acronym>
  <official_title>Effects of Empagliflozin on Diuresis and Renal Function in Patients With Acute Decompensated Heart Failure</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Christian Schulze</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Boehringer Ingelheim</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Zentrum für Klinische Studien Jena</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Jena University Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Heart failure is the most common hospital admission diagnosis and shows increasing incidence
      and prevalence in Germany, the United States and worldwide. Improvements in the primary
      treatment conditions for e.g. myocardial infarction and reduced primary mortality has
      resulted in an increasing group of patients with secondary cardiac abnormalities including
      chronic heart failure.

      Progressive cardiac dysfunction and failure are associated with exercise intolerance, volume
      retention, nocturia, dyspnoea among others. The most severe progression of heart failure is
      cardiac decompensation (also called: acute heart failure) and cardiogenic shock. Volume
      retention, abnormal renal function and diuretic resistance are hallmarks of this clinical
      phenotype. Currently, the only available treatment is diuresis through various combinations
      of diuretics and the addition of cardiac inotropes when cardiac hypoperfusion is documented.
      Patients with acute decompensated heart failure (ADHF) often develop a state of diuretic
      resistance characterized by a need of rising dosages of diuretics for adequate diuresis and
      urine production.

      ADHF patients also show metabolic abnormalities including insulin resistance or type 2
      diabetes mellitus.

      Empagliflozin is a potent and selective inhibitor of the sodium glucose cotransporter 2
      (SGLT2) used in the treatment of type 2 diabetes. By inhibiting SGLT2, empagliflozin reduces
      renal glucose reabsorption and increases urinary glucose excretion. In addition to reducing
      hyperglycaemia, empagliflozin is associated with osmotic diuresis, reductions in weight and
      blood pressure without increases in heart rate, and has favourable effects on markers of
      arterial stiffness and vascular resistance.

      The investigators propose a single center exploratory study to test the hypothesis that the
      application of empagliflozin in addition to standard diuretic regimens increases urine
      output, decreases the need for further acceleration of diuretic regimens, and positively
      influences renal function as well as metabolism including insulin resistance in ADHF
      patients. Thereby, empagliflozin may be effective in the prevention of complex cardio
      metabolic alterations involved in ADHF.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 29, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 30, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 30, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Single-center, prospective, double-blind, placebo-controlled, randomized and interventional exploratory study</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator)</masking>
    <masking_description>There will be two trial medications, the licensed medicinal product empagliflozin, trade name Jardiance®, 25 mg and matching placebo tablets. The placebo tablets will be indistinguishable by appearance, taste, smell, weight from the investigational product. Both will be stored in plastic containers containing 30 tablets each.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Total urinary output (UOP) as measured by daily volume summed up over 5 days</measure>
    <time_frame>5 days</time_frame>
    <description>Total UOP as summed over 5 days</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Renal function under treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>5 days</time_frame>
    <description>Change of creatinine values: increase in creatinine of &gt; 0.3 mg/dl, doubling of serum creatinine, need for renal replacement therapy</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Net fluid output</measure>
    <time_frame>5 days</time_frame>
    <description>UOP - fluid intake</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Worsening or persistent heart failure</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days</time_frame>
    <description>NYHA class (New York Heart Association functional heart failure classification)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Intermediate Care (IMC) / Intensive Care Unit (ICU) and hospital length of stay</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days</time_frame>
    <description>Duration in days</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Liver function</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days</time_frame>
    <description>bilirubin, serum aminotransferases, relevant change in coagulation status</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pulmonary function</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days</time_frame>
    <description>oxygen saturation without oxygen therapy/ need for oxygen in l/min, presence of rales, changes in chest x-ray (worsening/ improvement/ new infiltration)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of patients alive and out of hospital -after 30 days</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days</time_frame>
    <description>number of patients</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Safety Outcome: Number of Adverse Events and Serious Adverse Events including MedDRA-SAE Preferred Terms and SOCs in both groups</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days</time_frame>
    <description>Listing of all adverse events and serious adverse events, laboratory parameters as far as not efficacy parameters</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Acute Decompensated Heart Failure</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Verum arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>25 mg tablet of empagliflozin once daily for five days</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>one tablet of the matching Placebo once daily for five days</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Empagliflozin 25 mg</intervention_name>
    <description>Empagliflozin 25 mg film-coated tablets, for oral use administered once daily for 5 days in addition to routinely administered (weight adjusted) intravenous furosemide</description>
    <arm_group_label>Verum arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>matching Placebo, film-coated tablets, for oral use, matching to investigational product Jardiance® administered once daily for 5 days in addition to routinely administered (weight adjusted) intravenous furosemide</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients (age between 18-85 years) with acute decompensated heart failure (HF).

          -  Brain Natriuretic Peptide (BNP) &gt;100 pg/ml, or N-terminal pro-BNP (NT-proBNP)&gt;300
             pg/ml as defined by current clinical guidelines for the diagnosis of acute
             decompensated HF (European Society of Cardiology 2016 HF guideline)

          -  Patients with diabetes mellitus type 2 or impaired glucose tolerance as defined by
             current clinical guidelines (German and International Diabetes Society 2016: HbA1c&gt;6.5
             % (upper limit for this clinical trial 12 %) or fasting glucose &gt;7.0 mmol/l or any
             incidental glucose level &gt;11.1 mmol/l or abnormal oral glucose tolerance test with 2h
             plasma glucose &gt;7.8 mmol/l) or on antidiabetic medication or antidiabetic diet

          -  Patients without cognitive impairment, i.e. they must be capable of understanding the
             nature, significance and implications of the clinical trial and to form a rational
             intention in the light of the facts

          -  Written informed consent obtained

          -  Indication for an indwelling urinary catheter

          -  For women with childbearing potential (until 2 years after menopause):

               -  Negative pregnancy test

               -  regular and correct use of a highly effective contraceptive method with an error
                  rate of &lt;1% per year (e.g. combined (estrogen and progesteron) hormonal
                  contraception (oral, intravaginal, transdermal), progesteron-only hormonal
                  contraception (oral, injectable, implantable), intrauterine device (IUD),
                  intrauterine hormone-releasing system (IUS) tubal ligation (female
                  sterilization), hormon donating intrauterine device (&quot;hormonal spiral&quot;), double
                  barrier methods, sexual abstinence, vasectomy of the partner)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Type 1 diabetes mellitus

          -  Chronic Kidney Disease (CKD) with eGFR&lt; 30 ml/min, or end-stage renal failure with the
             need for chronic dialysis treatment

          -  Acute kidney injury (AKI) ≥ Acute Kidney Injury Network (AKIN) stage 2 or requiring
             dialysis treatment

          -  Current medication with SGLT-2 inhibitors

          -  Known intolerance or hypersensitivity to the active substance empagliflozin, lactose
             or any other of the excipients listed in section 6.1. of the summary of product
             characteristics (SmPC). A contraindication or intolerance to furosemide

          -  Acute heart failure without signs of congestion (&quot;dry&quot; patient)

          -  Indication for coronary angiography or any foreseeable administration of a contrast
             media

          -  Need for hemofiltration or any other form of extracorporeal therapy

          -  Planned surgery

          -  Previous participation in this trial or recent participation in another clinical trial
             (within the last 3 months before inclusion, so that medical product/s from previous
             trial participation/s have been fully washed out )Identification of any causes of
             heart failure leading to decompensation that needs urgent management (like acute
             coronary syndrome, severe unstable arrhythmias, mechanical causes, acute pulmonary
             embolism)

          -  Incapacity to understand and / or to provide written informed consent

          -  Ongoing reported alcohol abuse (daily alcohol intake of more than 2 drinks (liquor,
             beer or wine) in men and 1 drink in women, corresponding to 12/24 g of pure alcohol
             per day women / men and/ or obvious alcoholisation of the patient during screening )
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>85 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Christian Schulze, Prof. Dr.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Department of Internal Medicine I, Jena University Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Sabine Barta, Dr.</last_name>
    <phone>00493641</phone>
    <phone_ext>9396625</phone_ext>
    <email>sabine.barta@med.uni-jena.de</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of Internal Medicine I, Jena University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Jena</city>
        <zip>07747</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Christian Schulze, Professor</last_name>
      <phone>+49 3641 9 32 4198</phone>
      <email>christian.schulze@med.uni-jena.de</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Sissy Grund</last_name>
      <phone>+49 3641 9 32 4198</phone>
      <email>sissy.grund@med.uni-jena.de</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Germany</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 10, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 6, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 7, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 26, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 26, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 29, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Jena University Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Christian Schulze</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Prof. Dr. med. P. Christian Schulze</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>acute decompensated heart failure</keyword>
  <keyword>empagliflozin</keyword>
  <keyword>diuresis</keyword>
  <keyword>renal function</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Heart Failure</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Empagliflozin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

