<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04047589</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IUSCC-0690</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04047589</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Assessing Exercise Behavior and Preferences Among Patients and Oncologists</brief_title>
  <official_title>Assessing Exercise Behavior and Preferences Among Patients and Oncologists at Indiana University Simon Cancer Center</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Indiana University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Indiana University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to understand the preferences and barriers surrounding exercise
      of both the patients and oncologists within Indiana University Simon Cancer Center. This
      information will establish gaps in our current care and provide important information to
      guide future pilot interventions.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This descriptive, cross-sectional study will survey patients with a current or previous
      diagnosis of non-metastatic solid tumor malignancy who are being seen at the Indiana
      University Simon Cancer in Indianapolis, Indiana. Patients with active, incurable disease are
      excluded. Willing and eligible patients will complete a brief, 14 question survey while seen
      in the waiting room of the women's or multi-disciplinary clinics. We aim to survey 350
      patients over a 6 month period. Patients will fill out the survey at only one point in time
      and no patient identifiers will be kept.

      The physician survey will be emailed to oncologist/hematologists practicing within IUSCC who
      see patients at least once per week. Physicians will receive a survey at only one point in
      time. The survey will be anonymous and no physician identifiers will be kept.

      Primary objective Estimate the proportion of patients with curable solid tumor malignancies
      seen at the Indiana University Simon Cancer Center who are meeting exercise recommendations
      for cancer survivors (more than 150 minutes per week of moderate or 75 minutes per week of
      vigorous activity).

      Secondary objectives

        -  Assess patients' perceived barriers to exercise during cancer survivorship

        -  Assess patients' preferences for receiving exercise recommendations

        -  Assess oncologists' perceived barriers to making exercise recommendations

        -  Assess oncologists' preferences for exercise and physical activity resources that could
           be provided by the cancer center
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 13, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Cross-Sectional</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of patients who meet exercise recommendations.</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Patients self-reporting more than 150 minutes per week of moderate physical activity OR more than 75 minutes per week of vigorous physical activity</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient Perceived barriers to exercise during cancer survivorship via pilot survey</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Investigator created survey with 14 items regarding demographics, cancer history, exercise habits, and exercise as part of cancer treatment</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient preferences for receiving exercise recommendations via pilot survey</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Investigator created survey with 14 items regarding demographics, cancer history, exercise habits, and exercise as part of cancer treatment</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Provider perceived barriers to making exercise recommendations via pilot survey</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Investigator created survey with 14 items regarding demographics, cancer speciality, exercise habits, and exercise recommendations to patients and patient exercise habits</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Provider preferences for exercise and physical activity resources that could be provided by the cancer center via pilot survey</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Investigator created survey with 14 items regarding demographics, cancer speciality, exercise habits, and exercise recommendations to patients and patient exercise habits</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">365</enrollment>
  <condition>Solid Tumor</condition>
  <condition>Exercise</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Subjects</arm_group_label>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Providers</arm_group_label>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Survey regarding exercise habits, barriers to exercise, and experience with exercise services from the cancer center.</intervention_name>
    <description>Survey created at Indiana University to gain information regarding exercise habits, barriers to exercise, and experience with exercise services from the cancer center.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Subjects</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Survey regarding personal exercise habits and beliefs, barriers to making exercise recommendations</intervention_name>
    <description>Survey regarding personal exercise habits and beliefs, barriers to making exercise recommendations, and potential resources the cancer center might provide to help make effective exercise recommendations in the future</description>
    <arm_group_label>Providers</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Potential patients will be identified in the outpatient clinics (women's and
        multi-disciplinary) at the IU Simon Cancer Center. Physicians will be given the option of
        requesting that their patients not participate in the survey. When patients check in or are
        placed in an exam room, a trained member of the clinic staff will approach patients about
        possible participation in the survey study.

        Physicians seeing patients more than once per week in the outpatient clinics at the IU
        Simon Cancer Center will receive email invitation to participate in the survey. An online
        survey will be administered via Survey Monkey. This does not require an informed consent
        process. The survey has 14 questions and will take approximately 5 minutes to complete.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Physician survey Any oncologist/hematologist practicing within IUSCC regularly
             providing care for patients with solid tumor malignancies (seeing patients one or more
             days per week in the multidisciplinary or women's clinics with solid tumor
             malignancies). Physicians providing care only for hematologic (multiple myeloma,
             leukemia, lymphoma, transplant) or benign disorders will be excluded.

          -  Patient survey

               1. Patients with a current or previous diagnosis of stage 0-III or curable solid
                  tumor

               2. Patients receiving any component of their medical oncologic care at IUSCC

               3. Age ≥ 18 years

               4. Able to read and write English

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Metastatic disease at the time of study participation

          2. Inability to complete the survey
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Tarah Ballinger, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Indiana University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Tarah Ballinger, MD</last_name>
    <phone>317-944-3553</phone>
    <email>tarab@iu.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Joseph Baker</last_name>
    <email>bakerjom@iu.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Indiana University Melvin &amp; Bren Simon Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Indianapolis</city>
        <state>Indiana</state>
        <zip>46202</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Tarah Ballinger, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 5, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 5, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 7, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 13, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 13, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 14, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Indiana University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Tarah J Ballinger, MD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor of Clinical Medicine</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>solid tumor</keyword>
  <keyword>exercise</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

