<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04045249</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>RUTF18</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04045249</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Comparison of Different Feeding Protocols for the Treatment of Acute Malnutrition</brief_title>
  <official_title>Comparison Between Different Feeding Protocols and Existing Protocol for the Treatment of Acute Malnutrition (A Cluster Randomized Controlled Clinical Trial)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Integrated Reproductive Maternal Newborn &amp; Child Health and Nutrition Program, Punjab</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Integrated Reproductive Maternal Newborn &amp; Child Health and Nutrition Program, Punjab</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Though malnutrition is prevalent worldwide but its situation is alarming in low- and
      middle-income countries. Pakistan has also been facing an alarming situation of prevailing
      severe malnutrition. Malnutrition in its any form costs a huge intolerable burden not only on
      national health care system, but also on social and economic fabric of the nation. The
      current management of severe malnutrition is based on World Health Organization (WHO)
      guidelines and protocols which has been evolved from expert opinions and observational
      studies. The principles of these protocols have emerged from emergency settings and
      converting these protocols for developing countries where severe malnutrition, a routine
      burden is a critical challenge. In the absence of standard protocols for the treatment of
      uncomplicated severe malnutrition in non-emergency settings it is important to test and
      optimize different approaches to treat severely acute malnutrition (SAM). It is hypothesized
      that by optimizing, adapting and implementing time oriented and resource intensive
      approaches, a huge burden of high cost of RUTF may be reduced. While RUTF may be utilized to
      treat SAM children in emergency settings, it is not a substitute of local household foods.
      Therefore, a pilot study has been conducted to compare the various treatment protocols for
      malnourished children. We specifically hypothesized that a reduced dose of RUTF for reduced
      duration, combined with age-appropriate food intake from locally available resources can
      treat uncomplicated SAM children cost effectively as compared to standard national Community
      Management of Acute Malnutrition (CMAM) protocol currently implemented in Punjab, Pakistan.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Malnutrition signifies to inadequacies, immoderations or imbalances in an individual's
      consumption of nutrients or energy. The word malnutrition covers both under and
      over-nutrition. Undernutrition manifest in two different ways acute and chronic malnutrition.
      The acute malnutrition includes wasting while chronic malnutrition includes stunting. The
      situation of malnutrition has been perplexed in Pakistan in recent years and according to
      National Nutrition Survey (2018) rates of wasting are alarmingly high. Also, Pakistan ranks
      at 2nd position for infant and child mortality. The standard treatment of uncomplicated SAM
      in Pakistan often utilizes prolonged use of therapeutic food (RUTF), and after discharge
      results in high rates of relapse(official data from department of Health doesn't support this
      statement, according to them there is low rate of relapse). The present pilot study was
      conducted with the objective to find cost effective treatment protocols for treatment of
      uncomplicated SAM children. The study was conducted at The Children's Hospital and Institute
      of Child Health, Lahore in Out Patient Therapeutic Program (OTP) of Preventive Pediatrics
      Department. The children diagnosed with SAM aged 6-59 months without any specific gender
      preference were recruited. Weight, height and MUAC were measured at the time of enrolment in
      the study and Weight for Height (WHZ), Weight for Age (WAZ), Height for Age (HAZ) standard
      deviation (SD) Z scores and weight velocity was calculated for baseline. For current pilot
      study SAM children were grouped into 3 clusters. First, 30 children were grouped in 1st
      cluster, next 30 in 2nd cluster and further next 30 in 3rd cluster. Children in 1st cluster
      were treated as per standard CMAM protocols. Children in this cluster were provided RUTF as
      per admission weight of child until they attain 11.5cm MUAC or &gt;-3SD WHZ. The children in the
      2nd group (1st intervention group) were initially provided RUTF until they attain MUAC 11cm.
      After this, children were provided 50% of their required daily calories intake by RUTF and
      50% of the calories were provided by the home-based food. The children in the 3rd group (2nd
      intervention group) were initially provided RUTF until they attain MUAC 11 cm. After this,
      children were provided their 100% caloric requirement from home-based food along with
      micronutrients sachets (MMS). The discharge criteria for control group was according to the
      existing CMAM guidelines that is MUAC &gt; 11.5 cm. The discharge criteria for 2nd &amp; 3rd group
      was MUAC &gt; 12.5 cm and WHZ &gt; -2SD score. Follow-up home visits of all children were done
      according to a predefined protocol. During follow-up the control and intervention groups
      underwent weekly anthropometric measurements. Follow up of the study participants of each
      group was continued for one month. Growth rate, recovery rate, mortality rate, relapse
      frequency and duration of recovery were calculated for each group.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">December 10, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">April 25, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">April 25, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Study involved 3 arms; 1st arm was treated as per standard protocol. 2nd arm was provided half calories from RUTF and half from home based food, 3rd arm was provided home based food along with MMS</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Growth velocity</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Weight in Kg</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Growth velocity</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Height in cm</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Growth velocity</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Mid Upper Arm Circumference (MUAC) in cm</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of recovery from SAM</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Time required each child to reach MUAC &gt; 11.5</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of relapse</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Number of children relapsed during the trial</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of mortality</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Number of children dying during trial</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of recovery from Moderate Acute Malnutrition in 1st group</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Proportion of children who reach MUAC &gt; 12.5 cm</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of children having diarrhoea and acute respiratory infection during trial</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of children not coming for follow up visits due to any reason</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">90</enrollment>
  <condition>Malnutrition, Child</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>1st Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Children were treated as per standard CMAM protocols; provided RUTF until MUAC reaches 11.5 cm</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>2nd Group (1st Intervention group)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Children were initially provided RUTF until MUAC reach 11 cm then 50 % calories were provided from RUTF and 50% calories from home based food</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>3rd Group (2nd Intervention)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Children were initially provided RUTF until MUAC reach 11 cm then 100 % calories provided from home based food</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Home based food</intervention_name>
    <description>Home based food is compare able to RUTF</description>
    <arm_group_label>2nd Group (1st Intervention group)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>3rd Group (2nd Intervention)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Children 6-59 months with MUAC &lt;11.5cm and Weight for Height Z score &lt; -3SD

          -  Having good appetite, alert and clinically well

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  WHZ score - 4 SD

          -  MUAC &lt; 8 cm

          -  Secondary malnutrition diagnosed by a gastroenterologist and dietitian

          -  Family History

          -  Birth Anomolies

          -  Any hidden/ asymptomatic health conditions

          -  Any patient coming from out of city (Lahore)

          -  Anorexia

          -  High fever (&gt;104 F)

          -  Severe pallor

          -  Severe dehydration

          -  Lower respiratory tract infection

          -  Bipedal edema

          -  Visible severe wasting
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>6 Months</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>59 Months</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Zahra Khan, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>IRMNCH &amp; Nutrition Program</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The Children's Hospital &amp; The Institute of Child Health</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lahore</city>
        <state>Punjab</state>
        <zip>54000</zip>
        <country>Pakistan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Pakistan</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>August 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 29, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 2, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 5, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 2, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 2, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">August 5, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Integrated Reproductive Maternal Newborn &amp; Child Health and Nutrition Program, Punjab</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Dr. Zahra Khan</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Malnutrition</keyword>
  <keyword>RUTF</keyword>
  <keyword>Children</keyword>
  <keyword>Home base food</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Malnutrition</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Child Nutrition Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

