<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04047992</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>SPU-17-029</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04047992</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Seated Balance Using the Indego™</brief_title>
  <official_title>&quot;The Effects of Exoskeletal-Assisted Walking on Seated Balance Using the Indego™&quot;</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>James J. Peters Veterans Affairs Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>James J. Peters Veterans Affairs Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>Yes</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Exoskeleton-assisted walking (EAW) provides a new mobility option and appears to have
      potential therapeutic benefits for persons with SCI. However, present day technology is not
      sufficient to replace the wheelchair. During EAW, users stand upright, maintain static and
      dynamic balance by actively and passively stimulating trunk and lower limb muscles in a
      manner not challenged during wheelchair use. Preliminary results in our laboratory suggest
      that the indirect balance challenges and postural perturbations that result during EAW
      training transfer to better seated balance control, resulting in more independence during
      seated activities. The purpose of this pilot study is to determine the effects of EAW
      training on various measures of seated balance (primary outcomes) and body composition
      (secondary outcomes). Twenty people with SCI (T4 and below) who are wheelchair users for
      mobility and cannot walk independently will be recruited. The participants will receive 36
      sessions of EAW training in 12 weeks. The outcomes will be evaluated pre (baseline) and post
      (24 and 36 sessions). If EAW devices can be demonstrated to help people with SCI have better
      seated balance, in addition to the other potential benefits that are being investigated
      elsewhere, then exoskeletons may have the possibility to be more readily accepted in the
      clinical, home environments, and by the insurance companies.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Introduction/Background: People with spinal cord injury (SCI) can lose partial to complete
      voluntary control of arm, trunk and leg muscles, resulting in an inability to sit with
      stability, stand and/or walk. Because of poor trunk control during sitting, it may be
      challenging to reach for objects, dress or transfer independently, and the risk of a fall
      from their wheelchair is increased. Exoskeleton-assisted walking (EAW) provides upright, over
      ground mobility and has been demonstrated to be beneficial to improve patient-reported
      quality of life and some health-related outcomes. However, present day exoskeletons are not
      ready to replace the wheelchair. Our preliminary findings suggest that while walking in an
      exoskeleton, people with SCI are challenged to maintain upright balance by using their trunk
      muscles in a way that is rarely done from a wheelchair. Stimulation of the trunk muscles from
      upright postural challenges during EAW appears to benefit overall seated trunk control.

      Summary of Goals and Objectives: The purpose of this study is to determine whether EAW can
      improve the primary outcomes of: seated balance, seated activities of daily living, and trunk
      muscle use. Additional secondary outcomes for body composition will be studied. Twenty people
      with SCI (T4 and below) who are wheelchair users will be recruited to participate.

      Impact: The investigators believe that EAW training will significantly improve seated balance
      to improve wheelchair safety, stability and quality of life, thus, empowering people with SCI
      who use a wheelchair to live more independently. If EAW is demonstrated to have a significant
      benefit on seated balance, then use of these devices in the clinical and home environments
      may be further justified.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 1, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 30, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Seated Computerized Dynamic Posturography (sCDP)</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline after 8 weeks and after 12 weeks.</time_frame>
    <description>Seated balance will be measured by assessment of the limits of stability (LOS) using computerized dynamic posturography (SMART EquiTest, Natus). The SMART EquiTest® system utilizes a dynamic force plate to quantify the vertical forces exerted through the participant's center of gravity as s/he sits on a cushioned block with back unsupported and arms crossed over the clavicles.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Seated Activities of Daily Living (ADLs)</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline after 8 weeks and after 12 weeks.</time_frame>
    <description>Participants' seated ADLs will be assessed by self-reported Spinal Cord Independence Measure (SCIM) and Spinal Cord Injury - Functional Index (SCI-FI, short forms). Participants' functional performance of ADLs will be assessed using the timed t-shirt dressing test by a study team member.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Motor Evoked Potentials (MEPs)</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline after 8 weeks and after 12 weeks.</time_frame>
    <description>Leg muscles will be used to assess neuroplastic changes between the motor cortex and descending neural pathways below incomplete spinal lesions.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Spinal Cord Independence Measure (SCIM)</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline after 8 weeks and after 12 weeks.</time_frame>
    <description>The SCIM is a clinical tool to evaluate the independent performance of ADL especially for people with SCI.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Spinal Cord Injuries</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Exoskeleton Users</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>All participants will receive 36 sessions of supervised EAW training using Indego™ for 12 weeks (3 to 4 sessions per week, 4-6 hours per week). The goal is to complete all 36 sessions in 12 weeks, but allowing for a two-week carryover to accommodate schedule conflicts or missed sessions.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Indego™ Exoskeleton</intervention_name>
    <description>The Indego® is a powered exoskeleton that can be used as a mode of therapy in an institutional setting. Proper walking in this device requires the user to manipulate their center of gravity and balance by postural trunk excursions in order for the legs to take steps.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Exoskeleton Users</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Traumatic or non-traumatic SCI ≥6 months duration of SCI;

          2. Wheelchair-user for indoor and outdoor mobility;

          3. Level and completeness of injury T4 and below with complete or incomplete SCI (ISNCSCI
             A to D);

          4. Able to hold the crutches in hands with or without modifications; and

          5. Able to provide informed consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Diagnosis of neurological injury other than SCI;

          2. Progressive condition that would be expected to result in changing neurological
             status;

          3. Severe concurrent medical disease, illness or condition judged to be contraindicated
             by the Site Physician;

          4. Anthropocentric incompatibility to be fitted with the device;

          5. Traumatic or high impact lower extremity fracture within the past 2 years;

          6. Fragility, minimal trauma or low impact fracture of the lower extremity since spinal
             cord injury;

          7. Knee BMD &lt; 0.60 gm/cm2;

          8. Total hip BMD T-scores &lt; -3.5;

          9. Untreatable severe spasticity judged to be contraindicated by the Site Physician;

         10. Flexion contracture that is incompatible with the device;

         11. Limitations in ankle range of motion that cannot be adapted with an orthotic device
             (plantar flexion &gt; 00);

         12. Fracture of the foot by x-ray and confirmed by CT;

         13. Untreated or uncontrolled hypertension (systolic blood pressure &gt;140 mmHg; diastolic
             blood pressure &gt;90 mmHg);

         14. Unresolved orthostatic hypotension (systolic blood pressure &lt;90 mmHg; diastolic blood
             pressure &lt;60 mmHg) as judged to be contraindicated by the Site Physician;

         15. Current pressure ulcer of the arms, trunk, pelvic area, or lower extremities;

         16. History of seizure;

         17. Use of medications that significantly lower seizure threshold, such as tricyclic
             antidepressants, amphetamines, neuroleptics, dalfampridine, and bupropion;

         18. History of stroke, brain tumor, brain abscess, or multiple sclerosis;

         19. History of moderate or severe head trauma (loss of consciousness for greater than one
             hour or evidence of brain contusion or hemorrhage or depressed skull fracture on prior
             imaging);

         20. History of implanted brain/spine/nerve simulators, aneurysm clips, ferromagnetic
             metallic implants, or cardiac pacemaker/defibrillator;

         21. Psychopathology documentation in the medical record or history that may conflict with
             study objectives; and/or

         22. Pregnancy or women who plan to become pregnant during the study period.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>James J. Peters VA Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bronx</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10468</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Steven Knezevic, MS</last_name>
      <phone>718-584-9000</phone>
      <phone_ext>3130</phone_ext>
      <email>Steven.Knezevic@va.gov</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Pierre K Asselin, MS</last_name>
      <phone>718-584-9000</phone>
      <phone_ext>3124</phone_ext>
      <email>Pierre.Asselin@va.gov</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Annn M Spungen, EdD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>August 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 15, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 5, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 7, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 5, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 5, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">August 7, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>James J. Peters Veterans Affairs Medical Center</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Ann M. Spungen, EdD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Director, VA RR&amp;D National Center for the Medical Consequences of Spinal Cord Injury</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Spinal Cord Injuries</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

