<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04049357</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>0</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04049357</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Care for Colon 2015</brief_title>
  <acronym>CFC2015</acronym>
  <official_title>Colon Capsule Endoscopy in Bowel Cancer Screening. A Randomized Controlled Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Odense University Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Odense University Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>Yes</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The investigatior believe that implementing camera capsule endoscopy as a filter test to
      colonoscopy will increase screening participation, increase the number of individuals with
      detected intermediate- high risk adenomas or cancer, reduce the colonoscopy demand and reduce
      the number of complications.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The Danish national colorectal cancer screening program includes all citizens aged 50-74
      years, who are invited biennially to a fecal test for invisible blood in the stool. If the
      test is positive the citizen is invited for a colonoscopy. 90% of the test-positive undergo
      colonoscopy. The detected cancers are at a significant earlier stage and survival from
      screening detected cancer is higher. It is also expected that cancer incidence will drop due
      to removal of the advanced adenomas before they develop into cancer. Although initial results
      are positive, there is room for improvement. Additionally there are rare but serious
      complications to colonoscopy in the form of bleeding or bowel perforation.

      Through four years the investigators have tested the colon capsule endoscopy method, and find
      that the investigation is associated with significantly less discomfort and that the
      diagnostic ability to find polyps &gt; 1 cm is better than colonoscopy.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">October 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 1, 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 15, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>The investigators will include 124.214 consecutive citizens from the Region of Southern Denmark when they are invited for screening. The participants will be randomized into two groups using an automated randomization tool provided by Odense Patient data Explorative Network (OPEN). The randomization will be based on Zelen's pre-randomization principle and will take place prior to citizens receiving the invitation. The individuals are randomized into 62.107 people allocated in the intervention group and 62.107 allocated in the control group.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>CCE detection rate of polyps compared to OC</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 30 days</time_frame>
    <description>The investigators aim to conduct a large scale randomized trial to investigate the implementation of CCE as part of the Danish screening protocol.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">4629</enrollment>
  <condition>Colorectal Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Adenoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>The intervention group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>If the FIT test is returned and positive the individual can choose either Camera Capsule Endoscopy (CCE) or Optical colonoscopy (OC) as the primary bowel investigation. If OC is chosen, it is performed as standard and the participant outcomes remains analyzed in the intervention group as intention to treat.
If CCE is chosen an out-clinic CCE will be done at one of four regional sites. Overall and segmental bowel preparation grade (Leighton-Rex 1-4) and all pathological findings are reported. If the anal verge is identified without video blackout in the colon the transit is considered complete. Any incomplete CCE investigation will be followed by standard optical endoscopy to the extent needed to investigate the proportion of the colon not visualized by the capsule and remove any detected polyps. If the CCE is complete with complete transit and adequate preparation, individuals with more than two polyps or one polyp over 9 mm will be referred for colonoscopy.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>The control group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>The control group will be invited to screening as usual. The intervention group will be informed that if the fecal test is returned and positive they can either choose to have an initial colon capsule endoscopy, and only colonoscopy if significant findings are made or an initial colonoscopy as usual.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Camera Capsule Endoscopy/ PillCam</intervention_name>
    <description>Camera Capsule Endoscopy in screening</description>
    <arm_group_label>The intervention group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Participation in the Danish colorectal screening program

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  None
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>50 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>74 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <verification_date>August 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 5, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 7, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 8, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 7, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 7, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">August 8, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Odense University Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Morten Kobaek-Larsen</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Post. Doc.</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Camera Capsule Endoscopy</keyword>
  <keyword>Colorectal cancer screening</keyword>
  <keyword>Optical colonoscopy</keyword>
  <keyword>Colorectal cancer</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Colorectal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Adenoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

