<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04045574</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>DA001</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04045574</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>DAMP1: The 1T1T Concept Versus Conventional Implant Loading Protocol</brief_title>
  <official_title>DAMP1: The 1T1T Concept Versus Conventional Implant Loading Protocol: A Comparative Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Liege</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Liege</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The One tooth - One time (1T1T) innovative approach is a straightforward and cost-effective
      protocol to replace a missing tooth in the posterior region (Lambert and Mainjot 2017) (see
      Appendix). The digital impression of single unit implants right after the implant placement
      and the direct manufacturing of a Polymer-Infiltrated Ceramic Network (PICN) screw-retained
      crown allows the delivery of a final tooth in occlusion within the same day. The absence of
      lab procedures reduces the number of appointments, providing immediate results and high
      patient satisfaction. The prosthesis material choice is crucial in this procedure. Indeed,
      PICN high resilience, i.e. damping effect, could reduce peri-implant strain compared to
      ceramic materials (Magne, Silva et al. 2013) (Maminskas, Puisys et al. 2016), moreover its
      elastic modulus is close to tooth tissues, while other CAD-CAM composites value is too low
      and ceramic materials are too high. The rapid milling and manufacturing process, without any
      firing procedure, and the ease of adjustments (particularly to adjust proximal and occlusal
      contact points), make also PICNs well-adapted to chair-side systems. The material low
      stiffness and hardness can improve patient comfort and promote adaptation of the restorations
      to occlusal relationships with time. The 1T1T approach was presented as a proof of concept in
      a first international publication using tissue level implants from Straumann, which describes
      the whole protocol (Lambert and Mainjot 2017). Currently, a case series including 10 teeth is
      on-course, showing a 100% survival rate of implants and restorations after a 2-yr follow-up.
      These results are very promising but further clinical research is needed to validate such a
      protocol on a larger number of patients, on other implant systems as well as to compare this
      approach to conventional protocols.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The present study is designed as a single center comparative controlled trial. This study
      aims to compare immediate (1T1T) versus delayed loading with a final PICN screw-retained
      crown (DL-PICN), performed with CAD-CAM system. A total of 28 consecutive patients (56 teeth)
      above the age of 18 and presenting two single-unit edentulous space in the posterior region
      (molars or premolars, upper or lower jaw), will be considered for possible inclusion in the
      study, according to the inclusion and exclusion criteria (patients with high occlusal stress
      will be included).

      The performance of the different protocols will be tested in terms of (1) prostheses and
      implants survival and success rates following international standards (2) Patient reported
      outcome measures (PROMs); (3) time and cost. Moreover, restorations and antagonistic teeth
      wear will be studied trough ex-vivo analysis by profilometry of replica. The evaluations will
      be carried out at a follow-up period of 7 days, 2, 6 months and then every year up to 5
      years.

      Hypothesis is that the type of loading technique with a final PICN crown (1T1T or DL-PICN)
      does not influence prostheses and implants survival and success rates, but that 1T1T protocol
      improves patient-centered outcomes as well as time and cost effectiveness in comparison with
      DL-PICN.

      The overall cost of the restoration treatment will be 1600€ (instead of 2100€), which
      represents a saving of 500€ for the patient.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">September 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>single center comparative controlled trials</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
    <masking_description>the technique to be used for each site will be randomized</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Prostheses survival/success rates following international standards</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 5 years</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Implants survival/success rates following international standards</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 5 years</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient reported outcome measures (PROMs)</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Questionnaires will be used to assess outcome measure</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Time of protocols</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 2 months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Cost of protocols</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 2 months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">28</enrollment>
  <condition>Dental Implant Failure</condition>
  <condition>Dental Prosthesis Failure</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>DAMP1 :</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Single arm trial comparing a conventional technique with an experimental one, within the same patient.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>The 1T1T concept versus conventional implant loading protocol</intervention_name>
    <description>Implant placement followed by either a conventional or a delayed loading of a PICN screw-retained crown.</description>
    <arm_group_label>DAMP1 :</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Subject must have voluntarily signed the informed consent form before any study
             related action

          -  Age : 18 or above

          -  Men/Women

          -  Patient in good systemic health (ASA I/ II)

          -  No contraindication against oral surgical interventions

          -  Full mouth plaque score (FMPI) lower or equal than 25%

          -  Patient with two single unit edentulous space in the posterior area, upper or lower
             jaw, seeking for implant therapy

          -  Maximum two missing teeth per quadrant

          -  Two single unit edentulous spaces can be contiguous if there are three posterior teeth
             in occlusal contact in the tested half arch.

          -  After the crown placement, at least 3 posterior teeth must be in occlusal contact with
             the antagonistic teeth in the tested half arch.

          -  The tooth at the implant site must have been extracted or lost at least 12 weeks
             before the date of implantation.

          -  At least 8 mm of bone in the vertical dimension

          -  At least 6 mm of bone in the bucco-lingual dimension.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Autoimmune disease requiring medical treatment

          -  Medical conditions requiring prolonged use of steroids

          -  Use of Bisphosphonate intravenously or more then ˃ 3 years of oral use

          -  Infection (local or systemic) - patient with gingivitis or active local infection will
             undergo a medical treatment prior to his entrance to the study, each individual will
             be evaluated prior to study procedure for suitability, in case of systemic infection
             the evaluation will be based on medical anamneses, and if necessary will be referred
             to relevant medical tests.

          -  Current pregnancy or breastfeeding women

          -  Alcoholism or chronically drug abuse

          -  Immunocompromised patients

          -  Uncontrolled Diabetes

          -  Smokers (more than 10 cigarettes/day)

          -  Prisoners

          -  Conditions or circumstances, in the opinion of the investigator, which would prevent
             completion of study participation or interfere with analysis of study results, such as
             history of non-compliance, or unreliability.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Amélie Mainjot, DDS, MSc, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+32 496 95 30 30</phone>
    <email>a.mainjot@chu.ulg.ac.be</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Anoushka Davarpanah, DDS</last_name>
    <phone>+33 6 26 76 47 11</phone>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Institute of Dentistry University of Liege</name>
      <address>
        <city>Liege</city>
        <state>Choose A State</state>
        <zip>4020</zip>
        <country>Belgium</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Amélie Mainjot, DDS, MSc, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>+32 496 95 30 30</phone>
      <email>Amelie.Mainjot@uliege.be</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Anoushka Davarpanah, DDS</last_name>
      <phone>+33 6 26 76 47 11</phone>
      <email>anoushkadavarpanah@gmail.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Belgium</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>August 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 31, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 2, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 5, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 5, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 5, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">August 6, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Liege</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Mainjot Amélie</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Clinical Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>CAD-CAM system</keyword>
  <keyword>Immediate dental implant loading</keyword>
  <keyword>PICN</keyword>
  <keyword>Comparative study</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Prosthesis Failure</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

