<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04043520</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>18-2483</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>U54AG062319</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04043520</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Bioenergetic Effects of Aging and Menopause (BEAM)</brief_title>
  <acronym>BEAM</acronym>
  <official_title>Bioenergetic and Metabolic Consequences of the Loss of Ovarian Function in Women - 2018</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Colorado, Denver</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute on Aging (NIA)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Colorado, Denver</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The menopause transition is associated with increased risk for weight gain and a shift toward
      storing fat in the belly region, which may increase risk for cardiovascular disease and
      diabetes. The stress hormone cortisol is known to promote the accumulation of belly fat, and
      there is evidence that low estrogen is associated with higher cortisol levels. The first aim
      of the study is to determine whether low estrogen levels in premenopausal and early
      postmenopausal women increase cortisol levels in the blood and in fat tissue. When estrogen
      level decreases at the time of menopause, there is an increase in follicle-stimulating
      hormone, or FSH. Recent evidence in mice suggests that blocking FSH prevents the increase in
      belly fat. The second aim of the study is to determine whether decreasing the high FSH level
      in postmenopausal women causes a decrease in belly fat and changes other factors that are
      typically thought to be related to estrogen rather than FSH. Because estrogen and FSH levels
      fluctuate in premenopausal and early postmenopausal women, the investigators will use an
      approach that controls estrogen and FSH levels to address the aims. The investigators will
      use a drug that is typically used to treat endometriosis or uterine fibroids to reduce
      estrogen and FSH levels and an estrogen patch to increase estrogen in some women. The study
      will generate new knowledge on how menopause affects fat gain and disease risk.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Suspended</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    COVID-19 Closure
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 24, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 31, 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 31, 2024</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in the Microdialysis Cortisone Challenge (MCC) Index</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, week 12</time_frame>
    <description>The MCC Index is an in vivo measurement of local cortisol production in abdominal adipose tissue. A higher MCC Index is an indicator of more local cortisol production.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in the Oral Cortisone Challenge (OCC) Area Under the Curve (AUC)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, week 12</time_frame>
    <description>The OCC AUC is a systemic measurement of peripheral glucocorticoid metabolism. A higher OCC AUC is an indicator of more production of cortisol.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in lumbar spine Bone Mineral Density (BMD)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, week 24</time_frame>
    <description>Lumbar spine BMD is measured by dual-energy x-ray absorptiometry. A higher BMD is a general indicator of less risk for osteoporosis.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in resting energy expenditure (REE)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, week 12, week 24</time_frame>
    <description>REE is an index of metabolic rate at rest, measured by indirect calorimetry. A higher REE is an indicator of greater energy expenditure at rest.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in visceral fat area (VFA)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, week 24</time_frame>
    <description>VFA of the abdominal visceral region is measured by computed tomography. VFA is an indicator of the amount of fat stored in this region.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in flow-mediated dilation (FMD)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, week 12, week 24</time_frame>
    <description>FMD of the brachial artery as an index of vascular function. A higher number is a general indicator of better vascular function.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in proximal femur Bone Mineral Density (BMD)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, week 24</time_frame>
    <description>Proximal femur BMD is measured by dual-energy x-ray absorptiometry. A higher BMD is a general indicator of less risk for osteoporosis.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>5</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">95</enrollment>
  <condition>Menopause</condition>
  <condition>Obesity, Abdominal</condition>
  <condition>Aging</condition>
  <condition>Weight Gain</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Premenopausal: GnRH antagonist + estradiol</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Gonadotropin releasing hormone (GnRH) antagonist is degarelix acetate, 80 mg, delivered once as a subcutaneous injection
Estradiol is a transdermal patch 0.075 mg, applied weekly for 12 weeks</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Premenopausal: GnRH antagonist + placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>GnRH antagonist is degarelix acetate, 80 mg, delivered once as a subcutaneous injection
Placebo is a transdermal patch, applied weekly for 12 weeks</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Postmenopausal: GnRH antagonist + estradiol</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>GnRH antagonist is degarelix acetate, 80 mg, delivered twice as a subcutaneous injection (at baseline and after 12 weeks)
Estradiol is a transdermal patch 0.075 mg, applied weekly for 24 weeks</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Postmenopausal: GnRH antagonist + placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>GnRH antagonist is degarelix acetate, 80 mg, delivered twice as a subcutaneous injection (at baseline and after 12 weeks)
Placebo is a transdermal patch, applied weekly for 24 weeks</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Postmenopausal: placebo + placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Placebo (1) is normal saline, delivered twice as a subcutaneous injection (at baseline and after 12 weeks)
Placebo (2) is a transdermal patch, applied weekly for 24 weeks</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>GnRH antagonist</intervention_name>
    <description>GnRH antagonist will be given once for premenopausal women (12-week intervention) and twice for postmenopausal women (24-week intervention)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Postmenopausal: GnRH antagonist + estradiol</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Postmenopausal: GnRH antagonist + placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Premenopausal: GnRH antagonist + estradiol</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Premenopausal: GnRH antagonist + placebo</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Degarelix Acetate</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Estrogen Product</intervention_name>
    <description>Estrogen patches will be worn by those randomized to the Estradiol arms in both premenopausal and postmenopausal groups. Patches will be applied weekly and will be worn for the for entirety of the intervention (12 or 24 weeks).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Postmenopausal: GnRH antagonist + estradiol</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Premenopausal: GnRH antagonist + estradiol</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Estrogen transdermal patch</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo estradiol</intervention_name>
    <description>Placebo patches will be worn by those randomized to the placebo arms in both premenopausal and postmenopausal groups. Patches will be applied weekly and will be worn for the for entirety of the intervention (12 or 24 weeks).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Postmenopausal: GnRH antagonist + placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Postmenopausal: placebo + placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Premenopausal: GnRH antagonist + placebo</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Placebo transdermal patch</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo GnRH antagonist</intervention_name>
    <description>Postmenopausal women randomized to the placebo injection arm will receive two placebo drug injections of normal saline (24-week intervention)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Postmenopausal: placebo + placebo</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Placebo injection</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Volunteers will be healthy premenopausal and postmenopausal women who are willing and able
        to undergo the proposed hormone manipulation and study procedures. Premenopausal women will
        be aged 18 y or older with normal menstrual cycle function and FSH &lt;10 IU/L. Postmenopausal
        women will be those who are at least 6 months but not more than 7 years past the last
        menstrual period (i.e., late perimenopausal or early postmenopausal) with FSH &gt;30 IU/L. We
        will make a major effort to ensure that the women enrolled in this study come from all
        races and ethnicities and a wide range of socioeconomic and educational levels. Women will
        be excluded for the reasons listed below.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  for premenopausal women, irregular menstrual cycles defined as more than 1 missed
             cycle in the previous year

          -  abnormal vaginal bleeding

          -  on hormonal contraceptive or menopausal therapy or intention to start during the
             period of study

          -  positive pregnancy test or intention to become pregnant during the period of study

          -  lactation

          -  known hypersensitivity to degarelix acetate, estradiol, or medroxyprogesterone acetate

          -  Center for Epidemiological Studies Depression Scale (CES-D) score &lt;,16 (unless
             clinician follow-up and clinical judgement determine they are eligible (will be noted
             in study chart)

          -  current tobacco and/or vape use more than 2 times/week

          -  current marijuana or tetrahydrocannabinol (THC) use in any form more than 3 times/week

          -  regular self-reported alcohol consumption &gt;14 drinks/week

          -  BMI &gt;39 kg/m2

          -  use of glucocorticoids or drugs that affect glucocorticoid metabolism (e.g.,
             ketoconazole)

          -  severe osteopenia or osteoporosis, defined as femoral neck or lumbar spine t-score
             &lt;-2.0

          -  thyroid dysfunction, defined as an ultrasensitive TSH &lt;0.5 or &gt;5.0 mU/L; volunteers
             with abnormal thyroid stimulating hormone (TSH) values will be re-considered for
             participation in the study after follow-up evaluation by the PCP with initiation or
             adjustment of thyroid hormone replacement

          -  liver dysfunction, defined as liver function tests (AST, ALT) &gt;1.5 times the upper
             limit of normal

          -  uncontrolled hypertension defined as resting systolic BP &gt;150 mmHg or diastolic BP&gt;90
             mmHg; participants who do not meet these criteria at first screening will be
             re-evaluated, including after follow-up evaluation by the primary care provider (PCP)
             with initiation or adjustment of anti-hypertensive medications

          -  self-reported history of breast cancer or other estrogen-dependent neoplasms

          -  self-reported history of venous thromboembolism, pulmonary embolism, or other
             thromboembolic disorder

          -  self-reported history of cardiovascular disease
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Wendy M Kohrt, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Colorado, Denver</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Colorado - Anschutz Medical Campus</name>
      <address>
        <city>Aurora</city>
        <state>Colorado</state>
        <zip>80045</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 25, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 31, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 2, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 16, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 16, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 20, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Obesity, Abdominal</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Weight Gain</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Estradiol</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Estrogens</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Prolactin Release-Inhibiting Factors</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

