<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04043286</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>5190024</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04043286</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Effects of Dis/Reconnection of Implant Abutments on Peri-implant Bone Levels</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Effects of Disconnection and Reconnection of Implant Abutments on Peri-implant Bone Levels: a 1-year Prospective Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Loma Linda University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Nobel Biocare</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Loma Linda University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>Yes</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The aim of this prospective study is to assess the effects of definitive abutment connection
      at the time of implant placement on bone level changes in the areas of the posterior maxilla
      and mandible.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      A total of 38 implants will be placed in 19 patients with at least 2 missing posterior teeth
      in the maxilla and the mandible for this study. Definitive prefabricated abutments will be
      connected at implant placement. The abutment (control group) on one of the two implants will
      be randomly selected to go through one complete cycle of complete disconnection and
      reconnection by hand at 16- (DR1), 19- (DR2), 22- (DR3), and 24- (DR4) weeks after implant
      surgery. The abutment (test group) on the other implant will be left undisturbed throughout
      the duration of the study. All implants will remain unrestored within the study period (12
      months). Peri-implant bone level changes will be assessed using standardized periapical
      radiographs immediately after implant placement (T0), at 3-(T3), 6-(T6) and 12-(T12) month
      follow-up examinations and during each disconnection of the abutments.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 30, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 31, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 31, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Single center, prospective, randomized modified split mouth clinical trial</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in bone level between baseline surgery and 12 months</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline (prior to surgical implantation), and 12 months after surgical implantation</time_frame>
    <description>Bone level will be measured by periapical radiograph to assess for bone loss after dental implant</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Level of radiolucency after implant</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline (prior to surgical implantation), and 12 months after surgical implantation</time_frame>
    <description>A successful implant will be determined by the degree of radiolucency around the implant 12 months after surgery. Radiolucency will be measured by periapical radiograph at baseline prior to surgery and at 12 months after dental implant surgery. Normal degrees of radiolucency are within 2mm at the crestal region and no radiolucency around the body of the implant</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">19</enrollment>
  <condition>Bone Loss</condition>
  <condition>Gum Recession</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Healing abutments are connected on the implants on the day of surgery, which will be subjected to multiple disconnection and reconnection during the prosthetic phase</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Test group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Definitive abutments connected to the implants on the day of surgery. No disconnection or reconnection during the prosthetic phase</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Definitive abutment</intervention_name>
    <description>With two height options available, On1 Base are selected depending on the thickness of the soft tissue. It remains in position from implant placement to finalization, which leaves the soft tissue undisturbed for optimized healing, moved the restorative platform of Nobel Biocare conical connection implants from bone level to tissue level, thereby simplifying the restorative procedures</description>
    <arm_group_label>Test group</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>On1 Base</other_name>
    <other_name>On1 Concept</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Minimum age 18

          -  Good oral hygiene

          -  Healed site that possess two or more missing teeth in the maxillary or mandibular
             posterior region (excluding third molars)

          -  Adequate bone to accommodate at least a 4.3 mm diameter and 8mm length implant at each
             site

          -  Have at least 8mm interocclusal restorative space

          -  Willing to participate and attend the planned follow-up visits.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  History of alcohol/drug dependency, or any medical, physical, or psychological factor
             that might affect the surgical or prosthodontic procedures and follow-up examinations

          -  History of radiation therapy to the head and neck region

          -  History or current habit of smoking

          -  History or current habit of bruxism

          -  No opposing occluding dentition or prostheses

          -  Need for bone augmentation during implant placement

          -  Implant insertion torque value &lt;35 Ncm
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Joseph Kan, DDS, MS</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Loma Linda University School of Dentistry</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Yuen Lok Loretta Ching, DDS</last_name>
    <phone>9093289742</phone>
    <email>yching@llu.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Loma Linda University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Loma Linda</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>92354</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Yuen Lok Loretta Ching, BDS</last_name>
      <phone>909-328-9742</phone>
      <email>yching@llu.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Abrahamsson I, Berglundh T, Wennström J, Lindhe J. The peri-implant hard and soft tissues at different implant systems. A comparative study in the dog. Clin Oral Implants Res. 1996 Sep;7(3):212-9.</citation>
    <PMID>9151585</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Berglundh T, Lindhe J, Ericsson I, Marinello CP, Liljenberg B, Thomsen P. The soft tissue barrier at implants and teeth. Clin Oral Implants Res. 1991 Apr-Jun;2(2):81-90.</citation>
    <PMID>1809403</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Berglundh T, Lindhe J. Dimension of the periimplant mucosa. Biological width revisited. J Clin Periodontol. 1996 Oct;23(10):971-3.</citation>
    <PMID>8915028</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Squier CA, Collins P. The relationship between soft tissue attachment, epithelial downgrowth and surface porosity. J Periodontal Res. 1981 Jul;16(4):434-40.</citation>
    <PMID>6459440</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chehroudi B, Gould TR, Brunette DM. The role of connective tissue in inhibiting epithelial downgrowth on titanium-coated percutaneous implants. J Biomed Mater Res. 1992 Apr;26(4):493-515.</citation>
    <PMID>1601902</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ericsson I, Persson LG, Berglundh T, Marinello CP, Lindhe J, Klinge B. Different types of inflammatory reactions in peri-implant soft tissues. J Clin Periodontol. 1995 Mar;22(3):255-61.</citation>
    <PMID>7790533</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Broggini N, McManus LM, Hermann JS, Medina RU, Oates TW, Schenk RK, Buser D, Mellonig JT, Cochran DL. Persistent acute inflammation at the implant-abutment interface. J Dent Res. 2003 Mar;82(3):232-7.</citation>
    <PMID>12598555</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rompen E. The impact of the type and configuration of abutments and their (repeated) removal on the attachment level and marginal bone. Eur J Oral Implantol. 2012;5 Suppl:S83-90. Review. Erratum in: Eur J Oral Implantol. 2013 Winter;5(4):379.</citation>
    <PMID>22834397</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Abrahamsson I, Berglundh T, Lindhe J. The mucosal barrier following abutment dis/reconnection. An experimental study in dogs. J Clin Periodontol. 1997 Aug;24(8):568-72.</citation>
    <PMID>9266344</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Becker K, Mihatovic I, Golubovic V, Schwarz F. Impact of abutment material and dis-/re-connection on soft and hard tissue changes at implants with platform-switching. J Clin Periodontol. 2012 Aug;39(8):774-80. doi: 10.1111/j.1600-051X.2012.01911.x. Epub 2012 Jun 7.</citation>
    <PMID>22676071</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rodríguez X, Vela X, Méndez V, Segalà M, Calvo-Guirado JL, Tarnow DP. The effect of abutment dis/reconnections on peri-implant bone resorption: a radiologic study of platform-switched and non-platform-switched implants placed in animals. Clin Oral Implants Res. 2013 Mar;24(3):305-11. doi: 10.1111/j.1600-0501.2011.02317.x. Epub 2011 Oct 3.</citation>
    <PMID>22092773</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Alves CC, Muñoz F, Cantalapiedra A, Ramos I, Neves M, Blanco J. Marginal bone and soft tissue behavior following platform switching abutment connection/disconnection--a dog model study. Clin Oral Implants Res. 2015 Sep;26(9):983-91. doi: 10.1111/clr.12385. Epub 2014 Apr 16.</citation>
    <PMID>24735458</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Degidi M, Nardi D, Piattelli A. One abutment at one time: non-removal of an immediate abutment and its effect on bone healing around subcrestal tapered implants. Clin Oral Implants Res. 2011 Nov;22(11):1303-7. doi: 10.1111/j.1600-0501.2010.02111.x. Epub 2011 Feb 24.</citation>
    <PMID>21985288</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Degidi M, Nardi D, Daprile G, Piattelli A. Nonremoval of immediate abutments in cases involving subcrestally placed postextractive tapered single implants: a randomized controlled clinical study. Clin Implant Dent Relat Res. 2014 Dec;16(6):794-805. doi: 10.1111/cid.12051. Epub 2013 Mar 4.</citation>
    <PMID>23458566</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Canullo L, Bignozzi I, Cocchetto R, Cristalli MP, Iannello G. Immediate positioning of a definitive abutment versus repeated abutment replacements in post-extractive implants: 3-year follow-up of a randomised multicentre clinical trial. Eur J Oral Implantol. 2010 Winter;3(4):285-96.</citation>
    <PMID>21180681</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Grandi T, Guazzi P, Samarani R, Garuti G. Immediate positioning of definitive abutments versus repeated abutment replacements in immediately loaded implants: effects on bone healing at the 1-year follow-up of a multicentre randomised controlled trial. Eur J Oral Implantol. 2012 Spring;5(1):9-16.</citation>
    <PMID>22518376</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Berberi AN, Sabbagh JM, Aboushelib MN, Noujeim ZF, Salameh ZA. A 5-year comparison of marginal bone level following immediate loading of single-tooth implants placed in healed alveolar ridges and extraction sockets in the maxilla. Front Physiol. 2014 Jan 31;5:29. doi: 10.3389/fphys.2014.00029. eCollection 2014.</citation>
    <PMID>24550840</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Grandi T, Guazzi P, Samarani R, Maghaireh H, Grandi G. One abutment-one time versus a provisional abutment in immediately loaded post-extractive single implants: a 1-year follow-up of a multicentre randomised controlled trial. Eur J Oral Implantol. 2014 Summer;7(2):141-9.</citation>
    <PMID>24977249</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Molina A, Sanz-Sánchez I, Martín C, Blanco J, Sanz M. The effect of one-time abutment placement on interproximal bone levels and peri-implant soft tissues: a prospective randomized clinical trial. Clin Oral Implants Res. 2017 Apr;28(4):443-452. doi: 10.1111/clr.12818. Epub 2016 Mar 25.</citation>
    <PMID>27016157</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Koutouzis T, Koutouzis G, Gadalla H, Neiva R. The effect of healing abutment reconnection and disconnection on soft and hard peri-implant tissues: a short-term randomized controlled clinical trial. Int J Oral Maxillofac Implants. 2013 May-Jun;28(3):807-14. doi: 10.11607/jomi.3022.</citation>
    <PMID>23748313</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Luongo G, Bressan E, Grusovin MG, d'Avenia F, Neumann K, Sbricoli L, Esposito M. Do repeated changes of abutments have any influence on the stability of peri-implant tissues? Four-month post-loading preliminary results from a multicentre randomised controlled trial. Eur J Oral Implantol. 2015 Summer;8(2):129-40.</citation>
    <PMID>26021224</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Iglhaut G, Schwarz F, Winter RR, Mihatovic I, Stimmelmayr M, Schliephake H. Epithelial attachment and downgrowth on dental implant abutments--a comprehensive review. J Esthet Restor Dent. 2014 Sep-Oct;26(5):324-31. doi: 10.1111/jerd.12097. Epub 2014 Mar 11. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24612047</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Smith DE, Zarb GA. Criteria for success of osseointegrated endosseous implants. J Prosthet Dent. 1989 Nov;62(5):567-72. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>2691661</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mombelli A, van Oosten MA, Schurch E Jr, Land NP. The microbiota associated with successful or failing osseointegrated titanium implants. Oral Microbiol Immunol. 1987 Dec;2(4):145-51.</citation>
    <PMID>3507627</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Linkevicius T, Apse P, Grybauskas S, Puisys A. The influence of soft tissue thickness on crestal bone changes around implants: a 1-year prospective controlled clinical trial. Int J Oral Maxillofac Implants. 2009 Jul-Aug;24(4):712-9.</citation>
    <PMID>19885413</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wennström JL, Bengazi F, Lekholm U. The influence of the masticatory mucosa on the peri-implant soft tissue condition. Clin Oral Implants Res. 1994 Mar;5(1):1-8.</citation>
    <PMID>8038340</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>July 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 31, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 31, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 2, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 31, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 31, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">August 2, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Loma Linda University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Joseph Kan, DDS</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>One abutment one time</keyword>
  <keyword>Disconnection reconnection</keyword>
  <keyword>Definitive abutment</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Gingival Recession</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

