<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04049318</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>X</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04049318</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effects of a Structured Digital Osteoarthritis Self-management Program After 6 Months of Adherence</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effects of a Structured Digital Osteoarthritis Self-management Program After 6 Months of Adherence</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Lund University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Lund University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a study based on a cohort in a register of patients enrolled in a digital
      osteoarthritis self-management program, Joint Academy. The purpose of this study is to
      examine joint pain and the potential change of this pain, in patients with long-term
      adherence to a digital self-management program for individuals with knee- and hip
      osteoarthritis. The hypothesis, based on preliminary findings is that pain levels of those
      adhering to the program, decreases over time. To test the hypothesis, participants weekly
      pain report will be investigated whilst adhering to the digital program for 6- to 12 months,
      and statistically tests will be performed to find out whether significant differences can be
      seen over time.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Introduction Osteoarthritis (OA) is highly prevalent in older adults and a growing cause of
      disability. The importance of availability of primary treatment of OA is gaining momentum,
      and web-based self-management programs have in recent years become available. Evidence of
      short term effects of such programs are abundant, yet the evaluation of long term effects of
      these programs is scarce.

      Aim To investigate joint pain development over time from participation in a web-based OA
      self-management program for people with hip or knee OA.

      Methods Participants joined the program through advertisements and campaigns on the web.
      Included participants had a radiographic or clinical diagnosis of hip or knee OA (about 95%)
      from a physical therapist or physician. The intervention consisted of a digital, structured
      and individualized treatment program for people with hip or knee OA (Joint Academy®;
      www.jointacademy.com). The program consists of neuromuscular exercises appropriately adjusted
      to each patient in regard to degrees of complexity and difficulty and information in the form
      of text or video lessons (with quizzes on the material after each episode) on subjects
      related to OA, OA symptoms and its management.

      Outcome measures Joint pain in the hip or knee was assessed at baseline, and weeks 12, 24 and
      48 using the Numerical Rating Scale (NRS), a 0-10 scale where 0 is defined as No pain and 10
      is defined as Maximum pain. Minimal clinically important change (MCIC) of pain was defined as
      an improvement of 20%. As a measure of physical function, the 30-second chair stand test
      (30CST) was used and performed by the patient every other week, using an instruction video
      with a coupled visual timer. The patient entered the performed number of repetitions after
      each test. Physical function data was handled similarly to the NRS, with week 24 ±4 adjacent
      weeks and week 48±6 adjacent weeks included for those with available NRS data. All outcomes
      were self-assessed, self-centred, and chosen based on the International Consortium for Health
      Outcomes Measurement Standard Set for Hip &amp; Knee Osteoarthritis (ICHOM).

      Statistical analysis Summary data are described by the mean value, standard deviation and
      number of observations or the number and percent of the categories of interest. The
      group-specific mean treatment effect of duration on pain and repetitions (30CST - physical
      function), as well as differences in pain over time between hip and knee OA with or without
      additional covariates, were estimated and tested using random slopes and intercepts models.
      Pain development over time was plotted for hip and knee OA respectively.

      To describe patients adhering for six months with contrasting pain severity at baseline,
      participants were divided into same-sized tertiles based on reported baseline pain, with
      related descriptive data. Mean pain per time point was calculated and plotted for each group.
      Significance level was set to p&lt;0.05, and p-values and 95% confidence intervals were reported
      when applicable. Statistical calculations were performed in Statistical Package for Social
      Sciences (SPSS Version 25, IBM Corporation, New York, USA) and Stata 15.1 (StataCorp LLC,
      Texas, USA).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 14, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 14, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 14, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in NRS pain</measure>
    <time_frame>0-24 and 0-48 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>0 no pain, 10 max pain</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in 30 second chair stand test (30CST)</measure>
    <time_frame>0-24 and 0-48 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>sit to stand repetitions in 30 seconds</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">1709</enrollment>
  <condition>Osteoarthritis, Knee</condition>
  <condition>Osteoarthritis, Hip</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>24 weeks</arm_group_label>
    <description>Subjects who participated in the intervention who have data available at week 24</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>48 weeks</arm_group_label>
    <description>Subjects who participated in the intervention who have data available at week 48</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Education+ exercise (delivered digitally)</intervention_name>
    <description>The intervention consisted of a digital, structured and individualized treatment program for people with hip or knee OA (Joint Academy®; www.jointacademy.com). The program consists of neuromuscular exercises appropriately adjusted to each patient in regard to degrees of complexity and difficulty, continuous access to and dialogue with a physiotherapist through a chat function, and/or telephone , and information in the form of text or video lessons (with quizzes on the material after each episode) on subjects related to OA, OA symptoms and its management.</description>
    <arm_group_label>24 weeks</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>48 weeks</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        At the time of the study start (13th of March, 2019), the Joint Academy patient database
        contained data from 1709 Swedish participants who had reported one of their knees or hips
        as their most symptomatic joint
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  radiographic or clinical diagnosis of hip or knee OA (about 95%) from a physical
             therapist or physician

          -  had been treated in the digital non-surgical treatment program the first 3 weeks with
             a adherence of at least 70%

          -  had been included in the program at least 24 weeks prior to the data extraction

        Exclusion Criteria:

        -
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Håkan Nero, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Lund University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Arthro therapeutics</name>
      <address>
        <city>Malmö</city>
        <country>Sweden</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Sweden</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Thorstensson CA, Garellick G, Rystedt H, Dahlberg LE. Better Management of Patients with Osteoarthritis: Development and Nationwide Implementation of an Evidence-Based Supported Osteoarthritis Self-Management Programme. Musculoskeletal Care. 2015 Jun;13(2):67-75. doi: 10.1002/msc.1085. Epub 2014 Oct 24.</citation>
    <PMID>25345913</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cronström A, Dahlberg LE, Nero H, Ericson J, Hammarlund CS. 'I would never have done it if it hadn't been digital': a qualitative study on patients' experiences of a digital management programme for hip and knee osteoarthritis in Sweden. BMJ Open. 2019 May 24;9(5):e028388. doi: 10.1136/bmjopen-2018-028388.</citation>
    <PMID>31129601</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nero H, Ranstam J, Kiadaliri AA, Dahlberg LE. Evaluation of a digital platform for osteoarthritis treatment: study protocol for a randomised clinical study. BMJ Open. 2018 Nov 8;8(11):e022925. doi: 10.1136/bmjopen-2018-022925.</citation>
    <PMID>30413507</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nero H, Dahlberg J, Dahlberg LE. A 6-Week Web-Based Osteoarthritis Treatment Program: Observational Quasi-Experimental Study. J Med Internet Res. 2017 Dec 18;19(12):e422. doi: 10.2196/jmir.9255.</citation>
    <PMID>29254906</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cronström A, Nero H, Dahlberg LE. Factors Associated With Patients' Willingness to Consider Joint Surgery After Completion of a Digital Osteoarthritis Treatment Program: A Prospective Cohort Study. Arthritis Care Res (Hoboken). 2019 Sep;71(9):1194-1201. doi: 10.1002/acr.23772. Epub 2019 Jul 17.</citation>
    <PMID>30298990</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>August 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 5, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 7, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 8, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 7, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 7, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">August 8, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Exercise</keyword>
  <keyword>Education</keyword>
  <keyword>Digital treatment</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Osteoarthritis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Osteoarthritis, Knee</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Osteoarthritis, Hip</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

