<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04049890</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>FAI</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04049890</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Development and Validation of Family Adjustment Inventory</brief_title>
  <official_title>Development and Validation of a New Instrument to Evaluate Parents' Adjustment to Their Child's Chronic Disease: the Family Adjustment Inventory</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Meyer Children's Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Florence</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Meyer Children's Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      A diagnosis of chronic disease in childhood may be disruptive for families. Some parents show
      good adjustment, while others may have more difficulties.

      Aim of this study is to develop and validate a new psychometric instrument to help
      precociously detect parents' vulnerability in the process of adjustment to their child's
      chronic disease at different times of care.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      FAI was developed in two different forms:

        1. for parents with one children suffering from a chronic disease or ill children who has
           siblings younger than 3 years old - FAI-O (only child);

        2. for parents with at least two children, the brother/sister of the ill child has 3 years
           or more- FAS-S (siblings) The two forms are identical, with the exception that FAI-S has
           an additional dimension with respect to FAI-O, that specifically regards the involvement
           of siblings in the illness path of the sick brother/sister.

      Development of FAI followed several steps:

        -  definition of initial instrument dimensions

        -  item wording for each dimension

        -  definition of scoring

        -  focus group with parents of patients suffering from a chronic disease to evaluate item
           content and linguistic clarity

      Validation of FAI for each form (FAI-O and FAI-S):

      Validation consists in several steps, identical for the two versions but in different in
      timing, depending on the number of admnistration.

        -  first phase: the FAI is administered to parents of patients with different chronic
           disease (each form needs to reach the total of 300 administrations).

        -  second phase: statistical analysis aimed to obtain the final version of each FAI form
           (define actual dimensions and most adequate items)

        -  third phase: administration to a new sample of parents of children suffering from a
           chronic disease (each form needs to reach the total of 150 administrations).

        -  fourth phase: statistical analysis aimed to confirm the adequacy of the instrument
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 15, 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 31, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Only</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Cross-Sectional</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Perceived family adjustment</measure>
    <time_frame>Parents fill in the FAI one single time at enrollment</time_frame>
    <description>FAI (Family Adjustment Inventory) measures family adjustment. The preliminary versions of FAI-O consists in182 items and FAI-S in197 items, both scored on a 5-point likert scale from 0 to 4. Higher scores represent poorer adjustment.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Presence of distressful events happened in the last year</measure>
    <time_frame>Parents fill in the personal data questionnaire one single time at enrollment</time_frame>
    <description>The presence of distressful events is collected through a personal data questionnaire, specifically designed for this study in accordance to literature in the field</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">900</enrollment>
  <condition>Adjustment Reaction</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Parents of children with a chronic disease with no siblings</arm_group_label>
    <description>Parents of children suffering from a chronic disease who has no brother or sister over 3 years of age</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Parents of children with a chronic disease with siblings</arm_group_label>
    <description>Parents of children suffering from a chronic disease who one or more sibling over the age of 3 years old</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>FAI-O</intervention_name>
    <description>Administration of Family Adjustment Inventory in the version &quot;Only-child&quot;</description>
    <arm_group_label>Parents of children with a chronic disease with no siblings</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>FAI-S</intervention_name>
    <description>Administration of Family Adjustment Inventory in the version &quot;Sibling&quot;</description>
    <arm_group_label>Parents of children with a chronic disease with siblings</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Personal Data Questionnaire</intervention_name>
    <description>This form requires informations about child, respondent and partner (if any), and evaluates the presence of any distressful event happened during the last year</description>
    <arm_group_label>Parents of children with a chronic disease with no siblings</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Parents of children with a chronic disease with siblings</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Parents of patient with a child sufferinf from a chronic illness and treated in the
        hospital for this condition .
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  consent for participating in the study

          -  having a child suffering from a chronic illness and treated in the hospital in the
             following specialties: onco-hematology, neuro-oncology, diabetology, cystic fibrosis,
             metabolic disease, gastroenterology, cardiology, nephrology, rheumatology,
             allergology, pneumology, immunology, intensive care unit

          -  italian speaking

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  cognitive impairment

          -  no good knowledge of italian language
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Francesca Maffei, Msc</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Meyer Children's Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Rosanna Martin, MSc</last_name>
    <phone>055 5662475</phone>
    <phone_ext>0039</phone_ext>
    <email>rosanna.martin@meyer.it</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Laura Vagnoli, MSc</last_name>
    <phone>055 5662719</phone>
    <phone_ext>0039</phone_ext>
    <email>laura.vagnoli@meyer.it</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Meyer Children's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Firenze</city>
        <zip>50139</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Rosanna Martin, MSc</last_name>
      <phone>347-6852475</phone>
      <phone_ext>0039</phone_ext>
      <email>rosanna.martin@meyer.it</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Laura Vagnoli, MSc</last_name>
      <phone>055-5662719</phone>
      <phone_ext>0039</phone_ext>
      <email>laura.vagnoli@meyer.it</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Alessandra Bettini, MSc</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Elena Amore, MSc</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Italy</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Aneshensel CS, Pearlin LI, Mullan JT, Zarit SH, Whitlatch CJ (1995). Profiles in caregiving: the unexpected career. San Diego Academic Press, Inc.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Boer LM, Daudey L, Peters JB, Molema J, Prins JB, Vercoulen JH. Assessing the stages of the grieving process in chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD): validation of the Acceptance of Disease and Impairments Questionnaire (ADIQ). Int J Behav Med. 2014 Jun;21(3):561-70. doi: 10.1007/s12529-013-9312-3.</citation>
    <PMID>23645551</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bonner MJ, Hardy KK, Guill AB, McLaughlin C, Schweitzer H, Carter K. Development and validation of the parent experience of child illness. J Pediatr Psychol. 2006 Apr;31(3):310-21. Epub 2005 May 25.</citation>
    <PMID>15917492</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Klassen AF, Raina P, McIntosh C, Sung L, Klaassen RJ, O'Donnell M, Yanofsky R, Dix D. Parents of children with cancer: which factors explain differences in health-related quality of life. Int J Cancer. 2011 Sep 1;129(5):1190-8. doi: 10.1002/ijc.25737. Epub 2010 Dec 17.</citation>
    <PMID>21064097</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>McCubbin HI, McCubbin MA, Patterson JM, Cauble AE, Wilson LR, Warwick W. (1983). CHIP Coping Health Inventory for Parents: an assessment of parental coping patterns in the care of the chronically ill child. Journal of Marriage and Family, 45(2), 359-370.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Raina P, O'Donnell M, Schwellnus H, Rosenbaum P, King G, Brehaut J, Russell D, Swinton M, King S, Wong M, Walter SD, Wood E. Caregiving process and caregiver burden: conceptual models to guide research and practice. BMC Pediatr. 2004 Jan 14;4:1. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>14723791</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Raina P, O'Donnell M, Rosenbaum P, Brehaut J, Walter SD, Russell D, Swinton M, Zhu B, Wood E. The health and well-being of caregivers of children with cerebral palsy. Pediatrics. 2005 Jun;115(6):e626-36.</citation>
    <PMID>15930188</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rossi Ferrario S, Baiardi P, Zotti AM. Update on the family strain questionnaire: a tool for the general screening of caregiving-related problems. Qual Life Res. 2004 Oct;13(8):1425-34.</citation>
    <PMID>15503838</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 7, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 7, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 8, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 5, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 5, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 6, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Meyer Children's Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Rosanna Martin</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Pediatric Psychologist</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>adjustment</keyword>
  <keyword>family functioning</keyword>
  <keyword>chronic disease</keyword>
  <keyword>emotions</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Chronic Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

