<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04045223</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2119/2017</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04045223</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Mitochondrial DNA Triggering Epidural Related Maternal Fever</brief_title>
  <official_title>Circulating Cell-free Mitochondrial DNA Triggering Epidural Related Maternal Fever (ERMF) in Obstetric Anesthesia: a Pilot Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Medical University of Vienna</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Medical University of Vienna</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background: Giving birth is a critical moment for the mother and the fetus, potentially
      accompanied by stress, tissue damage, cell injury, placental hypoxia and sometimes
      multisystem vascular syndrome known as preeclampsia. Epidural analgesia with a local
      anesthetic is a common anesthetic approach during labor. Local anesthetics inhibit the
      oxidative phosphorylation and impair the synthesis of ATP, resulting in mitochondrial
      dysfunction and increased reactive oxygen species. Especially when the high demand of ATP
      during pregnancy cannot be reached, apoptosis will occur in an anaerobic environment. During
      apoptosis the cell membrane integrity is disturbed, releasing the cytoplasm into the blood
      circulation. Circulating cell-free mitochondrial DNA acts as a damage associated molecular
      pattern (DAMP) by activating the innate immune system leading to inflammation. These DAMPs
      are evolutionary conserved and have structural similarity to their bacterial ancestor.
      Therefore, cell-free mitochondria can act as a potent agent triggering the immune system in
      an autoimmune manner as well as a biomarker for cell damage and hypoxia.

      Objective: The aim of this study is to investigate to role of epidural analgesia during
      birth, quantifying the copy number of circulating cell-free mitochondrial DNA in maternal
      serum and the placenta compared to controls. The investigators hypothesize that epidural
      analgesia with a local anesthetic has an effect on cell-free mitochondrial DNA levels,
      promoting the pathogenesis of ERMF and early inflammation. In addition, circulating
      mitochondrial DNA could be a potent biomarker for cell damage, early placenta
      hypoxia/insufficiency or preeclampsia.

      Methods: For this study the investigators planned 3 groups each consisting of 15 patients.
      The intervention group (group 1) will be women with vaginal delivery having epidural
      analgesia and developing fever before delivery. The control group (group 2) will be women
      with vaginal delivery having an epidural analgesia without developing fever before delivery.
      Women with vaginal delivery without an epidural analgesia will serve as additional control
      (group 3). Blood will be taken at arrival at the delivery ward and immediately after delivery
      from a peripheral venous line. In addition, venous blood from the umbilical vein will be
      drawn postpartum. Axillary temperature will be measured routinely using a thermometer in a
      routine clinical fashion. Circulating cell-free mitochondrial DNA and other immunological
      markers will be quantified in maternal and umbilical cord (fetal) serum by real time
      quantitative PCR and statistical analysis will be performed by non-parametric tests.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 31, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 31, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>quantity of circulating cell-free mitochondrial DNA</measure>
    <time_frame>change from quantity of baseline mtDNA to quantity of mtDNA immediately after delivery</time_frame>
    <description>The aim of this study is to elucidate the influence of epidural analgesia (epidural analgesia or no epidural analgesia) during labor with regard to the quantity of circulating cell-free mitochondrial DNA in women developing ERMF.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>3</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">45</enrollment>
  <condition>Mitochondrial DNA</condition>
  <condition>Epidural Related Maternal Fever (ERMF)</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Epidural analgesia and fever</arm_group_label>
    <description>Group 1 will be patients with vaginal delivery and having an epidural analgesia that develop fever during delivery.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Epidural analgesia and no fever</arm_group_label>
    <description>Group 2 will be patients with vaginal delivery and having an epidural analgesia that do not develop fever during delivery.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>No epidural analgesia</arm_group_label>
    <description>Group 3 serves as additional control group and consists of patients having no epidural analgesia and no fever.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Blood samples</intervention_name>
    <description>Maternal blood will be taken at arrival at the delivery unit and after delivery. Furthermore, placental blood will be taken after delivery.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Epidural analgesia and fever</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Epidural analgesia and no fever</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>No epidural analgesia</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      cell-free mitochondrial DNA
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients must meet inclusion criteria and must give written consent. Informed consent will
        be obtained only for conscious patients preoperative. The cause of admission will be noted,
        baseline demographics and clinical history will be recorded. Patients included are giving
        birth at the Department of Obstetrics and Feto-Maternal Medicine at the Medical University
        of Vienna between July 2019 and July 2020. We are expecting to need to observe 15 patients
        per group in order to prove our hypothesis in this pilot study.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  women

          -  between 18 and 45 years

          -  Para 0 or Para 1

          -  Gestational week

          -  Elective procedure 37±0 to 42±0

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  younger than 18 years

          -  Emergency procedures

          -  No written consent

          -  Fever &lt;2 weeks

          -  Intraoperative conversion from one anesthetic or surgical procedure to another one.

          -  preeclampsia

          -  HELLP syndrome

          -  intrauterine growth reduction

          -  gestational diabetes mellitus

          -  autoimmune disease
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <gender_based>Yes</gender_based>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>45 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Christina Hafner, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+ 43 1 40400 41000</phone>
    <email>christina.hafner@meduniwien.ac.at</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Klaus Ulrich Klein, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+ 43 1 40400 41000</phone>
    <email>klaus.klein@meduniwien.ac.at</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of Anesthesia, General Intensive Care and Pain Management,Medical University of Vienna</name>
      <address>
        <city>Vienna</city>
        <zip>1090</zip>
        <country>Austria</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Austria</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>August 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 25, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 2, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 5, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 2, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 2, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">August 5, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Medical University of Vienna</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Ass.-Prof. PD Dr. Klaus Ulrich Klein</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principle Investigator, Klaus Ulrich Klein; MD</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Fever</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

