<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04041271</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>(717)108A-33</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04041271</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Jaw Kinematics and Muscle Activation in Patients With Non-specific Chronic Neck Pain</brief_title>
  <official_title>Jaw Kinematics and Muscle Activation in Patients With Non-specific Chronic Neck Pain</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Yang Ming University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Cheng-Hsin General Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Yang Ming University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Temporomandibular disorder (TMD) is a collective term for pain and dysfunction of the
      masticatory muscles and temporomandibular joint (TMJ). Typical signs and symptoms of TMD
      includes regional pain, noises from the TMJs and limitations in jaw movements. Altered jaw
      kinematics and muscle activity have also been reported. TMD may be related to neck problems.
      Over 50% of patients with TMD suffer from nonspecific neck pain. Patients with TMD often have
      symptoms over neck, including upper cervical spine movement impairment and reduced cervical
      muscles endurance. Conversely, TMD may also develop in patients with neck pain. Twenty to
      thirty-three percent of patients with neck pain also have TMD. Subjects with neck pain
      present with a twofold higher prevalence of TMD than those without neck pain. In patients
      with neck pain, the development or perpetuation of TMD may be due to the anatomical
      connection between TMJ and neck: neck posture affects the mandible position and sensory
      inputs from the cervical-mandibular region converge at the trigemino-cervical nucleus. Early
      identification of TMD is essential but to our knowledge, no study has investigated whether
      patients with neck pain demonstrate altered jaw movement and muscle activity, which is
      associated with TMD. The purposes of this proposal are to compare the jaw kinematics, muscle
      activity and muscle sensitivity in healthy individuals and patients with non-specific chronic
      neck pain (NCNP). This study also aimed to investigate the relationship between forward-head
      posture and the jaw kinematics, muscle activity as well as muscle sensitivity. With a
      cross-sectional exploratory study design, 30 healthy control subjects and 30 subjects with
      NCNP will be recruited. Clinical assessments will include cervical range of motion (CROM),
      pressure pain threshold (PPT) over the cervical-mandibular region and the cranial-cervical
      angle (CCA). Jaw kinematics will be measured by Ultrasonic Jaw Motion Analyzer (Zebris GmbH)
      during functional jaw movements. Muscle activities are record from bilateral anterior
      temporalis, masseter, sternocleidomastoid muscle and upper trapezius by surface
      electromyography during resting and clenching.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 11, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 15, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 1, 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational [Patient Registry]</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Control</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Cross-Sectional</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <target_duration>1 Day</target_duration>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Jaw maximum range of motion</measure>
    <time_frame>Immediately during the experiment</time_frame>
    <description>Including maximum mouth opening, lateral right, lateral left, and protrusion, which will be described with millimeter (mm)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Jaw velocity</measure>
    <time_frame>Immediately during the experiment</time_frame>
    <description>Jaw opening and closing velocity, which will be described with millimeter per second (mm/s)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Condylar rotation</measure>
    <time_frame>Immediately during the experiment</time_frame>
    <description>The rotation will be described with degree (°).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Condylar translation</measure>
    <time_frame>Immediately during the experiment</time_frame>
    <description>Including condylar translation and condylar path length, which will be described with millimeter (mm)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Muscle activation</measure>
    <time_frame>Immediately during the experiment</time_frame>
    <description>The root mean square of electromyography (EMG) data of the masseter, anterior temporalis, sternocleidomastoid muscle and upper trapezius will be normalized by the maximum voluntary contraction amplitude (percentage of maximal voluntary contraction, %).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cervical and jaw range of motion</measure>
    <time_frame>Immediately during the experiment</time_frame>
    <description>Including range of motion of cervical flexion, cervical extension, cervical side-bending,cervical rotation and cervical flexion-rotation as well as maximum mouth opening, jaw lateral right, jaw lateral left, protrusion. The motion will be described with degree (°).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pressure pain threshold</measure>
    <time_frame>Immediately during the experiment</time_frame>
    <description>Pressure pain threshold of masseter, anterior temporalis, sternocleidomastoid muscle, upper trapezius and suboccipitals will each be averaged and will be described with kg/cm2.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cranial-cervical angle</measure>
    <time_frame>Immediately during the experiment</time_frame>
    <description>Cranial-cervical angle will be measured as the included angle between the ear lobe, C7 spinous process and the horizontal line and will be described with degree (°).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Temporomandibular Disorder</condition>
  <condition>Nonspecific Chronic Neck Pain</condition>
  <condition>Biomechanical Phenomena</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Nonspecific chronic neck pain (NCNP) group</arm_group_label>
    <description>Subjects with nonspecific chronic neck pain will be included to perform clinical test and assess their jaw kinematics and muscle activation.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control group</arm_group_label>
    <description>Healthy control subjects will be included to compare the differences in jaw kinematics, muscle activation and clinical tests between healthy subjects and subjects with nonspecific chronic neck pain. Subjects in this group will received the same assessment as the NCNP group.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cervical range of motion (CROM)</intervention_name>
    <description>Subjects will perform full-range cervical flexion, extension, side-bending and rotation actively in sitting position. In supine position, cervical flexion-rotation will be performed passively by the assessor.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Nonspecific chronic neck pain (NCNP) group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pressure pain threshold (PPT)</intervention_name>
    <description>A digital algometer with rubber head will be used to apply pressure on the muscles of subjects. When the subjects start to feel pain, the algometer will be removed immediately.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Nonspecific chronic neck pain (NCNP) group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cranial-cervical angle (CCA)</intervention_name>
    <description>Subjects will stand in a relaxed position with colour markers on the earlobe and C7 spinous process. A photo of the head posture will be taken to calculate the included angle between the markers and the horizontal line.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Nonspecific chronic neck pain (NCNP) group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Jaw kinematics</intervention_name>
    <description>Jaw kinematics is measured by Ultrasonic Jaw Motion Analyzer (Zebris). The subjects will perform jaw opening, closing, lateral left, lateral right and protrusion for three times.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Nonspecific chronic neck pain (NCNP) group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Muscle activation</intervention_name>
    <description>Surface electromyography is used to assess the activities of bilateral masseter, anterior temporalis, sternocleidomastoid muscle and upper trapezius. Subjects will perform jaw resting and clenching.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Nonspecific chronic neck pain (NCNP) group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients with nonspecific chronic neck pain for at least 3 months and the matched healthy
        control subjects
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria (nonspecific chronic neck pain group):

          -  Aged between 20 to 65 years old

          -  Mechanical pain that provoked by sustained neck postures or specific neck movements
             without any identifiable diseases or structure anomalies

          -  Chronic or recurrent neck pain of at least 3 months duration

          -  Minimum of 3 points on the numerical pain rating scale (NPRS) over cervical region

          -  Without any pain, clicking or range of motion limitation over TMJ

        Inclusion Criteria (healthy control group):

          -  Age (± 5 years) and gender match to NCNP group

          -  No pain or clinical pathology involving the masticatory system or cervical spine for
             at least one year prior to the start of the study

        Exclusion Criteria (both groups):

          -  Serious injury, tumor, infection

          -  Recent cervical-cranial surgery

          -  Neurologic involvement

          -  Inflammatory rheumatic diseases

          -  Pregnancy

          -  Nonmechanical cause of neck pain (e.g. herniated disk, spinal fractures)

          -  Had been diagnosed with spinal conditions (e.g. spondylolisthesis)

          -  Shoulder pain within 1 years

          -  Loss of posterior tooth

          -  Dental pain or periodontal problems

          -  Orthodontic, orofacial myofunctional or TMD treatment within 3 months

          -  Use of analgesic or anti-inﬂammatory drugs within 3 days
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>20 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>60 Years</maximum_age>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Yin-Liang Lin, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+886-2-2826-7288</phone>
    <email>yinliang@ym.edu.tw</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Yang-Ming University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Taipei</city>
        <zip>112</zip>
        <country>Taiwan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Yin-Liang Lin, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>+886-2-28267288</phone>
      <email>yinliang@ym.edu.tw</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Taiwan</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 28, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 31, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 1, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 25, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 25, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 27, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Temporomandibular disorder</keyword>
  <keyword>Nonspecific chronic neck pain</keyword>
  <keyword>Jaw kinematics</keyword>
  <keyword>Muscle activity</keyword>
  <keyword>Muscle sensitivity</keyword>
  <keyword>Forward head</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Temporomandibular Joint Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Temporomandibular Joint Dysfunction Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neck Pain</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

