<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02550236</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>LIFE Child Leipzig</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02550236</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>LIFE Leipzig Research Centre for Civilization Diseases</brief_title>
  <acronym>LIFE-Child</acronym>
  <official_title>Prospective Population-based Childhood Cohort Study in the Leipzig Area Investigating Genetic, Environmental, and Metabolic Factors and Their Association With the Development of Civilization Diseases</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Leipzig</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>European Social Fund</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>European Regional Development Fund</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>State of Saxony</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Leipzig</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The Leipzig Research Centre for Civilization Diseases (LIFE) Child Study is a prospective
      longitudinal population-based study with a life course approach to health and disease.

      The LIFE Child Study focuses on two main research objectives:

        -  What are premises of normal growth, development and health in children?

        -  Which factors contribute to the development of non-communicable diseases such as
           childhood obesity and its co-morbidities, atopy and mental health problems?

      Detailed assessments will be conducted alongside long-term storage of biological samples in
      2,000 pregnant women and more than 10,000 children and their families.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      -  The LIFE Child study is part of LIFE, a life sciences research program of the University
           of Leipzig (Leipzig Research Centre for Civilization Diseases - LIFE). The measurements
           are performed in a well-equipped research centre located on the premises of the
           University Hospital of Leipzig.

        -  The study collects detailed information from clinical examinations, questionnaires and
           interviews and includes a collection of several types of biological materials at various
           time points (urine, hair, blood for direct analyses, genomic DNA, dried blood spots,
           paxgenes (for RNA isolation and expression/eQTL studies). Children and adolescents from
           0-18 years at baseline and their families are included. Participants will be followed
           annually over a period of ten years irrespective of the age at the first participation
           in the study.

        -  Prenatal examinations are conducted in the 24th and 36th week of gestation and postnatal
           examinations in 3., 6. and 12. month in the offspring. The birth cohort study collects
           detailed information from clinical examinations, questionnaires and interviews and
           biological materials (blood, cord blood, placental tissue, breast milk, hair, urine)

        -  In addition, the LIFE Child study focuses in certain disease cohorts and disease free
           controls in more detail. The aim of these subgroups is to examine aetiological
           associations and comorbidities with more in-depth methods. There are two disease
           cohorts: LIFE Child OBESITY, LIFE Child DEPRESSION.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2010</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Civilization diseases and their risk factors</measure>
    <time_frame>10 years</time_frame>
    <description>Assess lifestyle, metabolic and genetic risk factors of civilization diseases (e.g. diabetes mellitus, obesity, allergy, cardiovascular diseases) from fetal life to adulthood.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>3</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">12000</enrollment>
  <condition>Childhood Obesity</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>LIFE Child Health</arm_group_label>
    <description>The LIFE Child HEALTH cohort is a sample of 10.000 children and adolescents. A basic program that will be carried out annually at each study centre visit. This program includes clinical history (perinatal and past medical history, medications, allergies, immunizations, developmental history and family history) clinical examination, collection of blood, hair and urine samples, anthropometry and different age-dependent questionnaires. Questionnaires are completed by the parents and starting at the age of eight years also by the child itself.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>LIFE Child Obesity</arm_group_label>
    <description>The LIFE Child OBESITY cohort is a sample of 1,500 obese children and adolescents that will be assessed and compared to a lean control group (N=1,500) with equally detailed phenotyping including metabolic and cardiovascular evaluation. The LIFE Child OBESITY cohort (including the control group) performs the basic program of the LIFE Child HEALTH cohort plus additional parameters such as electrical bioimpedance, assessment of basal metabolic rate, oral glucose tolerance test, spiroergometry and measurement of endothelial function using EndoPAT.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>LIFE Child Health: Pregnancy/Birth</arm_group_label>
    <description>The LIFE child Pregnancy/Birth cohort is a sample of 2,000 pregnant women and their offspring. Prenatal examinations are conducted during the 24th to 26th and 34th to 36th week of gestation. During the first year of life, data is collected from children at 3, 6 and 12 month of age.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      -  blood samples for mRNA and DNA analysis

        -  serum samples

        -  plasma samples

        -  serum samples from oral glucose tolerance testing

        -  urine samples

        -  hair samples

        -  mother's milk
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        The LIFE Child study is a prospective longitudinal population-based cohort study. All
        children with their families and pregnant women of the area of Leipzig are eligible to
        participate in the LIFE Child study. This sample is supposed to represent the population of
        the city.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  children with their families and pregnant women of the area of Leipzig

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  severe diseases
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>18 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Wieland Kiess, Prof., MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Leipzig</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Antje Körner, Prof., MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Leipzig</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Wieland Kiess, Prof., MD</last_name>
    <email>wieland.kiess@medizin.uni-leipzig.de</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>LIFE Child</last_name>
    <email>contact@life.uni-leipzig.de</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>LIFE Leipzig Research Centre for Civilization Diseases, University of Leipzig</name>
      <address>
        <city>Leipzig</city>
        <state>Saxony</state>
        <zip>04103</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Wieland Kiess, Prof. MD</last_name>
      <email>wieland.kiess@medizin.uni-leipzig.de</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>LIFE Child</last_name>
      <email>contact@life.uni-leipzig.de</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Wieland Kiess, Prof., MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Antje Körner, Prof.,MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Germany</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://kik.uniklinikum-leipzig.de/</url>
    <description>University Hospital for Children and Adolescents, Leipzig</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://life.uni-leipzig.de/en/children_adolescents_and_pregnant_women.html</url>
    <description>LIFE child study, Leipzig</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://kik.uniklinikum-leipzig.de/kikcms.site,postext,arbeitsgruppen.html?PHPSESSID=4ka1kncm9nou4p59d83tjh0e21</url>
    <description>Center for Pediatric Research Leipzig (CPL)</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Poulain T, Baber R, Vogel M, Pietzner D, Kirsten T, Jurkutat A, Hiemisch A, Hilbert A, Kratzsch J, Thiery J, Fuchs M, Hirsch C, Rauscher FG, Loeffler M, Körner A, Nüchter M, Kiess W; LIFE Child study team. The LIFE Child study: a population-based perinatal and pediatric cohort in Germany. Eur J Epidemiol. 2017 Feb;32(2):145-158. doi: 10.1007/s10654-016-0216-9. Epub 2017 Jan 31.</citation>
    <PMID>28144813</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Quante M, Hesse M, Döhnert M, Fuchs M, Hirsch C, Sergeyev E, Casprzig N, Geserick M, Naumann S, Koch C, Sabin MA, Hiemisch A, Körner A, Kiess W; LIFE Child Study Investigators. The LIFE child study: a life course approach to disease and health. BMC Public Health. 2012 Nov 22;12:1021. doi: 10.1186/1471-2458-12-1021.</citation>
    <PMID>23181778</PMID>
  </reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Händel N, Mothes T, Petroff D, Baber R, Jurkutat A, Flemming G, Kiess W, Hiemisch A, Körner A, Schlumberger W, Thiery J, Wolf J. Will the Real Coeliac Disease Please Stand Up? Coeliac Disease Prevalence in the German LIFE Child Study. J Pediatr Gastroenterol Nutr. 2018 Oct;67(4):494-500. doi: 10.1097/MPG.0000000000002052.</citation>
    <PMID>29901554</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Berger T, Peschel T, Vogel M, Pietzner D, Poulain T, Jurkutat A, Meuret S, Engel C, Kiess W, Fuchs M. Speaking Voice in Children and Adolescents: Normative Data and Associations with BMI, Tanner Stage, and Singing Activity. J Voice. 2019 Jul;33(4):580.e21-580.e30. doi: 10.1016/j.jvoice.2018.01.006. Epub 2018 May 25.</citation>
    <PMID>29807693</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Schmidt R, Vogel M, Hiemisch A, Kiess W, Hilbert A. Pathological and non-pathological variants of restrictive eating behaviors in middle childhood: A latent class analysis. Appetite. 2018 Aug 1;127:257-265. doi: 10.1016/j.appet.2018.04.030. Epub 2018 May 5.</citation>
    <PMID>29738782</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Poulain T, Peschel T, Vogel M, Jurkutat A, Kiess W. Cross-sectional and longitudinal associations of screen time and physical activity with school performance at different types of secondary school. BMC Public Health. 2018 Apr 27;18(1):563. doi: 10.1186/s12889-018-5489-3.</citation>
    <PMID>29703168</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Poulain T, Vogel M, Neef M, Abicht F, Hilbert A, Genuneit J, Körner A, Kiess W. Reciprocal Associations between Electronic Media Use and Behavioral Difficulties in Preschoolers. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2018 Apr 21;15(4). pii: E814. doi: 10.3390/ijerph15040814.</citation>
    <PMID>29690498</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Hartmann AS, Poulain T, Vogel M, Hiemisch A, Kiess W, Hilbert A. Prevalence of pica and rumination behaviors in German children aged 7-14 and their associations with feeding, eating, and general psychopathology: a population-based study. Eur Child Adolesc Psychiatry. 2018 Nov;27(11):1499-1508. doi: 10.1007/s00787-018-1153-9. Epub 2018 Apr 19. Erratum in: Eur Child Adolesc Psychiatry. 2018 Jun 8;:.</citation>
    <PMID>29675593</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Rieger K, Vogel M, Engel C, Ceglarek U, Harms K, Wurst U, Lengfeld H, Richter M, Kiess W. Does physiological distribution of blood parameters in children depend on socioeconomic status? Results of a German cross-sectional study. BMJ Open. 2018 Mar 1;8(3):e019143. doi: 10.1136/bmjopen-2017-019143.</citation>
    <PMID>29500207</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Fabian S, Gelbrich B, Hiemisch A, Kiess W, Hirsch C; LIFE Child study team. Impact of overbite and overjet on oral health-related quality of life of children and adolescents. J Orofac Orthop. 2018 Jan;79(1):29-38. doi: 10.1007/s00056-017-0114-0. Epub 2017 Dec 19.</citation>
    <PMID>29260241</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Scharlau F, Pietzner D, Vogel M, Gaudl A, Ceglarek U, Thiery J, Kratzsch J, Hiemisch A, Kiess W. Evaluation of hair cortisol and cortisone change during pregnancy and the association with self-reported depression, somatization, and stress symptoms. Stress. 2018 Jan;21(1):43-50. doi: 10.1080/10253890.2017.1392507. Epub 2017 Oct 26.</citation>
    <PMID>29073819</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Loeffler-Wirth H, Vogel M, Kirsten T, Glock F, Poulain T, Körner A, Loeffler M, Kiess W, Binder H. Body typing of children and adolescents using 3D-body scanning. PLoS One. 2017 Oct 20;12(10):e0186881. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0186881. eCollection 2017.</citation>
    <PMID>29053732</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Herrmann J, Vogel M, Pietzner D, Kroll E, Wagner O, Schwarz S, Müller E, Kiess W, Richter M, Poulain T. Factors associated with the emotional health of children: high family income as a protective factor. Eur Child Adolesc Psychiatry. 2018 Mar;27(3):319-328. doi: 10.1007/s00787-017-1049-0. Epub 2017 Sep 23.</citation>
    <PMID>28942492</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Schmidt J, Guder U, Kreuz M, Löffler M, Kiess W, Hirsch C, Ziebolz D, Haak R. aMMP-8 in correlation to caries and periodontal condition in adolescents-results of the epidemiologic LIFE child study. Clin Oral Investig. 2018 Jan;22(1):449-460. doi: 10.1007/s00784-017-2132-0. Epub 2017 Jun 4.</citation>
    <PMID>28578462</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Weithase A, Vogel M, Kiep H, Schwarz S, Meißner L, Herrmann J, Rieger K, Koch C, Schuster V, Kiess W. [Quality of and Attendance at Healthy Child Clinics in Germany]. Dtsch Med Wochenschr. 2017 Apr;142(8):e42-e50. doi: 10.1055/s-0043-100841. Epub 2017 Apr 21. German.</citation>
    <PMID>28431439</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Kliem S, Schmidt R, Vogel M, Hiemisch A, Kiess W, Hilbert A. An 8-item short form of the Eating Disorder Examination-Questionnaire adapted for children (ChEDE-Q8). Int J Eat Disord. 2017 Jun;50(6):679-686. doi: 10.1002/eat.22658. Epub 2017 Jan 25.</citation>
    <PMID>28122128</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Glock F, Vogel M, Naumann S, Kuehnapfel A, Scholz M, Hiemisch A, Kirsten T, Rieger K, Koerner A, Loeffler M, Kiess W. Validity and intraobserver reliability of three-dimensional scanning compared with conventional anthropometry for children and adolescents from a population-based cohort study. Pediatr Res. 2017 May;81(5):736-744. doi: 10.1038/pr.2016.274. Epub 2017 Jan 4.</citation>
    <PMID>28052064</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Daxer J, Herttrich T, Zhao YY, Vogel M, Hiemisch A, Scheuermann K, Körner A, Kratzsch J, Kiess W, Quante M. Nocturnal levels of chemerin and progranulin in adolescents: influence of sex, body mass index, glucose metabolism and sleep. J Pediatr Endocrinol Metab. 2017 Jan 1;30(1):57-61. doi: 10.1515/jpem-2016-0378.</citation>
    <PMID>27941174</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Schmidt R, Richter R, Brauhardt A, Hiemisch A, Kiess W, Hilbert A. Parental feeding practices in families with children aged 2-13 years: Psychometric properties and child age-specific norms of the German version of the Child Feeding Questionnaire (CFQ). Appetite. 2017 Feb 1;109:154-164. doi: 10.1016/j.appet.2016.11.038. Epub 2016 Nov 30.</citation>
    <PMID>27915081</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Dathan-Stumpf A, Vogel M, Rieger K, Thiery J, Hiemisch A, Kiess W. Serum lipid levels were related to socio-demographic characteristics in a German population-based child cohort. Acta Paediatr. 2016 Aug;105(8):e360-7. doi: 10.1111/apa.13438. Epub 2016 May 22.</citation>
    <PMID>27096544</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Dathan-Stumpf A, Vogel M, Hiemisch A, Thiery J, Burkhardt R, Kratzsch J, Kiess W. Pediatric reference data of serum lipids and prevalence of dyslipidemia: Results from a population-based cohort in Germany. Clin Biochem. 2016 Jul;49(10-11):740-9. doi: 10.1016/j.clinbiochem.2016.02.010. Epub 2016 Mar 4.</citation>
    <PMID>26948098</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Klamt S, Vogel M, Kapellen TM, Hiemisch A, Prenzel F, Zachariae S, Ceglarek U, Thiery J, Kiess W. Association between IgE-mediated allergies and diabetes mellitus type 1 in children and adolescents. Pediatr Diabetes. 2015 Nov;16(7):493-503. doi: 10.1111/pedi.12298. Epub 2015 Jul 17.</citation>
    <PMID>26189407</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Quante M, Bruckmann S, Wallborn T, Wolf N, Sergeyev E, Adler M, Hesse M, Geserick M, Naumann S, Koch C, Nivarthi H, Engel C, Körner A, Kiess W, Hiemisch A; LIFE Child Study Investigators. Managing incidental findings and disclosure of results in a paediatric research cohort - the LIFE Child Study cohort. J Pediatr Endocrinol Metab. 2015 Jan;28(1-2):75-82. doi: 10.1515/jpem-2014-0079.</citation>
    <PMID>24695037</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>July 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>December 15, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 11, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 15, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 10, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 10, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 12, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Leipzig</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Antje Koerner, Prof. Dr. med.</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Prof. Dr. med. Antje Körner</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Children</keyword>
  <keyword>Obesity</keyword>
  <keyword>Pregnancy</keyword>
  <keyword>Growth</keyword>
  <keyword>Lifestyle</keyword>
  <keyword>Metabolic and cardiovascular health</keyword>
  <keyword>Birth</keyword>
  <keyword>Development</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pediatric Obesity</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

