<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02554682</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>15-011732</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02554682</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The P4 Intervention Study to Improve Adolescent Health</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Pilot Efficacy and Implementation Study of the Patients, Parents and Professionals Partnering to Improve Adolescent Health (P4) Intervention</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Children's Hospital of Philadelphia</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Children's Hospital of Philadelphia</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The primary objective is to conduct a pilot study to determine the efficacy of evidence-based
      interventions delivered in primary care clinic settings on parent-teen health communication.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Primary care provides a means by which to connect evidence-based interventions with patients;
      however, many interventions have been evaluated using randomized controlled trials (RCTs) in
      non-healthcare settings.

      The primary objective is to conduct a pilot study to determine the effect of evidence-based
      interventions delivered in primary care clinic settings on parent-teen communication about
      alcohol use, sexual health, and safe driving.

      Eligible participants are healthy adolescent patients from the Children's Hospital of
      Philadelphia (CHOP) primary care network with a well-child visit scheduled between the ages
      of 14 to 17 years with one parent willing to participate. Adolescents that hold an
      intermediate driver's license, that are pregnant, or that have pervasive development disorder
      or a developmental delay are excluded from this study.

      Parents will be given written psychoeducational intervention materials on communicating with
      their adolescents about alcohol use, sexual health, or safe driving (e.g.,booklets, tip sheet
      brochures, activity workbooks, web links), receive coaching about using the intervention
      materials, and provider endorsement of the materials during the well-child visit, as well as
      follow-up phone health coaching 2 weeks after the appointment.

      The primary endpoints are evaluating the difference between the intervention and control
      groups on parent-teen communication on the targeted health topics.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">April 10, 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">April 10, 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Factorial Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of Parent-teen Communication (General- All Groups)</measure>
    <time_frame>4-6 months post-enrollment</time_frame>
    <description>Parents completed the 20-item Parent-Adolescent Communication Scale (PACS) (Barnes &amp; Olson, 1985) which is scored such that a higher total score (sum of all items across scales) indicated better parent-adolescent communication. Teens answered the same questions, with only minor changes in wording when necessary. Scores were summed into an index that ranged from 41-96, α parent = 0.84, and 43-96, α teen = 0.87.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Frequency of Communication About Alcohol</measure>
    <time_frame>4-6 months post-enrollment</time_frame>
    <description>Frequency of communication about alcohol was measured with a single item followed by 4-point Likert-type response categories. Parents were asked: Since your teen's last well-child visit how much have you talked with your teen about alcohol? (Not at all (1), A little bit (2), Quite a bit (3), or A lot (4)). Teens were asked: Since your last well-child visit, how often have you and your (mother/father) talked about alcohol? (Never (1), Rarely (2), Sometimes (3), or Often (4)).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Frequency of Communication About Sex</measure>
    <time_frame>4-6 months post-enrollment</time_frame>
    <description>Frequency of communication about sex was measured with a single item followed by 4-point Likert-type response categories. Parents were asked: Since your teen's last well-child visit how much have you talked with your teen about sex? (Not at all (1), A little bit (2), Quite a bit (3), or A lot (4)). Teens were asked: Since your last well-child visit, how often have you and your (mother/father) talked about sex? (Never (1), Rarely (2), Sometimes (3), or Often (4)).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Parent-teen Communication About Reasons the Teen Wants to Drive</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months post-enrollment</time_frame>
    <description>Six months after baseline, parents reported on the frequency that they talked about reasons the teen wants to drive. Parents selected from one of the following response choices: &quot;never talked about&quot; (0); &quot;talked about once or twice&quot; (1); &quot;talked about three or four times&quot; (2); &quot;talked about a lot, about 5 times or more&quot; (3).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Parent-teen Communication About the Kinds of Risky Driving Situations That Might Come up in His or Her Friend Group</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months post-enrollment</time_frame>
    <description>Six months after baseline, parents reported on the frequency that they talked about the kinds of risky driving situations that might come up in his or her friend group. Parents selected from one of the following response choices: &quot;never talked about&quot; (0); &quot;talked about once or twice&quot; (1); &quot;talked about three or four times&quot; (2); &quot;talked about a lot, about 5 times or more&quot; (3).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Parent-teen Communication About Pennsylvania's Graduated Driver Licensing Laws</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months post-enrollment</time_frame>
    <description>Six months after baseline, parents reported on the frequency that they talked about about Pennsylvania's GDL laws. Parents selected from one of the following response choices: &quot;never talked about&quot; (0); &quot;talked about once or twice&quot; (1); &quot;talked about three or four times&quot; (2); &quot;talked about a lot, about 5 times or more&quot; (3).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Parent-teen Communication About Wearing a Seatbelt</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months post-enrollment</time_frame>
    <description>Six months after baseline, parents reported on the frequency that they talked about wearing a seatbelt. Parents selected from one of the following response choices: &quot;never talked about&quot; (0); &quot;talked about once or twice&quot; (1); &quot;talked about three or four times&quot; (2); &quot;talked about a lot, about 5 times or more&quot; (3).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Parent-teen Communication About Dangers of Distracted Driving</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months post-enrollment</time_frame>
    <description>Six months after baseline, parents reported on the frequency that they talked about dangers of distracted driving. Parents selected from one of the following response choices: &quot;never talked about&quot; (0); &quot;talked about once or twice&quot; (1); &quot;talked about three or four times&quot; (2); &quot;talked about a lot, about 5 times or more&quot; (3).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Parent-teen Communication About Being a Safe Passenger</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months post-enrollment</time_frame>
    <description>Six months after baseline, parents reported on the frequency that they talked about being a safe passenger. Parents selected from one of the following response choices: &quot;never talked about&quot; (0); &quot;talked about once or twice&quot; (1); &quot;talked about three or four times&quot; (2); &quot;talked about a lot, about 5 times or more&quot; (3).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Parent-teen Communication About What to do in a Crash</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months post-enrollment</time_frame>
    <description>Six months after baseline, parents reported on the frequency that they talked about what to do in a crash. Parents selected from one of the following response choices: &quot;never talked about&quot; (0); &quot;talked about once or twice&quot; (1); &quot;talked about three or four times&quot; (2); &quot;talked about a lot, about 5 times or more&quot; (3).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Parent-teen Communication About What to do if Stopped by a Police Officer</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months post-enrollment</time_frame>
    <description>Six months after baseline, parents reported on the frequency that they talked about what to do if stopped by a police officer. Parents selected from one of the following response choices: &quot;never talked about&quot; (0); &quot;talked about once or twice&quot; (1); &quot;talked about three or four times&quot; (2); &quot;talked about a lot, about 5 times or more&quot; (3).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Parent-teen Communication About Driving Under the Influence of Drugs or Alcohol</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months post-enrollment</time_frame>
    <description>Six months after baseline, parents reported on the frequency that they talked about driving under the influence of drugs or alcohol. Parents selected from one of the following response choices: &quot;never talked about&quot; (0); &quot;talked about once or twice&quot; (1); &quot;talked about three or four times&quot; (2); &quot;talked about a lot, about 5 times or more&quot; (3).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Parent-teen Communication About What to do if the Teen Needs a Safe Ride Home</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months post-enrollment</time_frame>
    <description>Six months after baseline, parents reported on the frequency that they talked about what to do if the teen needs a safe ride home. Parents selected from one of the following response choices: &quot;never talked about&quot; (0); &quot;talked about once or twice&quot; (1); &quot;talked about three or four times&quot; (2); &quot;talked about a lot, about 5 times or more&quot; (3).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Parent-teen Communication About Stopping a Friend From Driving Under the Influence of Drugs or Alcohol</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months post-enrollment</time_frame>
    <description>Six months after baseline, parents reported on the frequency that they talked about stopping a friend from driving under the influence of drugs or alcohol. Parents selected from one of the following response choices: &quot;never talked about&quot; (0); &quot;talked about once or twice&quot; (1); &quot;talked about three or four times&quot; (2); &quot;talked about a lot, about 5 times or more&quot; (3).stopping a friend from riding with a driver who is under the influence of drugs or alcohol</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Parent-teen Communication About Stopping a Friend From Riding With a Driver Who is Under the Influence of Drugs or Alcohol</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months post-enrollment</time_frame>
    <description>Six months after baseline, parents reported on the frequency that they talked about stopping a friend from riding with a driver who is under the influence of drugs or alcohol. Parents selected from one of the following response choices: &quot;never talked about&quot; (0); &quot;talked about once or twice&quot; (1); &quot;talked about three or four times&quot; (2); &quot;talked about a lot, about 5 times or more&quot; (3).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>5</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">348</enrollment>
  <condition>Adolescent Behavior</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sexual Health</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Parents of teens between the ages of 14 and 15 will review psychoeducational workbooks related to sexual health at a well-child visit appointment with the primary care giver (baseline); 2 weeks after baseline they will received a follow-up phone call and health coaching session to review the materials and ask questions; and then at 4 to 5 months post baseline we will collect data to assess the efficacy of the study materials.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Alcohol Prevention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Parents of teens between the ages of 14 and 15 will review psychoeducational workbooks related to alcohol prevention at a well-child visit appointment with the primary care giver (baseline); 2 weeks after baseline they will received a follow-up phone call and health coaching session to review the materials and ask questions; and then at 4 to 5 months post baseline we will collect data to assess the efficacy of the study materials.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sexual Health &amp; Alcohol Control Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Parents of teens between the ages of 14 and 15 will receive their usual care at their well-child visit appointment with their primary care giver (baseline) and then at 4 to 5 months post baseline we will collect data. At the end of the post data collection, the control group will get all of the study materials from both the sexual health and alcohol prevention groups.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Teen Driving</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Parents of teens between the ages of 16 and 17 who are planning on having the medical certification for the permit application completed and plan on taking their driving permit test in the next 8 weeks will review psychoeducational workbooks related to teen driving at a well-child visit appointment with the primary care giver (baseline); 2 weeks after baseline they will received a follow-up phone call and health coaching session to review the materials and ask questions; and then at 6 months post baseline we will collect data to assess the effectiveness of the study materials.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Teen Driving Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Parents of teens between the ages of 16 and 17 who are planning on having the medical certification for the permit application completed and plan on taking their driving permit test in the next 8 weeks will receive their usual care at their well-child visit appointment with their primary care giver (baseline) and then at 6 months post baseline we will collect data. At the end of the post data collection, the control group will get all of the study materials from the teen driving group.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sexual Health</intervention_name>
    <description>Psychoeducational workbook, worksheets, tip sheets, and health coaching session about sexual health, sexually transmitted disease (STD) prevention, and safe sex practices for teenager.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Sexual Health</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Alcohol Prevention</intervention_name>
    <description>Psychoeducational workbook, worksheets, tip sheets, and health coaching session about alcohol prevention and safety, underage drinking, and drinking and driving.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Alcohol Prevention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Teen Driving</intervention_name>
    <description>Psychoeducational workbook, worksheets, videos, tip sheets, and health coaching session about how parents can help supervise their teens' safe driving practices and how to talk with their teen about important safety topics for teen drivers.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Teen Driving</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. CHOP Primary Care patient

          2. Scheduled for a well-child visit that parent and teen both plan to attend within 3
             weeks of enrollment

          3. [Teen Driving Arm Only] Planning on having the medical certification for the permit
             application completed at their next well child visit and planning on taking their
             driving permit test in the next 8 weeks

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Not fluent in written or spoken English

          2. Developmental Delay or Pervasive Developmental Disorder

          3. Pregnant female

          4. [Teen Driving Arm Only] Already has driving permit (has taken and passed the knowledge
             test) and/or the medical certification for the permit application was not completed at
             the well child visit
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>14 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>17 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Carol A Ford, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Children's Hospital of Philadelphia</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The Children's Hospital of Philadelphia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19104</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kann L, Kinchen S, Shanklin SL, Flint KH, Kawkins J, Harris WA, Lowry R, Olsen EO, McManus T, Chyen D, Whittle L, Taylor E, Demissie Z, Brener N, Thornton J, Moore J, Zaza S; Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC). Youth risk behavior surveillance--United States, 2013. MMWR Suppl. 2014 Jun 13;63(4):1-168. Erratum in: MMWR Morb Wkly Rep. 2014 Jul 4;63(26):576.</citation>
    <PMID>24918634</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sales JM, Milhausen RR, Wingood GM, Diclemente RJ, Salazar LF, Crosby RA. Validation of a Parent-Adolescent Communication Scale for use in STD/HIV prevention interventions. Health Educ Behav. 2008 Jun;35(3):332-45. Epub 2006 Dec 15.</citation>
    <PMID>17200099</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ford CA, Cheek C, Culhane J, Fishman J, Mathew L, Salek EC, Webb D, Jaccard J. Parent and Adolescent Interest in Receiving Adolescent Health Communication Information From Primary Care Clinicians. J Adolesc Health. 2016 Aug;59(2):154-61. doi: 10.1016/j.jadohealth.2016.03.001. Epub 2016 Apr 14.</citation>
    <PMID>27151760</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ford CA, Davenport AF, Meier A, McRee AL. Partnerships between parents and health care professionals to improve adolescent health. J Adolesc Health. 2011 Jul;49(1):53-7. doi: 10.1016/j.jadohealth.2010.10.004. Epub 2011 Mar 12.</citation>
    <PMID>21700157</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Guilamo-Ramos V, Jaccard J, Turrisi R, Johansson M. Parental and school correlates of binge drinking among middle school students. Am J Public Health. 2005 May;95(5):894-9.</citation>
    <PMID>15855471</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Guilamo-Ramos V, Bouris A, Jaccard J, Gonzalez B, McCoy W, Aranda D. A parent-based intervention to reduce sexual risk behavior in early adolescence: building alliances between physicians, social workers, and parents. J Adolesc Health. 2011 Feb;48(2):159-63. doi: 10.1016/j.jadohealth.2010.06.007.</citation>
    <PMID>21257114</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hamilton BE, Martin JA, Ventura SJ. Births: preliminary data for 2009. Natl Vital Stat Rep. 2010 Dec;59(3):1-19.</citation>
    <PMID>25073731</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jaccard J, Dodge T, Dittus P. Parent-adolescent communication about sex and birth control: a conceptual framework. New Dir Child Adolesc Dev. 2002 Fall;(97):9-41. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>14964942</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kerr M, Stattin H. What parents know, how they know it, and several forms of adolescent adjustment: further support for a reinterpretation of monitoring. Dev Psychol. 2000 May;36(3):366-80.</citation>
    <PMID>10830980</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mayhew DR, Simpson HM, Pak A. Changes in collision rates among novice drivers during the first months of driving. Accid Anal Prev. 2003 Sep;35(5):683-91.</citation>
    <PMID>12850069</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>McCartt AT, Shabanova VI, Leaf WA. Driving experience, crashes and traffic citations of teenage beginning drivers. Accid Anal Prev. 2003 May;35(3):311-20.</citation>
    <PMID>12643948</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mirman JH, Curry AE, Winston FK, Wang W, Elliott MR, Schultheis MT, Fisher Thiel MC, Durbin DR. Effect of the teen driving plan on the driving performance of teenagers before licensure: a randomized clinical trial. JAMA Pediatr. 2014 Aug;168(8):764-71. doi: 10.1001/jamapediatrics.2014.252.</citation>
    <PMID>24957844</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mirman JH, Albert WD, Curry AE, Winston FK, Fisher Thiel MC, Durbin DR. TeenDrivingPlan effectiveness: the effect of quantity and diversity of supervised practice on teens' driving performance. J Adolesc Health. 2014 Nov;55(5):620-6. doi: 10.1016/j.jadohealth.2014.04.010. Epub 2014 Jun 9.</citation>
    <PMID>24925492</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Olson, D. H.. Family inventories: Inventories used in a national survey of families across the life cycle. St Paul, MN: Family Social Science, University of Minnesota. 1985</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Stattin H, Kerr M. Parental monitoring: a reinterpretation. Child Dev. 2000 Jul-Aug;71(4):1072-85.</citation>
    <PMID>11016567</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Turrisi R, Jaccard J, Taki R, Dunnam H, Grimes J. Examination of the short-term efficacy of a parent intervention to reduce college student drinking tendencies. Psychol Addict Behav. 2001 Dec;15(4):366-72.</citation>
    <PMID>11767270</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Weinstock H, Berman S, Cates W Jr. Sexually transmitted diseases among American youth: incidence and prevalence estimates, 2000. Perspect Sex Reprod Health. 2004 Jan-Feb;36(1):6-10.</citation>
    <PMID>14982671</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Winston FK, Mirman JH, Curry AE, Pfeiffer MR, Elliott MR, Durbin DR. Engagement with the TeenDrivingPlan and diversity of teens' supervised practice driving: lessons for internet-based learner driver interventions. Inj Prev. 2015 Feb;21(1):4-9. doi: 10.1136/injuryprev-2014-041212. Epub 2014 Jun 10.</citation>
    <PMID>24916684</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zimet G, Dahlem NV, Zimet SG, Farley GK. The multidimensional scale of perceived social support. Journal of Personality Assessment. 52;30-41. 1988.</citation>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 16, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 17, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 18, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <results_first_submitted>May 18, 2018</results_first_submitted>
  <results_first_submitted_qc>December 10, 2018</results_first_submitted_qc>
  <results_first_posted type="Actual">March 25, 2019</results_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 2, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 2, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 10, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Adolescent Health</keyword>
  <keyword>Sexual Health</keyword>
  <keyword>Parent-Teen Communication</keyword>
  <keyword>Teen Driving</keyword>
  <keyword>Alcohol Prevention</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <provided_document_section>
    <provided_document>
      <document_type>Study Protocol and Statistical Analysis Plan</document_type>
      <document_has_protocol>Yes</document_has_protocol>
      <document_has_icf>No</document_has_icf>
      <document_has_sap>Yes</document_has_sap>
      <document_date>September 16, 2016</document_date>
      <document_url>https://ClinicalTrials.gov/ProvidedDocs/82/NCT02554682/Prot_SAP_000.pdf</document_url>
    </provided_document>
  </provided_document_section>

  <clinical_results>

    <participant_flow>
      <recruitment_details>Adolescents between 14 and 17 years of age with an upcoming well-child visit and a parent were recruited from January 2016 through September 2016 from one urban primary care practice in the Pediatrics Research Consortium (PeRC) at Children’s Hospital of Philadelphia (CHOP).</recruitment_details>
      <pre_assignment_details>A total of 425 parent-adolescent dyads were contacted and screened. Of these, 188 (44%) did not meet eligibility criteria, 26 (6%) declined, and 37 (9%) could not be scheduled or reached again. 174 participant dyads we randomized into one of the five assignment groups.</pre_assignment_details>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="P1">
          <title>Sexual Health (Teen)</title>
          <description>Teens between the ages of 14 and 15 will review psychoeducational workbooks related to sexual health at a well-child visit appointment with the primary care giver (baseline); 2 weeks after baseline they will received a follow-up phone call and health coaching session to review the materials and ask questions; and then at 4 to 5 months post baseline we will collect data to assess the efficacy of the study materials.
Sexual Health: Psychoeducational workbook, worksheets, tip sheets, and health coaching session about sexual health, sexually transmitted disease (STD) prevention, and safe sex practices for teenager.</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="P2">
          <title>Sexual Health (Parent)</title>
          <description>Parents of teens between the ages of 14 and 15 will review psychoeducational workbooks related to sexual health at a well-child visit appointment with the primary care giver (baseline); 2 weeks after baseline they will received a follow-up phone call and health coaching session to review the materials and ask questions; and then at 4 to 5 months post baseline we will collect data to assess the efficacy of the study materials.
Sexual Health: Psychoeducational workbook, worksheets, tip sheets, and health coaching session about sexual health, sexually transmitted disease (STD) prevention, and safe sex practices for teenager.</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="P3">
          <title>Alcohol Prevention (Teen)</title>
          <description>Teens between the ages of 14 and 15 will review psychoeducational workbooks related to alcohol prevention at a well-child visit appointment with the primary care giver (baseline); 2 weeks after baseline they will received a follow-up phone call and health coaching session to review the materials and ask questions; and then at 4 to 5 months post baseline we will collect data to assess the efficacy of the study materials.
Alcohol Prevention: Psychoeducational workbook, worksheets, tip sheets, and health coaching session about alcohol prevention and safety, underage drinking, and drinking and driving.</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="P4">
          <title>Alcohol Prevention (Parent)</title>
          <description>Parents of teens between the ages of 14 and 15 will review psychoeducational workbooks related to alcohol prevention at a well-child visit appointment with the primary care giver (baseline); 2 weeks after baseline they will received a follow-up phone call and health coaching session to review the materials and ask questions; and then at 4 to 5 months post baseline we will collect data to assess the efficacy of the study materials.
Alcohol Prevention: Psychoeducational workbook, worksheets, tip sheets, and health coaching session about alcohol prevention and safety, underage drinking, and drinking and driving.</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="P5">
          <title>Sexual Health &amp; Alcohol Control Group (Teen)</title>
          <description>Teens between the ages of 14 and 15 will receive their usual care at their well-child visit appointment with their primary care giver (baseline) and then at 4 to 5 months post baseline we will collect data. At the end of the post data collection, the control group will get all of the study materials from both the sexual health and alcohol prevention groups.</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="P6">
          <title>Sexual Health &amp; Alcohol Group (Parent)</title>
          <description>Parents of teens between the ages of 14 and 15 will receive their usual care at their well-child visit appointment with their primary care giver (baseline) and then at 4 to 5 months post baseline we will collect data. At the end of the post data collection, the control group will get all of the study materials from both the sexual health and alcohol prevention groups.</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="P7">
          <title>Teen Driving (Teen)</title>
          <description>Teens between the ages of 16 and 17 who are planning on having the medical certification for the permit application completed and plan on taking their driving permit test in the next 8 weeks will review psychoeducational workbooks related to teen driving at a well-child visit appointment with the primary care giver (baseline); 2 weeks after baseline they will received a follow-up phone call and health coaching session to review the materials and ask questions; and then at 6 months post baseline we will collect data to assess the effectiveness of the study materials.
Teen Driving: Psychoeducational workbook, worksheets, videos, tip sheets, and health coaching session about how parents can help supervise their teens' safe driving practices and how to talk with their teen about important safety topics for teen drivers.</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="P8">
          <title>Teen Driving (Parent)</title>
          <description>Parents of teens between the ages of 16 and 17 who are planning on having the medical certification for the permit application completed and plan on taking their driving permit test in the next 8 weeks will review psychoeducational workbooks related to teen driving at a well-child visit appointment with the primary care giver (baseline); 2 weeks after baseline they will received a follow-up phone call and health coaching session to review the materials and ask questions; and then at 6 months post baseline we will collect data to assess the effectiveness of the study materials.
Teen Driving: Psychoeducational workbook, worksheets, videos, tip sheets, and health coaching session about how parents can help supervise their teens' safe driving practices and how to talk with their teen about important safety topics for teen drivers.</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="P9">
          <title>Teen Driving Control (Teen)</title>
          <description>Parents of teens between the ages of 16 and 17 who are planning on having the medical certification for the permit application completed and plan on taking their driving permit test in the next 8 weeks will receive their usual care at their well-child visit appointment with their primary care giver (baseline) and then at 6 months post baseline we will collect data. At the end of the post data collection, the control group will get all of the study materials from the teen driving group.</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="P10">
          <title>Teen Driving Control (Parent)</title>
          <description>Teens between the ages of 16 and 17 who are planning on having the medical certification for the permit application completed and plan on taking their driving permit test in the next 8 weeks will receive their usual care at their well-child visit appointment with their primary care giver (baseline) and then at 6 months post baseline we will collect data. At the end of the post data collection, the control group will get all of the study materials from the teen driving group.</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <period_list>
        <period>
          <title>Overall Study</title>
          <milestone_list>
            <milestone>
              <title>STARTED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="40"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="40"/>
                <participants group_id="P3" count="40"/>
                <participants group_id="P4" count="40"/>
                <participants group_id="P5" count="40"/>
                <participants group_id="P6" count="40"/>
                <participants group_id="P7" count="28"/>
                <participants group_id="P8" count="28"/>
                <participants group_id="P9" count="26"/>
                <participants group_id="P10" count="26"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>COMPLETED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="25"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="28"/>
                <participants group_id="P3" count="36"/>
                <participants group_id="P4" count="37"/>
                <participants group_id="P5" count="38"/>
                <participants group_id="P6" count="39"/>
                <participants group_id="P7" count="22"/>
                <participants group_id="P8" count="22"/>
                <participants group_id="P9" count="24"/>
                <participants group_id="P10" count="24"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>NOT COMPLETED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="15"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="12"/>
                <participants group_id="P3" count="4"/>
                <participants group_id="P4" count="3"/>
                <participants group_id="P5" count="2"/>
                <participants group_id="P6" count="1"/>
                <participants group_id="P7" count="6"/>
                <participants group_id="P8" count="6"/>
                <participants group_id="P9" count="2"/>
                <participants group_id="P10" count="2"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
          </milestone_list>
          <drop_withdraw_reason_list>
            <drop_withdraw_reason>
              <title>Lost to Follow-up</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="11"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="9"/>
                <participants group_id="P3" count="4"/>
                <participants group_id="P4" count="3"/>
                <participants group_id="P5" count="2"/>
                <participants group_id="P6" count="1"/>
                <participants group_id="P7" count="6"/>
                <participants group_id="P8" count="6"/>
                <participants group_id="P9" count="2"/>
                <participants group_id="P10" count="2"/>
              </participants_list>
            </drop_withdraw_reason>
            <drop_withdraw_reason>
              <title>Withdrawal by Subject</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="2"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="1"/>
                <participants group_id="P3" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P4" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P5" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P6" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P7" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P8" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P9" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P10" count="0"/>
              </participants_list>
            </drop_withdraw_reason>
            <drop_withdraw_reason>
              <title>Physician Decision</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="2"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="2"/>
                <participants group_id="P3" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P4" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P5" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P6" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P7" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P8" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P9" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P10" count="0"/>
              </participants_list>
            </drop_withdraw_reason>
          </drop_withdraw_reason_list>
        </period>
      </period_list>
    </participant_flow>

    <baseline>
      <population>One sexual health dyad (2 participants) never completed Baseline so was withdrawn by PI. Another sexual health dyad (2 participants) was withdrawn by PI after the teen had difficulty completing study procedures due to cognitive delays.</population>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="B1">
          <title>Sexual Health (Teen)</title>
          <description>Teens between the ages of 14 and 15 will review psychoeducational workbooks related to sexual health at a well-child visit appointment with the primary care giver (baseline); 2 weeks after baseline they will received a follow-up phone call and health coaching session to review the materials and ask questions; and then at 4 to 5 months post baseline we will collect data to assess the efficacy of the study materials.
Sexual Health: Psychoeducational workbook, worksheets, tip sheets, and health coaching session about sexual health, sexually transmitted disease (STD) prevention, and safe sex practices for teenager.</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="B2">
          <title>Sexual Health (Parent)</title>
          <description>Parents of teens between the ages of 14 and 15 will review psychoeducational workbooks related to sexual health at a well-child visit appointment with the primary care giver (baseline); 2 weeks after baseline they will received a follow-up phone call and health coaching session to review the materials and ask questions; and then at 4 to 5 months post baseline we will collect data to assess the efficacy of the study materials.
Sexual Health: Psychoeducational workbook, worksheets, tip sheets, and health coaching session about sexual health, sexually transmitted disease (STD) prevention, and safe sex practices for teenager.</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="B3">
          <title>Alcohol Prevention (Teen)</title>
          <description>Teens between the ages of 14 and 15 will review psychoeducational workbooks related to alcohol prevention at a well-child visit appointment with the primary care giver (baseline); 2 weeks after baseline they will received a follow-up phone call and health coaching session to review the materials and ask questions; and then at 4 to 5 months post baseline we will collect data to assess the efficacy of the study materials.
Alcohol Prevention: Psychoeducational workbook, worksheets, tip sheets, and health coaching session about alcohol prevention and safety, underage drinking, and drinking and driving.</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="B4">
          <title>Alcohol Prevention (Parent)</title>
          <description>Parents of teens between the ages of 14 and 15 will review psychoeducational workbooks related to alcohol prevention at a well-child visit appointment with the primary care giver (baseline); 2 weeks after baseline they will received a follow-up phone call and health coaching session to review the materials and ask questions; and then at 4 to 5 months post baseline we will collect data to assess the efficacy of the study materials.
Alcohol Prevention: Psychoeducational workbook, worksheets, tip sheets, and health coaching session about alcohol prevention and safety, underage drinking, and drinking and driving.</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="B5">
          <title>Sexual Health &amp; Alcohol Control Group (Teen)</title>
          <description>Teens between the ages of 14 and 15 will receive their usual care at their well-child visit appointment with their primary care giver (baseline) and then at 4 to 5 months post baseline we will collect data. At the end of the post data collection, the control group will get all of the study materials from both the sexual health and alcohol prevention groups.</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="B6">
          <title>Sexual Health &amp; Alcohol Control Group (Parent)</title>
          <description>Parents of teens between the ages of 14 and 15 will receive their usual care at their well-child visit appointment with their primary care giver (baseline) and then at 4 to 5 months post baseline we will collect data. At the end of the post data collection, the control group will get all of the study materials from both the sexual health and alcohol prevention groups.</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="B7">
          <title>Teen Driving (Teen)</title>
          <description>Teens between the ages of 16 and 17 who are planning on having the medical certification for the permit application completed and plan on taking their driving permit test in the next 8 weeks will review psychoeducational workbooks related to teen driving at a well-child visit appointment with the primary care giver (baseline); 2 weeks after baseline they will received a follow-up phone call and health coaching session to review the materials and ask questions; and then at 6 months post baseline we will collect data to assess the effectiveness of the study materials.
Teen Driving: Psychoeducational workbook, worksheets, videos, tip sheets, and health coaching session about how parents can help supervise their teens' safe driving practices and how to talk with their teen about important safety topics for teen drivers.</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="B8">
          <title>Teen Driving (Parent)</title>
          <description>Parents of teens between the ages of 16 and 17 who are planning on having the medical certification for the permit application completed and plan on taking their driving permit test in the next 8 weeks will review psychoeducational workbooks related to teen driving at a well-child visit appointment with the primary care giver (baseline); 2 weeks after baseline they will received a follow-up phone call and health coaching session to review the materials and ask questions; and then at 6 months post baseline we will collect data to assess the effectiveness of the study materials.
Teen Driving: Psychoeducational workbook, worksheets, videos, tip sheets, and health coaching session about how parents can help supervise their teens' safe driving practices and how to talk with their teen about important safety topics for teen drivers.</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="B9">
          <title>Teen Driving Control (Teens)</title>
          <description>Teens between the ages of 16 and 17 who are planning on having the medical certification for the permit application completed and plan on taking their driving permit test in the next 8 weeks will receive their usual care at their well-child visit appointment with their primary care giver (baseline) and then at 6 months post baseline we will collect data. At the end of the post data collection, the control group will get all of the study materials from the teen driving group.</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="B10">
          <title>Teen Driving Control (Parent)</title>
          <description>Parents of teens between the ages of 16 and 17 who are planning on having the medical certification for the permit application completed and plan on taking their driving permit test in the next 8 weeks will receive their usual care at their well-child visit appointment with their primary care giver (baseline) and then at 6 months post baseline we will collect data. At the end of the post data collection, the control group will get all of the study materials from the teen driving group.</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="B11">
          <title>Total</title>
          <description>Total of all reporting groups</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <analyzed_list>
        <analyzed>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <scope>Overall</scope>
          <count_list>
            <count group_id="B1" value="38"/>
            <count group_id="B2" value="38"/>
            <count group_id="B3" value="40"/>
            <count group_id="B4" value="40"/>
            <count group_id="B5" value="40"/>
            <count group_id="B6" value="40"/>
            <count group_id="B7" value="28"/>
            <count group_id="B8" value="28"/>
            <count group_id="B9" value="26"/>
            <count group_id="B10" value="26"/>
            <count group_id="B11" value="344"/>
          </count_list>
        </analyzed>
      </analyzed_list>
      <measure_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Age</title>
          <description>Baseline characteristics were collected via survey.</description>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <param>Count of Participants</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <title>&lt;=18 years</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="38"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="40"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B4" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B5" value="40"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B6" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B7" value="28"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B8" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B9" value="26"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B10" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B11" value="172"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Between 18 and 65 years</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="37"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B4" value="40"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B5" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B6" value="40"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B7" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B8" value="28"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B9" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B10" value="25"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B11" value="170"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>&gt;=65 years</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="1"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B4" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B5" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B6" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B7" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B8" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B9" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B10" value="1"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B11" value="2"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Age</title>
          <units>years</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>Standard Deviation</dispersion>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="14.71" spread=".53"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="45.13" spread="8.6"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="14.83" spread=".53"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B4" value="45.20" spread="5.8"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B5" value="15.05" spread=".58"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B6" value="47.05" spread="5.9"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B7" value="16.81" spread=".56"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B8" value="46.57" spread="7.88"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B9" value="16.40" spread=".40"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B10" value="49.58" spread="8.50"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B11" value="31.13" spread="16.47"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Sex: Female, Male</title>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <param>Count of Participants</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <title>Female</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="18"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="35"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="21"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B4" value="39"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B5" value="21"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B6" value="38"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B7" value="14"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B8" value="28"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B9" value="13"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B10" value="23"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B11" value="250"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Male</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="20"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="3"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="19"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B4" value="1"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B5" value="19"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B6" value="2"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B7" value="14"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B8" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B9" value="13"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B10" value="3"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B11" value="94"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Race (NIH/OMB)</title>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <param>Count of Participants</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <title>American Indian or Alaska Native</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="2"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B4" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B5" value="1"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B6" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B7" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B8" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B9" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B10" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B11" value="3"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Asian</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="1"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="1"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B4" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B5" value="1"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B6" value="1"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B7" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B8" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B9" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B10" value="1"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B11" value="5"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Native Hawaiian or Other Pacific Islander</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B4" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B5" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B6" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B7" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B8" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B9" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B10" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B11" value="0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Black or African American</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="19"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="20"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="22"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B4" value="22"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B5" value="19"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B6" value="20"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B7" value="24"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B8" value="19"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B9" value="18"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B10" value="17"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B11" value="200"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>White</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="16"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="17"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="13"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B4" value="15"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B5" value="18"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B6" value="18"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B7" value="4"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B8" value="4"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B9" value="7"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B10" value="6"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B11" value="118"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>More than one race</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="2"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="1"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="2"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B4" value="3"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B5" value="1"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B6" value="1"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B7" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B8" value="4"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B9" value="1"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B10" value="2"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B11" value="17"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Unknown or Not Reported</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B4" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B5" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B6" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B7" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B8" value="1"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B9" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B10" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B11" value="1"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Region of Enrollment</title>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <param>Count of Participants</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>United States</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="38"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="38"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="40"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B4" value="40"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B5" value="40"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B6" value="40"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B7" value="28"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B8" value="28"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B9" value="26"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B10" value="26"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B11" value="344"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </measure_list>
    </baseline>

    <outcome_list>
      <outcome>
        <type>Primary</type>
        <title>Quality of Parent-teen Communication (General- All Groups)</title>
        <description>Parents completed the 20-item Parent-Adolescent Communication Scale (PACS) (Barnes &amp; Olson, 1985) which is scored such that a higher total score (sum of all items across scales) indicated better parent-adolescent communication. Teens answered the same questions, with only minor changes in wording when necessary. Scores were summed into an index that ranged from 41-96, α parent = 0.84, and 43-96, α teen = 0.87.</description>
        <time_frame>4-6 months post-enrollment</time_frame>
        <population>Arm 1 only. Parents and teens analyzed separately. Arm 2 (teen driving) had different primary outcomes (see outcomes 4-15) and therefore was not included here.</population>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Sexual Health (Parent)</title>
            <description>Parents of teens between the ages of 14 and 15 will review psychoeducational workbooks related to sexual health at a well-child visit appointment with the primary care giver (baseline); 2 weeks after baseline they will received a follow-up phone call and health coaching session to review the materials and ask questions; and then at 4 to 5 months post baseline we will collect data to assess the efficacy of the study materials.
Sexual Health: Psychoeducational workbook, worksheets, tip sheets, and health coaching session about sexual health, sexually transmitted disease (STD) prevention, and safe sex practices for teenager.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>Sexual Health (Teen)</title>
            <description>Teens between the ages of 14 and 15 will review psychoeducational workbooks related to sexual health at a well-child visit appointment with the primary care giver (baseline); 2 weeks after baseline they will received a follow-up phone call and health coaching session to review the materials and ask questions; and then at 4 to 5 months post baseline we will collect data to assess the efficacy of the study materials.
Sexual Health: Psychoeducational workbook, worksheets, tip sheets, and health coaching session about sexual health, sexually transmitted disease (STD) prevention, and safe sex practices for teenager.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O3">
            <title>Alcohol Prevention (Parent)</title>
            <description>Parents of teens between the ages of 14 and 15 will review psychoeducational workbooks related to alcohol prevention at a well-child visit appointment with the primary care giver (baseline); 2 weeks after baseline they will received a follow-up phone call and health coaching session to review the materials and ask questions; and then at 4 to 5 months post baseline we will collect data to assess the efficacy of the study materials.
Alcohol Prevention: Psychoeducational workbook, worksheets, tip sheets, and health coaching session about alcohol prevention and safety, underage drinking, and drinking and driving.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O4">
            <title>Alcohol (Teen)</title>
            <description>Parents of teens between the ages of 14 and 15 will review psychoeducational workbooks related to alcohol prevention at a well-child visit appointment with the primary care giver (baseline); 2 weeks after baseline they will received a follow-up phone call and health coaching session to review the materials and ask questions; and then at 4 to 5 months post baseline we will collect data to assess the efficacy of the study materials.
Alcohol Prevention: Psychoeducational workbook, worksheets, tip sheets, and health coaching session about alcohol prevention and safety, underage drinking, and drinking and driving.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O5">
            <title>Sexual Health &amp; Alcohol Control Group (Parent)</title>
            <description>Parents of teens between the ages of 14 and 15 will receive their usual care at their well-child visit appointment with their primary care giver (baseline) and then at 4 to 5 months post baseline we will collect data. At the end of the post data collection, the control group will get all of the study materials from both the sexual health and alcohol prevention groups.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O6">
            <title>Sexual Health and Alcohol Control Group (Teen)</title>
            <description>Parents of teens between the ages of 14 and 15 will receive their usual care at their well-child visit appointment with their primary care giver (baseline) and then at 4 to 5 months post baseline we will collect data. At the end of the post data collection, the control group will get all of the study materials from both the sexual health and alcohol prevention groups.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Quality of Parent-teen Communication (General- All Groups)</title>
          <description>Parents completed the 20-item Parent-Adolescent Communication Scale (PACS) (Barnes &amp; Olson, 1985) which is scored such that a higher total score (sum of all items across scales) indicated better parent-adolescent communication. Teens answered the same questions, with only minor changes in wording when necessary. Scores were summed into an index that ranged from 41-96, α parent = 0.84, and 43-96, α teen = 0.87.</description>
          <population>Arm 1 only. Parents and teens analyzed separately. Arm 2 (teen driving) had different primary outcomes (see outcomes 4-15) and therefore was not included here.</population>
          <units>units on a scale</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>Standard Deviation</dispersion>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="28"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="25"/>
                <count group_id="O3" value="37"/>
                <count group_id="O4" value="36"/>
                <count group_id="O5" value="39"/>
                <count group_id="O6" value="38"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="77.8" spread="10.5"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="73.0" spread="9.4"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O3" value="77.2" spread="8.6"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O4" value="69.1" spread="8.4"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O5" value="77.4" spread="10.3"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O6" value="68.6" spread="11.1"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <analysis_list>
          <analysis>
            <group_id_list>
              <group_id>O3</group_id>
              <group_id>O5</group_id>
            </group_id_list>
            <non_inferiority_type>Superiority</non_inferiority_type>
            <p_value>.906</p_value>
            <method>Generalized Linear Model</method>
          </analysis>
          <analysis>
            <group_id_list>
              <group_id>O4</group_id>
              <group_id>O6</group_id>
            </group_id_list>
            <non_inferiority_type>Superiority</non_inferiority_type>
            <p_value>.796</p_value>
            <method>Generalized Linear Model</method>
          </analysis>
          <analysis>
            <group_id_list>
              <group_id>O1</group_id>
              <group_id>O5</group_id>
            </group_id_list>
            <non_inferiority_type>Superiority</non_inferiority_type>
            <p_value>.886</p_value>
            <method>Generalized Linear Model</method>
          </analysis>
          <analysis>
            <group_id_list>
              <group_id>O2</group_id>
              <group_id>O6</group_id>
            </group_id_list>
            <non_inferiority_type>Other</non_inferiority_type>
            <p_value>.082</p_value>
            <method>Generalized Linear Model</method>
          </analysis>
        </analysis_list>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Primary</type>
        <title>Frequency of Communication About Alcohol</title>
        <description>Frequency of communication about alcohol was measured with a single item followed by 4-point Likert-type response categories. Parents were asked: Since your teen's last well-child visit how much have you talked with your teen about alcohol? (Not at all (1), A little bit (2), Quite a bit (3), or A lot (4)). Teens were asked: Since your last well-child visit, how often have you and your (mother/father) talked about alcohol? (Never (1), Rarely (2), Sometimes (3), or Often (4)).</description>
        <time_frame>4-6 months post-enrollment</time_frame>
        <population>Arm 1 only. Parents and teens analyzed separately. Arm 2 (teen driving) had different primary outcomes (see outcomes 4-15) and therefore was not included here.</population>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Sexual Health (Teen)</title>
            <description>Teens between the ages of 14 and 15 will review psychoeducational workbooks related to sexual health at a well-child visit appointment with the primary care giver (baseline); 2 weeks after baseline they will received a follow-up phone call and health coaching session to review the materials and ask questions; and then at 4 to 5 months post baseline we will collect data to assess the efficacy of the study materials.
Sexual Health: Psychoeducational workbook, worksheets, tip sheets, and health coaching session about sexual health, sexually transmitted disease (STD) prevention, and safe sex practices for teenager.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>Sexual Health (Parent)</title>
            <description>Parents of teens between the ages of 14 and 15 will review psychoeducational workbooks related to sexual health at a well-child visit appointment with the primary care giver (baseline); 2 weeks after baseline they will received a follow-up phone call and health coaching session to review the materials and ask questions; and then at 4 to 5 months post baseline we will collect data to assess the efficacy of the study materials.
Sexual Health: Psychoeducational workbook, worksheets, tip sheets, and health coaching session about sexual health, sexually transmitted disease (STD) prevention, and safe sex practices for teenager.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O3">
            <title>Alcohol Prevention (Teen)</title>
            <description>Teens between the ages of 14 and 15 will review psychoeducational workbooks related to alcohol prevention at a well-child visit appointment with the primary care giver (baseline); 2 weeks after baseline they will received a follow-up phone call and health coaching session to review the materials and ask questions; and then at 4 to 5 months post baseline we will collect data to assess the efficacy of the study materials.
Alcohol Prevention: Psychoeducational workbook, worksheets, tip sheets, and health coaching session about alcohol prevention and safety, underage drinking, and drinking and driving.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O4">
            <title>Alcohol Prevention (Parent)</title>
            <description>Parents of teens between the ages of 14 and 15 will review psychoeducational workbooks related to alcohol prevention at a well-child visit appointment with the primary care giver (baseline); 2 weeks after baseline they will received a follow-up phone call and health coaching session to review the materials and ask questions; and then at 4 to 5 months post baseline we will collect data to assess the efficacy of the study materials.
Alcohol Prevention: Psychoeducational workbook, worksheets, tip sheets, and health coaching session about alcohol prevention and safety, underage drinking, and drinking and driving.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O5">
            <title>Sexual Health &amp; Alcohol Control Group (Teen)</title>
            <description>Teens between the ages of 14 and 15 will receive their usual care at their well-child visit appointment with their primary care giver (baseline) and then at 4 to 5 months post baseline we will collect data. At the end of the post data collection, the control group will get all of the study materials from both the sexual health and alcohol prevention groups.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O6">
            <title>Sexual Health &amp; Alcohol Group (Parent)</title>
            <description>Parents of teens between the ages of 14 and 15 will receive their usual care at their well-child visit appointment with their primary care giver (baseline) and then at 4 to 5 months post baseline we will collect data. At the end of the post data collection, the control group will get all of the study materials from both the sexual health and alcohol prevention groups.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Frequency of Communication About Alcohol</title>
          <description>Frequency of communication about alcohol was measured with a single item followed by 4-point Likert-type response categories. Parents were asked: Since your teen's last well-child visit how much have you talked with your teen about alcohol? (Not at all (1), A little bit (2), Quite a bit (3), or A lot (4)). Teens were asked: Since your last well-child visit, how often have you and your (mother/father) talked about alcohol? (Never (1), Rarely (2), Sometimes (3), or Often (4)).</description>
          <population>Arm 1 only. Parents and teens analyzed separately. Arm 2 (teen driving) had different primary outcomes (see outcomes 4-15) and therefore was not included here.</population>
          <units>units on a scale</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>Standard Deviation</dispersion>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="25"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="28"/>
                <count group_id="O3" value="36"/>
                <count group_id="O4" value="37"/>
                <count group_id="O5" value="38"/>
                <count group_id="O6" value="39"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="2.7" spread="1.0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="2.5" spread="0.8"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O3" value="2.9" spread="0.8"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O4" value="2.6" spread="0.8"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O5" value="2.4" spread="1.2"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O6" value="2.5" spread="0.9"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <analysis_list>
          <analysis>
            <group_id_list>
              <group_id>O4</group_id>
              <group_id>O6</group_id>
            </group_id_list>
            <non_inferiority_type>Superiority</non_inferiority_type>
            <p_value>0.677</p_value>
            <method>Generalized Linear Model</method>
          </analysis>
          <analysis>
            <group_id_list>
              <group_id>O3</group_id>
              <group_id>O5</group_id>
            </group_id_list>
            <non_inferiority_type>Superiority</non_inferiority_type>
            <p_value>0.020</p_value>
            <method>Generalized Linear Model</method>
          </analysis>
          <analysis>
            <group_id_list>
              <group_id>O2</group_id>
              <group_id>O6</group_id>
            </group_id_list>
            <non_inferiority_type>Superiority</non_inferiority_type>
            <p_value>.952</p_value>
            <method>Generalized Linear Model</method>
          </analysis>
          <analysis>
            <group_id_list>
              <group_id>O1</group_id>
              <group_id>O6</group_id>
            </group_id_list>
            <non_inferiority_type>Superiority</non_inferiority_type>
            <p_value>0.210</p_value>
            <method>Generalized Linear Model</method>
          </analysis>
        </analysis_list>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Primary</type>
        <title>Frequency of Communication About Sex</title>
        <description>Frequency of communication about sex was measured with a single item followed by 4-point Likert-type response categories. Parents were asked: Since your teen's last well-child visit how much have you talked with your teen about sex? (Not at all (1), A little bit (2), Quite a bit (3), or A lot (4)). Teens were asked: Since your last well-child visit, how often have you and your (mother/father) talked about sex? (Never (1), Rarely (2), Sometimes (3), or Often (4)).</description>
        <time_frame>4-6 months post-enrollment</time_frame>
        <population>Arm 1 only. Parents and teens analyzed separately. Arm 2 (teen driving) had different primary outcomes (see outcomes 4-15) and therefore was not included here.</population>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Sexual Health (Teen)</title>
            <description>Teens between the ages of 14 and 15 will review psychoeducational workbooks related to sexual health at a well-child visit appointment with the primary care giver (baseline); 2 weeks after baseline they will received a follow-up phone call and health coaching session to review the materials and ask questions; and then at 4 to 5 months post baseline we will collect data to assess the efficacy of the study materials.
Sexual Health: Psychoeducational workbook, worksheets, tip sheets, and health coaching session about sexual health, sexually transmitted disease (STD) prevention, and safe sex practices for teenager.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>Sexual Health (Parent)</title>
            <description>Parents of teens between the ages of 14 and 15 will review psychoeducational workbooks related to sexual health at a well-child visit appointment with the primary care giver (baseline); 2 weeks after baseline they will received a follow-up phone call and health coaching session to review the materials and ask questions; and then at 4 to 5 months post baseline we will collect data to assess the efficacy of the study materials.
Sexual Health: Psychoeducational workbook, worksheets, tip sheets, and health coaching session about sexual health, sexually transmitted disease (STD) prevention, and safe sex practices for teenager.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O3">
            <title>Alcohol Prevention (Teen)</title>
            <description>Teens between the ages of 14 and 15 will review psychoeducational workbooks related to alcohol prevention at a well-child visit appointment with the primary care giver (baseline); 2 weeks after baseline they will received a follow-up phone call and health coaching session to review the materials and ask questions; and then at 4 to 5 months post baseline we will collect data to assess the efficacy of the study materials.
Alcohol Prevention: Psychoeducational workbook, worksheets, tip sheets, and health coaching session about alcohol prevention and safety, underage drinking, and drinking and driving.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O4">
            <title>Alcohol Prevention (Parent)</title>
            <description>Parents of teens between the ages of 14 and 15 will review psychoeducational workbooks related to alcohol prevention at a well-child visit appointment with the primary care giver (baseline); 2 weeks after baseline they will received a follow-up phone call and health coaching session to review the materials and ask questions; and then at 4 to 5 months post baseline we will collect data to assess the efficacy of the study materials.
Alcohol Prevention: Psychoeducational workbook, worksheets, tip sheets, and health coaching session about alcohol prevention and safety, underage drinking, and drinking and driving.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O5">
            <title>Sexual Health &amp; Alcohol Control Group (Teen)</title>
            <description>Teens between the ages of 14 and 15 will receive their usual care at their well-child visit appointment with their primary care giver (baseline) and then at 4 to 5 months post baseline we will collect data. At the end of the post data collection, the control group will get all of the study materials from both the sexual health and alcohol prevention groups.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O6">
            <title>Sexual Health &amp; Alcohol Group (Parent)</title>
            <description>Parents of teens between the ages of 14 and 15 will receive their usual care at their well-child visit appointment with their primary care giver (baseline) and then at 4 to 5 months post baseline we will collect data. At the end of the post data collection, the control group will get all of the study materials from both the sexual health and alcohol prevention groups.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Frequency of Communication About Sex</title>
          <description>Frequency of communication about sex was measured with a single item followed by 4-point Likert-type response categories. Parents were asked: Since your teen's last well-child visit how much have you talked with your teen about sex? (Not at all (1), A little bit (2), Quite a bit (3), or A lot (4)). Teens were asked: Since your last well-child visit, how often have you and your (mother/father) talked about sex? (Never (1), Rarely (2), Sometimes (3), or Often (4)).</description>
          <population>Arm 1 only. Parents and teens analyzed separately. Arm 2 (teen driving) had different primary outcomes (see outcomes 4-15) and therefore was not included here.</population>
          <units>units on a scale</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>Standard Deviation</dispersion>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="25"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="28"/>
                <count group_id="O3" value="36"/>
                <count group_id="O4" value="37"/>
                <count group_id="O5" value="38"/>
                <count group_id="O6" value="39"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="2.3" spread="0.8"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="2.8" spread="0.8"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O3" value="2.1" spread="1.1"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O4" value="2.3" spread="0.9"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O5" value="1.8" spread="0.8"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O6" value="2.4" spread="1.0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <analysis_list>
          <analysis>
            <group_id_list>
              <group_id>O4</group_id>
              <group_id>O6</group_id>
            </group_id_list>
            <non_inferiority_type>Superiority</non_inferiority_type>
            <p_value>0.505</p_value>
            <method>Generalized Linear Model</method>
          </analysis>
          <analysis>
            <group_id_list>
              <group_id>O3</group_id>
              <group_id>O5</group_id>
            </group_id_list>
            <non_inferiority_type>Superiority</non_inferiority_type>
            <p_value>.176</p_value>
            <method>Generalized Linear Model</method>
          </analysis>
          <analysis>
            <group_id_list>
              <group_id>O2</group_id>
              <group_id>O6</group_id>
            </group_id_list>
            <non_inferiority_type>Superiority</non_inferiority_type>
            <p_value>0.134</p_value>
            <method>Generalized Linear Model</method>
          </analysis>
          <analysis>
            <group_id_list>
              <group_id>O1</group_id>
              <group_id>O5</group_id>
            </group_id_list>
            <non_inferiority_type>Superiority</non_inferiority_type>
            <p_value>0.029</p_value>
            <method>Generalized Linear Model</method>
          </analysis>
        </analysis_list>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Primary</type>
        <title>Parent-teen Communication About Reasons the Teen Wants to Drive</title>
        <description>Six months after baseline, parents reported on the frequency that they talked about reasons the teen wants to drive. Parents selected from one of the following response choices: &quot;never talked about&quot; (0); &quot;talked about once or twice&quot; (1); &quot;talked about three or four times&quot; (2); &quot;talked about a lot, about 5 times or more&quot; (3).</description>
        <time_frame>6 months post-enrollment</time_frame>
        <population>Parent Population</population>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Teen Driving (Parents)</title>
            <description>Parents of teens between the ages of 16 and 17 who are planning on having the medical certification for the permit application completed and plan on taking their driving permit test in the next 8 weeks will review psychoeducational workbooks related to teen driving at a well-child visit appointment with the primary care giver (baseline); 2 weeks after baseline they will received a follow-up phone call and health coaching session to review the materials and ask questions; and then at 6 months post baseline we will collect data to assess the effectiveness of the study materials.
Teen Driving: Psychoeducational workbook, worksheets, videos, tip sheets, and health coaching session about how parents can help supervise their teens' safe driving practices and how to talk with their teen about important safety topics for teen drivers.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>Teen Driving Control (Parents)</title>
            <description>Parents of teens between the ages of 16 and 17 who are planning on having the medical certification for the permit application completed and plan on taking their driving permit test in the next 8 weeks will receive their usual care at their well-child visit appointment with their primary care giver (baseline) and then at 6 months post baseline we will collect data. At the end of the post data collection, the control group will get all of the study materials from the teen driving group.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Parent-teen Communication About Reasons the Teen Wants to Drive</title>
          <description>Six months after baseline, parents reported on the frequency that they talked about reasons the teen wants to drive. Parents selected from one of the following response choices: &quot;never talked about&quot; (0); &quot;talked about once or twice&quot; (1); &quot;talked about three or four times&quot; (2); &quot;talked about a lot, about 5 times or more&quot; (3).</description>
          <population>Parent Population</population>
          <units>units on a scale</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>Standard Deviation</dispersion>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="22"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="24"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="2.32" spread=".89"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="1.75" spread=".90"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <analysis_list>
          <analysis>
            <group_id_list>
              <group_id>O1</group_id>
              <group_id>O2</group_id>
            </group_id_list>
            <non_inferiority_type>Superiority</non_inferiority_type>
            <p_value>.037</p_value>
            <method>t-test, 2 sided</method>
          </analysis>
        </analysis_list>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Primary</type>
        <title>Parent-teen Communication About the Kinds of Risky Driving Situations That Might Come up in His or Her Friend Group</title>
        <description>Six months after baseline, parents reported on the frequency that they talked about the kinds of risky driving situations that might come up in his or her friend group. Parents selected from one of the following response choices: &quot;never talked about&quot; (0); &quot;talked about once or twice&quot; (1); &quot;talked about three or four times&quot; (2); &quot;talked about a lot, about 5 times or more&quot; (3).</description>
        <time_frame>6 months post-enrollment</time_frame>
        <population>Parent Population</population>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Teen Driving (Parents)</title>
            <description>Parents of teens between the ages of 16 and 17 who are planning on having the medical certification for the permit application completed and plan on taking their driving permit test in the next 8 weeks will review psychoeducational workbooks related to teen driving at a well-child visit appointment with the primary care giver (baseline); 2 weeks after baseline they will received a follow-up phone call and health coaching session to review the materials and ask questions; and then at 6 months post baseline we will collect data to assess the effectiveness of the study materials.
Teen Driving: Psychoeducational workbook, worksheets, videos, tip sheets, and health coaching session about how parents can help supervise their teens' safe driving practices and how to talk with their teen about important safety topics for teen drivers.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>Teen Driving Control (Parents)</title>
            <description>Parents of teens between the ages of 16 and 17 who are planning on having the medical certification for the permit application completed and plan on taking their driving permit test in the next 8 weeks will receive their usual care at their well-child visit appointment with their primary care giver (baseline) and then at 6 months post baseline we will collect data. At the end of the post data collection, the control group will get all of the study materials from the teen driving group.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Parent-teen Communication About the Kinds of Risky Driving Situations That Might Come up in His or Her Friend Group</title>
          <description>Six months after baseline, parents reported on the frequency that they talked about the kinds of risky driving situations that might come up in his or her friend group. Parents selected from one of the following response choices: &quot;never talked about&quot; (0); &quot;talked about once or twice&quot; (1); &quot;talked about three or four times&quot; (2); &quot;talked about a lot, about 5 times or more&quot; (3).</description>
          <population>Parent Population</population>
          <units>units on a scale</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>Standard Deviation</dispersion>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="22"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="24"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="2.59" spread=".73"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="1.79" spread=".98"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <analysis_list>
          <analysis>
            <group_id_list>
              <group_id>O1</group_id>
              <group_id>O2</group_id>
            </group_id_list>
            <non_inferiority_type>Superiority</non_inferiority_type>
            <p_value>.003</p_value>
            <method>t-test, 2 sided</method>
          </analysis>
        </analysis_list>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Primary</type>
        <title>Parent-teen Communication About Pennsylvania's Graduated Driver Licensing Laws</title>
        <description>Six months after baseline, parents reported on the frequency that they talked about about Pennsylvania's GDL laws. Parents selected from one of the following response choices: &quot;never talked about&quot; (0); &quot;talked about once or twice&quot; (1); &quot;talked about three or four times&quot; (2); &quot;talked about a lot, about 5 times or more&quot; (3).</description>
        <time_frame>6 months post-enrollment</time_frame>
        <population>Parent Population</population>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Teen Driving (Parents)</title>
            <description>Parents of teens between the ages of 16 and 17 who are planning on having the medical certification for the permit application completed and plan on taking their driving permit test in the next 8 weeks will review psychoeducational workbooks related to teen driving at a well-child visit appointment with the primary care giver (baseline); 2 weeks after baseline they will received a follow-up phone call and health coaching session to review the materials and ask questions; and then at 6 months post baseline we will collect data to assess the effectiveness of the study materials.
Teen Driving: Psychoeducational workbook, worksheets, videos, tip sheets, and health coaching session about how parents can help supervise their teens' safe driving practices and how to talk with their teen about important safety topics for teen drivers.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>Teen Driving Control (Parents)</title>
            <description>Parents of teens between the ages of 16 and 17 who are planning on having the medical certification for the permit application completed and plan on taking their driving permit test in the next 8 weeks will receive their usual care at their well-child visit appointment with their primary care giver (baseline) and then at 6 months post baseline we will collect data. At the end of the post data collection, the control group will get all of the study materials from the teen driving group.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Parent-teen Communication About Pennsylvania's Graduated Driver Licensing Laws</title>
          <description>Six months after baseline, parents reported on the frequency that they talked about about Pennsylvania's GDL laws. Parents selected from one of the following response choices: &quot;never talked about&quot; (0); &quot;talked about once or twice&quot; (1); &quot;talked about three or four times&quot; (2); &quot;talked about a lot, about 5 times or more&quot; (3).</description>
          <population>Parent Population</population>
          <units>units on a scale</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>Standard Deviation</dispersion>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="22"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="24"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="1.82" spread=".85"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value=".71" spread="1.08"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <analysis_list>
          <analysis>
            <group_id_list>
              <group_id>O1</group_id>
              <group_id>O2</group_id>
            </group_id_list>
            <non_inferiority_type>Superiority</non_inferiority_type>
            <p_value>&lt;.001</p_value>
            <method>t-test, 2 sided</method>
          </analysis>
        </analysis_list>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Primary</type>
        <title>Parent-teen Communication About Wearing a Seatbelt</title>
        <description>Six months after baseline, parents reported on the frequency that they talked about wearing a seatbelt. Parents selected from one of the following response choices: &quot;never talked about&quot; (0); &quot;talked about once or twice&quot; (1); &quot;talked about three or four times&quot; (2); &quot;talked about a lot, about 5 times or more&quot; (3).</description>
        <time_frame>6 months post-enrollment</time_frame>
        <population>Parent Population</population>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Teen Driving (Parents)</title>
            <description>Parents of teens between the ages of 16 and 17 who are planning on having the medical certification for the permit application completed and plan on taking their driving permit test in the next 8 weeks will review psychoeducational workbooks related to teen driving at a well-child visit appointment with the primary care giver (baseline); 2 weeks after baseline they will received a follow-up phone call and health coaching session to review the materials and ask questions; and then at 6 months post baseline we will collect data to assess the effectiveness of the study materials.
Teen Driving: Psychoeducational workbook, worksheets, videos, tip sheets, and health coaching session about how parents can help supervise their teens' safe driving practices and how to talk with their teen about important safety topics for teen drivers.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>Teen Driving Control (Parents)</title>
            <description>Parents of teens between the ages of 16 and 17 who are planning on having the medical certification for the permit application completed and plan on taking their driving permit test in the next 8 weeks will receive their usual care at their well-child visit appointment with their primary care giver (baseline) and then at 6 months post baseline we will collect data. At the end of the post data collection, the control group will get all of the study materials from the teen driving group.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Parent-teen Communication About Wearing a Seatbelt</title>
          <description>Six months after baseline, parents reported on the frequency that they talked about wearing a seatbelt. Parents selected from one of the following response choices: &quot;never talked about&quot; (0); &quot;talked about once or twice&quot; (1); &quot;talked about three or four times&quot; (2); &quot;talked about a lot, about 5 times or more&quot; (3).</description>
          <population>Parent Population</population>
          <units>units on a scale</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>Standard Deviation</dispersion>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="22"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="24"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="2.68" spread=".72"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="2.79" spread=".59"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <analysis_list>
          <analysis>
            <group_id_list>
              <group_id>O1</group_id>
              <group_id>O2</group_id>
            </group_id_list>
            <non_inferiority_type>Superiority</non_inferiority_type>
            <p_value>.571</p_value>
            <method>t-test, 2 sided</method>
          </analysis>
        </analysis_list>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Primary</type>
        <title>Parent-teen Communication About Dangers of Distracted Driving</title>
        <description>Six months after baseline, parents reported on the frequency that they talked about dangers of distracted driving. Parents selected from one of the following response choices: &quot;never talked about&quot; (0); &quot;talked about once or twice&quot; (1); &quot;talked about three or four times&quot; (2); &quot;talked about a lot, about 5 times or more&quot; (3).</description>
        <time_frame>6 months post-enrollment</time_frame>
        <population>Parent Population</population>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Teen Driving (Parents)</title>
            <description>Parents of teens between the ages of 16 and 17 who are planning on having the medical certification for the permit application completed and plan on taking their driving permit test in the next 8 weeks will review psychoeducational workbooks related to teen driving at a well-child visit appointment with the primary care giver (baseline); 2 weeks after baseline they will received a follow-up phone call and health coaching session to review the materials and ask questions; and then at 6 months post baseline we will collect data to assess the effectiveness of the study materials.
Teen Driving: Psychoeducational workbook, worksheets, videos, tip sheets, and health coaching session about how parents can help supervise their teens' safe driving practices and how to talk with their teen about important safety topics for teen drivers.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>Teen Driving Control (Parents)</title>
            <description>Parents of teens between the ages of 16 and 17 who are planning on having the medical certification for the permit application completed and plan on taking their driving permit test in the next 8 weeks will receive their usual care at their well-child visit appointment with their primary care giver (baseline) and then at 6 months post baseline we will collect data. At the end of the post data collection, the control group will get all of the study materials from the teen driving group.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Parent-teen Communication About Dangers of Distracted Driving</title>
          <description>Six months after baseline, parents reported on the frequency that they talked about dangers of distracted driving. Parents selected from one of the following response choices: &quot;never talked about&quot; (0); &quot;talked about once or twice&quot; (1); &quot;talked about three or four times&quot; (2); &quot;talked about a lot, about 5 times or more&quot; (3).</description>
          <population>Parent Population</population>
          <units>units on a scale</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>Standard Deviation</dispersion>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="22"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="24"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="2.77" spread=".43"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="2.63" spread=".71"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <analysis_list>
          <analysis>
            <group_id_list>
              <group_id>O1</group_id>
              <group_id>O2</group_id>
            </group_id_list>
            <non_inferiority_type>Superiority</non_inferiority_type>
            <p_value>.394</p_value>
            <method>t-test, 2 sided</method>
          </analysis>
        </analysis_list>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Primary</type>
        <title>Parent-teen Communication About Being a Safe Passenger</title>
        <description>Six months after baseline, parents reported on the frequency that they talked about being a safe passenger. Parents selected from one of the following response choices: &quot;never talked about&quot; (0); &quot;talked about once or twice&quot; (1); &quot;talked about three or four times&quot; (2); &quot;talked about a lot, about 5 times or more&quot; (3).</description>
        <time_frame>6 months post-enrollment</time_frame>
        <population>Parent Population</population>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Teen Driving (Parent)</title>
            <description>Parents of teens between the ages of 16 and 17 who are planning on having the medical certification for the permit application completed and plan on taking their driving permit test in the next 8 weeks will review psychoeducational workbooks related to teen driving at a well-child visit appointment with the primary care giver (baseline); 2 weeks after baseline they will received a follow-up phone call and health coaching session to review the materials and ask questions; and then at 6 months post baseline we will collect data to assess the effectiveness of the study materials.
Teen Driving: Psychoeducational workbook, worksheets, videos, tip sheets, and health coaching session about how parents can help supervise their teens' safe driving practices and how to talk with their teen about important safety topics for teen drivers.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>Teen Driving Control (Parent)</title>
            <description>Parents of teens between the ages of 16 and 17 who are planning on having the medical certification for the permit application completed and plan on taking their driving permit test in the next 8 weeks will receive their usual care at their well-child visit appointment with their primary care giver (baseline) and then at 6 months post baseline we will collect data. At the end of the post data collection, the control group will get all of the study materials from the teen driving group.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Parent-teen Communication About Being a Safe Passenger</title>
          <description>Six months after baseline, parents reported on the frequency that they talked about being a safe passenger. Parents selected from one of the following response choices: &quot;never talked about&quot; (0); &quot;talked about once or twice&quot; (1); &quot;talked about three or four times&quot; (2); &quot;talked about a lot, about 5 times or more&quot; (3).</description>
          <population>Parent Population</population>
          <units>units on a scale</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>Standard Deviation</dispersion>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="22"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="24"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="2.55" spread=".67"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="1.71" spread="1.27"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <analysis_list>
          <analysis>
            <group_id_list>
              <group_id>O1</group_id>
              <group_id>O2</group_id>
            </group_id_list>
            <non_inferiority_type>Superiority</non_inferiority_type>
            <p_value>.008</p_value>
            <method>t-test, 2 sided</method>
          </analysis>
        </analysis_list>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Primary</type>
        <title>Parent-teen Communication About What to do in a Crash</title>
        <description>Six months after baseline, parents reported on the frequency that they talked about what to do in a crash. Parents selected from one of the following response choices: &quot;never talked about&quot; (0); &quot;talked about once or twice&quot; (1); &quot;talked about three or four times&quot; (2); &quot;talked about a lot, about 5 times or more&quot; (3).</description>
        <time_frame>6 months post-enrollment</time_frame>
        <population>Parent Population</population>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Teen Driving</title>
            <description>Parents of teens between the ages of 16 and 17 who are planning on having the medical certification for the permit application completed and plan on taking their driving permit test in the next 8 weeks will review psychoeducational workbooks related to teen driving at a well-child visit appointment with the primary care giver (baseline); 2 weeks after baseline they will received a follow-up phone call and health coaching session to review the materials and ask questions; and then at 6 months post baseline we will collect data to assess the effectiveness of the study materials.
Teen Driving: Psychoeducational workbook, worksheets, videos, tip sheets, and health coaching session about how parents can help supervise their teens' safe driving practices and how to talk with their teen about important safety topics for teen drivers.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>Teen Driving Control</title>
            <description>Parents of teens between the ages of 16 and 17 who are planning on having the medical certification for the permit application completed and plan on taking their driving permit test in the next 8 weeks will receive their usual care at their well-child visit appointment with their primary care giver (baseline) and then at 6 months post baseline we will collect data. At the end of the post data collection, the control group will get all of the study materials from the teen driving group.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Parent-teen Communication About What to do in a Crash</title>
          <description>Six months after baseline, parents reported on the frequency that they talked about what to do in a crash. Parents selected from one of the following response choices: &quot;never talked about&quot; (0); &quot;talked about once or twice&quot; (1); &quot;talked about three or four times&quot; (2); &quot;talked about a lot, about 5 times or more&quot; (3).</description>
          <population>Parent Population</population>
          <units>units on a scale</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>Standard Deviation</dispersion>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="22"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="24"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="2.00" spread="1.23"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value=".46" spread=".83"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <analysis_list>
          <analysis>
            <group_id_list>
              <group_id>O1</group_id>
              <group_id>O2</group_id>
            </group_id_list>
            <non_inferiority_type>Superiority</non_inferiority_type>
            <p_value>&lt;.001</p_value>
            <method>t-test, 2 sided</method>
          </analysis>
        </analysis_list>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Primary</type>
        <title>Parent-teen Communication About What to do if Stopped by a Police Officer</title>
        <description>Six months after baseline, parents reported on the frequency that they talked about what to do if stopped by a police officer. Parents selected from one of the following response choices: &quot;never talked about&quot; (0); &quot;talked about once or twice&quot; (1); &quot;talked about three or four times&quot; (2); &quot;talked about a lot, about 5 times or more&quot; (3).</description>
        <time_frame>6 months post-enrollment</time_frame>
        <population>Parent Population</population>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Teen Driving (Parent)</title>
            <description>Parents of teens between the ages of 16 and 17 who are planning on having the medical certification for the permit application completed and plan on taking their driving permit test in the next 8 weeks will review psychoeducational workbooks related to teen driving at a well-child visit appointment with the primary care giver (baseline); 2 weeks after baseline they will received a follow-up phone call and health coaching session to review the materials and ask questions; and then at 6 months post baseline we will collect data to assess the effectiveness of the study materials.
Teen Driving: Psychoeducational workbook, worksheets, videos, tip sheets, and health coaching session about how parents can help supervise their teens' safe driving practices and how to talk with their teen about important safety topics for teen drivers.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>Teen Driving Control (Parent)</title>
            <description>Parents of teens between the ages of 16 and 17 who are planning on having the medical certification for the permit application completed and plan on taking their driving permit test in the next 8 weeks will receive their usual care at their well-child visit appointment with their primary care giver (baseline) and then at 6 months post baseline we will collect data. At the end of the post data collection, the control group will get all of the study materials from the teen driving group.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Parent-teen Communication About What to do if Stopped by a Police Officer</title>
          <description>Six months after baseline, parents reported on the frequency that they talked about what to do if stopped by a police officer. Parents selected from one of the following response choices: &quot;never talked about&quot; (0); &quot;talked about once or twice&quot; (1); &quot;talked about three or four times&quot; (2); &quot;talked about a lot, about 5 times or more&quot; (3).</description>
          <population>Parent Population</population>
          <units>units on a scale</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>Standard Deviation</dispersion>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="22"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="24"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="2.27" spread=".88"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="1.25" spread="1.07"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <analysis_list>
          <analysis>
            <group_id_list>
              <group_id>O1</group_id>
              <group_id>O2</group_id>
            </group_id_list>
            <non_inferiority_type>Superiority</non_inferiority_type>
            <p_value>.001</p_value>
            <method>t-test, 2 sided</method>
          </analysis>
        </analysis_list>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Primary</type>
        <title>Parent-teen Communication About Driving Under the Influence of Drugs or Alcohol</title>
        <description>Six months after baseline, parents reported on the frequency that they talked about driving under the influence of drugs or alcohol. Parents selected from one of the following response choices: &quot;never talked about&quot; (0); &quot;talked about once or twice&quot; (1); &quot;talked about three or four times&quot; (2); &quot;talked about a lot, about 5 times or more&quot; (3).</description>
        <time_frame>6 months post-enrollment</time_frame>
        <population>Parent Population</population>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Teen Driving (Parent)</title>
            <description>Parents of teens between the ages of 16 and 17 who are planning on having the medical certification for the permit application completed and plan on taking their driving permit test in the next 8 weeks will review psychoeducational workbooks related to teen driving at a well-child visit appointment with the primary care giver (baseline); 2 weeks after baseline they will received a follow-up phone call and health coaching session to review the materials and ask questions; and then at 6 months post baseline we will collect data to assess the effectiveness of the study materials.
Teen Driving: Psychoeducational workbook, worksheets, videos, tip sheets, and health coaching session about how parents can help supervise their teens' safe driving practices and how to talk with their teen about important safety topics for teen drivers.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>Teen Driving Control (Parent)</title>
            <description>Parents of teens between the ages of 16 and 17 who are planning on having the medical certification for the permit application completed and plan on taking their driving permit test in the next 8 weeks will receive their usual care at their well-child visit appointment with their primary care giver (baseline) and then at 6 months post baseline we will collect data. At the end of the post data collection, the control group will get all of the study materials from the teen driving group.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Parent-teen Communication About Driving Under the Influence of Drugs or Alcohol</title>
          <description>Six months after baseline, parents reported on the frequency that they talked about driving under the influence of drugs or alcohol. Parents selected from one of the following response choices: &quot;never talked about&quot; (0); &quot;talked about once or twice&quot; (1); &quot;talked about three or four times&quot; (2); &quot;talked about a lot, about 5 times or more&quot; (3).</description>
          <population>Parent Population</population>
          <units>units on a scale</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>Standard Deviation</dispersion>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="22"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="24"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="1.73" spread="1.16"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="1.21" spread="1.29"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <analysis_list>
          <analysis>
            <group_id_list>
              <group_id>O1</group_id>
              <group_id>O2</group_id>
            </group_id_list>
            <non_inferiority_type>Superiority</non_inferiority_type>
            <p_value>.159</p_value>
            <method>t-test, 2 sided</method>
          </analysis>
        </analysis_list>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Primary</type>
        <title>Parent-teen Communication About What to do if the Teen Needs a Safe Ride Home</title>
        <description>Six months after baseline, parents reported on the frequency that they talked about what to do if the teen needs a safe ride home. Parents selected from one of the following response choices: &quot;never talked about&quot; (0); &quot;talked about once or twice&quot; (1); &quot;talked about three or four times&quot; (2); &quot;talked about a lot, about 5 times or more&quot; (3).</description>
        <time_frame>6 months post-enrollment</time_frame>
        <population>Parent Population</population>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Teen Driving (Parent)</title>
            <description>Parents of teens between the ages of 16 and 17 who are planning on having the medical certification for the permit application completed and plan on taking their driving permit test in the next 8 weeks will review psychoeducational workbooks related to teen driving at a well-child visit appointment with the primary care giver (baseline); 2 weeks after baseline they will received a follow-up phone call and health coaching session to review the materials and ask questions; and then at 6 months post baseline we will collect data to assess the effectiveness of the study materials.
Teen Driving: Psychoeducational workbook, worksheets, videos, tip sheets, and health coaching session about how parents can help supervise their teens' safe driving practices and how to talk with their teen about important safety topics for teen drivers.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>Teen Driving Control (Parent)</title>
            <description>Parents of teens between the ages of 16 and 17 who are planning on having the medical certification for the permit application completed and plan on taking their driving permit test in the next 8 weeks will receive their usual care at their well-child visit appointment with their primary care giver (baseline) and then at 6 months post baseline we will collect data. At the end of the post data collection, the control group will get all of the study materials from the teen driving group.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Parent-teen Communication About What to do if the Teen Needs a Safe Ride Home</title>
          <description>Six months after baseline, parents reported on the frequency that they talked about what to do if the teen needs a safe ride home. Parents selected from one of the following response choices: &quot;never talked about&quot; (0); &quot;talked about once or twice&quot; (1); &quot;talked about three or four times&quot; (2); &quot;talked about a lot, about 5 times or more&quot; (3).</description>
          <population>Parent Population</population>
          <units>units on a scale</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>Standard Deviation</dispersion>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="22"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="24"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="2.45" spread=".86"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="1.96" spread="1.20"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <analysis_list>
          <analysis>
            <group_id_list>
              <group_id>O1</group_id>
              <group_id>O2</group_id>
            </group_id_list>
            <non_inferiority_type>Superiority</non_inferiority_type>
            <p_value>.112</p_value>
            <method>t-test, 2 sided</method>
          </analysis>
        </analysis_list>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Primary</type>
        <title>Parent-teen Communication About Stopping a Friend From Driving Under the Influence of Drugs or Alcohol</title>
        <description>Six months after baseline, parents reported on the frequency that they talked about stopping a friend from driving under the influence of drugs or alcohol. Parents selected from one of the following response choices: &quot;never talked about&quot; (0); &quot;talked about once or twice&quot; (1); &quot;talked about three or four times&quot; (2); &quot;talked about a lot, about 5 times or more&quot; (3).stopping a friend from riding with a driver who is under the influence of drugs or alcohol</description>
        <time_frame>6 months post-enrollment</time_frame>
        <population>Parent Population</population>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Teen Driving (Parent)</title>
            <description>Parents of teens between the ages of 16 and 17 who are planning on having the medical certification for the permit application completed and plan on taking their driving permit test in the next 8 weeks will review psychoeducational workbooks related to teen driving at a well-child visit appointment with the primary care giver (baseline); 2 weeks after baseline they will received a follow-up phone call and health coaching session to review the materials and ask questions; and then at 6 months post baseline we will collect data to assess the effectiveness of the study materials.
Teen Driving: Psychoeducational workbook, worksheets, videos, tip sheets, and health coaching session about how parents can help supervise their teens' safe driving practices and how to talk with their teen about important safety topics for teen drivers.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>Teen Driving Control (Parent)</title>
            <description>Parents of teens between the ages of 16 and 17 who are planning on having the medical certification for the permit application completed and plan on taking their driving permit test in the next 8 weeks will receive their usual care at their well-child visit appointment with their primary care giver (baseline) and then at 6 months post baseline we will collect data. At the end of the post data collection, the control group will get all of the study materials from the teen driving group.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Parent-teen Communication About Stopping a Friend From Driving Under the Influence of Drugs or Alcohol</title>
          <description>Six months after baseline, parents reported on the frequency that they talked about stopping a friend from driving under the influence of drugs or alcohol. Parents selected from one of the following response choices: &quot;never talked about&quot; (0); &quot;talked about once or twice&quot; (1); &quot;talked about three or four times&quot; (2); &quot;talked about a lot, about 5 times or more&quot; (3).stopping a friend from riding with a driver who is under the influence of drugs or alcohol</description>
          <population>Parent Population</population>
          <units>units on a scale</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>Standard Deviation</dispersion>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="22"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="24"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="2.64" spread=".66"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="2.29" spread=".955"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <analysis_list>
          <analysis>
            <group_id_list>
              <group_id>O1</group_id>
            </group_id_list>
            <non_inferiority_type>Superiority</non_inferiority_type>
            <p_value>.165</p_value>
            <method>t-test, 2 sided</method>
          </analysis>
        </analysis_list>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Primary</type>
        <title>Parent-teen Communication About Stopping a Friend From Riding With a Driver Who is Under the Influence of Drugs or Alcohol</title>
        <description>Six months after baseline, parents reported on the frequency that they talked about stopping a friend from riding with a driver who is under the influence of drugs or alcohol. Parents selected from one of the following response choices: &quot;never talked about&quot; (0); &quot;talked about once or twice&quot; (1); &quot;talked about three or four times&quot; (2); &quot;talked about a lot, about 5 times or more&quot; (3).</description>
        <time_frame>6 months post-enrollment</time_frame>
        <population>Parent Population</population>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Teen Driving (Parent)</title>
            <description>Parents of teens between the ages of 16 and 17 who are planning on having the medical certification for the permit application completed and plan on taking their driving permit test in the next 8 weeks will review psychoeducational workbooks related to teen driving at a well-child visit appointment with the primary care giver (baseline); 2 weeks after baseline they will received a follow-up phone call and health coaching session to review the materials and ask questions; and then at 6 months post baseline we will collect data to assess the effectiveness of the study materials.
Teen Driving: Psychoeducational workbook, worksheets, videos, tip sheets, and health coaching session about how parents can help supervise their teens' safe driving practices and how to talk with their teen about important safety topics for teen drivers.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>Teen Driving Control (Parent)</title>
            <description>Parents of teens between the ages of 16 and 17 who are planning on having the medical certification for the permit application completed and plan on taking their driving permit test in the next 8 weeks will receive their usual care at their well-child visit appointment with their primary care giver (baseline) and then at 6 months post baseline we will collect data. At the end of the post data collection, the control group will get all of the study materials from the teen driving group.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Parent-teen Communication About Stopping a Friend From Riding With a Driver Who is Under the Influence of Drugs or Alcohol</title>
          <description>Six months after baseline, parents reported on the frequency that they talked about stopping a friend from riding with a driver who is under the influence of drugs or alcohol. Parents selected from one of the following response choices: &quot;never talked about&quot; (0); &quot;talked about once or twice&quot; (1); &quot;talked about three or four times&quot; (2); &quot;talked about a lot, about 5 times or more&quot; (3).</description>
          <population>Parent Population</population>
          <units>units on a scale</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>Standard Deviation</dispersion>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="22"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="24"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="1.68" spread="1.17"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value=".71" spread="1.12"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <analysis_list>
          <analysis>
            <group_id_list>
              <group_id>O1</group_id>
              <group_id>O2</group_id>
            </group_id_list>
            <non_inferiority_type>Superiority</non_inferiority_type>
            <p_value>.006</p_value>
            <method>t-test, 2 sided</method>
          </analysis>
        </analysis_list>
      </outcome>
    </outcome_list>

    <reported_events>
      <time_frame>Adverse event data was collected at each time point (e.g. Baseline, 2wk follow up, final follow up).</time_frame>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="E1">
          <title>Sexual Health</title>
          <description>Parents of teens between the ages of 14 and 15 will review psychoeducational workbooks related to sexual health at a well-child visit appointment with the primary care giver (baseline); 2 weeks after baseline they will received a follow-up phone call and health coaching session to review the materials and ask questions; and then at 4 to 5 months post baseline we will collect data to assess the efficacy of the study materials.
Sexual Health: Psychoeducational workbook, worksheets, tip sheets, and health coaching session about sexual health, sexually transmitted disease (STD) prevention, and safe sex practices for teenager.</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="E2">
          <title>Alcohol Prevention</title>
          <description>Parents of teens between the ages of 14 and 15 will review psychoeducational workbooks related to alcohol prevention at a well-child visit appointment with the primary care giver (baseline); 2 weeks after baseline they will received a follow-up phone call and health coaching session to review the materials and ask questions; and then at 4 to 5 months post baseline we will collect data to assess the efficacy of the study materials.
Alcohol Prevention: Psychoeducational workbook, worksheets, tip sheets, and health coaching session about alcohol prevention and safety, underage drinking, and drinking and driving.</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="E3">
          <title>Sexual Health &amp; Alcohol Control Group</title>
          <description>Parents of teens between the ages of 14 and 15 will receive their usual care at their well-child visit appointment with their primary care giver (baseline) and then at 4 to 5 months post baseline we will collect data. At the end of the post data collection, the control group will get all of the study materials from both the sexual health and alcohol prevention groups.</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="E4">
          <title>Teen Driving</title>
          <description>Parents of teens between the ages of 16 and 17 who are planning on having the medical certification for the permit application completed and plan on taking their driving permit test in the next 8 weeks will review psychoeducational workbooks related to teen driving at a well-child visit appointment with the primary care giver (baseline); 2 weeks after baseline they will received a follow-up phone call and health coaching session to review the materials and ask questions; and then at 6 months post baseline we will collect data to assess the effectiveness of the study materials.
Teen Driving: Psychoeducational workbook, worksheets, videos, tip sheets, and health coaching session about how parents can help supervise their teens' safe driving practices and how to talk with their teen about important safety topics for teen drivers.</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="E5">
          <title>Teen Driving Control</title>
          <description>Parents of teens between the ages of 16 and 17 who are planning on having the medical certification for the permit application completed and plan on taking their driving permit test in the next 8 weeks will receive their usual care at their well-child visit appointment with their primary care giver (baseline) and then at 6 months post baseline we will collect data. At the end of the post data collection, the control group will get all of the study materials from the teen driving group.</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <serious_events>
        <category_list>
          <category>
            <title>Total</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, all-cause mortality</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="80"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="80"/>
                <counts group_id="E3" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="80"/>
                <counts group_id="E4" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="56"/>
                <counts group_id="E5" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="52"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, serious adverse events</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="80"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="80"/>
                <counts group_id="E3" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="80"/>
                <counts group_id="E4" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="56"/>
                <counts group_id="E5" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="52"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
        </category_list>
      </serious_events>
      <other_events>
        <frequency_threshold>0</frequency_threshold>
        <category_list>
          <category>
            <title>Total</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, other adverse events</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="80"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="80"/>
                <counts group_id="E3" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="80"/>
                <counts group_id="E4" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="56"/>
                <counts group_id="E5" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="52"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
        </category_list>
      </other_events>
    </reported_events>

    <certain_agreements>
      <pi_employee>All Principal Investigators ARE employed by the organization sponsoring the study.</pi_employee>
      <restrictive_agreement>There is NOT an agreement between Principal Investigators and the Sponsor (or its agents) that restricts the PI's rights to discuss or publish trial results after the trial is completed. </restrictive_agreement>
    </certain_agreements>
    <point_of_contact>
      <name_or_title>Dr. Carol Ford</name_or_title>
      <organization>Children's Hospital of Philadelphia</organization>
      <phone>267-426-3938 ext 63938</phone>
      <email>fordc@email.chop.edu</email>
    </point_of_contact>
  </clinical_results>
</clinical_study>

