<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03200587</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HCI102309</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03200587</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Cabometyx and Avelumab in Patients With Metastatic Renal Cell Carcinoma (mRCC)</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase 1B, Open Label, Dose-finding Study to Evaluate the Safety and Tolerability of Cabometyx and Avelumab in Patients With Metastatic Renal Cell Carcinoma (mRCC)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Utah</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>EMD Serono</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Utah</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is an open-label, non-controlled, non-randomized, phase I dose-finding, of Cabometyx +
      Avelumab, to establish safety, feasibility, and the maximum tolerated dose (MTD) or
      Recommended Phase 2 Dose (RP2D) of Cabometyx in combination with Avelumab, and to investigate
      preliminary efficacy. The MTD or RP2D determined in this study will be used for a future
      study to formally test efficacy. The MTD determined by dose escalation will be the
      recommended Phase 2 dose.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 21, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">April 14, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>A phase 1B, open label, dose-finding study</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Determine the recommended Phase II dose</measure>
    <time_frame>1 cycle (28 days)</time_frame>
    <description>To assess the safety and tolerability of Avelumab + Cabometyx in subjects with mRCC and determine the recommended Phase II dose (RP2D). Safety, tolerability, adverse events (AEs), serious adverse events (SAEs), dose-limiting toxicities (DLTs).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression Free Survival (PFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years (Most patients are expected to be on treatment for approximately 10 months)</time_frame>
    <description>To describe the clinical activity of Avelumab + Cabometyx in subjects with mRCC</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">12</enrollment>
  <condition>Renal Cell Carcinoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Avelumab and cabozantinib, all patients</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Avelumab</intervention_name>
    <description>Avelumab 10 mg/kg infusion every 2 weeks (Days 1 and 15) of every 28 day cycle for up to 12 cycles</description>
    <arm_group_label>Avelumab and cabozantinib, all patients</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cabozantinib</intervention_name>
    <description>Cabozantinib oral daily at 20 (starting dose 1), 40 (Dose Level 2) or 60 mg (Dose Level 3)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Avelumab and cabozantinib, all patients</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Cabometyx</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Optional Pre-Screening Eligibility for Patients Scheduled for Cytoreductive Nephrectomy

          -  Male or female subject aged ≥ 18 years.

          -  Clinically, subject is a candidate for RCC diagnostic procedure (biopsy or surgery).

          -  Subject meets standard of care eligibility criteria for consideration of treatment
             with immunotherapy using a checkpoint inhibitor following surgical resection or
             biopsy.

        Treatment Inclusion

          -  Male or female subject aged ≥ 18 years.

          -  Histologically proven renal cell carcinoma with a clear cell component.

          -  Radiographic evidence of metastatic disease.

          -  Measureable disease by RECIST 1.1

          -  ECOG Score 0-2

          -  Adequate organ function as described in the protocol

          -  Negative serum or urine pregnancy test at screening for women of childbearing
             potential

          -  Highly effective contraception for both male and female subjects throughout the study
             and for at least 120 days after last Avelumab treatment administration if the risk of
             conception exists

          -  Able to provide informed consent and willing to sign an approved consent form that
             conforms to federal and institutional guidelines.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Current use of immunosuppressive medication, EXCEPT for the following:

               1. intranasal, inhaled, topical steroids, or local steroid injection (e.g.,
                  intra-articular injection);

               2. Systemic corticosteroids at physiologic doses ≤ 10 mg/day of prednisone or
                  equivalent;

               3. Steroids as premedication for hypersensitivity reactions (e.g., CT scan
                  premedication).

          -  Active autoimmune disease that might deteriorate when receiving an immuno-stimulatory
             agent per treating physician's clinical judgment. Subjects with diabetes type I,
             vitiligo, psoriasis, or hypo- or hyperthyroid diseases not requiring immunosuppressive
             treatment are eligible.

          -  Prior organ transplantation including allogenic stem-cell transplantation.

          -  Active infection requiring intravenous antibiotics (antibiotics should have been
             completed prior to registration).

          -  Known history of testing positive for HIV or known acquired immunodeficiency syndrome.

          -  Known active hepatitis B virus (HBV) or hepatitis C virus (HCV) infection. If the
             patient has a history of HBV or HCV then confirmatory PCR testing is required to
             confirm the disease is not active.

          -  Live vaccinations within 4 weeks of the first dose of Avelumab and while on trial is
             prohibited.

          -  Piror exposure to checkpoint therapy or Cabozantinib.

          -  Known prior severe hypersensitivity to investigational product or any component in its
             formulations, including known severe hypersensitivity reactions to monoclonal
             antibodies (NCI CTCAE v4.03 Grade ≥ 3).

          -  Clinically significant (i.e., active) cardiovascular disease: cerebral vascular
             accident/stroke (&lt; 6 months prior to enrollment), myocardial infarction (&lt; 6 months
             prior to enrollment), unstable angina, congestive heart failure (≥ New York Heart
             Association Classification Class II), or serious cardiac arrhythmia requiring
             medication.

          -  Persisting toxicity related to prior therapy (NCI CTCAE v. 4.03 Grade &gt; 1); however,
             alopecia, sensory neuropathy Grade ≤ 2, or other Grade ≤ 2 not constituting a safety
             risk based on investigator's judgment are acceptable.

          -  Other severe acute or chronic medical conditions including colitis, inflammatory bowel
             disease, pneumonitis, pulmonary fibrosis or psychiatric conditions including recent
             (within the past year) or active suicidal ideation or behavior; or laboratory
             abnormalities that may increase the risk associated with study participation or study
             treatment administration or may interfere with the interpretation of study results
             and, in the judgment of the investigator, would make the patient inappropriate for
             entry into this study.

          -  Subjects taking prohibited medications as described in protocol. A washout period of
             prohibited medications for a period of at least two weeks or as clinically indicated
             should occur prior to the start of treatment

          -  Pregnant women or lactating women who are breastfeeding are excluded from this study.

          -  Stroke (including transient ischemic attack (TIA), myocardial infarction, or other
             ischemic event or symptomatic pulmonary embolism (PE) less than or equal to 6 months
             before dose of Cabometyx.

          -  Subjects with a diagnosis of deep vein thrombosis (DVT) or incidentally detected
             asymptomatic PE on routine scans are allowed if stable and treated with therapeutic
             anticoagulation for at least 2 weeks before first dose.

          -  Clinically significant hematuria, hematemesis, or hemoptysis of &gt; 0.5 teaspoon (2.5
             ml) of red blood, or other history of significant bleeding (e.g., pulmonary
             hemorrhage) within 12 weeks before first dose.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Neeraj Agarwal, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Huntsman Cancer Institute</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Huntsman Cancer Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Salt Lake City</city>
        <state>Utah</state>
        <zip>84112</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 23, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 23, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 27, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 7, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 7, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 9, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Metastatic</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Renal Cell</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

