<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04106882</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2017D001434</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04106882</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Dynamic Connectivity Under Metabolic Constraints</brief_title>
  <official_title>Dynamic Connectivity Under Metabolic Constraints</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Stony Brook University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Martinos Center for Biomedical Imaging</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Stony Brook University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The investigators are studying the impact of insulin resistance on the acceleration of brain
      aging and testing whether increased neuron insulin resistance can be counteracted by
      utilization of alternate metabolic pathways (e.g., ketones rather than glucose). This study
      has three Arms, which together provide synergistic data. For all three Arms, subjects are
      tested in a within-subjects design that consists of 2-3 testing sessions, 1-14 days apart,
      and counter-balanced for order. Impact of fuel (glucose in one session, ketones in the other)
      on brain metabolism and associated functioning is measured during each session. For Arms 1-2,
      the primary experimental measure is functional magnetic resonance imaging (fMRI), which is
      used to trace the self-organization of functional networks following changes in energy supply
      and demand. Arm 1 tests the impact of endogenous ketones produced by switching to a low
      carbohydrate diet, while Arm 2 tests the impact of exogenous ketones consumed as a
      nutritional supplement. For Arm 3, simultaneous magnetic resonance
      spectroscopy/positron-emission tomography (MR/PET) is used to quantify the impact of
      exogenous ketones on production of glutamate and GABA, key neurotransmitters.

      Subjects will be given the option to participate in more than one of the Arms, but doing so
      is not expected nor required.

      Prior to scans, subjects will receive a clinician-administered History and Physical (H&amp;P),
      which includes vital signs, an oral glucose tolerance test (OGTT), and the comprehensive
      metabolic blood panel. These will be used to assess diabetes, kidney disease, and
      electrolytes. If subjects pass screening, they will be provided the option to participate in
      one or more Arms, which include neuroimaging. To provide a quantitative measure of
      time-varying metabolic activity throughout the scan, based upon quantitative models of
      glucose and ketone regulation, as well as to be able to implement safety stopping rules (see
      below), the investigators will obtain pin-prick blood samples three times: prior to the scan,
      following consumption of the glucose or ketone drink, and following completion of the scan.
      To assess effects of increased metabolic demand, the investigators measure brain response to
      cognitive load, transitioning from resting-state to spatial reasoning through a spatial
      navigation video task. To assess effects of increased metabolic supply, the investigators
      measure brain response to glucose or ketone bolus.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 19, 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Diet related changes in brain network stability will be assessed by fMRI BOLD measurements.</measure>
    <time_frame>Within two weeks of enrollment completion</time_frame>
    <description>Changes in BOLD signal measurements will be observed between baseline and during a glycolytic, fasting, or ketotic state.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Glucose uptake will be measured by PET, with and without ketone supplement</measure>
    <time_frame>Within two weeks of enrollment completion</time_frame>
    <description>Continuous FDG PET infusion is used as a measure of glucose uptake during rest and task, with and without the ketone supplement.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Neurotransmitter production with and without ketone supplement will be measured by magnetic resonance spectroscopy</measure>
    <time_frame>Within two weeks of enrollment completion</time_frame>
    <description>Changes in neurotransmitter concentration under metabolic demands (i.e., task vs resting-state) with and without ketone supplement will be assessed by magnetic resonance spectroscopy.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cognitive performance will be assessed by Mini Mental State Exam (MMSE).</measure>
    <time_frame>Within two weeks of enrollment completion</time_frame>
    <description>All subjects will undergo cognitive testing prior to MRI scanning using the MMSE exam.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cognitive performance will be assessed by CNS Vital Signs.</measure>
    <time_frame>Within two weeks of enrollment completion</time_frame>
    <description>All subjects will undergo cognitive testing prior to MRI scanning using the CNS Vital Signs exam.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Insulin resistance will be assessed by HbA1C.</measure>
    <time_frame>Within two weeks of enrollment completion</time_frame>
    <description>All subjects will be tested for insulin resistance prior to MRI scanning using veinous blood collected and tested for HbA1C.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Insulin resistance will be assessed by blood insulin level.</measure>
    <time_frame>Within two weeks of enrollment completion</time_frame>
    <description>All subjects will be tested for insulin resistance prior to MRI scanning using veinous blood collected and tested for insulin during a 2-hour Oral Glucose Tolerance Test (OGTT).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Insulin resistance will be assessed by blood glucose level.</measure>
    <time_frame>Within two weeks of enrollment completion</time_frame>
    <description>All subjects will be tested for insulin resistance prior to MRI scanning using veinous blood collected and tested for glucose during a 2-hour Oral Glucose Tolerance Test (OGTT).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">80</enrollment>
  <condition>Insulin Resistance</condition>
  <condition>Healthy</condition>
  <condition>Diet Modification</condition>
  <condition>Aging</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 1: Metabolic Manipulation via Diet fMRI</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>All subjects are tested three times, each in a different diet-induced metabolic state: glycolytic (glucose burning), fasting (8 hours no food), and ketotic (fat burning). While having their brains scanned with MRI, subjects are initially tested at rest, and then perform a task. Midway through the session, subjects are removed from the scanner and drink up to 75g glucose. Data analyses quantify network reorganization in response to changing energy constraints (i.e., cognitive demand, fuel).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 2: Metabolic Manipulation via Ketone Supplement fMRI</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>All subjects are tested twice, both times in a fasting condition (8 hours no food, unrestricted water). While having their brains scanned with MRI, subjects are initially tested at rest, and then perform a task. Midway through the session, subjects are removed from the scanner and drink either of two fuel sources. In the ketotic (ketone burning) session they will drink a ketone sports drink dosed at 395mg/kg. During the glycolytic (glucose burning) session the same subjects will drink a bolus of glucose, calorie-matched to the ketones. Data analyses quantify network reorganization in response to changing energy constraints (i.e., cognitive demand, fuel).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 3: Metabolic Manipulation via Ketone Supplement MR/PET</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>All subjects are tested twice, both times in a fasting condition (8 hours no food, unrestricted water). For both sessions, the investigators will intravenously administer the FDG radioisotope continuously throughout the scan. Thus, PET will map glucose uptake across the brain, while MRS is simultaneously used to measure production of the neurotransmitters glutamine and GABA. While having their brains scanned with MR/PET, subjects are initially tested at rest, and then perform a task. Subjects will drink a ketone sports drink dosed at 395mg/kg. During the glycolytic (glucose burning) session the same subjects will drink a bolus of glucose, calorie-matched to the ketones.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ketones</intervention_name>
    <description>Supplement administered mid-scan.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 2: Metabolic Manipulation via Ketone Supplement fMRI</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 3: Metabolic Manipulation via Ketone Supplement MR/PET</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Glucose</intervention_name>
    <description>Supplement administered mid-scan.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 1: Metabolic Manipulation via Diet fMRI</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 2: Metabolic Manipulation via Ketone Supplement fMRI</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 3: Metabolic Manipulation via Ketone Supplement MR/PET</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  claustrophobia

          -  history of neurological disease, heart attack, stroke, kidney disease, or myxedema

          -  chronic usage of alcohol

          -  current usage of psychotropic medication

          -  Type 1 diabetes mellitus

          -  Regular consumption of insulin, Metformin® or other medications (statins, NSAIDs,
             beta-blockers, glucocorticoids) that affect glucose and/or insulin utilization.

          -  difficulty swallowing

          -  pregnancy

          -  breastfeeding

          -  For PET: research imaging-related radiation exposure that exceeds current MGH
             Radiology Radiation Safety Commitee guidelines.

        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  BMI &lt; 30

          -  MRI compatible

          -  For PET with Optional 150 ml Blood Sampling Only: Must weigh at least 110 lbs to
             minimize risks per PHRC guidelines.

          -  20/20 vision or correctable to 20/20 with contact lenses
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>79 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Lilianne Mujica-Parodi, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>631-371-4413</phone>
    <email>lilianne.strey@stonybrook.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Liam McMahon, BA</last_name>
    <email>liam.mcmahon@stonybrook.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Martinos Center for Biomedical Research, Building 149</name>
      <address>
        <city>Charlestown</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02129</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Bioengineering Building , Stony Brook University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Stony Brook</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>11794</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Lilianne Mujica-Parodi, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 17, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 25, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 27, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 25, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 25, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">September 27, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>insulin resistance</keyword>
  <keyword>exogenous ketone</keyword>
  <keyword>glucose</keyword>
  <keyword>diet</keyword>
  <keyword>aging</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Insulin Resistance</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

