<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04107545</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>RBHP 2019 DUCLOS</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2019-A00699-48</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04107545</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Metabolic, Functional and Nutritional Responses to Weight Cycling in Athletes: The WAVE Study</brief_title>
  <acronym>WAVE</acronym>
  <official_title>Metabolic, Functional and Nutritional Responses to Weight Cycling in Athletes: The WAVE Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University Hospital, Clermont-Ferrand</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Laboratoire AME2P</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Université de Fribourg, Department of Endocrinology, Metabolism and Cardiovascular System</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Leeds, Appetite Control and Energy Balance Research</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University Hospital, Clermont-Ferrand</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Many elite athletes are submitted to frequent rapid weight loss periods to meet their
      competition weight category and then experience weight cycling (lowing and gaining weight
      regularly). This weight cycling induce severe temporary energetic and metabolic changes and
      when repeated over time can lead to permanent metabolic adaptations that might favor
      metabolic disorders, body weight gain and body composition changes (favoring fat mass). The
      exact effects of this weight cycling are not clear yet, especially in terms of metabolic,
      energetics, nutritional functional and psychological impacts. Better understand these
      adaptations and their variations during weight loss and weight gain in regular weight cycler
      is of main importance to prevent these athletes for future health issues.

      The aim of the present project if to assess these metabolic, functional, energetic and
      nutritional adaptations during weight loss, weight stable and weight gain periods in athletes
      experiencing regular weight cycling.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      After an inclusion visit to ensure the eligibility of athletes to complete the entire study,
      each subject will perform 3 experimental sessions of 2 visits each : i) two visits during a
      period of maintenance of body weight (CON); ii) two visits during weight loss (WL); iii) two
      visits during a weight regain (WG). The order of the periods (maintenance, loss or weight
      gain) will depend on the dynamics of the weight variations of each athlete (endurance sport
      and weight class) during the season and will therefore be individualized.

      All experiments will be conducted in the same way for the CON, WL or WG session.

      Upon arrival, each subject will perform a resting metabolism with continuous measurement of
      heart rate variability (≈ 30 min). Then, from 8:30, blood and saliva samples will be taken (≈
      10 min). Then (≈ 8:45), they will perform anthropometric and body composition measurements
      (waist circumference, hip circumference, bioimpedance, DXA) (≈ 30 min). Following these
      measurements (≈ 9:15), the subjects will eat a standardized breakfast and the report to food
      will be evaluated thanks to the Leeds Foods Preference Questionnaire before and after the
      meal. They will then be asked (≈ 10h) to complete the Profile of Mood State Questionnaire to
      measure the athlete's psychological state. Participants will then perform a measurement of
      muscle function (≈ 10:30).

      During the second visit, carried out between 1 and 5 days after the first visit, the maximum
      aerobic capacity of the athletes will be evaluated by mid-morning stress test.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">November 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Body temperature</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 , Day 60 , Day 90</time_frame>
    <description>body temperature will be assessed using the bodyCap temperature monitor that records body temperature for up to 48h. this will be assessed for 24h on the three different phase (i) period of maintenance of body weight (CON); ii) two visits during weight loss (WL); iii) two visits during a weight regain (WG).)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Body fat mass</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 , Day 60 , Day 90</time_frame>
    <description>the percentage of body fat will be assessed using X-ray absorptiometry (DXA)
. This will be assessed on the three different phase (i) period of maintenance of body weight (CON); ii) two visits during weight loss (WL); iii) two visits during a weight regain (WG).)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Body fat free mass</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 , Day 60 , Day 90</time_frame>
    <description>the percentage of body fat free will be assessed using X-ray absorptiometry (DXA)
. This will be assessed on the three different phase (i) period of maintenance of body weight (CON); ii) two visits during weight loss (WL); iii) two visits during a weight regain (WG).)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Food reward</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 , Day 60 , Day 90</time_frame>
    <description>The participants will be asked to complete a validated computer-based procedure to measure food reward (Leeds Food Preference Questionnaire; LFPQ) (Finlayson, King et al. 2008). This will be assessed on the three different phase (i) period of maintenance of body weight (CON); ii) two visits during weight loss (WL); iii) two visits during a weight regain (WG).)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Basal Metabolic rate</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 , Day 60 , Day 90</time_frame>
    <description>the resting energy expenditure will be assessed at rest during 30 minutes using indirect calorimetry (COSMED Fitmate Pro)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cortisol</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 , Day 60 , Day 90</time_frame>
    <description>Cortisol concentrations will be assessed in the fasting state using salivary sample.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Measure of insulin mlUI/L</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 , Day 60 , Day 90</time_frame>
    <description>Insulin concentrations will be assessed in the fasting state using blood sample.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Measure of glucose g/L</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 , Day 60 , Day 90</time_frame>
    <description>Glucose concentrations will be assessed in the fasting state using blood sample.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Measure of triglycerides g/L</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 , Day 60 , Day 90</time_frame>
    <description>triglycerides concentrations will be assessed in the fasting state using blood sample.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Measure of LDL g/L</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 , Day 60 , Day 90</time_frame>
    <description>LDL concentrations will be assessed in the fasting state using blood sample.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Measure of HDL g/L</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 , Day 60 , Day 90</time_frame>
    <description>HDL concentrations will be assessed in the fasting state using blood sample.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Measure of cholesterol g/L</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 , Day 60 , Day 90</time_frame>
    <description>cholesterol concentrations will be assessed in the fasting state using blood sample.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Psychological profile</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 , Day 60 , Day 90</time_frame>
    <description>The psychological profile of the athletes will be assessed using the Profile of Mood state questionnaire that is a self-reported short pain and paper questionnaire.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Muscle strength</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 , Day 60 , Day 90</time_frame>
    <description>the muscle strength (in watt) will be assessed during a forced isometric contraction on a biodex.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">48</enrollment>
  <condition>Athletes</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>athletes</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>48 elite athletes, 24 men and 24 women, experiencing regular weight cycling.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>athletes</intervention_name>
    <description>Control of body temperature using the bodyCap temperature monitor that records body temperature for up to 48h (three times)</description>
    <arm_group_label>athletes</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects aged 18 to 35 (inclusive),

          -  exercising at least 4 sessions of endurance or weight-based sporting activities per
             week for a performance objective,

          -  having variations of at least 5% of their weight body during the last 3 sporting
             seasons (a sporting season corresponds to a year during which alternates the periods
             of training, recovery and participation in official competitions).

          -  Subject capable of providing informed consent to participate

          -  Subject with a social security insurance.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Medical or surgical history deemed by the investigator to be incompatible with the
             study.

          -  Presence of chronic pathology.

          -  Disorders of eating behavior.

          -  Subjects born very prematurely defined as a pregnancy inferior to 28 weeks.

          -  Subjects having used a treatment for a small stature (eg growth hormone).

          -  For women: irregular menstruation (changes in menstrual cycles ≥ 6 days).

          -  Sports subjects with a stable weight during the last three sporting seasons (weight
             variation &lt;5%).

          -  Take medication that can change body temperature.

          -  Pregnant or lactating women.

          -  Subjects with gastrointestinal complications and / or contraindications to ingestion
             of the capsule (eg diverticulosis, inflammatory bowel disease, gastrointestinal
             surgery ...).

          -  Subjects needing MRI during ingestion of the capsule or having a pacemaker or other
             implanted electro-medical device.

          -  Person under guardianship or not subject to a social security scheme.

          -  Refusal to sign the information and consent leaflet.

          -  Refusal of participation
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>35 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Martine Duclos</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University Hospital, Clermont-Ferrand</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Lise Laclautre</last_name>
    <phone>334.73.754.963</phone>
    <email>promo_interne_drci@chu-clermontferrand.fr</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Chu Clermont Ferrand</name>
      <address>
        <city>Clermont-Ferrand</city>
        <zip>63003</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 20, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 26, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 27, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 26, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 26, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">September 27, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>weight cycling</keyword>
  <keyword>sport</keyword>
  <keyword>appetite</keyword>
  <keyword>energy metabolism</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

