<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04109027</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>N3141-R</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04109027</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Strengthening Neuro-Cognitive Skills for Success in School, Work and Beyond</brief_title>
  <official_title>Strengthening Neuro-Cognitive Skills for Success in School, Work and Beyond</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>VA Office of Research and Development</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>VA Office of Research and Development</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      For many Veterans, success in achieving goals at work, school and in other aspects of life
      are top priorities. The abilities to regulate attention, remember key information, and stay
      calm and on track are fundamental to this success. Unfortunately, Veterans who have
      experienced a traumatic brain injury (TBI) often struggle with these very abilities, and a
      number of barriers can make it difficult for them to access the help Veterans need.
      Tele-rehabilitation has the potential to overcome some of these barriers and increase access
      to care, enabling providers to better reach Veterans 'where they are' in their communities.
      This project will assess two different approaches to brain injury rehabilitation that seek to
      help Veterans build personal strengths to better accomplish their goals. Both approaches will
      be delivered remotely via tele-rehabilitation and augmented by digital apps to best support
      Veterans' learning in community settings outside the VA.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This project will offer two training approaches targeting difficulties with goal-directed
      functioning associated with traumatic brain injury. Both approaches will be delivered
      remotely via tele-rehabilitation and augmented by digital apps - an intervention framework
      that addresses known barriers to engagement (e.g., convenience and access) and provides tools
      to intensify training. The study will be open to eligible Veterans (ages 21-60 years old)
      with history of mild-to-moderate TBI who experience difficulties with cognitive-emotional
      regulation and goal-directed functioning. After screening for eligibility and providing
      informed consent, participants will be allocated by permuted block randomization into one of
      two treatments: Education to optimize brain functioning (OPT), which will teach Veterans
      about brain health, brain injury and factors that affect brain functioning, or training in
      goal-directed state regulation skills (GSR), which will teach Veterans skills for regulating
      cognitive-emotional functioning during goal pursuit. A special emphasis on outreach will be
      to recruit student Veterans with TBI.

      Each intervention will be matched for delivery method, expectation of benefit, workload and
      attention, and overall duration. Training will last approximately five weeks, accommodating
      typical academic schedules. Participants will undergo multi-level assessments at baseline
      (prior to interventions), immediately after training, and at 3 months follow-up, administered
      in-person by staff at study sites. In order to investigate effects on goal-directed
      functioning at multiple levels, assessments will include (1) measures of performance on
      neurocognitive tasks; (2) functional performance on complex, goal-based tasks; (3) ratings of
      changes in functioning in personal life, and (4) progress toward personal goals as measured
      with goal attainment scaling procedures. Data will be analyzed to assess immediate and long
      term changes associated with each intervention; immediate and long-term differences between
      the interventions; and moderators and mediators of intervention effects.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">September 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2, 2024</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Randomized trial with two active comparison interventions</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>Outcomes assessors and investigators will be blinded to study arm. Participants will have equal expectations of learning and benefit from the two active comparisons, though they cannot be blinded to the content of the training interventions. Trainers will have to be aware of the training content.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Selective Information Processing</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline to 2 weeks post-intervention</time_frame>
    <description>In order to test a primary hypothesis related to potential intervention mechanisms, the investigators will use the well-established Automated Operation Span Task (OSPAN) to measure working memory in the presence of distractions. Specifically, the OSPAN sums correctly recalled and ordered items from a memory set in the presence of distractors. The investigators elected to use this psychometric measure due to its sensitivity, precision, and test-retest stability in order to maximize the ability to detect longitudinal changes on the primary outcome of interest.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Observed Functional performance</measure>
    <time_frame>2 weeks post-intervention, 3 months post-intervention</time_frame>
    <description>The Goal Processing Scale (GPS) measures goal-directed functioning in a complex, ecologically-valid setting. This timed procedure requires participants gather information on three different self-selected activities. Throughout the task, participants are required to follow specific rules and manage unanticipated challenges (e.g., distractions). Evaluators, following a well-specified manual, rate participants' performance across multiple domains of functioning (e.g., maintaining attention in a distracting environment, cognitive flexibility) while they complete the task. The outcome variable of interest will be changes to the GPS total score. GPS scores range from 0 - 10, with higher scores reflecting better goal-directed functioning. Positive change scores will reflect pre-post training improvements to goal-directed functioning, with negative change scores reflecting pre-post worsening of goal-directed functioning.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progress Towards Goal Attainment</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months post-intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Goal Attainment Scaling (GAS) procedures will be used for setting and measuring progress toward participant goals. GAS is a six-step process to quantify clinically meaningful change. GAS is a highly individualized but quantitative outcome measure. Participants will define goals to complete and identify objective and observable outcomes for each goal, consisting of outcomes both better and worse than anticipated. Participants weigh goals based upon their estimated difficulty level and priority. GAS scores range from -2 to +2, with negative scores indicating participants achieved less than expected, a score of &quot;0&quot; indicating that participants achieved at expectation, and positive scores indicating that participants scored better than expected. The outcome of interest will be the weighted average of each GAS score evaluated post-intervention.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">120</enrollment>
  <condition>TBI</condition>
  <condition>Cognitive Dysfunction</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>BrainStrong-GSR</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Goal-directed State Regulation Training (GSR)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>BrainStrong-OPT</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Optimization of Brain Functioning (OPT)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>BrainStrong-GSR</intervention_name>
    <description>Goal-directed State Regulation Training (GSR)</description>
    <arm_group_label>BrainStrong-GSR</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Goal-directed State Regulation Training (GSR)</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>BrainStrong-OPT</intervention_name>
    <description>Optimization of Brain Functioning (OPT)</description>
    <arm_group_label>BrainStrong-OPT</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Optimization of Brain Functioning (OPT)</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Post 9/11 Veterans

          -  age 21-60; with history of mild-moderate TBI (including reported mechanism of head
             injury and alteration of consciousness);

          -  in the chronic, stable phase of recovery (&gt;6 months from injury); with at least 1
             self-reported cognitive symptom, --including difficulties with working memory; and
             interested in goal-setting and intensive training.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Severely apathetic/abulic, aphasic, or other reasons for being unable or unwilling to
             participate in training;

          -  severe cognitive dysfunction (below 2 standard deviations on two composite cognitive
             domains);

          -  schizophrenia;

          -  bipolar disorder;

          -  history of other neurological disorders;

          -  current medical illnesses that may alter mental status or disrupt participation in the
             study;

          -  active psychotropic medication changes;

          -  symptom magnification or malingering.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>21 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>60 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Anthony J. W. Chen, MD MA</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>VA Northern California Health Care System, Mather, CA</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Miguel A Sanchez</last_name>
    <phone>(925) 372-2292</phone>
    <email>Miguel.Sanchez@va.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Dawn C Schwenke, PhD MS</last_name>
    <phone>(916) 843-2776</phone>
    <email>Dawn.Schwenke@va.gov</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>VA Northern California Health Care System, Mather, CA</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sacramento</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>95655</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jefferson Lee</last_name>
      <phone>(916) 843-2769</phone>
      <email>Jefferson.Lee2@va.gov</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Laura L Jones</last_name>
      <phone>(916) 366-5333</phone>
      <email>Laura.Jones01@va.gov</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Anthony J. W. Chen, MD MA</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 26, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 26, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 30, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 29, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 29, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 30, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>attention</keyword>
  <keyword>working memory</keyword>
  <keyword>executive functioning</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cognitive Dysfunction</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

