<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04105296</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2501</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04105296</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Epidural Stimulation After Spinal Cord Injury</brief_title>
  <acronym>ESL-SCI</acronym>
  <official_title>Epidural Stimulation for Locomotion After Spinal Cord Injury</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>McGuire Research Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>McGuire Research Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_unapproved_device>Yes</is_unapproved_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of the current study is to determine the effects of applying epidural stimulation
      (ES) on motor control recovery in Veterans with SCI. The intervention will be accompanied
      with the use of a powered exoskeleton (EKSO®) for 6 months to facilitate standing and to
      produce step-like movement in persons with chronic motor complete (AIS A or B) SCI and level
      of injury below C5 . Walking speed, distance, muscle activation pattern as measured by
      surface EMG and walking parameters including stand-up time, walking time, distance will be
      considered primary outcome variables. Cardiovascular performance, as measured by resting
      blood pressure and heart rate, peak oxygen consumption during walking, energy expenditure,
      whole and regional body composition assessments will also be measured. The effects of
      training (ES+EKSO) on , and speed of walking will also be evaluated.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Five veterans with chronic motor complete SCI (AIS A or B) will be recruited to participate
      in the current trial. The primary objective is to determine how implantation of an epidural
      stimulator can help to control movement in the leg muscles to stand and perform stepping.
      Participants will be trained using a robotic suit and parallel bars. The procedure of using
      epidural stimulation with the robotic suit is experimental. The participant will be scheduled
      to perform temporary implantation followed by permanent implantation. Seven days later, two
      8-electrode arrays of Vectris lead will be implanted in an operating room. The research team
      will be responsible for helping the participants to trigger the paralyzed muscles from supine
      and sitting using for 5 days per week. Participants would be required to come for study
      visits twice daily for 2 hours per day. Each visit will last approximately 1 hour in the
      morning and 1 hour in the evening. During these visits, participants will practice walking
      with a robotic suit for 30-60 minutes followed by overground walking between parallel bars,
      or with a walker or crutches.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">January 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 30, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 30, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Device Feasibility</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Six minute-walk and 10-meter walk distance Tests</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Walking distance and speed will also be determined</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Surface electromyography of 6 different muscle groups</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>The EMG activity from 6 major leg muscles will be measured during locomotion</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Systolic and Diastolic Blood Pressure</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>During sitting, standing and walking</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Oxygen uptake using Portable Indirect Calorimetry</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>During sitting, standing and walking</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Body composition assessment of fat mass and fat-free mass using dual energy x-ray absorptiometry (DXA)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Before and after training</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">5</enrollment>
  <condition>Spinal Cord Injuries</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>EKSO+ES</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>6 months of exoskeleton training with spinal cord epidural stimulation.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>EKSO+ES</intervention_name>
    <description>6 months of exoskeleton training with epidural stimulation.</description>
    <arm_group_label>EKSO+ES</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. A written clearance by the medical doctor to ensure that the participant is safely
             able to engage in the program.

          2. Participants who require assistance with activities of daily living, must have a
             caregiver or companion with them throughout their participation in the study.

          3. Participants will have to be 2 years post-injury with any level of injury below C5 and
             using wheelchair as the primary mode of mobility. The study is primarily exploratory,
             and all participants will be between 18-70 years old with SCI.

          4. Hip width (distance between two greater trochanters), upper leg length (greater
             trochanter to the lateral aspect of joint line of the knee joint) and lower leg length
             (lateral aspect of joint line of the knee joint to the bottom of the foot) that can
             fit the robotic suit.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Unhealed fracture in either lower or upper extremities

          2. Severe scoliosis, hip knee ROM or flexion knee contractures preventing positioning in
             an exoskeleton or plantarflexion deformity greater than 20 degrees.

          3. High resting blood pressure greater than 140/80 mmHg and or sudden hypotension upon
             standing as characterized by drop in blood pressure by 20 mmHg especially in persons
             with tetraplegia.

          4. Other medical conditions including cardiovascular disease, uncontrolled type II DM,
             uncontrolled hypertension, and those on insulin, pressures sores stage 3 or greater,
             or symptomatic urinary tract infection.

          5. Unable to fit in the device for any reason.

          6. Taking anti-coagulants or anti-platelet agents, including aspirin if unable to be off
             this medication for medical reasons.

          7. Implanted pacemakers and/or implanted defibrillator devices.

          8. Any condition that, in the judgment of the principal investigator or medical provider,
             precludes safe participation in the study and/or increases the risk of infection.

          9. Dual Energy X-ray Absorptiometry (DXA) T-Score less than -2.5. Scans done will include
             total body, dual hips and knees.

         10. Functional upper and lower extremity range of motion (ROM), strength, spasticity and
             skin integrity will also have assessed prior to enrollment in the program. The
             Modified Ashworth Scale will be used to ensure safety of the participants prior to
             engagement in the rehabilitation program. Participants with severe spasticity or
             limited ROM will be excluded in the trial. This will be done based on the
             manufacture's recommendation.

         11. Other exclusion criteria may include the followings

               -  subjects with uncontrolled autonomic dysreflexia

               -  subjects with concurrent severe neurological injuries other than SCI: MS, CP,
                  TBI, stroke;

               -  subjects with unresolved deep vein thrombosis (DVT);

               -  subjects with prosthetic lower limbs;

               -  subjects with psychiatric or cognitive impairments which will interfere with
                  proper operation of both the spinal cord stimulator as well as the exoskeleton;

               -  subjects with an unhealed spinal fracture or unstable spine; and

               -  subjects with known cardiac pathology which precludes safe participation
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ashraf S Gorgey, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Hunter Holmes McGuire VA Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Ashraf S Gorgey, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>8046755000</phone>
    <phone_ext>3386</phone_ext>
    <email>ashraf.gorgey@va.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Robert Trainer, MD</last_name>
    <email>Robert.Trainer@va.gov</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hunter Holmes McGuire VA Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Richmond</city>
        <state>Virginia</state>
        <zip>23249</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 23, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 24, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 26, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 2, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 2, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 3, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Spinal Cord Injuries</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Wounds and Injuries</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>IPD will be available in the form of published case reports as well as scientific presentations in national and international meetings.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

