<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04105465</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PJBGNDRSCH</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04105465</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study to Evaluate the Role of PlasmaJet in Patients Undergoing Groin Node Dissection for Vulval Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>Randomised,Crossover, Feasibility Study to Evaluate the PlasmaJet in the Management of Lymphedema and Lymphocyst Formation in Patients Undergoing Bilateral Groin Node Dissection (BGND) for Vulval Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Royal Surrey County Hospital NHS Foundation Trust</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Royal Surrey County Hospital NHS Foundation Trust</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Surgery for vulvar cancer involves removal of the central tumour as well as groin node
      dissection as indicated depending on the stage of tumour. Groin node dissection is associated
      with significant complications including lymphorrea, lymphocyst formation, wound breakdown as
      well as long term complications including lymphedema.

      This study has been designed with each patient acting as their own control to investigate if
      using the PlasmaJet during surgery is associated with a reduction in the above mentioned
      complications.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Vulvar malignancy is the fourth most common malignancy of the female genital tract. Surgical
      excision achieves excellent local control and remains the mainstay of treatment.

      Surgical excision depends on the extent of disease and may be in the form of wide local
      excision or radical vulvectomy. Lymphadenectomy in the form of bilateral groin node
      dissection (BGND) is performed for all central tumors with depth of invasion greater than 1
      mm, unless there is significant comorbidity contraindicating this, but is known to cause
      significant postoperative morbidity. Immediate postoperative complications include breakdown
      and lymphocyst formation in more than 50% of cases. The PlasmaJet is a novel device that
      produces a jet of pure argon plasma by heating pressurized argon gas. Energy from the argon
      plasma transfers to tissue as light, heat, and kinetic energy.

      Following ethical approval, a prospective, crossover, doubleblind, randomized, control trial
      to assess the PJ system, with the primary outcome being the possibility of reduction in wound
      breakdown and lymphocyst and lymphedema formation following BGND for vulvar cancer was
      opened.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Conflict with another study that was opened to recruitment
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">July 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>The trial design was conceived as a single site, double blind, crossover study in which each patient would be their own control would offer the most useful information.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>A double blind system was applied. Since randomisation was performed in theatre, the patient was unaware of the side that the PJ device was applied. This was not mentioned in the operation notes either. As a result, the nursing team on the inpatient ward were also blinded to the randomisation.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Feasibility of recruitment into the pilot study.The rate (% and absolute rate) of recruitment</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with treatment-related adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>Upto 1 year following surgery</time_frame>
    <description>To document the side-effect profile post-operatively following surgery with the PJ device.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Risk of groin lymphorrea/ lymphocyst formation using daily drain outputs</measure>
    <time_frame>Upto 1 year following surgery</time_frame>
    <description>To explore the potential and safety of the PJ device in the prevention of groin lymphocyst formation by prophylactic coagulation of lymph vessels in patients undergoing BGND for vulval cancer</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Wound Infection</measure>
    <time_frame>Upto 3months following surgery or till groins healed whichever is sooner</time_frame>
    <description>Rate of wound infection following standard surgery vs PlasmaJet use in the groins will be assessed</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Length of Stay</measure>
    <time_frame>Until 14 days following surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Length of hospital stay following surgery will be recorded as well as any readmissions</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Lymphedema using the CTC V3.0 grading system</measure>
    <time_frame>Upto two years following study entry</time_frame>
    <description>Grade of lymphedema to be assessed at each clinic visit for two years following surgery</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">21</enrollment>
  <condition>Vulvar Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Groin Node</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Surgery without trial (PJ) device</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>All steps of surgery are conducted as per standard practice in accordance with the current practice at the time. In all cases a bilateral inguino-femoral groin node dissection was performed, with en-bloc removal of the superficial and deep inguinal nodes with conservation of the long saphenous vein.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Surgery with trial (PJ) device</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Use of the PJ was limited to the randomised side only. All steps of surgery are conducted as per standard practice in accordance with the current practice at the time. In all cases a bilateral inguino-femoral groin node dissection was performed, with en-bloc removal of the superficial and deep inguinal nodes with conservation of the long saphenous vein. Haemostasis was ensured with diathermy and ties and just prior to wound closure, the surgeon used the PlasmaJet on the indicated groin to seal the lymph vessels and channels at a setting of 40% by spraying the argon plasma over the entire exposed surgical field at a distance of 10 mm from the surface to the tip of the instrument.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>PlasmaJet</intervention_name>
    <description>The PlasmaJet device is used following groin node dissection on the side randomised to receive it as per protocol specifications</description>
    <arm_group_label>Surgery with trial (PJ) device</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  To be included in this study, all women should undergo BGND during their treatment
             pathway for histologically confirmed vulval cancer.

          -  Participant is willing and able to provide informed consent.

          -  Aged 18 years or above.

          -  Participant willing to allow General Practitioner and other health care professionals,
             if appropriate, to be notified of participation in study.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Women with vulval cancer who do not undergo BGND.

          -  Women with any previous groin surgery

          -  Women with any previous radiotherapy to the pelvic area including the groins

          -  Patient choice

          -  Women who are pregnant, lactating or planning pregnancy during the course of the study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <gender_based>Yes</gender_based>
    <gender_description>Women undergoing BGND during their treatment pathway for histologically confirmed vulval cancer</gender_description>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Thumuluru K Madhuri, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Royal Surrey County Hospitals NHS Foundation Trust</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of Gynaecological Oncology, Royal Surrey County Hospital NHS Foundation Trust</name>
      <address>
        <city>Guildford</city>
        <state>Surrey</state>
        <zip>GU2 7XX</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 11, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 25, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 26, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 26, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 26, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">September 27, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Royal Surrey County Hospital NHS Foundation Trust</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Dr Thumuluru Kavitha Madhuri</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Senior Clinical Fellow</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>vulvar cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>groin node dissection</keyword>
  <keyword>bilateral groin node dissection</keyword>
  <keyword>lymphedema</keyword>
  <keyword>lymphocyst</keyword>
  <keyword>lymphorrea</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Vulvar Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphadenopathy</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>No patient indentifiable data will be shared however anonymised data can be made available on request</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

