<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04101422</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MCC-20007</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04101422</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Utilizing Augmented Reality as an Adjunct for Smoking Cessation</brief_title>
  <official_title>Utilizing Augmented Reality as an Adjunct for Smoking Cessation; Development and Initial Validation</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>H. Lee Moffitt Cancer Center and Research Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institutes of Health (NIH)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>H. Lee Moffitt Cancer Center and Research Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of the study is to develop an preliminary test a tobacco smoking-related
      augmented reality (AR) paradigm for eventual development as an adjunctive tobacco cessation
      intervention.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 19, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 1, 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 1, 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Urge to Smoke</measure>
    <time_frame>Pilot Testing and Laboratory Validation Sessions 1 and 2: Base line and post-cue presentation. Testing AR Application: Baseline to up to day 7</time_frame>
    <description>Participants will rate their urge to smoke on a 10-point Likert scale from 1 (absolutely no urge to smoke) to 10 (strongest urge to smoke).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Reality/Co-Existence</measure>
    <time_frame>Base line to post image presentation or post session</time_frame>
    <description>Three items will be used to assess the quality of the AR experience. Reality (How real did the object seem to you?) Environment Co-Existence (How well did the the object appear to be part of the scene?) and User Co-Existence (How much did you feel the object was right there in front of you?). These 3 items will be assessed using a 10 point Likert Scale from from 1 (Not at all) to 10 (Very much).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>5</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">172</enrollment>
  <condition>Smoking</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Development of Augmented Reality (AR) Application</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Investigators will collaborate with an AR software specialist to develop AR stimuli that are embedded within a basic digital application.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Pilot Testing of AR Application</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>AR stimuli (smoking, e.g, cigarette, ashtray, lighter; and non-smoking, e.g., pen, notebook, eraser) will be piloted on a small group of smokers to receive feedback and modify as needed. Participants will answer questions from a 10 point Likert scale that will asses urge from 1 (absolutely no urge to smoke) to 10 (strongest urge to smoke) and reality/co-existence (how realistic the item looks, and it's integration into the environment), from 1 (Not at all) to 10 (Very Much). Participants will then be asked additional open-ended questions about the quality of the images following the ratings of the images.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Laboratory Validation of AR Stimuli Session 1: Cue Reactivity</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>142 study participants will attend 1st lab based session that will test cue-reactivity. Participant will be randomized to view either AR images, or in vivo items first. Order of presentation of items will also be randomized within the type (AR or in vivo).Session 1 should last under 1 hour.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Laboratory Validation of AR Stimuli Session 2: Extinction</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will be randomized into either the extinction or control group. 28 trials of AR cues will be presented for each group. Both groups will receive the same neutral cue in Trial 1 (to establish baseline urge) and the same smoking cue in Trial 2 (for pre-test cue-reactivity). The extinction group will receive smoking cues for trials 3-26, whereas the control group will receive neutral cues. Both groups will receive matched smoking cues for trial (27) followed by matched neutral cues for the final trial (28), for post-test cuereactivity. Each cue will be presented for 1 minute and will be shown 4 times in trials 3-26. Following each cue, participants will complete the single-item measure of urge. Following the final trial (28) for both groups, participants will be presented with one of their own cigarettes and asked to take at least one puff. Latency to smoke will later be determined using time stamps on the video recording. Session 2 is expected to last 1.25 hours.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Testing AR Application</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>20 Participants will be instructed to use the AR app that presents smoking-related stimuli (cigarette, ashtray, lighter) in locations/situations where they typically smoke with the goal of at least 5 uses per day for 7 days. Usage and rating data will be collected in real-time. Participants will also be asked to rate their urge to smoke on the smartphone app at selected times. Participants will then return to the lab to provide additional feedback on the app, answer questions related to smoking behavior, and receive an in-person interview on their perceptions of the app as a potential cessation tool. Participants will use the smart phone application for 7 days.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Augmented Reality 1</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will use an Augmented Reality (AR) application on smart phones. The AR application will create simulated examples of AR stimuli (cigarettes, lighters, ashtrays) and non-smoking related stimuli (pens, notebook, eraser).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Pilot Testing of AR Application</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Augmented Reality 2</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will use an Augmented Reality (AR) application on smart phones. The AR application will create simulated examples of smoking related AR stimuli (cigarettes, lighters, ashtrays) as well as non-smoking images (pens, notebook, etc.). They will also be presented with real smoking (e.g., ashtray) and non-smoking (e.g., pencil) items. Their urge to smoke rating following each presentation will be compared for AR images vs. vivo items, and smoking-related vs. non-smoking related.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Laboratory Validation of AR Stimuli Session 1: Cue Reactivity</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Augmented Reality 3</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will use an Augmented Reality )AR) application on smart phones in locations and situations where they typically smoke. the application will create simulated examples of AR stimuli (cigarettes, lighters, ashtrays). Participants will have a goal of using application at least 5 times per day for 7 days. Usage and rating data will be collected in real-time.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Testing AR Application</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Augmented Reality 4</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will use an Augmented Reality (AR) application on smart phones. The AR application will create simulated examples of AR stimuli (cigarettes, lighters, ashtrays) as well as non-smoking images (pens, notebook, etc.) Their urge to smoke rating following each presentation will be compared from baseline urge to smoke. The post-test urge to smoke will be compared between control group and extinction group.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Laboratory Validation of AR Stimuli Session 2: Extinction</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Currently smoking ≥ 3 cigarettes per day for the past year

          -  Breath carbon monoxide (CO) level ≥ 5 ppm

          -  Motivated to quit smoking

          -  Valid home address in the Tampa Bay area

          -  Functioning telephone number

          -  Can speak, read, and write in English

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Regular use (e.g., no more than 1/3 of month) of other tobacco products (cigars)

          -  Household member already enrolled in the study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Christine Vinci, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Moffitt Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Thomas Brandon, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Moffitt Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Christine Vinci, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <phone>(813)745-5421</phone>
    <email>Christine.Vinci@Moffitt.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Thomas Brandon, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <phone>(813) 745-1750</phone>
    <email>Thomas.Brandon@Moffitt.org</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Moffitt Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tampa</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33612</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Christine Vinci, Ph.D.</last_name>
      <phone>813-745-5421</phone>
      <email>Christine.Vinci@Moffitt.org</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Thomas Brandon, Ph.D.</last_name>
      <phone>(813) 745-1750</phone>
      <email>Thomas.Brandon@Moffitt.org</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Steve Sutton, Ph.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 23, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 23, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 24, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 3, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 3, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 6, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Quit Smoking</keyword>
  <keyword>Augmented Reality</keyword>
  <keyword>Smoking</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

