<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04101747</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>XC2</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04101747</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>To Explore the Diversity of Intestinal Flora in Patients With Advanced HCC Combin ed With Anti-PD-1 and Targeted Drug Therapy and the Correlation Between Metabolites and Therapeutic Effect</brief_title>
  <official_title>To Explore the Diversity of Intestinal Flora in Patients With Advanced Hepatocellular Carcinoma Receiving Anti-PD-1 Combined With Targeted Drug Therapy and the Correlation Between Metabolites and Therapeutic Effect:A Multi-Center Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Sun Yat-sen University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Sun Yat-Sen Memorial Hospital of Sun Yat-Sen University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>First Affiliated Hospital, Sun Yat-Sen University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Sun Yat-sen University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The study is to explore the correlation between intestinal flora diversity and meta bolites
      in patients with advanced lver cancer rceiving Anti-PD-1 combined target-ed drug therapy,so
      that to get the analysis of intestinal flora of PD-1 inhibitors in liver cancer.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The combination of PD-1/PD-L1 inhibitors and targeted drugs as a promising strategy for the
      treatment of hepatocellular carcinoma has a breakthrough significance for the treatment of
      some advanced and refractory tumors.However,studies have shown that intestinal flora
      diversity indicates a good prognosis of PD-1/PD-L1 inhibitors in the treatment of non-small
      cell lung cancer, the intestinal flora analysis of PD-1 inhibitors in hepatocellular
      carcinoma is still a new field to be explored.

      This study is to select patients who meet the criteria of entry and discharge, sign informed
      consent, obtain patients'clinical data, pathological and case data, and enter the database.
      Before the treatment of PD-1 (no more than 24 hours), during the treatment of PD-1 (every
      time before treatment, three weeks, a total of 11 follow-up visits), at the end of treatment,
      fecal samples were collected in sterile containers for 5-10g, and feces were stored at 4
      degrees C, frozen at - 80 degrees C within 24 hours; the response to treatment was evaluated
      every 6 weeks, and the disease was first evaluated clinically. The patients were divided into
      response group (R) (partial response or stable condition) or non-response group (NR) (disease
      progression) according to RECIST 1.1 evaluation criteria. Subgroup had high diversity of
      bacteria and low diversity of bacteria, and were observed continuously until the end of
      treatment. The bacterial ribosomal DNA was extracted, metabolites were detected and flow
      cytometry was used to analyze the data. The baseline intestinal microflora diversity,
      microflora diversity mapping, continuous Shannon index curve change mapping were compared
      between groups and within groups, and correlation validation was carried out.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">November 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 30, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 30, 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Objective response rate (RR)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to approximately 3 years</time_frame>
    <description>To analyse the Objective response rate (RR) of patients with advanced HCC receiving anti-PD-1 combined with targeted drug therapy</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Disease control rate (DCR)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to approximately 3 years</time_frame>
    <description>To exprole the Disease control rate (DCR) of patients with advanced HCC receiving anti-PD-1 combined with targeted drug therapy</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of intestinal flora</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to approximately 3 years</time_frame>
    <description>To exprole the Number of intestinal flora of patients with advanced HCC receiving anti-PD-1 combined with targeted drug therapy</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Advanced Hepatocellular Carcinoma</condition>
  <biospec_retention>Samples Without DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Before the treatment of PD-1 (no more than 24 hours), during the treatment of PD-1 (every
      time before treatment, three weeks treatment, a total of 11 follow-up visits), at the end of
      treatment, fecal samples were collected in sterile containers for 5-10 g, feces were stored
      at 4 C, frozen at - 80 C within 24 hours.
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Include patients who meet the entry and discharge criteria, obtain patients'clinical data,
        pathological and case data, enter the database, collect fecal samples of 5-10g, evaluate
        the response to treatment every 6 weeks, and conduct data analysis, compare the baseline
        intestinal microflora diversity between and within groups, microflora diversity mapping,
        continuous Shannon fingers. Number curve mapping, attention to follow-up patients, record
        treatment, progress, other toxic and side effects and combined drug use information.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients signed informed voluntary enrollment and expected survival of more than 12
             weeks;

          -  Patients with HCC confirmed by histopathology or cytology or clinic are HBV-related
             HCC;

          -  No systematic treatment for HCC has been received in the past, excluding local
             chemotherapy drugs used in TACE/TAI;

          -  Not suitable for surgical treatment;

          -  Child-Pugh Class: Grade A or B (≤7 points);

          -  BCLC stage C;

          -  ECOG PS≤1;

          -  At least one measurable lesion (according to RECIST v1.1 requirement, the length of
             spiral CT of the lesion is ≥10mm or the short diameter of enlarged lymph nodes is ≥15
             mm);

          -  Organ Function Requirements (within 7 days before treatment):

        Blood routine examination: WBC (&gt;1.5 *109/L); PLT (&gt;75 *109/L); HB (&gt;90 g/L); no blood
        transfusion within 14 days before screening, G-CSF drug correction) Liver function tests:
        ALB (&gt; 29 g/L); TBiL (&lt; 1.5 * ULN); ALT, AST, AKP (&lt; 5 * ULN); INR (&lt; 2.3) or PT (&lt; 6
        seconds) exceeding normal control Renal function: Cr &lt; 1.5 ULN or CCr &gt; 50 mL/min

          -  Patients with active hepatitis B virus (HBV) infection: must receive anti HBV
             treatment;

          -  Fertility women should abstinence or use reliable methods of contraception during the
             observation of curative effect. Serum HCG test must be negative within 7 days before
             the study treatment, and must be non-lactating. When it comes to abstinence, partners
             should also have reliable and effective contraception;

          -  Assessment of patients who are eligible for anti-PD-1 combined with targeted drug
             therapy;

          -  Consent to sign informed consent and follow up for a long time.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Known hepatocholangiocarcinoma, sarcomatoid HCC, mixed cell carcinoma and lamellar
             cell carcinoma; other active malignant tumor except HCC within 5 years or
             simultaneously;

          -  Patients with moderate or severe ascites need therapeutic puncture and drainage or
             Child score &gt; 2 (except those with small amount of ascites without clinical symptoms);

          -  Patients with a history of gastrointestinal bleeding or risk of bleeding within 6
             months before the start of the study, such as severe esophageal varices, locally
             active gastrointestinal ulcer lesions, and positive persistent fecal occult blood;

          -  Known hereditary or acquired bleeding or thrombotic tendency, thrombosis or embolism
             occurred within 6 months before treatment, and aspirin &gt; 325 mg/day was taken within
             10 days before treatment;

          -  It is known that there is a history of severe allergy to any monoclonal antibody or
             anti-angiogenesis targeted drug;

          -  Severe infections occurred within 4 weeks before the start of the study, including but
             not limited to hospitalization due to infections, bacteremia or complications of
             severe pneumonia;

          -  Previous treatment with other anti-PD-1 antibodies or other immunotherapy against
             PD-1/PD-L1;

          -  Complicated with other hepatitis virus infection or alcoholic liver disease,
             hereditary metabolic liver disease, autoimmune liver disease and other liver diseases;

          -  Congenital or acquired immunodeficiency (HIV, or treatment with immunosuppressive
             agents or systemic hormones within 14 days before treatment (&gt;10mg/d prednisone or
             other hormones)

          -  There are cardiopulmonary diseases that can not be well controlled, such as cardiac
             insufficiency above NYHA II or LVEF &lt; 50% by color Doppler echocardiography, COPD with
             repeated pulmonary infections.

          -  Intravenous antibiotics or prophylactic antibiotics were given in the past month.
             -Receive immunopotentiation therapy, such as thymosin, Ridaxian, etc.

          -  Other factors that may affect the results of the study or lead to the forced
             termination of the study, such as alcoholism, drug abuse, other serious diseases
             (including mental disorders) requiring combined treatment, accompanied by family or
             social factors, may affect patient safety.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Chan Xie, Professor</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>The Third Affliated Hosoital of Sun Yat-Sun University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Chan Xie, Professor</last_name>
    <phone>8620-85252043</phone>
    <email>happyxiechan@hotmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <verification_date>August 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 22, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 22, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 24, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 22, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 22, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">September 24, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Sun Yat-sen University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Chan Xie</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor of department of infectious disease Third Affiliated Hospital,Sun Yat-Sen University</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Advanced hepatocellular carcinoma</keyword>
  <keyword>Combination of PD-1/PD-L1 Inhibitors and Targeted Drugs</keyword>
  <keyword>Diversity of intestinal flora</keyword>
  <keyword>Metabolites</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Hepatocellular</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

