<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04101565</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IRB00226367</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>1R21HD097453-01A1</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04101565</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Text4Father Pilot Feasibility, Acceptability Study</brief_title>
  <acronym>Text4Father</acronym>
  <official_title>Feasibility, Acceptability, &amp; Preliminary Efficacy of Text4Father for Improving Infant &amp; Family Health</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Johns Hopkins University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Eunice Kennedy Shriver National Institute of Child Health and Human Development (NICHD)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Johns Hopkins University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study evaluates the feasibility, acceptability, and preliminary efficacy of Text4Father
      among first-time lower income fathers. Half of the participants will receive Text4Father - a
      text messaging educational program - from mid-pregnancy through 2 months of postnatal age,
      while the other half will receive usual care.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Text4Father, a multi-modal text messaging program, is designed to increase first-time lower
      income fathers' knowledge, self-efficacy, and behavioral engagement on infant care and
      parenting. Text4Father consists of 48-weeks of twice weekly texts written at a 5th grade
      reading level. Texts include resource links and instructions to support behavior change
      (e.g., videos, infographics), starting mid-pregnancy and continuing through 2 months of
      postnatal age. Text content was developed using formative research and feedback from the
      target population, consensus building with experts, and an evidence-based review.

      Usual maternity care does not involve expectant fathers in education. Further, while father
      engagement is widely advocated, few public health and clinical approaches aim to engage
      expectant fathers during the prenatal period and first months after birth - a critical window
      of opportunity that has been insufficiently leveraged to promote father engagement when
      fathers describe being unsure of father role.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">December 26, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>2 groups will be enrolled and randomized to receipt or not receipt of the intervention.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Feasibility of overall recruitment</measure>
    <time_frame>At Baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Feasibility of recruitment: Proportion of eligible fathers who consent to study participation and recruitment by resident status.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Feasibility of overall retention</measure>
    <time_frame>Follow-up (7 months)</time_frame>
    <description>Feasibility of retention: Proportion of enrolled participants who complete 7-month follow-up survey (2-months of postnatal age).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Intervention usability</measure>
    <time_frame>Follow-up (7 months)</time_frame>
    <description>12 item self-report measure among participating intervention fathers with higher score indicating greater perceived usability of technology (text messaging program). This measure is scaled with range from 1 (low) to 5 (high).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Intervention acceptability</measure>
    <time_frame>Follow-up (7 months)</time_frame>
    <description>8 item self-report measure among participating intervention fathers with higher score indicating greater perceived acceptability of technology (text messaging program). This measure is scaled with range from 1 (low) to 5 (high).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Self-efficacy: Parenting Sense of Competence Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and 7 months</time_frame>
    <description>17 item self-report measure with higher score indicating greater confidence in overall parenting skills to assess for mean change on Parenting Sense of Competence (PSOC) from baseline (during pregnancy) to follow-up (2 months post-birth). This measure is scaled with range from 1 (low) to 6 (high).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">120</enrollment>
  <condition>Fathers</condition>
  <condition>Mhealth</condition>
  <condition>Mobile Health</condition>
  <condition>Nuclear Family</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Text4Father</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Receipt of twice-weekly texts that include resource links and instructions to support behavior change (e.g., videos, infographics) and start mid-pregnancy and continuing through 2 months of baby's age.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Usual care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Usual care that is consistent with typical maternity care in involving expectant fathers.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Text4Father</intervention_name>
    <description>Receipt of twice-weekly texts that include resource links and instructions to support behavior change (e.g., videos, infographics) and start mid-pregnancy and continuing through 2 months of age.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Text4Father</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Stated willingness to comply with all study procedures and availability for the
             duration of the study

          -  Self-reported expectant father and pregnant partner (expectant mother)

          -  Aged ≥18 years

          -  In a romantic relationship and expect to continue to be in this relationship during
             the study period

          -  Able to speak English

          -  Lower socioeconomic status (SES) (e.g., high school/general education or
             vocational/trade school or less; or qualify for Medicaid/public insurance, WIC, SNAP,
             food stamps)

          -  Access to necessary resources for participating in a technology-based intervention
             (i.e., cell phone) and willing/able to receive/send texts

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Individuals who are not able to provide informed consent.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Arik V Marcell, MD, MPH</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Johns Hopkins University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Arik V Marcell, MD, MPH</last_name>
    <phone>14432878946</phone>
    <email>amarcell@jhu.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Johns Hopkins Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21287</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Arik V Marcell, MD, MPH</last_name>
      <phone>443-287-8946</phone>
      <email>amarcell@jhu.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 23, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 23, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 24, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 6, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 6, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 8, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Fatherhood</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>The final version of collected data will be made available within thirty (30) months after the end of the data collection. Data will be preserved and made accessible along with relevant documentation via the chosen repository (e.g., through open access (Open Inter-university Consortium for Political and Social Research (ICPSR)) if possible). Johns Hopkins University School of Medicine will review the disclosure protection of the de-identified datasets. If they conclude that the risk of disclosure is too great for public access, then ICPSR's Traditional Restricted Data or Physical Data Enclave will be used for some or all of the data, with restricted access solely to approved researchers.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

