<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04101994</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>201701518A0</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04101994</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Augmented Effects of Virtual-reality Cycling Training on Upper Limb Motor Functions by NIBS in Patients With CP</brief_title>
  <official_title>Augmented Effects of Virtual-reality Cycling Training on Upper Limb Motor Functions by Noninvasive Brain Stimulation in Patients With Cerebral Palsy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Chang Gung Memorial Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Chang Gung Memorial Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Cerebral palsy (CP) is the most common childhood motor disability. Weakness, spasticity, and
      loss of dexterity are the major problems in patients with CP. A novel virtual-reality cycling
      training (VCT) program was to enhance promising muscle strength and motor function through
      promoting the participant compliance and motivation. Non-invasive brain stimulation (NIBS),
      such as repetitive transcranial magnetic stimulation (rTMS) and transcranial electric
      stimulation (TES) has potential to augment the training effects in motor neurorehabilitation
      via the modulation on neuroplasticity. Therefore, this study propose a novel intervention
      protocol to induce superior benefits on upper extremity (UE) motor function in patients with
      CP.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study aims to investigate the augmented effects of VCT on neuromotor control and UE
      motor function by NIBS in patients with CP. We hypothesize that NIBS can augment the VCT
      effects on neuromotor control and UE motor function in patients with CP because combined
      therapy integrated peripheral modification techniques (VCT) and central modulation (NIBS).
      These effects may further enhance the activity of daily living (ADL), participation, and
      health related quality of life (HRQOL). This project is executed in the following two phases:
      to investigate the augmented effects of VCT on neuromotor control and UE motor function in
      patients with CP by rTMS in phase 1 (0-1.5 years) and tCS in phase 2 (1.5-3 years).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 26, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 6, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 6, 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline Bruininks- Oseretsky Test of Motor Proficiency II at after six weeks of treatment and three month</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, after 6 weeks of treatment, 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>The Bruininks- Oseretsky Test of Motor Proficiency II (BOT-2) provides an overview of fine and gross motor skills in children and school-aged adolescents.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline Goal Attainment Scale at after six weeks of treatment and three month</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, after 6 weeks of treatment, 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Goal Attainment Scale (GAS) is used to help a person with cerebral palsy and their family develop personal goals for therapy (for each item minimum value is -2 and maximum value is 2, higher scores mean a better outcome).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline Melbourne Assessment 2 at after six weeks of treatment and three month</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, after 6 weeks of treatment, 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>The Melbourne Assessment 2 (MA2) is a valid and reliable tool for evaluating quality of upper limb movement in children with a neurological impairment aged 2.5 to 15 years.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline Quality of upper extremity skills test at after six weeks of treatment and three month</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, after 6 weeks of treatment, 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>The Quality of upper extremity skills test (QUEST) is an outcome measure that evaluates movement patterns and hand function in children with cerebral palsy.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline Box and block test at after six weeks of treatment and three month</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, after 6 weeks of treatment, 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>The Box and Block Test (BBT) measures unilateral gross manual dexterity.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline Nine-Hole test at after six weeks of treatment and three month</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, after 6 weeks of treatment, 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>The Nine-Hole Peg Test (NHPT) is used to measure finger dexterity in patients with various neurological diagnoses.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline Functional Independence Measure at after six weeks of treatment and three month</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, after 6 weeks of treatment, 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Functional Independence Measure for Children:Applicable to infants and adolescents. The main purpose is to understand and track children's life function performance, progress and goal achievement. There are three main areas: self-care, mobility, and cognition. The score is from 1 to 7 points, 1 is completely dependent, and 7 is completely independent.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline Pediatric Motor Activity Log at after six weeks of treatment and three month</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, after 6 weeks of treatment, 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>The Pediatric Motor Activity Log (PMAL) is a structured interview intended to examine how often and how well a child uses his/her involved upper extremity (UE) in their natural environment outside the therapeutic setting.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline ABILHAND Questionnaire at after six weeks of treatment and three month</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, after 6 weeks of treatment, 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>The ABILHAND questionnaire assesses bimanual ability as an interview-based test focused on the patient's perceived difficulty. The ABILHAND-KIDS questionnaire is filled in by the parent of the child by rating the child's perceived difficulty of bimanual activities.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline Assessment of Preschool Children's Participation at after six weeks of treatment and three month</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, after 6 weeks of treatment, 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Preferences for Activity of Children(APCP): For children between the ages of two and five, the questionnaire model is used to allow parents to circle the level. There are 45 questions in total, so that the case or parent can review the activities in the past 4 months and ask if the child have done this activity (1 point means yes, 0 points means no).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline Children Assessment of Participation and Enjoyment at after six weeks of treatment and three month</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, after 6 weeks of treatment, 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Children Assessment of Participation and Enjoyment(CAPE): Applicable to children or adolescents between the ages of six and twenty one, through questionnaires through self-reports or interviews, a total of 55 questions, asking children about the activities involved in the past four months (1 point for yes, 0 for no).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline Cerebral Palsy Quality of Life at after six weeks of treatment and three month</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, after 6 weeks of treatment, 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>The comparison of baseline of Cerebral Palsy Quality of Life for CP after different therapy.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline Motor Evoked Potential at after six weeks of treatment and three month</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, after 6 weeks of treatment, 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>The comparison of baseline of Motor Evoked Potential for CP after different therapy.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline Myoton at after six weeks of treatment and three month</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, after 6 weeks of treatment, 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>The comparison of baseline of Myoton for CP after different therapy.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline Hand dynamometer at after six weeks of treatment and three month</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, after 6 weeks of treatment, 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>The comparison of baseline of hand dynamometer for CP after different therapy.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline Motion analysis at after six weeks of treatment and three month</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, after 6 weeks of treatment, 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>All participants will be instructed to perform a series of upper-extremity tasks. The tasks include reaching and grasping. An 8-camera motion analysis system (Vicon system, 3-D Oxfort Metrics Ltd, Oxford, UK) is used in conjunction with a personal computer to capture the movement of markers placed on the participant's body; analog signals were collected simultaneously. Movements were recorded at 120 Hz and digitally low-pass filtered at 5 Hz using a second-order Butterworth filter. Reference markers are placed on the distal interphalangeal joints of the thumb and index finger, the styloid process of the ulna, proximal end of the second metacarpal, and the object.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>8</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">80</enrollment>
  <condition>Cerebral Palsy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>VCT and real rTMS</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>In virtual cycling training and intermittent theta burst stimulation group (VCT + iTBS group), they received VCT and iTBS (80% of active motor threshold) on affected hemisphere.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>VCT and sham rTMS</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>In virtual cycling training and sham theta burst stimulation group (VCT + iTBS group), they received VCT and sham TBS stimulation.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>real rTMS</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>In intermittent theta burst stimulation (iTBS group), they received iTBS (80% of active motor threshold) on affected hemisphere.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>sham rTMS</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Sham Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>In sham theta burst stimulation (sham TBS group), they received sham TBS stimulation.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>VCT and real TES</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>In virtual cycling training and transcranial electric stimulation group (VCT + TES group), they received TES stimulation over motor cortex.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>VCT and sham TES</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>In virtual cycling training and sham transcranial electric stimulation group (VCT + sham TES group), they received VCT and sham TES stimulation.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>real TES</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>In transcranial electric stimulation group (TES group), they received TES stimulation over motor cortex.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>sham TES</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Sham Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>In sham transcranial electric stimulation group (sham TES group), they received sham TES stimulation.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Virtual cycling training</intervention_name>
    <description>Virtual cycling training is a convenient and easy approach for muscle strengthening.</description>
    <arm_group_label>VCT and real TES</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>VCT and real rTMS</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>VCT and sham TES</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>VCT and sham rTMS</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Repetitive transcranial magnetic stimulation</intervention_name>
    <description>Intermittent theta burst stimulation produces short TBS trains intermittently to facilitate cortical excitability.</description>
    <arm_group_label>VCT and real rTMS</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>VCT and sham rTMS</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>real rTMS</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>sham rTMS</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Transcranial electric stimulation</intervention_name>
    <description>TES is a constant current with low intensity delivered to the skull through surface electrodes.</description>
    <arm_group_label>VCT and real TES</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>VCT and sham TES</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>real TES</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>sham TES</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Diagnosis of CP according to clinical criteria

          -  Age 5-20 years

          -  No use of botulinum toxin in the past 4 months

          -  No significant perceptual or communication disturbances

          -  No other peripheral or central nervous system dysfunction

          -  No active inflammatory or pathologic changes in upper limb joints during the previous
             6 months

          -  No active medical problems, such as pneumonia, upper gastrointestinal bleeding, or
             urinary tract infection

          -  No active problems of epilepsy and EEG without epileptiform discharge

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Metabolic disorders, such as inborn error of metabolism, electrolyte, and endocrine
             disorders

          -  Active infectious disease, such as meningitis and encephalitis

          -  Patients with active medical problems, such as pneumonia, upper gastrointestinal
             bleeding, or urinary tract infection

          -  Poor compliance or intolerance for the TMS therapy

          -  Subjects with metallic implants or pregnancy.

          -  EEG show epileptiform discharge

          -  Patients with family history of epilipsy

          -  Patients with symptoms that are restricted from tDCS, such as epilepsy, migraine and
             unstable health condition
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>5 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>20 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Chia-Ling Chen, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Chang Gung Memorial Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Chia-Ling Chen, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+886-3-3281200</phone>
    <phone_ext>8148</phone_ext>
    <email>clingchen@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Chang Gung Memorial Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Taoyuan</city>
        <zip>333</zip>
        <country>Taiwan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Chia-Ling Chen, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>+886-3-3281200</phone>
      <phone_ext>8147</phone_ext>
      <email>clingchen@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Chia-Ling Chen, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Taiwan</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 22, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 22, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 25, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 5, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 5, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 7, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>virtual cycling training</keyword>
  <keyword>Non-invasive brain stimulation</keyword>
  <keyword>repetitive transcranial magnetic stimulation</keyword>
  <keyword>transcranial electric stimulation</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cerebral Palsy</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

