<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04100135</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>GSO 17-03</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04100135</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>GORE® CARDIOFORM Septal Occluder Migraine Clinical Study</brief_title>
  <acronym>RELIEF</acronym>
  <official_title>GORE® CARDIOFORM Septal Occluder Migraine Clinical Study: A Study to Evaluate the Safety and Efficacy of Transcatheter Closure of Patent Foramen Ovale for Relief of Migraine Headaches</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>W.L.Gore &amp; Associates</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>W.L.Gore &amp; Associates</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Multi-center, prospective, randomized, placebo- and sham-controlled study to evaluate the
      GORE® CARDIOFORM Septal Occluder for migraine headache relief
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">October 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2026</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2024</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Reduction in Migraine Headache Days: mean reduction in the number of migraine headache days per month from baseline to follow-up</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 40</time_frame>
    <description>Primary Efficacy Endpoint</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of subjects with any Serious Adverse Event (SAE) related to the study device or study procedure from procedure through 30 days post-procedure</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days post-procedure</time_frame>
    <description>Primary Safety Endpoint</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">150</enrollment>
  <condition>Migraine</condition>
  <condition>Patent Foramen Ovale</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Test Arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Device PFO closure with the GORE® CARDIOFORM Septal Occluder</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control Arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Sham Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Sham device PFO closure (PFO not closed)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Actual device PFO closure</intervention_name>
    <description>Actual PFO closure with the GORE® CARDIOFORM Septal Occluder</description>
    <arm_group_label>Test Arm</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>GORE® CARDIOFORM Septal Occluder</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Thienopyridine (clopidogrel or prasugrel)</intervention_name>
    <description>Thienopyridine tablets (clopidogrel or prasugrel) administered for 6 months following device procedure</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control Arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Test Arm</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Plavix</other_name>
    <other_name>Effient</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sham device PFO closure</intervention_name>
    <description>Sham (simulated) device PFO closure with result of no device implantation and no PFO closure</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control Arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Subject is 18-55 years of age at the screening visit.

          2. Subject is willing and capable of complying with the study protocol requirements,
             including the specified follow-up period, and can be contacted by telephone.

          3. Subject signed an Informed Consent Form prior to study participation.

          4. Subject's symptoms meet International Classification of Headache Disorders - 3
             (ICHD-3) Diagnostic Criteria for migraine with or without aura.

          5. Subject has at least one year of migraine symptom duration.

          6. Subject had migraine onset younger than 50 years of age.

          7. Subject has more than one migraine headache day per week by history - headache day
             defined as: headache that meets ICHD-3 criteria and lasts at least four hours or
             administration of acute medication before four hours (regardless of clinical response
             to acute medication).

          8. Subject has tried and failed at least two preventive medications at adequate dosage
             for an adequate duration, in the judgement of the study site neurologist, and be from
             two separate classifications of the following classes of drugs: antidepressants,
             antihypertensive, anticonvulsant, onabotulinumtoxin A, CGRP inhibitors or other
             treatments with at least one positive randomized controlled trial (See APPENDIX A).

          9. Subject must exhibit stable dosage on their preventative migraine medication for at
             least two months prior to the screening visit and agree to continue preventative
             medication at current dosage throughout the duration of the study.

         10. Female subjects are currently not pregnant and not planning pregnancy during their
             participation in the study.

         11. Female subjects capable of becoming pregnant agree to use birth control or abstinence
             during their participation in the study.

         12. Presence of Patent Foramen Ovale (PFO), as determined initially by positive bubble
             study utilizing Transthoracic Echocardiography (TTE) or transesophageal
             echocardiography (TEE), demonstrating right-to-left shunting.

         13. Subject is willing to complete daily electronic migraine headache log.

         14. Subject is not planning surgery during their participation the study.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Subject is currently enrolled in any pre-approval investigational study. (Does not
             apply to long-term post-market studies unless participation might interfere clinically
             with the RELIEF endpoints.)

          2. Subject has known organic issues which may cause headaches (e.g. temporo-mandibular
             joint, brain tumor, cervical spinal issues, known seizure disorder, etc.).

          3. Subjects with hemicrania continua, post-traumatic headache, or other trigeminal
             autonomic cephalalgia secondary headache disorders.

          4. Subject has known hypersensitivity or contraindication to thienopyridines.

          5. Subject is currently taking a P2Y12 inhibitor (See APPENDIX B).

          6. Subject has need for chronic oral anticoagulation therapy (e.g., atrial fibrillation,
             mechanical heart valve, etc.) (See APPENDIX B).

          7. Subject has need for chronic antiplatelet therapy.

          8. Subject has need for daily use of non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs) (See
             APPENDIX B).

          9. Subject has a history of thrombocytopenia within one year, or platelet count &lt;100,000
             mm3 identified during the screening phase.

         10. Subject has severe hepatic impairment with reduced synthetic function as documented by
             prolongation of PT / PTT or total bilirubin &gt; 3.0 mg / dL identified during the
             screening phase.

         11. Subject has any history of stroke, TIA, or intracranial hemorrhage.

         12. Subject has previously implanted pacemaker, IVC filter, PFO closure device, ASD
             closure device, left atrial appendage closure device OR any cardiac surgical or
             interventional history which, in the investigator's opinion, would preclude them from
             study participation.

         13. Subject has documented right-to-left shunt source in addition to PFO, such as
             pulmonary arteriovenous malformation.

         14. Subject used opioids or butalbital-containing medications for acute migraine headache
             treatment four or more times per month on average within the past six months.

         15. Subject abuses alcohol and/or drugs in the opinion of the Investigator.

         16. Subject is unable to understand the study requirements or has a history of
             non-compliance with medical advice.

         17. Subject has a history of clinically significant bleeding within six months of the
             screening visit, any active bleeding, or active peptic ulcer disease.

         18. Subject has an uncontrolled arrhythmia or, if on therapy, within the past 90 days has
             evidence of arrhythmia control failure (e.g., supraventricular tachycardia while under
             rate control or atrial fibrillation while under rhythm control).

         19. Subject has elevated pulmonary vascular resistance (PVR) which, in the opinion of the
             implanting physician, precludes safe defect closure.

         20. Subject has uncontrolled systemic hypertension at the time of screening, in the
             opinion of the investigator.

         21. In the opinion of the Investigator, patient has anatomic criteria identified during
             the screening evaluation and/or the screening echocardiogram that are unfavorable for
             successful placement of the GORE® CARDIOFORM Septal Occluder.

         22. Subject has active infection at the time of screening that cannot be treated.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>55 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Erik Ramirez</last_name>
    <phone>480-828-5597</phone>
    <email>eramirez@wlgore.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Kathy Sullivan</last_name>
    <phone>928-814-6669</phone>
    <email>kasulliv@wlgore.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 20, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 23, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 24, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 16, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 16, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 20, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Migraine Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Foramen Ovale, Patent</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Clopidogrel</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Prasugrel Hydrochloride</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

