<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04103177</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>201762</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>19/EM/0042</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04103177</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Physical Activity in Haemodialysis Patients: a Feasibility Study</brief_title>
  <acronym>PA-CKD</acronym>
  <official_title>A Structured Exercise and Educational Intervention to Increase Physical Activity in Haemodialysis Patients: a Feasibility Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Oxford Brookes University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Oxford University Hospitals NHS Trust</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Oxford Brookes University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      There is a well established link between physical inactivity and increased mortality in the
      general population and across many of the more common disease areas including chronic kidney
      disease (CKD). Patients with CKD have very high levels of morbidity and mortality and are
      known to have low fitness levels. Randomised controlled trials of exercise have demonstrated
      the benefits of physical activity for CKD patients. Despite this, physical activity levels
      remain low and translating these research findings into clinical practice is challenging.

      This feasibility study aims to assess the feasibility and acceptability of an instructor led
      structured exercise programme which includes an educational component to engage and increase
      physical activity levels in haemodialysis patients attending the Oxford University Hospitals
      Trust haemodialysis unit. Consented participants will fill in a self reported physical
      activity questionnaire (Human Activity Profile), partake in functional mobility assessments
      including (Timed-Up and Go) and a chair based exercise programme. At the end of the study,
      participants, and nursing staff will undertake a semi-structured interview aimed at
      understanding acceptability of the intervention. The results of this feasibility study will
      then be used to inform whether a larger trial in haemodialysis patients is feasible. All
      questionnaires, physical activity interventions and interviews will be undertaken during
      routine visits to the haemodialysis unit.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      There is a well established link between physical inactivity and increased mortality in the
      general population and patients with chronic kidney disease (CKD) have low fitness levels
      when compared to their healthy counterparts (50% of expected norm when commencing dialysis
      therapy). Trials have shown that physical activity confers many physical and mental health
      benefits in this patient population, with improvements in fitness, walking capacity, health
      of the heart and quality of life; indeed, national guidelines now consider physical activity
      to be a cornerstone of disease management (Cochrane Collaboration 2006; Workgroup KD 2005).
      CKD patients have lower levels of physical activity than age-matched controls; this is
      particularly marked for older patients and those on dialysis. The Department of Health
      recommends ≥150 mins/ week of moderate intensity PA (accumulated in bouts of at least 10
      minutes) for the general population (DoH UK Physical Activity Guidelines 2011). Many studies
      have sought to characterise the most effective forms of exercise for CKD patients. Recent
      attention has focussed on intradialytic cycling, with studies showing benefits not only for
      fitness and endurance but also muscle strength, power, and physical function. However,
      translating research guided physical activity programmes into routine clinical practice is
      challenging, requiring consideration of patients' physical and psychological barriers to
      exercise.

      Assessing the impact of any activity programme requires comparison of health and exercise
      behaviours pre and post intervention. Several self-report physical activity questionnaires
      are available but the Human Activity Profile has been validated in CKD patients (Johansen et
      al. 2001). However, information obtained from patient self-reporting is subjective and prone
      to bias. Objective measurement devices such as accelerometers are more accurate.

      Feasibility of an effective intervention to increase physical activity requires understanding
      of perceptions of exercise in the population of interest. In this way, the intervention can
      be specifically targeted to take account of perceived benefits and barriers towards physical
      activity and thereby increase compliance. This study will provide: 1)feasibility and
      acceptability of an instructor led chair based exercise programme and educational package
      (booklet); 2) both self-report and objective measurements of physical activity levels in a
      sample of haemodialysis patients. This key information will later be used to assess whether a
      informed large scale PA intervention study in haemodialysis patients is feasible.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">September 15, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 30, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 30, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>This pilot study will incorporate instructor led guidance of a range of chair-based exercises that focus on balance, strength, fitness, endurance and flexibility with some exercises having a cardiovascular component. These chair based exercises are drawn from programmes recommended for similar long term clinical conditions (e.g cardiovascular disease, sarcopenia, frail and elderly and renal disease) and can be performed in the clinical environment or at home.The intervention is multifaceted comprising of the following; an education booklet about PA and the chair based exercise programme, face to face instructor led support detailing the chair based exercises and instructor/nurse led motivational interviewing.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Semi structured interviews and questionnaires targeted to determine participant acceptability of PA intervention and the people delivering it</measure>
    <time_frame>Interviews should last no longer than an hour and will be conducted at month 3 post baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Interviews with patients and staff</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change is being assessed 3 metre Timed Up and Go</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline functional mobility at 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Functional activity, 1 minute to complete</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change is being assessed 10 metre walk test</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline functional mobility at 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Functional activity, 5 minutes to complete</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change is being assessed Hand grip strength</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline arm strength at 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Functional strength, 2 minutes to complete.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change is being assessed Wrist worn accelerometery data</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline of activity at 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Accelerometers to be worn for one week at 3 time points to assess daily activity</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change is being assessed EQ-5D-3L questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline quality of life at 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>This is a self-completing short questionnaire comprising questions on the following 5 areas: mobility, self-care and daily activities. This should take no longer to complete.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change is being assessed IPOS Renal questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline quality of life at 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>This is self-completing questionnaire comprising of 11 questions assessing renal symptoms with other items for additional concerns. 10 minutes to complete</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change is being assessed Human Activity profile questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline of physical activity at 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>This tick box questionnaire consists of 94 questions and seeks to determine the activities participants currently do. 15 minutes to complete</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Falls and Fractures questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline</time_frame>
    <description>We wish to know if participants have had any falls or fractures in the last 6 months and assess baseline mobility level.
Questions are based on Yes or No
Referred medical falls clinic☐ Referred therapy falls clinic☐ Referred non-FLS primary care No. of falls, slips, trips in last 12 months= Indoor Gait: range from 1-2 Outdoor Gait: range from 1-2 Any Indoor falls- yes or no
Broken bones in adult hood= Yes/No</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Client Service Receipt Inventory Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Participants will be given as short tick-box questionnaire to collect information regarding other hospitals facilities they have visited including General Practitioner visits over the last 6 months. This will exclude routine visits to haemodialysis.
Hospital departments and services used in last 6 months- No=0 Yes=1 Use of community care services in last 6 months- No=0 Yes=1 Diagnostic tests in last 6 months- No=0 Yes=1 Use of mobility aids in last 6 months- No=0 Yes=1 Adaptations at home in last 6 months-No=0 Yes=1 Changes in informal care in last 6 months months- No=0 Yes=1 Journeys to receive care in last 6 months No=0 Yes=1 Current occupation range of 1-7</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">20</enrollment>
  <condition>End Stage Renal Failure on Dialysis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>20 participants to receive physical activity educational booklet with instructions on chair based exercises, Instructor-led training on how to perform the chair based exercises, two times a week, over a 6 week period, and motivational interviewing and prompts.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Chair based exercises in the dialysis environment</intervention_name>
    <description>Each participant will be given an educational / information booklet. It will include when the right time to engage in Physical Activity. The Chair-based Exercise Program will be the focus of the exercise intervention with written step- by-step instructions with demonstrative image of the exercises. Further details included in this booklet will include, information regarding the benefits of exercise including walking and safety measures in undertaking the exercises.
Sports Exercise Instructor led Chair-based Exercise Programme Patients will be given Sports Exercise Instructor led training on how to perform the chair-based exercises, for 6 weeks. This will be delivered during one of the patients' dialysis sessions. The Instructor will deliver a short 10 minute session to patients and deliver safety instruction.
Motivational interviewing Motivational interviewing will consist of discussion to encourage the participant without coercion and help them develop goals.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  • Participant is willing and able to give informed consent for participation in the
             trial.

               -  Male or Female, aged 18 years or above.

               -  Undergoing regular haemodialysis (2 or 3 times per week) in the Oxford Main and
                  Tarver Dialysis Units

               -  Is able and willing to comply with all trial requirements.

               -  Willing to allow his or her General Practitioner and consultant, if appropriate,
                  to be notified of participation in the trial.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Unable to give consent

          -  Poor dialysis compliance

          -  Female participant who is pregnant, lactating or planning pregnancy during the course
             of the trial.

          -  Participant with life expectancy of less than 1 month and/or receiving palliative
             care.

          -  Any other significant disease or disorder which, in the opinion of the Investigator,
             may either put the participants at risk because of participation in the trial, or may
             influence the result of the trial, or the participant's ability to participate in the
             trial.

          -  Planning to leave Oxford Dialysis units within the study trial

          -  Absolute contra-indications to PA including:

               -  Recent significant change in resting ECG suggesting significant ischaemia, recent
                  Myocardial Infarction within 2 days or acute cardiac event

               -  Unstable angina

               -  Uncontrolled cardiac arrhythmia causing symptoms or haemodynamic compromise

               -  Symptomatic severe aortic stenosis

               -  Uncontrolled symptomatic heart failure

               -  Acute pulmonary embolus or infarction

               -  Acute myocarditis or pericarditis

               -  Third degree heart block

               -  Suspected or know dissecting aortic aneurysm

               -  Acute systemic infection, accompanied by fever, body aches or swollen lymph
                  glands
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Helen Dawes, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Oxford Brookes University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Sheera Sutherland</last_name>
    <phone>00441865225813</phone>
    <email>Sheera.Sutherland@ouh.nhs.uk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Helen Dawes</last_name>
    <email>hdawes@brookes.ac.uk</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <verification_date>September 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 19, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 23, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 25, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 23, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 23, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">September 25, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Oxford Brookes University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Helen Dawes</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Director Centre for Movement, Occupational and Rehabilitation Sciences</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Kidney Failure, Chronic</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Individual patient data will be shared with other researchers in accordance with NHS Information Governance Policy (NHS Information Sharing Policy v2) and Oxford Brookes data sharing policies (Oxford Brookes IT policies). Plans for data sharing will be included in the data management plan, as well as the trial protocol. A data sharing statement will be included in the consent form and information provided in the patient information leaflet.
Data will be pseudonymised wherever possible prior to being shared with other researchers and the information required to &quot;decode&quot; this data will be stored securely elsewhere, in accordance with ICH GCP guidelines. If this is not possible then consent will be obtained from participants and approval sought from the HRA prior to the trial commencing.</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>Time frame: Once all data analysis has taken place and the core findings have been published, they will be archived securely using Arkivum (see above). Dataset preparation will be carried out by individuals with an understanding of data management and basic statistics, with quality control provided by a further individual who is independent of the process. Researchers will be able to apply to access archived data as required.</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>Once data has been archived in Arkivum, access will be granted to researchers in accordance with NHS and Oxford Brookes policies. Data access requests will be made via an application form detailing the specific requirements and the proposed research and publication plan, which will be reviewed against specific eligibility criteria by data custodians or by an external Independent Review Panel. Decisions about requests will be made promptly (no more than 3 months after receipt of request) and details of all data requests and their outcomes will be made publicly available (data requesters should be informed of this in advance of this).
Funds for responsible data sharing will be requested from trial funders as part of initial trial grant applications.</ipd_access_criteria>
    <ipd_url>http://arkivum.com</ipd_url>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

