<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04107935</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>STUDY19080005</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>1R34DK123370-01</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04107935</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Telemedicine for Reach, Education, Access and Treatment-ongoing</brief_title>
  <acronym>TREAT-ON</acronym>
  <official_title>Telemedicine for Reach, Education, Access and Treatment-ongoing</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Pittsburgh</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases (NIDDK)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Pittsburgh</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Diabetes (DM) management requires health care providers to provide patients with the
      appropriate amount of time, education and support that are necessary for quality care.
      Unfortunately, this is often impeded by limited access to resources, particularly in rural
      communities where DM rates are high and providers are scarce. Therefore, study investigators
      propose addressing these issues by implementing a model of care that includes diabetes
      educator (DE)-led planned visits with a real-time videoconferencing telemedicine program for
      ongoing patient support to improve DM outcomes.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Health care systems need to seek ways through quality improvement, care coordination, and
      workforce capacity to support quality care. It has been proposed that new models of care
      coupled with technology are needed. DM provides an ideal model for testing new approaches as
      the number of people with DM continues to rise, with an inverse shortage of health providers
      available to meet their needs. Most patients with Type 2 DM (T2DM) are seen in primary care
      (PC) where providers report barriers to comprehensive care that include limited time,
      educational resources, added workload and feeling ill-equipped to counsel patients on
      behavior change. Efforts to restructure PC are underway, like DE-led planned management
      visits, reported to improve healthy behaviors and outcomes in patients at high risk. DEs are
      well suited to support the skills, decision making, self-care behaviors, problem solving and
      active collaboration with the care team that serve as the foundation for diabetes
      self-management education and key to an effective planned visit. DEs supporting care and
      self-management education in PC have been shown to improve access and outcomes. For patients
      to sustain a lifetime of behavior to effectively self-manage, continued support to sustain
      the ongoing skills, knowledge, and behaviors required to manage their condition is needed.
      Given the need for enduring support and scarcity of providers, particularly in underserved
      rural areas, efforts to understand how best to re-design practice to involve DEs in PC and
      utilize technology to enable and scale engagement in self-management and ongoing support must
      be considered. The purpose of this application is to evaluate the deployment of Telemedicine
      for Reach, Education, Access, Treatment and Ongoing Support (TREAT-ON), a DE-driven, PC-based
      telemedicine model that relies on PC practice redesign to afford access to real-time ongoing
      support. Investigators hypothesize that the TREAT-ON model will help individuals identified
      as being high risk in an underserved rural community to achieve and sustain improvements in
      clinical, psychosocial and behavioral outcomes, and aim to demonstrate the model's viability
      in terms of feasibility and acceptability to inform future testing of TREAT-ON.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Enrolling by invitation</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 4, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 15, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 15, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Health Services Research</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in glycemic control at 12 months</measure>
    <time_frame>As available from baseline through 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Hemoglobin A1c</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in diabetes self-care behaviors at 12 months</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 3 months, 6 month, and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Summary of Diabetes Self-care Activities Measure (SDSCA). This instrument will be used to evaluate self-care with questions about number of days in a week that the participant reports self-care behaviors related to general diet, specific diet, exercise, blood glucose testing. Individual items are scored 0 to 7 for number of days each behavior is performed. The more frequently the behavior occurs, the better, with the exception of smoking. Correlations with other measures of diet and exercise generally support validity of SDSCA subscales (Toobert et al, 2000).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in medication adherence at 12 months</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 3 months, 6 months, and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Medication adherence will be assessed with the 8-item Morisky Medication Adherence Scale (MMAS-8). The scales includes 8 items. Scores can range from 0 to 8; the higher the score, the more adherent the respondent is considered.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in diabetes distress at 12 months</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 3 months, 6 months, and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Diabetes distress will be evaluated with the 17-item Diabetes Distress Scale (DDS17), which assesses four dimensions of distress - emotional, regimen, interpersonal and physician (Polonsky et al, 2005), and has shown a consistent pattern of relationships with HbA1c, diabetes self-efficacy, diet and physical activity in multiple samples of patients with T2DM (Fisher et al, 2012). Individual items are scored from 1 to 6; total scores are the average of all individual item scores; higher scores indicate greater distress.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in diabetes empowerment at 12 months</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 3 month, 6 months, and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Empowerment will be measured using the 8-item Diabetes Empowerment Scale-Short Form (DES-SF), which measures an individual's perceived ability to manage psychosocial aspects of diabetes, assess dissatisfaction and readiness to change self-management plans and set and achieve diabetes goals (Anderson et al, 2000; Anderson et al, 2003). Possible scores are 1 to 5 for each item, summed for a possible total score of 8 to 40. Higher scores indicate greater empowerment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Intervention acceptability</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Telemedicine Usability Questionnaire will be used to assess telehealth usefulness, ease of use and learnability, interface quality, patient-clinician interaction, reliability, satisfaction and future use and will include additional items specific to this study. Individual items are scored on a scale from one to five, with one being strongly disagree to five being strongly agree. The higher the score infers the better the usability of the telehealth service.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Diabetes Mellitus</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Usual Care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>TREAT-ON</intervention_name>
    <description>TREAT-ON is a DE-driven self-management and support program that is delivered primarily through a real-time telemedicine videoconferencing platform. Like the usual care intervention, &quot;high risk&quot; patients with DM receiving care in underserved practices will be identified by a nurse practice-based manager (PCBM) and referred to a DE for self management services. Participants will complete an initial face-to-face visit with the DE to assess needs and develop a self-management treatment plan and goals. Via telemedicine videoconferencing, follow-up visits will be delivered by the DE to participants in their homes. Follow-up visits will be used to evaluate and support progress towards meeting and sustaining self-management goals and outcomes.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Usual Care</intervention_name>
    <description>A retrospective control group will be formed from individuals who have previously participated in a program called the &quot;Diabetes High Risk Initiative.&quot; In this program, patients receiving care in underserved practices are identified by a nurse PBCM to be at high risk for DM complications and/or unplanned care and referred to a DE for self management services delivered through primary care. Patients typically participate in one face-to-face visit with the DE to assess needs and develop self-management goals and then one to two follow-up encounters (generally conducted by telephone) with the PBCM or DE.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Usual Care</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Intervention group: UPMC Health Plan patient-members who are 18-75y, have diagnosis of
             type 2 diabetes, are considered &quot;high risk&quot; (HbA1c &gt;9%), receiving care at
             participating Federally Qualified Health Centers, and willing and able to participate
             in a technology-supported intervention.

          -  Control group: The control group will be selected from individuals who have already
             participated in the UPMC Health Plan's Diabetes High Risk Initiative.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Non UPMC Health Plan patients

          -  Not enrolled in the UPMC Health Plan Diabetes High Risk Initiative

          -  Less than 18 or greater than 75 years of age

          -  Unwilling/unable to participate in the telemedicine diabetes education program
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Linda Siminerio, RN, PhD, CDE</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Pittsburgh</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Pittsburgh Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pittsburgh</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>15213</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 25, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 25, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 27, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 27, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 27, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 31, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Pittsburgh</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Linda Siminerio</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Self management education and support</keyword>
  <keyword>Telemedicine</keyword>
  <keyword>Rural</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>After completion of the study, study investigators will prepare a consolidated dataset with all data collected as part of this study (e.g., clinical, behavioral, psychosocial, and satisfaction). All potentially identifying information will be removed. All publications will state that this dataset is available from the PI. In addition, study investigators will prepare a Manual of Operations with a detailed description of the diabetes self-management and support intervention, the technology delivery system and a full description of the TREAT-ON model for dissemination.</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Informed Consent Form (ICF)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>Study protocol and data set - After publication. ICF - After data collection is completed.</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>Study protocol and data set - other researchers will have to request access. ICF will be added to clinicaltrials.gov protocol</ipd_access_criteria>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

