<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04108429</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>K08MH112878-IET</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>K08MH112878</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04108429</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>IntelliCare in College Students - Implementation (ICCS-I)</brief_title>
  <official_title>Expanding College Student Mental Health With Stress Management Mobile Technologies - Campus Wide Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Northwestern University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Mental Health (NIMH)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Northwestern University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study is a hybrid effectiveness-implementation trial of the smartphone student
      stress-management app IntelliCare for college students. This intervention will be tested with
      University of Illinois at Chicago (UIC) and Northern Illinois University (NIU) students.
      During the study, participants will complete measures of depressive and anxious symptoms, as
      well as measures of mental health literacy, within the app.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      In this study, students will be recruited to use the IntelliCare Hub app and encouraged to
      use it daily.The overall aim of this study is to pilot the program, evaluation metrics,
      implementation strategies, data collection and assessment procedures for a larger
      implementation trial. During the trial, participants will be prompted to complete the PHQ-8
      and GAD-7 every week. At monthly intervals, participants will be prompted within the app to
      complete the Depression Literacy Questionnaire and Anxiety Literacy Questionnaire to measure
      mental health literacy, the Knowledge and Beliefs about Services scale to measure knowledge
      of campus mental health services, the Barriers to Mental Health Help-Seeking questionnaire to
      measure treatment barriers, and the Cognitive and Behavioral Response to Stress Scale to
      measure cognitive and behavioral coping skills. Counseling center utilization data will be
      extracted from the participating counseling centers' electronic medical records.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 5, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 15, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 15, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Mobile self-help intervention</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient Health Questionnaire - 9 (PHQ-9) - Depression Severity Module</measure>
    <time_frame>Change in weekly symptom reports from baseline to end of one year program use</time_frame>
    <description>The PHQ-9 measures degree of depression severity. Possible range of scores for the PHQ-9 is 0-27. Higher values represent a worse outcome.
Specifically, scores of 0-4 indicate minimal or no depression; 5-9 is mild; 10-14 is moderate; 15-19 is moderately severe; and 20-27 is severe</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Generalized Anxiety Disorder Scale - 7 (GAD-7)</measure>
    <time_frame>Change in weekly symptom reports from baseline to end of one year program use</time_frame>
    <description>The GAD-7 is a self-administered 7 item instrument that uses some of the DSM-V criteria for GAD (General Anxiety Disorder) to identify probable cases of GAD along with measuring anxiety symptom severity. GAD-7 total score for the seven items ranges from 0 to 21. Higher values represent a worse outcome. Specifically, scores of 1-4 indicate minimal anxiety symptoms; 5-9 is mild anxiety symptoms; 10-14 is moderate anxiety symptoms; and 15-21 is severe anxiety symptoms.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Counseling center utilization data (e.g. counts of individual counseling sessions)</measure>
    <time_frame>Change in biweekly session utilization from baseline to end of one year implementation period</time_frame>
    <description>Counseling session utilization data will be examined on a biweekly basis to determine if the introduction of the IntelliCare for College Students program impacts counseling center utilization. Counts of types of sessions (e.g. individual counseling sessions, group counseling, crisis appointment) will be examine over time to look at potential changes.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean Number of Treatment App Use Sessions by Study Week</measure>
    <time_frame>Change in app use sessions from baseline to end of one year program use</time_frame>
    <description>Treatment app use sessions will be drawn from the study app and examined for change</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Anxiety Literacy Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>Change in monthly questionnaire scores from baseline to end of one year program use</time_frame>
    <description>This is a measure of mental health literacy, specifically about symptoms of anxiety. Participants respond &quot;True&quot; or &quot;False&quot; to statements about anxiety and the correct responses are tallied to create total score. The range of score is range of scores is 0-22 with higher scores indicating greater literacy.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Depression Literacy Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>Change in monthly questionnaire scores from baseline to end of one year program use</time_frame>
    <description>This is a measure of mental health literacy, specifically about symptoms of depression. Participants respond &quot;True&quot; or &quot;False&quot; to statements about depression and the correct responses are tallied to create total score. The range of scores is 0-22 with higher scores indicating greater literacy.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cognitive and Behavioral Response to Stress Scale (CB-RSS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Change in monthly questionnaire scores from baseline to end of one year program use</time_frame>
    <description>The CB-RSS is a 9 item measure of the frequency and perceived helpfulness of cognitive and behavioral coping skills. There are 4 subscales representing &quot;Cognitive frequency&quot; &quot;Cognitive helpfulness&quot; &quot;Behavioral frequency&quot; and &quot;Behavioral helpfulness.&quot; Participants respond to the frequency items on a scale of 0 = Never to 6 = Always and to the helpfulness items on a scale of 0 = Not at all helpful to 6 = Extremely helpful. The scores range from 0-24 on the Cognitive subscales and from 0-30 on the Behavioral subscales. Higher values represent a better outcome.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Knowledge and Beliefs about Services Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>Change in monthly questionnaire scores from baseline to end of one year program use</time_frame>
    <description>The Knowledge and Beliefs about Services Scale is a 5 item questionnaire in which participants indicate how much they agree with the statement about knowing where to go for professional help for mental or emotional health, how negative or positive they've heard the mental health and psychological counseling services are on their campus, how many close friends or family members have sought mental health treatment, and how helpful they perceive medication and therapy are for people their age who are clinically depressed. Each item is examined individually and there is no total score.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">3000</enrollment>
  <condition>Depression</condition>
  <condition>Anxiety</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Mobile self-help intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will have open access to the IntelliCare system.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>IntelliCare for College Students</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will receive access to the IntelliCare system, which consists of apps with a variety of resources, including lessons and tools designed to teach skills for mood management. It is suggested that participants utilize the mobile phone tools every day</description>
    <arm_group_label>Mobile self-help intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Participant is a student at the University of Illinois in Chicago or Northern Illinois
             University. *Participant owns a smartphone capable of running Android 7 (or higher) or
             iOS11 (or higher).

          -  Participant is 18 years of age or older

        Exclusion Criteria:

        *None
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Emily G Lattie</last_name>
    <phone>3125033741</phone>
    <email>emily.lattie@northwestern.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Northwestern University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chicago</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60642</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Emily G Lattie</last_name>
      <phone>312-503-3741</phone>
      <email>emily.lattie@northwestern.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 24, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 26, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 30, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 24, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 24, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 26, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Northwestern University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Emily G Lattie</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Mental health</keyword>
  <keyword>App</keyword>
  <keyword>Mobile phone</keyword>
  <keyword>Stress management</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Depression</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

