<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03142152</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CVP 1670-01</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03142152</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The CARILLON Trial - Assessment of the Carillon® Mitral Contour System® in Treating Functional Mitral Regurgitation Associated With Heart Failure</brief_title>
  <official_title>Assessment of the Carillon® Mitral Contour System® in Treating Functional Mitral Regurgitation Associated With Heart Failure - The CARILLON Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Cardiac Dimensions, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Cardiac Dimensions Pty Ltd</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_unapproved_device>Yes</is_unapproved_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The objective of this prospective, multi-center, randomized, double-blind trial is to assess
      the safety and efficacy of the CARILLON Mitral Contour System in treating subjects with
      functional mitral regurgitation (FMR) associated with heart failure, compared to a randomized
      Control group which is medically managed according to heart failure guidelines.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      A total of 352 subjects will be randomized at up to 75 investigational sites in the United
      States, Canada, Europe and Australia. Subjects will be randomized into one of two study
      groups using a 1:1 (Intervention : Control) ratio.

      Study subjects who are eligible for this clinical study will undergo a transthoracic
      echocardiographic examination prior to randomization to evaluate the inclusion criteria
      associated with the severity of mitral regurgitation as well as a review by a Central Review
      Committee to determine appropriateness for the implant procedure. On the day of the
      procedure, a coronary angiogram will be performed to evaluate the coronary artery anatomy and
      a venogram to assess the suitability of the coronary sinus/great cardiac vein (CS/GCV) for
      placement of the CARILLON implant. If the subject meets the anatomic requirements for device
      placement, the subject will be randomized. Subjects who meet all eligibility criteria will be
      randomized into one of two study groups (Intervention or Control).

      Subjects randomized to the Intervention group will undergo the CARILLON implant procedure.
      With the distal aspect of the device anchored, incremental tension will be applied to plicate
      the peri-annular tissue. After the proximal anchor of the implant is locked in place, safety
      and efficacy will be reconfirmed prior to releasing the CARILLON implant from the delivery
      system.

      Subjects randomized to the Control group will experience an index procedure similar to the
      Intervention group (without device placement) to ensure that they will not be able to deduce
      the group assignment based on the type of intervention or time associated with the procedure.

      After the study subjects are discharged, the subjects' primary care specialists
      (cardiologist/heart failure physician) and clinical investigation site staff will coordinate
      follow-up evaluations. Subjects will be evaluated at one (1), six (6), twelve (12), eighteen
      (18) and twenty-four (24) months post-randomization, to assess long-term safety, and
      functional and clinical status. After the 24-month evaluation, all subjects will be
      unblinded. All Intervention and Control subjects will be followed with an abbreviated annual
      contact for an additional three (3) years, for a total of five (5) years. Any additional
      therapies which are required to treat symptomatic or advancing disease subjects will be
      reviewed by a Central Review Committee for endpoint evaluation as long as the subject was
      treated &gt;6months after randomization so that all subjects may remain on the trial for the
      entire 5 years of follow up.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 1, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 1, 2025</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 1, 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Primary Safety Objective - Freedom from Major Adverse Events</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Freedom from a composite of major adverse events (defined as Device Embolization, Vessel Erosion, Cardiac Perforation, and occurrence of cardiac surgery or percutaneous coronary intervention) in the Intervention group is greater than performance goal of 90%.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Primary Efficacy Objective 1 - Hierarchical Clinical Composite</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>To demonstrate that the Carillon Mitral Contour System (Intervention) group is superior to the Control group on the hierarchical composite endpoint of death, transplant or LVAD, percutaneous or surgical mitral valve intervention, heart failure hospitalization, and improvement in six-minute walk distance at 12 months.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Secondary Efficacy Objective 1- Regurgitant Volume</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>To compare regurgitant volume change relative to control from baseline through 12 months of follow up</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Secondary Efficacy Objective 2 - HFH Days</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>To compare heart failure hospitalization days in the Intervention group relative to the Control group, from the time of the index procedure through twelve (12) months.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Secondary Efficacy Objective 3 - Change in LV End-Systolic Volume</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>To demonstrate an improvement from baseline in the parameter left ventricular end-systolic volume (LVESV) associated with the CARILLON Mitral Contour System (Intervention group) relative to the Control group.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Secondary Efficacy Objective 4 - Change in 6 Minute Walk Distance</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>To demonstrate a significantly greater improvement from baseline in six-minute walk distance associated with the CARILLON Mitral Contour System (Intervention group) relative to the Control group.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Secondary Efficacy Objective 5 - Change in KCCQ</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>To demonstrate the improvement from baseline in the overall summary score of the Kansas City Cardiomyopathy Questionnaire (KCCQ) associated with the CARILLON Mitral Contour System (Intervention group) relative to the Control group.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Secondary Efficacy Objective 6 - Change in NYHA Classification</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>To demonstrate the improvement in the proportion of patients who improve by at least one NYHA class from baseline associated with the CARILLON Mitral Contour System (Intervention group) relative to the Control group.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Secondary Safety Objective - Freedom from peri-procedural Major Adverse Events</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days or hospital discharge date, whichever is longer</time_frame>
    <description>Freedom from a composite of major adverse events (defined as Death, Myocardial Infarction, Device Embolization, Vessel Erosion, Cardiac Perforation, and occurrence of cardiac surgery or percutaneous coronary intervention) in the Intervention group is greater than 80%.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">352</enrollment>
  <condition>Functional Mitral Regurgitation</condition>
  <condition>Heart Failure</condition>
  <condition>Mitral Valve Insufficiency</condition>
  <condition>Heart Diseases</condition>
  <condition>Cardiovascular Diseases</condition>
  <condition>Heart Valve Diseases</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Carillon Mitral Contour System and Guideline Directed Heart Failure Medication</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Guideline Directed Heart Failure Medication</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Carillon Mitral Contour System</intervention_name>
    <description>The CARILLON implant (mXE2) is designed to be deployed, tensioned, and locked in the coronary vein in order to reshape the mitral annulus and thus reduce mitral annular dilation and mitral regurgitation.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention Group</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Carillon mXE2</other_name>
    <other_name>Percutaneous mitral valve repair</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Guideline Directed Heart Failure Medication</intervention_name>
    <description>Heart failure medication per ACC/AHA guidelines</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Diagnosis of ischemic or non-ischemic cardiomyopathy

          2. Symptomatic functional (secondary) mitral regurgitation defined as both: - 2+
             (Moderate), 3+ (Moderate/Severe), or 4+ (Severe).

             Note: 4+ can only be included if multidisciplinary site assessment (including a
             surgeon) determines that surgery is not necessary within the 1-year follow-up period
             for this study.

          3. NYHA Class II, III, or IV

          4. Six Minute Walk distance ≥ 150 meters and ≤ 450 meters

          5. Left Ventricular Ejection Fraction ≤ 50%

          6. LVESD ≤ 70 mm Note: As assessed by Imaging Core Laboratory.

          7. Corrected BNP of &gt; 300 pg/ml, or corrected NT-proBNP &gt; 1500 pg/ml, or one or more
             heart failure hospitalizations within one year prior to consent

          8. Guideline directed heart failure medication regimen.

          9. Age ≥ 18 years old

         10. CARILLON implant can be sized and placed in accordance with the IFU

         11. The subject or the subject's legal representative has been informed of the nature of
             the trial and agrees to its provisions, including the possibility of randomization to
             the Control group and returning for all required post-procedure follow-up visits, and
             has provided written informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Recipient of intravenous positive-inotrope infusion or intra-aortic balloon pump
             support within the past 30 days

          2. Heart failure hospitalization within the past 30 days

          3. Anticipated need of left ventricular assist device within twelve (12) months

          4. Class I indication for cardiac resynchronization therapy (CRT), or anticipated need
             for CRT within twelve (12) months

          5. Primary renal dysfunction or compromised renal function as reflected by an estimated
             Glomerular Filtration Rate (eGFR) &lt; 30 ml/min, as assessed by MDRD formula, or
             patients on dialysis

          6. Heart transplant candidate or prior orthotopic heart transplantation

          7. Presence of a mechanical or bio-prosthetic mitral valve or, mitral valve annuloplasty,
             or leaflet repair device.

          8. Hypertrophic cardiomyopathy, infiltrative cardiomyopathy, restrictive cardiomyopathy
             or constrictive pericarditis

          9. Echocardiographic documentation of non-compaction cardiomyopathy as assessed by the
             Imaging Core Laboratory

         10. Pre-existing device (e.g., pacing lead) in coronary sinus (CS) / great cardiac vein
             (GCV)

         11. Significant organic mitral valve pathology (e.g., moderate or severe myxomatous
             degeneration, with or without mitral leaflet prolapse, rheumatic disease, full or
             partial chordal rupture), as assessed by the Imaging Core Laboratory

         12. Severe tricuspid regurgitation associated with right ventricular dysfunction and
             enlargement, as assessed by the Imaging Core Laboratory

         13. Severe mitral annular calcification

         14. Severe aortic stenosis

         15. Not a candidate for right internal jugular venous cannulation

         16. Hospitalization in past 30 days due to myocardial infarction, coronary artery bypass
             graft surgery or unstable angina

         17. Cerebral vascular event within the past 30 days

         18. Hospitalization in the past 30 days for coronary angioplasty or stent placement or ICD
             implant

         19. Pulmonary embolus or deep vein thrombosis within the past six (6) months

         20. Expected to require any cardiac surgery, including surgery for coronary artery disease
             (CAD) or valve disease within one (1) year

         21. Expected to require any percutaneous coronary intervention within 30 days of the index
             procedure.

         22. Hemodynamic instability defined as sustained systolic blood pressure &lt; 90 mmHg with or
             without afterload reduction, cardiogenic shock or the need for inotropic support or
             intra-aortic balloon pump or other hemodynamic support device

         23. Presence of left atrial appendage (LAA) clot or presence of LAA occluder

         24. Anemia defined as hemoglobin &lt; 9.0 mg/dL

         25. Currently participating in an investigational drug or device study that has not
             completed the primary endpoint or that clinically interferes with the current study
             endpoints

         26. Known hypersensitivity or contraindication to procedural medications which cannot be
             adequately managed medically

         27. Active infections requiring current antibiotic therapy

         28. Chronic, severe, medical conditions or pathology, other than heart failure, that will
             prevent likely survival beyond twelve (12) months

         29. Female subjects pregnant or planning to become pregnant in the next five (5) years

         30. Subjects unable to perform the required study assessments (e.g., 6 minute walk test)

         31. Any other medical condition that, in the judgment of the Investigator, makes the
             patient a poor candidate for this study

         32. Subjects belonging to a vulnerable population per investigator's judgment or subject
             has any kind of disorder that compromises his/her ability to give written informed
             consent and/or comply with the study procedures
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Samir Kapadia, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>The Cleveland Clinic</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Randall Starling, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>The Cleveland Clinic</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Marc Gillinov, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>The Cleveland Clinic</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Dignity Health Research Institute at Mercy Gilbert and Chandler Regional Medical Centers</name>
      <address>
        <city>Gilbert</city>
        <state>Arizona</state>
        <zip>85297</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Banner University Hospital- Phoenix</name>
      <address>
        <city>Phoenix</city>
        <state>Arizona</state>
        <zip>85006</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Banner University Tuscon</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tucson</city>
        <state>Arizona</state>
        <zip>85724</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Loma Linda University Health</name>
      <address>
        <city>Loma Linda</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>92354</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UCLA Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90095</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of California- San Francisco</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Francisco</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94143</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Yale</name>
      <address>
        <city>New Haven</city>
        <state>Connecticut</state>
        <zip>06520</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Medstar</name>
      <address>
        <city>Washington</city>
        <state>District of Columbia</state>
        <zip>20010</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Delray Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Delray Beach</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33484</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Baptist Hospital of Miami</name>
      <address>
        <city>Miami</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33101</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Miami</name>
      <address>
        <city>Miami</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33136</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cleveland Clinic- Weston</name>
      <address>
        <city>Weston</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33331</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Piedmont Heart Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Atlanta</city>
        <state>Georgia</state>
        <zip>30309</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Carle Foundation Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Champaign</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>61801</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Rush University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chicago</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60612</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>NorthShore University Health System</name>
      <address>
        <city>Evanston</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60201</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Prairie Heart Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Springfield</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>62701</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Kentucky Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lexington</city>
        <state>Kentucky</state>
        <zip>40536</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ochsner Health System</name>
      <address>
        <city>New Orleans</city>
        <state>Louisiana</state>
        <zip>70121</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Maine Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Scarborough</city>
        <state>Maine</state>
        <zip>04074</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>St. Elizabeths</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02135</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Massachusetts General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02145</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Baystate Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Springfield</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>01199</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Michigan</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ann Arbor</city>
        <state>Michigan</state>
        <zip>48859</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Beaumont Health</name>
      <address>
        <city>Royal Oak</city>
        <state>Michigan</state>
        <zip>48073</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ascension St. Marys Research Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Saginaw</city>
        <state>Michigan</state>
        <zip>48601</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Minnesota</name>
      <address>
        <city>Minneapolis</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55455</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Columbia University Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10027</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>New York Presbyterian- Weill Cornell Medical College</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10065</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Vassar Brothers- Hudson Valley Cardiovascular Practice</name>
      <address>
        <city>Poughkeepsie</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>12601</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UNC- Chapel Hill</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chapel Hill</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27599</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cleveland Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cleveland</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>44195</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Oklahoma Heart Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Oklahoma City</city>
        <state>Oklahoma</state>
        <zip>73120</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Geisinger Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Danville</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>17822</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Pennsylvania</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19014</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UPMC Presbyterian</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pittsburgh</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>15213</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Centennial Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nashville</city>
        <state>Tennessee</state>
        <zip>37203</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Henrico Doctors Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Henrico</city>
        <state>Virginia</state>
        <zip>23229</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sentara Norfolk General</name>
      <address>
        <city>Norfolk</city>
        <state>Virginia</state>
        <zip>23501</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Washington</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seattle</city>
        <state>Washington</state>
        <zip>98112</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Pole Sante Republique</name>
      <address>
        <city>Clermont Ferrand</city>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>European Interbalkan Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Thessaloníki</city>
        <country>Greece</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Centrum Medyczne Hcp</name>
      <address>
        <city>Poznan</city>
        <zip>61-485</zip>
        <country>Poland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Uniwersytecki Szpital Kliniczny</name>
      <address>
        <city>Wroclaw</city>
        <country>Poland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Leeds Teaching Hospital NHS</name>
      <address>
        <city>Leeds</city>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
    <country>Greece</country>
    <country>Poland</country>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <removed_countries>
    <country>Czechia</country>
  </removed_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schofer J, Siminiak T, Haude M, Herrman JP, Vainer J, Wu JC, Levy WC, Mauri L, Feldman T, Kwong RY, Kaye DM, Duffy SJ, Tübler T, Degen H, Brandt MC, Van Bibber R, Goldberg S, Reuter DG, Hoppe UC. Percutaneous mitral annuloplasty for functional mitral regurgitation: results of the CARILLON Mitral Annuloplasty Device European Union Study. Circulation. 2009 Jul 28;120(4):326-33. doi: 10.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.109.849885. Epub 2009 Jul 13.</citation>
    <PMID>19597051</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Siminiak T, Wu JC, Haude M, Hoppe UC, Sadowski J, Lipiecki J, Fajadet J, Shah AM, Feldman T, Kaye DM, Goldberg SL, Levy WC, Solomon SD, Reuter DG. Treatment of functional mitral regurgitation by percutaneous annuloplasty: results of the TITAN Trial. Eur J Heart Fail. 2012 Aug;14(8):931-8. doi: 10.1093/eurjhf/hfs076. Epub 2012 May 21.</citation>
    <PMID>22613584</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lipiecki J, Siminiak T, Sievert H, Müller-Ehmsen J, Degen H, Wu JC, Schandrin C, Kalmucki P, Hofmann I, Reuter D, Goldberg SL, Haude M. Coronary sinus-based percutaneous annuloplasty as treatment for functional mitral regurgitation: the TITAN II trial. Open Heart. 2016 Jul 8;3(2):e000411. doi: 10.1136/openhrt-2016-000411. eCollection 2016.</citation>
    <PMID>27493761</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 2, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 3, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 5, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 20, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 20, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 21, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Functional Mitral Regurgitation</keyword>
  <keyword>Percutaneous Mitral Valve Repair</keyword>
  <keyword>Percutaneous Mitral Valve Annuloplasty</keyword>
  <keyword>Coronary Sinus Annuloplasty</keyword>
  <keyword>Secondary Mitral Regurgitation</keyword>
  <keyword>Functional MR</keyword>
  <keyword>FMR</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Heart Failure</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Heart Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Mitral Valve Insufficiency</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Heart Valve Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cardiovascular Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

