<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03144245</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>AMV564-101</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03144245</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study of AMV564 in Patients With AML</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase 1, First in Human, Open Label, Dose Escalation Study of AMV564, a CD33 x CD3 Tandem Diabody in Patients With Relapsed or Refractory Acute Myeloid Leukemia</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Amphivena Therapeutics, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Amphivena Therapeutics, Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a first in human, non randomized, open-label, dose escalation study to investigate
      the safety, tolerability and preliminary efficacy of AMV564.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study is a first in human, Phase 1, open label, multicenter, dose escalation study with
      expansion at the RP2D to evaluate the safety, tolerability and preliminary antileukemic
      activity of AMV564 in patients with relapsed or refractory acute myeloid leukemia (AML).

      AMV564 will be given on Days 1-14 of a 4-week cycle, or Days 1-28 of a 6-week cycle,via CIV
      or subcutaneous administration for 1 or more treatment cycles as monotherapy or in
      combination with pembrolizumab.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 20, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 21, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 21, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Dose escalation + expansion stage: incidence of all adverse events and serious adverse events (safety and tolerability)</measure>
    <time_frame>42 months</time_frame>
    <description>Number of participants with adverse events as a measure of safety and tolerability.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Expansion stage: Efficacy - Remission Rate</measure>
    <time_frame>42 months</time_frame>
    <description>Proportion of participants who achieve complete remission, complete remission with incomplete recovery or partial remission</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">53</enrollment>
  <condition>Acute Myeloid Leukemia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>AMV564</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Continuous infusion or subcutaneous dosing of AMV564 at increasing dose levels</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Combination AMV564</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Continuous infusion or subcutaneous dosing of AMV564 at increasing dose levels in combination with pembrolizumab</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>AMV564</intervention_name>
    <description>AMV564 for administration via continuous intravenous daily infusion or subcutaneous dosing</description>
    <arm_group_label>AMV564</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Combination Product</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>AMV564 in combination with pembrolizumab</intervention_name>
    <description>AMV564 for administration via continuous intravenous daily infusion or subcutaneous dosing.in combination with pembrolizumab given IV every 21 days</description>
    <arm_group_label>Combination AMV564</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  ≥ 18 years of age at the time of signing informed consent

          -  Diagnosis of AML according to the World Health Organization (WHO) 2008 criteria

          -  Relapsed or refractory disease meeting the following criteria:

               1. Primary refractory, ie, refractory to induction with a standard intensive
                  anthracycline/cytarabine-based regimen or a non-intensive regimen (e.g.,
                  decitabine, azacytidine, low-dose cytarabine) for patients ineligible for an
                  intensive anthracycline/cytarabine-based therapy

               2. First untreated relapse after a first CR lasting less than 12 months or first
                  relapse refractory to salvage therapy regardless of length of first CR; or

               3. Second or later relapse. Relapse is defined as the reappearance of leukemic
                  blasts in the peripheral blood or ≥ 5% leukemic blasts in the bone marrow after
                  prior achievement of a CR or CRi.

        OR Patients with newly diagnosed therapy-related AML, AML progressed from antecedent MDS or
        CMML treated with hypomethylating agents, or de novo AML with MDS-related cytogenetic
        abnormalities (per 2008 WHO criteria) and who are not candidates for (or decline) intensive
        remission induction therapy

          -  No more than 3 prior induction/salvage regimens to treat active disease, and no more
             than 1 prior stem cell transplant. Any number of continuous cycles of therapy with an
             individual hypomethylating agent count as one induction or salvage regimen.

          -  Blasts at least 5% in bone marrow

          -  Peripheral white blood cell (WBC) count: no upper limit at Screening, but must be &lt; 10
             x 109/L on Day 1 prior to treatment; patients with excessive blasts may be treated
             with hydroxyurea to bring counts down.

          -  Chemistry laboratory parameters within the following range:

               1. Aspartate aminotransferase (AST) and alanine aminotransferase (ALT) ≤ 2x the
                  upper limit of normal (ULN)

               2. Total bilirubin ≤ 1.5x the ULN; patients with Gilbert's syndrome can enroll if
                  conjugated bilirubin is within normal limits.

               3. Creatinine clearance &gt; 50 mL/min (measured or calculated by Cockcroft-Gault
                  method)

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status of 0 or 1. Patients with
             ECOG score of 2 may be included, after discussion with the Sponsor Medical Monitor, if
             score is influenced by symptoms attributable to underlying AML disease.

          -  Willing to complete all scheduled visits and assessments at the institution
             administering therapy

          -  Able to read, understand and provide written informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Patients who meet any of the following criteria will be excluded from the study.

          -  History of, or known, central nervous system (CNS) disease involvement, or prior
             history of National Cancer Institute (NCI) Common Toxicity Criteria for Adverse Events
             (CTCAE) Grade ≥ 3 drug-related CNS toxicity

          -  Prior allogeneic transplant (dose escalation only)

          -  Prior solid organ transplantation

          -  Treatment with anti-thymocyte globulin (ATG) within 14 days prior to start date

          -  Treatment with any local or systemic antineoplastic therapy or radiation within 14
             days prior to the initiation of AMV564 administration (hydroxyurea is exempted if used
             to reduce total WBC counts)

          -  Clinically significant cardiac disease,

          -  Pulmonary, renal, hepatic, gastrointestinal, neurological or psychiatric disease that
             would limit compliance with study requirements

          -  Evidence of active, uncontrolled, viral, bacterial, or systemic fungal infection.
             Prophylactic therapy according to institutional protocols is acceptable.

          -  Known positive test result for human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) or acquired immune
             deficiency syndrome (AIDS)

          -  Active hepatitis C virus (HCV) or hepatitis B virus (HBV). Patients who are positive
             for hepatitis B core antibody, hepatitis B surface antigen, or hepatitis C antibody
             must have a negative polymerase chain reaction (PCR) result before enrollment. Those
             who are PCR positive will be excluded.

          -  Second primary malignancy that has not been in remission for greater than 3 years.
             Exceptions that do not require a 3-year remission include: non-melanoma skin cancer;
             cervical carcinoma in situ on biopsy or squamous intraepithelial lesion on
             Papanicolaou (PAP) smear; localized prostate cancer (Gleason score &lt; 6); or resected
             melanoma in situ.

          -  Major trauma or major surgery within 28 days prior to the initiation of AMV564
             treatment

          -  Any serious underlying medical or psychiatric condition (e.g. alcohol or drug abuse),
             dementia or altered mental status or any issue that would impair the ability of the
             patient to understand informed consent or that in the opinion of the investigator
             would contraindicate the patient's participation in the study or confound the results
             of the study.

          -  Ability to become pregnant. However, female patients who have a negative serum or
             urine pregnancy test before enrollment and agree to use two highly effective forms of
             contraception (oral, injected or implanted hormonal contraception and condom;
             intrauterine device and condom; diaphragm with spermicidal gel and condom) during the
             trial and for 90 days afterward (90 days after the end of AMV564 treatment) are
             considered eligible.

          -  Male patients with partners of childbearing potential.

          -  Pregnant or breastfeeding women

          -  Is a participant or plans to participate in another interventional clinical study,
             while taking part in this protocol. Participation in an observational study is
             acceptable.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Patrick Chun, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Amphivena Therapeutics, Inc.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of California, San Francisco</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Francisco</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94143</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Northwestern</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chicago</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60611</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Johns Hopkins University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21287</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Washington University School of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Saint Louis</city>
        <state>Missouri</state>
        <zip>63110</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>New York Medical College</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hawthorne</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10532</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Weill Cornell Medical College, The New York Presbyterian Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10021</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The Ohio State University Comprehensive Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Columbus</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>43210</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Pennsylvania</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19104</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>MD Anderson Cancer Center, The University of Texas</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>70030-4009</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Fred Hutchinson Cancer Research</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seattle</city>
        <state>Washington</state>
        <zip>98109-1024</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>April 25, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 4, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 8, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 21, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 21, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 26, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>AML</keyword>
  <keyword>treatment</keyword>
  <keyword>relapsed</keyword>
  <keyword>refractory</keyword>
  <keyword>phase 1</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Leukemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Myeloid</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Myeloid, Acute</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pembrolizumab</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

