<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03393975</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>281102</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2017-000858-18</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03393975</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study of Prophylactic and On-demand Treatment of Congenital Thrombotic Thrombocytopenic Purpura (cTTP) With BAX 930 (rADAMTS13)</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase 3, Prospective, Randomized, Controlled, Open-Label, Multicenter, 2-Period Crossover Study With a Single Arm Continuation Evaluating the Safety and Efficacy of BAX 930 (rADAMTS13) in the Prophylactic and On-demand Treatment of Participants With Severe Congenital Thrombotic Thrombocytopenic Purpura (cTTP) (Upshaw-Schulman Syndrome)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Baxalta now part of Shire</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Baxalta Innovations GmbH, now part of Shire</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Shire</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to assess safety and efficacy of BAX 930 in the prevention and
      treatment of acute episodes of thrombotic thrombocytopenic purpura (TTP) in participants with
      severe congenital deficiency of ADAMTS13 (cTTP; defined as plasma ADAMTS13 lesser then [&lt;] 10
      percent [%], as measured by the fluorescent resonance energy transfer-VWF73 [FRETS] assay).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study consists of 2 cohorts with total duration of 69 months. 1) Prophylaxis Treatment
      Cohort: This cohort consists of 3 periods (period 1, 2, 3) and 2 cross-over pharmacokinetic
      (PK I and PK II) assessments with a washout period of 14 days (+ or - 2 days) between the
      doses in PK . Participants in prophylaxis cohort will be randomized equally to 1 of 2
      treatment orders either BAX 930-SoC or SoC-BAX 930. 2) On-Demand Treatment Cohort:
      Participants in on-demand cohort will be randomized to receive urgent treatment with either
      the SoC or BAX 930. Upon resolution of the acute event, participants may choose to move to
      the prophylaxis cohort of the study or discontinue entirely. Participants electing to move to
      the prophylaxis cohort will move directly to Period 1 and will not be part of PK 1
      evaluation. Participants who will randomize to receive BAX 930 in the on-demand arm, will
      receive BAX 930 ORT until BAX 930 SIN becomes available.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 20, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 1, 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 1, 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>This is a Phase 3, prospective, randomized, controlled, open-label, multicenter, 2-period crossover study with a single arm continuation evaluating the safety and efficacy of BAX 930 in the prophylactic and on-demand treatment of participants with severe congenital thrombotic thrombocytopenic purpura (cTTP).</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants With Acute Thrombotic Thrombocytopenic Purpura (TTP) Episodes</measure>
    <time_frame>Throughout the study period of approximately 69 months</time_frame>
    <description>Number of participants with acute TTP episodes among participants receiving either BAX 930 or standard of care (SoC) prophylactically during the corresponding treatment periods will be assessed.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Acute Thrombotic Thrombocytopenic Purpura (TTP) Episodes Responding to BAX 930</measure>
    <time_frame>Throughout the study period of approximately 69 months</time_frame>
    <description>Number of acute thrombotic thrombocytopenic purpura episodes responding to BAX 930, is defined as not requiring the use of another ADAMTS13-containing agent.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants With Acute Thrombotic Thrombocytopenic Purpura (TTP) Episodes Responding to BAX 930</measure>
    <time_frame>Throughout the study period of approximately 69 months</time_frame>
    <description>Number of participants with acute thrombotic thrombocytopenic purpura episodes responding to BAX 930, is defined as not requiring the use of another ADAMTS13-containing agent.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to Resolution of Clinical Symptomatology</measure>
    <time_frame>Throughout the study period of approximately 69 months</time_frame>
    <description>Time to resolution of clinical symptomatology, if present, and normalization of laboratory parameters platelet count greater than or equal to (&gt;=) 150,000/microliters (mcL); lactate dehydrogenase (LDH) lesser than or equal to (&lt;=)1.5×upper limit of normal (ULN) following initiation of treatment in acute TTP episodes with BAX 930 or standard of care (SoC) agent.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants With Thrombocytopenia</measure>
    <time_frame>Throughout the study period of approximately 69 months</time_frame>
    <description>Thrombocytopenia is defined as a drop in platelet count &gt;= 25 percent (%) of baseline or a platelet count lesser than (&lt;) 150,000/mcgL. Number of participants with thrombocytopenia will be assessed.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants With Microangiopathic Hemolytic Anemia</measure>
    <time_frame>Throughout the study period of approximately 69 months</time_frame>
    <description>Microangiopathic hemolytic anemia is defined as an elevation of LDH greater than (&gt;) 1.5× ULN. Number of participants with microangiopathic hemolytic anemia will be assessed.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants With Neurological symptoms</measure>
    <time_frame>Throughout the study period of approximately 69 months</time_frame>
    <description>Neurological symptoms includes (e.g., confusion, dysphonia, dysarthria, focal or general motor symptoms including seizures). Number of participants with neurological symptoms will be assessed.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants With Renal Dysfunction</measure>
    <time_frame>Throughout the study period of approximately 69 months</time_frame>
    <description>Renal dysfunction is defined as an increase in serum creatinine &gt;1.5× baseline at screening. Number of participants with renal dysfunction will be assessed.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants With Abdominal Pain</measure>
    <time_frame>Throughout the study period of approximately 69 months</time_frame>
    <description>Number of participants with abdominal pain in the prophylactic cohort will be assessed.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants With Supplemental Doses</measure>
    <time_frame>Throughout the study period of approximately 69 months</time_frame>
    <description>Number of participants with supplemental doses prompted by subacute manifestations will be assessed.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants With Dose Modification</measure>
    <time_frame>Throughout the study period of approximately 69 months</time_frame>
    <description>Number of participants with dose modification not prompted by an acute event will be assessed.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants With Acute Thrombotic Thrombocytopenic Purpura (TTP) Episodes on Their Final Dose</measure>
    <time_frame>Throughout the study period of approximately 69 months</time_frame>
    <description>Number of participants with acute TTP episodes on their final dose and dosing regimen for the prophylactic cohort will be assessed.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants with Adverse Events (AEs) and Serious Adverse Events (SAEs)</measure>
    <time_frame>Throughout the study period of approximately 69 months</time_frame>
    <description>An AE is defined as any untoward medical occurrence in a participants administered an IP that does not necessarily have a causal relationship with the treatment. A SAE is defined as an untoward medical occurrence that at any dose meets 1 or more of the following criteria: death; initial or prolonged in-patient hospitalization; life threatening experience (immediate risk of dying); persistent or significant disability/incapacity; congenital anomaly, medically important event (may not be immediately lifethreatening or result in death or require hospitalization but may require medical or surgical intervention to prevent 1 of the other outcomes: intensive treatment, confirmed seroconversion for human immunodeficiency viruses (HIV), severe hypersensitivity/allergic reactions, uncomplicated pregnancies etc).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants With Antibodies to ADAMTS13</measure>
    <time_frame>Throughout the study period of approximately 69 months</time_frame>
    <description>Number of participants with binding and inhibitory antibodies to ADAMTS13 will be assessed.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants With Clinically Relevant Changes in Vital Signs</measure>
    <time_frame>Throughout the study period of approximately 69 months</time_frame>
    <description>Vital signs includes pulse rate, blood pressure, respiration rate, and temperature. Number of participants with clinical relevant changes in vital signs will be reported.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants With Clinically Relevant Changes in Clinical Chemistry</measure>
    <time_frame>Throughout the study period of approximately 69 months</time_frame>
    <description>Clinical laboratory evaluations includes clinical chemistry (sodium, potassium, chloride, alanine aminotransferase (ALT), aspartate aminotransferase (AST), lactate dehydrogenase (LDH), bilirubin, alkaline phosphatase, blood urea nitrogen, creatinine, and glucose). Number of participants with clinically relevant changes in clinical laboratory evaluations will be reported.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants with Clinically Relevant Changes in Hematology</measure>
    <time_frame>Throughout the study period of approximately 69 months</time_frame>
    <description>Hematology includes red blood cell (RBC) count, hemoglobin, hematocrit, haptoglobin, reticulocyte count, mean corpuscular volume (MCV), mean corpuscular hemoglobin (MCH), mean corpuscular hemoglobin concentration (MCHC), leukocytes (i.e., white blood cell count) with differential (i.e., basophils, eosinophils, lymphocytes, monocytes, and neutrophils) and platelet counts. Number of participants with clinically relevant changes in Hematology will be reported.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Estimated Total Quantity of ADAMTS13 Administered During the Treatment of Acute Events</measure>
    <time_frame>Throughout the study period of approximately 69 months</time_frame>
    <description>Estimated total quantity of ADAMTS13 administered during the treatment of acute events will be assessed. Acute events typically require 3-4 days of intensified treatment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incremental Recovery (IR) of ADMATS13 Activity and ADMATS13 Antigen for SoC Agent and BAX 930 in Plasma</measure>
    <time_frame>Start of treatment periods and end of Treatment Period 2 prophylactic cohort. &lt;12 years: within 60 min pre-infusion; and post-infusion at 6 timepoints up to 7 days. &gt;=12 years: within 60 min pre-infusion; and post-infusion at 12 timepoints up to 12 days</time_frame>
    <description>ADAMTS13 activity will be measured by the fluorescent resonance energy transfer (FRETS) assay, ADAMTS13 antigen will be measured using a commercial ADAMTS13 enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA) employing ADAMTS13 antigen. IR is defined as body weight normalized maximum increase in plasma ADAMTS13 antigen and activity level. IR of ADMATS13 activity and ADMATS13 antigen for SoC agent and BAX 930 in plasma will be assessed.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Area Under the Plasma curve [AUC] of ADMATS13 Activity and ADMATS13 Antigen for SoC Agent and BAX 930 in Plasma</measure>
    <time_frame>Start of treatment periods and end of Treatment Period 2 prophylactic cohort. &lt;12 years: within 60 min pre-infusion; and post-infusion at 6 timepoints up to 7 days. &gt;=12 years: within 60 min pre-infusion; and post-infusion at 12 timepoints up to 12 day</time_frame>
    <description>AUC of ADMATS13 activity and ADMATS13 antigen for SoC agent and BAX 930 in plasma will be assessed.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Terminal Half-Life (T1/2) of ADMATS13 Activity and ADMATS13 Antigen for SoC Agent and BAX 930 in Plasma</measure>
    <time_frame>Start of treatment periods and end of Treatment Period 2 prophylactic cohort. &lt;12 years: within 60 min pre-infusion; and post-infusion at 6 time points up to 7 days. &gt;=12 years: within 60 min pre-infusion; and post-infusion at 12 timepoints up to 12 day</time_frame>
    <description>T1/2 of ADMATS13 activity and ADMATS13 antigen for SoC agent and BAX 930 in plasma will be assessed.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean Residence Time (MRT) of ADMATS13 Activity and ADMATS13 Antigen for SoC Agent and BAX 930 in Plasma</measure>
    <time_frame>Start of treatment periods and end of Treatment Period 2 prophylactic cohort. &lt;12 years: within 60 min pre-infusion; and post-infusion at 6 timepoints up to 7 days. &gt;=12 years: within 60 min pre-infusion; and post-infusion at 12 timepoints up to 12 days</time_frame>
    <description>MRT of ADMATS13 activity and ADMATS13 antigen for SoC agent and BAX 930 in plasma will be assessed.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clearance (CL) of ADMATS13 Activity and ADMATS13 Antigen for SoC Agent and BAX 930 in Plasma</measure>
    <time_frame>Start of treatment periods and end of Treatment Period 2 prophylactic cohort. &lt;12 years: within 60 min pre-infusion; and post-infusion at 6 timepoints up to 7 days. &gt;=12 years: within 60 min pre-infusion; and post-infusion at 12 timepoints up to 12 days</time_frame>
    <description>CL of ADMATS13 activity and ADMATS13 antigen for SoC agent and BAX 930 in plasma will be assessed.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Volume at Steady State (Vss) of ADMATS13 Activity and ADMATS13 Antigen for SoC Agent and BAX 930 in Plasma</measure>
    <time_frame>Start of treatment periods and end of Treatment Period 2 prophylactic cohort. &lt;12 years: within 60 min pre-infusion; and post-infusion at 6 timepoints up to 7 days. &gt;=12 years: within 60 min pre-infusion; and post-infusion at 12 timepoints up to 12 days</time_frame>
    <description>Vss of ADMATS13 activity and ADMATS13 antigen for SoC agent and BAX 930 in plasma will be assessed.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum Concentration (Cmax) of ADMATS13 Activity and ADMATS13 Antigen for SoC Agent and BAX 930 in Plasma</measure>
    <time_frame>Start of treatment periods and end of Treatment Period 2 prophylactic cohort. &lt;12 years: within 60 min pre-infusion; and post-infusion at 6 timepoints up to 7 days. &gt;=12 years: within 60 min pre-infusion; and post-infusion at 12 timepoints up to 12 days</time_frame>
    <description>Cmax of ADMATS13 activity and ADMATS13 antigen for SoC agent and BAX 930 in plasma will be assessed.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assessment of Von Willebrand Factor: Antigen (VWF:Ag)</measure>
    <time_frame>Start of treatment periods and end of Treatment Period 2 prophylactic cohort. &lt;12 years: within 60 min pre-infusion; and post-infusion at 6 timepoints up to 7 days. &gt;=12 years: within 60 min pre-infusion; and post-infusion at 12 timepoints up to 12 days</time_frame>
    <description>VWF:Ag is a measure of total VWF protein and will be assessed using a sandwich ELISA employing polyclonal anti-human-VWF antibodies. Assessments of VWF:Ag at baseline and following infusion of the SoC agent and BAX 930 treatment during the initial PK assessment will be reported.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assessment of Von Willebrand Factor: Ristocetin Cofactor Activity (VWF: RCo)</measure>
    <time_frame>Start of treatment periods and end of Treatment Period 2 prophylactic cohort. &lt;12 years: within 60 min pre-infusion; and post-infusion at 6 timepoints up to 7 days. &gt;=12 years: within 60 min pre-infusion; and post-infusion at 12 timepoints up to 12 days</time_frame>
    <description>VWF:RCo will provide a measure of the ability of VWF to bind platelet glycoprotein Ib. Stabilized platelets are agglutinated in the presence of VWF and the antibiotic Ristocetin. Assessments of VWF:RCo at baseline and following infusion of the SoC agent and BAX 930 treatment during the initial PK assessment will be reported.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assessment of Von Willebrand Factor (VWF) Multimer</measure>
    <time_frame>Start of treatment periods and end of Treatment Period 2 prophylactic cohort. &lt;12 years: within 60 min pre-infusion; and post-infusion at 6 timepoints up to 7 days. &gt;=12 years: within 60 min pre-infusion; and post-infusion at 12 timepoints up to 12 days</time_frame>
    <description>VWF multimer pattern (small, intermediate, large, and ultra large) will be assessed using low-resolution sodium dodecyl sulfate (SDS)-agarose gel electrophoresis. Assessments of VWF multimer at baseline and following infusion of the SoC agent and BAX 930 treatment during the initial PK assessment will be reported.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assessment of ADAMTS13 Activity (Pre-Infusion ADAMTS13 Levels) and VWF Parameters</measure>
    <time_frame>Start of treatment periods and end of Treatment Period 2 prophylactic cohort. &lt;12 years: within 60 min pre-infusion; and post-infusion at 6 timepoints up to 7 days. &gt;=12 years: within 60 min pre-infusion; and post-infusion at 12 timepoints up to 12 days</time_frame>
    <description>Assessment of ADAMTS13 activity (pre-infusion ADAMTS13 levels) and VWF parameters prior to each infusion of SoC or BAX 930 and at the time of acute event presentation will be reported.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Health Related Quality of Life (HRQoL): cTTP-Specific Patient reported outcomes (PROs)</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 0, End of period 1 (approximately 6 months), End of period 2 (approximately 12 months), and End of period 3 (approximately 19 months), or non-scheduled acute event (as needed)</time_frame>
    <description>The congenital thrombotic thrombocytopenic purpura (cTTP)-specific patient-reported outcomes (PRO) instrument consists of 26 questions designed to assess the patient's experience of fatigue, joint, muscle, abdominal and chest pain in the previous 24 hours, neurologic manifestations, bruising, feelings of depression and mood alterations, and activity limitation in the past 7 days, and patient's attitudes, experienced side effects, work/school absences and travel impact associated with treatment received for TTP during the previous 2 weeks. The cTTP PRO assessment is focused on measuring the symptoms and impacts of the disease. The scores range from 0 to 152. Higher scores indicate a better quality of life.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Health Related Quality of Life (HRQoL): 36-Item Short Form Health Survey (SF-36)</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 0, End of period 1 (approximately 6 months), End of period 2 (approximately 12 months), and End of period 3 (approximately 19 months), or non-scheduled acute event (as needed)</time_frame>
    <description>The SF-36 is a generic quality-of-life instrument that has been widely used to assess health-related quality of life (HRQoL) of participants. Generic instruments are used in general populations to assess a wide range of domains applicable to a variety of health states, conditions, and diseases. The SF-36 consists of 36 items that are aggregated into 8 multi-item scales (physical functioning, role-physical, bodily pain, general health, vitality, social functioning, role-emotional, and mental health), with scores ranging from 0 to 100. Higher scores indicate better HRQoL.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Health Related Quality of Life (HRQoL): Abbreviated 9-item Treatment Satisfaction Questionnaire for Medication (TSQM-9)</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 0, End of period 1 (approximately 6 months), End of period 2 (approximately 12 months), and End of period 3 (approximately 19 months), or non-scheduled acute event (as needed)</time_frame>
    <description>TSQM is a global satisfaction scale used to assess the overall level of participant's satisfaction or dissatisfaction with their medications. TSQM-9 is a 9-item, validated, self-administered instrument used to assess participant's satisfaction with medication. The three domains assessed are effectiveness, convenience, and global satisfaction. The score of each of the 3 domains is based on an algorithm to create a score of 0 to 100. Higher score indicated greater satisfaction in that domain.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Health Related Quality of Life (HRQoL): EuroQol 5 Dimensions Questionnaire 3-Level (EQ-5D-3L)</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 0, End of period 1 (approximately 6 months), End of period 2 (approximately 12 months), and End of period 3 (approximately 19 months), or non-scheduled acute event (as needed)</time_frame>
    <description>EQ-5D-3L health questionnaire is a participant answered questionnaire scoring 5 dimensions - mobility, self-care, usual activities, pain/discomfort and anxiety/depression. The EQ-5D total score ranges from 0 (worst health state) to 1 (perfect health state) and 1 reflects the best outcome.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Health Related Quality of Life (HRQoL): EQ-5D-youth (EQ-5D-Y)</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 0, End of period 1 (approximately 6 months), End of period 2 (approximately 12 months), and End of period 3 (approximately 19 months), or non-scheduled acute event (as needed)</time_frame>
    <description>EQ-5D-Y health questionnaire is a participant answered questionnaire scoring 5 dimensions - mobility, self-care, usual activities, pain/discomfort and anxiety/depression. The EQ-5D total score ranges from 0 (worst health state) to 1 (perfect health state) and 1 reflects the best outcome.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Health Related Quality of Life (HRQoL): Pediatric Quality of Life Inventory (Ped QL)</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 0, End of period 1 (approximately 6 months), End of period 2 (approximately 12 months), and End of period 3 (approximately 19 months), or non-scheduled acute event (as needed)</time_frame>
    <description>The Peds QL is a generic health related quality of life instrument designed specifically for a pediatric population and captures following domains: physical functioning, emotional functioning, social functioning, school functioning, psychosocial summary, physical health and total score. The Peds-QL total score consist of all 23 items of all domains. This modular instrument uses a 5-point scale: from 0 (never) to 4 (almost always). Items are reversed scored and linearly transformed to a 0-100 scale as follows: 0=100, 1=75, 2=50, 3=25, 4=0. Higher scores indicate better quality of life.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Resource Utilization: Length of Hospital Stay for Acute TTP Episodes</measure>
    <time_frame>Throughout the study period of approximately 69 months</time_frame>
    <description>Number of days participants stay in hospital for Acute TTP episodes will be assessed.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Resource Utilization: Resource Utilization During Prophylaxis</measure>
    <time_frame>Throughout the study period of approximately 69 months</time_frame>
    <description>Number of participants utilized during prophylaxis will be assessed.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Resource Utilization: Days Missed From School or Work due to TTP-Related Illness</measure>
    <time_frame>Throughout the study period of approximately 69 months</time_frame>
    <description>Number of days missed from school or work due to TTP-related illness will be assessed.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">68</enrollment>
  <condition>Congenital Thrombotic Thrombocytopenic Purpura</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Prophylaxis Cohort I</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants randomized to SOC arm in prophylactic cohort will receive PK dose of their current SoC product followed by a single dose intravenous (IV) infusions of 40 International units per kilogram (IU/kg) BAX-930 ORT at 14 days later in PK I with a washout period of 14 days (+ or - 2 days). In period 1 participants will receive IV infusions of 40 IU/kg dose of BAX-930 ORT once every 2 weeks (Q2W) for 6 months followed by SOC in period 2 for the next six months. After period 2, participants will receive a single dose IV infusions of 40 IU/kg BAX-930 ORT followed by IV infusions of 40 IU/kg BAX-930 SIN in PK II with a washout period of 14 days (+ or - 2 days). All the participants in period 3 will receive BAX-930 SIN prophylactic dose of IV infusions of 40 IU/kg for another 6 months.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Prophylaxis Cohort II</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants randomized to BAX-930 arm in prophylactic cohort will receive a single dose IV infusions of 40 IU/kg BAX-930 ORT followed by a PK dose of their current SoC product at 14 days later in PK I with a washout period of 14 days (+ or - 2 days). In period 1 participants will receive SOC for the next six months followed by IV infusions of 40 IU/kg dose of BAX-930 ORT once Q2W for 6 months in period 2. Thereafter participants will receive a single dose IV infusions of 40 IU/kg BAX-930 SIN followed by IV infusions of 40 IU/kg BAX-930 ORT in PK II with a washout period of 14 days (+ or - 2 days). All the participants in period 3 will receive BAX-930 SIN prophylactic dose IV infusions of 40 IU/kg for another 6 months.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>On Demand Cohort I</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants randomized to SOC arm in On-demand cohort will receive the investigator-recommended SOC and dosing regimen during the acute event. In period 1 participants will receive IV infusions of 40 IU/kg dose of BAX-930 ORT once every 2 weeks (Q2W) for 6 months followed by SOC in period 2 for the next six months. Thereafter participants will receive a single dose IV infusions of 40 IU/kg BAX-930 ORT followed by IV infusions of 40 IU/kg BAX-930 SIN in PK II with a washout period of 14 days (+ or - 2 days). All the participants in period 3 will receive BAX-930 SIN prophylactic dose IV infusions of 40 IU/kg for another 6 months.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>On Demand Cohort II</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants randomized to BAX-930 arm in On-demand cohort will receive initial dose of IV infusions 40 IU/kg [+/- 4 IU/kg] BAX-930 ORT or BAX-930 SIN infusion then a subsequent dose IV infusions of 20 IU/kg [+/- 2 IU/kg] BAX-930 ORT or BAX-930 SIN infusion on Day 2 and an additional daily dose IV infusions of 15 IU/kg [+/- 1.5 IU/kg] BAX 930 until 2 days after the acute event is resolved. In period 1 participants will receive SOC for the next six months followed by IV infusions of 40 IU/kg dose of BAX-930 ORT once Q2W for 6 months in period 2. Thereafter participants will receive a single dose IV infusions of 40 IU/kg BAX-930 SIN followed by IV infusions of 40 IU/kg BAX-930 ORT in PK II with a washout period of 14 days (+ or - 2 days). All the participants in period 3 will receive BAX-930 SIN prophylactic dose IV infusions of 40 IU/kg for another 6 months.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>BAX930</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants in prophylaxis cohort will receive IV infusions of 40 IU/kg BAX 930 ORT during Period 1 and Period 2 and switch to BAX 930 SIN during Period 3 for six months once in a week or twice in a week. In On-demand cohort participants will receive daily IV dose of BAX-930.</description>
    <arm_group_label>On Demand Cohort I</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>On Demand Cohort II</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Prophylaxis Cohort I</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Prophylaxis Cohort II</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>rADAMTS13</other_name>
    <other_name>SHP-655</other_name>
    <other_name>TAK-755</other_name>
    <other_name>recombinant ADAMTS13</other_name>
    <other_name>BAX 930</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Standard of care</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will receive Investigator-recommended Standard of care (SoC).</description>
    <arm_group_label>On Demand Cohort I</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>On Demand Cohort II</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Prophylaxis Cohort I</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Prophylaxis Cohort II</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Participant or legally authorized representative has provided signed informed consent
             greater than or equal to (&gt;=) 18 years of age and/or assent form (signed by legal
             representative if participants is less than (&lt;) 18 years of age).

          -  Participant is 0 to 70 years of age, inclusive, at the time of screening.
             (Participants &lt; 18 years of age will be enrolled only after at least 5 adults (&gt;= 18
             years of age) each have at least 10 exposures with BAX 930 and reviewed by the Data
             Monitoring Committee (DMC). In France, no participants younger than 18 years of age
             will be enrolled into the study before the first adult participant has been treated
             with BAX 930 for a minimum of 6 months.

          -  Participant has a documented diagnosis of severe hereditary ADAMTS13 deficiency,
             defined as:

               -  Confirmed by molecular genetic testing, documented in participant history or at
                  screening, and

               -  A disintegrin and metalloprotease with a thrombospondin type 1 motif, member 13
                  (ADAMTS13) activity &lt; 10 percent (%) as measured by the fluorescent resonance
                  energy transfer- von Willebrand factor73 (FRETS-VWF73) assay, documented in
                  participant history or at screening (participants currently receiving standard of
                  care (SoC) prophylactic therapy may exceed 10% ADAMTS13 activity at screening).

        Note: Participants currently receiving prophylactic therapy will be screened immediately
        prior to their usual prophylactic infusion

          -  Participant does not display any severe thrombotic thrombocytopenic purpura (TTP)
             signs (platelet count &lt; 100,000/ microliter (μL) and elevation of lactate
             dehydrogenase (LDH) greater than (&gt;2) × upper limit of normal (ULN)) at screening.
             (Prophylactic cohort only).

          -  Participant is currently on a prophylactic dosing regimen or has a documented history
             of at least 1 TTP event and an ability to tolerate SoC prophylactic dosing
             (prophylactic cohort only).

          -  Participants &gt;= 16 years of age must have a Karnofsky score &gt;= 70% and participants &lt;
             16 years of age must have a Lansky score &gt;= 80%.

          -  Participant is hepatitis C virus (HCV)-negative as confirmed by antibody or polymerase
             chain reaction testing OR HCV-positive if their disease is chronic but stable.

          -  If female of childbearing potential, participant presents with a negative blood or
             urine pregnancy test, confirmed no more than 7 days before the first administration,
             and agrees to employ adequate birth control measures for the duration of the study and
             to undergo quarterly pregnancy testing.

          -  Sexually active males must use an accepted and effective method of contraception
             during the treatment and until a minimum of 16 days after the last dose administered.

          -  Participant is willing and able to comply with the requirements of the protocol.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Participant has been diagnosed with any other TTP-like disorder (microangiopathic
             hemolytic anemia), including acquired TTP.

          -  Participant has known hypersensitivity to hamster proteins.

          -  Participant has experienced an acute TTP episode less than 30 days prior to screening
             (prophylactic cohort only).

          -  Participant has a medical history or presence of a functional ADAMTS13 inhibitor at
             screening.

          -  Participant has a medical history of genetic or acquired immune deficiency that would
             interfere with the assessment of product immunogenicity, including participants who
             are human immunodeficiency virus (HIV)-positive with an absolute cluster of
             differentiation 4 (CD4) count &lt; 200/ Cubic Millimeter (mm^3) or who are receiving
             chronic immunosuppressive drugs.

          -  Participant has been diagnosed with severe cardiovascular disease (New York Heart
             Association classes 3 to 4).

          -  Participant with end stage renal disease requiring chronic dialysis.

          -  Participant has been diagnosed with hepatic dysfunction, as evidenced by, but not
             limited to, any of the following:

               -  Serum alanine aminotransferase (ALT) &gt;= 2× upper limit of normal (ULN).

               -  Severe hypoalbuminemia &lt; 24 gram per liter (g/L).

               -  Portal vein hypertension (e.g., presence of otherwise unexplained splenomegaly,
                  history of esophageal varices).

          -  In the opinion of the investigator, the participant has another clinically significant
             concomitant disease that may pose additional risks for the participant.

          -  Participant has been treated with an immunomodulatory drug, excluding topical
             treatment (e.g., ointments, nasal sprays), within 30 days prior to enrollment. Use of
             corticosteroids in conjunction with administration of fresh frozen plasma (FFP) to
             prevent allergic manifestations is permitted.

          -  Participant has an acute illness (e.g., influenza, flu-like syndrome, allergic
             rhinitis/conjunctivitis, bronchial asthma) at the time of screening (prophylaxis
             cohort only).

          -  Participant is receiving or anticipates receiving another investigational drug and/or
             interventional drug within 30 days before enrollment.

          -  Participant has a history of drug and/or alcohol abuse within the last 2 years.

          -  Participant has a progressive fatal disease and/or life expectancy of less than 3
             months.

          -  Participant is identified by the investigator as being unable or unwilling to
             cooperate with study procedures.

          -  Participant suffers from a mental condition rendering him/her unable to understand the
             nature, scope, and possible consequences of the study and/or evidence of an
             uncooperative attitude.

          -  Participant is a family member or employee of the sponsor or investigator.

          -  If female, participant is pregnant or lactating at the time of enrollment.

          -  Any contraindication to standard of care medicinal product(s) as per local prescribing
             information.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Study Director</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Shire</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Shire Contact</last_name>
    <phone>+1 866 842 5335</phone>
    <email>ClinicalTransparency@shire.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Childrens Healthcare of Atlanta</name>
      <address>
        <city>Atlanta</city>
        <state>Georgia</state>
        <zip>30322</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Site Contact</last_name>
      <phone>404-727-1608</phone>
      <email>ana.antun@emoryhealthcare.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ana Antun</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Duke University Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Durham</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27705</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Site Contact</last_name>
      <phone>919-660-7050</phone>
      <email>ara.metjian@duke.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>ara metjian</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cincinnati Children's Hospital Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cincinnati</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>45229</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Site Contact</last_name>
      <phone>513-636-8716</phone>
      <email>eric.mullins@cchmc.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Eric Mullins</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mid Ohio Heart Clinic Inc</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dublin</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>43017</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Site Contact</last_name>
      <phone>614-293-2887</phone>
      <email>spero.cataland@osumc.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Spero Cataland</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Oklahoma</name>
      <address>
        <city>Oklahoma City</city>
        <state>Oklahoma</state>
        <zip>73104</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Site Contact</last_name>
      <phone>405-271-8299</phone>
      <email>sami-ibrahami@ouhsc.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Sami Ibrahimi</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The Methodist Hospital Research Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Site Contact</last_name>
      <email>lrice@houstonmethodist.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Laurence Rice</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>AKH - Medizinische Universität Wien</name>
      <address>
        <city>Vienna</city>
        <zip>1090</zip>
        <country>Austria</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Site Contact</last_name>
      <phone>+4314040044100</phone>
      <email>paul.knoebl@meduniwien.ac.at</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Paul Knoebl</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hopital Claude Huriez - CHU Lille</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lille</city>
        <zip>59037</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Site Contact</last_name>
      <phone>+33320444371</phone>
      <email>francois.provot@chru-lille.fr</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Francois Provot</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hôpital Saint-Antoine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Paris</city>
        <zip>75012</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Site Contact</last_name>
      <phone>+33149282162</phone>
      <email>paul.coppo@aphp.fr</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Paul Coppo</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hôpital Robert Debré - Paris</name>
      <address>
        <city>Paris</city>
        <zip>75935</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Site Contact</last_name>
      <phone>+33140032467</phone>
      <email>georges.deschenes@rdb.aphp.fr</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Georges Deschenes</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Universitaetsklinikum Jena, Klinik fuer Kinder-und Jugendmedizin</name>
      <address>
        <city>Jena</city>
        <zip>07747</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Site Contact</last_name>
      <phone>+493641938426</phone>
      <email>karim.kentouche@med.uni-jena.de</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Karim Kentouche</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Fondazione IRCCS CA' Granda Ospedale Maggiore Policlinico</name>
      <address>
        <city>Milano</city>
        <zip>20122</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Site Contact</last_name>
      <phone>+390255035421</phone>
      <email>flora.peyvandi@unimi.it</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Flora Peyvandi</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Fondazione Policlinico Universitario Agostino Gemelli IRCCS</name>
      <address>
        <city>Roma</city>
        <zip>168</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Site Contact</last_name>
      <phone>+39630156329</phone>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Raimondo De Cristofaro</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Kyushu University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Fukuoka-shi</city>
        <state>Fukuoka-Ken</state>
        <zip>812-8582</zip>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Site Contact</last_name>
      <phone>+81926411151</phone>
      <email>ischii@pediatr.med.kyushu-u.ac.jp</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Masataka Ishimura</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hyogo College of Medicine Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nishinomiya</city>
        <state>Hyogo</state>
        <zip>663-8501</zip>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Site Contact</last_name>
      <phone>+81798456111</phone>
      <email>parasol@mua.biglobe.ne.jp</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Satoshi Higasa</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Medical Hospital, Tokyo Medical and Dental University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bunkyo City</city>
        <state>Tokyo</state>
        <zip>113-8519</zip>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Site Contact</last_name>
      <phone>+81358035646</phone>
      <email>mkajiwara.bldt@tmd.ac.jp</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Michiko Kajiwara</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Instytut Hematologii i Transfuzjologii</name>
      <address>
        <city>Warszawa</city>
        <zip>02-776</zip>
        <country>Poland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Site Contact</last_name>
      <phone>+482234961581</phone>
      <email>jwindyga@ihit.waw.pl</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jerzy Wyndiga</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital General Universitario de Alicante</name>
      <address>
        <city>Alicante</city>
        <state>Valencia</state>
        <zip>03010</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Site Contact</last_name>
      <phone>+34965938300</phone>
      <email>marco_pas@gva.es</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Pascual Marco Vera</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital de Cruces</name>
      <address>
        <city>Barakaldo</city>
        <state>Vizcaya</state>
        <zip>48903</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Site Contact</last_name>
      <phone>+34946006089</phone>
      <email>delorbebarreto2@osakidetza.eus</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Rafael Andres Del Ombre Barreto</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Universitari i Politecnic La Fe</name>
      <address>
        <city>València</city>
        <zip>46026</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Site Contact</last_name>
      <phone>+34961244865</phone>
      <email>sbonanad@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Santiago Bonanad</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Inselspital - Universitaetsspital Bern</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bern</city>
        <zip>3010</zip>
        <country>Switzerland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Site Contact</last_name>
      <phone>+41316329022</phone>
      <email>johanna.kremer@insel.ch</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Johanna Kremer Hovinga</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University College London Hospitals</name>
      <address>
        <city>London</city>
        <state>Greater London</state>
        <zip>NW1 2PG</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Site Contact</last_name>
      <phone>+442034479984</phone>
      <email>marie.scully@uclh.nhs.uk</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Marie Ann Scully</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Austria</country>
    <country>France</country>
    <country>Germany</country>
    <country>Italy</country>
    <country>Japan</country>
    <country>Poland</country>
    <country>Spain</country>
    <country>Switzerland</country>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 5, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 3, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 9, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 11, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 11, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 13, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Purpura</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Purpura, Thrombocytopenic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Purpura, Thrombotic Thrombocytopenic</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Shire provides access to the de-identified individual participant data for eligible studies to aid qualified researchers in addressing legitimate scientific objectives. These IPDs will be provided following approval of a data sharing request, and under the terms of a data sharing agreement.</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Statistical Analysis Plan (SAP)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Informed Consent Form (ICF)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Clinical Study Report (CSR)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_access_criteria>IPD from eligible studies will be shared with qualified researchers according to the criteria and process described in the Data Sharing section of the www.shiretrials.com website. For approved requests, the researchers will be provided access to anonymized data (to respect patient privacy in line with applicable laws and regulations) and with information necessary to address the research objectives under the terms of a data sharing agreement.</ipd_access_criteria>
    <ipd_url>https://www.shiretrials.com/en/our-commitment-to-transparency/data-sharing-with-researchers</ipd_url>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

