<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04141059</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>OLIGOSKIN</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04141059</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effect of Oligopin® on Skin Ageing</brief_title>
  <acronym>OLIGOSKIN</acronym>
  <official_title>Effect of a French Maritim Pine Bark Extract Oligopin® on Skin Ageing. Double Blind, Parallel, Randomized, Placebo Controled Intervention Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Technological Centre of Nutrition and Health, Spain</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Eurecat</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Hospital Universitari Sant Joan de Reus</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University Rovira i Virgili</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Les Dérivés Résiniques et Terpéniques (DRT) S.A.S.</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Technological Centre of Nutrition and Health, Spain</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Extrinsic or exogenous ageing is caused by repetitive exposure of the skin to harmful agents,
      while primary cause the exposure to ultraviolet (UV) radiation, known as photoageing,
      including solar effect. Chronic solar UV exposure has multiple damaging effects on skin, such
      as wrinkling, dryness, dyspigmentation, epidermal thinning and increasing fragility. In
      addition, solar exposure and age increase a subepidermal band.

      Fibrillar collagen, which is synthesized from fibroblasts, is the predominant extracellular
      matrix (ECM) component of the dermis. Collagen type I and III are considered to be the major
      interstitial, fiber forming collagen in normal human dermis. In addition, the dermis contains
      collagen types IV (gelatine), V and VI. Other important component of the EMC of the dermis
      are elastic fibers being elastin (ELN) their main component and play a critical role in skin
      elasticity and the reduction of elastic fiber production results in impaired elasticity. UV
      radiation induces ECM degeneration and consequently an increase in fragility and loss of
      elasticity of the skin. This process is mediated by an increase in matrix metalloproteinases
      (MMPs) expression in human skin which are responsible for degrading ECM proteins, such as
      collagen, fibronectin and elastin. The natural inhibitors of MMPs are tissue inhibitors of
      metalloproteinases (TIMPs), being TIMP-1 the most relevant TIMP affecting collagen
      metabolism.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Orally administered ingredients can have positive effects on skin characteristics by
      modulating the internal factors leading to the changes associated with photoageing. Thus, the
      use of food ingredients and supplements that claim to reduce the risk of skin disorders or
      alleviate skin ageing is increasing.

      Between these ingredients, polyphenols obtained from botanical extracts has been used for
      cosmetic applications, including Pycnogenol®, a French Maritime Pine Bark extract (FMPBE).
      showing photoprotective effect against UV-light induced skin damages, and an improvement in
      hydratation and elasticity of skin in human clinical trials. In another clinical trial,
      treatment with a different FMPBE called Flavangenol®, significantly decreased skin photo-aged
      scores. Other human intervention studies with oral administration of polyphenol extracts of
      different origins such as citrus extract (NutroxSun®), red orange fruit extract (Red Orange
      Complex®), Polypodium leucotomos and Pomegranate extracts (PPmix® and Fernblock®) have
      demonstrated beneficials effects of these supplements on improvement of skin characteristics.

      The results of the studies cited above suggest that oral administration of polyphenols rich
      extracts and especially of FMPBE is a promising approach for nutritional photoprotection of
      skin, reducing photoageing.

      Nevertheless, it must be taken into account that most of these studies have been done with a
      low number of subjects, with combination with other ingredients and/or without placebo group.
      Thus, well designed clinical trials with a correct volunteer's number are required to obtain
      robust results about the effects of FMPBE on skin ageing.

      Dérivés Résiniques et Terpéniques (DRT) is a company that has developed and commercialize
      Oligopin®, a polyphenol extract derived from French maritime pine bark. Oligopin® is
      characterized by a practical absence of tannins ( &lt; 1%) and a high content in low molecular
      weight oligomeric procyanidins (OPC &gt; 70%; dimers about 20%), a distinctive feature of other
      proanthocyanidin-rich extracts such as Pycnogenol® which contained about 5% of dimers.

      Furthermore, although the insoluble products in water are low in both products, lower and
      more adequate concentrations are present in Oligopin® (Oligopin ® typically 2 to 4% to a
      maximum at 5% versus Pycnogenol®: 6% - 8.1%).

      The degree of polymerization of OPC can determine its absorption across cell membranes and,
      as it has been observed in rats, only a certain OPC of a lower degree of polymerization is
      absorbed during transit in the gut. Consequently, the effect of FMPB extract could be
      determined, in part, by the quality of its OPC.

      The hypothesis of the present study is that circulating metabolic fraction of Oligopin® might
      exert beneficial actions on collagen metabolism, which is directly linked to skin strength
      and elasticity.

      In consequence, the daily consumption of Oligopin® will exert beneficial effects on skin
      ageing through the modulation of the proteins involved in the metabolism of collagen in
      humans.

      The main objective of the study is to determine the beneficial effects of Oligopin® on skin
      aging, through the improvement of skin elasticity in participants with photo-aging.

      The secondary objectives of the study are:

        -  To evaluate the effects of Oligopin® on skin aging through the measurement of wrinkles,
           spots, skin hydration and subepidermal band.

        -  To evaluate the effects of Oligopin® on the dynamics of collagen and elastin through the
           determination of different biomarkers in serum and the expression of genes in peripheral
           blood mononuclear cells (PBMCs).

        -  To discover new biomarkers of the effects of Oligopin® through transcriptomic analysis
           in PBMCs and serum metabolomic analysis.

        -  To characterize the metabolites of Oligopin® (MFO) in plasma.

        -  To establish potential correlations between specific metabolites of MFO and the
           beneficial effects of Oligopin® on the skin, as well as between serum biomarkers and
           PBMC.

        -  To evaluate the ability of the MFO to modulate the dynamics of collagen through the use
           of cellular models of human fibroblasts.

      In an initial phase, an acute postprandial study will be carried out with 20 of the 60
      volunteers with the consumption of 700 mg of Oligopin® in a single day, with the aim of
      obtaining the MFO. With MFO, the mechanisms by which Oligopin® exerts the beneficial effects
      on skin aging will be studied through in vitro studies with cellular models. The 60
      participants will participate in the second phase of the study, which will be randomly
      divided into two groups of 30 participants, depending on whether they consume a 100 mg
      Oligopin® capsule or a placebo capsule, with the same appearance as the Oligopin® capsule but
      will not contain the botanical extract. In this second phase, participants will consume one
      capsule each day for a total of 6 weeks.

      During the study there will be 5 visits, one of selection (V0), one of the first phase of the
      study (V1; week 1) and 3 visits of the second phase of the study (V2, V3 and V4; weeks 2, 3
      and 4).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">November 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in skin elasticity</measure>
    <time_frame>At weeks 2, 3 and 4</time_frame>
    <description>Skin elasticity measured by using a Cutometer® MPA 580</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in skin wrinkles</measure>
    <time_frame>At weeks 2, 3 and 4</time_frame>
    <description>Skin wrinkles measured using DermoPrime System</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in skin hydratation</measure>
    <time_frame>At weeks 2, 3 and 4</time_frame>
    <description>Skin hydratation measured using DermoPrime System</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in skin spots</measure>
    <time_frame>At weeks 2, 3 and 4</time_frame>
    <description>Skin spots measured using DermoPrime System</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in subepidermal low-echogenic band</measure>
    <time_frame>At weeks 2, 3 and 4</time_frame>
    <description>Subepidermal low-echogenic band measured by ultrasound echogenicity quantitative approach</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in biomarkers of collagen and elastin dynamics in serum</measure>
    <time_frame>At weeks 2 and 4</time_frame>
    <description>Serum levels of Human Procollagen I N-Terminal Propeptide, Human Procollagen I C-Terminal Propeptide, Human C-Telopeptide of Type I Collagen, Fibronectin, Elastin, Hyaluronic acid, MMP-1, TIMP-1. These biomarkers will be measured using humans ELISA kits.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in expression levels of genes related to collagen synthesis and degradation in PBMCs</measure>
    <time_frame>At weeks 2 and 4</time_frame>
    <description>Expression levels in PBMCs by quantitative polymerase chain reaction (qPCR) of the following genes: Collagen type I alpha 1 chain gene (Col1a1), Collagen type I alpha 2 chain gene (Col1a2), Mmp-2, Timp-1.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Oligopin® long-term blood metabolites characterization</measure>
    <time_frame>At weeks 2 and 4</time_frame>
    <description>Oligopin® blood metabolites will be measured by liquid chromatography quadruple Time-of-Flight (LC-qTOF). It will be analyzed the correlations between specific Oligopin® metabolites and its effects on skin, as well as on serum and PBMCs biomarkers.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Transcriptomics in PBMCs</measure>
    <time_frame>At weeks 2 and 4</time_frame>
    <description>Transcriptomics in PBMCs analyzed using microarrays Agilent technologies</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Metabolomics in serum</measure>
    <time_frame>At weeks 2 and 4</time_frame>
    <description>Non-targeted metabolomics of aqueous and lipid fraction of serum samples measured using proton nuclear magnetic resonance</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Postprandial Oligopin® blood metabolites characterization</measure>
    <time_frame>At week 1</time_frame>
    <description>Postprandial Oligopin® blood metabolites characterization after 700 mg Oligopin® consumption and measured by LC-qTOF. The measurements will be done at 0 hours, 2 hours and 6 hours.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Capacity of Oligopin® blood metabolites to modulate collagen levels</measure>
    <time_frame>At week 1</time_frame>
    <description>The capacity of Oligopin® blood metabolites to modulate collagen dynamics using human fibroblast cell line treated with Oligopin® blood metabolites and determination of total collagen concentration in cells and cultured media. The measurements will be done at 0 hours, 2 hours and 6 hours.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Capacity of Oligopin® blood metabolites to modulate secreted collagen type I</measure>
    <time_frame>At week 1</time_frame>
    <description>The capacity of Oligopin® blood metabolites to modulate collagen dynamics using human fibroblast cell line treated with Oligopin® blood metabolites and determination of secreted collagen type I. The measurements will be done at 0 hours, 2 hours and 6 hours.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Capacity of Oligopin® blood metabolites to modulate secreted collagen type III</measure>
    <time_frame>At week 1</time_frame>
    <description>The capacity of Oligopin® blood metabolites to modulate collagen dynamics using human fibroblast cell line treated with Oligopin® blood metabolites and determination of secreted collagen type III. The measurements will be done at 0 hours, 2 hours and 6 hours.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Capacity of Oligopin® blood metabolites to modulate pyruvate target genes</measure>
    <time_frame>At week 1</time_frame>
    <description>The capacity of Oligopin® blood metabolites to modulate collagen dynamics using human fibroblast cell line treated with Oligopin® blood metabolites and determination of mRNA levels of pyruvate target genes in cells measuring expression levels of elastin, Col1a1, Col1a2, Col3a1, Mmp-1 and Timp-1 genes. The measurements will be done at 0 hours, 2 hours and 6 hours.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Capacity of Oligopin® blood metabolites to modulate MMP-1 activity</measure>
    <time_frame>At week 1</time_frame>
    <description>The capacity of Oligopin® blood metabolites to modulate collagen dynamics using human fibroblast cell line treated with Oligopin® blood metabolites and determination of MMP-1 activity in culture medium. The measurements will be done at 0 hours, 2 hours and 6 hours.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Capacity of Oligopin® blood metabolites to modulate TIMP-1 levels</measure>
    <time_frame>At week 1</time_frame>
    <description>The capacity of Oligopin® blood metabolites to modulate collagen dynamics using human fibroblast cell line treated with Oligopin® blood metabolites and determination of TIMP-1 levels in culture medium. The measurements will be done at 0 hours, 2 hours and 6 hours.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Capacity of Oligopin® blood metabolites to inhibit MMP-1 activity</measure>
    <time_frame>At week 1</time_frame>
    <description>The capacity of Oligopin® blood metabolites to modulate collagen dynamics using human fibroblast cell line treated with Oligopin® blood metabolites and determination of inhibitory effect on MMP-1. The measurements will be done at 0 hours, 2 hours and 6 hours.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Capacity of Oligopin® blood metabolites to inhibit MMP-2 activity</measure>
    <time_frame>At week 1</time_frame>
    <description>The capacity of Oligopin® blood metabolites to modulate collagen dynamics using human fibroblast cell line treated with Oligopin® blood metabolites and determination of inhibitory effect on MMP-2. The measurements will be done at 0 hours, 2 hours and 6 hours.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Capacity of Oligopin® blood metabolites to inhibit MMP-9 activity</measure>
    <time_frame>At week 1</time_frame>
    <description>The capacity of Oligopin® blood metabolites to modulate collagen dynamics using human fibroblast cell line treated with Oligopin® blood metabolites and determination of inhibitory effect on MMP-9. The measurements will be done at 0 hours, 2 hours and 6 hours.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Effect of Oligopin® blood metabolites on collagen fibers cross-linking</measure>
    <time_frame>At week 1</time_frame>
    <description>The effect of Oligopin® blood metabolites to modulate collagen dynamics using human fibroblast cell line treated with Oligopin® blood metabolites and determination of collagen fibers cross-linking effect. The measurements will be done at 0 hours, 2 hours and 6 hours.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Skin Aging</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Oligopin</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Intervention group that will intake 100 mg of Oligopin® for 6 weeks</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Placebo group that will intake 250 mg of Maltodextrin</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Oligopin</intervention_name>
    <description>Oligopin capsules composition is :100 mg Oligopin®, 150 mg Maltodextrin, 1.5 mg Mg stearate.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Oligopin</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Placebo capsules composition is: 250 mg Maltodextrin and 1.5 mg Mg stearate</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Men and women 35 years or more age.

          -  Fitzpatrick skin phototype II-IV.

          -  Signed informed consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Present intolerances and/or food allergies related to Oligopin®.

          -  Being pregnant or intending to become pregnant.

          -  Be in breastfeeding period.

          -  Be a smoker.

          -  Participate in or have participate in a clinical trial or nutritional intervention
             study in the last 30 days prior to inclusion in the study.

          -  Present some chronic gastrointestinal disease.

          -  Present some chronic disease with clinical manifestation.

          -  Receive or are planning to receive facial cosmetic procedures such as facial peel,
             dermabrasion, laser treatments within six months prior to start the study.

          -  Take supplements or multivitamin supplements or phytotherapeutic products that
             interfere with the treatment under study up to 30 days before the start of the study.

          -  Has or are planning to take acne treatments, photoaging treatments or topical
             prescription products indicated for improving the appearance or condition of skin
             within 30 days.

          -  Present any skin disease (e.g., atopic skin, eczema, neurodermatitis or psoriasis) or
             other dermatological disorders (e.g., scars, sunburn or moles).

          -  Intensive sun or artificial UV exposure (solarium) on the test area within 30 days
             prior to study start or planned during the study period.

          -  Being unable to follow the study guidelines.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>35 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Rosa Solà, Dr</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>UTNS (Eurecat_Reus)/HUSJR. Reus, Tarragona, Spain.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Rosa M Valls, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>0034 636944723</phone>
    <email>estudis@ctns.cat</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Anna Crescenti, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+34977770958</phone>
    <email>anna.crescenti@eurecat.org</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Centro Tecnológico de Nutrición y Salud (Eurecat-Reus)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Reus</city>
        <state>Tarragona</state>
        <zip>43204</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Rosa Valls, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>+34 636 944 723</phone>
      <email>estudis@ctns.cat</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Anna Crescenti, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>+34 977 77 09 58</phone>
      <email>anna.crescenti@eurecat.org</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Spain</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://eurecat.org</url>
    <description>Technological Centre of Nutrition and Health. Eurecat_Reus.</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>October 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 17, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 24, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 28, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 24, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 24, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 28, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Photoaging</keyword>
  <keyword>Polyphenols</keyword>
  <keyword>Natural extracts</keyword>
  <keyword>Collagen metabolism</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

