<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04143724</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ACE-536-B-THAL-004</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>U1111-1241-4168</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>2019-000208-13</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04143724</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study of Safety &amp; PK of Luspatercept (ACE-536) in Pediatric Subjects Who Require Regular RBC Transfusions Due to Beta (β)-Thalassemia.</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase 2A Open-label Multicenter Study to Evaluate the Safety and Pharmacokinetics of Luspatercept in Pediatric Subjects Who Require Regular Red Blood Cell Transfusions Due to B-Thalassemia</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Celgene</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Acceleron Pharma, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Celgene</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a Phase 2a study to evaluate the safety and pharmacokinetics (PK) of luspatercept in
      pediatric subjects who require regular RBC transfusions due to β-thalassemia. At least 12
      subjects are planned to be enrolled per each of the 4 age-group strata at 2 different dose
      levels. Any subject benefiting from the study treatment (at the Investigator's discretion),
      at the completion of the Treatment Period, will be offered the opportunity to continue
      luspatercept and long-term follow-up in the Long-term Treatment and Follow-up Period.
      Subjects entering the Long-term Treatment and Follow-up Period will continue to receive
      luspatercept at the same dose level as during the Treatment Period for up to 5 years from
      their first dose (Cycle 1 Day 1) or when the drug is approved for pediatric patients
      (whichever comes first). Subjects who receive treatment for the full 5 years will then have
      an End of Treatment visit and then a Post End of Treatment visit (12 weeks from last dose).
      Any subject that discontinues treatment prior to 5 years from Cycle 1 Day 1 will be have an
      End of Treatment visit, a Post End of Treatment visit (12 weeks from last dose), and then
      will continue in Long-Term Posttreatment Follow-up until 5 years from Cycle 1 Day 1 or until
      they withdraw consent/assent, are lost to follow-up, or the End of Trial, whichever occurs
      first.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a Phase 2a study to evaluate the safety and pharmacokinetics (PK) of luspatercept in
      pediatric subjects who require regular red blood cell (RBC) transfusions due to β-thalassemia
      and to determine the recommended dose (RD) to be used in the planned confirmatory pediatric
      study.

      The primary endpoints are the determination of the RD and the development of a PK model that
      describes the PK exposure data of luspatercept and associated variability.

      The secondary endpoints include change in RBC transfusion burden, change in hemoglobin
      levels, safety, frequency of antidrug antibodies and its effect on safety and
      Exposure-response relationships for measures of activities and toxicity.

      The study will consist of the following periods:

        -  Screening/Run-in Period

        -  Treatment Period

        -  Posttreatment Follow-up Period

        -  Long-term Treatment and Follow-up Period

      Subject screening procedures will occur during the Screening/Run-in Period, within 12 weeks
      prior to the start of study treatment. Subjects who meet the study eligibility criteria will
      be enrolled into the Treatment Period.

      Patients enrolled into the study should have β-thalassaemia (including Hemoglobin
      E/β-thalassaemia) with ≥ 4 RBC transfusions in the 24 weeks prior to enrollment with no
      transfusion-free period ≥ 42 days during that period.

      Subjects in all planned dose escalation cohorts will receive luspatercept, administered as a
      subcutaneous (SC) injection, every 3 weeks (21 days) for up to 4 cycles (84 days) in the
      Treatment Period. Dose delay(s) and dose reduction(s) may be required for individual
      subjects.

      Each dose escalation cohort will consist of up to 6 subjects. Subjects will be treated at one
      of 2 dose levels, 0.75 mg/kg or 1.0 mg/kg, and enrollment will be sequential in descending
      order of age:

        -  Cohort 1: 12 to &lt; 18 years: Luspatercept 0.75 mg/kg, administered SC once every 21 days
           (for up to 4 cycles)

        -  Cohort 2: 12 to &lt; 18 years: Luspatercept 1.0 mg/kg, administered SC once every 21 days
           (for up to 4 cycles)

        -  Cohort 3: 6 to &lt; 12 years: Luspatercept 0.75 mg/kg, administered SC once every 21 days
           (for up to 4 cycles)

        -  Cohort 4: 6 to &lt; 12 years: Luspatercept 1.0 mg/kg, administered SC once every 21 days
           (for up to 4 cycles)

        -  Cohort 5: 2 to &lt; 6 years: Luspatercept 0.75 mg/kg, administered SC once every 21 days
           (for up to 4 cycles)

        -  Cohort 6: 2 to &lt; 6 years: Luspatercept 1.0 mg/kg, administered SC once every 21 days
           (for up to 4 cycles)

        -  Cohort 7: 6 months to &lt; 2 years: Luspatercept 0.75 mg/kg, administered SC once every 21
           days (for up to 4 cycles)

        -  Cohort 8: 6 months to &lt; 2 years: Luspatercept 1.0 mg/kg, administered SC once every 21
           days (for up to 4 cycles).

      The first dose of luspatercept should be administered at least 14 days after the last
      transfusion prior to enrollment. Subject enrollment via the Integrated Response Technology
      (IRT) system and study treatment administration should be on the same day (Cycle 1 Day 1),
      provided that the eligibility criteria are met. Otherwise, the subject will need to be
      rescreened.

      Once all 6 subjects in a cohort have completed the first cycle (Study Day 22), a Dose Review
      Team (DRT), consisting of the Celgene Medical Monitor, Celgene lead safety physician, Celgene
      biostatistician, other Celgene functional area representatives or designees, as appropriate,
      and all active site Investigators and/or designees (at sites with a subject who has received
      study drug), will review all safety data, including dose-limiting toxicities (DLTs), adverse
      events (AEs), serious adverse events (SAEs), and laboratory results (including hematology and
      chemistry) reported during Cycle 1 of each dose level.

      A DLT, using the current active version of the National Cancer Institute Common Toxicity
      Criteria for Adverse Events, version 5.0 (NCI-CTCAE v.5.0), is defined as any of the
      following toxicities at any dose level occurring within 21 days of the first administered
      dose:

        -  Treatment-related SAE of ≥ Grade 3

        -  Treatment-related nonhematologic AE of ≥ Grade 3

        -  Treatment-related hematologic AE of ≥ Grade 4

      The DRT recommendations to enroll the next cohort at the next planned dose level and/or
      proceed to the next lower age group will be based in part upon the following criteria:

        -  If a DLT occurs in ≤ 1 subject (out of 6) in a cohort within 21 days following the
           initial dose of luspatercept, the next planned dose level and/or next lower age group
           dose may proceed;

        -  If a DLT occurs in ≥ 2 subjects (out of 6) in a cohort within 21 days following the
           initial dose of luspatercept, the next planned dose level and/or the next lower age
           group should not proceed;

        -  If a hemoglobin increase of ≥ 2.0 g/dL (confirmed within 14 days after initial study
           treatment administration and not attributable to RBC transfusion) occurs in ≥ 2 subjects
           (out of 6) in a cohort, the decision to proceed to the next planned dose level and/or
           the next lower age group will need to be evaluated by the DRT.

      At least 12 subjects are planned to be enrolled with up to 12 subjects per age-group strata
      eligible for the Dose Determining Sets (DDS). With up to 4 age groups, a total of up to 48
      subjects are to be included in the DDS.

      This is a Phase 2a study to evaluate the safety and pharmacokinetics (PK) of luspatercept in
      pediatric subjects who require regular red blood cell (RBC) transfusions due to β-thalassemia
      and to determine the recommended dose (RD) to be used in the planned confirmatory pediatric
      study.

      The primary endpoints are the determination of the RD and the development of a
      pharmacokinetic (PK) model that describes the PK exposure data of luspatercept and associated
      variability.

      The secondary endpoints include change in RBC transfusion burden, change in hemoglobin
      levels, safety, frequency of antidrug antibodies and its effect on safety and
      Exposure-response relationships for measures of activities and toxicity.

      The study will consist of the following periods:

        -  Screening/Run-in Period

        -  Treatment Period

        -  Posttreatment Follow-up Period

        -  Long-term Treatment and Follow-up Period

      Subject screening procedures will occur during the Screening/Run-in Period, within 12 weeks
      prior to the start of study treatment. Subjects who meet the study eligibility criteria will
      be enrolled into the Treatment Period.

      Patients enrolled into the study should have β-thalassaemia (including Hemoglobin
      E/β-thalassaemia) with ≥ 4 RBC transfusions in the 24 weeks prior to enrollment with no
      transfusion-free period ≥ 42 days during that period.

      Subjects in all planned dose escalation cohorts will receive luspatercept, administered as a
      subcutaneous (SC) injection, every 3 weeks (21 days) for up to 4 cycles (84 days) in the
      Treatment Period. Dose delay(s) and dose reduction(s) may be required for individual
      subjects.

      Each dose escalation cohort will consist of up to 6 subjects. Subjects will be treated at one
      of 2 dose levels, 0.75 mg/kg or 1.0 mg/kg, and enrollment will be sequential in descending
      order of age:

        -  Cohort 1: 12 to &lt; 18 years: Luspatercept 0.75 mg/kg, administered SC once every 21 days
           (for up to 4 cycles)

        -  Cohort 2: 12 to &lt; 18 years: Luspatercept 1.0 mg/kg, administered SC once every 21 days
           (for up to 4 cycles)

        -  Cohort 3: 6 to &lt; 12 years: Luspatercept 0.75 mg/kg, administered SC once every 21 days
           (for up to 4 cycles)

        -  Cohort 4: 6 to &lt; 12 years: Luspatercept 1.0 mg/kg, administered SC once every 21 days
           (for up to 4 cycles)

        -  Cohort 5: 2 to &lt; 6 years: Luspatercept 0.75 mg/kg, administered SC once every 21 days
           (for up to 4 cycles)

        -  Cohort 6: 2 to &lt; 6 years: Luspatercept 1.0 mg/kg, administered SC once every 21 days
           (for up to 4 cycles)

        -  Cohort 7: 6 months to &lt; 2 years: Luspatercept 0.75 mg/kg, administered SC once every 21
           days (for up to 4 cycles)

        -  Cohort 8: 6 months to &lt; 2 years: Luspatercept 1.0 mg/kg, administered SC once every 21
           days (for up to 4 cycles)

      The first dose of luspatercept should be administered at least 14 days after the last
      transfusion prior to enrollment. Subject enrollment via the Integrated Response Technology
      (IRT) system and study treatment administration should be on the same day (Cycle 1 Day 1),
      provided that the eligibility criteria are met. Otherwise, the subject will need to be
      rescreened.

      Once all 6 subjects in a cohort have completed the first cycle (Study Day 22), a Dose Review
      Team (DRT), consisting of the Celgene Medical Monitor, Celgene lead safety physician, Celgene
      biostatistician, other Celgene functional area representatives or designees, as appropriate,
      and all active site Investigators and/or designees (at sites with a subject who has received
      study drug), will review all safety data, including dose-limiting toxicities (DLTs), adverse
      events (AEs), serious adverse events (SAEs), and laboratory results (including hematology and
      chemistry) reported during Cycle 1 of each dose level.

      A DLT, using the current active version of the National Cancer Institute Common Toxicity
      Criteria for Adverse Events, version 5.0 (NCI-CTCAE v.5.0), is defined as any of the
      following toxicities at any dose level occurring within 21 days of the first administered
      dose:

        -  Treatment-related SAE of ≥ Grade 3

        -  Treatment-related nonhematologic AE of ≥ Grade 3

        -  Treatment-related hematologic AE of ≥ Grade 4

      The DRT recommendations to enroll the next cohort at the next planned dose level and/or
      proceed to the next lower age group will be based in part upon the following criteria:

        -  If a DLT occurs in ≤ 1 subject (out of 6) in a cohort within 21 days following the
           initial dose of luspatercept, the next planned dose level and/or next lower age group
           dose may proceed;

        -  If a DLT occurs in ≥ 2 subjects (out of 6) in a cohort within 21 days following the
           initial dose of luspatercept, the next planned dose level and/or the next lower age
           group should not proceed;

        -  If a hemoglobin increase of ≥ 2.0 g/dL (confirmed within 14 days after initial study
           treatment administration and not attributable to RBC transfusion) occurs in ≥ 2 subjects
           (out of 6) in a cohort, the decision to proceed to the next planned dose level and/or
           the next lower age group will need to be evaluated by the DRT.

      At least 12 subjects are planned to be enrolled with up to 12 subjects per age-group strata
      eligible for the Dose Determining Sets (DDS). With up to 4 age groups, a total of up to 48
      subjects are to be included in the DDS.

      To minimize safety risk to subjects, best supportive care will be available, including RBC
      transfusions, iron-chelating agents, use of antibiotic therapy, antiviral and antifungal
      therapy, and/or nutritional support as needed.

      Dose interruptions/delays and dose reductions may be used to manage toxicities. Subjects can
      receive study treatment for up to 4 cycles during the Treatment Period, until study treatment
      becomes intolerable, or the subject wishes to discontinue study treatment for any reason. The
      decision to discontinue a subject from study treatment, is the responsibility of the treating
      physician; however, prior to discontinuing a subject, it is recommended that the Investigator
      contact the Medical Monitor and forward appropriate supporting documents for review and
      discussion. Subjects are to undergo end-of-treatment evaluations when study treatment is
      discontinued. The reason for treatment discontinuation will be recorded in the electronic
      case report form (eCRF) pages and in the source document.

      During the Treatment Period, any subjects discontinued from study treatment will continue to
      be assessed in the Posttreatment Follow-up Period for AEs, concomitant medications,
      concomitant procedures, transfusions, hematologic improvement, and subsequent therapies.

      Any subject benefiting from the study treatment (at the Investigator's discretion), at the
      completion of the Treatment Period, will be offered the opportunity to continue luspatercept
      and long-term follow-up in the Long-term Treatment and Follow-up Period. Subjects entering
      the Long-term Treatment and Follow-up Period will continue to receive luspatercept at the
      same dose level as during the Treatment Period for up to 5 years from their first dose (Cycle
      1 Day 1) or when the drug is approved for pediatric patients (whichever comes first).
      Subjects who receive treatment for the full 5 years will then have an End of Treatment (EOT)
      visit and then a Post End of Treatment visit (12 weeks from last dose). Any subject that
      discontinues treatment prior to 5 years from Cycle 1 Day 1 will be have an End of Treatment
      visit, a Post End of Treatment visit (12 weeks from last dose), and then will continue in
      Long-Term Posttreatment Follow-up until 5 years from Cycle 1 Day 1.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 7, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2, 2026</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 4, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Sequential Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Determination of the Recommended Dose</measure>
    <time_frame>At the end of Cycle 1 (each Cycle is 21 days)</time_frame>
    <description>Determine the recommended dose of luspatercept that is safe and tolerable in pediatric subjects with transfusion-dependent B-thalassemia.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetics - Cmax</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Day 148 (+/-) 7 days</time_frame>
    <description>Maximum plasma concentration of drug</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetics - AUC</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Day 148 (+/-) 7 days</time_frame>
    <description>Area under the plasma concentration-time curve from time zero extrapolated to infinity</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To evaluate the change in RBC transfusion burden</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 15 weeks (Up to 12 weeks for the Treatment Period plus 3 weeks post last dose (End of Treatment), thus a total of 15 weeks)</time_frame>
    <description>Change from baseline as continuous variable</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To evaluate the change in hemoglobin levels over the course of the study</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 15 weeks (Up to 12 weeks for the Treatment Period plus 3 weeks post last dose (End of Treatment), thus a total of 15 weeks)</time_frame>
    <description>Change from baseline as continuous variable</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety Adverse Events (AEs)</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Frequency/severity and seriousness of AEs, defined as any noxious, unintended, or untoward medical occurrence that may appear or worsen in a subject during the course of a study. It may be a new intercurrent illness, a worsening concomitant illness, an injury, or any concomitant impairment of the subject's health, including laboratory test values, regardless of etiology. Any worsening (ie, any clinically significant adverse change in the frequency or intensity of a preexisting condition) should be considered an AE.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Frequency of antidrug antibodies and its effect on safety</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <description>ADA measurements; key AEs and safety endpoints by ADA results (positive versus negative)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Exposure-response relationships for measures of activities and toxicity</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 15 weeks (Up to 12 weeks for the Treatment Period plus 3 weeks post last dose (End of Treatment), thus a total of 15 weeks)</time_frame>
    <description>Exposure-response assessed by the time the subject is exposed to treatment to the change in response (e.g. either transfusion, Hb or AE).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>8</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">48</enrollment>
  <condition>Beta-Thalassemia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 1: 12 to &lt; 18 years - Luspatercept 0.75 mg/kg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Luspatercept 0.75 mg/kg, administered SC once every 21 days (for up to 4 cycles)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 2: 12 to &lt; 18 years: Luspatercept 1.0 mg/kg,</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Luspatercept 1.0 mg/kg, administered SC once every 21 days (for up to 4 cycles)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 3: 6 to &lt; 12 years: Luspatercept 0.75 mg/kg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Luspatercept 0.75 mg/kg, administered SC once every 21 days (for up to 4 cycles)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 4: 6 to &lt; 12 years: Luspatercept 1.0 mg/kg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Luspatercept 1.0 mg/kg, administered SC once every 21 days (for up to 4 cycles)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 5: 2 to &lt; 6 years: Luspatercept 0.75 mg/kg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Luspatercept 0.75 mg/kg, administered SC once every 21 days (for up to 4 cycles)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 6: 2 to &lt; 6 years: Luspatercept 1.0 mg/kg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Luspatercept 1.0 mg/kg, administered SC once every 21 days (for up to 4 cycles)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 7: 6 months to &lt; 2 years: Luspatercept 0.75 mg/kg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Luspatercept 0.75 mg/kg, administered SC once every 21 days (for up to 4 cycles)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 8: 6 months to &lt; 2 years: Luspatercept 1.0 mg/kg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Luspatercept 1.0 mg/kg, administered SC once every 21 days (for up to 4 cycles)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ACE-536</intervention_name>
    <description>Subjects will start with luspatercept at 0.75mg/kg and the Dose review team (DRT) will evaluate all toxicities of each subject after Cycle 1 and determine whether or not to enroll the next cohort at the next planned dose level and/or next lower age group</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 1: 12 to &lt; 18 years - Luspatercept 0.75 mg/kg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 3: 6 to &lt; 12 years: Luspatercept 0.75 mg/kg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 5: 2 to &lt; 6 years: Luspatercept 0.75 mg/kg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 7: 6 months to &lt; 2 years: Luspatercept 0.75 mg/kg</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Luspatercept</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ACE-536</intervention_name>
    <description>Subjects will start with luspatercept at 1.0mg/kg and the Dose review team (DRT) will evaluate all toxicities of each subject after Cycle 1 and determine whether or not to enroll the next cohort at the next planned dose level and/or next lower age group</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 2: 12 to &lt; 18 years: Luspatercept 1.0 mg/kg,</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 4: 6 to &lt; 12 years: Luspatercept 1.0 mg/kg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 6: 2 to &lt; 6 years: Luspatercept 1.0 mg/kg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 8: 6 months to &lt; 2 years: Luspatercept 1.0 mg/kg</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Luspatercept</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Subjects must satisfy the following criteria to be enrolled into the study:

          1. Subject must be 6 months to &lt; 18 years of age at the time of signing the informed
             consent form (ICF)/informed assent form (IAF).

          2. Subject (and when applicable, parent/legal representative) must understand and
             voluntarily sign an ICF/IAF prior to conducting any study-related
             assessments/procedures.

          3. Subject (and when applicable, parent/legal representative) is willing and able to
             adhere to the study visit schedule and other protocol requirements.

          4. Subject must have documented diagnosis of β-thalassemia or Hemoglobin E/β-thalassemia.

          5. Subject is regularly transfused, defined as: ≥ 4 RBC transfusions in the 24 weeks
             prior to enrollment with no transfusion-free period ≥ 42 days during that period.

             Note: For the purpose of the study, transfusions administered over 2 or 3 consecutive
             days are considered as part of a single transfusion event.

          6. Subject has Karnofsky (age ≥16 years) or Lansky (age &lt; 16 years) performance status
             score ≥ 50 at screening.

          7. Female children of childbearing potential (FCCBP), females of childbearing potential
             (FCBP), and male subjects that have reached puberty (and when applicable, parent/legal
             representative) must agree to undergo physician-approved reproductive education and
             discuss the side effects of the study therapy on reproduction.

          8. Female children of childbearing potential, defined as females who have achieved
             menarche and/or breast development in Tanner Stage 2 or greater and have not undergone
             a hysterectomy or bilateral oophorectomy and females of childbearing potential
             (FCBP)defined as a sexually mature woman who has achieved menarche at some point, has
             not undergone a hysterectomy or bilateral oophorectomy and has not been naturally
             postmenopausal for at least 24 consecutive months (ie, has had menses at any time in
             the preceding 24 consecutive months) must meet the following conditions below (Note:
             Secondary amenorrhea from any cause does not rule out childbearing potential):

               -  Medically supervised serum pregnancy tests with a sensitivity of at least 25
                  mIU/mL must be conducted in Female children of childbearing potential (FCCBP)/
                  females of childbearing potential (FCBP), including those who commit to complete
                  abstinence. Female children of childbearing potential/ females of childbearing
                  potential (FCBP)must have 2 negative pregnancy tests as verified by the
                  Investigator prior to starting study therapy. Female children of childbearing
                  potential/ females of childbearing potential (FCBP)must agree to ongoing
                  pregnancy testing during the course of the study, after the end of study
                  treatment, and end of the study.

               -  Female subjects must, as appropriate to age and at the discretion of the site
                  Investigator, either commit to true abstinence* from heterosexual contact (which
                  must be reviewed on a monthly basis) or agree to use, and be able to comply with,
                  effective** contraception without interruption, 28 days prior to starting IP,
                  during the study therapy (including dose interruptions), and for 12 weeks
                  (approximately 5 times the mean terminal t1/2 of luspatercept based on
                  multiple-dose PK data) after discontinuation of study therapy.

          9. Male subjects, as appropriate to age and the discretion of the study physician:

               -  Must practice true abstinence* (which must be reviewed on a monthly basis) or
                  agree to use a synthetic or latex condom during sexual contact with a pregnant
                  female or a Female children of childbearing potential (FCCBP)/FCBP while
                  participating in the study, during dose interruptions and for at least 12 weeks
                  (approximately 5 times the mean terminal t1/2 of luspatercept based on
                  multiple-dose PK data) following IP discontinuation, even if he has undergone a
                  successful vasectomy

                    -  True abstinence is acceptable when this is in line with the preferred and
                       usual lifestyle of the subject. [Periodic abstinence (eg, calendar,
                       ovulation, symptothermal, post-ovulation methods) and withdrawal are not
                       acceptable methods of contraception.] ** Agreement to use highly effective
                       methods of contraception that alone or in combination result in a failure
                       rate of a Pearl index of less than 1% per year when used consistently and
                       correctly throughout the course of the study. Such methods include: Combined
                       (estrogen and progesterone/progestin containing) hormonal contraception:
                       Oral; Intravaginal; Transdermal; Progestogen/progestin only hormonal
                       contraception associated with inhibition of ovulation: Oral; Injectable
                       hormonal contraception; Implantable hormonal contraception; Placement of an
                       intrauterine device (IUD); Placement of an intrauterine hormone-releasing
                       system (IUS); Bilateral tubal occlusion; Vasectomized partner; Sexual
                       Abstinence.

        Exclusion Criteria:

        The presence of any of the following will exclude a subject from enrollment into the study:

          1. Subject has any significant medical condition, laboratory abnormality, or psychiatric
             illness that would prevent the subject from participating in the study.

          2. Subject has any condition including the presence of laboratory abnormalities, which
             places the subject at unacceptable risk if he/she were to participate in the study.

          3. Subject has any condition that confounds the ability to interpret data from the study.

          4. Subject has a diagnosis of Hemoglobin S/β-thalassemia or alpha (α)-thalassemia (eg,
             Hemoglobin H); β-thalassemia combined with α-thalassemia is allowed.

          5. Subject has evidence of active hepatitis C (HCV) infection, or active infectious
             hepatitis B (HBV), or known positive human immunodeficiency virus (HIV).

          6. Subject has deep vein thrombosis (DVT), stroke, or other thromboembolic event(s)
             (except clogged indwelling catheter) requiring medical intervention ≤ 24 weeks prior
             to enrollment.

          7. Subject has chronic anticoagulant therapy ≤ 28 days prior to enrollment (Anticoagulant
             therapies used for prophylaxis for surgery or high risk procedures as well as low
             molecular weight [LMW] heparin for superficial vein thrombosis [SVT] and chronic
             aspirin are allowed).

          8. Subject has platelet count &gt; 1000 x 109/L.

          9. Subject has poorly controlled diabetes mellitus within 24 weeks prior to enrollment as
             defined by short term (eg, hyperosmolar or ketoacidotic crisis) and/or history of
             diabetic cardiovascular complications (eg, stroke or myocardial infarction).

         10. Subject has treatment with another investigational drug or device ≤ 28 days prior to
             enrollment.

         11. Subject has prior exposure to sotatercept (ACE-011) or luspatercept (ACE-536).

         12. Subject has used an erythropoiesis-stimulating agent (ESA) ≤ 24 weeks prior to
             enrollment.

         13. Subject use of iron chelation therapy (ICT), if initiated ≤ 8 weeks prior to
             enrollment (allowed if initiated &gt; 8 weeks before or during treatment).

         14. Subject use of hydroxyurea treatment ≤ 24 weeks prior to enrollment.

         15. Subject is pregnant or breastfeeding female.

         16. Subject has uncontrolled hypertension. Controlled hypertension for this protocol is
             considered ≤ Grade 1 according to NCI CTCAE version 5.0.

         17. Subject has major organ damage, including:

               1. Symptomatic splenomegaly

               2. Liver disease with alanine aminotransferase (ALT)/aspartate aminotransferase
                  (AST) &gt; 3X the upper limit of normal (ULN) for age

               3. Heart disease, heart failure as classified by the New York Heart Association
                  (NYHA) classification 3 or higher, or significant arrhythmia requiring treatment,
                  or recent myocardial infarction within 6 months of enrollment

               4. Lung disease, including pulmonary fibrosis or pulmonary hypertension which are
                  clinically significant

               5. Renal insufficiency defined as:

                    -  A serum creatinine based on age/gender based on threshold derived from
                       Schwartz formula for estimating GFR utilizing child length and stature data
                       published by the Centers for Disease Control

         18. Subject has proteinuria ≥ Grade 3 according to NCI CTCAE version 5.0.

         19. Subject use of chronic systemic glucocorticoids ≤ 12 weeks prior to enrollment
             (physiologic replacement therapy for adrenal insufficiency is allowed). Single day
             glucocorticoid treatment (eg, for prevention or treatment of transfusion reactions) is
             allowed.

         20. Subject has major surgery ≤ 12 weeks prior to enrollment (subjects must have
             completely recovered from any previous surgery prior to enrollment).

         21. Subject has history of severe allergic or anaphylactic reactions or hypersensitivity
             to recombinant proteins or excipients in the IP (see IB).

         22. Subject use of cytotoxic agents, immunosuppressants ≤ 28 days prior to enrollment (ie,
             antithymocite globulin (ATG) or cyclosporine).

         23. Subject has history of malignancy with the exception of:

               1. Curatively resected nonmelanoma skin cancer.

               2. Curatively treated cervical carcinoma in situ.

               3. Other solid tumor with no known active disease in the opinion of the
                  Investigator.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>6 Months</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>18 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Bouchra Benettaib, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Celgene Corporation</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Associate Director Clinical Trial Disclosure</last_name>
    <phone>1-888-260-1599</phone>
    <email>clinicaltrialdisclosure@celgene.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Children's Hospital of Los Angeles</name>
      <address>
        <city>Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90027</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Universitatsklinikum Ulm</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ulm</city>
        <zip>89081</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>General Children's Hospital &quot;Agia Sophia&quot;</name>
      <address>
        <city>Athens</city>
        <zip>115 27</zip>
        <country>Greece</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ente Ospedaliero Ospedali Galliera - Centro della Microcitemia e delle Anemie Congenite</name>
      <address>
        <city>Genoa</city>
        <zip>16128</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Azienda Ospedaliera Universitaria &quot;Federico II&quot;</name>
      <address>
        <city>Napoli</city>
        <zip>80131</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Azienda Ospedaliero Universitaria S. Luigi Gonzaga</name>
      <address>
        <city>Orbassano</city>
        <zip>10043</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Siriraj Hospital Mahidol University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bangkok</city>
        <zip>10700</zip>
        <country>Thailand</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ege Universitesi Tip Fakultesi Hastanesi</name>
      <address>
        <city>Izmir</city>
        <zip>35100</zip>
        <country>Turkey</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Germany</country>
    <country>Greece</country>
    <country>Italy</country>
    <country>Thailand</country>
    <country>Turkey</country>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 2, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 28, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 29, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 21, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 21, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 23, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>ACE-536</keyword>
  <keyword>Luspatercept</keyword>
  <keyword>Pharmacokinetics</keyword>
  <keyword>Beta-Thalassemia</keyword>
  <keyword>Red Blood Cell Transfusion</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Thalassemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>beta-Thalassemia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Immunoglobulin Fc Fragments</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Information relating to our policy on data sharing and the process for requesting data can be found at the following link:
https://www.celgene.com/research-development/clinical-trials/clinical-trials-data-sharing/</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Statistical Analysis Plan (SAP)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Informed Consent Form (ICF)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Clinical Study Report (CSR)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Analytic Code</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>See Plan Description</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>See Plan Description</ipd_access_criteria>
    <ipd_url>https://www.celgene.com/research-development/clinical-trials/clinical-trials-data-sharing/</ipd_url>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

