<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04141345</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>201701459B0</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04141345</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Comorbid Chronic Lung Disease on Heart Failure</brief_title>
  <official_title>Influence of Comorbid Chronic Lung Disease on Heart Failure Long-Term Outcomes: Relevance of Ventilatory Inefficiency</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Chang Gung Memorial Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Chang Gung Memorial Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Comorbid chronic lung disease (CLD) increases mortality in heart failure (HF) patients.
      Understanding the predictors and pathophysiology of HF can improve the efficacy of HF
      treatment. This study evaluated the cardiopulmonary exercise test (CPET) results to identify
      significant predictors on long-term outcomes in HF patients with CLD.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The CPET was administered in a cohort of 169 HF outpatients with exercise intolerance at a
      tertiary referral center between May 2007 and July 2010. A CLD was defined as abnormal
      spirometry accompanied by clinical symptoms and signs included in the Global Initiative for
      Chronic Obstructive Lung Disease criteria. The primary endpoint was defined as CV mortality
      or the first HF hospitalization. Totally 49 events occurred before the end of follow up in
      January 2018.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 2007</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">January 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">July 2010</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Retrospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants That Had Occurrence of the Composite Endpoint, Which is Defined as Either Cardiovascular (CV) Death or First Heart Failure (HF) Hospitalization</measure>
    <time_frame>May, 2007 ~ January, 2018</time_frame>
    <description>Number of participants that had occurrence of the composite endpoint, which is defined as either CV death or first HF hospitalization</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">169</enrollment>
  <condition>Comorbid Chronic Lung Disease on Heart Failure</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Heart failure with chronic lung disease</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients were recruited consecutively based on clinical assessment of risk factors for HF and echocardiographic evidence of systolic dysfunction or diastolic dysfunction. Risk factors for HF were defined as hypertension, atherosclerotic disease, obesity, chronic obstructive lung disease, metabolic syndrome, smoking, and family history of HF. In patients with normal LVEF (&lt;50), diagnosis of diastolic dysfunction was based on echocardiographic parameters. Chronic lung disease (CLD) was defined as spirometry with obstructive lung disease or restrictive lung disease with accompanying clinical symptoms and signs included in the Global Initiative for Chronic Obstructive Lung Disease (GOLD) criteria.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Heart failure without chronic lung disease</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients were recruited consecutively based on clinical assessment of risk factors for HF and echocardiographic evidence of systolic dysfunction or diastolic dysfunction. Risk factors for HF were defined as hypertension, atherosclerotic disease, obesity, chronic obstructive lung disease, metabolic syndrome, smoking, and family history of HF. In patients with normal LVEF (&lt;50), diagnosis of diastolic dysfunction was based on echocardiographic parameters. Chronic lung disease (CLD) was defined as spirometry with obstructive lung disease or restrictive lung disease with accompanying clinical symptoms and signs included in the Global Initiative for Chronic Obstructive Lung Disease (GOLD) criteria. HF patients who did not have chronic lung disease were assigned as a non-CLD group.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>cardiopulmonary exercise test</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients performed an upright graded bicycle exercise using a personalized protocol or performed a motorized treadmill exercise using a modified Bruce protocol. Peak VO2 and peak respiratory exchange ratio (RER) were defined as the highest 30-second average value obtained during exercise. The anaerobic threshold (AT) was determined by V-slope method. The VE(minute ventilation)/VCO2 (carbon dioxide production) at AT was calculated as the average VE/VCO2 for 1 minute during AT and immediately after AT. If AT could not be determined, the lowest VE/VCO2 was determined by averaging the three lowest consecutive 0.5-minute data points.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Heart failure with chronic lung disease</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Heart failure without chronic lung disease</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        A cohort of 169 HF outpatients with exercise intolerance took the CPET at a tertiary
        referral center between May 2007 and July 2010. Patients were recruited consecutively based
        on clinical assessment of risk factors for HF and echocardiographic evidence of systolic
        dysfunction or diastolic dysfunction. In patients with normal LVEF (&gt;=50), the diagnosis of
        diastolic dysfunction was based on echocardiographic parameters. Chronic lung disease (CLD)
        was defined as spirometry with obstructive lung disease or restrictive lung disease with
        accompanying clinical symptoms and signs included in the Global Initiative for Chronic
        Obstructive Lung Disease (GOLD) criteria.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  outpatients ≥ 18 years of age, male or female.

          -  Patients with a diagnosis of heart failure with clinical symptoms and echocardiography
             evidence

          -  Patients received cardiopulmonary exercise test exams

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Cannot tolerance exercise test due to muscular-skeletal disorder

          -  Cannot co-operate all functional studies

          -  Family reject to participate in this project
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <verification_date>October 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 24, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 24, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 28, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 24, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 24, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 28, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lung Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Heart Failure</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>We will discuss with other investigators about individual participant data (IPD) sharing.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

