<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04144595</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>GI19-00006</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04144595</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Association Between Low Plasma Glucose After Oral Glucose Tolerance Test in Pregnancy With Impaired Fetal Growth</brief_title>
  <official_title>Association Between Low Plasma Glucose After Oral Glucose Tolerance Test in Pregnancy With Impaired Fetal Growth</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Hospital Universitario Dr. Jose E. Gonzalez</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Hospital Universitario Dr. Jose E. Gonzalez</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Objective: To study the association of low maternal plasma glucose in 2 hour 75 g oral
      glucose tolerance test (OGTT) in women with impaired birth weight and determinate if this
      result is predictive of low birth weight (&lt;10th percentile according to the INTERGROWTH-21st
      newborn weight standards for gestational age/sex).

      Materials and methods: OGTT at 24-34 week gestation will be performed in pregnant women, the
      birth weight will be compared between women with low fasting plasma glucose (FPG) (&lt;10th
      percentile, &lt;65 mg/dL) and normal FPG (≥10th percentile, ≥ 65 mg/dL) also for 1 and 2-hour
      plasma glucose (1-h PG/2-h PG). Receiver operating characteristic curve analysis will be used
      to determine the optimal lower OGTT threshold for the prediction of low birth weight.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Maternal hypoglycemia has been reported to be linked with low birth weight and poor neonatal
      outcome. OGTT is performed routinely in pregnancy and hypoglycemia following this screening
      test is often encountered and the implication of this finding for the fetal growth is
      unclear.

      The aim of study will be determinate the association of low maternal plasma glucose in OGTT
      in women with impaired birth weight and determinate if this result is predictive of low birth
      weight (&lt;10th percentile according to the INTERGROWTH-21st newborn weight standards for
      gestational age/sex).

      The study population will consist of patients with singleton pregnancies who will undergo
      OGTT at 24-34 weeks, have regular medical checkups throughout their entire pregnancy, deliver
      on or after 25 week gestation and fulfill inclusion criteria.

      The birth weight will be compared between women with low fasting plasma glucose (FPG) (&lt;10th
      percentile, &lt;65 mg/dL*) and normal FPG (≥10th percentile, ≥ 65 mg/dL) also for 1 and 2-hour
      plasma glucose (1-h PG/2-h PG). Receiver operating characteristic curve analysis will be used
      to determine the optimal lower OGTT threshold for the prediction of low birth weight.

      This study will be performed according to the standards of the Helsinki Declaration and
      approval was obtained from the ethics and educational issues coordinating committee of our
      University Hospital.

      *Determinated previously in a pilot study
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">November 30, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">October 28, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Birth weight &lt;10th percentile</measure>
    <time_frame>Newborn birth weight delivered on or after 25 week gestation will be recorded within the first hour after delivery</time_frame>
    <description>Birth weight &lt;10th percentile according to the INTERGROWTH-21st newborn weight standards for gestational age/sex.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Birthweight &lt;3th percentile</measure>
    <time_frame>Newborn birth weight delivered on or after 25 week gestation will be recorded within the first hour after delivery</time_frame>
    <description>Birthweight &lt;3th percentile according to the INTERGROWTH-21st newborn weight standards for gestational age/sex.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Birth weight &lt;2500 g</measure>
    <time_frame>Newborn birth weight delivered on or after 37 week gestation will be recorded within the first hour after delivery</time_frame>
    <description>Birth weight &lt;2500 g of newborn delivered on or after 37 week gestation</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">300</enrollment>
  <condition>Oral Glucose Tolerance Test</condition>
  <condition>Low Birth Weight</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Low plasma glucose</arm_group_label>
    <description>This group will be formed by women with low plasma glucose: fasting plasma glucose (&lt;10th percentile, &lt;65 mg/dL), 1 or 2-hour low plasma glucose results after OGTT.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Normal plasma glucose</arm_group_label>
    <description>This group will be formed by women with normal plasma glucose: fasting plasma glucose ( ≥10th percentile, ≥65 mg/dL but &lt; 92 mg/dL), 1 or 2-hour normal glucose (&lt; 180 mg/dL and 153 mg/dL, respectively) results after OGTT.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>2 hour 75 g Oral glucose tolerance test</intervention_name>
    <description>In pregnant women between 24 and 34 weeks of gestational age, plasma glucose was recorded after an overnight fast. Following consumption of 75 g glucose in 200 mL water over 10 min, the equivalent 1 hour and 2 hour values was recorded</description>
    <arm_group_label>Low plasma glucose</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Normal plasma glucose</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        The study population consisted of patients with singleton pregnancies who underwent OGTT at
        24-34 weeks, had regular medical checkups throughout their entire pregnancy, had delivered
        on or after 25 week gestation and had fulfilled inclusion criteria. This study was
        performed according to the standards of the Helsinki Declaration and approval was obtained
        from the ethics and educational issues coordinating committee of our University Hospital.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Women with singleton pregnancy who underwent OGTT at 24-34 weeks and had regular
             medical checkups throughout their entire pregnancy.

          -  Gestational age was determined based on the last menstrual period. If gestational age
             according to the last menstrual period differed by more than 7 days from that
             according to ultrasonography at &lt;11 weeks, the latter was used to assign gestational
             age.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Inaccurate gestational age

          -  OGTT being drawn outside the prescribed window of 24 to 34 weeks gestation.

          -  Patients who could not swallow the OGTT solution or vomited afterward were excluded
             from the study.

          -  Patients who were diagnosed with gestational diabetes at any time during their
             pregnancy were excluded.

          -  The following comorbidities or complications that could affect fetal growth also were
             excluded: cardiac disease, preeclampsia, gestational hypertension, tobacco use,
             alcohol intake, stimulant drugs use, maternal systemic diseases (e.g., hypertension,
             pregestational diabetes, autoimmune disease, thrombotic disease, thyroid disease),
             intrauterine infectious diseases (e.g., cytomegalovirus, rubella, toxoplasmosis,
             syphilis), major neonatal anomalies or genetic and structural disorders (e.g., trisomy
             21, trisomy 18, trisomy 13, congenital heart disease), placental disorders, and
             umbilical cord abnormalities.

          -  Patients with high risk for preeclampsia, intrauterine growth restriction, trisomy 21,
             trisomy 18 and trisomy 13 in the first trimester screening test.

          -  Patients with incomplete or missing data were also excluded.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <gender_based>Yes</gender_based>
    <gender_description>Pregnant women at 24-28 week gestation</gender_description>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Flavio Hernández Castro, MD PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Obstetrics Department Universidad Autónoma de Nuevo León</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Universitario Dr. José Eleuterio González</name>
      <address>
        <city>Monterrey</city>
        <state>Nuevo León</state>
        <zip>64460</zip>
        <country>Mexico</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Mexico</country>
  </location_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Nayak AU, Vijay AMA, Indusekhar R, Kalidindi S, Katreddy VM, Varadhan L. Association of hypoglycaemia in screening oral glucose tolerance test in pregnancy with low birth weight fetus. World J Diabetes. 2019 May 15;10(5):304-310. doi: 10.4239/wjd.v10.i5.304.</citation>
    <PMID>31139317</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Shinohara S, Uchida Y, Hirai M, Hirata S, Suzuki K. Relationship between maternal hypoglycaemia and small-for-gestational-age infants according to maternal weight status: a retrospective cohort study in two hospitals. BMJ Open. 2016 Dec 2;6(12):e013749. doi: 10.1136/bmjopen-2016-013749.</citation>
    <PMID>27913562</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Topçu HO, İskender CT, Çelen Ş, Oskovi A, Uygur D, Erkaya S. Maternal hypoglycemia on 50 g glucose challenge test: outcomes are influenced by fetal gender. J Perinat Med. 2016 May 1;44(4):369-76. doi: 10.1515/jpm-2015-0060.</citation>
    <PMID>25918915</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Rogne T, Jacobsen GW. Association between low blood glucose increase during glucose tolerance tests in pregnancy and impaired fetal growth. Acta Obstet Gynecol Scand. 2014 Nov;93(11):1160-9. doi: 10.1111/aogs.12365. Epub 2014 Mar 26.</citation>
    <PMID>24576054</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Melamed N, Hiersch L, Peled Y, Hod M, Wiznitzer A, Yogev Y. The association between low 50 g glucose challenge test result and fetal growth restriction. J Matern Fetal Neonatal Med. 2013 Jul;26(11):1107-11. doi: 10.3109/14767058.2013.770460. Epub 2013 Feb 27.</citation>
    <PMID>23350735</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Vadakekut ES, McCoy SJ, Payton ME. Association of maternal hypoglycemia with low birth weight and low placental weight: a retrospective investigation. J Am Osteopath Assoc. 2011 Mar;111(3):148-52.</citation>
    <PMID>21464263</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Feinberg JH, Magann EF, Morrison JC, Holman JR, Polizzotto MJ. Does maternal hypoglycemia during screening glucose assessment identify a pregnancy at-risk for adverse perinatal outcome? J Perinatol. 2005 Aug;25(8):509-13.</citation>
    <PMID>15908987</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Leng J, Hay J, Liu G, Zhang J, Wang J, Liu H, Yang X, Liu J. Small-for-gestational age and its association with maternal blood glucose, body mass index and stature: a perinatal cohort study among Chinese women. BMJ Open. 2016 Sep 15;6(9):e010984. doi: 10.1136/bmjopen-2015-010984.</citation>
    <PMID>27633632</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>January 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 28, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 28, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 30, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 9, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 9, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 13, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Hospital Universitario Dr. Jose E. Gonzalez</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Dr. med Flavio Hernández Castro</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Glucose Tolerance Test</keyword>
  <keyword>Low Birth Weight</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Birth Weight</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

