<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04140110</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ENCHANTED2</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04140110</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Second Enhanced Control of Hypertension and Thrombectomy Stroke Study (ENCHANTED2)</brief_title>
  <acronym>ENCHANTED2</acronym>
  <official_title>Second Enhanced Control of Hypertension and Thrombectomy Stroke Study (ENCHANTED2)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>The George Institute for Global Health, China</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Changhai Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>The George Institute for Global Health, China</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      ENCHANTED2 is an international, multicenter, prospective, randomised, open, blinded end-point
      assessed (PROBE) trial, to assessf different approaches to blood pressure (BP) in acute
      ischemic stroke (AIS) patients who have undergone mechanical thrombectomy (MT). There are two
      nested substudies evaluating different approaches to secondary prevention in this high-risk
      stroke population.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Objectives: To determine the effectiveness of more intensive BP lowering target (&lt;120 mmHg)
      compared to higher BP management target (140-180mmHg) on functional outcome in patients with
      successful recanalization post-MT for AIS due to large vessel occlusion (LVO).

      Inclusion Criteria:

        1. Age ≥18 years;

        2. Diagnosis of AIS with LVO confirmed by brain imaging;

        3. Fulfill local criteria for MT therapy;

        4. Achieve successful recanalization (TICI score ≥2b) after MT;

        5. Provide written informed consent (or approved surrogate);

        6. Persistent (2 readings &lt;10 mins) systolic BP ≥140 mmHg &lt;3 hours after recanalization;

        7. No definite indication/contraindication to different intensities of BP lowering
           treatment;

      Exclusion Criteria:

        1. Unlikely to benefit from therapy (e.g. advanced dementia) or very high likelihood of
           early death post-MT, judged by responsible treating clinician.

        2. Other medical illness that interferes with outcome assessments and follow-up (e.g. known
           significant pre-stroke disability (mRS scores 3-5), advance cancer and renal failure);

        3. Specific contraindications to any of the BP agents to be used (eg, patients who are
           hypersensitive (allergic) to any of the ingredients);

        4. Need for following concomitant medication, including phosphodiesterase inhibitors and
           monoamine oxidase inhibitors.

        5. Patients with aortic isthmus stenosis and arteriovenous shunt (exception: patients with
           haemodynamically inactive dialysis shunt).

        6. Women who are lactating.

        7. Currently participating in another trial which would interfere with outcome assessments.

      Outcome Measures Primary outcome: functional recovery, defined as a shift (improvement) in
      scores on the modified Rankin scale (mRS) at 90 days.

      Secondary outcomes: any intracranial haemorrhage (ICH), symptomatic intracerebral haemorrhage
      (sICH), early neurological deterioration, imaging assessment (e.g. infarct size, edema
      volume), death, disability, HRQoL, duration of hospitalization, residence; and health service
      use for calculation of resources and costs.

      Randomisation and intervention: Randomisation is via a central internet-based system,
      stratified by site, time from symptom onset to recanalization (&lt;6, ≥6 hours), baseline
      neurological impairment on the National Institutes for Health Stroke Scale (NIHSS, &lt;17 vs
      ≥17), to ensure balance in key prognostic factors.

      Intensive BP lowering group: to commence intravenous BP lowering therapy immediately after
      randomization, with systolic BP target (&lt;120 mmHg) achieved within 30 minutes, and maintained
      for at least 72 hours (or hospital discharge if earlier).

      Control group: to receive guideline-recommended BP control strategy to maintain BP level &lt;180
      mmHg after MT procedure, but BP lowering treatment given only for BP ≥150 mmHg to achieve
      target ≥140 mmHg.

      Substudies: Patients enrolled in main study can also be randomised into 2 substudies
      according to separate eligibility criteria. Both are pilot studies embedded in main trial to
      recruit as many patients to inform sample size estimates for a further main study.

      Substudy #1: Timing of anticoagulation Objective: To determine the effectiveness of early
      initiation of anticoagulation (at Day 4±2 of stroke onset) compared with late initiation (at
      Day 12±2) on a composite outcome of recurrent AIS, sICH, systemic embolism and/or vascular
      death within 90 days in patients with AF-related AIS due to LVO who receive MT. Randomisation
      (allocation 1:1 ratio) via same system as main study and stratified by site, NIHSS score at
      24 hours (&lt;10 vs ≥10) and anticoagulation intent (warfarin vs DOACs). Randomised patients
      will be allocated to either early group of initiating OAC therapy at Day 4±2 day of stroke
      onset, or late group of initiating OAC therapy at Day 12±2 of stroke onset. Primary outcome:
      composite of recurrent AIS, sICH, systemic embolism and/or vascular death within 90 days
      after randomisation.

      Substudy #2: Duration of dual antiplatelet therapy (DAPT):

      Objective: To determine the effectiveness of short duration of DAPT (&lt;6 weeks) compared with
      standard duration (3 months or more) on recurrence rate within 12 months in patients with AIS
      due to large artery atherosclerosis (LAA) who are eligible for DAPT post-MT. Randomisation
      (allocation 1:1 ratio) will be done via the same system as the main study and stratified by
      site, and NIHSS score at 24 hours (&lt;10 vs ≥10). Randomised patients will be allocated to
      either short duration group of receiving DAPT (aspirin 100 mg and clopidogrel 75 mg per day)
      for 6 weeks, or standard duration group receiving DAPT for 3 months. DAPT is started &lt;48
      hours post-randomization, and maintained changed to antiplatelet monotherapy (aspirin or
      clopidogrel) thereafter. Primary outcome is new stroke event (AIS or ICH) over 12 months.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">April 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 28, 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 28, 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Different intensities of blood pressure management using locally available intravenous antihypertensive agents</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>Open intervention; outcome assessments undertaken by trained research staff who are kept blind to treatment allocation</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Level of disability</measure>
    <time_frame>90 days (3 months)</time_frame>
    <description>a shift (improvement) in scores (0-6) on the modified Rankin scale</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>intracerebral hemorrhage (ICH)</measure>
    <time_frame>90 days</time_frame>
    <description>any or symptomatic ICH (sICH) after MT</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Imaging endpoints</measure>
    <time_frame>24-48 hours</time_frame>
    <description>infarct size growth</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Death or neurological severity</measure>
    <time_frame>7 days</time_frame>
    <description>Death or dependency measured by National Institutes of Health stroke scale (NIHSS)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Others</measure>
    <time_frame>90 days</time_frame>
    <description>Death or major disability (mRS 3-6); separately on death and disability (mRS 3-5); health-related quality of life (HRQoL) using EQ-5D; duration of hospitalisation; residence and hospital service cost.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">2236</enrollment>
  <condition>Acute Ischemic Stroke</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Achieving SBP level of &lt;120 mmHg within 30 minutes after randomisation, and maintaining this level at least 72 hours.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>BP lowering treatment can be given only when BP level ≥150 mmHg in order to achieve the target of ≥140 mmHg, and maintaining this level at least 72 hours.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Intensive BP lowering</intervention_name>
    <description>The aim is to achieve a systolic BP level of &lt;120mmHg within 30 minutes after randomisation and to maintain this BP level for the next 72 hours (or until hospital discharge or death if this should occur earlier).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Adult (age ≥18 years)

          2. Clinical diagnosis of AIS with LVO (anterior or posterior circulation) on imaging

          3. To receive MT &lt;24 hours after AIS onset according to local guidelines

          4. Successful recanalization (TICI score ≥2b)

          5. Sustained systolic BP ≥140 mmHg (defined as 2 readings) within 3 hours post-MT

          6. Provide informed consent (or by appropriate proxy, according to local requirements)

          7. No definite indication/contraindication to either immediate intensive BP lowering (to
             a systolic target &lt;120 mmHg) or standard BP management (BP lowering treatment could be
             given only SBP &gt;150mmHg)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Considered unlikely to benefit from therapy (e.g. advanced dementia, major pre-stroke
             disability, high likelihood of early death on the basis of clinical assessment), as
             judged by the responsible treating clinician

          2. Major co-morbid disease that interferes with outcome assessments and follow up [e.g.
             cancer, chronic airflow disease, severe heart failure, known significant pre-stroke
             disability (mRS scores 3-5)]

          3. Specific contraindications to any of the BP agents to be used (eg, patients who are
             hypersensitive (allergic) to any of the ingredients)

          4. Need for following concomitant medication, including phosphodiesterase inhibitors and
             monoamine oxidase inhibitors.

          5. Patients with aortic isthmus stenosis and arteriovenous shunt (exception: patients
             with haemodynamically inactive dialysis shunt).

          6. Women who are lactating.

          7. Currently participating in another trial which may interfere with outcome assessments
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <gender_based>Yes</gender_based>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Craig Anderson</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>The George Institute for Global Health, China</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Lily Song, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+86 13916466400</phone>
    <email>lsong@georgeinstitute.org.cn</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <verification_date>October 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 22, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 23, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 25, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 23, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 23, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 25, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>The George Institute for Global Health, China</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Craig Anderson</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Executive Director</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Acute ischemic stroke</keyword>
  <keyword>Large vessel occlusion</keyword>
  <keyword>Mechanical thrombectomy</keyword>
  <keyword>Blood pressure management</keyword>
  <keyword>Antiplatelet therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Anticoagulation therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Randomised clinical trial</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Stroke</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hypertension</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Data can be shared with bona fide researchers after after publication of the main results, based on a submitted protocol to the research office of The George Institute for Global Health, Sydney Australia.</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Statistical Analysis Plan (SAP)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Informed Consent Form (ICF)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Clinical Study Report (CSR)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Analytic Code</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>Data sharing will be available from 12 months after publication of the main results.</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>The data sharing will be only for the purposes of health and medical research and within the constraints of the consent under which the data were originally gathered.
The Custodian of the Collection will not consider any Proposals for data sharing that unblind, or potentially unblind, randomised comparisons in active / ongoing trials.
Requesters should be employees of a recognised academic institution, health service organisation, commercial research organisation or from the pharmaceutical industry. Requesters must have experience in medical research.
Requesters must be able to demonstrate through their peer review publications in the area of interest their ability to carry out the proposed use of the requested dataset from a Collection.
The Requesters must not have a conflict of interest that may potentially influence their interpretation of any analyses.</ipd_access_criteria>
    <ipd_url>http://georgeinstitute.org.au</ipd_url>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

