<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04142294</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>83676/A001</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04142294</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Safety of Graded-Dose of Histidine in Humans</brief_title>
  <official_title>Safety of Graded-Dose of Histidine as Determined by Circulating Analytes, Sleep Records, Physical Activity, Anthropometric Measurements, and Mood</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Cornell University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Cornell University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Histidine is an essential amino acid with health benefits that include anti-inflammatory,
      anti-oxidant, glucoregulatory, and weight management. The current expert opinion for
      histidine intake is 8 and 12 mg/(kg body weight per day), an estimate that was extrapolated
      from the infant requirement for histidine. Further, the clinical safety of histidine
      supplementation above the average dietary intake has not been determined.The overarching
      objectives are to 1) measure the safety of histidine supplementation and 2) measure the
      potential benefits of histidine at doses above the average intake and current recommendation
      in a healthy adult population.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Histidine is an essential amino acid with health benefits that include anti-inflammatory,
      anti-oxidant, glucoregulatory, and weight management. Because of the extended period of time
      (&gt;35 days) that is required to deplete body histidine pools in adults, it has not been
      possible to fully determine histidine requirements. The current expert opinion for histidine
      intake is 8 and 12 mg/(kg body weight per day), an estimate that was extrapolated from the
      infant requirement for histidine. The average intake of histidine from a normal adult diet in
      the U.S., Europe, and Japan was reported between 2.12 and 2.40 g/day with the 99th percentile
      intake in men at 50-70 years of age consuming 5.20 g/day. The clinical safety of histidine
      supplementation above the average dietary intake has not been determined. Therefore, this
      study will utilize graded doses of histidine that are at are moderately above the average
      intake to identify safety and benefits of histidine in a healthy human population. Further,
      the clinical safety of histidine supplementation above the average dietary intake has not
      been determined.The overarching objectives are to 1) measure the safety of histidine
      supplementation and 2) measure the potential benefits of histidine at doses above the average
      intake and current recommendation in a healthy adult population. Following the completion and
      review of a health history questionnaire, vitals, and a biochemical panel, participants will
      be deemed healthy by a nurse practitioner and able to participate. After baseline measures
      are obtained, supplements (encapsulated histidine) will be provided at three graded doses (4
      g/day, 8 g/day and 12 g/day) a forth dose (16 g/day) will be consumed if no adverse effects
      are observed at the three graded doses. Each dose will be for 28 days followed by a three
      week recovery period. At baseline, weeks 2 and 4 of supplement, and recovery a basic
      biochemical panel, anthropometric, urinary and serum zinc, will be conducted. Additionally,
      body composition will be conducted at baseline and week 4 of each dose. Changes in dietary
      intake and physical activity will be measured with 4-day food records and Actigraph activity
      monitors, respectively. Changes in sleep patterns will be measured with the Pittsburgh sleep
      questionnaire.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 21, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">August 31, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">August 31, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Sequential Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Histidine supplementation trial, non-randomized, sequential delivery of graded doses of the amino acid histidine. All participants serve as their own controls. Following baseline measurements, subjects ingest encapsulated high quality histidine for four continuous weeks at graded doses of 4, 8 and 12 g/day. A forth dose at 16 g/day is assessed if no adverse outcomes are observed for the three graded doses. Histidine doses are suggested based on experience with other amino acids (relative difference of average intake and metabolic limits). Each dose is followed by a 3-week minimum recovery period. During the recovery period, subjects will continue to be monitored (vitals and weight) but no supplementation is consumed. At the conclusion of each washout period, before the start of the next dose, subjects provide a blood sample, vitals (blood pressure and heart rate), weight, 4-day diet record, sleep log, hunger and satiety VAS, mood VAS, and physical activity monitoring.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in concentration of zinc in mg/ml</measure>
    <time_frame>at week 0 and 4 of each dose</time_frame>
    <description>The safety of histidine supplementation at each dose is monitored through blood markers of zinc</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in concentration of liver enzymes (ALT, ALP, and AST) in Units per Liter</measure>
    <time_frame>at weeks 0 (washout), 2 and 4 of each dose</time_frame>
    <description>The safety of histidine supplementation at each dose is monitored through circulating liver enzymes</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in body weight in kilograms</measure>
    <time_frame>at weeks 0 (washout), 2 and 4 of each dose</time_frame>
    <description>The safety of histidine supplementation at each dose is monitored through changes in weight</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in concentration of total protein and albumin in g/dl</measure>
    <time_frame>at weeks 2 and 4 of each dose</time_frame>
    <description>The safety of histidine supplementation at each dose is monitored through circulating total protein and albumin</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in concentration of blood urea nitrogen, Creatinine, bilirubin and glucose each in mg/gL</measure>
    <time_frame>at weeks 0 (washout), 2 and 4 of each dose</time_frame>
    <description>The safety of histidine supplementation at each dose is monitored through circulating blood urea nitrogen, Creatinine, bilirubin and glucose</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in concentration of C-reactive protein mg/L</measure>
    <time_frame>at weeks 0 (washout), 2 and 4 of each dose</time_frame>
    <description>The safety of histidine supplementation at each dose is monitored through circulating CRP</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>HgbA1c in %</measure>
    <time_frame>at week 4 of each dose</time_frame>
    <description>The safety of histidine supplementation at each dose is monitored through circulating HgbA1c</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in heart rate in beats per minute</measure>
    <time_frame>weeks 0 (baseline and washout), 1, 2, 3, and 4 of each dose</time_frame>
    <description>The safety of histidine supplementation at each dose is monitored through heart rate</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in systolic and diastolic blood pressures in mmHG</measure>
    <time_frame>weeks 0 (baseline and washout), 1, 2, 3, and 4 of each dose</time_frame>
    <description>The safety of histidine supplementation at each dose is monitored through blood pressure</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in hours of sleep</measure>
    <time_frame>week 0 to 4 of each dose</time_frame>
    <description>The effects of histidine will be assessed with changes in sleep pattern as determined using a subjective measurement tool</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in dietary intake of energy, macronutrients, and amino acids measured in kcals and g/day with 4 day food record</measure>
    <time_frame>week 0 to 4 of each dose</time_frame>
    <description>The effects of histidine will be assessed with changes dietary intake as determined with 4 day food records</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in physical activity measured in steps per day</measure>
    <time_frame>week 0 to 4 of each dose</time_frame>
    <description>The effects of histidine will be assessed with changes in physical activity patterns using an Actigraph</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in subjective mood measured in arbitrary units</measure>
    <time_frame>week 0 to 4 of each dose</time_frame>
    <description>The effects of histidine will be assessed with changes in mood as determined using a subjective visual analog scale. 100 mm line is anchored by two opposing statements. The higher number the greater the mood.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in subjective desire to eat measured in arbitrary units</measure>
    <time_frame>week 0 to 4 of each dose</time_frame>
    <description>The effects of histidine will be assessed with changes in desire to eat will be determined using a visual analog scale. 100 mm line is anchored by two opposing statements. The greater the number the stronger the desire.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Healthy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>4 g / day histidine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>subjects ingest encapsulated high quality histidine for four continuous weeks at 4 g/day.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>8 g / day histidine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>subjects ingest encapsulated high quality histidine for four continuous weeks at 8 g/day</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>12 g /day histidine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>subjects ingest encapsulated high quality histidine for four continuous weeks at 12 g/day</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>16 g /day histidine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>subjects ingest encapsulated high quality histidine for four continuous weeks at 16 g/day. The 16 g /day dose will be administered if no adverse effects are observed for doses 4-12 g/day</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Histidine</intervention_name>
    <description>ingestion of encapsulated high quality histidine for four continuous weeks followed by a washout period of 3 weeks</description>
    <arm_group_label>12 g /day histidine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>16 g /day histidine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>4 g / day histidine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>8 g / day histidine</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        • healthy young males and females aged 21-50 y.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  A body-mass index (BMI) &lt;19.9 kg/m2 or &gt; 29.9 kg/m2

          -  taking/on immunosuppressive medications or prescription anti-coagulation therapy

          -  pregnancy

          -  breastfeeding

          -  musculoskeletal disorder

          -  diabetes

          -  alcoholism (&gt;11 drinks per week for women, &gt;14 drinks per week for men) or other drug
             addiction

          -  acute illness

          -  inability to travel to Cornell University campus

          -  A blood pressure at or above 140/90

          -  For individuals desiring to participate in the optional biopsy, a history of a
             negative or allergic reaction to local anesthetic is an exclusion criteria
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>21 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>50 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Human Metabolic Research Unit</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ithaca</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>14853</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 30, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 25, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 29, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 25, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 25, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 29, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Cornell University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Anna Thalacker-Mercer</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

