<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04143698</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>1388902</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04143698</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Reusable Versus Disposable Duodenoscopes for ERCP</brief_title>
  <official_title>Randomized Trial Comparing Reusable and Disposable Duodenoscopes for ERCP</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>AdventHealth</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>AdventHealth</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The aim of this randomized trial is to evaluate the technical aspects of disposable
      duodenoscopes and to compare the technical outcomes between the disposable (single-use) and
      reusable duodenoscopes.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Given the recent reports on infection outbreaks, including carbapenem-resistant
      Enterobacteriaceae (CRE), caused by contaminated duodenoscopes used at endoscopic retrograde
      cholangiopancreatography (ERCP), a disposable (single-use) duodenoscope (Exalt, Single-Use
      Duodenoscope, Boston Scientific Corporation, Natick, MA) has been developed to circumvent
      this issue. However, there are currently no data on the technical features and outcomes of
      disposable duodenoscopes, in comparison with reusable duodenoscopes.

      The aim of this randomized trial is therefore to evaluate the technical aspects of disposable
      duodenoscopes and to compare the technical outcomes between the two duodenoscope types.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 24, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 6, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 20, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Cannulation</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day</time_frame>
    <description>The ease of cannulation of the desired duct (biliary or pancreatic), as measured by the total number of cannulation attempts to achieve successful cannulation of the desired duct.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Ease of passage of duodenoscope and imaging and mechanical function of the duodenoscope</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day</time_frame>
    <description>Ease of maneuverability of the duodenoscope to reach the major papilla, the imaging and mechanical function of the duodenoscope, measured on a five point scale with 1 being the easiest and 5 being the most difficult.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Ease of completion of interventions</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day</time_frame>
    <description>Ease of completion of each step of the ERCP procedure, measured on a 5 point scale with 1 being the easiest and 5 being the most difficult.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of use of advanced cannulation techniques</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day</time_frame>
    <description>Need for use of advanced cannulation techniques</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of cross-over</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day</time_frame>
    <description>Rate of cross-over to the alternate duodenoscope for completion of the procedure</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time taken for cannulation</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day</time_frame>
    <description>Time taken for cannulation</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Total duration of the procedure</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day</time_frame>
    <description>Total duration of the procedure</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>7 days and 30 days</time_frame>
    <description>Assessment of AEs and SAEs</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">98</enrollment>
  <condition>Endoscopic Retrograde Cholangiopancreatography</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Disposable (single-use) duodenoscope</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>This group will be using the disposable (single-use) duodenoscope during endoscopic retrograde cholangiopancreatography (ERCP).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Reusable duodenoscope</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>This group will be using the reusable duodenoscope during endoscopic retrograde cholangiopancreatography (ERCP).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>endoscopic retrograde cholangiopancreatography</intervention_name>
    <description>The duodenoscope will be passed to the duodenum in the standard fashion. Once the papilla has been identified in the duodenum, cannulation of the desired duct will be performed in the standard fashion, with the type of accessories used left to the discretion of the individual endoscopist performing the procedure. If cannulation is considered difficult, advanced cannulation techniques can be used per standard of care at the discretion of the individual endoscopist. The types of accessories used will be left to the discretion of the individual endoscopist and will be dependent on procedure indication and personal preference. Cross-over to the alternate duodenoscope type can be performed at any time if the desired technical maneuver cannot be performed with the designated duodenoscope.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Disposable (single-use) duodenoscope</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Reusable duodenoscope</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>ERCP</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Age ≥ 18 years old

          2. Patients with native papilla

          3. Requiring an ERCP procedure for biliary or pancreatic duct disorder, based on clinical
             symptoms and radiological findings at computed tomography or magnetic resonance
             cholangiopancreatography

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Age &lt;18 years old

          2. Unable to obtain informed consent

          3. Pregnancy

          4. Altered upper gastrointestinal surgical anatomy

          5. Patients with percutaneous transhepatic biliary drainage catheters

          6. Prior history of ERCP
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Shyam Varadarajulu, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>AdventHealth Orlando</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>AdventHealth Orlando</name>
      <address>
        <city>Orlando</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>32803</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rauwers AW, Voor In 't Holt AF, Buijs JG, de Groot W, Hansen BE, Bruno MJ, Vos MC. High prevalence rate of digestive tract bacteria in duodenoscopes: a nationwide study. Gut. 2018 Sep;67(9):1637-1645. doi: 10.1136/gutjnl-2017-315082. Epub 2018 Apr 10.</citation>
    <PMID>29636382</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kim S, Russell D, Mohamadnejad M, Makker J, Sedarat A, Watson RR, Yang S, Hemarajata P, Humphries R, Rubin Z, Muthusamy VR. Risk factors associated with the transmission of carbapenem-resistant Enterobacteriaceae via contaminated duodenoscopes. Gastrointest Endosc. 2016 Jun;83(6):1121-9. doi: 10.1016/j.gie.2016.03.790. Epub 2016 Mar 16.</citation>
    <PMID>26993149</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Alrabaa SF, Nguyen P, Sanderson R, Baluch A, Sandin RL, Kelker D, Karlapalem C, Thompson P, Sams K, Martin S, Montero J, Greene JN. Early identification and control of carbapenemase-producing Klebsiella pneumoniae, originating from contaminated endoscopic equipment. Am J Infect Control. 2013 Jun;41(6):562-4. doi: 10.1016/j.ajic.2012.07.008. Epub 2012 Nov 18.</citation>
    <PMID>23171594</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Epstein L, Hunter JC, Arwady MA, Tsai V, Stein L, Gribogiannis M, Frias M, Guh AY, Laufer AS, Black S, Pacilli M, Moulton-Meissner H, Rasheed JK, Avillan JJ, Kitchel B, Limbago BM, MacCannell D, Lonsway D, Noble-Wang J, Conway J, Conover C, Vernon M, Kallen AJ. New Delhi metallo-β-lactamase-producing carbapenem-resistant Escherichia coli associated with exposure to duodenoscopes. JAMA. 2014 Oct 8;312(14):1447-55. doi: 10.1001/jama.2014.12720.</citation>
    <PMID>25291580</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cotton PB, Eisen G, Romagnuolo J, Vargo J, Baron T, Tarnasky P, Schutz S, Jacobson B, Bott C, Petersen B. Grading the complexity of endoscopic procedures: results of an ASGE working party. Gastrointest Endosc. 2011 May;73(5):868-74. doi: 10.1016/j.gie.2010.12.036. Epub 2011 Mar 5.</citation>
    <PMID>21377673</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sahar N, La Selva D, Gluck M, Gan SI, Irani S, Larsen M, Ross AS, Kozarek RA. The ASGE grading system for ERCP can predict success and complication rates in a tertiary referral hospital. Surg Endosc. 2019 Feb;33(2):448-453. doi: 10.1007/s00464-018-6317-7. Epub 2018 Jul 9.</citation>
    <PMID>29987568</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Testoni PA, Mariani A, Aabakken L, Arvanitakis M, Bories E, Costamagna G, Devière J, Dinis-Ribeiro M, Dumonceau JM, Giovannini M, Gyokeres T, Hafner M, Halttunen J, Hassan C, Lopes L, Papanikolaou IS, Tham TC, Tringali A, van Hooft J, Williams EJ. Papillary cannulation and sphincterotomy techniques at ERCP: European Society of Gastrointestinal Endoscopy (ESGE) Clinical Guideline. Endoscopy. 2016 Jul;48(7):657-83. doi: 10.1055/s-0042-108641. Epub 2016 Jun 14.</citation>
    <PMID>27299638</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Liao WC, Angsuwatcharakon P, Isayama H, Dhir V, Devereaux B, Khor CJ, Ponnudurai R, Lakhtakia S, Lee DK, Ratanachu-Ek T, Yasuda I, Dy FT, Ho SH, Makmun D, Liang HL, Draganov PV, Rerknimitr R, Wang HP. International consensus recommendations for difficult biliary access. Gastrointest Endosc. 2017 Feb;85(2):295-304. doi: 10.1016/j.gie.2016.09.037. Epub 2016 Oct 5. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>27720741</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bassi M, Luigiano C, Ghersi S, Fabbri C, Gibiino G, Balzani L, Iabichino G, Tringali A, Manta R, Mutignani M, Cennamo V. A multicenter randomized trial comparing the use of touch versus no-touch guidewire technique for deep biliary cannulation: the TNT study. Gastrointest Endosc. 2018 Jan;87(1):196-201. doi: 10.1016/j.gie.2017.05.008. Epub 2017 May 18.</citation>
    <PMID>28527615</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hwang JC, Yoo BM, Yang MJ, Lee YK, Lee JY, Lim K, Noh CK, Cho HJ, Kim SS, Kim JH. A prospective randomized study of loop-tip versus straight-tip guidewire in wire-guided biliary cannulation. Surg Endosc. 2018 Apr;32(4):1708-1713. doi: 10.1007/s00464-017-5851-z. Epub 2017 Sep 15.</citation>
    <PMID>28916891</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bassan MS, Sundaralingam P, Fanning SB, Lau J, Menon J, Ong E, Rerknimitr R, Seo DW, Teo EK, Wang HP, Reddy DN, Goh KL, Bourke MJ. The impact of wire caliber on ERCP outcomes: a multicenter randomized controlled trial of 0.025-inch and 0.035-inch guidewires. Gastrointest Endosc. 2018 Jun;87(6):1454-1460. doi: 10.1016/j.gie.2017.11.037. Epub 2018 Jan 6.</citation>
    <PMID>29317269</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Buxbaum J, Leonor P, Tung J, Lane C, Sahakian A, Laine L. Randomized Trial of Endoscopist-Controlled vs. Assistant-Controlled Wire-Guided Cannulation of the Bile Duct. Am J Gastroenterol. 2016 Dec;111(12):1841-1847. doi: 10.1038/ajg.2016.268. Epub 2016 Jul 5.</citation>
    <PMID>27377519</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 5, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 28, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 29, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 22, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 22, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 23, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>duodenoscopes; ERCP</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

