<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04142177</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2009</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04142177</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Sequential and Comparative Evaluation of Pain Treatment Effectiveness Response</brief_title>
  <acronym>SCEPTER</acronym>
  <official_title>CSP #2009 - Sequential and Comparative Evaluation of Pain Treatment Effectiveness Response: The SCEPTER Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>VA Office of Research and Development</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>VA Office of Research and Development</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Chronic low back pain (cLBP) is common. Most Americans will have at least one episode of low
      back pain in their lifetimes. Approximately 50% of all US Veterans have chronic pain, and
      CLBP is the most common type of pain in this population. This study will use a sequential
      randomized, pragmatic, 2-step comparative effectiveness study design. The main goal is to
      identify the best approach for treating cLBP using commonly recommended non-surgical and
      non-pharmacological options. The first step compares continued care and active monitoring
      (CCAM) to internet-based pain self-management (Pain EASE) and an enhanced physical therapy
      intervention that combines Pain EASE with tailored exercise and physical activity. Patients
      who do not have a significant decrease in pain interference (a functional outcome) in Step 1
      and those desiring additional treatment will be randomized in Step 2 to yoga, spinal
      manipulation therapy (SMT), or therapist-delivered cognitive behavioral therapy (CBT).
      Participants proceeding to randomization in Step 2 will be allowed to exclude up to one of
      the three Step 2 treatments based on their preferences. The investigators' primary hypothesis
      for the first treatment step is that an enhanced physical therapy intervention that combines
      pain self-management education with a tailored exercise program will reduce pain interference
      greater than internet-based pain self-management alone or CCAM in Veterans with cLBP. The
      primary outcome is change in pain interference at 3 months, measured using the Brief Pain
      Inventory (BPI) pain interference subscale. Study participants will be followed for one year
      after initiation of their final study treatments to assess the durability of treatment
      effects. The study plans to randomize 2529 patients across 20 centers.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Chronic low back pain (cLBP) is common. The point prevalence of low back pain in the US is
      about 25%, and the majority of Americans will have at least one episode of low back pain in
      their lifetimes. Approximately 50% of all US Veterans have chronic pain, and cLBP is the most
      common type of pain in this population. Low back pain is the second most common condition
      leading patients to seek a physician's care. In addition, cLBP is costly. Healthcare
      expenditure for low back pain in the US is greater than $30 billion per year, and total
      expenditures including the cost of disability approach $100 billion per year. In fact, low
      back pain is the most common cause of work-related disability and is a major cause of
      service- connected disability amongst US Veterans. Making matters worse, the US is in the
      midst of a growing opioid abuse epidemic having its roots in the lack of understanding of how
      to effectively treat cLBP and other common forms of acute and chronic pain.

      Using a sequential randomized, pragmatic, 2-step comparative effectiveness study design, the
      main goal is to identify the optimal approach to cLBP treatment employing commonly
      recommended non-surgical, non-pharmacological options. Options for treatment in this trial
      were selected based on the VA's stepped-care model for the treatment of chronic pain,
      availability of treatments, controversies in current clinical practice, and the surveyed
      preferences of both Veterans with cLBP and VA healthcare providers. The implementation of
      study results has been kept closely in mind, and stakeholder input has been incorporated.

      The first step compares continued care and active monitoring arm (CCAM) to internet-based
      pain self-management (Pain EASE) and an enhanced physical therapy intervention that combines
      Pain EASE with tailored exercise and physical activity. The utility of tailored exercise
      requiring physical therapist guidance added to internet-based self-management has not been
      examined. A CCAM arm is included in this step to definitively assess the effectiveness of
      these initial treatment options. Patients failing to achieve clinically significant
      reductions in pain interference (a functional outcome) in Step 1 and those desiring
      additional treatment will be randomized in Step 2 to yoga, spinal manipulation therapy (SMT),
      or therapist-delivered cognitive behavioral therapy (CBT). These options appear in consensus
      guidelines although little information is available to help patients and providers select the
      most effective option. Each option has a distinct theoretical basis for effectiveness with
      yoga described as a mind-body therapy, SMT as a technique to adjust the structural
      relationships of the spine, and CBT as a psychological or behavioral approach. While the
      literature suggests approximate clinical equipoise between these treatments, costs, side
      effects, access to specific options and patient/provider acceptance may differ significantly.
      Participants proceeding to randomization in Step 2 will be allowed to exclude up to one of
      the three Step 2 treatments based on their preferences.

      The investigators' primary hypothesis corresponding to the first treatment step is that an
      enhanced physical therapy intervention that combines pain self-management education with a
      tailored exercise program will reduce pain interference greater than internet-based pain
      self-management alone or CCAM in Veterans with cLBP. For the second step, the study has been
      powered to detect clinically meaningful pairwise differences among the three treatments. The
      primary outcome is change in pain interference at 3 months, measured using the Brief Pain
      Inventory (BPI) pain interference subscale. This is a widely accepted functional outcome in
      musculoskeletal pain trials and emphasizes an endpoint important to patients, providers and
      healthcare management systems. Study participants will be followed for one year after
      initiation of their final study treatments to assess the durability of treatment effects.

      The investigators will leverage the power of this large study and maximize its impact by
      incorporating additional outcome measures as recommended by the Initiative on Methods,
      Measurement, and Pain Assessment in Clinical Trials (IMMPACT) consortium and other pain
      trials consensus groups. These secondary outcomes include pain severity, physical
      functioning, depression, anxiety, fatigue, sleep, global impression of change, and quality of
      life. The investigators will evaluate the impact of patient characteristics, treatment
      preferences and expectations on study outcomes as these variables have been identified in
      smaller studies to modify treatment response. To derive information rapidly translatable to
      changes in VA care, the investigators will collect information critical for implementation of
      the treatment strategies under study. Key implementation factors will include treatment
      fidelity, treatment adherence, patient acceptance, provider acceptance, logistical
      feasibility, and resource requirements. Finally, a carefully designed costs and downstream
      budget impact aim will provide additional practical information for clinical managers and
      policy makers related to non-pharmacological treatments for cLBP.

      The study will involve diverse VA centers with respect to geographical region, racial
      characteristics of the population served and facility size. The study plans to randomize 2529
      patients across 20 centers. Preliminary site surveys indicate a high level of enthusiasm for
      the project. In addition, a query of the VA's Corporate Data Warehouse (CDW) identified more
      than 850,000 potential cLBP study subjects receiving regular care through VA. Twenty-five VA
      medical centers have more than 10,000 potentially eligible patients underscoring the high
      prevalence of cLBP. The investigators' pragmatic trial design will incorporate broad
      eligibility criteria.

      Chronic low back pain is an enormous problem for the VA, the United States and many other
      countries. This study will provide definitive information concerning the effectiveness,
      costs, acceptability, and implementation of several commonly used, patient-preferred,
      non-pharmacological treatment options. All the selected treatment options carry relatively
      low levels of risk, are guideline congruent, and are consistent with stepped-care models of
      healthcare delivery used by the VA and other healthcare organizations. The impact on VA
      healthcare is expected to be large and immediate.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">April 1, 2021</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 11, 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 7, 2024</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Sequential Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>sequential randomized, pragmatic, 2-step comparative effectiveness study design</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>This is a single-blinded study. The participants, Local Site Investigators (LSIs) and Site Coordinators will have the information on participant treatment assignment. Central Research Assistants (RAs) who collect primary and secondary outcome measures over the phone will be blinded to treatment assignment. The study team who manage the day-to-day study operations (including Study Chairs, National Study Coordinator, and study team members at Cooperative Studies Program Coordinating Centers [CSPCC] and Clinical Research Pharmacy Coordinating Centers [CRPCC] may have information on specific individual participant treatment assignment only when the information is needed to perform their work.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Brief Pain Inventory (BPI) Interference scale</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months post-treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Linear mixed effects models will be used to compare the primary outcome (change in pain interference score from pre-treatment to 3 months after treatment) between Step 1 treatments in all participants and between Step 2 treatments in Step 1 non-responders. The mixed effects model will include treatment and study site as fixed effects, and therapist as random effects. For the comparison of Step 1 treatments, the model will also include a fixed effect for opioid use at study entry.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>6</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">2529</enrollment>
  <condition>Chronic Low Back Pain</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Internet-based pain self-management program</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Internet-based treatment (Step 1 Treatment)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Enhanced Physical Therapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Intervention that combines the internet-based pain self-management program with tailored exercise and physical activity guided by a physical therapist (Step 1 treatment)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Continued Care and Active Monitoring (CCAM)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>CCAM will not be standardized keeping in line with the pragmatic nature of this trial. CCAM may be variable across sites and for individual participants reflecting de facto clinical practice for cLBP. Clinical practice may involve pharmacological and non-pharmacological treatments for cLBP. Current analgesics (including opioids, acetaminophen, NSAIDs, topical analgesics (capsaicin), serotonin-norepinephrine reuptake inhibitors (SNRIs), tricyclic antidepressants, skeletal muscle relaxants, and alpha-2-delta ligands (gabapentin-like drugs)) and non-pharmacological treatments may be continued by participants. CCAM participants will be encouraged to discuss pain problems with their treating physician, but not begin new treatments if possible. Patients will specifically be discouraged from starting CBT, chiropractic, or yoga. Other than this, there will be no attempt by study personnel to influence pain management (Step 1 Treatment)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cognitive Behavioral Therapy (CBT)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants randomized to CBT in Step 2 will receive face-to-face treatment with a trained therapist using the VA's CBT-chronic pain (CBT-CP) protocol involving one planning session and 9 treatment sessions (10 total) over 3 months (Step 2 Treatment).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Spinal Manipulation Therapy (SMT)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>After examination by a qualified Doctor of Chiropractic (DC), a SMT intervention consisting of up to 10 sessions over 3 months will be designed focusing on spinal manipulation and/or mobilization of the lower thoracic, lumbar and/or sacroiliac joints. Adjunctive use of myofascial and/or stretching techniques are allowed as they are commonly used along with SMT, and can be considered a standard accompaniment to SMT (Step 2 Treatment).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Yoga</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The Yoga for Veterans with cLBP program consists of up to 10 weekly, 60-minute instructor-led sessions along with 15-20 minutes of yoga practiced at home each non-session day. The initial session is 75 minutes (15 minutes longer than the other sessions). The yoga program can be considered classical hatha yoga with influences from Iyengar and Viniyoga yoga. These styles emphasize modifications and adaptations including the use of props such as straps and blocks to minimize the risk of injury and make the poses accessible to people with health problems and limitations (Iyengar, 1979). The instructor leads participants through a series of 23 yoga poses (32 total variations) at a slow-moderate pace (Step 2 Treatment).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pain EASE</intervention_name>
    <description>The internet-based pain self-management program consists of open access to the Pain EASE program (Pain E-health for Activity, Skills, and Education) for the duration of participation in the trial. Pain EASE has 10 pain coping skill modules: pain education, setting personal goals, planning meaningful activities, physical activity (stretching, body mechanics, and a pedometer-based walking program), relaxation, developing healthy thinking patterns, pacing and problem-solving, improving sleep, effective communication, and future planning.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Enhanced Physical Therapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Internet-based pain self-management program</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Tailored exercise</intervention_name>
    <description>Findings from the initial examination and the Keele STarT Back Screening Tool (Hill, et al., 2011) will be used by the physical therapist to guide and tailor the intervention to individual participants which will involve up to 8 treatment sessions with ongoing home exercise. For most participants, exercise and physical activity will focus on walking in addition to motor control and stabilization exercises for the low back with flexibility exercises when lumbar spine stiffness is present.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Enhanced Physical Therapy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Continued Care and Active Monitoring</intervention_name>
    <description>CCAM will not be standardized keeping in line with the pragmatic nature of this trial. CCAM may be variable across sites and for individual participants reflecting de facto clinical practice for cLBP. Clinical practice may involve pharmacological and non-pharmacological treatments for cLBP. Current analgesics (including opioids, acetaminophen, NSAIDs, topical analgesics (capsaicin), serotonin-norepinephrine reuptake inhibitors (SNRIs), tricyclic antidepressants, skeletal muscle relaxants, and alpha-2-delta ligands (gabapentin-like drugs)) and non-pharmacological treatments may be continued by participants. CCAM participants will be encouraged to discuss pain problems with their treating physician, but not begin new treatments if possible. Patients will specifically be discouraged from starting CBT, chiropractic, or yoga. Other than this, there will be no attempt by study personnel to influence pain management.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Continued Care and Active Monitoring (CCAM)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cognitive Behavioral Therapy (CBT)</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants randomized to CBT in Step 2 will receive face-to-face treatment with a trained therapist using the VA's CBT-chronic pain (CBT-CP) protocol involving one planning session and 9 treatment sessions (10 total) over 3 months. The VA's CBT-CP protocol consists of 11 core CBT-CP modules that can be completed in up to 10 sessions. Weekly, individual sessions of 45-50 minutes are recommended, although it is recognized that bi-weekly or other arrangements are often made to fit practical needs.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cognitive Behavioral Therapy (CBT)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Spinal Manipulation Therapy (SMT)</intervention_name>
    <description>After examination by a qualified Doctor of Chiropractic (DC), a SMT intervention consisting of up to 10 sessions over 3 months will be designed focusing on spinal manipulation and/or mobilization of the lower thoracic, lumbar and/or sacroiliac joints. Adjunctive use of myofascial and/or stretching techniques are allowed as they are commonly used along with SMT, and can be considered a standard accompaniment to SMT.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Spinal Manipulation Therapy (SMT)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Yoga</intervention_name>
    <description>The Yoga for Veterans with cLBP program consists of up to 10 weekly, 60-minute instructor-led sessions along with 15-20 minutes of yoga practiced at home each non-session day. The initial session is 75 minutes (15 minutes longer than the other sessions). The yoga program can be considered classical hatha yoga with influences from Iyengar and Viniyoga yoga. These styles emphasize modifications and adaptations including the use of props such as straps and blocks to minimize the risk of injury and make the poses accessible to people with health problems and limitations (Iyengar, 1979). The instructor leads participants through a series of 23 yoga poses (32 total variations) at a slow-moderate pace.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Yoga</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        To be eligible to participate in this study, an individual must meet all the following
        criteria:

          1. Chronic low back pain current and present for at least 6 months;

          2. Moderate-severe average daily back pain severity (Numeric Rating Scale (NRS) greater
             than or equal to 4 and no greater than 10);

          3. Moderate-severe pain-related disability (Roland Morris Disability Questionnaire score
             greater than or equal to 7);

          4. Age 18 years or older, either sex, any racial or ethnic background;

          5. Able to comprehend and willing to sign the study informed consent form;

          6. Able to attend in-person treatment sessions;

          7. Anticipate continuing care at the enrolling VA for the period of the study;

          8. Stable access to the internet at home, work, or other location (e.g. mobile phone).

        Exclusion Criteria:

        An individual who meets any of the following criteria will be excluded from participation
        in this study:

          1. Currently enrolled in any other interventional study unless exempted by CSP;

          2. Acute or chronic illness that would prevent the Veteran from receiving study
             treatments offered (e.g., uncontrolled hypertension, recent myocardial infarction
             within the last 6 months, unstable angina, acute congestive heart failure);

          3. Neurological impairment related to disease of the spine or other causes preventing
             participation in any of the treatment modalities under study;

          4. Current or recent (last 3 months) treatment involving Cognitive Behavioral Therapy,
             Spinal manipulation therapy, or Yoga;

          5. Current severe alcohol or substance abuse use disorder;

          6. Severe psychiatric illness (e.g. current psychosis, current suicidal ideation, or
             psychiatric illness requiring hospitalization within the last 6 months);

          7. Undergoing evaluation for back surgery or planned back surgery;

          8. Cognitive or severe hearing or visual impairment preventing participation in treatment
             options or outcome measure assessments;

          9. Pregnancy;

         10. Refusal to provide written consent.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>David J Clark, PhD MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>VA Palo Alto Health Care System, Palo Alto, CA</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Matthew J. Bair, MD MS</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Richard L. Roudebush VA Medical Center, Indianapolis, IN</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Colleen M Fitzsimmons</last_name>
    <phone>(650) 493-5000</phone>
    <phone_ext>21123</phone_ext>
    <email>Colleen.Fitzsimmons@va.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Phoenix VA Health Care System, Phoenix, AZ</name>
      <address>
        <city>Phoenix</city>
        <state>Arizona</state>
        <zip>85012</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Heather Okvat, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>602-277-5551</phone>
      <phone_ext>2449</phone_ext>
      <email>heather.okvat@va.gov</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>VA Loma Linda Healthcare System, Loma Linda, CA</name>
      <address>
        <city>Loma Linda</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>92357</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Thomas Edell, MD</last_name>
      <phone>909-801-5127</phone>
      <email>Thomas.Edell@va.gov</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>VA Long Beach Healthcare System, Long Beach, CA</name>
      <address>
        <city>Long Beach</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90822</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Patricia Nance, MD</last_name>
      <phone>562-826-8000</phone>
      <phone_ext>4288</phone_ext>
      <email>patricia.nance@va.gov</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>VA Palo Alto Health Care System, Palo Alto, CA</name>
      <address>
        <city>Palo Alto</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94304-1290</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Mitchell J Wong, MD</last_name>
      <phone>650-493-5000</phone>
      <phone_ext>65529</phone_ext>
      <email>Mitchell.Wong@va.gov</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>David J Clark, PhD MD</last_name>
      <role>Study Chair</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Bay Pines VA Healthcare System, Pay Pines, FL</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bay Pines</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33744</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ryan Diana, DC</last_name>
      <phone>570-233-0931</phone>
      <email>ryan.diana@va.gov</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Orlando VA Medical Center, Orlando, FL</name>
      <address>
        <city>Orlando</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>32803</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Adam Golden, MD</last_name>
      <phone>407-631-4011</phone>
      <email>adam.golden@va.gov</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Atlanta VA Medical and Rehab Center, Decatur, GA</name>
      <address>
        <city>Decatur</city>
        <state>Georgia</state>
        <zip>30033</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jerry Kalangara, MD</last_name>
      <phone>404-329-2201</phone>
      <email>jerry.kalangara1@va.gov</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Richard L. Roudebush VA Medical Center, Indianapolis, IN</name>
      <address>
        <city>Indianapolis</city>
        <state>Indiana</state>
        <zip>46202-2884</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Robert B Barber, MD</last_name>
      <phone>317-850-8143</phone>
      <email>Robert.Barber3@va.gov</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Baltimore VA Medical Center VA Maryland Health Care System, Baltimore, MD</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21201</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Beth Hogans, MD</last_name>
      <phone>410-605-7000</phone>
      <email>beth.hogans@va.gov</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>VA Boston Healthcare System Jamaica Plain Campus, Jamaica Plain, MA</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02130</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Erica Scioli, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>857-364-5696</phone>
      <email>ericarose.scioli@va.gov</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>St. Louis VA Medical Center John Cochran Division, St. Louis, MO</name>
      <address>
        <city>Saint Louis</city>
        <state>Missouri</state>
        <zip>63106</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jason Napuli, DC</last_name>
      <phone>727-771-5975</phone>
      <email>jason.napuli@va.gov</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>VA Southern Nevada Healthcare System, North Las Vegas, NV</name>
      <address>
        <city>Las Vegas</city>
        <state>Nevada</state>
        <zip>89106</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Trevor Nogueira, MD</last_name>
      <phone>702-791-9000</phone>
      <email>trevor.nogueira@va.gov</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Asheville VA Medical Center, Asheville, NC</name>
      <address>
        <city>Asheville</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>28805</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>James Michalets, MD</last_name>
      <phone>828-298-7911</phone>
      <phone_ext>5286</phone_ext>
      <email>james.michalets@va.gov</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Salisbury W.G. (Bill) Hefner VA Medical Center, Salisbury, NC</name>
      <address>
        <city>Salisbury</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>28144</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>James Plunkett, MD</last_name>
      <phone>704-638-9000</phone>
      <phone_ext>3066</phone_ext>
      <email>james.plunkett@va.gov</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>VA Portland Health Care System, Portland, OR</name>
      <address>
        <city>Portland</city>
        <state>Oregon</state>
        <zip>97239</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Stephanie K Liu, MD</last_name>
      <phone>646-591-7011</phone>
      <email>stephanie.liu@va.gov</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Tennessee Valley Healthcare System Nashville Campus, Nashville, TN</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nashville</city>
        <state>Tennessee</state>
        <zip>37212-2637</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jason Cook, DC</last_name>
      <phone>615-225-2842</phone>
      <email>jason.cook2@va.gov</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>South Texas Health Care System, San Antonio, TX</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Antonio</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>78229</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>John Finnell, MPH</last_name>
      <phone>210-617-5300</phone>
      <phone_ext>19327</phone_ext>
      <email>john.finnell@va.gov</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>VA Salt Lake City Health Care System, Salt Lake City, UT</name>
      <address>
        <city>Salt Lake City</city>
        <state>Utah</state>
        <zip>84148</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Scott Swasey, MD</last_name>
      <phone>801-582-1565</phone>
      <phone_ext>2838</phone_ext>
      <email>scott.swasey@va.gov</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hampton VA Medical Center, Hampton, VA</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hampton</city>
        <state>Virginia</state>
        <zip>23667</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ajay Manhapra, MD</last_name>
      <phone>757-722-9961</phone>
      <phone_ext>5916</phone_ext>
      <email>ajay.manhapra@va.gov</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hunter Holmes McGuire VA Medical Center, Richmond, VA</name>
      <address>
        <city>Richmond</city>
        <state>Virginia</state>
        <zip>23249</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>David Drake, MD</last_name>
      <phone>804-675-5188</phone>
      <email>david.drake4@va.gov</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 25, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 25, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 29, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 23, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 23, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 25, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>chronic low back pain</keyword>
  <keyword>severe low back pain</keyword>
  <keyword>pain</keyword>
  <keyword>non-pharmacological treatment</keyword>
  <keyword>self-management</keyword>
  <keyword>physical therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>exercise</keyword>
  <keyword>yoga</keyword>
  <keyword>cognitive behavioral therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>spinal manipulation therapy</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Back Pain</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Low Back Pain</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

