<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04140006</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>034118</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04140006</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Efficacy of Antiresorptive and Bone Forming Material on Dental Implants</brief_title>
  <official_title>Evaluation of Topical Application of Alendronate Sodium In-situ Gel and Recombinant Human Bone Morphogenic Protein 2 on Dental Implant Stability and Crestal Bone Level: A Randomized Controlled Clinical Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Baghdad</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Baghdad</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Insertion of a metal implant is considered one of the most common surgeries for fracture
      treatment, joint replacement, and dental implants. The success rate of these implants depends
      on their fixation which is in turn related primarily on the strength of the bone holding
      them. Studies evaluating the influence of local application of antiresorptive drugs, like
      bisphosphonates, on implanted endoprostheses whether orthopedic or dental is increasing
      annually with more and more experimental studies as well as clinical trials worldwide. On the
      other hand implants that release medications that enhance bone formation will lead to
      improved implant fixation and success. The objective of this study was to evaluate the effect
      of topical application of alendronate sodium gel and recombinant human bone morphogenic
      protein 2 on dental implant stability and crestal bone level.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Bisphosphonates (BPs), which are so called because they have two phosphonate (PO3) groups,
      are structurally similar to natural pyrophosphate (PP), a normal product of human metabolism
      that has a calcium chelating property. They are used to treat bone metastases, osteoporosis,
      Paget's disease, and other skeletal disorders.

      During bone remodeling, osteoclast bone resorptive action is impeded by BPs which are
      released into the resorption lacunae. These cells take up BPs from resorption lacunae and the
      BPs then trigger the osteoclasts to undergo apoptosis. It has been found that an adjunct
      treatment of implant site with BPs solution might be beneficial to initial osseointegration
      of immediately or delayed loaded dental implants without interfering significantly with
      peri-implant bone remodeling over time.

      Oral or intravenous administrations are the classical BPs treatment modalities with many
      studies show their positive effect on peri-implant bone. More efficient delivery systems to
      the target sites have been investigated to minimize BPs side effects and alter their
      biodistribution in order to improve their bioavailability; one of those new systems is
      topical application. Topical application of BPs enhances osseointegration, promote
      implant-bone contact and increase the amount of bone peripheral to dental implants. Minimal
      amounts of bisphosphonates was found to improve early implant fixation and to be less prone
      to cause osteonecrosis of the jaw, this might lead to new possibilities for orthopedic
      surgery in osteoporotic bones and for dental implants with a smaller risk of such
      complication in comparison with systemic treatment.

      In order to maximize anabolism and minimize catabolism, new coating strategies have been
      evolved to enhanced bone formation onto the implant surface which is more desired than only
      reduce bone resorption around it. So to improve implant osseointegration, a dedicated
      drug-loading ability to locally target bone disorders has been developed to combine
      antiresorptive and anabolic agents, such as bone morphogenic protein, which for instance and
      in osteoporotic bone, will improve bone healing process.

      With a view to diminishing the side effects caused by the systemic use of BPs, such as
      oesophagitis and osteonecrosis of the jaw, and to maximize anabolism and minimize catabolism,
      recent studies have sought alternative systems for local delivery of these agents with or
      without bone forming agent, either by means of immobilizing on the implant surface (coating
      or immersion in BPs solution), or by applying the drug directly to the surgical site before
      implant insertion either as an irrigant or gel.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Enrolling by invitation</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 1, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 1, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Factorial Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Implant stability</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Mean implant stability between different comparators following implants insertion by using resonance frequency analysis scaled from 1 to 100</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Implant stability</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks post surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Mean implant stability between different comparators following implants insertion by using resonance frequency analysis scaled from 1 to 100</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Implant stability</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks post loading</time_frame>
    <description>Mean implant stability between different comparators following implants loading by using resonance frequency analysis scaled from 1 to 100</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Crestal bone level</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks post surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Mean crestal bone level between different comparators following implants insertion by using cone beam computerized tomography measured from the first bone implant contact by millimeters</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Crestal bone level</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks post loading</time_frame>
    <description>Mean crestal bone level between different comparators following implants loading by using cone beam computerized tomography measured from the first bone implant contact by millimeters</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Bone density around dental implant</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks post surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Mean difference in bone density around dental implants between different comparators following implants insertion by using cone beam computerized tomography with hounsfield unit</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Bone density around dental implant</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks post loading</time_frame>
    <description>Mean difference in bone density around dental implants between different comparators following implants loading by using cone beam computerized tomography with hounsfield unit</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Partial Edentulism</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Alendronate Gel (ALN)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>After preparation, 0.05 ml of the gel containing 100 µg of ALN will be injected in the osteotomy site immediately before fixture insertion (20 fixtures)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Bone Morphogenic Protein Gel (BMP)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>After preparation, 0.05 ml of the gel containing 100 µg of BMP will be injected in the osteotomy site immediately before fixture insertion (20 fixtures)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Mixture Gel of ALN and BMP</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>After preparation, 0.05 ml of mixture gel containing 50 µg of ALN and 50 µg of BMP will be injected in the osteotomy site immediately before fixture insertion (20 fixtures)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Sham Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>After preparation, the fixture will be inserted without topical application of any medication (20 fixtures)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ALN Gel</intervention_name>
    <description>Flapped surgery for insertion of dental implant with topical application of ALN gel</description>
    <arm_group_label>Alendronate Gel (ALN)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Alendronate Sodium trihydrate, m.w 325.12, Pharmaceutical Secondary standard, PHR 1599</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>BMP Gel</intervention_name>
    <description>Flapped surgery for insertion of dental implant with topical application of BMP gel</description>
    <arm_group_label>Bone Morphogenic Protein Gel (BMP)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>CowellBMP, recombinant human bone morphogenic protein type 2, rhBMP2</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Mixed Gel</intervention_name>
    <description>Flapped surgery for insertion of dental implant with topical application of mixed gel of ALN and BMP</description>
    <arm_group_label>Mixture Gel of ALN and BMP</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Mixture of Alendronate Sodium trihydrate, m.w 325.12, Pharmaceutical Secondary standard, PHR 1599, and CowellBMP, recombinant human bone morphogenic protein type 2, rhBMP2</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Control</intervention_name>
    <description>Flapped surgery for insertion of dental implant without topical application of any gel</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>No treatment</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion criteria Otherwise healthy patients over 18 years or with systemic diseases that
        do not interfere with bone healing Having single or multiple missing teeth in maxilla
        and/or mandible Having an alveolar ridge of sufficient vertical and horizontal dimensions
        and considered straightforward cases according to SAC classification

        Exclusion criteria Patients with active or chronic infection or inflammation in the implant
        zone History of radiotherapy to the head and neck Past or current treatment with
        oral/intramuscular/intravenous bisphosphonates or other drugs altering bone metabolism
        Heavy smokers or with sever periodontitis
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Salwan Y Bede</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Baghdad</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>College of dentistry, University of Baghdad</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baghdad</city>
        <state>Bab-Almoadham</state>
        <zip>1417</zip>
        <country>Iraq</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Iraq</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 26, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 24, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 25, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 24, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 24, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 25, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Baghdad</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Dhuha A. Al-assaf</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Alendronate</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

