<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04147767</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>RD19/123502</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04147767</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Plant Sterol INtervention for Cancer Prevention (PINC)</brief_title>
  <acronym>PINC</acronym>
  <official_title>Randomised Control Cross-over Trial to Test How Dietary Plant Sterols Modify Tumour Promoting Capabilities of Non-tumour Host Cells in Volunteers With Elevated LDL-C</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Leeds</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>The Leeds Teaching Hospitals NHS Trust</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Oslo</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Leeds</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Several types of human cells convert cholesterol into other molecules, including oxysterols.
      Oxysterols can promote breast cancer growth and help tumours to spread. Some breast cancer
      types recruit other cells (host cells) able to produce oxysterols within the local cancer
      environment.

      How these other cells help breast tumours metastasize or resist chemotherapy is not well
      understood, but epidemiological and clinical studies suggest elevated LDL-C is associated
      with worse survival, poorer response to therapy and an increased propensity for disease
      relapse in breast cancer patients. In this trial the investigators will test how an LDL-C
      lowering dietary intervention (using commercially available phytosterol added food products),
      alters the ability of non-cancer cells (adipocytes, fibroblasts and macrophages) collected
      from high LDL-C volunteers to change chemotherapy response and metastatic process in breast
      cancer cells.

      In this trial, volunteers with high LDL-C levels will be recruited by the University of
      Leeds, and divided randomly into two arms that cross over. The experimental period (yogurt
      drink enriched with phytosterols) and placebo period (non-enriched yogurt drink) will each
      last for 8 weeks, alternated with a 4 weeks of wash-out period. Samples will be collected 4
      times (week-0, week-8, week-12, week-20) during the study and will include blood, white blood
      cells (macrophages), and fat tissue cells. Measurements will include oxysterol, LDL-C and
      phytosterol concentrations (volunteers' serum/plasma, media from the host cells/breast cancer
      experimental culture) and how the host cells alter the behaviour of cancer cells in the
      laboratory.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Delivery of cholesterol to extra-hepatic tissues by LDL has a profound impact on different
      host cell types, many of which themselves have been implicated in BCa metastasis and
      chemoresistance.

      Despite accumulating data, it is still unknown how host-cells help breast tumours metastasise
      or evade chemotherapy. The molecular link between cholesterol and metastasis may involve the
      enzymatic hydroxylation (an intermediate step in bile acid synthesis) of cholesterol. The
      synthesis and secretion of oxysterols into the tumour microenvironment and this is
      exacerbated in individuals with elevated LDL-cholesterol. This process, occurring largely in
      macrophages, adipocytes and fibroblasts, leads to biosynthesis and cellular export of
      oxysterols , which drive DNA mutations through oxidative stress, confer resistance to
      chemotherapy, enhance BCa growth and metastasis, and are elevated in serum of BCa patients at
      metastatic relapse. Our pilot data show non-cancer host-cells activate oxysterols signalling
      and drug resistance protein expression and confer chemotherapy resistance in adjacent cancer
      cells.

      The investigators therefore propose to test the hypothesis that the reason epidemiological
      and clinical studies find elevated LDL-C and its co-morbidities associate with worse survival
      in BCa patients, is because the host-cells of these patients have enhanced cholesterol
      metabolic flux leading to increased oxysterols production and improved tolerance of
      chemotherapy and promotion of cancer metastatic pathways.

      This trial is a multicentre cross-over double blind clinical trial in which volunteers with
      LDL-C ≥160mg/dL (4.1 mmol/L), recruited at the University of Leeds and/or identified through
      Horizon 2020 project PATHWAY-27, will be randomised into two arms of intervention, Group A
      (experimental arm) will be given an yoghurt drink enriched with PSS and Group B (placebo
      comparator) will be given yoghurt drink non-enriched with PSS. Each dietary intervention will
      last for 8 weeks, alternated with a 4 weeks of wash out period. This trial wants to highlight
      the superiority of the PSS (yoghurt drink enriched) to placebo (yoghurt drink non-enriched)
      intervention on the improvement of the serum/plasma and host cells (adipocytes and
      macrophages) LDL-C, oxysterols , PSS levels in high LDL-C levels volunteers and in respective
      conditioned media from the host cells/BCa cell lines co-culture, and superiority of the PSS
      to placebo intervention on the improvement of the cholesterol panel levels involved in BCa
      tolerance of chemotherapy and metastatic progression, according also to the molecular and
      genetical pathways.

      Because of the unknown effect of PSS on the oxysterols metabolism and of its consequent
      chemotherapy and anti-metastatic proprieties, the trial will be divided in two phases (I and
      II):

      I. In this pilot phase the investigators will explore the effects of PSS intervention in 10
      volunteers, evaluate feasibility of study protocol (participant recruitment and retention),
      and changes in mean and SD in oxysterols /PSS concentrations making changes to dose and power
      calculations if necessary. If the intervention causes any noteworthy effect in oxysterols
      serum/blood levels and/or on host cell co-culture with BCa cells the study will continue to
      Phase II:

      II. In this phase a further 40 volunteers will be enrolled in the study satisfying our power
      calculation prediction to observe an effect.

      This randomized cross-over double blind clinical trial will be run mainly at the School of
      Food Science and Nutrition, of the University of Leeds (FS&amp;N). Each site will have a
      nominated principle investigator. This will be in collaboration with the NHS - Leeds Teaching
      Hospitals Trust (LTHT), the Leeds Institute of Biomedical &amp; Clinical Sciences of the Faculty
      of Medicine and Health of the University of Leeds (LIBACS) and the Department of Chemistry of
      the University of Oslo (DC).

      At each step point (Day 56, day 84 and day 140), the following trial assessments and
      procedures will be taken:

        -  Weight measurement;

        -  Participants diary card checking;

        -  Adverse effects and safety;

        -  Blood Pressure;

        -  Food intervention compliance checking by asking participants to return yoghurt packages
           back to trial team and relative recordings;

        -  24h dietary recall questionnaire interview;

        -  LDL-C, HDL-C, Total Cholesterol, Triglycerides, non-HDL-C blood concentration and
           HDL-C/LDL-C ratio measurement;

        -  Serum/plasma OHCs concentration measurement;

        -  Serum/plasma PSS concentration measurement;

        -  Medium LDL-C concentration measurement after host cells co-culture with breast cancer
           cell lines;

        -  Medium OHCs concentration measurement after host cells co-culture with breast cancer
           cell lines;

        -  Medium PSS concentration measurement after host cells co-culture with breast cancer cell
           lines;

        -  Adipocytes, macrophages and breast cancer cell lines cell lines OHCs content
           measurement;

        -  Migratory and chemoresistance properties of the breast cancer cell lines cell lines
           after host cells co-culture.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 10, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 31, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 31, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Enrolled participants will undergo 1:1 simple randomisation by the CI, to either Experimental arm or placebo arm.. Evaluations after intervention will be made at the end of the first 8 weeks of intervention (Day 56; 8th week) and at the end of the second 8 weeks intervention (Day 140; 20th week). Since a wash out period between the two food products consumption is provided, another evaluation after wash out period (Day 84; 12th week) will be performed. The wash out period consist in a 4 weeks food products free period, where will be ask to participants to maintain their usual dietary and life style habits excluding the consumption of any yoghurt drinks.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>All trial investigators will be blinded to the intervention, except for the CI. The CI will keep a record of interventions administrated. All trial participants and outcome assessors will be blinded to the intervention. Each food product has the same flavour and taste, as well as the same packaging to ensure blinding in maintained throughout study.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To change circulating oxysterols levels after phytosterols intervention.</measure>
    <time_frame>Serum/plasma oxysterols concentrations will be measured during all the steps of the trial (baseline, 8th week, 12nd week, 20th week)</time_frame>
    <description>The changes of oxysterols content in serum/plasma after 8 weeks of phytosterols intervention compared to placebo. After the dietary intervention, we expect to observe a change of -20% in circulating 27-hydroxycholesterol content (marker of oxysterols systemic levels).
Concentration of oxysterols using LC-MS/MS measurement of plasma in 50 subjects after placebo and after intervention.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change intra-cellular adipocyte and macrophages oxysterols concentrations</measure>
    <time_frame>Serum/plasma/medium oxysterols concentrations will be measured during all the steps of the trial (baseline, 8th week, 12nd week, 20th week)</time_frame>
    <description>Concentration of oxysterols using LC-MS/MS measurement of host cells in 50 subjects after placebo and after intervention.
Effect of phytosterols enriched foods consumption compared to placebo intervention on migratory and chemoresistance properties of breast cancer cell lines (MDA.MB.231, MDA.MB.468, MCF7 and T47D) when in co-culture with the host-cells collected in each step of the trial.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Study of adipocytes and macrophages interaction with breast cancer cell lines</measure>
    <time_frame>Protein expression will be measured during all the steps of the trial (baseline, 8th week, 12nd week, 20th week)</time_frame>
    <description>Effect of phytosterols enriched foods consumption compared to placebo intervention on migratory and chemoresistance properties of breast cancer cell lines (MDA.MB.231, MDA.MB.468, MCF7 and T47D) when in co-culture with the host-cells collected in each step of the trial.
Changes in proteins expression of oxysterols target genes.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Study of adipocytes and macrophages interaction with breast cancer cell lines</measure>
    <time_frame>Gene expression will be measured during all the steps of the trial (baseline, 8th week, 12nd week, 20th week)</time_frame>
    <description>Effect of phytosterols enriched foods consumption compared to placebo intervention on migratory and chemoresistance properties of breast cancer cell lines (MDA.MB.231, MDA.MB.468, MCF7 and T47D) when in co-culture with the host-cells collected in each step of the trial.
Changes in gene expression of oxysterols target genes.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Study the effect of phytosterols on LDL-C</measure>
    <time_frame>Serum/plasma phytosterols and lipid concentrations will be measured during all the steps of the trial (baseline, 8th week, 12nd week, 20th week)</time_frame>
    <description>Study of the effect of phytosterols on LDL-C concentration in 50 subjects after placebo and after intervention using Alere Afinion™.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Study the effect of phytosterols on HDL-C</measure>
    <time_frame>Serum/plasma phytosterols and lipid concentrations will be measured during all the steps of the trial (baseline, 8th week, 12nd week, 20th week)</time_frame>
    <description>Study of the effect of phytosterols on HDL-C concentration in 50 subjects after placebo and after intervention using Alere Afinion™.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Study the effect of phytosterols on Total Cholesterol</measure>
    <time_frame>Serum/plasma phytosterols and lipid concentrations will be measured during all the steps of the trial (baseline, 8th week, 12nd week, 20th week)</time_frame>
    <description>Study of the effect of phytosterols on Total Cholesterol concentration in 50 subjects after placebo and after intervention using Alere Afinion™.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Study the effect of phytosterols on Triglycerides</measure>
    <time_frame>Serum/plasma phytosterols and lipid concentrations will be measured during all the steps of the trial (baseline, 8th week, 12nd week, 20th week)</time_frame>
    <description>Study of the effect of phytosterols on Triglycerides concentration in 50 subjects after placebo and after intervention using Alere Afinion™.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Study the effect of phytosterols on non-HDL-C</measure>
    <time_frame>Serum/plasma phytosterols and lipid concentrations will be measured during all the steps of the trial (baseline, 8th week, 12nd week, 20th week)</time_frame>
    <description>Study of the effect of phytosterols on non-HDL-C concentration in 50 subjects after placebo and after intervention using Alere Afinion™.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quantify phytosterols in blood samples from volunteers.</measure>
    <time_frame>Serum/plasma phytosterols and lipid concentrations will be measured during all the steps of the trial (baseline, 8th week, 12nd week, 20th week)</time_frame>
    <description>Phytosterols panel serum/plasma levels after phytosterols enriched food or placebo intervention during all the steps of the trial.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Study RNA sequences changes in the oxysterols/LDL-C pathway and secondary breast cancer before and after phytosterols intervention .</measure>
    <time_frame>RNA will be studied during all the steps of the trial (baseline, 8th week, 12nd week, 20th week)</time_frame>
    <description>RNA sequence will be measured with RNA-seq techniques before and after phytosterols intervention to identify the molecular effectors of the paracrine regulatory systems in the oxysterols, LDL-C and secondary BCa pattern.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Study changes in the interactions between proteins and DNA in the oxysterols/LDL-C pathway and secondary breast cancer before and after phytosterols intervention .</measure>
    <time_frame>interactions between proteins and DNA will be studied during all the steps of the trial (baseline, 8th week, 12nd week, 20th week)</time_frame>
    <description>Changes in interactions between proteins and DNA and using Chip/seq will be measured before and after phytosterols intervention to identify the molecular effectors of the paracrine regulatory systems in the oxysterols, LDL-C and secondary BCa pattern.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Hypercholesterolemia</condition>
  <condition>Breast Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Obesity</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Phytosterols Arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The investigational food product &quot;Cholesterol Reducing Strawberry Yogurt Drink (Tesco)&quot; is a strawberry yogurt drink with added plant sterols. A 100g bottle (one serving) of cholesterol lowering strawberry yogurt drink contains 2g of free plant sterols. The magnitude of the effect given by this enriched food product, providing a daily intake of 1,5-2,4 g plant sterols/stanols, refers to the lowering/reducing blood cholesterol effects in the range &quot;7 % to 10 %&quot; within 2 to 3 weeks of treatment, as specified by Commission Regulation (EU) 384/2010 of 05/05/2010.
The dietary intervention will consist in 8 weeks consumption of PSS enriched Yogurt Drink, which provide a daily PSS intake of 3.4g/100g bottle plant sterols ester equivalent to 2g/100g bottle of free plant sterols.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo Arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The investigational food product &quot;Low Fat Strawberry Yogurt Drinks (Morrisons)&quot; is a strawberry flavoured yogurt drink with sweetener and sugar, vitamin C, B6 and D, British milk.
Placebo intervention consists in 8 weeks consumption of PSS non-enriched Yogurt Drinks. The placebo intervention is needed for the study design chosen (randomized double-blind placebo-controlled cross-over clinical trial). Placebo will be used in order to determine the efficacy of PSS intervention, comparing the effects of the two compounds (PSS and placebo) in the same experimental conditions and then avoiding bias.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cholesterol Reducing Strawberry Yogurt Drink (Tesco Ltd)</intervention_name>
    <description>Ingredients: Skimmed Milk, Strawberry Juice from Concentrate (5%), Plant Sterols Ester (3.4%)***, Sugar, Maize Starch, Flavourings, Colour (Anthocyanins), Starter Culture including Bifidobacterium (Milk), Thickener (Carob Gum), Sweetener (Sucralose), Milk Proteins.
*** Equivalent to 2% Free Plant Sterols</description>
    <arm_group_label>Phytosterols Arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Low Fat Strawberry Yogurt Drinks (Morrisons Ltd)</intervention_name>
    <description>Ingredients: Yogurt (Milk), Water, Sugar, Strawberry Purée (1%), Modified Maize Starch, Carrot Concentrate, Flavouring, Acidity Regulator (Citric Acid), Vitamin C, Colour (Paprika Extract), Sweetener (Sucralose), Vitamin D, Vitamin B6.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo Arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Subjects capable of giving informed consent;

          2. Non-pregnant, non-nursing female;

          3. Age between 18-65 years old;

          4. LDL-C ≥160mg/dL (4.1mmol/L):

          5. BMI ≥25 (kg/m2)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Subjects who are under treatment with lipophilic statins;

          2. Subjects under any other supplementation that improve cholesterol levels (i.e.
             monacolin, other PSS enriched products);

          3. Subjects under any weight loss or lipid lowering dietary plan;

          4. Present or past chronic diseases: CVDs, cancer, know positive hepatitis B virus
             surface antigen (HBsAg), hepatitis C (HCV) antibody or HIV, cirrhosis,
             gastrointestinal disorders (i.e. irritable bowel syndrome, Crohn's disease, celiac
             disease, bowel control problems), kidney diseases, autoimmune diseases, endocrine
             disorders, metabolic diseases (i.e. diabetes type I and type II, familiar
             hypercholesterolemia), neurological diseases;

          5. Diagnosed eating disorders according to the Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of
             Mental Disorders 5 (DSM-5);

          6. Past or planned within the trial period bariatric surgery;

          7. Past or planned within the trial period gastrointestinal resections;

          8. Corticosteroid and chronic inflammatory therapy;

          9. Consumption within the preceding 8 weeks of other compounds capable of influencing
             cholesterol metabolism (bile acid-binding resins, ezetimibe, psyllium, fish oil
             supplements, soya lecithin, phytoestrogens and other PSS-fortified foods);

         10. Females pregnant or females who are planning pregnancy;

         11. Females breastfeeding;

         12. Phytosterolemia diseases;

         13. Participants with allergies to any of the substances presents in the yoghurt drink
             chosen for the trial: citric acid, anhydrous, sodium chloride, disodium edetate
             dehydrate, polysorbate 80, sodium hydroxide, Hypersensitivity to E. Coli derived
             proteins, nuts, peanuts, egg and soy proteins. Participants with a latex allergy are
             also not eligible as the inner needle cover of the pre-filled syringe contains dry
             natural rubber (a derivative of latex);

         14. Participants with allergies to lidocaine;

         15. Participation in other dietary or clinical trials.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <gender_based>Yes</gender_based>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>James L Thorne, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Leeds</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>James L Thorne, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+440113343 0684</phone>
    <email>J.L.Thorne@leeds.ac.uk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Leeds</name>
      <address>
        <city>Leeds</city>
        <state>West Yorkshire</state>
        <zip>LS29JT</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>James L Thorne, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>+440113 343 0684</phone>
      <email>J.L.Thorne@leeds.ac.uk</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Giorgia, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>+440113 343 7724</phone>
      <email>G.Cioccoloni@leeds.ac.uk</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 21, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 29, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">November 1, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 18, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 18, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 20, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Leeds</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>James Thorne</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Chief Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>oxysterol</keyword>
  <keyword>breast cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>phytosterols</keyword>
  <keyword>cholesterol metabolism</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hypercholesterolemia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Data will be published in scientific journals, which will depend on the outcome of data analysis. Anonymized research data will be deposited with the University of Leeds data repository.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

