<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04147052</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IRB00116581</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>K23HD086154</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04147052</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>iSLEEPms: An Internet-Delivered Intervention for Sleep Disturbance in Multiple Sclerosis</brief_title>
  <official_title>An Internet-delivered Cognitive Behavioral Intervention for Sleep Disturbance in Multiple Sclerosis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Johns Hopkins University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Eunice Kennedy Shriver National Institute of Child Health and Human Development (NICHD)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Johns Hopkins University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Sleep disturbance is reported in over 50% of individuals with multiple sclerosis (MS).
      Although cognitive behavioral therapy is considered the first-line, gold-standard treatment
      for insomnia, cognitive behavioral therapy for insomnia (CBT-I) has not been sufficiently
      investigated in people with MS. Furthermore, although several online CBT-I programs have been
      shown to be effective in the general population, these programs have not been tailored to
      meet the unique needs of the MS community. This pilot study investigates a novel
      internet-delivered intervention based on CBT-I.

      This study is a pilot randomized controlled trial to test the preliminary effects of
      iSLEEPms, a CBT-I-based online intervention with telephone support for individuals with MS.
      After completing a baseline assessment (Week 1), 90 participants with MS will be randomized
      (1:1) to four weeks (Weeks 2-5) of iSLEEPms (intervention group) or treatment as usual (TAU;
      control group), and complete post-treatment (Week 6) and follow-up (Week 12) assessments.
      iSLEEPms participants will complete four weekly modules through the study website, and will
      receive brief weekly support calls from study personnel. TAU participants will continue usual
      care without access to the study website or support calls.

      The primary outcomes will be patient-reported and actigraphic measures of sleep quality and
      quantity. Secondary outcomes will be treatment satisfaction, adherence, and integrity
      (iSLEEPms group only). Exploratory outcomes will be common symptoms exacerbated by sleep
      disturbance, including fatigue, depression, and cognitive dysfunction.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">September 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 31, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 31, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in the Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index (PSQI) total score</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline (Week 1), Post-intervention (Week 6), and Follow-up (Week 12)</time_frame>
    <description>The PSQI is a 9-item participant-reported measure that assesses sleep quality. Scores range from 0 to 21 points, with higher scores indicating poorer sleep quality. Scores ≥ 5 are clinically significant.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in the Insomnia Severity Index (ISI) total score</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline (Week 1), Post-intervention (Week 6), and Follow-up (Week 12)</time_frame>
    <description>The ISI is a 7-item participant-reported measure that assesses insomnia symptoms. Scores range from 0 to 28 points (each item is rated 0-4), with higher scores indicating greater insomnia. Scores ≥ 11 are clinically significant.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in actigraphic total sleep time (TST)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline (Week 1), Post-intervention (Week 6), and Follow-up (Week 12)</time_frame>
    <description>Wrist actigraphy devices objectively assess TST, in minutes. TSTs &lt; 360 min are considered clinically significant.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in actigraphic sleep efficiency (SE)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline (Week 1), Post-intervention (Week 6), and Follow-up (Week 12)</time_frame>
    <description>Wrist actigraphy devices objectively assess SE as a % of time asleep while in bed. SEs &lt; 85% are considered clinically significant.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in actigraphic sleep latency (SL)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline (Week 1), Post-intervention (Week 6), and Follow-up (Week 12)</time_frame>
    <description>Wrist actigraphy devices objectively assess SL, in minutes. SLs &gt; 30 min are considered clinically significant.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in actigraphic wake after sleep onset (WASO)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline (Week 1), Post-intervention (Week 6), and Follow-up (Week 12)</time_frame>
    <description>Wrist actigraphy devices objectively assess WASO, in minutes. WASOs &gt; 30 min are considered clinically significant.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in the Modified Fatigue Impact Scale (MFIS) total score</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline (Week 1), Post-intervention (Week 6), and Follow-up (Week 12)</time_frame>
    <description>The MFIS is a 21-item participant-reported measure that assesses how much fatigue impacts physical, cognitive, and psychosocial functioning. Scores range from 0 to 84 (each item is rated 0-4), with higher scores indicating a greater impact of fatigue. Scores ≥ 38 are clinically significant. The scale has three subscales (Physical, 9 items; Cognitive, 10 items; and Psychosocial, 2 items).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in the Beck Depression Inventory - Fast Screen (BDI-FS) total score</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline (Week 1), Post-intervention (Week 6), and Follow-up (Week 12)</time_frame>
    <description>The BDI-FS is a 7-item participant-reported measure of depressive symptom severity. Scores range from 0 to 21 (each item rated 0-3), with higher scores indicating greater depressive symptom severity. Scores ≥ 4 are clinically significant.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in the MS Neuropsychological Screening Questionnaire (MSNQ) total score</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline (Week 1), Post-intervention (Week 6), and Follow-up (Week 12)</time_frame>
    <description>The MSNQ is a 15-item participant-reported measure of subjective cognitive dysfunction. Scores range from 0 to 60 (each item rated 0-4), with higher scores indicating greater perceived cognitive dysfunction.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in the TestMyBrain Memorizing Words (MW) score</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline (Week 1), Post-intervention (Week 6), and Follow-up (Week 12)</time_frame>
    <description>TestMyBrain.org is an online platform that objectively assesses cognitive dysfunction. MW is a verbal paired associates test. Participants learn and memorize 25 word pairs and are asked to recall them after a delay. Higher scores indicate better verbal memory performance.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in the TestMyBrain Memorizing Pictures (MP) score</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline (Week 1), Post-intervention (Week 6), and Follow-up (Week 12)</time_frame>
    <description>TestMyBrain.org is an online platform that objectively assesses cognitive dysfunction. MP is a visual paired associates test. Participants learn and memorize 24 pictures pairs and are asked to recall them after a delay. Higher scores indicate better visual memory performance.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in the TestMyBrain Matching Shapes and Numbers (MSN) score</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline (Week 1), Post-intervention (Week 6), and Follow-up (Week 12)</time_frame>
    <description>TestMyBrain.org is an online platform that objectively assesses cognitive dysfunction. MSN is a speeded digit-symbol coding task. Participants use a key provided on the screen to quickly match 9 unique symbols with their correctly paired digits as quickly as possible. Higher scores indicate faster processing speed.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in the TestMyBrain Fast Choices (FC) score</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline (Week 1), Post-intervention (Week 6), and Follow-up (Week 12)</time_frame>
    <description>TestMyBrain.org is an online platform that objectively assesses cognitive dysfunction. FC is a choice reaction time test. Participants view arrows and quickly judge their direction. Higher scores indicate faster processing speed.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Treatment Satisfaction Scale (TSS) total score (iSLEEPms group only)</measure>
    <time_frame>Post-intervention (Week 6)</time_frame>
    <description>The TSS a 7-item participant-reported measure adapted from the Consumer Report Treatment Satisfaction Scale to assess satisfaction with iSLEEPms. The 7 items (each item rated 1 to 5) are averaged to calculate a total score, with higher scores indicating greater symptom improvement during the iSLEEPms program.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>iSLEEPms treatment adherence (iSLEEPMS group only)</measure>
    <time_frame>During the iSLEEPms intervention (Weeks 2-5)</time_frame>
    <description>Treatment adherence will be assessed based on completion of each of the four weekly iSLEEPms modules, including completion of the online sleep diary form, a brief questionnaire assessing comprehension of module content, and a brief call with study personnel. A total score will be determined based on the percentage of weekly modules.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>iSLEEPms treatment integrity (iSLEEPMS group only)</measure>
    <time_frame>During the iSLEEPms intervention (Weeks 2-5)</time_frame>
    <description>Treatment integrity will be assessed based on coverage of coverage of 17 CBT-I elements, adapted from the Treatment Components Adherence Scale. A total score will be determined based on the percentage of elements covered over the four-week iSLEEPms intervention.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">90</enrollment>
  <condition>Multiple Sclerosis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>iSLEEPms</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants randomized to iSLEEPms complete a 4-week online program with telephone support, based on CBT-I.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment As Usual</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants randomized to TAU continue their usual care and are encouraged to avoid starting any new sleep treatment unless deemed necessary by a health care provider.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>iSLEEPms</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants randomized to iSLEEPms complete four weekly online modules through the study website. Modules are interactive and focus on typical elements of CBT-I, adapted for individuals with MS: education about sleep in MS, sleep restriction, and stimulus control; sleep hygiene and relaxation; and cognitive restructuring around sleep and coping with MS. Sleep diaries are reviewed each week by study personnel, and personalized feedback is provided to participants to guide treatment.</description>
    <arm_group_label>iSLEEPms</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Ages 18 and older

          -  MS diagnosis56 of at least 1 year duration

          -  Able to speak and read English

          -  Sleep disturbance as indicated by an ISI score of at least 11

          -  Willingness to commit to a 4-week intervention and 12-week follow-up assessment

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Neurological disorder other than MS

          -  Hazardous alcohol use, as indicated by the Alcohol Use Disorders Identification Test
             (AUDIT-C)

          -  Hazardous substance use, as indicated by the Drug Abuse Screening Test (DAST-10)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Abbey J Hughes</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Johns Hopkins University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Abbey J Hughes, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>410-502-9234</phone>
    <email>abbeyjhughes@jhmi.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 25, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 29, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 31, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 16, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 16, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 20, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Multiple Sclerosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dyssomnias</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Parasomnias</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sclerosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

