<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04144491</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>01/09-19</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04144491</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effect of L. Rhamnosus Yoba on RTI and Other Health Outcomes Among Children (3-6 Years) in Uganda</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Nutritional Trial on Effect of Probiotic Yoghurt Containing Lactobacillus Rhamnosus Yoba on Respiratory Tract Infection and Other Health Outcomes Among Children Aged 3-6 Years in Southwest Uganda</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>VU University of Amsterdam</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Yoba for Life Foundation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>VU University of Amsterdam</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a nutritional trial with two arms: 1) Intervention arm of Probiotic Yoghurt
      containing Lactobacillus rhamnosus yoba 2012 and 2) Control arm of custard-like dairy
      product. The study subjects are 200 children between the age of 3-6 years that attend a
      school in Southwestern Uganda, Sheema district. Children will be randomized and enrolled in
      either the yoghurt (100 children) or the placebo (100 children) arm. The children will be
      monitored for 3 weeks in the baseline in regards to the incidence of common childhood
      diseases. During these three weeks, stool, saliva and urine samples will be collected. Also
      measurement of anthropometric indicators (weight and height) will take place. Subsequently,
      the children will consume either 100ml yoghurt or 100ml placebo product, once per day for
      five days per week for nine weeks, while being daily monitored in regards to the incidence of
      common childhood diseases. The same samples (stool, urine and saliva) and assessments
      (anthropometric) will take place at end line.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a nutritional trial with two arms: 1) Intervention arm of Probiotic Yoghurt
      containing Lactobacillus rhamnosus yoba 2012 and 2) Placebo arm of custard-like dairy
      product. The study subjects are 200 children between the age of 3-6 years that attend a
      school in Southwestern Uganda, Sheema district. Children will be randomized and enrolled in
      either the yoghurt (100 children) or the placebo (100 children) arm. The children will be
      monitored for 3 weeks in the baseline in regards to the incidence of common childhood
      diseases. During these three weeks, stool, saliva and urine samples will be collected. Also
      measurement of anthropometric indicators (weight and height) will take place. Subsequently,
      the children will consume either 100ml yoghurt or 100ml placebo product, once per day for
      five days per week for nine weeks, while being daily monitored in regards to the incidence of
      common childhood diseases. The same samples (stool, urine and saliva) and assessments
      (anthropometric) will take place at end line. The yoghurt and the placebo product will be
      locally sourced in the district where the school is located. Monitoring and data collection
      tools are:

        1. Baseline, mid line and end line questionnaire administered to parents to identify
           confounding factors (e.g. use of medication and diet from home) of treatment and control
           group.

        2. Weight and height measurements at baseline and end line in both the treatment and
           control group (total 2 times).

        3. Daily monitoring of the incidence of RTIs, diarrhoea, skin rashes or other diseases in
           treatment and control groups by a nurse, registered in a mobile application.

        4. Collection of urine samples every 4 weeks for 3 months (total 4 times), for assessment
           of impact of the intervention on system health.

        5. Collection of stool samples at baseline and end line, for assessment of impact of the
           intervention on gut health.

        6. Collection of saliva samples before and towards the end of the intervention, for
           assessment of impact of the intervention on immune biomarkers

      The consumption of probiotic yoghurt at school as paid for by the parents, is currently being
      promoted by an Non-Governmental Organization (NGO) in the region. Following this program,
      children from a primary school that includes a pre-primary section, in which both the
      management and the parents have recently decided to purchase yoghurt for the pupils on
      regular basis will be recruited. The study subjects (children) are recruited at these
      institutions, after consent from the parent has been obtained. The parent is free to provide
      his/her child with yoghurt, even if the parent does not consent for the child to take part in
      the study.

      The study will start three weeks before either yoghurt or placebo consumption commences, in
      order to establish a solid baseline. With the help of tablets and a specially designed mobile
      application, nurses will keep track of their pupils' health by tracking incidence of
      diarrhoea, respiratory tract infections, skin rashes and other diseases. Teachers will keep
      track of the daily attendance of pupils.

      Measurements of weight and height will be measured by a nurse at baseline and end line. The
      measurements will be conducted with the help of Standard Operations Procedures as provided by
      Life Study and analyzed with the help of World Health Organization (WHO) guidelines. Urine
      samples will be taken from the children at baseline, after 4 weeks, after 8 weeks, and at end
      line (12 weeks). Stool samples and saliva samples will be taken at the beginning and the end
      of the study.

      During these 3 months in which the children will be monitored, a questionnaire will be
      administered to the parents of the children at the start, middle and end of the study. The
      primary objective and content of the questionnaire is related to diet of the children outside
      school, in order to determine whether there are significant differences between the diets of
      the children in the treatment group and in the control group. The questionnaires will
      furthermore include questions about absenteeism and causes thereof, incidence of diarrhoea,
      Respiratory Tract Infections (RTI) or any other diseases, and the use of any type of drug or
      treatment, in order to verify and supplement the information provided by the class-teacher.
      Lastly, information on the vaccination history of the child will be obtained from the parent
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 16, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 30, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">November 29, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The number of children on each individual day that suffers from Respiratory Tract Infections</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>To compare the incidence of respiratory tract infections among children aged 3-6 years in Southwest Uganda before, during and after an intervention with probiotic yoghurt containing Lactobacillus rhamnosus yoba</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in weight of children during the study period</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>To monitor changes in weight of children aged 3-6 years in Southwest Uganda who consume yoghurt containing Lactobacillus rhamnosus yoba.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in height of the children during the study period</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>To monitor changes in height of children aged 3-6 years in Southwest Uganda who consume yoghurt containing Lactobacillus rhamnosus yoba.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The number of children on each individual day that suffers from Diarrhea</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>To compare the incidence of diarrhea among the children before, during and after the intervention.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The number of children on each individual day that suffers from any form of skin diseases</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>To compare the incidence of skin rashes among the children before, during and after the intervention.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The number of children on each individual day that is absent</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>To compare absenteeism as a result of sickness among the children before, during and after the intervention.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Differences in the metabolic profile of childrens urine between baseline and after 9 weeks of intervention using 1H-Nuclear Magnetic Resonance (NMR) Spectroscopy</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>To compare metabolic profile in the urine of the children before, during and after the intervention</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Differences in the microbial profile of childrens stool between baseline and after 9 weeks of intervention using Next Generation Sequencing (NGS) in combination with Fluorescence In Situ Hybridisation hyphenated to Flow Cytometry (Flow-FISH)</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>To compare the microbial profile in the stool of the children before and after the intervention.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Differences in the immune markers of childrens saliva between baseline and after 9 weeks of intervention</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>To compare immune markers (secretory immunoglobulin A (IgA), secretory leukoprotease inhibitor (SLPI), immunoglobulin M (IgM), immunoglobulin G (IgG), cytokines chemokines and growth factors) in the saliva of the children before and after the intervention</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">195</enrollment>
  <condition>Respiratory Tract Infections</condition>
  <condition>Diarrhea</condition>
  <condition>Skin Diseases</condition>
  <condition>Tinea Capitis</condition>
  <condition>Common Cold</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Yoghurt</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Yoghurt, containing Lactobacillus rhamnosus yoba 2012, Streptococcus thermophilus C104, whole milk, 5% sugar, 0.1% strawberry or vanilla flavor essence.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Custard</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Custard, containing whole milk, 5% sugar, 0.1% strawberry or vanilla flavor essence, 4% modified corn starch.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Probiotic</intervention_name>
    <description>Probiotics are defined by the Food and Agricultural Organization (FAO)/WHO as &quot;live microorganisms, which when consumed in adequate amounts, confer a health benefit on the host&quot;. Lactobacillus rhamnosus GG (LGG) is the most documented probiotic bacteria, with many proven unique characteristics and therewith associated health benefits. No adverse effects of the consumption of LGG in healthy infants have been reported. The Lactobacillus rhamnosus yoba containing yoghurt drink, which is locally produced and subsequently consumed by resource-poor communities in rural Uganda has been described. The strain used in this intervention is a generic variant of LGG, called Lactobacillus rhamnosus yoba 2012. LGG is consumed as part of food all over the world, and is not a drug.
100ml of yoghurt containing Lactobacillus rhamnosus yoba 2012 will be consumed 5 days per week, for 9 weeks.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Yoghurt</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Lactobacillus rhamnosus yoba 2012</other_name>
    <other_name>Lactobacillus rhamnosus GG</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>100ml of custard will be consumed 5 days per week, for 9 weeks.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Custard</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Children of a pre-primary institution in Southwest Uganda are targetted

          -  During interactions with the pre-primary institutions prior to the study, the parents
             of the children have agreed to pay for their child to either take probiotic yoghurt
             (100ml five times per week).

          -  Parents are willing to provide written consent for their child to participate in the
             study

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  The child does not comply with the inclusion criteria

          -  The child has an aversion against yoghurt or milk products

          -  The child is lactose-intolerant as indicated by the parent, or has any other medical
             condition that will prevent him/her from taking yoghurt or milk products
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>3 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>7 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Remco Kort, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>VU Amsterdam</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Paragon primary and nursery School</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kabwohe</city>
        <state>Sheema</state>
        <country>Uganda</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Uganda</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dezateux, C., Williams, J., Walton, S., Wells, J., 2016. Life Study Standard Operating Procedures: Adult Anthropometry.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Williams, J., Walton, S., Wells, J., 2016. Life Study Standard Operating Procedures: Infant Anthropometry.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>World Health Organization (Ed.), 2007. WHO child growth standards: head circumference-for-age, arm circumference-for-age, triceps skinfold-for-age and subscapular skinfold-for-age: methods and development. World Health Organization, Geneva</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>World Health Organization (Ed.), 2006. WHO child growth standards: length/height-for-age, weight-for-age, weight-for-length, weight-for-height and body mass index-for-age ; methods and development. WHO Press, Geneva.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pineiro M, Stanton C. Probiotic bacteria: legislative framework-- requirements to evidence basis. J Nutr. 2007 Mar;137(3 Suppl 2):850S-3S. doi: 10.1093/jn/137.3.850S.</citation>
    <PMID>17311986</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Petschow BW, Figueroa R, Harris CL, Beck LB, Ziegler E, Goldin B. Effects of feeding an infant formula containing Lactobacillus GG on the colonization of the intestine: a dose-response study in healthy infants. J Clin Gastroenterol. 2005 Oct;39(9):786-90.</citation>
    <PMID>16145341</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Scalabrin D, Harris C, Johnston WH, Berseth CL. Long-term safety assessment in children who received hydrolyzed protein formulas with Lactobacillus rhamnosus GG: a 5-year follow-up. Eur J Pediatr. 2017 Feb;176(2):217-224. doi: 10.1007/s00431-016-2825-4. Epub 2016 Dec 15.</citation>
    <PMID>27975116</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kort R, Westerik N, Mariela Serrano L, Douillard FP, Gottstein W, Mukisa IM, Tuijn CJ, Basten L, Hafkamp B, Meijer WC, Teusink B, de Vos WM, Reid G, Sybesma W. A novel consortium of Lactobacillus rhamnosus and Streptococcus thermophilus for increased access to functional fermented foods. Microb Cell Fact. 2015 Dec 8;14:195. doi: 10.1186/s12934-015-0370-x.</citation>
    <PMID>26643044</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kort R, Sybesma W. Probiotics for every body. Trends Biotechnol. 2012 Dec;30(12):613-5. doi: 10.1016/j.tibtech.2012.09.002. Epub 2012 Sep 29. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23031355</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>November 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 14, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 27, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 30, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 29, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 29, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">December 2, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>VU University of Amsterdam</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Remco Kort</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Lactobacillus rhamnosus yoba 2012</keyword>
  <keyword>Children</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Infection</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Respiratory Tract Infections</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Tinea Capitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Common Cold</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Skin Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diarrhea</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

