<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04141696</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>200003</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>20-NR-0003</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04141696</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Proof-of-Concept Trial on the Effect of Ketamine on Fatigue</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Proof-of-Concept Trial on the Effect of Ketamine on Fatigue</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Nursing Research (NINR)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      Many people experience fatigue as a side effect of their illnesses and treatments. There are
      no medicines to treat fatigue, but a drug called ketamine has reduced fatigue in depressed
      people. Researchers hope that ketamine, compared to a drug called midazolam, can reduce
      fatigue in people with illnesses.

      Objective:

      To test whether ketamine reduces fatigue in cancer survivors and people with chronic illness.

      Eligibility:

      Adults 18 and older who have fatigue and are cancer survivors or have been diagnosed with a
      chronic illness such as chronic fatigue syndrome and lupus.

      Design:

      Participants will be screened with a physical exam, medical history, blood and urine tests,
      questions about their fatigue, and breathalyzer test.

      During phase 1, participants will complete rating their fatigue using questionnaires. They
      will be provided thinking, memory, and motivation tests. They will also take a handgrip test.
      For this study, the participant will have an IV, which a needle guides a thin plastic tube
      (intravenous or IV line) into an arm in their vein. An IV will be required for two of the
      visits. They will get a single dose of either ketamine or midazolam through an IV line over
      40 minutes. Participants must be accompanied by a responsible friend/family/colleague to take
      them home after getting the study drug.

      Participants will have follow-up visits where they repeat the above tests. They will also
      have follow-up phone calls.

      Phase 2 is the same as phase 1, but participants get the other study drug.

      The study lasts 1 month. Each phase lasts 2 weeks. Participants will have 6-8 total NIH
      visits. For the whole study, they will wear a device on their wrists that records physical
      activity.

      Drug side effects can include vivid dreams, seeing colors, perceiving time as moving slower
      or faster than normal, dizziness, headache, restlessness, nausea, or vomiting, among others.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Purpose: The purpose of the study is to investigate the anti-fatigue effects of ketamine in
      individuals with chronic illness.

      Background: Although the underlying mechanisms of fatigue have been studied in several
      disease conditions, the etiology, mechanisms, and risk factors remain elusive and this
      symptom remains poorly managed. Fatigue is conceptualized as a multidimensional symptom which
      incorporates temporal, sensory, cognitive/mental, affective/emotional, behavioral, and
      physiological dimensions. It is described as a common, chronic, and disabling symptom in
      individuals with Sjogren s syndrome and those with systemic lupus erythematosus. We recently
      observed that upregulation of glutamate receptors (e.g.,GRM5) can predict individuals who
      will develop chronic fatigue one year after completing cancer therapy, suggesting that
      fatigue may share common glutamatergic markers with depression. Ketamine is an
      N-methyl-D-aspartate (NMDA) receptor antagonist and has been reported to have rapid
      anti-depressant effects, and we recently found that it also has rapid anti-fatigue effects.
      Evidence suggest that severe fatigue in diverse medical conditions is driven by similar
      biological mechanisms, hence identifying a potential anti-fatigue agent in one medical
      condition may be a valuable anti-fatigue therapy for other fatiguing conditions.

      Population for Study: This proof-of-concept study will enroll 59 individuals (target n of
      completers = 50) with chronic fatigue.

      Key Inclusion/Exclusion Criteria: Participants must have a fatigue visual analog scale

      (VAS) score of greater than or equal to 50 mm (on a 0-100 mm horizontal scale). The greater
      than or equal to 50 mm fatigue VAS score is considered clinically important fatigue cutoff
      score for patients with chronic illness, and also captures the effectivity outcome of a
      previous pharmacologic intervention for fatigue. The participants must not have any
      progressive or unstable conditions or be taking medications that cause fatigue.

      Methodology: This is a phase II, randomized, double-blind (study team and participants),
      active comparator-controlled, cross-over trial. After determining eligibility during the
      screening visit, the participant will be randomized to determine the sequence of study
      drug/active comparator to take during each phase.

      Main Study Events / Estimates of Duration and Time Commitments: The study has two periods,
      and each period is approximately two weeks long (total of four weeks). The study (both
      periods, excluding the screening visit) will require eight NIH outpatient visits and three
      phone calls.

      Primary and Representative Secondary Outcomes: The primary outcome measure of the study is
      the change in self-reported fatigue VAS score before and three days after receiving ketamine
      or active comparator (midazolam). A 20% decrease in fatigue VAS score three days after
      ketamine treatment will be considered the primary indicator of efficacy in this study. The
      secondary outcomes of this study include: symptoms, physical activity count, skeletal muscle
      strength, motivation score, cognitive function test scores, changes in gene expression or
      protein levels of pro-inflammatory markers (e.g., lymphotoxin, IFNy, TNF alpha) typically
      seen in fatigue, and neurometabolite (e.g., BDNF) levels and bioenergetic markers (e.g.,
      oxygen consumption rate from peripheral blood mononuclear cells [PBMCs]) and after a dose of
      ketamine or active comparator.

      General Analytic Plans: A linear mixed model with restricted maximum likelihood estimation
      will be used to examine changes in fatigue symptoms over the course of the trial where all
      participants with at least a pre-dose and one post-dose measure will be included.
      Within-subjects factors will include time with pre-dose and all other points. The interaction
      between time and ketamine treatment will be included along with the fixed intercept. Multiple
      test corrections (e.g., Bonferroni post hoc tests) will be used to examine differences
      between levels of significant effects.

      The primary outcome measure of the study is the change in fatigue score as measured by the
      self-reported fatigue instrument.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">July 31, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 30, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 30, 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>change in self-reported fatigue score</measure>
    <time_frame>before and 3 days after receiving Ketamine or active placebo</time_frame>
    <description>The primary outcome measure of the study is the percentage placebo change in self-reported fatigue VAS score before and 3 daysafter receiving ketamine or active placebo for each individual study participant. A 20% change in fatigue VAS score 3 days after ketamine treatment will be considered indication of efficacy in thisstudy.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cognition; skeletal muscle strength; motivation</measure>
    <time_frame>before and after a dose of Ketamine or active placebo at multiple time points (at +40 min, at +80 min, at +120 min, at +230 min, at 24hours, at 7 days, and at 14 days).</time_frame>
    <description>cognition; skeletal muscle strength; motivation</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in gene expression or protein levels of pro-inflammatorymarkers levels and bioenergetic markers</measure>
    <time_frame>before and after a dose of Ketamine or active placebo at multiple time points (at +40 min, at +80 min, at +120 min, at +230 min, at 24hours, at 7 days, and at 14 days).</time_frame>
    <description>change in gene expression or protein levels of pro inflammatory markers levels and bioenergetic markers</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">59</enrollment>
  <condition>Fatigue</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Ketamine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Given intravenously over 40 minutes</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Midazolam</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Given intravenously over 40 minutes</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ketamine</intervention_name>
    <description>Given intravenously over 40 minutes</description>
    <arm_group_label>Ketamine</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Midazolam</intervention_name>
    <description>Given intravenously over 40 minutes</description>
    <arm_group_label>Midazolam</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

               1. Have chronic, persistent fatigue for at least 6 months;

                    1. Intensity greater than or equal to 50 mm using fatigue VAS (on a 0-100 mm
                       horizontal fatigue scale, 0 = no fatigue, 100 = worst fatigue).

                    2. Chronicity greater than or equal to six months using the first item of the
                       revised Piper Fatigue Scale.

               2. Be a cancer survivor with a documented medical report of completing primary
                  cancer treatment &gt; 6 months ago (except hormone and vaccine therapies) OR
                  diagnosed as having ME/CFS with clinical documentation that patient meets the
                  2015 IOM Diagnostic Criteria;

               3. Able to provide written informed consent;

               4. Able to have an accompanying responsible adult for drug infusion study visits;

               5. &gt;= 18 years of age at the time of signing the informed consent form;

               6. Participants may be NIH employees/staff (see below for some exclusion);

               7. For individuals of childbearing potential; must use at least one of the following
                  highly effective birth control methods for the duration of the study:

          -  Prescribed hormonal oral contraceptives, vaginal ring, or transdermal patch.

          -  Intrauterine device (IUD).

          -  Intrauterine hormone-releasing system (IUS).

          -  Depot/implantable hormone (e.g., Depo-provera , Implanon).

          -  Bilateral tubal occlusion/ligation.

             8. For individuals of non-childbearing potential; as defined by the following
             criteria:

          -  Postmenopausal defined as 12 months of spontaneous amenorrhea or follicle-stimulating
             hormone (FSH) serum level &gt; 40mIU/mL;. appropriate documentation is required.

          -  Surgically sterile by hysterectomy and/or bilateral oophorectomy with appropriate
             documentation of surgical procedure.

          -  Has a congenital condition resulting in no uterus. OR

          -  Is sterile

          -  Has documentation confirming vasectomy

          -  Agrees to use an appropriate method of contraception (e.g. barrier method with
             spermicide) for the duration of the study

        EXCLUSION CRITIERIA:

          1. Total body irradiation or cranial irradiation for cancer;

          2. Has a diagnosis of progressive or unstable disease to any body system causing
             clinically significant fatigue (e.g., class IV congestive heart failure, end-stage
             renal disease, liver failure, stage IV chronic obstructive pulmonary disease)
             including patients with systemic infections (e.g., human immunodeficiency virus (HIV),
             active hepatitis);

          3. Individuals with comorbid conditions other than clinically stable cardiovascular and
             metabolic conditions;

          4. Current or past psychiatric disorders including medically documented depression with
             psychosis, bipolar disorder, schizophrenia;

          5. Clinically documented post-traumatic stress syndrome and/or traumatic brain injury
             because of the high risk for ketamine to exacerbate symptoms including hallucinations;

          6. Categorized as a high-risk drinker (&gt;=5 drinks/day and &gt;=15 drinks/week for men, &gt;=4
             drinks/day and &gt;=8 drinks/week for women). (&quot;Dietary Guidelines for Americans
             2015-2020,&quot; U.S. Department of Health and Human Services and U.S. Department of
             Agriculture);

          7. Detectable blood alcohol content (BAC) &gt;1 mg/dL using breathalyzer;

          8. Current substance use disorder within the last five years as diagnosed on the
             Structured Clinical Interview for DSM-5 (SCID-5) or positive urine toxicology results
             at enrollment;

          9. Participants with clinical hypothyroidism or hyperthyroidism defined by abnormal
             thyroid stimulating hormone TSH;

         10. Poorly controlled hypertension as judged by the Principal Investigator and confirmed
             by repeat assessment during the screening period (SBP &gt;160 and DBP &gt; 100 in all
             readings);

         11. Any medical condition causing impairment in mobility (e.g., stroke with residual
             neuromuscular weakness). This may prohibit the assessment of study outcomes, such as
             physical activity;

         12. Any change in dose of regularly scheduled medication or initiation of a new medication
             (excluding PRN medications) within four weeks prior to signing the informed consent
             form and throughout the entire duration of the study;

         13. Taking concomitant medication known to interact with ketamine and/or midazolam 14 days
             prior to study drug administration and during the study. The medications are shown
             below:

               -  LIST OF PSYCHIATRIC MEDICATIONS ALLOWED AND NOT ALLOWED DURING THE STUDY*

                    -  Drug class: Antidepressants;

                         -  Episodic Use(as needed): No; Chronic Use:No;

                         -  Restrictions: Treatment with fluoxetine or aripiprazole is an exclusion
                            because of their long half-life.

                    -  Drug class: Antipsychotics;

                       --- Episodic Use(as needed): No; Chronic Use:No

                    -  Drug class: Anxiolytics;

                       --- Episodic Use(as needed): No; Chronic Use:No;

                    -  Drug class: Mood Stabilizers;

                       --- Episodic Use(as needed): No; Chronic Use:No;

                    -  Drug class: Psychotropic drugs not otherwise specified (including herbal
                       products);

                         -  Episodic Use(as needed): No; Chronic Use:No;

                         -  Restrictions: No drugs with psychomotor effects or with anxiolytic,
                            stimulant, antipsychotic, or sedative properties are allowed.

                    -  Drug class: Sedatives/Hypnotics;

                       --- Episodic Use(as needed): No; Chronic Use:No

                    -  Drug class: Analgesics;

                         -  Episodic Use(as needed): Yes; Chronic Use:No;

                         -  Restrictions: Non-narcotic analgesics only

                    -  Drug class: Anorexics (sibuteramine);

                       --- Episodic Use(as needed): No; Chronic Use:No

                    -  Drug class: Antacids;

                       --- Episodic Use(as needed): Yes; Chronic Use:Yes;

                    -  Drug class: Antianginal Agents;

                       --- Episodic Use(as needed): No; Chronic Use:No;

                    -  Drug class: Antiarrhythmics;

                       --- Episodic Use(as needed): No; Chronic Use:No;

                    -  Drug class: Antiasthma Agents;

                         -  Episodic Use(as needed): Yes; Chronic Use:Yes

                         -  Restrictions: Systematic corticosteroids are not allowed

                    -  Drug class: Antibiotics;

                         -  Episodic Use(as needed): Yes; Chronic Use:No;

                         -  Except erythromycin (see P450-3A4 enzyme inhibitors below)

                    -  Drug class: Anticholinergics;

                       --- Episodic Use(as needed): No; Chronic Use:No;

                    -  Drug class: Anticoagulants;

                       --- Episodic Use(as needed): No; Chronic Use:No;

                    -  Drug class: Anticonvulsants;

                         -  Episodic Use(as needed): No; Chronic Use:No;

                         -  Restrictions: Carbamazepine, phenytoin, and oxcarbazepine are 3A4
                            inducers and significantly decrease perampanel levels. Topiramate may
                            increase perampanel levels up to 20%

                    -  Drug class: Antidiarrheal Preparations;

                       --- Episodic Use(as needed): Yes; Chronic Use:No;

                    -  Drug class: Analgesics-Systemic;

                       --- Episodic Use(as needed): No; Chronic Use:No;

                    -  Drug class: Analgesics-Topical;

                       --- Episodic Use(as needed): Yes; Chronic Use:Yes;

                    -  Drug class: Antihistamines-Nonsedating;

                       --- Episodic Use(as needed): Yes; Chronic Use:Yes;

                    -  Drug class: Antihistamines-Sedating;

                       --- Episodic Use(as needed): N; Chronic Use:No;

                    -  Drug class: Antihypertensives;

                         -  Episodic Use(as needed): Yes; Chronic Use:Y;

                         -  Restrictions: Non-narcotic analgesics only

                    -  Drug class: Anti-inflammatory Drugs;

                         -  Episodic Use(as needed): Yes; Chronic Use:Y(a);

                         -  Restrictions: Systematic corticosteroids are not allowed.

                    -  Drug class: Antinauseants;

                       --- Episodic Use(as needed): Yes; Chronic Use:Yes;

                    -  Drug class: Antineoplastics;

                       --- Episodic Use(as needed): No; Chronic Use:No;

                    -  Drug class: Antiobesity;

                       --- Episodic Use(as needed): No; Chronic Use:No;

                    -  Drug class: Antivirals;

                         -  Episodic Use(as needed): No; Chronic Use:No;

                         -  Restrictions: Except for treatment of HSV with agents without CNS
                            activity e.g. acyclovir, ganciclovir, famciclovir, valacyclovir

                    -  Drug class: Cough/Cold Preparations;

                         -  Episodic Use(as needed): Yes; Chronic Use:No;

                         -  Restrictions: Dextromethorphan preps- N/N, Guaifenesin - Y/Y,
                            Pseudoephedrine- N/N

                    -  Drug class: Diuretics;

                         -  Episodic Use(as needed): Yes; Chronic Use:Y(b);

                         -  Restrictions: Non-narcotic analgesics only

                    -  Drug class: H2-Blockers/ PPI;

                         -  Episodic Use(as needed): Yes; Chronic Use:Y(b);

                         -  Restrictions: Except cimetidine (see P450-3A4 enzyme inhibitors below)

                    -  Drug class: Hormones;

                         -  Episodic Use(as needed): N; Chronic Use:Y(b);

                         -  Restrictions: Only thyroid hormone replacement, oral contraceptives,
                            and estrogen replacement therapy are allowed.

                    -  Drug class: Hypoglycemic Agents;

                         -  Episodic Use(as needed): No; Chronic Use:Yes(b);

                         -  Restrictions: Only oral hypoglycemic agents are allowed.

                    -  Drug class: Antihyperlipidemics

                       --- Episodic Use(as needed): No; Chronic Use:No(b);

                    -  Drug class: Insulin

                       --- Episodic Use(as needed): No; Chronic Use:No;

                    -  Drug class: Laxatives

                       --- Episodic Use(as needed): Yes; Chronic Use:Yes;

                    -  Drug class: Muscle Relaxants

                       --- Episodic Use(as needed): No; Chronic Use:No;

                    -  Drug class: P450-3A4 enzyme inhibitors

                         -  Episodic Use(as needed): No; Chronic Use:No;

                         -  Restrictions: Including cimetidine, erythromycin, diltiazem, verapamil,
                            ketoconazole, and itraconazole (topical ketoconazole allowed)

                    -  Drug class: Protease Inhibitor

                         -  Episodic Use(as needed): No; Chronic Use:No;

                         -  Restrictions: Including Saquinavir

             a Allowed only if being taken prior to enrolling in the study.

             b Allowed only if being taken for at least 2 months prior to enrolling in the study
             and the dose has been stable for at least 1 month.

             *Some medications in the above table may be indicated for exclusionary conditions;
             therefore, it would be unlikely that participants meeting inclusion will be taking
             them.

         14. Medical diagnosis of sleep disorder requiring medical intervention such as obstructive
             sleep apnea that increase risks of sedation;

         15. Medically diagnosed kidney disease;

         16. Medically diagnosed acute narrow-angle glaucoma;

         17. Allergic to ketamine, benzodiazepines, flumazenil;

         18. With poor IV access;

         19. NINR employees or subordinates, relatives, and/or co-workers of NINR employees/staff
             or study investigators;

         20. Pregnant or lactating individuals.

         21. Ongoing medical condition that is deemed by the Principal Investigator to interfere
             with the conduct or assessments of the study or safety of the participant.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Leorey N Saligan, C.R.N.P.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Institute of Nursing Research (NINR)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Angela Wang, R.N.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 841-5085</phone>
    <email>tzu-fang.wang@nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>For more information at the NIH Clinical Center contact Office of Patient Recruitment (OPR)</last_name>
      <phone>800-411-1222</phone>
      <phone_ext>TTY8664111010</phone_ext>
      <email>prpl@cc.nih.gov</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?A_2020-NR-0003.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Saligan LN, Luckenbaugh DA, Slonena EE, Machado-Vieira R, Zarate CA Jr. An assessment of the anti-fatigue effects of ketamine from a double-blind, placebo-controlled, crossover study in bipolar disorder. J Affect Disord. 2016 Apr;194:115-9. doi: 10.1016/j.jad.2016.01.009. Epub 2016 Jan 19.</citation>
    <PMID>26807672</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sharpe M, Wilks D. Fatigue. BMJ. 2002 Aug 31;325(7362):480-3. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>12202331</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>July 16, 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 25, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 25, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 28, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 25, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 25, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">July 28, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Anesthetics</keyword>
  <keyword>Signs and Symptoms</keyword>
  <keyword>Midazolam</keyword>
  <keyword>Physiological Effects of Drugs</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Fatigue</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Midazolam</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ketamine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

