<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04149236</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>19-1828</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04149236</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Qualitative Study of Cultural Perception of Health in Rural Guatemala</brief_title>
  <acronym>deCiPHeRGap</acronym>
  <official_title>A Qualitative Study of Cultural Perception of Health in Rural Guatemala</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Colorado, Denver</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Colorado, Denver</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The Investigators will be giving a survey to ~100 people in a rural community in Guatemala to
      discover beliefs and perspectives that the Participants have surrounding various aspects of
      healthcare. The Investigators aim to do this in order to be able to better serve the
      population in the community by discovering specific information about them from the
      Participants and how the Participants about different health practices. The Investigators
      will answer their research questions through the questionnaire that will allow participants
      to explain their viewpoints about a variety of medical topics.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The design of this cross-sectional study is centered around a structured questionnaire of a
      mixed qualitative and quantitative nature that is composed primarily of yes/no or Likert
      scale responses. All questions are written with the intent that they may be understood by
      those participants without any formal education. The investigators will recruit participants
      that are currently using the services of the Trifinio clinic in rural Guatemala as these are
      likely to fit inclusion criteria and will be able to benefit from potential future services
      that will be directed by the findings of this questionnaire. For all participants, Likert
      scale questions will be used with a series of faces to help indicate meanings for the answers
      and to decrease possibility of misinterpretation. Participants will be recruited through
      non-probabilistic sampling and the use of snowball sampling. Screening of these participants
      for exclusion criteria will be performed before questionnaires are distributed. The questions
      of the questionnaire are designed to elicit information about certain beliefs or preferences
      related to healthcare in a structured manner that allows us to compare answers and determine
      trends, prevalence, and associations that are likely to exist among community members.
      Participation will be completely voluntary and informed consent will be obtained from each
      participant before they are given the questionnaire. For participants who are illiterate or
      would prefer to have the informed consent and questionnaire read aloud to them, this will be
      done by one of the CITI-trained investigators. Recorded data will only include questionnaire
      responses and will not include any identifying information. We will be using randomized
      numbers in order to refer to completed questionnaires, but these numbers will have no
      identifying aspects and will be used for the sole purpose of keeping track of the gathered
      data. The information gathered will be de-identified and stored and password-protected
      through REDCap.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">February 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Other</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Cross-Sectional</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Prevalence of Gaps in Knowledge Surrounding Health Services</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1</time_frame>
    <description>A survey with yes/no questions whether a participant is aware of health services available to them. Answers will be scored as 1 = Yes/Aware or 0=No/Not Aware.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Perceptions of Healthcare, as Determined by Agreeability of Statements</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1</time_frame>
    <description>Likert scale responses will be shown to participants who will choose among 5 answers ranging from &quot;Very Much So Disagree&quot; to &quot;Very Much So Agree&quot;. The answers chosen will be summed and put into percentages that each answer receives, demonstrating prevalence of those beliefs among the participants.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Qualitative Research</condition>
  <condition>Beliefs</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        The study population will consist of local rural Guatemalans that live within 50 km of the
        clinic site that wish to participate in completing a questionnaire to better inform the
        clinic of community needs, educational opportunities, and available resources.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age 18-64

          -  Willing and able to participate in the questionnaire (if participant is illiterate,
             they will have the option to have each question and all responses read to them aloud
             by one of the trained researchers)

          -  Live in one of the communities within 50 km of the research site

          -  Those participants born in Guatemala

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  &lt; 18 or &gt;64 years old

          -  Decisionally challenged

          -  Refusal or inability to give consent

          -  Those born outside of Guatemala

          -  Those living in areas &gt; 50 km from the research site
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>64 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>James L Martin</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Colorado, Denver</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>James L Martin, PharmD(c)</last_name>
    <phone>512-538-5929</phone>
    <email>james.3.martin@cuanschutz.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <verification_date>January 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 29, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 31, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">November 4, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 13, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 13, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 18, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Culture</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>The Investigators will de-identify participants and pool total data after questionnaire completion. The results of pooled data may be shared but individual participant data will not be.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

