<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04144712</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>FWA 000017685</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04144712</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Caffeine as Respiratory Stimulant in Preterm Infants</brief_title>
  <official_title>High Versus Low Dose Caffeine as Respiratory Stimulant in Preterm Infants</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Ain Shams University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Ain Shams University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>Yes</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      comparison between rate of occurance of apnea of prematurity AOP when using high and low dose
      caffeine
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Caffeine is one of the widely used medications in the neonatal care units and in spite of its
      widespread use in preterm infants, there has been little information about the optimal
      efficient dose in those patients Caffeine therapy for treatment of apnea of prematurity (AOP)
      is well established over the past few years, yet the optimal loading and maintenance dose of
      caffeine in preterm infants is not well-studied AOP is a common complication of preterm
      birth, which affects more than 80 % of neonates with a birth weight less than 1,000 g.
      Methylxanthine (MGs), including caffeine and theophylline, are a mainstay in the treatment
      and prevention of AOP The efficiency of caffeine, as a preferred methylxanthine, to stimulate
      respiration has been well proven as it has a significant favorable impact on neonatal
      morbidity as bronchopulmonary dysplasia (BPD) and patent ductus arteriosus (PDA) ligation.
      Also, the results of previous studies revealed that caffeine enhances respiratory muscle
      strength and lung function followed by easier weaning of mechanical ventilation in premature
      infants. Besides, a rapid and sustained increase in diaphragmatic activity and tidal volume
      was reported in preterm infants followed by caffeine administration Previous studies have
      shown that caffeine citrate was generally well tolerated by premature neonates in clinical
      trials and declined the incidence of apnea in this population compared with placebo. Also,
      caffeine is related to superior outcomes due to its lower toxicity and it is a preferred drug
      for apnea in preterm infants with respiratory problems. It has also a significant function as
      a noninvasive respiratory support. It facilitates the transition from invasive to noninvasive
      support, reduces the duration of positive airway pressure support and decreases the risk of
      BPD in preterm infants The optimum caffeine dose in preterm infants with AOP has not been
      well studied as well as heterogeneous reports on the optimal loading and maintenance dose of
      caffeine in several studies in terms of benefits and risks. Many investigations have been
      conducted about various dosing regimens in the improvement or prevention of respiratory
      disorders of premature infants. These dosage regimens, although, have been associated with
      varying degrees of success The aim of this study is to determine if the use of caffeine in
      doses higher than the currently standard dose can decrease the frequency of apnea in preterm
      infants without causing significant side effects
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">April 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>The current study will be carried on preterm infants admitted to the Neonatal Intensive Care Unit (NICU), Ain Shams University 80 Patients divided into two groups each group will contain 40 subjects Group sample sizes of 40 and 40 achieve 83% power to detect a difference of -7.0 regarding frequency of apnea attacks between the null hypothesis that both group means are 9.0 and the alternative hypothesis that the mean of group 2 is 16.0 with known group standard deviations of 3.7 and 5.2 and with a significance level (alpha) of 0.05000 using a two-sided Mann-Whitney test assuming that the actual distribution is uniform</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Care Provider)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>High Versus Low Dose Caffeine as Respiratory Stimulant in Preterm Infants</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline</time_frame>
    <description>assess occurrence of apnea of prematurity between infants receiving high and low dose caffeine</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">80</enrollment>
  <condition>Apnea of Prematurity</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>High Dose arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>subjects will receive the high dose of the drug</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>low dose arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>subject will receive low dose of the drug</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Caffeine Citrate</intervention_name>
    <description>study rate of occurrence of Apnea of Prematurity between the 2 groups</description>
    <arm_group_label>High Dose arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>low dose arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  • Preterm infants with a gestational age &lt;32 weeks in room air or CPAP (prophylactic).

               -  Preterm infants with gestational age 32-34 weeks who exhibited apnea of
                  prematurity within the first 10 days of life in room air or CPAP

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  • Major congenital malformations.

               -  Chromosomal anomalies.

               -  Preterm infants on mechanical ventilation.

               -  Preterm infants on NIPPV.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>10 Days</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Yasmin A Farid, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Pediatric Department Faculty of Medicine Ain shams University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ola G Badr El-Deen, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Pediatric Department Faculty of Medicine Ain shams University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Eslam M Mazrou, MBBCH</last_name>
    <phone>20201009429972</phone>
    <email>eslammazrou@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Faculty of Medicine ain shams University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cairo</city>
        <zip>11591</zip>
        <country>Egypt</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Yasmin A Farid, MD</last_name>
      <phone>20101001449558</phone>
      <email>yasmin_aly_farid@hotmail.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Egypt</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Faramarzi F, Shiran M, Rafati M, Farhadi R, Salehifar E, Nakhshab M. The efficacy and safety of two different doses of caffeine in respiratory function of preterm infants. Caspian J Intern Med. 2018 Winter;9(1):46-53. doi: 10.22088/cjim.9.1.46.</citation>
    <PMID>29387319</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schmidt B, Roberts RS, Davis P, Doyle LW, Barrington KJ, Ohlsson A, Solimano A, Tin W; Caffeine for Apnea of Prematurity Trial Group. Caffeine therapy for apnea of prematurity. N Engl J Med. 2006 May 18;354(20):2112-21.</citation>
    <PMID>16707748</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kraaijenga JV, Hutten GJ, de Jongh FH, van Kaam AH. The Effect of Caffeine on Diaphragmatic Activity and Tidal Volume in Preterm Infants. J Pediatr. 2015 Jul;167(1):70-5. doi: 10.1016/j.jpeds.2015.04.040. Epub 2015 May 15.</citation>
    <PMID>25982138</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mohammed S, Nour I, Shabaan AE, Shouman B, Abdel-Hady H, Nasef N. High versus low-dose caffeine for apnea of prematurity: a randomized controlled trial. Eur J Pediatr. 2015 Jul;174(7):949-56. doi: 10.1007/s00431-015-2494-8. Epub 2015 Feb 3.</citation>
    <PMID>25644724</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zhao Y, Tian X, Liu G. [Clinical effectiveness of different doses of caffeine for primary apnea in preterm infants]. Zhonghua Er Ke Za Zhi. 2016 Jan;54(1):33-6. doi: 10.3760/cma.j.issn.0578-1310.2016.01.008. Chinese.</citation>
    <PMID>26791921</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>October 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 28, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 29, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 30, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 6, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 6, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 7, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Ain Shams University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Eslam Mohammed Ali Mazrou</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator, Pediatric Resident</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Premature Birth</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Caffeine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Caffeine citrate</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

