<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04146376</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>VIPStudy</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04146376</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Von Willebrand Factor in Pregnancy (VIP) Study</brief_title>
  <acronym>VIP</acronym>
  <official_title>Von Willebrand Factor in Pregnancy (VIP) Study: A Multicenter Study of Wilate Use in Von Willebrand Disease for Childbirth</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Bloodworks</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Mary M. Gooley Hemophilia Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Ergomed</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Octapharma</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Bloodworks</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      In pregnant women with von Willebrand disease (VWD) who by the third trimester do not have
      von Willebrand factor (VWF) or factor VIII (FVIII) levels greater than 50-100%, specific
      guidance is lacking for delivery planning in terms of how high of a VWF level should be
      achieved to reduce bleeding.

      This is a prospective, open-label, cohort study in women with VWD using Wilate VWF
      replacement therapy to maintain trough or minimum VWF levels of 100-150% for delivery and the
      immediate postpartum period, followed by levels of 50-100% for 5-10 days after delivery,
      depending upon the route of delivery. The primary objective is to document the rate of
      primary postpartum hemorrhage (PPH). The secondary objective is to document further
      effectiveness outcomes and safety.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      For pregnant women with von Willebrand disease (VWD) who by the third trimester do not have
      von Willebrand factor (VWF) or factor VIII (FVIII) levels &gt; 50-100%, specific guidance is
      lacking for delivery planning for how high a VWF level should be achieved. Specifically,
      guidance is lacking on whether VWF replacement therapy should target a VWF minimum level in
      the 100-150% range, i.e., a range closer to the 200-250% levels observed in normal pregnancy.

      This is a prospective, open-label, cohort study using Wilate VWF replacement therapy, trough
      or minimum VWF levels of 100-150% will be maintained for delivery in women with VWD whose
      third trimester VWF levels are &lt;100%. This group is termed &quot;non-correctors&quot;. Women with VWD
      whose third trimester VWF levels spontaneously rise to &gt;100% will be assigned to the
      &quot;corrector&quot; group, and these women will not receive VWF replacement therapy. All patients
      will receive tranexamic acid for 14 days postpartum. Outcome parameters will be assessed for
      all patients.

      The investigators or qualified research personnel will approach all consecutive pregnant VWD
      patients until 65 non-corrector patients have completed the study protocol, and up to 30
      corrector patients have completed the study protocol. Patients with gestational week 34-38
      von Willebrand factor activity (VWF:Act) or von Willebrand factor ristocetin cofactor
      (VWF:RCo), and/or Factor VIII procoagulant activity (FVIII:C) less than 100 percent will be
      used to assign patients to the non-corrector group. When VWF collagen binding (VWF:CB)
      laboratory monitoring can be performed, patients with an isolated VWF:CB type 2 defect can
      also be enrolled.

      Rate of primary postpartum hemorrhage, severe postpartum hemorrhage, secondary postpartum
      hemorrhage will be measured. Safety and secondary laboratory measures will be assessed.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 12, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>rate of primary postpartum hemorrhage (PPH)</measure>
    <time_frame>within 24 hours postpartum</time_frame>
    <description>estimated blood loss greater than or equal to 1000 mL, or severe PPH defined as estimated blood loss greater than 2000 mL within 24 hours postpartum, as indicated by: visual estimation, pre- and post- weight of blood soaked materials, photospectrometry</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>rate of secondary postpartum hemorrhage (PPH)</measure>
    <time_frame>24 hours to 6 weeks postpartum</time_frame>
    <description>excessive blood loss: any transfusions not anticipated in the antepartum birth plan, including number and type of blood products transfused within 48 hours after treatment, any transfusions not anticipated in the antepartum birth plan, including number and type of blood products transfused beyond 48 hours after treatment, change in antepartum hemoglobin, change in pictorial blood assessment chart (PBAC) score, number of patients needing interventions for bleeding (e.g., use of Bakri balloon, angiographic embolization, B-Lynch sutures, surgical arterial ligation, or hysterectomy for persistent bleeding), iron levels (serum iron, TIBC, and ferritin) 6 weeks postpartum</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>occurrence of venous or arterial thrombus</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 42 days postpartum</time_frame>
    <description>clinically documented venous or arterial thrombus</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>occurrence of infusion-related reactions</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 42 days postpartum</time_frame>
    <description>clinically documented infusion-related reactions</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>laboratory assessment of efficacy and VWF replacement</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 42 days postpartum</time_frame>
    <description>central laboratory assessment of VWF parameters relative to bleeding</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">110</enrollment>
  <condition>Von Willebrand Diseases</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Non-Corrector</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients with gestational week 34-38 von Willebrand factor activity, or von Willebrand factor ristocetin cofactor, or Factor VIII procoagulant activity less than 100 percent will be termed non-correctors. When laboratory monitoring can be performed, patients with an isolated von Willebrand factor collagen binding type 2 defect, von Willebrand factor collagen binding less than 100 percent can also be enrolled and determined as a non-corrector.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Corrector</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients with von Willebrand factor parameter levels greater than or equal to 100 percent self-corrected at gestational weeks 34-38 will be termed correctors.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Use of a postpartum diary and additional blood draws</intervention_name>
    <description>A diary will be used to capture postpartum hemorrhage (PPH), Wilate and tranexamic acid use, other drug use, bleeding episodes, and treatment schedules.
Several blood draws additional to what is expected for routine clinical care will also be taken.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Non-Corrector</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>VWF replacement therapy with Wilate</intervention_name>
    <description>This study design uses on-label Wilate for VWF replacement therapy for delivery and the postpartum period in VWD patients whose VWF levels are &lt;100% in the third trimester of pregnancy</description>
    <arm_group_label>Non-Corrector</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Tranexamic acid</intervention_name>
    <description>This study design uses tranexamic acid for prophylaxis for postpartum hemorrhage for all women with VWD</description>
    <arm_group_label>Corrector</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Non-Corrector</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Use of a postpartum diary and additional blood draws.</intervention_name>
    <description>A diary will be used to capture postpartum hemorrhage (PPH), tranexamic acid use, other drug use, bleeding episodes, and treatment schedules.
Several blood draws additional to what is expected for routine clinical care will also be taken.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Corrector</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Plasma collection for coagulation parameters Whole blood collection for DNA and RNA analysis
      Cord blood sample
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        The investigators or qualified research personnel will approach all consecutive pregnant
        VWD patients. Patients who meet all of the inclusion criteria and none of the exclusion
        criteria are eligible for this study.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  von Willebrand Disease (VWD) patients defined prepartum as Type 1 per National Heart,
             Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI) criterion of von Willebrand Factor (VWF) level less
             than 30 percent, or Type 2, or Type 3

          -  VWF and Factor VIII (FVIII) levels obtained in gestational weeks 34-38 will determine
             enrollment in the non-corrector or corrector group:

          -  Patients with gestational week 34-38 VWF:Ag, VWF:Act (or VWF:RCo), or FVIII:Act less
             than 100 percent will be enrolled in the non-corrector group. In patients with an
             isolated VWF:CB type 2 defect, VWF:CB less than 100 percent can also be determined as
             a non-corrector

          -  Patients with VWF parameter levels greater than or equal to 100 percent self-corrected
             at gestational weeks 34-38 will be enrolled in the corrector group

          -  Written informed consent from the patient prepartum, before gestational week 39

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Presence of other concurrent disorder of hemostasis, platelet dysfunction, or collagen
             disorders

          -  Presence of liver disease or renal disease, clinical suspicion or diagnosis of
             preeclampsia or eclampsia, HELLP syndrome, TTP, DIC, or other acquired vasculopathy or
             coagulopathy

          -  Age less than 18 years

          -  Inability of the local laboratory to monitor the VWF laboratory tests needed during
             the course of treatment to determine Wilate dosing adjustments
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jill M Johnsen, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Bloodworks</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Barbara A Konkle, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Bloodworks</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Peter A Kouides, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Mary M. Gooley Hemophilia Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Sarah Ruuska, MPH</last_name>
    <phone>206-689-6193</phone>
    <email>sarahru@bloodworksnw.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Nadine Bolliger, MA</last_name>
    <phone>206-689-6139</phone>
    <email>nbolliger@bloodworksnw.org</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Washington Center for Bleeding Disorders at Bloodworks</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seattle</city>
        <state>Washington</state>
        <zip>98104</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Nadine Bolliger, MA</last_name>
      <phone>206-689-6139</phone>
      <email>NBolliger@bloodworksnw.org</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Sarah Ruuska, MPH</last_name>
      <phone>206-689-6193</phone>
      <email>SarahRu@bloodworksnw.org</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jill Johnsen, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>James AH, Konkle BA, Kouides P, Ragni MV, Thames B, Gupta S, Sood S, Fletcher SK, Philipp CS. Postpartum von Willebrand factor levels in women with and without von Willebrand disease and implications for prophylaxis. Haemophilia. 2015 Jan;21(1):81-7. doi: 10.1111/hae.12568. Epub 2014 Oct 21.</citation>
    <PMID>25333737</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Drury-Stewart DN, Lannert KW, Chung DW, Teramura GT, Zimring JC, Konkle BA, Gammill HS, Johnsen JM. Complex changes in von Willebrand factor-associated parameters are acquired during uncomplicated pregnancy. PLoS One. 2014 Nov 19;9(11):e112935. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0112935. eCollection 2014.</citation>
    <PMID>25409031</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kouides PA. Present day management of inherited bleeding disorders in pregnancy. Expert Rev Hematol. 2016 Oct;9(10):987-95. doi: 10.1080/17474086.2016.1216312. Epub 2016 Aug 2. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>27459638</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Abbassi-Ghanavati M, Greer LG, Cunningham FG. Pregnancy and laboratory studies: a reference table for clinicians. Obstet Gynecol. 2009 Dec;114(6):1326-31. doi: 10.1097/AOG.0b013e3181c2bde8. Review. Erratum in: Obstet Gynecol. 2010 Feb;115(2 Pt 1):387.</citation>
    <PMID>19935037</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Szecsi PB, Jørgensen M, Klajnbard A, Andersen MR, Colov NP, Stender S. Haemostatic reference intervals in pregnancy. Thromb Haemost. 2010 Apr;103(4):718-27. doi: 10.1160/TH09-10-0704. Epub 2010 Feb 19.</citation>
    <PMID>20174768</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Huq FY, Kulkarni A, Agbim EC, Riddell A, Tuddenham E, Kadir RA. Changes in the levels of factor VIII and von Willebrand factor in the puerperium. Haemophilia. 2012 Mar;18(2):241-5. doi: 10.1111/j.1365-2516.2011.02625.x. Epub 2011 Sep 28.</citation>
    <PMID>21951573</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nichols WL, Hultin MB, James AH, Manco-Johnson MJ, Montgomery RR, Ortel TL, Rick ME, Sadler JE, Weinstein M, Yawn BP. von Willebrand disease (VWD): evidence-based diagnosis and management guidelines, the National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI) Expert Panel report (USA). Haemophilia. 2008 Mar;14(2):171-232. doi: 10.1111/j.1365-2516.2007.01643.x.</citation>
    <PMID>18315614</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Demers C, Derzko C, David M, Douglas J; Society of Obstetricians and Gynecologists of Canada. Gynaecological and obstetric management of women with inherited bleeding disorders. J Obstet Gynaecol Can. 2005 Jul;27(7):707-32. English, French.</citation>
    <PMID>16100628</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mannucci PM, Franchini M, Castaman G, Federici AB; Italian Association of Hemophilia Centers. Evidence-based recommendations on the treatment of von Willebrand disease in Italy. Blood Transfus. 2009 Apr;7(2):117-26. doi: 10.2450/2008.0052-08.</citation>
    <PMID>19503633</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Laffan MA, Lester W, O'Donnell JS, Will A, Tait RC, Goodeve A, Millar CM, Keeling DM. The diagnosis and management of von Willebrand disease: a United Kingdom Haemophilia Centre Doctors Organization guideline approved by the British Committee for Standards in Haematology. Br J Haematol. 2014 Nov;167(4):453-65. doi: 10.1111/bjh.13064. Epub 2014 Aug 12. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25113304</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Stoof SC, van Steenbergen HW, Zwagemaker A, Sanders YV, Cannegieter SC, Duvekot JJ, Leebeek FW, Peters M, Kruip MJ, Eikenboom J. Primary postpartum haemorrhage in women with von Willebrand disease or carriership of haemophilia despite specialised care: a retrospective survey. Haemophilia. 2015 Jul;21(4):505-12. doi: 10.1111/hae.12635. Epub 2015 Feb 16.</citation>
    <PMID>25688733</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hawke L, Grabell J, Sim W, Thibeault L, Muir E, Hopman W, Smith G, James P. Obstetric bleeding among women with inherited bleeding disorders: a retrospective study. Haemophilia. 2016 Nov;22(6):906-911. doi: 10.1111/hae.13067. Epub 2016 Oct 5.</citation>
    <PMID>27704714</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Janssen CA, Scholten PC, Heintz AP. A simple visual assessment technique to discriminate between menorrhagia and normal menstrual blood loss. Obstet Gynecol. 1995 Jun;85(6):977-82.</citation>
    <PMID>7770270</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>James AH, Jamison MG. Bleeding events and other complications during pregnancy and childbirth in women with von Willebrand disease. J Thromb Haemost. 2007 Jun;5(6):1165-9.</citation>
    <PMID>17403089</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kirtava A, Drews C, Lally C, Dilley A, Evatt B. Medical, reproductive and psychosocial experiences of women diagnosed with von Willebrand's disease receiving care in haemophilia treatment centres: a case-control study. Haemophilia. 2003 May;9(3):292-7.</citation>
    <PMID>12694520</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Govorov I, Löfgren S, Chaireti R, Holmström M, Bremme K, Mints M. Postpartum Hemorrhage in Women with Von Willebrand Disease - A Retrospective Observational Study. PLoS One. 2016 Oct 25;11(10):e0164683. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0164683. eCollection 2016. Erratum in: PLoS One. 2017 Feb 9;12 (2):e0172185.</citation>
    <PMID>27780267</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>James AH, Cooper DL, Paidas MJ. A global quantitative survey of hemostatic assessment in postpartum hemorrhage and experience with associated bleeding disorders. Int J Womens Health. 2017 Jul 3;9:477-485. doi: 10.2147/IJWH.S132135. eCollection 2017.</citation>
    <PMID>28740434</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kujovich JL. von Willebrand disease and pregnancy. J Thromb Haemost. 2005 Feb;3(2):246-53. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>15670029</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 29, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 29, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 31, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 6, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 6, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 7, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Bloodworks</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Jill Johnsen</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Member, Bloodworks Northwest Research Institute</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>von Willebrand Disease</keyword>
  <keyword>von Willebrand Factor</keyword>
  <keyword>postpartum hemorrhage</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Von Willebrand Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Tranexamic Acid</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

