<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04148365</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>257448</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04148365</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Medication Compliance in the Paediatric Uveitis Population Reported by the Patients and Parents</brief_title>
  <official_title>Medication Compliance in the Paediatric Uveitis Population Reported by the Patients and Parents</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Manchester University NHS Foundation Trust</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Manchester University NHS Foundation Trust</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Little is known about eye drop regime adherence in the paediatric population. In particular,
      no previous research has investigated this in the paediatric uveitis population, a group who
      can require doses up to six times daily, and at frequencies that change month to month. The
      aim of the study is to quantify the range of adherence to eye drop medication, and to
      investigate some of the reasons for non-compliance in a child specific study. By learning
      more about compliance, this will help create treatments that are better suited to children.

      The study will recruit 50 children receiving eye drop treatment. After an interval of 1 week
      or more the children and their parents will be asked to complete a questionnaire about the
      frequency of the drops prescribed, and the frequency that they have used over the last
      interval. It will also ask questions about difficulties encountered administering the drops.

      Changes in eye drop bottle weight will be measured during the interval and the result
      compared.

      The information gathered from the questionnaires will be used to compare reports of adherence
      between the parent and child, the child's age and the bottle weight. The reasons reported for
      difficulties with adherence will also be reported. This is a preliminary investigatory study
      to identify whether an issue with medication non-adherence exists. The findings will be used
      to tailor further research into this area.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Purpose This study aims to provide new information about compliance with medications amongst
      children and adolescents in an outpatient Ophthalmic setting.

      Previous studies have demonstrated in other conditions that adherence to eye drop regimes is
      extremely varied (50% to 90% of prescribed drops (Tan 2005)) in a range of paediatric
      conditions including myopia, amblyopia, herpes simplex keratitis, allergic conjunctivitis.
      There has not been any research into eye drop adherence in the paediatric uveitis population.
      Previous enquiries into quality of life in JIA have not included questions about drop
      adherence, frequency of flare ups or drop side effects (van Dijkhuizen 2018). Although this
      condition is not common, the prevalence of paediatric uveitis is 27.9 per 100,000
      (Päivönsalo-Hietanen 2000), it has severe sight threatening complications despite modern
      treatment. The burden of disease can be substantial due to eye drops up to six times daily
      and weekly appointments during active episodes, as well as surveillance every 3-4 months in
      between flares.

      There are certain issues that are specific to uveitis which require investigation. These
      include the high frequency of steroid drops, changes in frequency on a week by week basis,
      and the fact that it is an asymptomatic condition in the early stages. Other studies
      reporting drop adherence in the paediatric population are limited because definitions of
      adherence and its measurement is inconsistent, and often not the primary outcome of a study.
      Parents and clinicians have expressed concerns about how achievable very frequent dosing is.
      If a threshold above which eye drop adherence becomes very unreliable exists, for instance
      more than four times each day, then clinicans could adjust treatment regimes to reflect this.
      This may encourage clinicans to be able to confidently advocate moving on to alternative
      therapies, such as biological treatment rather than increasing drop frequency.

      By measuring and understanding medication adherence in the paediatric and adolescent
      population helps design interventions to improve compliance and assess their success.
      Evidence of paediatric specific issues may also lead to the development of age adapted
      formulations or trial of existing products in novel ways, for instance slow release steroid
      inserts following paediatric cataract surgery (SY Lee 2002).

      Design Treatment will not be impacted by the study. There is no randomisation. Compliance may
      be impacted by awareness of being involved in a study. This is a major limitation of the
      study.

      However previous studies have been conducted investigating compliance and their finding have
      been held to be valid.

      A effort has been made in the design of PIS to provide patients with information about the
      study while limiting the impression that their medication compliance is under scrutiny.
      Additional vague questions have been added to the questionnaire to obscure the focus of the
      questions.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 14, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 1, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 1, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Only</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Cross-Sectional</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Frequency of reported medication errors (missed doses) among paediatric uveitis population.</measure>
    <time_frame>01/07/2020</time_frame>
    <description>to determine what level of compliance with eye drop regimes currently exists in the paediatric uveitis population.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>What factors effect adherence to eye drop regimes? Including the frequency of eye drops and who administers the eye drops.</measure>
    <time_frame>01/07/2020</time_frame>
    <description>Idenifying factors affecting adherence to taking eye drops</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Does the age of the child influence compliance?</measure>
    <time_frame>01/07/2020</time_frame>
    <description>What age is best compliant with eye drops</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>In children that are old enough to report drop use, is reported compliance comparable between child and parent?</measure>
    <time_frame>01/07/2020</time_frame>
    <description>Parent and child compliancy</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Uveitis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Paediatric Uveitis</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients with Uveitis below the age of 18 years.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Paediatric uveitis population who attend Paediatric Ophthalmology Department Uveitis
        Clinic.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Any child attending the Paediatric Ophthalmology Department Uveitis Clinic who is
             receiving eye drop treatment.

          -  Children with a diagnosis of uveitis receiving eye drop treatment between 0-18 years
             of age at the time of recruitment.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Children with follow up more than 3 months after the first meeting and consent will
             subsequently be excluded.

          -  At present the study does not have sufficient funding for translators. Potential
             participants that do not speak sufficient English to understand and respond to the
             questionnaire will be excluded. We hope to obtain additional funding following this
             preliminary research. A priority of any further work will be to provide translators
             and achieve a more inclusive approach.

          -  Children not accompanied by a person with parental responsibility will be excluded if
             they cannot provide their own consent.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>18 Years</maximum_age>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jane Ashworth</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Consultant Peadiatric Ophthalmologist</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Philippa Doyle</last_name>
    <phone>0161 276 3432</phone>
    <email>Philippa.doyle@mft.nhs.uk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Monika Cien</last_name>
    <phone>0161 701 1765</phone>
    <email>Monika.cien@mft.nhs.uk</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Manchester Royal Eye Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Manchester</city>
        <zip>M13 9WL</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Philippa Doyle</last_name>
      <phone>0161 276 3432</phone>
      <email>Philippa.Doyle@mft.nhs.uk</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Monika Cien</last_name>
      <phone>0161 701 1765</phone>
      <email>Monika.Cien@mft.nhs.uk</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 30, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 31, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">November 1, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 16, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 16, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 17, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Paediatrics</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Uveitis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

