<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04145323</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2019-0557</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>SMPH/SURGERY/SURGTRAMA</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>A539714</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>UW19043</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04145323</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Novel Application of Indocyanine Green as a Biomarker to Identify Tissue Necrosis in Mastectomy Patients</brief_title>
  <official_title>Novel Application of Indocyanine Green as a Biomarker to Identify Tissue Necrosis in Mastectomy Patients</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Wisconsin, Madison</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Wisconsin, Madison</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Breast reconstruction is a common procedure that can dramatically improve the quality of life
      and satisfaction for women who undergo mastectomy, with over 100,000 procedures performed in
      the U.S. in 2018. The success of this procedure, however, is limited by its complications,
      including mastectomy skin flap necrosis, which occurs at a rate a 10-15%. Mastectomy skin
      flap necrosis causes significant morbidity in patients undergoing breast reconstruction,
      potentially compromising results and delaying oncologic management. In addition, necrosis can
      lead to infection, implant loss, and need for reoperation.

      Current approaches to identify mastectomy skin flap necrosis rely largely on the surgeon's
      assessment of skin flap color, capillary refill, temperature turgor and dermal bleeding.
      However, clinical assessment of necrosis is subjective and is not a reliable predictor of
      postoperative complications. ICG microangiography is an accepted adjunct method to aid in
      clinical judgment by identifying poor perfusion as a surrogate marker for tissue at risk for
      necrosis during reconstructive surgical procedures. However, transient alterations in blood
      flow seen by this method may not represent actual necrosis. Furthermore, the common practice
      of using vasoconstriction methods to prevent massive blood loss in plastic surgery also
      alters microperfusion and renders the microangiography inaccurate. There is an unmet need for
      reliable methods to identify mastectomy skin flap necrosis during or post breast
      reconstruction procedure in order to improve patient outcomes.

      Recently in animal models of burn or ischemic injuries, ICG dye was shown to preferentially
      bind to exposed phospholipids in the membranes of necrotic cells, thus acting as a biomarker
      for necrotic tissue, when imaged a day after injection rather than minutes after injection,
      as is standard for microangiographic use of ICG. This necrosis-avid property of ICG has broad
      translational potential for clinical use in a variety of disease processes that result in
      necrosis. However, no clinical application of the necrosis-avid property of ICG has been
      reported yet. In this study, the investigator will test the feasibility of combining the
      necrosis-avid property of ICG and the SPY imaging system at University of Wisconsin hospital
      to obtain delayed imaging of ICG fluorescence for direct necrosis detection in breast
      reconstruction in mastectomy patients.

      This project is an early feasibility study to establish whether ICG imaging, in a delayed
      fashion, can be used in mastectomy patients to aid in the detection of necrotic tissue in
      breast reconstruction wounds. Investigators will use the preliminary data generated from this
      pilot study to generate hypotheses and to power future studies.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 25, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 19, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 19, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Early Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Sequential Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Comparison of Necrotic tissue area determined visually by the operating surgeon vs indocyanine Green (ICG) microangiography</measure>
    <time_frame>24 hour post ICG injection</time_frame>
    <description>Compare the risk of necrosis as determined visually by the operating surgeon at the time of mastectomy and reconstruction vs using microangiographic properties of ICG.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to achieve the peak fluorescent signal from necrotic tissue using ICG</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 3 days</time_frame>
    <description>Sequential fluorescence images of necrotic tissue identified by ICG fluorescence will be collected over time to identify the peak signal of fluorescence and determine correlation to time from surgery.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage overlap of identified areas of necrosis determined by ICG and clinical standard of care</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 3 days</time_frame>
    <description>Compare identified areas of necrosis between ICG and clinical outcome to determine the percentage overlap of necrosis.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">10</enrollment>
  <condition>Breast Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Necrosis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>ICG microangiography for necrotic tissue determination</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>During flap procedure, the study area of the patient will be imaged with a white light digital camera prior to a 5 mg dose of ICG as per FDA approved protocol for use of SPY device in microangiography. Following ICG injection, the study area will undergo fluorescence imaging using the SPY system to obtain microangiography perfusion data (baseline imaging - Standard of Care). During the standard postoperative evaluation (approximately 4 hours after baseline) and 24 hours after baseline, the study area will undergo repeat digital photography and fluorescence imaging using SPY for necrosis avid detection of ICG (Research only session). This evaluation with digital photography and fluorescence imaging will continue every 24 hours for the first 3 days after surgery or one day prior to discharge(Research only session).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ICG microangiography</intervention_name>
    <description>Indocyanine Green (ICG) is a FDA approved dye which preferentially bind to exposed phospholipids in the membranes of necrotic cells, thus acting as a biomarker for necrotic tissue.</description>
    <arm_group_label>ICG microangiography for necrotic tissue determination</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Female, age 18 years or older

          -  Subject undergoes mastectomy

          -  Subject receives intraoperative ICG during their breast reconstruction procedure

          -  Subject is expected to need at least 4 days of hospitalization as determined by the
             attending plastic surgeon on admission

          -  Subject understands the study procedures and can provide informed consent to
             participate in the study and authorization for release of relevant protected health
             information to the study investigator.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Subject has known contraindication to ICG injection, i.e. previous reaction to ICG
             (adverse event rate 1 in 42,00010)

          -  Subject has Iodine allergy

          -  Subject is pregnant
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <gender_based>Yes</gender_based>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Angela L Gibson, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Wisconsin, Madison</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Samuel O Poore, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Wisconsin, Madison</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Wisconsin</name>
      <address>
        <city>Madison</city>
        <state>Wisconsin</state>
        <zip>53792</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 28, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 28, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 30, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 16, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 16, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 18, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>mastectomy</keyword>
  <keyword>Breast reconstruction</keyword>
  <keyword>necrosis</keyword>
  <keyword>Indocyanine Green</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Necrosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

