<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04146025</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>833693</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04146025</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Nurtured in Nature</brief_title>
  <official_title>Leveraging Urban Nature, Behavioral Economics, and Mobile Platforms to Prevent Postpartum Depression</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Pennsylvania</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Pennsylvania</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The investigators pilot test a Nature Coach Intervention in a population of postpartum women,
      to increase the amount of time people spend outside in local nature, with the goal of
      preventing postpartum depression.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Postpartum depression (PPD), characterized by feelings of sadness, irritability, and fatigue
      following the birth of a child, occurs in 10-15% of women. PPD peaks within the first 2-3
      months following delivery, but can occur anytime in the first year, representing one of the
      most common complications of childbearing. The consequences go beyond impaired functioning
      for the woman, and include harmful effects on the cognitive and emotional development of the
      woman's infant. Despite this, many women are undiagnosed and do not get adequate treatment.

      Living near and spending time in green space is associated with a host of mental health
      benefits, including reduced depression and improved well-being. Research has shown that women
      who live near more green space have improved birth outcomes such as higher birthweight
      infants.

      Despite the growing body of evidence linking nature with improved mental health, spending
      time in green space is not a standard health promoting tool to address mental illness.
      Behavioral economics concepts have been used successfully in promoting other preventative
      health behaviors such as physical activity and healthy eating.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 12, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 1, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">January 1, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Green space use</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>This will be measured using Global Positioning System (GPS) data to see the amount of time spent in green space.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Prevention of postpartum depression</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>This will be measured using the Edinburgh Postnatal Depression Scale. The Edinburgh Postnatal Depression Scale is a 10-statement scale that was developed to identify women who may have postpartum depression. Each answer is given a score of 0 to 3.The maximum score is 30
Questions 1, 2, &amp; 4 are scored 0, 1, 2 or 3 with the first choice option scored as a 0 and the last choice option scored as 3. Questions 3, 5-10 are reverse scored, with the first choice option scored as a 3 and the last choice option scored as a 0. A score of 10 or more suggests that minor or major depression may be present.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Improvement in general well-being</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>This will be measured using the World Health Organization-5 (WHO-5) Well-being Index. The WHO-5 Well-Being Index is a questionnaire that measures current mental well-being,with the time frame being the previous two weeks.This is five items rated on 6-point Likert scale (All of the time, Most of the time, More than half the time, Less than half the time, Some of the time, At no time). The raw score is calculated by totaling the figures of the five answers. The raw score ranges from 0 to 25, 0 representing worst possible and 25 representing best possible quality of life.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Postpartum Depression</condition>
  <condition>Pregnancy Related</condition>
  <condition>Environmental Exposure</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Nature Coach Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The Nature Coach Intervention consists of 3 components - home visit, text message follow up, and goal feedback.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Education only</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Nature Coach Intervention</intervention_name>
    <description>Home visit. During the 1-hour home visit, the coach will (a) provide education about the health benefits of nature, (b) identify nearby nature targets for the participant to visit, (c) complete a pre-commitment contract based on individualized weekly nature goals, and (d) brainstorm barriers and solutions to reaching the goals.
Personalized weekly text messages. Texts will serve as reminders of goals set with the Nature Coach, as well as encouragement to meet the goals. The context of text messages with change slightly based on individual participants, the goals they set, and the barriers they identify.
Goal feedback- At the end of each week, participants will receive a progression badge via text message that shows the amount of days and time they spent in nature, and how this matched up to the goal set with the Nature Coach.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Nature Coach Intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  18 years old and older

          -  Delivery of a living child

          -  Ambulatory

          -  Live in West or Southwest Philadelphia

          -  Have a smart phone

          -  Able to understand and respond to an oral interview in English

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Baby in Neonatal Intensive Care Unit

          -  Mother has not been in Intensive Care Unit pre/post-delivery

          -  Gestational age less than 37 weeks

          -  Department of Human Services involvement
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <gender_based>Yes</gender_based>
    <gender_description>Postpartum women living in West and South West Philadelphia</gender_description>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Eugenia South, MD MS</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Pennsylvania</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Pennsylvania</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19104</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 2, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 29, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 31, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 23, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 23, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 24, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Depression, Postpartum</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depression</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

