<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04142424</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>D7830C00001</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04142424</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study to Understand the Safety, Tolerability of a Single Dose of AZD2693 and How the AZD2693 Behaves Inside the Body When Given to Overweight/Mildly Obese Healthy Male Subjects and Healthy Female Subjects of Non-childbearing Potential and Patients With Non-alcoholic Steatohepatitis</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase I, Randomized, Single-blind, Placebo-controlled Study to Assess the Safety, Tolerability and Pharmacokinetics of AZD2693 Following Single Ascending Dose Administration in Male and Female Subjects of Non-childbearing Potential in 3 Populations: Overweight But Otherwise Healthy Subjects, Healthy Chinese and Japanese Subjects, and Patients With Non-alcoholic Steatohepatitis (NASH) Homozygous for the PNPLA3 148M Risk Allele</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>AstraZeneca</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Parexel</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>AstraZeneca</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This Phase 1, first-in-human (FiH), single-ascending-dose (SAD) study, will assess the safety
      and tolerability of AZD2693 and characterize the pharmacokinetics (PK) of AZD2693, following
      subcutaneous (SC) SAD administration of AZD2693 in male and female subjects of non
      -childbearing potential in 3 Populations: overweight but otherwise healthy subjects, healthy
      Chinese and Japanese subjects, and patients with NASH homozygous for the patatin-like
      phospholipase domain-containing protein 3 (PNPLA3) 148M Risk Allele
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a Phase I, FiH, randomized, single blind, placebo-controlled study to assess the
      safety, tolerability and PK of AZD2693 following SAD administration. The study is being
      performed at a single study center; additional sites may be included, if appropriate. Details
      of planned cohorts are as follows:

        1. Overweight/mildly obese, but otherwise healthy subjects:

           Up to 64 overweight/mildly obese but otherwise healthy male subjects and female subjects
           of non-childbearing potential, aged 18 to 55 years, will be enrolled into this study.
           Six cohorts of 8 subjects each are planned. Depending on emerging data, up to 2
           additional cohorts may be added to test additional dose levels at the discretion of the
           Sponsor.

           Within each cohort, 6 subjects will be randomized to receive AZD2693, at 1 dose level,
           and 2 subjects randomized to receive placebo. Dosing for each ascending dose cohort will
           proceed with 2 subjects in a sentinel cohort, such that 1 subject will be randomized to
           receive placebo and 1 subject will be randomized to receive AZD2693.

        2. NASH patients:

           Up to 42 NASH patients homozygous for the PNPLA3 148M risk allele, male subjects and
           female subjects of non-childbearing potential, aged 18 - 65 years, will be enrolled into
           this study.

           Two cohorts, each consisting of 21 subjects are planned. Within each cohort, 14 subjects
           will be randomized to receive AZD2693 and 7 subjects randomized to receive placebo. Two
           dose levels of AZD2693 are planned to be assessed.

        3. Japanese and Chinese subjects:

      Up to 16 healthy (body mass index [BMI] up to 32 kg/m2 allowed) Japanese and 8 Chinese male
      subjects and female subjects of non childbearing potential, aged 18 to 55 years, may be
      enrolled into this study. Two cohorts of Japanese and one cohort of Chinese subjects are
      planned. Each cohort will consist of 8 subjects. Within each cohort, 6 subjects will be
      randomized to receive AZD2693 and 2 subjects randomized to receive placebo. Individual
      cohorts will be dosed after the Principal Investigator (PI) reviews the safety data from the
      sentinel pair in the corresponding dose level in the healthy subject cohorts.

      The study will comprise of:

        -  A Screening Period of maximum 28 days (or maximum 60 days for NASH patients).

        -  A Dosing Session during which subjects will be resident at the Clinical Unit from the
           day before IMP administration (Day -1) until at least 3 days after IMP administration
           with discharge on Day 4 (NASH patients are discharged on Day 3). IMP will be delivered
           after an overnight fast on Day 1.

        -  A Follow-Up Period of 16 weeks that will consist of 9 Follow-Up Visits, for which the
           subjects will return to the Clinical Unit at 1, 2, 4, 6, 8, 10, 12, 14, and 16 weeks
           post dose.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 28, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 18, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 18, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>This is a randomized, single blind, placebo-controlled study.
Overweight/mildly obese, but otherwise healthy subjects:
Six cohorts of 8 subjects each are planned. Within each cohort, 6 subjects will be randomized to receive AZD2693, at 1 dose level, and 2 subjects randomized to receive placebo.
NASH patients:
Two cohorts, each consisting of 21 subjects are planned. Within each cohort, 14 subjects will be randomized to receive AZD2693 and 7 subjects randomized to receive placebo.
Japanese and Chinese subjects:
Two cohorts of Japanese and one cohort of Chinese subjects are planned. Each cohort will consist of 8 subjects. Within each cohort, 6 subjects will be randomized to receive AZD2693 and 2 subjects randomized to receive placebo.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator)</masking>
    <masking_description>This study is single blind (in which the study center staff including the Principal Investigator have to remain blinded during the clinical conduct of a given cohort) with regard to treatment (AZD2693 or placebo) at each dose level. The subjects will be blinded throughout the study.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of subjects with adverse event and/or abnormal vital signs, laboratory and/or physical examination findings</measure>
    <time_frame>From screening upto Week 16 (follow-up)</time_frame>
    <description>To investigate the safety and tolerability of SC administration of single ascending doses of AZD2693</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum observed plasma drug concentration (Cmax)</measure>
    <time_frame>At Day 1 Pre-dose, 0.25hours[h], 0.5h, 1h, 1.5h, 2h, 2.5h, 3h, 4h, 5h, 6h, 8h, 12h, 24h, 36h, 48h and 72h post-dose and 1, 2, 4, 8, 12 and 16 weeks post-dose</time_frame>
    <description>To characterize the PK of AZD2693 following SC administration of SAD of AZD2693</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to reach maximum observed concentration following drug administration (tmax)</measure>
    <time_frame>At Day 1 Pre-dose, 0.25hours[h], 0.5h, 1h, 1.5h, 2h, 2.5h, 3h, 4h, 5h, 6h, 8h, 12h, 24h, 36h, 48h and 72h post-dose and 1, 2, 4, 8, 12 and 16 weeks post-dose</time_frame>
    <description>To characterize the PK of AZD2693 following SC administration of SAD of AZD2693</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Apparent terminal elimination half-life associated with the terminal slope (λz) of the semi-logarithmic concentration-time curve, estimated as (ln2)/λz (t½λz)</measure>
    <time_frame>At Day 1 Pre-dose, 0.25hours[h], 0.5h, 1h, 1.5h, 2h, 2.5h, 3h, 4h, 5h, 6h, 8h, 12h, 24h, 36h, 48h and 72h post-dose and 1, 2, 4, 8, 12 and 16 weeks post-dose</time_frame>
    <description>To characterize the PK of AZD2693 following SC administration of SAD of AZD2693</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Area under the plasma concentration-time curve from time zero to 48 hours after dosing [AUC(0-48h)]</measure>
    <time_frame>At Day 1 Pre-dose, 0.25hours[h], 0.5h, 1h, 1.5h, 2h, 2.5h, 3h, 4h, 5h, 6h, 8h, 12h, 24h, 36h, 48h and 72h post-dose and 1, 2, 4, 8, 12 and 16 weeks post-dose</time_frame>
    <description>To characterize the PK of AZD2693 following SC administration of SAD of AZD2693</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Area under the plasma concentration-curve from time zero to the time of last quantifiable analyte concentration (AUClast)</measure>
    <time_frame>At Day 1 Pre-dose, 0.25hours[h], 0.5h, 1h, 1.5h, 2h, 2.5h, 3h, 4h, 5h, 6h, 8h, 12h, 24h, 36h, 48h and 72h post-dose and 1, 2, 4, 8, 12 and 16 weeks post-dose</time_frame>
    <description>To characterize the PK of AZD2693 following SC administration of SAD of AZD2693</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Area under the concentration-time curve from time zero extrapolated to infinity (AUC)</measure>
    <time_frame>At Day 1 Pre-dose, 0.25hours[h], 0.5h, 1h, 1.5h, 2h, 2.5h, 3h, 4h, 5h, 6h, 8h, 12h, 24h, 36h, 48h and 72h post-dose and 1, 2, 4, 8, 12 and 16 weeks post-dose</time_frame>
    <description>To characterize the PK of AZD2693 following SC administration of SAD of AZD2693</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Apparent total body clearance of drug from plasma after extravascular administration calculated as Dose/AUC (CL/F)</measure>
    <time_frame>At Day 1 Pre-dose, 0.25hours[h], 0.5h, 1h, 1.5h, 2h, 2.5h, 3h, 4h, 5h, 6h, 8h, 12h, 24h, 36h, 48h and 72h post-dose and 1, 2, 4, 8, 12 and 16 weeks post-dose</time_frame>
    <description>To characterize the PK of AZD2693 following SC administration of SAD of AZD2693</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean residence time (MRT)</measure>
    <time_frame>At Day 1 Pre-dose, 0.25hours[h], 0.5h, 1h, 1.5h, 2h, 2.5h, 3h, 4h, 5h, 6h, 8h, 12h, 24h, 36h, 48h and 72h post-dose and 1, 2, 4, 8, 12 and 16 weeks post-dose</time_frame>
    <description>To characterize the PK of AZD2693 following SC administration of SAD of AZD2693</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time delay between drug administration and the first observed concentration in plasma (tlag)</measure>
    <time_frame>At Day 1 Pre-dose, 0.25hours[h], 0.5h, 1h, 1.5h, 2h, 2.5h, 3h, 4h, 5h, 6h, 8h, 12h, 24h, 36h, 48h and 72h post-dose and 1, 2, 4, 8, 12 and 16 weeks post-dose</time_frame>
    <description>To characterize the PK of AZD2693 following SC administration of SAD of AZD2693</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Apparent volume of distribution for parent drug at terminal phase (extravascular administration), estimated by dividing CL/F by λz (Vz/F)</measure>
    <time_frame>At Day 1 Pre-dose, 0.25hours[h], 0.5h, 1h, 1.5h, 2h, 2.5h, 3h, 4h, 5h, 6h, 8h, 12h, 24h, 36h, 48h and 72h post-dose and 1, 2, 4, 8, 12 and 16 weeks post-dose</time_frame>
    <description>To characterize the PK of AZD2693 following SC administration of SAD of AZD2693</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Area under the plasma concentration-time curve from time zero to time of last quantifiable analyte concentration divided by the dose administered (AUClast/D)</measure>
    <time_frame>At Day 1 Pre-dose, 0.25hours[h], 0.5h, 1h, 1.5h, 2h, 2.5h, 3h, 4h, 5h, 6h, 8h, 12h, 24h, 36h, 48h and 72h post-dose and 1, 2, 4, 8, 12 and 16 weeks post-dose</time_frame>
    <description>To characterize the PK of AZD2693 following SC administration of SAD of AZD2693</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Area under the plasma concentration-time curve from time zero extrapolated to infinity divided by the dose administered (AUC/D)</measure>
    <time_frame>At Day 1 Pre-dose, 0.25hours[h], 0.5h, 1h, 1.5h, 2h, 2.5h, 3h, 4h, 5h, 6h, 8h, 12h, 24h, 36h, 48h and 72h post-dose and 1, 2, 4, 8, 12 and 16 weeks post-dose</time_frame>
    <description>To characterize the PK of AZD2693 following SC administration of SAD of AZD2693</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Observed maximum plasma concentration divided by the dose administered (Cmax/D)</measure>
    <time_frame>At Day 1 Pre-dose, 0.25hours[h], 0.5h, 1h, 1.5h, 2h, 2.5h, 3h, 4h, 5h, 6h, 8h, 12h, 24h, 36h, 48h and 72h post-dose and 1, 2, 4, 8, 12 and 16 weeks post-dose</time_frame>
    <description>To characterize the PK of AZD2693 following SC administration of SAD of AZD2693</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Amount of analyte excreted into the urine from time t1 to t2 [Ae(t1-t2)]</measure>
    <time_frame>At Pre-dose, 0-6hours[h], 6-12h and then 0-12h intervals up to 72h post-dose</time_frame>
    <description>To characterize the PK of AZD2693 following SC administration of SAD of AZD2693</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cumulative amount of analyte excreted into the urine from time zero through the last sampling interval [Ae(0-last)]</measure>
    <time_frame>At Pre-dose, 0-6hours[h], 6-12h and then 0-12h intervals up to 72h post-dose</time_frame>
    <description>To characterize the PK of AZD2693 following SC administration of SAD of AZD2693</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Fraction of dose excreted unchanged into the urine from time t1 to t2 [fe(t1-t2)]</measure>
    <time_frame>At Pre-dose, 0-6hours[h], 6-12h and then 0-12h intervals up to 72h post-dose</time_frame>
    <description>To characterize the PK of AZD2693 following SC administration of SAD of AZD2693</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cumulative fraction (%) of dose excreted unchanged into the urine from time zero to the last measured time point [fe(0-last)]</measure>
    <time_frame>At Pre-dose, 0-6hours[h], 6-12h and then 0-12h intervals up to 72h post-dose</time_frame>
    <description>To characterize the PK of AZD2693 following SC administration of SAD of AZD2693</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Renal clearance of drug from plasma, estimated by dividing Ae(0-t) by AUC(0-t) where the 0-t interval is the same for both Ae and AUC [CLR]</measure>
    <time_frame>At Pre-dose, 0-6hours[h], 6-12h and then 0-12h intervals up to 72h post-dose</time_frame>
    <description>To characterize the PK of AZD2693 following SC administration of SAD of AZD2693</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in liver fat content (LFC) from baseline assessment</measure>
    <time_frame>At screening and follow-up visits on Weeks 4, 8 and 12 post-dose</time_frame>
    <description>To assess the effect of AZD2693 on changes in LFC using magnetic resonance imaging based proton density fat fraction (MRI-PDFF) compared to placebo</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>11</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">115</enrollment>
  <condition>Metabolic Diseases</condition>
  <condition>Non-alcoholic Steatohepatitis (NASH)</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 1 healthy subjects : AZD2693 Dose 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Each overweight/mildly obese but otherwise healthy male subjects and female subjects of non-childbearing potential will receive a single dose of AZD2693 dose 1 or placebo in the form of SC injection in the abdomen</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 2 healthy subjects : AZD2693 Dose 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Each overweight/mildly obese but otherwise healthy male subjects and female subjects of non-childbearing potential will receive a single dose of AZD2693 dose 2 or placebo in the form of SC injection in the abdomen</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 3 healthy subjects : AZD2693 Dose 3</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Each overweight/mildly obese but otherwise healthy male subjects and female subjects of non-childbearing potential will receive a single dose of AZD2693 dose 3 or placebo in the form of SC injection in the abdomen</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 4 healthy subjects : AZD2693 Dose 4</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Each overweight/mildly obese but otherwise healthy male subjects and female subjects of non-childbearing potential will receive a single dose of AZD2693 dose 4 or placebo in the form of SC injection in the abdomen</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 5 healthy subjects : AZD2693 Dose 5</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Each overweight/mildly obese but otherwise healthy male subjects and female subjects of non-childbearing potential will receive a single dose of AZD2693 dose 5 or placebo in the form of SC injection in the abdomen</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 6 healthy subjects: AZD2693 Dose 6</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Each overweight/mildly obese but otherwise healthy male subjects and female subjects of non-childbearing potential will receive a single dose of AZD2693 dose 6 or placebo in the form of SC injection in the abdomen</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 7 NASH patients: AZD2693 dose 7</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Each NASH patient will receive a single dose of AZD2693 dose 7 or placebo in the form of SC injection in the abdomen</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 8 NASH patients : AZD2693 Dose 8</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Each NASH patient will receive a single dose of AZD2693 dose 8 or placebo in the form of SC injection in the abdomen</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 9 Japanese subject : AZD2693 Dose 9</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Each Japanese subject will receive a single dose of AZD2693 dose 9 or placebo in the form of SC injection in the abdomen</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 10 Japanese subjects : AZD2693 Dose 10</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Each Japanese subject will receive a single dose of AZD2693 dose 10 or placebo in the form of SC injection in the abdomen</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 11 Chinese subjects : AZD2693 Dose 11</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Each Chinese subject will receive a single dose of AZD2693 dose 11 or placebo in the form of SC injection in the abdomen</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>AZD2693</intervention_name>
    <description>Within each cohort, subjects/patients will be randomized to receive AZD2693. Dosing for each ascending dose cohort in this study will start with 2 subjects/patients in 1 sentinel cohort, consisting of 1 subject/patient randomized to receive placebo and 1 subject/patient randomized to receive AZD2693.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 1 healthy subjects : AZD2693 Dose 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 10 Japanese subjects : AZD2693 Dose 10</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 11 Chinese subjects : AZD2693 Dose 11</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 2 healthy subjects : AZD2693 Dose 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 3 healthy subjects : AZD2693 Dose 3</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 4 healthy subjects : AZD2693 Dose 4</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 5 healthy subjects : AZD2693 Dose 5</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 6 healthy subjects: AZD2693 Dose 6</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 7 NASH patients: AZD2693 dose 7</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 8 NASH patients : AZD2693 Dose 8</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 9 Japanese subject : AZD2693 Dose 9</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Within each cohort, subjects/patients will be randomized to receive placebo. Dosing for each ascending dose cohort in this study will start with 2 subjects/patients in 1 sentinel cohort, consisting of 1 subject/patient randomized to receive placebo and 1 subject/patient randomized to receive AZD2693.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 1 healthy subjects : AZD2693 Dose 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 10 Japanese subjects : AZD2693 Dose 10</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 11 Chinese subjects : AZD2693 Dose 11</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 2 healthy subjects : AZD2693 Dose 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 3 healthy subjects : AZD2693 Dose 3</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 4 healthy subjects : AZD2693 Dose 4</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 5 healthy subjects : AZD2693 Dose 5</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 6 healthy subjects: AZD2693 Dose 6</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 7 NASH patients: AZD2693 dose 7</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 8 NASH patients : AZD2693 Dose 8</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 9 Japanese subject : AZD2693 Dose 9</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Provision of signed and dated, written informed consent prior to any study specific
             procedures.

          -  Male subjects and female subjects of non-childbearing potential aged 18 - 55 years (or
             18 - 65 years for NASH patients) with suitable veins for cannulation or repeated
             venipuncture.

          -  Females must have a negative pregnancy test at the Screening Visit and on admission to
             the Clinical Unit, must not be lactating and must be of non-child-bearing potential,
             confirmed at the Screening Visit by fulfilling one of the following criteria:

        A. Postmenopausal defined as amenorrhea for at least 12 months or more following cessation
        of all exogenous hormonal treatments and follicle-stimulating hormone (FSH) levels in the
        postmenopausal range.

        B. Documentation of irreversible surgical sterilization by hysterectomy, bilateral
        oophorectomy or bilateral salpingectomy but not tubal ligation.

          -  Have a body mass index (BMI) between 25 and 32 kg/m^2 for healthy subjects, 25 and 40
             kg/m2 for NASH patients, or between 18 and 32 kg/m2 for Japanese and Chinese subjects,
             and weigh at least 60 kg (or 50 kg for Japanese and Chinese subjects).

          -  Willing to participate in retrospective genotyping analysis for PNPLA3. This criterion
             is not applicable for NASH patients.

          -  Willing and able to comply with all required study procedures.

        Applicable to NASH patients only:

          -  An MRI-PDFF ≥8% and one of the following:

               1. A previous liver biopsy with stage 0-2 fibrosis in the previous 24 months, or

               2. For those without a previous biopsy, an MRE between 2.55 Kpa and 3.63 Kpa, or

               3. For those without MRE, a vibration-controlled transient elastography (VCTE)
                  between 7.1 Kpa and 9.9 Kpa.

          -  Homozygous for the PNPLA3 148M SNP rs738409 (PNPLA3 148 MM). Patients must be willing
             to participate in prospective genotyping analysis of PNPLA3 for inclusion in the
             study.

          -  Provision of signed and dated written Optional Genetic Research Information informed
             consent prior to collection of samples for optional genetic research that supports
             Genomic Initiative. Participants who do not wish to participate in the genetic
             research may still participate in the study.

          -  Provision of signed, written and dated informed consent for prior to collection of
             samples for mandatory Companion Diagnostic Development.

        Applicable to Japanese and Chinese subjects only:

          -  A Japanese subject is defined as having both parents and 4 grandparents who are
             ethnically Japanese. This includes second and third generation Japanese whose parents
             or grandparents are living in a country other than Japan.

          -  A Chinese subject is defined as having both parents and 4 grandparents who are
             ethnically Chinese. This includes second and third generation Chinese whose parents or
             grandparents are living in a country other than China.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  History of any clinically important disease or disorder which, in the opinion of the
             Investigator, may either put the subject at risk because of participation in the
             study, or influence the results or the subject's ability to participate in the study.

          -  History or presence of gastrointestinal, hepatic or renal disease or any other
             condition known to interfere with absorption, distribution, metabolism or excretion of
             drugs.

          -  Any clinically important illness, medical/surgical procedure or trauma within 4 weeks
             of the first administration of IMP.

          -  Any clinically significant cardiovascular event within the last 6 months prior to the
             Screening Visit.

          -  Any laboratory values with the following deviations at Screening or Day -1:

               1. Alanine aminotransferase (ALT) &gt; upper limit of normal (ULN) (or &gt; 1.5 x ULN for
                  NASH patients)

               2. Aspartate aminotransferase (AST) &gt; ULN (or &gt; 1.5 x ULN for NASH patients)

               3. Creatinine &gt; ULN

               4. White blood cell (WBC) count &lt; LLN

               5. Hemoglobin &lt; LLN

               6. Platelet count &lt;LLN

               7. Activated partial thrombin time &gt; ULN and PT &gt; ULN

               8. Estimated glomerular filtration rate (eGFR) &lt; 90mL/min/1.73m^2 calculated using
                  Chronic Kidney Disease Epidemiology Collaboration (CKD-EPI) (eGFR &lt; 60
                  mL/min/1.73m² for NASH patients and for Japanese and Chinese subjects)

               9. Urinary albumin-to-creatinine ratio (ACR) &gt; 3 mg/μmol (30 mg/g)

          -  Any other clinically important abnormalities in clinical chemistry, hematology or
             urinalysis results, than those described under previous exclusion criterion above, as
             judged by the Investigator at Screening or Day -1.

          -  Any positive result on Screening for serum hepatitis B surface antigen, hepatitis C
             antibody and human immunodeficiency virus (HIV).

          -  Abnormal vital signs, after 10 minutes supine rest, defined as any of the following at
             Screening or Day -1:

          -  Systolic BP &lt; 90 mmHg or &gt; 140 mmHg (or &lt; 95 mmHg or &gt; 160 mmHg for NASH patients).
             For NASH patients, blood pressure medication should be optimized according to national
             guidelines and per investigator judgement.

          -  Diastolic blood pressure (BP) &lt; 50 mmHg or &gt; 90 mmHg.

          -  HR &lt; 45 or &gt; 90 bpm.

          -  Any clinically important abnormalities in rhythm, conduction or morphology of the
             resting electrocardiogram (ECG) and any clinically important abnormalities in the
             12-lead ECG as considered by the Investigator that may interfere with the
             interpretation of QTc interval changes, including abnormal ST-T-wave morphology,
             particularly in the protocol defined primary lead (in NASH patients some abnormalities
             in ST-T wave morphology is acceptable even if influencing the primary lead if not
             considered clinically important by the Investigator) or left ventricular hypertrophy
             at Screening or Day -1:

          -  Prolonged QTcF &gt; 450 ms.

          -  Shortened QTcF &lt; 340 ms.

          -  Family history of long QT syndrome.

          -  PR (PQ) interval shortening &lt; 120 ms (PR &gt; 110 ms but &lt; 120 ms is acceptable if there
             is no evidence of ventricular pre-excitation).

          -  PR (PQ) interval prolongation (&gt; 240 ms; or &gt; 220 ms for NASH patients) intermittent
             second (Wenckebach block while asleep is not exclusive) or third degree
             atrioventricular (AV) block, or AV dissociation.

          -  Persistent or intermittent complete bundle branch block (BBB), incomplete bundle
             branch block (IBBB), or intraventricular conduction delay (IVCD) with QRS &gt; 110 ms.
             Subjects with QRS &gt; 110 ms but &lt; 115 ms are acceptable if there is no evidence of e.g.
             ventricular hypertrophy or pre-excitation. Note: In NASH patients QRS &lt; 120 ms is
             allowed but NASH patients with persistent or intermittent BBB should be excluded ≥ 120
             ms.

          -  Known or suspected history of drug abuse as judged by the Investigator.

          -  Smokers with &gt; 10 cigarettes/day and unable to comply with the nicotine restrictions
             during the study.

          -  History of alcohol abuse or excessive intake of alcohol. Definition of excessive
             intake: an average weekly intake of &gt;21 drinks/week for men or &gt;14 drinks/week for
             women. One drink is equivalent to (14 g alcohol).

          -  Positive screen for drugs of abuse at Screening or admission to the Clinical Unit or
             positive screen for alcohol on admission to the Clinical Unit prior to the first
             administration of the IMP.

          -  History of severe allergy/hypersensitivity or ongoing clinically important
             allergy/hypersensitivity, as judged by the Investigator or history of hypersensitivity
             to drugs with a similar chemical structure or class to AZD2693.

          -  Excessive intake of caffeine-containing drinks or food (e.g., coffee, tea, chocolate,
             Red Bull®-like drinks) as judged by the Investigator.

          -  Use of any prescribed or nonprescribed medication including antacids, analgesics
             (other than paracetamol/acetaminophen), herbal remedies, mega-dose vitamins (intake of
             20 to 600 times the recommended daily dose) and minerals during the 2 weeks prior to
             the first administration of IMP or longer if the medication has a long half-life.

          -  Plasma donation within one month of the Screening Visit or any blood donation/blood
             loss &gt; 500 mL during the 3 months prior to the Screening Visit.

          -  Has received another new chemical entity (defined as a compound which has not been
             approved for marketing) within 30 days of last follow-up to first administration of
             IMP or, if known, 5 half-lives from last dose to first administration of IMP,
             whichever is the longest.

          -  Blood dyscrasias with increased risk of bleeding including Idiopathic Thrombocytopenic
             Purpura (ITP) and Thrombotic Thrombocytopenic Purpura or symptoms of increased risk of
             bleeding (frequent bleeding gums or nose bleeds).

          -  Involvement of any AstraZeneca or Clinical Unit employee or their close relatives.

          -  Judgment by the Investigator that the subject should not participate in the study if
             they have any ongoing or recent (i.e., during the Screening period) minor medical
             complaints that may interfere with the interpretation of study data or are considered
             unlikely to comply with study procedures, restrictions and requirements.

          -  Subjects who are vegans or have medical dietary restrictions, or who are not willing
             to comply with the dietary requirements in the study as judged by the Investigator.

          -  Subjects who cannot communicate reliably with the Investigator.

          -  Vulnerable subjects, e.g., kept in detention, protected adults under guardianship,
             trusteeship, or committed to an institution by governmental or juridical order.

          -  Previous bone marrow transplant.

          -  Non-leukocyte depleted whole blood transfusion within 120 days of the date of the
             genotyping sample collection.

          -  Males who are unwilling to use an acceptable method of birth control.

          -  Applicable to NASH patients only:

          -  History or presence of significant neurological or psychiatric disease/mental illness.

          -  History of malignancy within the last 5 years, excluding successful treatment of basal
             cell skin carcinoma or in situ carcinoma of cervix.

          -  Suspicion of or known Gilbert's syndrome.

          -  Weight loss of more than 5% within the last 6 months prior to randomization. Plans to
             initiate a weight loss diet or to undergo bariatric surgery.

          -  History of liver transplant, or current placement on a liver transplant list.

          -  History or presence of hepatic disease (with the exception of hepatic steatosis, NASH)
             or Evidence of other known forms of known chronic liver disease such as alcoholic
             liver disease, hepatitis B, hepatitis C, primary biliary cirrhosis (PBC), primary
             sclerotic cirrhosis (PSC), autoimmune hepatitis, Wilson disease, iron overload,
             alpha-1-antitrypsin deficiency, drug-induced liver injury, known or suspected
             hepatocellular carcinoma (HCC).

          -  Histological presence of cirrhosis.

          -  Use of drugs with enzyme inducing properties such as St John's Wort within 3 weeks
             prior to the first administration of IMP.

          -  Changes in any current medication (initiation, dose change or cessation) that may
             impact the study readouts (as judged by the Investigator) within one month prior to
             screening. The criterion does not apply to medication prescribed for occasional use.

          -  Use of anabolic steroids and systemic treatment with glucocorticosteroids within 3
             months prior to the Screening Visit.

          -  Total bilirubin &gt; 1 mg/dL, international normalized ratio (INR) &gt; 1.2 or alkaline
             phosphatase (ALP) ≥ 250 U/L.

          -  Contraindication to MRI, such as: participants with pacemakers, metallic cardiac
             valves, magnetic material such as surgical clips, implanted electronic infusion pumps
             or other conditions that would preclude proximity to a strong magnetic field;
             participants with a history of extreme claustrophobia; or participants who cannot fit
             inside the MRI scanner cavity.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>55 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>David Han, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Parexel Early Clinical Unit - Los Angeles</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>AstraZeneca Clinical Study Information Center</last_name>
    <phone>1-877-240-9479</phone>
    <email>information.center@astrazeneca.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Glendale</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>91206</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 22, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 25, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 29, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 22, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 22, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 24, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Single-ascending-dose (SAD)</keyword>
  <keyword>First-in-human (FiH)</keyword>
  <keyword>Chinese</keyword>
  <keyword>Japanese</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Fatty Liver</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Non-alcoholic Fatty Liver Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Metabolic Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Overweight</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Qualified researchers can request access to anonymized individual patient-level data from AstraZeneca group of companies sponsored clinical trials via the request portal. All request will be evaluated as per the AZ disclosure commitment: https://astrazenecagrouptrials.pharmacm.com/ST/Submission/Disclosure Yes, indicates that AZ are accepting requests for IPD, but this does not mean all requests will be shared.</ipd_description>
    <ipd_time_frame>AstraZeneca will meet or exceed data availability as per the commitments made to the EFPIA Pharma Data Sharing Principles. For details of our timelines, please rerefer to our disclosure commitment at https://astrazenecagrouptrials.pharmacm.com/ST/Submission/Disclosure.</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>When a request has been approved AstraZeneca will provide access to the de-identified individual patient-level data in an approved sponsored tool . Signed Data Sharing Agreement (non-negotiable contract for data accessors) must be in place before accessing requested information. Additionally, all users will need to accept the terms and conditions of the SAS MSE to gain access. For additional details, please review the Disclosure Statements at https://astrazenecagrouptrials.pharmacm.com/ST/Submission/Disclosure.</ipd_access_criteria>
    <ipd_url>https://astrazenecagroup-dt.pharmacm.com/DT/Home</ipd_url>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

