<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04143477</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>015K-CL-CNA1</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04143477</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study to Evaluate the Pharmacokinetics and Safety of ASP015K in Healthy Chinese Subjects</brief_title>
  <official_title>An Open-Label, Single and Multiple Dose Study to Evaluate the Pharmacokinetics and Safety of ASP015K in Healthy Chinese Subjects</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Astellas Pharma China, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Astellas Pharma Inc</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to evaluate the pharmacokinetics and safety of ASP015K after
      single-dose and multiple-dose administration in healthy Chinese participants.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">December 5, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Sequential Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with adverse events (AEs)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Day 20</time_frame>
    <description>An AE is defined as any untoward medical occurrence in a participant administered a study drug or who has undergone study procedures and which does not necessarily have a causal relationship with this treatment. An AE can therefore be any unintended sign (including an abnormal laboratory finding), symptom or disease temporally associated with the use of a study drug, whether or not related to the study drug.
An AE is considered &quot;serious&quot; if, in the view of either the investigator or Sponsor, it results in any of the following outcomes: Death, life-threatening, persistent or significant disability/incapacity, congenital anomaly or birth defect, hospitalization, or medically important event.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with laboratory value abnormalities and/or AEs</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Day 20</time_frame>
    <description>Number of participants with potentially clinically significant laboratory values.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with vital sign abnormalities and/or AEs</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Day 20</time_frame>
    <description>Number of participants with potentially clinically significant vital sign values.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with 12-lead electrocardiogram (ECG) abnormalities and/or AEs</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Day 20</time_frame>
    <description>Number of participants with potentially clinically significant 12-ECG values.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with physical examination abnormalities and/or AEs</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Day 20</time_frame>
    <description>Number of participants with potentially clinically significant physical examination observations.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetics (PK) of peficitinib: Area under the concentration-time curve (AUC) from the time of dosing extrapolated to time infinity (AUCinf)</measure>
    <time_frame>On Day 1</time_frame>
    <description>AUCinf will be recorded from the PK serum samples collected.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>PK of peficitinib: AUC from the time of dosing to the last measurable concentration (AUClast)</measure>
    <time_frame>On Day 1 and 8</time_frame>
    <description>AUClast will be recorded from the PK serum samples collected.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>PK of peficitinib: AUC from the time of dosing to 24 hours post dose (AUC24h)</measure>
    <time_frame>On Day 1, 8 and 13</time_frame>
    <description>AUC24h will be recorded from the PK serum samples collected.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>PK of peficitinib: Apparent total systemic clearance after extravascular dosing (CL/F)</measure>
    <time_frame>On Day 1 and 13</time_frame>
    <description>CL/F will be recorded from the PK serum samples collected.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>PK of peficitinib: Maximum concertation (Cmax)</measure>
    <time_frame>On Day 1, 8 and 13</time_frame>
    <description>Cmax will be recorded from the PK serum samples collected.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>PK of peficitinib: Terminal elimination rate constant (Lambdaz)</measure>
    <time_frame>On Day 1 and 13</time_frame>
    <description>Lambdaz will be recorded from the PK serum samples collected.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>PK of peficitinib: Terminal elimination half-life (t1/2)</measure>
    <time_frame>On Day 1 and 13</time_frame>
    <description>t1/2 will be recorded from the PK serum samples collected.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>PK of peficitinib: Time of the maximum concentration (tmax)</measure>
    <time_frame>On Day 1, 8 and 13</time_frame>
    <description>tmax will be recorded from the PK serum samples collected.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>PK of peficitinib: Apparent volume of distribution during the terminal elimination phase after single extravascular dosing (VzF)</measure>
    <time_frame>On Day 1</time_frame>
    <description>VzF will be recorded from the PK serum samples collected.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>PK of peficitinib: Concentration immediately prior to dosing at multiple dosing (Ctrough)</measure>
    <time_frame>On Day 9 to 12 and 13</time_frame>
    <description>Ctrough will be recorded from the PK serum samples collected.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>PK of peficitinib: Concentration at 24 hours post dosing (C24h)</measure>
    <time_frame>On Day 13</time_frame>
    <description>C24h will be recorded from the PK serum samples collected.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>PK of peficitinib: Peak trough ratio (PTR)</measure>
    <time_frame>On Day 13</time_frame>
    <description>PTR will be recorded from the PK serum samples collected.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>PK of peficitinib: Accumulation ratio calculated using AUC (Rac(AUC24h))</measure>
    <time_frame>On Day 13</time_frame>
    <description>Rac(AUC) will be recorded from the PK serum samples collected.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>PK of peficitinib: Accumulation ratio calculated using the maximum concentration (Rac (Cmax))</measure>
    <time_frame>On Day 13</time_frame>
    <description>Rac(Cmax)will be recorded from the PK serum samples collected.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>PK of peficitinib metabolite: AUCinf</measure>
    <time_frame>On Day 1</time_frame>
    <description>AUCinf will be recorded from the PK serum samples collected.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>PK of peficitinib metabolite: AUClast</measure>
    <time_frame>On Day 1 and 8</time_frame>
    <description>AUClast will be recorded from the PK serum samples collected.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>PK of peficitinib metabolite: AUC24h</measure>
    <time_frame>On Day 1, 8 and 13</time_frame>
    <description>AUC24h will be recorded from the PK serum samples collected.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>PK of peficitinib metabolite: Cmax</measure>
    <time_frame>On Day 1, 8 and 13</time_frame>
    <description>Cmax will be recorded from the PK serum samples collected.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>PK of peficitinib metabolite: Lambdaz</measure>
    <time_frame>On Day 1 and 13</time_frame>
    <description>Lambdaz will be recorded from the PK serum samples collected.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>PK of peficitinib metabolite: t1/2</measure>
    <time_frame>On Day 1 and 13</time_frame>
    <description>t1/2 will be recorded from the PK serum samples collected.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>PK of peficitinib metabolite: tmax</measure>
    <time_frame>On Day 1, 8 and 13</time_frame>
    <description>tmax will be recorded from the PK serum samples collected.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>PK of peficitinib metabolite: Ctrough</measure>
    <time_frame>On Day 9 to 12 and 13</time_frame>
    <description>Ctrough will be recorded from the PK serum samples collected.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>PK of peficitinib metabolite: C24h</measure>
    <time_frame>On Day 13</time_frame>
    <description>C24h will be recorded from the PK serum samples collected.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>PK of peficitinib metabolite: PTR</measure>
    <time_frame>On Day 13</time_frame>
    <description>PTR will be recorded from the PK serum samples collected.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>PK of peficitinib metabolite: Rac(AUC24h)</measure>
    <time_frame>On Day 13</time_frame>
    <description>Rac(AUC24h) will be recorded from the PK serum samples collected.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>PK of peficitinib metabolite: Rac(Cmax)</measure>
    <time_frame>On Day 13</time_frame>
    <description>Rac(Cmax) will be recorded from the PK serum samples collected.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>PK of peficitinib metabolite: Metabolite to parent ratio of the area under the concentration-time curve corrected by the molecular weight ratio of parent to metabolite (MPR)</measure>
    <time_frame>On Day 1, 8 and 13</time_frame>
    <description>MPR will be recorded from the PK serum samples collected.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">36</enrollment>
  <condition>Healthy Volunteers</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Peficitinib dose-A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will receive a single dose of A under fasted condition Day 1, followed by multiple doses of A under fed condition once daily in the morning from Day 8 till Day 13.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Peficitinib dose-B</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will receive a single dose of B under fasted condition Day 1, followed by multiple doses of B under fed condition once daily in the morning from Day 8 till Day 13.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Peficitinib dose-C</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will receive a single dose of C under fasted condition Day 1, followed by multiple doses of C under fed condition once daily in the morning from Day 8 till Day 13.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>peficitinib</intervention_name>
    <description>Oral</description>
    <arm_group_label>Peficitinib dose-A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Peficitinib dose-B</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Peficitinib dose-C</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>ASP015K</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Normal Body Mass index (BMI) and weight: BMI[= weight kg/(height m)^2] &gt; 19 kg/m^2 and
             ≤ 24 kg/m^2, the weight is no less than 50 kg for male and 45 kg for female at
             screening.

          -  Female subject must either: Be of non-childbearing potential, postmenopausal (defined
             as at least 1 year without any menses) prior to screening, or documented surgically
             sterile. Or, if of childbearing potential: agree not to try to become pregnant during
             the study and for 60 days after the final study drug administration, must have a
             negative pregnancy at Screening and Day -1, and if heterosexually active, agree to
             consistently use 1 form of highly effective birth control starting at Screening and
             throughout the study period, and for 60 days after the final study drug
             administration.

          -  Female subject must agree not to breastfeed starting at Screening and throughout the
             study period, and for 60 days after the final study drug administration.

          -  Female subject must not donate ova starting at Screening and throughout the study
             period, and for 60 days after the final study drug administration.

          -  Male subject and female spouse/partners who are of childbearing potential must be
             using 1 form of highly effective birth control starting at Screening and throughout
             the study period, and for 90 days after the final study drug administration.

          -  Male subject must not donate sperm starting at Screening and throughout the study
             period, and for 90 days after the final study drug administration.

          -  Subject agrees not to participate in another interventional study while participating
             in the present study, defined as signing the informed consent form until completion of
             the last study visit.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Female subject who has been pregnant within 6 months prior to screening or breast
             feeding within 3 months prior to screening.

          -  Subject has a known or suspected hypersensitivity to ASP015K, or any components of the
             formulation used.

          -  Subject has any of the liver chemistry tests (aspartate aminotransferase [AST],
             alanine aminotransferase [ALT], alkaline phosphatase [ALP], gamma-glutamyl transferase
             [GGT] and total bilirubin [TBL]) above the upper limit of normal on Day -1. In such a
             case, the assessment may be repeated once.

          -  Subjects who meet any of the following criterion for laboratory tests on Day -1.
             Normal ranges of each test specified at the study site or test/assay organization will
             be used as the normal ranges in this study. In such a case, the assessment may be
             repeated once.

               -  Hematology: a deviation of +20% from the upper limit or −20% from the lower limit
                  of the normal range, and clinically significant.

               -  Blood biochemistry: a deviation from the normal range regarding serum creatinine,
                  serum electrolytes (Na, K, and Cl), or fasting blood glucose; a deviation of +20%
                  from the upper limit or −20% from the lower limit of the normal range regarding
                  laboratory test items other than above, and clinically significant. However, the
                  lower limit of the normal range will not be established for lactate dehydrogenase
                  (LD), creatinine kinase (CK), total cholesterol, triglyceride, urea, serum
                  creatinine, and uric acid, whose deviation from the lower limit is considered not
                  clinically significant.

               -  Urinalysis: a deviation from the normal range of each urinalysis test item.

          -  Subject has any clinically significant history of allergic conditions (including drug
             allergies, asthma, eczema, or anaphylactic reactions, but excluding untreated,
             asymptomatic, seasonal allergies at time of dosing).

          -  Subject has any history or evidence of any clinically significant cardiovascular,
             gastrointestinal endocrinologic, hematologic, hepatic, immunologic, metabolic,
             urologic, respiratory,pulmonary, neurologic, cerebrovascular, lymphatic, dermatologic,
             psychiatric, renal, and/or other major disease or malignancy.

          -  Subject has/had febrile illness or symptomatic, viral, bacterial (including upper
             respiratory infection), or fungal (noncutaneous) infection within 1 week prior to Day
             -1.

          -  Subject has any clinically significant abnormality in the physical examination,
             12-lead electrocardiogram (ECG) and protocol defined clinical laboratory tests at
             Screening or Day -1.

          -  Subject has a pulse rate &lt; 45 or &gt; 100 bpm; systolic blood pressure (SBP) &gt; 140 mmHg;
             diastolic blood pressure (DBP) &gt; 90 mmHg (measurements taken after subject has been
             resting in sit position for 5 min; pulse will be measured automatically) at screening
             or on Day -1. If the pulse rate or blood pressure exceeds the limits above, 1
             additional test can be taken.

          -  Subjects with abnormal body temperature, defined as axillary temperature &gt;37.3 ºC or
             &lt;35.0 ºC at Screening or Day -1.

          -  Subject has a corrected QT interval (QTcF) of &gt; 430 ms (for males) and &gt; 450 ms (for
             females) at screen or on Day -1(at screen and on Day-1, will be performed). If the
             QTcF exceeds the limits above on Day-1, 1 additional ECG test can be taken.

          -  Subject has any history or evidence of congenital short QT syndrome(defined as QTc &lt;
             330 ms).

          -  Subject has any history of gastrointestinal resection (excepted appendectomy)..

          -  Subject has developed upper gastrointestinal symptoms within 1 week prior to Day -1.

          -  Subject applies to any of the following concerns with regard to tuberculosis.

               -  History of active tuberculosis

               -  Abnormalities detected in a chest X-ray test at Screening

               -  Contact with infectious tuberculous patients

               -  T-spot or Quantiferon Gold test show tuberculosisinfection positive.

          -  Subject applies to any of the following concerns with regard to infection other than
             tuberculosis.

               -  Complication or history of severe herpes zoster or herpes zoster disseminated.

               -  At least twice of relapse of localized herpes zoster

               -  Inpatient hospital care for severe infectious diseases within 90 days prior to
                  Day -1

               -  Treatment with intravenous antibiotics within 90 days prior to Day -1
                  (prophylactic antibiotics are not applicable).

               -  Other than above, with a high risk of developing infectious disease (subjects
                  with urethral catheterisation etc.).

          -  Subject has vaccination of live vaccines or live attenuated vaccines within 56 days
             prior to Day -1 (inactivated vaccines such as influenza vaccine and pneumococcal
             vaccines are not applicable.).

          -  Subject has used any prescribed or nonprescribed drugs (including vitamins or natural
             and herbal remedies, e.g. St. John's Wort) in the 2 weeks prior to study drug
             administration.

          -  Subject has a history of smoking more than 10 cigarettes (or equivalent amount of
             tobacco) per day within 3 months prior to admission to the clinical unit.

          -  Subject has a history of drinking more than 21 units of alcohol per week (1 unit = 10
             g pure alcohol = 250 mL of beer [5%] or 35 mL of spirits [35%] or 100 mL of wine
             [12%]) (&gt; 14units of alcohol for female subjects) within 3 months prior to admission
             to the clinical unit or the subject tests positive for alcohol or drugs of abuse at
             Screening or Day -1 (amphetamines,barbiturates, benzodiazepines, cannabinoids,
             cocaine, and opiates).

          -  Subject has used any drugs of abuse within 3 months prior to admission to the clinical
             unit.

          -  Subject has had significant blood loss, donated 1 unit (450 mL) of blood or more, or
             received a transfusion of any blood or blood products within 60 days or donated plasma
             within 7 days prior to Day -1.

          -  Subject has a positive serology test for hepatitis B surface antigen (HBsAg),
             antihepatitis A virus (immunodeficiency virus [Ig]M), anti-hepatitis C virus,
             anti-hepatitis B core or antihuman immunodeficiency virus (HIV) at Screening.

          -  Subject has participated in any clinical study or has been treated with any
             investigational drugs within 3 moths prior to screening.

          -  Subject has any condition which makes the subject unsuitable for study participation.

          -  Subject is an employee of the Astellas Group, Clinical Research Organization (CRO) or
             the clinical unit.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>45 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Medical Moniter, Senior Manager</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Astellas Pharma China, Inc.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Astellas Pharma China Inc.</last_name>
    <phone>+86-(0)10-85216666</phone>
    <email>astellas.registration@astellas.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Site CN86001</name>
      <address>
        <city>Beijing</city>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 27, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 27, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 29, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 8, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 8, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 9, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>peficitinib</keyword>
  <keyword>ASP015K</keyword>
  <keyword>pharmacokinetics</keyword>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Peficitinib</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Access to anonymized individual participant level data will not be provided for this trial as it meets one or more of the exceptions described on www.clinicalstudydatarequest.com under &quot;Sponsor Specific Details for Astellas.&quot;</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

