<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04141410</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>13875 17/18 PO</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04141410</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Global Longitudinal Strain Assessment in Cardiogenic Shock During Sepsis</brief_title>
  <acronym>GLASSES-1</acronym>
  <official_title>Levosimendan and Global Longitudinal Strain Assessment in Cardiogenic Shock Sepsis (GLASSES 1): a Study Protocol for an Observational Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Azienda USL Toscana Centro</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Azienda USL Toscana Centro</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Cardiogenic shock is a condition of low cardiac output that represents the end of a
      progressive deterioration of cardiac function. The main cause is ischemic heart disease but
      there are several causes of non-ischemic nature including sepsis.

      Sepsis is characterized by a picture of organ dysfunction caused by an altered response of
      the body to an infection. Its most serious form is septic shock, defined as a picture of
      sepsis in which the underlying abnormalities in the cardiovascular system and cellular
      metabolism are such as to increase mortality. An organ failure correlates directly with the
      function of others and this interdependence is especially evident when a cardiovascular
      failure is established. 3 Cardiac dysfunction in sepsis can be defined as that of a syndrome
      characterized by low cardiac output not related to myocardial ischemia.

      The use of levosimendan in cardiogenic shock during sepsis was first described in a 2005 case
      report. Since then there have been small studies and other case reports that have shown
      improvements in right and left ventricular contractility, ventricular coupling,
      cardiopulmonary performance, global oxygen transport, renal and splanchnic perfusion when
      compared to dobutamine and placebo. Other beneficial effects of this drug have emerged,
      including an anti-inflammatory, antioxidant and antiapoptotic action with a possible
      protection from ischemia-reperfusion damage.

      The present study aims to evaluate the correct use of levosimendan, after the occurrence of
      cardiogenic shock on a low cardiac index has been ascertained, with the aim of weaning from
      inotropic drugs in infusion.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The present is an observational single centre no profit study. The duration is expected to be
      12 months from September 2019.

      The study will be conducted by enrolling patients aged 18 to 80 years in intensive care with
      diagnosis of septic shock according to the Third National Consensus Definitions for Sepsis
      and Septic Shock2, with the need for infusion of vasoactive drugs to maintain a PAM &gt; 65
      mmHg. The following will be subjected to echocardiographic examination with Sparq ultrasound
      machine (Philips Healthcare, Best, the Netherlands) and 3.6 MHz cardiology probe through
      which will be acquired the apical projections 2, 3 and 4 chambers necessary to calculate the
      global longitudinal strain (GLS) through AutoSTRAIN© (TOMTEC Imaging Systems GmbH,
      Unterschleissheim, Germany).

      During the echocardiographic examination, the Ea/Ees ratio (ventricle-arterial coupling) will
      also be calculated using the method modified on a single beat of Chen (t0) 18 using the
      IElastance® application. Patients will be monitored with the PiCCO® system (Pulse index
      Continuous Cardiac Output, Pulsion Medical systems, Munich, Germany) which measures the
      cardiac index (CI) and the Stroke Volume Index (SVI). Those with Ea//Ees &gt; 1, cardiac index
      values &lt; 2.5 L/min/m2 and/or Stroke Volume Index &lt; 30 mL/beat/m2 will be considered eligible
      to enroll in the study. In these patients, dobutamine infusion will be started from 5
      mcg/kg/min following the bundles of the Surviving Sepsis Campaign at dosages that allow to
      obtain an CI &gt;2.5 L/min/m2 and/or Stroke Volume Index &gt;30 mL/beat/m2. With 24 hours to go
      before the dobutamine infusion starts, CI and SVI will be recalculated using PiCCO®, GLS and
      ventricle-arterial coupling index by ultrasound investigation and then levosimendan infusion
      will begin for 24 hours starting with an infusion of 0.1 mcg/kg/min in order to wean the
      patient from dobutamine infusion. Once the infusion cycle of the calcium-sensitizing drug has
      been carried out, if possible, the infusion of dobutamine will be reduced until it stops and
      CI, SVI, GLS and Ea/Ees will also be re-evaluated. The same echocardiographic evaluations and
      hemodynamic calculations using PiCCO® will be performed 72 and 96 hours after the start of
      the dobutamine infusion. All patients enrolled will be followed up by a Medical Outcomes
      Survey Short-Form 36 (SF-36) questionnaire 28 days and 90 days after discharge from intensive
      care.

      It should be noted that all the procedures described (including echocardiographic monitoring)
      comply in quantity and frequency with the normal practice of care and management of patients
      admitted to intensive care with diagnosis of cardiogenic shock during sepsis in Azienda USL
      Toscana Centro.

      In addition, the parameters measured during the echocardiographic examination are derived
      from the reprocessing of the images collected during the examination and therefore simply
      represent an in-depth examination for diagnostic purposes performed according to current
      practice at the Centre.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 21, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 21, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 21, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Control</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Global Longitudinal Strain ≥ 15%</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 1 week</time_frame>
    <description>Recovery of normal values of GLS ≥ 15% after infusion of dobutamine and levosimendan</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mortality</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Mortality reduction 30% based on studies where GLS &gt;-15% had half the mortality in those who had a value &lt; 15%.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">35</enrollment>
  <condition>Sepsis</condition>
  <condition>Septic Shock</condition>
  <condition>Cardiogenic Shock</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Levosimendan</intervention_name>
    <description>Use of Levosimendan in cardiogenic shock during sepsis</description>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Echocardiography</intervention_name>
    <description>Use of global longitudinal strain in cardiogenic shock during sepsis</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Eligible patients will be those admitted to the intensive care units of the hospital Santo
        Stefano in Prato with diagnosis of cardiogenic shock during sepsis and who will present the
        following criteria for inclusion.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Informed Consent

          -  Age between 18 and 80 years old

          -  Diagnosis di Sepsis following criteria of Third National Consensus Definitions for
             Sepsis and Septic Shock 2

          -  Diagnosis of Cardiogenic Shock with Heart Index &lt; 2.5 L/min/m2 calculated by PiCCO
             thermodilution method and/or Diagnosis of Stroke Cardiogenic Shock Volume Index &lt; 30
             mL/beat/m2 calculated by PiCCO thermodilution method

          -  Patients applying for treatment with dobutamine and levosimendan according to the
             procedure laid down in current clinical practice at the Centre

          -  Ventricle coupling Arterial Ea/Ees &gt; 1 via IElastance application

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Age &lt; 18 years and &gt; 80 years

          -  Pre-existing diagnosis of heart failure at a reduced or preserved ejection fraction

          -  History of valvular heart disease or valve replacement and/or PM implant

          -  Severe pulmonary hypertension and chronic pulmonary heart

          -  Poor acoustic windows for echocardiography

          -  History of hypersensitivity or allergy to levosimendan
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Iacopo Cappellini, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Azienda USL Toscana Centro</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Iacopo Cappellini, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+393398921412</phone>
    <email>jacopocappellini@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Iacopo Cappellini</last_name>
    <phone>+393398921412</phone>
    <email>jacopocappellini@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ospedale Santo Stefano</name>
      <address>
        <city>Prato</city>
        <state>FI</state>
        <zip>59100</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Iacopo Cappellini, MD</last_name>
      <phone>3398921412</phone>
      <email>iacopo.cappellini@uslcentro.toscana.it</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Italy</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 24, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 25, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 28, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 25, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 25, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 28, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Azienda USL Toscana Centro</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Iacopo Cappellini</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Sepsis</keyword>
  <keyword>Septic Shock</keyword>
  <keyword>Cardiogenic Shock</keyword>
  <keyword>Speckle Tracking Echocardiography</keyword>
  <keyword>Levosimendan</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Sepsis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Toxemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Shock, Septic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Shock, Cardiogenic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Shock</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Simendan</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Statistical Analysis Plan (SAP)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Informed Consent Form (ICF)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>Data will be available for 1 year from October 2019</ipd_time_frame>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

