<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04143243</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>D3117-R</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04143243</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>One-day Life Skills Workshop for Veterans With TBI, Pain, and Psychopathology: Evaluating Efficacy and Mechanism of Change</brief_title>
  <official_title>One-day Life Skills Workshop for Veterans With TBI, Pain, and Psychopathology: Evaluating Efficacy and Mechanism of Change</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>VA Office of Research and Development</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>VA Office of Research and Development</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Mild traumatic brain injury (mTBI) is the signature wound of Veterans returning from the
      operations in Iraq and Afghanistan (i.e., OIF/OEF/OND), with up to 20 percent experiencing
      persistent post-concussive symptoms. Among Veterans with mTBI, the majority also experience
      stress-based psychopathology (e.g., depression, post-traumatic stress disorder, and/or
      generalized anxiety disorder) and chronic pain. To cope with distress, pain, and other
      difficulties, Veterans often turn to maladaptive avoidant coping strategies which offer short
      term relief but exacerbate/maintain mental health problems and have detrimental long-term
      effects on social, occupational, and community reintegration. Unfortunately, Veterans face
      important barriers to seeking mental health treatment, including stigma and logistical
      issues. This proposal aims to examine 1) the impact of a Veteran-centered, non-stigmatizing,
      1-day &quot;life skills group workshop&quot; on overall distress and reintegration; and 2) the
      mechanisms by which this treatment might work as well as possible influences on treatment
      efficacy.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Traumatic brain injury (TBI) is the signature wound of Veterans returning from Operations
      Iraqi Freedom, Operation Enduring Freedom and Operation New Dawn (OIF/OEF/OND), with up to 20
      percent exposed to a mild TBI (mTBI) and experiencing persistent post-concussive symptoms.
      Among those with a mTBI diagnosis, the majority also suffers from stress-based
      psychopathology (e.g., depression, post-traumatic stress disorder, generalized anxiety
      disorder), as well as chronic pain. To cope with distress, pain, and other difficulties,
      Veterans often turn to maladaptive avoidant coping strategies which offer short term relief
      but exacerbate/maintain mental health problems and have detrimental long-term effects on
      social, occupational, and community reintegration. Unfortunately, Veterans face significant
      barriers to engaging in mental health treatment, including stigma, the belief that one should
      overcome psychological difficulties on his/her own, and concern that receiving such care
      would negatively impact their careers. Practical barriers, including time constraints,
      distance from a treatment facility, and competing priorities (e.g., work and family demands),
      are also barriers to care. Even among Veterans who start mental health treatment, only a
      small minority complete a recommended course of evidence-based therapy.

      Acceptance and Commitment Therapy (ACT) is a trans-diagnostic treatment model that helps
      patients to overcome avoidance by promoting acceptance-based coping and engagement in
      meaningful life activities. In this context, Veterans are asked to think about their &quot;new
      mission(s)&quot; after leaving the military and the importance of engaging in actions that fulfill
      their mission even when it may be difficult. ACT has established efficacy in the treatment of
      depression, anxiety, and chronic pain, and has been effectively implemented in various
      treatment-delivery formats, including 1-day group workshops. A 1-day ACT workshop addresses
      specific needs of Veterans with mTBI, stress-based psychopathology, and chronic pain
      (polytrauma triad) and important barriers to treatment. It 1) is trans-diagnostic (i.e.,
      applies to more than one condition); 2) targets avoidance-based coping; 3) cultivates
      acceptance-based coping and builds on Veteran's values and goals to motivate them to make
      difficult decisions; 4) is delivered efficiently and thus more accessible; 5) is less
      stigmatizing and thus acceptable; and 6) address problems with treatment adherence and
      completion.

      With the support of an RR&amp;D SPiRE pilot grant, the PIs developed a 1-day 'ACT on Life'
      workshop tailored specifically for the needs of Veterans with mTBI, stress-based
      psychopathology, and chronic pain. Veterans with this polytrauma were then randomly assigned
      to the 'ACT on Life' workshop (N=20) or to Treatment as Usual (TAU; N=12). All Veterans
      attending the 1-day ACT workshop completed it, and relative to TAU, exhibited greater
      improvements in distress and reintegration at the 3-month follow-up (effect sizes .68 and
      .47, respectively). Building on these promising preliminary findings, the investigators now
      propose to conduct a more rigorous randomized controlled trial with 212 Veterans to compare
      the efficacy of the 1-day ACT workshop to an active treatment comparison (Education,
      Resources, and Support; ERS) on symptoms of distress and social, occupational, and community
      reintegration. The investigators will also examine mediators and moderators of treatment
      response to identify which ACT components are directly responsible for treatment
      effectiveness and whether treatment benefits are constrained by various personal factors.

      Establishing the efficacy of a 1-day ACT workshop for OEF/OEF/OND Veterans with mTBI and
      multiple coexistent conditions addresses key priorities of VHA RR&amp;D: 1. developing
      interventions which will improve the psychological health status of Veterans who have
      specific needs; and 2. enhancing the community, social, and occupational reintegration and
      functioning of post-deployment Veterans so that they may function more fully in society.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>ACT plus Education, Resources and Support ('ACT on Life') workshop compared to Education, Resources, &amp; Support only workshop (ERS)</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>Patients will not be told which group they are being allocated to. Follow-up assessments will be administered by anl interviewer blinded to patient assignment.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The Depression Anxiety and Stress Scale (DASS-21)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>This 21-item measure consists of three self-report scales that measure current symptoms of depression, anxiety, and stress and a total score. It has shown adequate construct validity, internal consistency, and convergent and discriminant validity. It has been used extensively in clinical trials, including those with military populations</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Military to Civilian Questionnaire (M2C-Q)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>This 16-item self-report measure assesses post-deployment difficulties with reintegration during the previous month. Respondents rate the level of difficulty on a 5-point scale from No Difficulty to Extreme Difficulty. The following domains are covered by the M2C-Q: Social relations, community engagement, perceived meaning in life, self-care and leisure, and parenting. Higher scores reflecting greater difficulty with reintegration.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The PTSD Checklist for DSM-5 (PCL-5)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>This self-report measure assesses symptoms of PTSD based on criteria of the Diagnostic and Statistical Manual for Mental Disorders - Version 5 (DSM-5). This 20-item scale is available from the National Center for PTSD and is extensively used in Veteran populations</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Defense and Veterans Pain Rating Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>This pain assessment tool assesses severity of pain as well as the impact of pain on usual activity and sleep, on mood, and on stress levels. It utilizes a numerical rating scale enhanced by functional word descriptors, color coding, and facial expressions matched to pain levels. It is a reliable and valid instrument developed for use in military populations</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Acceptance and Action Questionnaire-II</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>This self-report measures assesses experiential avoidance, or the tendency to avoid unwanted internal experiences (e.g., &quot;I try hard to avoid feeling depressed or anxious&quot;), as well as acceptance, the term used to describe the counter process (e.g., &quot;My thoughts and feelings do not get in the way of how I want to live my life&quot;). The AAQ was designed to measure mechanisms hypothesized to be at work in ACT treatments and has been found to mediate behavioral outcomes in ACT interventions 23. It has been shown to have good internal consistency and validity.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Valued Living Questionnaire (VLQ)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>This self-report measure assesses engagement in valued areas of life. Participants first rate the importance of 10 life domains (e.g., family, work, friends, spirituality, etc.) on a 10-point Likert scale (1 = not at all important to 10 = extremely important). They then rate the degree to which their actions over the past week were consistent with each value, from 1 (not at all consistent) to 10 (extremely consistent). The discrepancy between consistency and importance reflects the degree to which a person is engaging in meaningful life areas</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Self-reported service utilization</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Frequency of visits for physical and emotional problems in inpatient, emergency room, and outpatient settings, as well as frequency of medical or community services during which emotional or functional problems were discussed will be assessed at each contact.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">212</enrollment>
  <condition>Traumatic Brain Injury</condition>
  <condition>Chronic Pain</condition>
  <condition>Post Traumatic Stress Disorder</condition>
  <condition>Depression</condition>
  <condition>Anxiety</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>ACT on Life</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Acceptance and Commitment Therapy plus Education, Resources and Support ('ACT on Life').
The ACT+ERS intervention will include: 1) Acceptance and Mindfulness Training (2-3 hours); 2) Committed Action Training (2-3 hours) involving helping Veterans clarify what matters most to them and what they want to stand for in life, how they want to behave, and what sorts of strengths and qualities they want to develop; and; 3) Education, Resources, and Support (1 hour).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Education, Resources, and Support</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Information provided in the ERS workshop was compiled from existing VHA and community resources. Veterans will be educated about 1) symptoms of depression, anxiety and PTSD and how these conditions do and do not impact daily life and functional ability; 2) common difficulties and challenges with reintegration into civilian life; 3) mild TBI, differences between civilian and Veteran TBIs, shared/crossover symptoms (for example, memory and concentration difficulties, sleep disturbance, irritability can be symptoms of depression, PTSD, and mild TBI); 4) chronic pain; how it is often often misinterpreted as on-going damage, leading to fear of physical activities and resulting in increased sedentary behavior and declines in physical functioning; and 5) treatment options and resources. Basic resource counseling will include guidance on the evidence-based treatments available at VHA. Problem solving, relaxation, and deep breathing techniques will be covered</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ACT on Life</intervention_name>
    <description>1 day group workshop of ACT plus ERS</description>
    <arm_group_label>ACT on Life</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>ACT plus ERS</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Education, Resources, and Support</intervention_name>
    <description>1 day group workshop of Education, Resources, and Support</description>
    <arm_group_label>Education, Resources, and Support</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>ERS</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  OIF/OEF/OND Veteran

          -  Stress-based psychopathology, as operationalized by a diagnosis of major depressive
             disorder, generalized anxiety disorder, or PTSD on the M.I.N.I. International
             Neuropsychiatric interview (M.I.N.I.)

          -  Deployment-related mild TBI according to the definition of VA/DOD Clinical Practice
             Guidelines and determined by interview on the Boston Assessment of TBI-Lifetime
             (BAT-L)

          -  Pain intensity and level of interference reported to be 5 (moderate) on the Defense
             and Veterans Pain Rating Scale (DVPRS)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  History of bipolar disorder or primary psychotic disorder (e.g., schizophrenia,
             schizoaffective disorder) on the M.I.N.I.

          -  A current diagnosis of severe substance use disorder on the M.I.N.I.

          -  Moderate to severe suicide risk on the suicidality scale on the M.I.N.I.

          -  History of neurological illness not related to TBI (self-reported and confirmed by Dr.
             Jorge)

          -  Severe medical illness (e.g. liver failure, severe coronary artery disease and /or
             heart failure) posing a new and significant stress burden and requiring intensive
             treatment (self-reported and confirmed by Dr. Jorge)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Lilian N. Dindo, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Michael E. DeBakey VA Medical Center, Houston, TX</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Lilian N Dindo, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>(713) 440-4637</phone>
    <email>lilian.dindo@va.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Ricardo E Jorge, MD</last_name>
    <phone>(319) 338-0581</phone>
    <email>Ricardo.Jorge@va.gov</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Michael E. DeBakey VA Medical Center, Houston, TX</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Lilian N Dindo, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>713-440-4637</phone>
      <email>lilian.dindo@va.gov</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Mark E Kunik, MD MPH</last_name>
      <phone>(713) 794-8646</phone>
      <email>kunik.marke@va.gov</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Lilian N. Dindo, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 25, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 25, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 29, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 22, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 22, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 24, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Acceptance and Commitment Therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Veterans</keyword>
  <keyword>polytrauma</keyword>
  <keyword>traumatic brain injury</keyword>
  <keyword>chronic pain</keyword>
  <keyword>Post Traumatic Stress Disorder</keyword>
  <keyword>depression</keyword>
  <keyword>Anxiety</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Brain Injuries</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Brain Injuries, Traumatic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Chronic Pain</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depression</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Stress Disorders, Traumatic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Stress Disorders, Post-Traumatic</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

