<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04141631</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>RECHMPL19_0042</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04141631</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Transfusion Savings in Heart Surgery: Impact of Individual Strategy by Erythropoietin and Metabolic Adjustment (ScvO2)</brief_title>
  <acronym>BLOOCOST</acronym>
  <official_title>Patient Blood Management in Cardiac Surgery by Erythropoietin, Ferric Carboxymaltose and Metabolic Adjustment (ScvO2): A Randomized Controlled Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University Hospital, Montpellier</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University Hospital, Montpellier</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Preoperative anemia, bleeding and transfusions have been recognized as a &quot;Deadly triad&quot; in
      cardiac surgery associated with an increased morbidity,mortality, and costs related. Thus
      strategies to reduce unnecessary RBC transfusions and to optimize preoperative anemia must be
      developed .The study evaluate an individual blood conservation strategy based on patient
      blood management bundles in cardiac surgery patients: optimisation perioperative hemoglobin
      level by erythropoietin and ferric carboxymaltose (Ferinject) associated with the use of
      ScV02 to guide perioperative erythrocyte transfusion.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Preoperative anemia is the most common haematological abnormalities in cardiac surgery
      affecting 20 to 40% of patients and is becoming increasingly prevalent due to an ageing
      population with more chronic diseases.Preoperative anemia is independently associated with
      increased risk of adverse outcome following cardiac surgery but also implies blood
      transfusions which, associated with anemia, increase significantly perioperative cardiac
      morbidity and mortality. Therefore, strategies of blood conservation to optimize anemia and
      to minimize transfusion have been developped in the concept of the Blood Patient Management
      (BPM). To correct anemia, intravenous iron has been shown to be an effective treatment with
      increase hemoglobin (Hb) level in the perioperative period. It is now established that
      intravenous iron, as ferric carboxymaltose (Ferinject) is better tolerated compared to oral
      supplementation with better stimulation of erythropoiesis and,consequently, higher Hb levels.
      Based on promising results in the orthopedic surgery patients, the use of recombinant human
      erythropoietin (EPO) has also been proposed in cardiac surgery. Secondly, because even one
      red blood cells products (RBC) compromises postoperative outcome, guidelines suggest to adopt
      restrictive threshold of Hb levels to decide RBC transfusion. However, beyond the fact that
      RBC transfusion correct Hb level, the final goal of blood transfusion is to improve oxygen
      delivery to hypoxemic tissue. In this respect, the relevance of the use of a Hb threshold to
      guide transfusion have been questioned. Venous oxygen saturation (SvO2) and ScvO2 (central
      oxygen venous saturation), global parameters of tissue oxygenation, in stable hemodynamic and
      respiratory conditions, may be an relevant marker of anemia tolerance. Recently, the
      investigators demonstrated the lack of benefit in terms of ScvO2 increase during erythrocyte
      transfusion if ScvO2 was &gt; 65%.

      In order to reduce exposure to transfusion, the management of anemia with EPO and
      perioperative intravenous FCM associated with the use of ScvO2 could be interesting to both
      improve Hb levels and reduce RBC transfusion.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 13, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 31, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 31, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Transfusion incidence at hospital discharge</measure>
    <time_frame>up to Day 28</time_frame>
    <description>Number of patients transfused of blood units</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>ICU transfusion incidence</measure>
    <time_frame>at ICU discharge or up to Day 28</time_frame>
    <description>Number of blood units transfused during ICU stay</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>total of blood units transfused</measure>
    <time_frame>up to day 28</time_frame>
    <description>number of blood units administered per patient</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hemoglobin level at discharge</measure>
    <time_frame>at surgery discharge or at Day 28</time_frame>
    <description>the last hemoglobin value</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The total duration of mechanical ventilation</measure>
    <time_frame>at ICU discharge or up to Day 28</time_frame>
    <description>The total duration of mechanical ventilation in ICU</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>length of stay in ICU</measure>
    <time_frame>up to day 28</time_frame>
    <description>numbers of days in ICU</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Length of hospital stay</measure>
    <time_frame>at day 28</time_frame>
    <description>Length of stay during hospitalization (Between 1 and 28 day)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of Mortality</measure>
    <time_frame>at day 28</time_frame>
    <description>Incidence of 28-day mortality</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of postoperative events in ICU</measure>
    <time_frame>at day 28</time_frame>
    <description>AKI (KDIGO criteria), Cardiac dysfunction (acute heart failure requiring inotrope or extracorporeal life support (ECLS), arrythmia), vascular dysfunction (norepinephrine support without sepsis), respiratory dysfunction (non invasive ventilation devices, secondary intubation,mechanical ventilation more than 12 hours), septic complications (sepsis/septic shock)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">128</enrollment>
  <condition>Cardiac Surgery</condition>
  <condition>Transfusion</condition>
  <condition>Perioperative Anemia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>STOP Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>EPO (600UI/Kg, sub-cutaneous) and Ferric Carboxymaltose (FCM) (20 mg/kg in 250 mL of saline solution 0.9% over 15 min) will be administered if
Hb &lt; 12g/dL the day before surgery
Hb ≥ 7g/dL AND ScvO2 &gt; 65% in postoperative ICU stay
Postoperative Transfusion will be guided by ScvO2 values :
if Hb ≤ 8 g/dL AND ScvO2 ≤ 65% or if Hb &lt; 7g/dL independently of ScVO2 value</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Only postoperative anemia will be managed:
RBC transfusion will be performed if Hb ≤ 8 g/dL (2017 EACTS/EACTA guidelines)
Iron sucrose administration if Hb &gt; 8g/dL : 2 injections of 200 mg according to Height (+/- 70 Kg) in 250 mL of saline solution 0.9% over 1h30 into 48 h intervals without exceeding a total dose of 15mg/kg.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>EPO (600UI/Kg, sub-cutaneous) and Ferric Carboxymaltose (FCM) (20 mg/kg in 250 mL of saline solution 0.9% over 15 min)</intervention_name>
    <description>EPO (600UI/Kg, sub-cutaneous) and Ferric Carboxymaltose (FCM) (20 mg/kg in 250 mL of saline solution 0.9% over 15 min) will be administered if
Hb &lt; 12g/dL the day before surgery
Hb ≥ 7g/dL AND ScvO2 &gt; 65% in postoperative ICU stay
Postoperative Transfusion will be guided by ScvO2 values :
if Hb ≤ 8 g/dL AND ScvO2 ≤ 65% or if Hb &lt; 7g/dL independently of ScVO2 value</description>
    <arm_group_label>STOP Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Scheduled Cardiac surgery for more than 24 hours

          -  High risk of perioperative transfusion defined by a TRUST Score ≥ 3

          -  Veno-Venous catheter in Superior vena cava territory

          -  Patient Affiliate or beneficiary of social security

          -  Collection on free, informed and written consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  EPO and FCM contraindication

          -  Patients already treated by EPO at the time of inclusion

          -  Non controlled Infectious endocarditis defined by ESC guidelines 2015

          -  Patients including in an other research

          -  Patients whose physical and/or psychological health is severely impaired and who,
             according to the investigator, may affect the participant's compliance with the study.

          -  Patients deprived from his rights (guardianship or tutelage measure)

          -  Patients who refuses to sign the consent

          -  pregnant or lactating woman
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>90 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Marine SAOUR, Doctor</last_name>
    <phone>0033467335958</phone>
    <email>m-saour@chu-montpellier.fr</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>DEpartement d'anesthésie et réanimation D - Arnaud de Villeneuve</name>
      <address>
        <city>Montpellier</city>
        <zip>34295</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>MArine Saour, Doctor</last_name>
      <phone>003367335958</phone>
      <email>m-saour@chu-montpellier.fr</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ranucci M, Baryshnikova E, Castelvecchio S, Pelissero G; Surgical and Clinical Outcome Research (SCORE) Group. Major bleeding, transfusions, and anemia: the deadly triad of cardiac surgery. Ann Thorac Surg. 2013 Aug;96(2):478-85. doi: 10.1016/j.athoracsur.2013.03.015. Epub 2013 May 11.</citation>
    <PMID>23673069</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Plicht B, Lind A, Erbel R. [Infective endocarditis : New ESC guidelines 2015]. Internist (Berl). 2016 Jul;57(7):675-90. doi: 10.1007/s00108-016-0086-y. Review. German.</citation>
    <PMID>27307162</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Alghamdi AA, Davis A, Brister S, Corey P, Logan A. Development and validation of Transfusion Risk Understanding Scoring Tool (TRUST) to stratify cardiac surgery patients according to their blood transfusion needs. Transfusion. 2006 Jul;46(7):1120-9.</citation>
    <PMID>16836558</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Task Force on Patient Blood Management for Adult Cardiac Surgery of the European Association for Cardio-Thoracic Surgery (EACTS) and the European Association of Cardiothoracic Anaesthesiology (EACTA), Boer C, Meesters MI, Milojevic M, Benedetto U, Bolliger D, von Heymann C, Jeppsson A, Koster A, Osnabrugge RL, Ranucci M, Ravn HB, Vonk ABA, Wahba A, Pagano D. 2017 EACTS/EACTA Guidelines on patient blood management for adult cardiac surgery. J Cardiothorac Vasc Anesth. 2018 Feb;32(1):88-120. doi: 10.1053/j.jvca.2017.06.026. Epub 2017 Sep 30. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>29029990</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 4, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 24, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 28, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 20, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 20, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 23, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Perioperative Erythropoietin</keyword>
  <keyword>Perioperative Iron</keyword>
  <keyword>ScVO2</keyword>
  <keyword>Patient blood Management</keyword>
  <keyword>Blood Transfusion</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

