<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03988296</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Pro00102072</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03988296</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Molecular Diagnostic Methods for Detection of Plasmodium Knowlesi</brief_title>
  <official_title>Adapting Novel Molecular Diagnostic Methods for Detection of Plasmodium Knowlesi in Sarawak, Malaysia</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Duke University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Duke University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study aims to determine the sensitivity, specificity, and practical value of two new
      molecular diagnostic assays compared to a more classical nested molecular diagnostic assay
      and the routine microscopy (both of which are the current gold standard) in detection of P.
      knowlesi.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 11, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">August 22, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">August 22, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Only</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Cross-Sectional</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of patients with a possible diagnosis of malaria</measure>
    <time_frame>10 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Possible diagnosis of malaria as defined in accordance with the inclusion and exclusion criteria. Giemsa-stained thick and thin smears will be prepared for verification of parasitaemia by microscopy in the respective hospital laboratories</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Statistical association between risk factors and diagnostic assays results.</measure>
    <time_frame>10 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>A brief enrollment questionnaire will be used to determine a statistical association between demographic and behavioral/occupational risk factors and the assays results combined</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">116</enrollment>
  <condition>Plasmodium Knowlesi Infection</condition>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      5ml Whole blood samples will be collected in a labeled EDTA acid tube. A minimum of 250ul of
      whole blood will be used to prepare dried blood spots on filter cards at the time of patient
      enrollment in the respective hospital. Extracted DNA from the remaining whole blood sample
      will be used to conduct molecular assays at Clinical Research Centre Sibu Hospital. Extracted
      DNA will be tested with the new single-step polymerase chain reaction (PCR) and the nested
      PCR at Sibu Hospital. An aliquot of same DNA will be shipped on dry ice to the CDC (Georgia,
      USA) for performing photo-induced electron transfer - polymerase chain reaction (PET-PCR)
      assays
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Both adults and children &gt; 7 years old suspected for malaria and meeting inclusion criteria
        will be eligible to participate. Study subjects will be enrolled at Sarawak Hospitals, both
        hospitalized and outpatients, using an informed consent process (or assent for children
        7-18 years) that permits the completion of a brief questionnaire and collection of a blood
        sample.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Suspected for malaria infection; fever (axillary or tympanic temperature ≥ 37.5 °C or
             oral or rectal temperature of ≥ 38 °C) with chills, worsening malaise, headache
             lassitude, fatigue, abdominal discomfort, muscle and joint aches, anorexia,
             perspiration, or vomiting at the time of evaluation or within the past 48 hours

          -  Written informed consent is obtained.

          -  For Children (&gt;7 to &lt;18 years): parent or legal guardian provides written informed
             consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients living in, or returning from malaria endemic area outside of Sarawak within 2
             weeks of illness onset

          -  They have a clear alternative diagnosis other than malaria by a trained health care
             professional.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>7 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Gregory C. Gray, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Duke University Medical Centre</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Kapit Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kapit</city>
        <state>Sarawak</state>
        <zip>96800</zip>
        <country>Malaysia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sarikei Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sarikei</city>
        <state>Sarawak</state>
        <zip>96100</zip>
        <country>Malaysia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sibu Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sibu</city>
        <state>Sarawak</state>
        <zip>96000</zip>
        <country>Malaysia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Malaysia</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Richards J, Mueller I. Identifying the risks for human transmission of Plasmodium knowlesi. Lancet Planet Health. 2017 Jun;1(3):e83-e85. doi: 10.1016/S2542-5196(17)30053-0. Epub 2017 Jun 9.</citation>
    <PMID>29851611</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Imai N, White MT, Ghani AC, Drakeley CJ. Transmission and control of Plasmodium knowlesi: a mathematical modelling study. PLoS Negl Trop Dis. 2014 Jul 24;8(7):e2978. doi: 10.1371/journal.pntd.0002978. eCollection 2014 Jul.</citation>
    <PMID>25058400</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Singh B, Daneshvar C. Human infections and detection of Plasmodium knowlesi. Clin Microbiol Rev. 2013 Apr;26(2):165-84. doi: 10.1128/CMR.00079-12. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23554413</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Singh B, Kim Sung L, Matusop A, Radhakrishnan A, Shamsul SS, Cox-Singh J, Thomas A, Conway DJ. A large focus of naturally acquired Plasmodium knowlesi infections in human beings. Lancet. 2004 Mar 27;363(9414):1017-24.</citation>
    <PMID>15051281</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Barber BE, William T, Grigg MJ, Yeo TW, Anstey NM. Limitations of microscopy to differentiate Plasmodium species in a region co-endemic for Plasmodium falciparum, Plasmodium vivax and Plasmodium knowlesi. Malar J. 2013 Jan 8;12:8. doi: 10.1186/1475-2875-12-8.</citation>
    <PMID>23294844</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Komaki-Yasuda K, Vincent JP, Nakatsu M, Kato Y, Ohmagari N, Kano S. A novel PCR-based system for the detection of four species of human malaria parasites and Plasmodium knowlesi. PLoS One. 2018 Jan 25;13(1):e0191886. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0191886. eCollection 2018.</citation>
    <PMID>29370297</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lucchi NW, Poorak M, Oberstaller J, DeBarry J, Srinivasamoorthy G, Goldman I, Xayavong M, da Silva AJ, Peterson DS, Barnwell JW, Kissinger J, Udhayakumar V. A new single-step PCR assay for the detection of the zoonotic malaria parasite Plasmodium knowlesi. PLoS One. 2012;7(2):e31848. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0031848. Epub 2012 Feb 20.</citation>
    <PMID>22363751</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lucchi NW, Narayanan J, Karell MA, Xayavong M, Kariuki S, DaSilva AJ, Hill V, Udhayakumar V. Molecular diagnosis of malaria by photo-induced electron transfer fluorogenic primers: PET-PCR. PLoS One. 2013;8(2):e56677. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0056677. Epub 2013 Feb 20.</citation>
    <PMID>23437209</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 13, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 13, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 17, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 30, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 30, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 2, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Monkey malaria</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Malaria</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Subjects' anonymity will be maintained and confidentiality of records and documents that could identify subjects will be protected, respecting the privacy and confidentiality rules in accordance with applicable regulatory requirements. Only the site principle investigators will be able to backlink the study data to the patient's medical record.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

