<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03988231</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IRB_00121324</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03988231</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Enoxaparin Versus Placebo for Venous Thromboembolism Prevention in Low Risk Cancer Patients After Surgical Procedures: a Randomized, Double Blind, Placebo Controlled Clinical Trial Pilot Study</brief_title>
  <official_title>Enoxaparin Versus Placebo for Venous Thromboembolism Prevention in Low Risk Cancer Patients After Surgical Procedures: a Randomized, Double Blind, Placebo Controlled Clinical Trial Pilot Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Utah</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Utah</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Post-surgical bleeding is a major source of morbidity in cancer patients, and ramifications
      can include need for transfusion, increased length of hospital stay, unexpected return to the
      operating room, or even death. Current guidelines support that all cancer patients who
      require surgical procedures receive post-operative blood thinners to minimize risk for blood
      clots in the legs or lungs, known as venous thromboembolism (VTE), but these medications have
      an unfavorable risk/benefit relationship among patients at low risk for VTE. The proposed
      work will pilot a randomized, double blind, placebo controlled trial to critically examine
      the role of de-implementation of current guidelines that mandate blood thinning medications
      among cancer patients at low risk for VTE who require surgical procedures; the pilot trial
      will allow optimization of the design of a future pragmatic multicenter trial, which
      ultimately would maximize patient safety after surgical procedures for cancer.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Post-operative bleeding is a major source of morbidity in cancer patients who require
      surgery. Bleeding is a primary concern for oncology providers because of its short and long
      term implications, including unanticipated transfusion, increased length of hospitalization,
      unexpected return to the operating room, or even death. Despite these risks, current
      guidelines for prevention of venous thromboembolism (VTE) in surgical patients support
      provision of anticoagulant medications to all post-operative patients. New data shows that
      current practice has an unfavorable risk/benefit relationship for the majority of cancer
      patients who need surgery.

      Cancer and need for a surgical procedure are two recognized risk factors for VTE—this has
      created the perception that post-operative anticoagulants are appropriate for all cancer
      patients. Current VTE prevention guidelines are largely geared toward the &quot;average&quot; cancer
      patient who requires surgery, based on aggregate data from large groups of surgical patients
      who have similar procedures. Emerging data demonstrates that the 2005 Caprini score, a
      patient-centric VTE risk calculator, can identify a 15-fold variation in post-operative VTE
      risk among the overall surgical population. Data from our National Comprehensive Cancer
      Network (NCCN) center support that the Caprini score is valid specifically in oncologic
      surgery patients, and that 50% of cancer patients have Caprini scores ≤6 with an expected
      90-day VTE rate of less than one percent. Our preliminary data show that low risk Caprini ≤6
      patients have a substantial increase in bleeding (3.8% vs. 1.8%) but have no demonstrable VTE
      risk reduction when post-operative anticoagulants are provided.

      Current guidelines that mandate chemical prophylaxis for cancer patients who have surgical
      procedures require a strategy that has no proven benefit and may produce a bleeding-related
      harm. The proposed work will utilize current paradigms of individualized VTE risk
      stratification to identify cancer surgery patients at low risk for VTE and will examine the
      impact of de-implementation of chemical prophylaxis in this low risk population The
      investigators will conduct a randomized, double blind, placebo controlled pilot trial at the
      Huntsman Cancer Institute, which is an NCCN site. The trial will identify surgical patients
      at low risk (Caprini score ≤6) for post-operative VTE and will randomize them to standard of
      care (enoxaparin 40mg once daily) versus placebo for the duration of inpatient stay. The
      trial will generate critical, real world data from an NCCN site that quantifies patient
      eligibility &amp; patient and provider willingness to randomize as well as expected 90-day
      attrition and event rates. This pilot study would generate trial-specific infrastructure and
      experience while providing data necessary for sample size calculations for a larger pragmatic
      trial to fully examine the impact of chemical prophylaxis de-implementation in cancer surgery
      patients at low risk for VTE.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">July 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator)</masking>
    <masking_description>Randomized, double blind, placebo controlled trial</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>90-day symptomatic venous thromboembolism</measure>
    <time_frame>90 days</time_frame>
    <description>Symptomatic VTE will include 1) any deep venous thrombosis event, including upper limb, lower limb, or central veins (inferior vena cava, portal vein, etc) that is confirmed with imaging including but not limited to duplex ultrasound, CT scan, or venogram and/or 2) any pulmonary embolus event that is confirmed with imaging, including but not limited to CT scan, venogram, or V/Q scan and/or 3) any autopsy-proven VTE and/or 4) 90-day mortality in which VTE cannot be excluded (eg PEA arrest with no autopsy performed).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>90-day clinically relevant bleeding</measure>
    <time_frame>90 days</time_frame>
    <description>Symptomatic or clinically overt bleeding that is associated with one or more of a) transfusion of ≥2 units of blood, b) hemoglobin decrease of &gt;2g/dL, or c) need for reoperation or invasive intervention such as wound opening or percutaneous drainage procedure and/or
Symptomatic or clinically overt bleeding at a critical anatomic site, including intracranial, intraspinal, intraocular, retroperitoneal, intraarticular, pericardial, or within a muscle compartment causing compartment syndrome
Fatal bleeding, in which the bleeding event directly contributes to death or causes clinical deterioration leading to death
In addition, we include clinically overt bleeding in which the surgeon chooses to discontinue study drug (enoxaparin versus placebo) prior to hospital discharge as a bleeding event.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">105</enrollment>
  <condition>Venous Thromboembolism</condition>
  <condition>Bleeding as Surgical Complication (Treatment)</condition>
  <condition>Deep Venous Thrombosis</condition>
  <condition>Pulmonary Embolism</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Enoxaparin 40mg once daily</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>All patients will have enoxaparin prophylaxis or placebo initiated at 8 hours after surgery. Prophylaxis or placebo will be provided every 24 hours and will be continued for the duration of inpatient stay.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>All patients will have enoxaparin prophylaxis or placebo initiated at 8 hours after surgery. Prophylaxis or placebo will be provided every 24 hours and will be continued for the duration of inpatient stay.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Receipt of enoxaparin</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients will be randomized to enoxaparin 40mg once daily versus saline placebo at 8 hours after surgery and continued for the duration of inpatient stay.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Enoxaparin 40mg once daily</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients will be randomized to enoxaparin 40mg once daily versus saline placebo at 8 hours after surgery and continued for the duration of inpatient stay.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        The five most common cancers in the United States, based on National Cancer Institute data,
        include breast, lung, urologic (prostate and bladder), colorectal, and melanoma. As such,
        we will conduct our work in these patient populations to make our results as generalizable
        as possible.

        Inclusion criteria will include:

          -  Adult (age≥18) patients

          -  Surgical procedure under general anesthesia

          -  Caprini score ≤6

          -  Expected post-operative stay will be at least 23 hours (these are the patients for
             whom current guidelines mandate provision of chemical prophylaxis, but for whom
             current clinical practice demonstrates equipoise.)

        Exclusion criteria will include:

          -  Contraindication to use of enoxaparin

          -  Intracranial bleeding/stroke

          -  Hematoma or bleeding disorder

          -  Heparin-induced thrombocytopenia positive

          -  Creatinine clearance ≤ 30mL/min

          -  Serum creatinine &gt;1.6mg/dL

          -  Planned epidural anesthesia

          -  Scheduled return to the operating room within 90 days will be a criteria for
             exclusion—we will only consent patients for whom a single operative procedure is
             scheduled to avoid interruption of post-operative anticoagulation or placebo for a
             second operative procedure

          -  Patients with platelet count &lt;50k/uL will be excluded only with &quot;a positive in vitro
             test for anti-platelet antibody in the presence of enoxaparin sodium,&quot; per the
             enoxaparin package insert.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Christopher Pannucci, MD MS</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Utah</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Christopher Pannucci, MD MS</last_name>
    <phone>8015817719</phone>
    <email>christopher.pannucci@hsc.utah.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <verification_date>January 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 13, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 13, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 17, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 24, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 24, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 27, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Utah</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Christopher Pannucci</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pulmonary Embolism</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Thrombosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Thromboembolism</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Embolism</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Venous Thromboembolism</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Venous Thrombosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Enoxaparin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

