<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03980743</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>3622461</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03980743</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Interactive Obesity Treatment Approach (iOTA) for Obesity Prevention in Adults With Early Serious Mental Illness: iOTA-SMI</brief_title>
  <acronym>iOTA-eSMI</acronym>
  <official_title>Adaptation of an Evidence-based Interactive Obesity Treatment Approach (iOTA) for Obesity Prevention in Adults With Early Serious Mental Illness: iOTA-SMI</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Washington University School of Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Washington University School of Medicine</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Using a design-for-dissemination approach, this application proposes to use combined methods
      to adapt and pilot test an interactive obesity treatment approach (iOTA) for obesity
      prevention in early serious mental illness (eSMI) that uses text messaging to provide
      between-visit support. Derived from the lifestyle intervention used in the Diabetes
      Prevention Program, the parent iOTA targets diet, activity and adherence using web-based and
      health coach support.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Most obesity and related complications in serious mental illness (SMI) occur in the context
      of chronic psychiatric illness, but there are few treatments that work. Behavioral
      interventions face challenges with long-term effectiveness, implementation and
      sustainability. Medications have modest effectiveness at best, and/or pose serious side
      effect risks. This study focuses on prevention of chronic obesity by adapting and pilot
      testing a prevention-focused, interactive obesity treatment approach (iOTA) for use in
      persons with early-phase SMI (eSMI) experiencing initial weight gain, overweight or
      early-stage obesity. The intervention will be adapted from the most studied, effective iOTA,
      derived from the Diabetes Prevention Program. The parent iOTA uses health coaches who extend
      their sustainable reach with scalable, inexpensive, semi-automated text messaging. Using a
      formal evaluation process and a specific implementation science framework, planned
      adaptations for this application will address mechanisms to improve health-related awareness,
      insight and self-efficacy skills.

      Aim 1: Evaluate barriers and facilitators for intervention engagement, effectiveness and
      implementation, and identify needed adaptations of the prior iOTA for use in obesity
      attenuation in eSMI.

      Aim 2: Adapt the prior iOTA for use in obesity attenuation in eSMI, aiming to maximize
      acceptability, engagement, sustainable reach and target engagement for eSMI.

      Aim 3: Conduct a randomized pilot and feasibility study of iOTA-eSMI in a diverse sample of
      adults aged 18-45 with eSMI and initial weight gain, overweight or early class I obesity,
      comparing iOTA-eSMI to a health education condition.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 16, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 31, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 31, 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Body Mass Index</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 4, 8, 12, 16, 20, 24 and 36 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>weight in kilograms/height in meters squared</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Self Efficacy for Healthy Eating and Exercise</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 4, 8, 12, 16, 20, 24 and 36 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>This questionnaire includes 32 questions in two domains of self efficacy: 1) healthy eating and 2) exercise. Respondents are asked to recall how confident they have felt in doing positive health behaviors since the last study visit. Responses are on a likert scale of 1 - 5 (1 - 2 = I know I cannot do; 3 - 4 = Maybe I can; 5 = I know I can).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Psychophysical Skills &amp; Insight</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 4, 8, 12, 16, 20, 24 and 36 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>This questionnaire includes 10 questions, with three separate subscales (Self-determination, Cognitive control and Interoceptive Awareness). Respondents are asked to rate their own skills since the last study visit. Responses are on a likert scale of 1-5 (1 = never, 2 = rarely, 3 = sometimes, 4 = often, 5 = always). Scores are generated for each subscale, as well as a total score. Higher scores indicate greater degree of psychophysical awareness &amp; skills.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage response rate to text prompts</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 4, 8, 12, 16, 20, 24 and 36 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Treatment engagement</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Intervention feasibility, usability and acceptability as measured by the Contextual Technology Adaptation Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 4, 8, 12, 16, 20, 24 and 36 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>This questionnaire includes 35 questions, with five separate subscales (feedback on: the overall iOTA program, automatic text messages, personalized text messages, in-person visits and between-session phone check-ins). Respondents are asked to rate feasibility, acceptability and usability of the text messaging portion of the intervention since the last study visit. Responses are on a likert scale of 1-3 (1 = not at all/negative; 2 = moderate/neutral; 3 = always/positive). Scores are generated for each subscale, as well as a total score. Higher scores indicate more positive experiences.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Obesity</condition>
  <condition>Overweight</condition>
  <condition>Severe Mental Disorder</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>iOTA text messaging intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>There will be a 6 month &quot;active&quot; treatment phase consisting of monthly meetings with a study health coach to develop reasonable health goals and interactive text messaging to provide daily support and self-monitoring of behavior change goals between in-person visits. Participants may receive phone calls between visits from their health coach for additional support if needed. Following the active treatment phase, participants will receive daily health-related text messages for another 3 months.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Health Education text messaging intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>There will be a 6 month &quot;active&quot; treatment phase consisting of monthly in-person visits with a health coach to learn about healthy eating and activity behaviors, including developing readiness for health behavior change. Participants will not set specific health goals, but will receive weekly text messages about general health tips related to their in-person visits. Following the active treatment phase, participants will receive daily health-related text messages for another 3 months.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>iOTA text messaging intervention</intervention_name>
    <description>Over 6 months, participants in the iOTA arm will have monthly in-person visits with a health coach who will work with the participant to set goals for the upcoming month related to healthy eating and activity. The participant will receive daily text message health tips related to their goals, and will be prompted once a week to respond with a text indicating their weight and how they are doing with their goals. Following the 6-month active treatment phase, participants will receive text messages only for another 3 months.</description>
    <arm_group_label>iOTA text messaging intervention</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>iOTA</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Health Education text messaging intervention</intervention_name>
    <description>Over 6 months, participants in the Health Ed arm will also have monthly in-person visits with a health coach who will provide education on energy balance and problem-solving. Specific goals will not be set, but the health coach will assist participants in problem-solving any challenges. Participants will receive a weekly automated motivational text message health tip from the study related to what they learned in their health coaching sessions. Following the 6-month active treatment phase, participants will receive text messages only for another 3 months.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Health Education text messaging intervention</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Health Ed</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Aged 18-45 years

          -  &quot;At-risk&quot; weight defined as greater than 7% weight gain from baseline body weight in
             the prior 2 years, overweight (BMI 25-29.9) or class I obesity (BMI 30-32.49)

          -  Psychiatric disorder with less than 5 years of treatment

          -  Receiving case management services in one of the two CMHC study sites

          -  Rapid Estimate of Adult Literacy in Medicine-Short Form (REALM SF) score greater than
             4

          -  University of California, San Diego Brief Assessment of Capacity to Consent (UBACC)
             score greater than 14

          -  Not taking weight loss medications or participating in another behavioral weight loss
             intervention

          -  Willing and able to provide written informed consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Taking weight loss medications or participating in another behavioral weight loss
             intervention

          -  Documented diagnosis of diabetes and/or treatment with an antidiabetes agent
             (diagnoses of hypertension and hyperlipidemia acceptable)

          -  REALM SF61 score &lt; 4

          -  UBACC score &lt; 14

          -  Acute suicidality at time of screening

          -  Unwilling or unable to provide written informed consent.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>45 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ginger Nicol, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Washington University School of Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Bridget Kirk, BS</last_name>
    <phone>(314) 362-5939</phone>
    <email>bridget.kirk@wustl.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Julie Schweiger, CCRC</last_name>
    <phone>(314) 362-3153</phone>
    <email>schweigj@wustl.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>South Florida Behavioral Health Network</name>
      <address>
        <city>Miami</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33126</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Judy Hickson</last_name>
      <phone>786-235-7147</phone>
      <email>jhickson@sfbhn.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>John W Newcomer, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Washington University in St. Louis Medical School</name>
      <address>
        <city>Saint Louis</city>
        <state>Missouri</state>
        <zip>63110</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Bridget Kirk, BS</last_name>
      <phone>314-362-5939</phone>
      <email>bridget.kirk@wustl.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 4, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 7, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 10, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 24, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 24, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 25, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Obesity</keyword>
  <keyword>Overweight</keyword>
  <keyword>Severe Mental illness</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Obesity</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Overweight</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Mental Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

