<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03982693</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>19-05-H-01</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03982693</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Trial to Assess Chelation Therapy in Critical Limb Ischemia</brief_title>
  <acronym>TACT3a</acronym>
  <official_title>Trial to Assess Chelation Therapy in Critical Limb Ischemia</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Mt. Sinai Medical Center, Miami</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Mt. Sinai Medical Center, Miami</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      TACT3a is a double blind, placebo-controlled, randomized trial to test a novel therapy,
      edetate disodium-based chelation of environmentally acquired toxic metals, to reduce
      cardiovascular events including amputation in high-risk diabetic patients.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      TACT3a is a double blind, placebo-controlled, randomized trial to test a novel therapy,
      edetate disodium-based chelation of environmentally acquired toxic metals, to reduce
      cardiovascular events including amputation in high-risk diabetic patients.

      The study plans to enroll 50 patients with diabetes and critical limb ischemia (CLI) to
      prevent the major cardiovascular endpoints of major amputation, coronary revascularization,
      stroke, Myocardial Infarction (MI), or death (all-cause) during an average 1.25 years of
      follow-up. Patients will be randomly assigned to chelation or placebo with a 3:2 (30 active,
      20 placebo) allocation ratio. Treatment will consist of 40 active or placebo infusions over
      30 weeks. Active therapy will be the same edetate disodium-based infusion used safely and
      successfully in a previous published study, Trial to Assess Chelation Therapy (TACT).
      Baseline and post infusion urine metals will be collected. Following the final infusion,
      patients will be contacted quarterly until the end of the study.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 19, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator)</masking>
    <masking_description>double-blind</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Prevention of major cardiovascular endpoints</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years (average follow-up 1.25 years)</time_frame>
    <description>Major cardiovascular endpoints include: coronary revascularization, stroke, MI, death (all-cause), or major amputation</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Amputations</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years (average follow-up 1.25 years)</time_frame>
    <description>Major amputations due to vascular disease. Major amputations are defined as any procedure that results in amputation at the level above the ankle. 49, 50
Total amputations due to vascular disease</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Heart failure</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years (average follow-up 1.25 years)</time_frame>
    <description>• Heart failure hospitalizations or prolonged (&gt;12 hours) ER stay for heart failure</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in Pain severity</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years (average follow-up 1.25 years)</time_frame>
    <description>• Any changes in pain will be recorded at baseline, infusions 10, 20, 40 (or final), and end of study recorded using the Patient-Reported Outcomes Measurement Information System (PROMIS) Pain Interference- Short Form 8a. The scale range is 1 to 5, with 1 being the best outcome (no pain interference) and 5 the worse (very much interference)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Urine Metals</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>• Changes in urine metal levels measured at the Metals Core Lab and measured at baseline and infusion 40 (or final).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in Quality of Life</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years (average follow-up 1.25 years)</time_frame>
    <description>• Health-related quality of life (QOL) changes recorded at baseline, 10, 20, 40 (or final), and end of study using the 36-Item Short Form Health Survey (SF-36 v2). The 36 questions assess eight health-related concepts: physical functioning, role limitations due to physical health problems (role physical), bodily pain, general health, energy levels/fatigue (vitality), social functioning, role limitations due to emotional problems (role emotional), and psychological distress (mental health). The scales vary depending on the question asked.The survey will be used to detect change (better or worse) in participants' health state over the course of the study.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Wound Severity</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years (average follow-up 1.25 years)</time_frame>
    <description>Wound severity (quantified and imaged with HIPAA-compliant photography) photographed at baseline 10, 20, 40 (or final), and end of study</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in skin perfusion pressure in the ankle</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years (average follow-up 1.25 years)</time_frame>
    <description>• Changes in skin perfusion pressure will be measured at 10, 20, 40 (or final), and end of study, using the ankle-brachial index (mmHg)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in skin perfusion pressure in the toe</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years (average follow-up 1.25 years)</time_frame>
    <description>• Changes in skin perfusion pressure will be measured at 10, 20, 40 (or final), and end of study, using the toe-brachial index (mmHg).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in PAD Quality of Life</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years (average follow-up 1.25 years)</time_frame>
    <description>• PAD related quality of life (QOL) changes recorded at baseline, 10, 20, 40 (or final), and end of study using the Peripheral Artery Questionnaire (PAQ), which is a 20-item questionnaire measuring physical limitations, symptoms, symptom stability, treatment satisfaction, quality of life, and social function. The scales vary depending on the question asked. The survey will be used to detect change (better or worse) in participants responses over the course of the study.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Critical Limb Ischemia</condition>
  <condition>Diabetes</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Active</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>edetate disodium (EDTA)dff active infusion</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Placebo infusion</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Edetate Disodium</intervention_name>
    <description>The solution contains up to 3 g of edetate disodium adjusted based on creatinine clearance, 2 g of magnesium chloride, 100 mg of procaine hydrochloride, 2500 U of heparin, 7 g of ascorbate, 2 milliequivalent (mEq) potassium chloride (KCl), 840 mg sodium bicarbonate, 250 mg pantothenic acid, 100 mg of thiamine, 100 mg of pyridoxine, and sterile water to complete 500 mL.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Active</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>TACT EDTA infusion</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Placebo infusions consist of 500 ml normal saline.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age ≥ 50 years

          -  History of diabetes, defined as medical record evidence or patient report of currently
             using insulin or oral hypoglycemic agents, or with a history of fasting blood glucose
             measurement of 126 mg/dL or higher, or a history of HbA1c of 6.5% or higher.

          -  Significant stenosis (≥ 75%) of two or more infra-popliteal arteries in the affected
             limb as verified by at least one imaging technique (angiography, magnetic resonance
             angiogram, coronary computed tomography angiogram, or doppler examination) within 6
             months prior to enrollment;

          -  History of CLI defined as moderate or high-risk infra-popliteal chronic critical limb
             ischemia (Rutherford Clinical Severity Score 4 or 5) defined as:

               -  The presence of rest pain or non-healing ulceration or gangrene for at least 2
                  weeks plus documentation of severely compromised tissue perfusion:

               -  If there is tissue loss, a resting ankle systolic pressure of ≤ 60 mmHg in the
                  affected limb; or a resting toe systolic pressure of ≤ 40 mmHg or a tissue
                  perfusion pressure (TPP) &lt;40 mmHg.

               -  If there is no tissue loss, a resting ankle pressure of ≤ 50 mmHg or resting toe
                  systolic pressure of ≤ 30 mmHg or a tissue perfusion pressure (TPP) &lt; 30 mmHg.

          -  Not a candidate or a failed candidate for surgical or transcatheter revascularization;

          -  Able to give informed consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Arterial insufficiency in the lower extremity as the result of a non-atherosclerotic
             disorder.

          -  Subjects with evidence of active infection (e.g., cellulitis, osteomyelitis) or deep
             ulceration exposing bone or tendon or extensive heel ulceration

          -  Subjects with extensive gangrene extending above the Metatarsophalangeal (MT) joint

          -  Subjects in whom there is severe pain at rest uncontrollable with pain medications

          -  Prior intravenous chelation therapy consisting of &gt; 1 infusion within 5 years; if only
             1 infusion took place, patient cannot be enrolled for at least 12 months after said
             infusion.

          -  Oral chelation with an FDA-approved chelating agent within 2 years

          -  Allergy to any components of the study drug

          -  Coronary or carotid revascularization within 3 months

          -  Planned leg revascularization within 1 month of enrollment

          -  Symptomatic or clinically evident acute heart failure

          -  Heart failure hospitalization within 3 months

          -  Blood pressure &gt;160/100

          -  No venous access

          -  Estimated glomerular filtration ratee (GFR) &lt; 30 mL/min per 1.73 m2 or lower (CKD
             stages 1-3) calculated with the Modification of Diet in Renal Disease Study (MDRD)
             equation

          -  Known or suspected acute kidney injury using prevalent Kidney Disease: Improving
             Global Outcomes (KDIGO) criteria

          -  Platelet count &lt;100,000/mm3

          -  Cigarette smoking within the last 3 months

          -  Liver disease or Alanine aminotransferase (ALT), aspartate aminotransferase (AST) &gt;
             2.0 times the upper limit of normal (this will require clearance by the Study PI)

          -  Diseases of copper, iron, or calcium metabolism (other than osteopenia or
             osteoporosis, or simple iron deficiency). These require evaluation by the Study PI

          -  Inability to tolerate the study-required fluid load

          -  Other medical condition likely to affect patient survival within 3 years

          -  Women of child-bearing potential

          -  Any factor that suggests that the potential participant will not be able to adhere to
             the protocol.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>50 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Gervasio Lamas, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Icahn School of Medicine at Mount Sinai</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Francisco Ujueta, MD</last_name>
    <phone>305-674-2162</phone>
    <email>Francisco.Ujueta@msmc.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Beatriz Acevedo</last_name>
    <phone>305-674-2162</phone>
    <email>Beatriz.Acevedo@msmc.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mount Sinai Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Miami Beach</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33140</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Francisco Ujueta, MD</last_name>
      <phone>305-674-2162</phone>
      <email>Francisco.Ujueta@msmc.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Beatriz Acevedo</last_name>
      <phone>305-674-2162</phone>
      <email>Beatriz.Acevedo@msmc.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Arenas IA, Navas-Acien A, Ergui I, Lamas GA. Enhanced vasculotoxic metal excretion in post-myocardial infarction patients following a single edetate disodium-based infusion. Environ Res. 2017 Oct;158:443-449. doi: 10.1016/j.envres.2017.06.039. Epub 2017 Jul 6.</citation>
    <PMID>28689036</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lamas GA, Goertz C, Boineau R, Mark DB, Rozema T, Nahin RL, Drisko JA, Lee KL. Design of the Trial to Assess Chelation Therapy (TACT). Am Heart J. 2012 Jan;163(1):7-12. doi: 10.1016/j.ahj.2011.10.002.</citation>
    <PMID>22172430</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Escolar E, Lamas GA, Mark DB, Boineau R, Goertz C, Rosenberg Y, Nahin RL, Ouyang P, Rozema T, Magaziner A, Nahas R, Lewis EF, Lindblad L, Lee KL. The effect of an EDTA-based chelation regimen on patients with diabetes mellitus and prior myocardial infarction in the Trial to Assess Chelation Therapy (TACT). Circ Cardiovasc Qual Outcomes. 2014 Jan;7(1):15-24. doi: 10.1161/CIRCOUTCOMES.113.000663. Epub 2013 Nov 19.</citation>
    <PMID>24254885</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ujueta F, Arenas IA, Diaz D, Yates T, Beasley R, Navas-Acien A, Lamas GA. Cadmium level and severity of peripheral artery disease in patients with coronary artery disease. Eur J Prev Cardiol. 2019 Sep;26(13):1456-1458. doi: 10.1177/2047487318796585. Epub 2018 Aug 28.</citation>
    <PMID>30152247</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ujueta F, Arenas IA, Escolar E, Diaz D, Boineau R, Mark DB, Golden P, Lindblad L, Kim H, Lee KL, Lamas GA. The effect of EDTA-based chelation on patients with diabetes and peripheral artery disease in the Trial to Assess Chelation Therapy (TACT). J Diabetes Complications. 2019 Jul;33(7):490-494. doi: 10.1016/j.jdiacomp.2019.04.005. Epub 2019 Apr 14.</citation>
    <PMID>31101487</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 27, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 9, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 11, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 21, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 21, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 25, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Mt. Sinai Medical Center, Miami</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Gervasio Lamas, MD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Chelation</keyword>
  <keyword>Critical Limb Ischemia</keyword>
  <keyword>Diabetes</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Ischemia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Edetic Acid</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pentetic Acid</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

