<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03981458</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HATPIN</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>8904</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03981458</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Hyaluronate for the Treatment and Prevention of Recurrent Urinary Tract Infection in Women Suffering Atrophic Vaginitis</brief_title>
  <acronym>HATPIN</acronym>
  <official_title>Hyaluronate for the Treatment and Prevention of Recurrent Urinary Tract Infection in Women Suffering Atrophic Vaginitis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Newcastle-upon-Tyne Hospitals NHS Trust</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>The Urology Foundation, UK</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Newcastle-upon-Tyne Hospitals NHS Trust</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      In post-menopausal women, the condition atrophic vaginitis results from the loss of oestrogen
      and is characterised by dyspareunia (pain during intercourse), vaginal dryness, and vaginal
      irritation. It is often diagnosed alongside recurrent urinary tract infections (rUTIs) and
      may increase susceptibility to rUTI. Topical vaginal oestrogen can be used to re-condition
      the vaginal epithelium and also reduces the incidence of rUTIs. However, patients often
      express concerns about using oestrogen, a hormonal treatment. Studies also report
      side-effects including vaginal bleeding, discharge, burning and itching that underpin
      significant (28%) drop-out rates. Hence, alternative non-hormonal, non-antibiotic based
      therapies that treat the vaginal atrophy, but also reduce the incidence of rUTI are needed.

      Recurrent UTI in adult women is common. Bacteria from the gut can colonise the vulvar
      epithelia and then the bladder, causing uncomfortable urinary symptoms (cystitis). The
      lifetime risk of a UTI is around 40% in adult women which increases in post-menopausal women.
      Annually, UTI incidence is 3%. Of those affected, 5% will suffer rUTI, rising to 13% in the
      over 60 population. This equates to over 300,000 of the adult female UK population annually
      affected by rUTI. The most frequent treatment for rUTIs is low dose antibiotics, but this
      treatment causes the bacteria carried by such women to become antibiotic resistant, which
      exacerbates the clinical problem. The prevalence of antimicrobial multi-resistance within
      post-menopausal women suffering from rUTI is around 25% and was shown to rise to more than
      80% following prolonged antibiotics. These data support the use of non-antibiotic treatment
      strategies that prevent rUTI and the emergence of drug resistant micro-organisms.

      This study will compare two groups with differing treatment strategies. One group will be
      primarily treated for atrophic vaginitis with topical vaginal hyaluronate and the other will
      be primarily treated for their recurrent UTI with intravesical hyaluronate.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Study purpose A potential alternative to prophylactic antibiotic treatment and topical
      vaginal estrogen treatments is the compound hyaluronate (HA). HA is already utilised in the
      UK to treat rUTIs, but is delivered as a bladder instillation (Ialuril®). A small
      meta-analysis of intravesical hyaluronate therapy incorporating four studies (two randomised,
      two non-randomised, 143 patients) investigating the use of this treatment in recurrent UTI,
      reported a statistically significant improvement in the rates of recurrent UTI (mean
      difference −3.4 episodes per patient year, 95% confidence interval −4.3 to −2.5). HA is also
      available as a vaginal cream, Hyalofemme®, which is used clinically to treat atrophic
      vaginitis. The evidence suggests that many women suffering vaginal atrophy also experience
      recurrent UTIs. However, the effect of HA treatment in reducing concomitant rUTIs in such
      patients has not been reported.

      The need for this study is also supported by current guidance documents. The 2012 Scottish
      Intercollegiate Guideline Network (SIGN) guideline emphasises the need to avoid &quot;unnecessary
      antibiotic prescribing,&quot; specifically highlighting the issue of antibiotic-resistant [E.
      coli] UTI. Additionally, the UK antimicrobial resistance strategy documents antibiotic
      resistance as a key concern and as such, lends support to the investigation, and use of
      alternative antimicrobial therapies. The use of non-antibiotic preventative treatments for
      rUTI has also been accentuated by current UK, European and USA guidelines to minimise
      antibiotic resistance. Therefore, this pilot study investigating the efficacy of a treatment
      already prescribed for vaginal atrophy in reducing concomitant rUTI is not only addressing
      current directives, but will help inform whether topical HA therapy can be extended to all
      rUTI sufferers, thus helping to reduce global antibiotic use.

      Evidence supporting the effectiveness of hyaluronate (HA) in treating rUTI is available, but
      at present the therapy is administered directly to the bladder, which involves
      catheterisation, managed through hospital visits. In contrast a HA topical treatment can be
      patient managed at home. If from the data collated the topical HA therapy shows a comparable
      efficacy in reducing rUTI, then these data will underpin a large-scale clinical trial
      examining the use of this non-hormonal, non-antibiotic based agent for the treatment and
      prevention of rUTI in patients.

      While the focus of this initial study is on post-menopausal women suffering vaginal atrophy
      and rUTI, it is also anticipated that this treatment could be broadened to all women
      suffering rUTIs. One particular target group are females carrying the TLR5392Stop
      polymorphism who are at increased risk of rUTI, thus signalling an era of personalised
      medicine for an infection related disease. It is also envisaged that topical HA therapy could
      be prescribed as a urethral barrier cream for men suffering uncomplicated rUTI.

      Study design This study was designed through a collaboration of clinical urologists and basic
      scientists with an interest in the concomitance of atrophic vaginitis and recurrent UTI. The
      proposal was peer-reviewed before funding was granted by The Urology Foundation. This
      single-centre study is located at the Urology Department, Freeman Hospital, Newcastle upon
      Tyne Hospitals NHS Foundation Trust, NE7 7DN. Participants recruited will be post-menopausal
      women identified as either having gone through the menopause naturally or having had an
      oophorectomy, and not on hormone replacement therapy (HRT) in the last two years, and who
      suffer from vaginal atrophy and rUTI. Patients will have either 3 confirmed episodes of UTI
      in the preceding year or 2 episodes in the last 6 months. Patients will exhibit the symptoms
      and signs of atrophic vaginitis, which will be diagnosed by their responsible clinician. The
      study duration is 24 months, with a patient recruitment period of 12 months. Patient follow
      up and laboratory work will proceed until the end of month 23, with data analyses and final
      report preparation in the final month.

      The design incorporates a patient-randomised study that directly compares two treatments for
      women with atrophic vaginitis and rUTI during a 9-month period. One treatment is an
      intravesical instillation of hyaluronate into the bladder (Ialuril) delivered via catheter
      focussed primarily on treating rUTI. This is once weekly for 6 weeks, followed by once every
      two weeks for 6 weeks, then once per month (maintenance) for the remaining study period. The
      alternative treatment is focussed on primarily treating atrophic vaginitis using a licensed
      vaginal hyaluronate product (Hyalofemme) used topically once every 3 days, continually for
      the 9 month study period.

      Participants in both study arms would continue to receive antibiotic treatment for
      breakthrough UTI as needed. Recruitment is planned at 3-4 patients per month, allowing us to
      meet a target of 40 participants over the recruitment period, which allows for a 25%
      attrition rate. Using data from Damiano et al, two groups of 16 patients are required to
      achieve 80% power at the 5% significance level for detecting a clinically significant
      reduction of one less UTI during the 9-month treatment and monitoring period.

      Recruitment

        1. Patient Identification All adult women with atrophic vaginitis and rUTI will be made
           aware of the study during their clinic appointment and those eligible can consider
           whether they wish to participate prior to assessment. The study will also be publicised
           so that colleagues in allied specialities such as urogynaecology and nephrology, who may
           receive referrals of women with atrophic vaginitis and rUTI, are aware of the study and
           can identify potential participants.

           For the study, post-menopausal women with symptoms or signs of atrophic vaginitis
           referred to a hospital urology clinic with associated rUTI will be asked if they would
           like to participate. In the study, atrophic vaginitis will be diagnosed on clinical
           grounds and rUTI will be defined as at least 3 episodes in the past year (or 2 episodes
           in the last 6 months). Patients will undergo routine tests to rule out any structural or
           functional abnormality of their urinary system. The treatment given to each participant
           will be decided randomly.

           Patients with underlying structural or functional abnormalities of the urinary tract
           following diagnosis by renal tract ultrasound scan (USS) and an endoscopic examination
           of the bladder under local anaesthesia (flexible cystoscopy) will be excluded from the
           study. A recent local audit in Newcastle (unpublished data, n=200) has revealed that
           contributory structural or functional abnormalities are detected in less than 10% of
           patients. Therefore, it is estimated that approximately 90% of patients matching our
           criteria and referred with atrophic vaginitis and rUTI will be eligible to be approached
           for inclusion to the study.

           Recruitment will involve a clear explanation of the trial including the background,
           study protocol and aims.

        2. Screening Clinical staff at each site will identify eligible participants through direct
           contact or by searches of electronic records held in each Trust. They will then give or
           send potentially eligible patients brief study information. If interested potential
           participants can then agree to be approached by research staff and be provided with
           further study information. Invitation material will include brief details of the need
           and purpose of the study and eligibility criteria. It will emphasise the pragmatic
           nature of the study and give a realistic indication of the burden to participants. All
           patients given study information will be recorded in the screening log. All subjects who
           agree to consider participation will be seen by local research staff or the study
           coordinator to go through the consent and randomisation procedure. A case report form
           will be initiated and baseline data collected.

           A screening log will be kept by local site research staff to document details of
           subjects invited to participate in the study and reasons for non-participation. The log
           will also ensure potential participants who are ineligible or decline participation are
           approached only once.

        3. Consent All participants will undergo a process of informed consent. Participants will
           be free to withdraw their consent at any time.

      The informed consent discussion will be undertaken by appropriately trained staff. This will
      include medical staff and research nurses/study coordinators involved in the study who will
      give time for participants to ask any questions they may have following review of the study
      information pack. The consent process will include written information concerning the need
      and overall benefit of the study as well as verbal discussions. The latter will include a
      check of understanding concerning benefits and risks, and ensuring that participants accept
      that the treatment will be allocated at random regardless of any personal preference they may
      have.

      Following delivery of the study information, participants will be given at least 24 hours and
      as much time as they need to decide whether they would like to participate. Those wishing to
      take part will provide written informed consent by signing and dating the study consent form,
      which will be witnessed and dated by a member of the research team with documented, delegated
      responsibility to do so. Written informed consent will always be obtained prior to
      randomisation. The original signed consent form will be retained in the Investigator Site
      File, with a copy filed in the clinical notes, a copy given to the participant. The
      participant will specifically consent to their General Practitioner (GP) being informed of
      their participation in the study. The right to refuse to participate without giving reasons
      will be respected.

      Participants will be given the option of consenting to storage of blood, urine and vaginal
      douche samples for future research. They will also be asked if they would be willing for the
      inclusion of data collected for this study in future research. Any further research would be
      subject to separate review by an ethics committee.

      Inclusion/exclusion and risk Selection bias will be minimised by including all
      post-menopausal female patients with atrophic vaginitis and recurrent uncomplicated UTI, and
      not receiving hormonal supplements or hyaluronate as eligible participants. There are
      deliberately few exclusion criteria set to enable the findings of this study to be
      generalised. Both treatments are licensed, exhibit a low side-effect profile and have little
      interaction with other common medications, which limits absolute contra-indications to either
      therapy. Eligible patients and their responsible clinician will need to be sufficiently
      uncertain of the optimum treatment for vaginal atrophy and rUTI to allow randomisation and
      prevent selection bias.

      Confidentiality Initial screening of patients will be carried out by trained clinical staff
      associated with either the urology clinic at Freeman Hospital or the network of Research
      Nurses. Following this, informed consent will be taken by appropriately trained staff and the
      patients randomised into the trial. Case Report Forms to collect the information required by
      researchers will contain the minimum required patient-identifiers. All staff have completed
      GDPR training.

      Conflict of interest This study is pragmatic in design and, apart from random allocation of
      treatment option and participant completion of diaries and questionnaires, participant care
      will follow standard pathways in participating secondary care NHS sites. Both Ialuril and
      Hyalofemme are licensed and approved for routine NHS use. It will be ensured that all
      participants have access as desired to the use of other measures to reduce the risk of UTI
      such as adequate fluid intake, avoidance of constipation and cranberry extract. However,
      patients receiving hormonal supplementation are not appropriate for this study. Participants
      in both study groups will receive on demand discrete courses of antibiotics as decided by the
      responsible clinician for symptomatic UTI. Use of all these adjunctive treatments will be
      recorded on case report forms.

      Participants will be given the option of consenting to storage of blood, urine and vaginal
      douche samples for future research. Participants will also be asked if they would be willing
      for the inclusion of data collected for this study in future research. Any further research
      would be subject to separate review by an ethics committee. Upon completion a short, clearly
      written summary of the research findings will be supplied to all participants. Any findings
      resulting from the research will be published in scientific or medical journals.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Atrophic vaginitis and recurrent urinary tract infection are often found concurrently in post-menopausal women. The argument over which condition appeared first, or if one is caused by the other, is prevalent in clinical settings and there is no official guidance as to which should be treated first. We propose two arms to this study - one treating the atrophic vaginitis via use of Hyalofemme cream (hyaluronate cream), and the other treating recurrent UTI by use of Ialuril (hyaluronate bladder instillation). We intend to investigate the effect on the incidence of UTI in the patients with both treatments, as well as focusing on some markers of the immune response in the urine and vaginal douche samples from these participants.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Reduced incidence of medically confirmed urinary tract infection</measure>
    <time_frame>Number of UTIs will be assessed at both 6 months (end of treatment) and 9 months (end of follow-up period)</time_frame>
    <description>Occurrence of symptomatic UTI with prescription and taking of a treatment course of antibiotics for UTI. Applicable for both treatment arms in comparison to baseline established in the previous 12 months.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of microbiologically-proven UTIs</measure>
    <time_frame>6 and 9 months</time_frame>
    <description>Occurrence of symptomatic UTI and the demonstration of a positive urine culture, rather than UTI symptoms potentially caused by interstitial cystitis without bacterial infection.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Effect on vaginal atrophy</measure>
    <time_frame>3, 6 and 9 months</time_frame>
    <description>The two treatment arms will be compared to baseline to discover whether any improvement in vaginal atrophy symptoms are seen with either treatment. This will be assessed via questionnaires to determine symptoms experienced and their severity at 0 (baseline), 3, 6 and 9 months. Symptoms that participants will be asked to assess are as follows:
Frequency of urination
Urgency of urination
Pain or burning during urination
Partial bladder emptying
Fever or shivers
Pain in the lower abdomen or pelvis
Lower back pain
Blood in the urine Participants will rank the severity of these symptoms from &quot;Did not have&quot; to &quot;Severe&quot;, and how troublesome they were from &quot;Not at all&quot; to &quot;A lot&quot; by marking a line to indicate where the participant feels their symptoms lie. Upon analysis of the questionnaires, placement of this mark will be measured and used to determine differences in symptoms from baseline throughout the study.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Uropathogen identification</measure>
    <time_frame>9 months</time_frame>
    <description>Urine samples will be analysed for the presence of bacteria. If any are found they will be cultured, identified and potentially undergo molecular typing to discover whether particular strains are more prevalent in patients suffering from concurrent rUTI and atrophic vaginitis.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Innate immune response in urine and vaginal douche samples measured by ELISA for cytokines and antimicrobial peptides (e.g. interleukin-8, beta-defensin 2).</measure>
    <time_frame>9 months</time_frame>
    <description>Urine and vaginal douche samples will be collected at baseline and at 3-monthly intervals. These will be analysed by ELISA for the presence of innate immune markers and cytokines, such as defensins, interleukin-8 and lipocalin. A potential change in expression may indicate that this is partly how the treatments help to prevent against UTI.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Analysis of polymorphisms in receptor proteins known to be involved in UTI</measure>
    <time_frame>9 months</time_frame>
    <description>Patient blood samples will be collected at baseline and DNA extracted. These will be examined for SNPs in genes such as TLR5, which encodes a receptor protein known to affect patient response to bacteria in cases of UTI.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Participant quality of life - does either treatment increase overall quality of life by decreasing symptoms from UTI and/or atrophy?</measure>
    <time_frame>3, 6 and 9 months</time_frame>
    <description>Participants will be asked to complete questionnaires (EQ-5D) pertaining to their overall health and quality of life at baseline and at 3-monthly intervals to determine whether treatments are improving their overall health and general wellbeing at 0, 3, 6 and 9 months. This is a validated questionnaire commonly used in healthcare to determine general health and includes assessments of mobility, self-care, ability to carry out normal activity, pain/discomfort levels and anxiety/depression. This also asks participants to assess their overall health state by marking on a scale from 0-100, with higher numbers representing the best imaginable state of health.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Reduction in antibiotic use for UTI as a result of hyaluronate treatment by either route of administration</measure>
    <time_frame>Results will be analysed at both end of treatment (6 months) and end of follow-up (9 months)</time_frame>
    <description>Incidences of antibiotic use, in general and specifically for UTI, will be recorded to observe whether the treatments result in fewer courses of antibiotics being prescribed.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Atrophic Vaginitis</condition>
  <condition>Urinary Tract Infections</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Hyalofemme</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Hyalofemme is a cream/gel containing hyaluronic acid, designed to be applied vaginally. This is primarily used in treatment of atrophic vaginitis and is applied by the patient once every three days. We intend treatment to continue for 6 months.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Ialuril</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Ialuril is a bladder instillation designed to be delivered to the bladder via catheter. This is primarily used in patients suffering from recurrent UTI and acts to help rebuild the lining of the bladder, reducing irritation. Ialuril is applied weekly for 6 weeks, followed by every 2 weeks for 6 weeks, then once monthly for maintenance. Treatment will be continued for 6 months.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Hyalofemme</intervention_name>
    <description>Gel made with hyaluronic acid to be applied vaginally to treat atrophic vaginitis.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Hyalofemme</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Hyaluronic acid gel</other_name>
    <other_name>Hyaluronate gel</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ialuril</intervention_name>
    <description>Bladder instillation of hyaluronic acid to treat recurrent UTI.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Ialuril</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Hyaluronic acid instillation</other_name>
    <other_name>Hyaluronate instillation</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  • Postmenopausal women not receiving hormonal supplementation.

               -  Women with atrophic vaginitis and rUTI who, in consultation with a clinician,
                  have decided that either hyaluronate treatment (intravesical or vaginal) is an
                  appropriate option.

               -  Women who have suffered at least three episodes of symptomatic UTI within the
                  preceding 12 months or two episodes in the last 6 months.

               -  Able to attend a urology clinic for catheterisation on a regular basis (initially
                  weekly) to initiate intravesical bladder instillation treatment.

               -  Able to apply vaginal hyaluronate gel at home every 3 days.

               -  Able to give informed consent for participation in study.

               -  Able and willing to adhere to a 9-month study period.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  • Postmenopausal women receiving hormonal supplementation (e.g. HRT or oestrogen
             creams).

               -  Women unable to use hyaluronate e.g. due to previous sensitivity issues.

               -  Women with urinary tract abnormalities that are considered to be contributory to
                  the occurrence of rUTI.

               -  Presence of symptomatic UTI - this will be treated and symptoms resolved prior to
                  randomisation.

               -  Women currently using hyaluronate for either treatment of atrophic vaginitis or
                  prevention of recurrent UTI or women who have used either study treatment in the
                  preceding 12 months.

               -  Women receiving prophylactic antibiotics.

               -  Catheter usage.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>30 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>90 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Christopher Harding, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Newcastle-upon-Tyne Hospitals NHS Trust</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Christopher Harding, MD</last_name>
    <phone>0191 2337321</phone>
    <email>chris.harding@nuth.nhs.uk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Judith Hall, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>0191 2088346</phone>
    <email>judith.hall@ncl.ac.uk</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Freeman Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Newcastle upon Tyne</city>
        <state>Tyne And Wear</state>
        <zip>NE7 7DN</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Christopher Harding, MA MB BChir MD</last_name>
      <phone>0191 233 6161</phone>
      <phone_ext>37597</phone_ext>
      <email>chris.harding@nuth.nhs.uk</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 29, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 7, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 10, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 3, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 3, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 8, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Infection</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Communicable Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Urinary Tract Infections</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vaginitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Atrophic Vaginitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Atrophy</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hyaluronic Acid</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

