<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03986294</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NL64126.018.17</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03986294</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Second Line Treatment With Nal-IRI and S1 in Pancreatic Cancer</brief_title>
  <acronym>NAPAN</acronym>
  <official_title>A Randomized Phase II Study of Second Line Treatment With Liposomal Irinotecan and S1 Versus Liposomal Irinotecan and 5-fluorouracil in Patients With Metastatic Pancreatic Cancer Who Failed on First Line Gemcitabine-based Chemotherapy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Academisch Medisch Centrum - Universiteit van Amsterdam (AMC-UvA)</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>UMC Utrecht</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Isala</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Maastricht University Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Vall de Hebron, Barcelona, Spain</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University Hospital Verona, Italy</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Odense University Hospital, Denmark</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Medical University of Vienna</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Academisch Medisch Centrum - Universiteit van Amsterdam (AMC-UvA)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To determine the optimal second line treatment strategy in patients with metastatic
      pancreatic cancer who underwent a therapy with gemcitabine.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The 5-year survival of patients with pancreatic cancer is less than 5%. Despite improvements
      over the past years with the introduction of FOLFIRINOX (5-fluorouracil, irinotecan,
      oxaliplatin and leucovorin) and gemcitabine and nab-paclitaxel, the vast majority will have
      disease recurrence or progression within 6 months. Single-arm phase II studies have been
      conducted after gemcitabine-based therapy. Randomized clinical trial data are limited in this
      setting, but the conclusion up to recently was that there is no superior chemotherapeutic
      regimen after gemcitabine failure. However, the NAPOLI trial altered the treatment landscape.
      In this trial, patients with metastatic pancreatic cancer that progressed after treatment
      with gemcitabine-based chemotherapy received liposomal irinotecan (nal-IRI) either as single
      agent or in combination with 5-fluorouracil/ leucovorin (5-FU/LV), or 5-FU/LV alone. Patients
      treated with the combination of nal-IRI plus 5-FU/LV experienced a median survival of 6.1
      months versus 4.2 months for the 5-FU/LV group.

      Recently, two studies on the clinical use of S-1 for pancreatic cancer have been reported
      from Japan. In the first study, S-1 demonstrated non-inferiority to gemcitabine in overall
      survival (OS) for advanced pancreatic cancer. In the second study, S-1 showed superiority to
      adjuvant chemotherapy with gemcitabine in OS. In addition to gemcitabine, S-1 is now regarded
      as the key drug in the management of pancreatic cancer in Japan. Phase II studies of S-1 in
      patients with gemcitabine-resistant pancreatic cancer have demonstrated moderate activity
      with acceptable toxicity. Although there has been no confirmed evidence based on phase III
      trials, S-1 would be a feasible treatment option in this patient population.

      Objective:

      To determine the optimal second line treatment strategy in patients with metastatic
      pancreatic cancer, whereby the hypothesis is, based on studies conducted in the Asian
      population, that the combination of S-1 and nal-IRI will be superior compared to 5-FU/ LV and
      nal-IRI, in terms of progression free survival. Therefore, patients will be randomized, after
      the optimal dose of S-1 and nal-IRI has been determined in the run in phase, between S-1 in
      combination with nal-IRI and 5-FU/LV in combination with nal-IRI during the phase II part of
      the study.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">December 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 1, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 1, 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>DLT of Nal-IRI with S1</measure>
    <time_frame>36 months</time_frame>
    <description>Dose limiting toxicity (DLT) of nal-IRI when co-administered with fixed dose S1 in patients with metastatic pancreatic cancer</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>MTD of Nal-IRI with S1</measure>
    <time_frame>36 months</time_frame>
    <description>Maximum tolerated dose (MTD) of nal-IRI when co-administered with fixed dose S1 in patients with metastatic pancreatic cancer</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression free survival of NaI-IRI with S1</measure>
    <time_frame>36 months</time_frame>
    <description>Determination of the efficacy between the treatment arms in terms of progression free survival.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival</measure>
    <time_frame>36 months</time_frame>
    <description>To determine the overall survival (OS) benefit of nal-IRI combined with S-1, compared with nal-IRI combined with 5-FU/LV, in subjects pre-treated with gemcitabine based chemotherapy for metastatic pancreatic ductal adenocarcinoma.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Response rate according to RECIST 1.1</measure>
    <time_frame>36 months</time_frame>
    <description>To determine the response rate according to RECIST 1.1 of nal-IRI combined with S-1, compared with nal-IRI combined with 5-FU/LV, in subjects pre-treated with gemcitabine based chemotherapy for metastatic pancreatic ductal adenocarcinoma.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse events according NCI CTC version 4.0</measure>
    <time_frame>36 months</time_frame>
    <description>To determine the adverse events according to NCI CTC version 4.0 of nal-IRI combined with S-1, compared with nal-IRI combined with 5-FU/LV, in subjects pre-treated with gemcitabine based chemotherapy for metastatic pancreatic ductal adenocarcinoma.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of life QoL (QLQ-C30)</measure>
    <time_frame>36 months</time_frame>
    <description>To determine Quality of life (QoL) benefit of nal-IRI combined with S-1, compared with nal-IRI combined with 5-FU/LV, in subjects pre-treated with gemcitabine based chemotherapy for metastatic pancreatic ductal adenocarcinoma using a questionnaire QLQ-C30.Scale ranges 1-4, 1 is very good, 4 is very bad. Higher values represent a worse outcome.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>stromal markers</measure>
    <time_frame>36 months</time_frame>
    <description>To assess expression of relative abundance of stroma in metastatic tumor tissue and stromal markers, including ADAM12 in metastatic tumor tissue and blood as predictor of response to treatment and survival.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Imaging (MRI)</measure>
    <time_frame>36 months</time_frame>
    <description>To explore, by imaging the number of participants with the effects of the treatment combination on tumor vascularity, and stromal density.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>ctDNA</measure>
    <time_frame>36 months</time_frame>
    <description>To explore the number of participants with changes in ctDNA.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">122</enrollment>
  <condition>Metastatic Pancreatic Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>S1 and liposomal irinotecan</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>S-1 will be given for 14 consecutive days, twice daily, followed by 2 weeks rest. Nal-IRI will be administered as an iv infusion on day 1 and 15. Treatment will be repeated every 4 wks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Liposomal irinotecan, Leucovorin and 5-fluoracil</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Nal-IRI 80 mg/m2 administered first, followed by LV 400 mg/m2, followed by 5-FU 2400 mg/m2 as an IV infusion over 46-hrs on days 1-3. Each cycle consists of 14 days. Treatment will be repeated every 2 wks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>S1 + Nal-IRI</intervention_name>
    <description>S-1 will be given for 14 consecutive days, twice daily, followed by 2 weeks rest. Nal-IRI will be administered as an intravenous infusion on day 1 and 15. Courses of treatment will be repeated every 4 weeks.</description>
    <arm_group_label>S1 and liposomal irinotecan</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Nal-IRI+Leucovorin+5-FU</intervention_name>
    <description>Nal-IRI 80 mg/m2 will be administered first, followed by LV 400 mg/m2, followed by 5-FU 2400 mg/m2 as an IV infusion over 46-hours on days 1-3. Each cycle consists of 14 days. Courses of treatment will be repeated every 2 weeks.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Liposomal irinotecan, Leucovorin and 5-fluoracil</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>S1 and liposomal irinotecan</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Subjects must satisfy all of the following inclusion criteria to be enrolled in the study.

          1. Able to understand and provide written informed consent

          2. ≥ 18 years of age

          3. Histologically or cytologically confirmed adenocarcinoma of pancreas

          4. Documented metastatic disease, according to RECIST 1.1.

          5. Previously treated with gemcitabine or gemcitabine containing therapy, or progression
             within 6 months of adjuvant gemcitabine based treatment

          6. Adequate hepatic, renal and hematological function

        Exclusion Criteria:

        A potential subject who meets any of the following criteria will be excluded from
        participation in this study:

          1. Serum total bilirubin ≥1.5 x ULN (biliary drainage is allowed for biliary obstruction)

          2. Severe renal impairment (CLcr ≤ 30 ml/min)

          3. Inadequate bone marrow reserves as evidenced by:

               1. ANC ≤ 1,5 x 10 9 /L; or

               2. Platelet count ≤ 100 x 10 9 /L;

          4. WHO/PS 0-1

          5. Any clinically significant disorder impacting the risk-benefit balance negatively per
             physician's judgment

          6. Any clinically significant gastrointestinal disorder, including hepatic disorders,
             bleeding, inflammation, occlusion, or diarrhea &gt; grade 1

          7. Severe arterial thromboembolic events (myocardial infarction, unstable angina
             pectoris, stroke) in last 6 months

          8. NYHA Class III or IV congestive heart failure, ventricular arrhythmias or uncontrolled
             blood pressure. Or known abnormal ECG with clinically significant abnormal findings

          9. Active infection or an unexplained fever &gt;38.5°C (excluding tumor fever), which in the
             physician's opinion might compromise the patient's health

         10. Current use or any use in last two weeks of strong CYP3A-enzyme inducers/inhibitors
             and/or strong UGT1A inhibitors

         11. Known hypersensitivity to any of the components of liposomal irinotecan (Nal-IRI)
             other liposomal irinotecan formulations, irinotecan, fluoropyrimidines, or leucovorin.

         12. Hypersensitivity to any of the active substances (tegafur, gimeracil, and oteracil)

         13. Previous treatment with fluoropyrimidine therapy

         14. Known dihydropyrimidine dehydrogenase (DPD) deficiency

         15. Breast feeding, known pregnancy, positive serum pregnancy test or unwillingness to use
             a reliable method of birth control, during therapy and for 3 months following the last
             dose of liposomal irinotecan (Nal-IRI).

        Treatment within 4 weeks with DPD inhibitors, including sorivudine or its chemically
        related analogues such as brivudine.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>J W Wilmink, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Ademic Medical Center Amsterdam</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>J W Wilmink, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>31 20 5665955</phone>
    <email>j.w.wilmink@amsterdamumc.nl</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>E. N. Pijnappel, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>31 20 5665955</phone>
    <email>e.n.pijnappel@amsterdamumc.nl</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Academic Medical Center, Medical Oncology</name>
      <address>
        <city>Amsterdam</city>
        <zip>1100 DD</zip>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>J. W. Wilmink, MD, PhD, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>31 20 5665955</phone>
      <email>j.w.wilmink@amsterdamumc.nl</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Lyda ter Hofstede</last_name>
      <phone>31 20 5668229</phone>
      <email>trialmedonc@amc.uva.nl</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>H. WM van Laarhoven, MD, PhD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>J. W. Wilmink, M.D., Ph.D.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Netherlands</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 11, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 11, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 14, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 7, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 7, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 9, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Academisch Medisch Centrum - Universiteit van Amsterdam (AMC-UvA)</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>J.W. Wilmink</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principle investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Liposomal irinotecan</keyword>
  <keyword>S1</keyword>
  <keyword>Pancreatic cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Second line</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pancreatic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Leucovorin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

