<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03982108</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IU-260133</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03982108</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Comparison of Two Arthroscopic Rotator Cuff Repair Techniques: Knot-tying Versus Knotless Suture-bridge Technique</brief_title>
  <official_title>Comparison of Repair Integrity and Functional Outcomes Between Knot-tying and Knotless Suture-bridge Arthroscopic Rotator Cuff Repair: a Prospective Randomized Clinical Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Koray Sahin</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Istanbul University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>Yes</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Suture-bridge technique has been widely used for rotator cuff tears with many studies showing
      superior clinical results and lower failure rates compared to other techniques. This study
      aims to compare clinical outcomes and radiological integrity of arthroscopic rotator cuff
      repair between knot-tying and knotless suture-bridge techniques. The possibility of tendon
      strangulation and necrosis at the medial row when performing a suture-bridge technique may
      lead to retear and structural failure. In order to avoid this complication, the knots used at
      the medial row and their tension might be a factor to consider. Our hypothesis is that a
      knotless suture-bridge technique might avoid tendon strangulation thus might have lower
      retear rates.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study has been planned as a prospective randomized clinical trial. We used a completely
      computer-generated list in order to randomize all participants to receive one of two
      treatments (https://www.random.org/sequences/).

      Rotator cuff tear diagnosis will be made by physical examination and magnetic resonance
      imaging. Participants who agree to be enrolled to study will be examined one day prior to
      surgery. Half of the participants will undergo an arthroscopic rotator cuff repair with
      knot-tying suture-bridge technique, while the other half will receive a knotless
      suture-bridge technique. All the surgeries will be performed by the same senior surgeon
      experienced in shoulder surgery under general anesthesia with participant in beach-chair
      position.

      All participants will receive a standard postoperative rehabilitation program starting
      immediately after surgery with active elbow and passive shoulder exercises. The operated
      upper extremity will be placed in a sling for 6 weeks. Active-assisted exercises will be
      started at 6 weeks postoperatively.

      Postoperative evaluations will be performed regularly at 2 weeks, 6 weeks, 3 months, 6
      months, 12 months postoperatively and each following year. The results of last follow-up will
      be analyzed. To assess repair integrity and tendon healing, a postoperative magnetic
      resonance imaging scan will be performed to all participants at 6 months postoperatively. The
      results of prospective clinical follow-up data and radiological evaluation will be analyzed
      in order to compare clinical outcomes, failure rates and patterns of knot-tying and knotless
      suture-bridge arthroscopic rotator cuff repair techniques.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 3, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">July 2, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">July 2, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Sugaya classification of rotator cuff integrity</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months postoperatively</time_frame>
    <description>This is a classification system described by Sugaya et al. which uses magnetic resonance imaging in order to evaluate tendon integrity after rotator cuff repair. Postoperative cuff integrity is classified into 5 categories: type I, sufficient thickness with homogenously low intensity; type II, sufficient thickness with partial high intensity; type III, insufficient thickness without discontinuity; type IV, presence of minor discontinuity; type V, presence of major discontinuity</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Constant shoulder score</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline Constant shoulder score at 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>This is a clinical functional assessment test used for shoulder disorders. The score consists of 4 sections: pain, activities of daily living, mobility and strength.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Shoulder range of motion</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline range of motion at 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Shoulder abduction, forward flexion, external rotation, internal rotation and extension degrees measured by a goniometer</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Visual analog scale for pain</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline visual analog scale for pain at 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>A visual scale which classifies the intensity of pain between 0-10.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Retear patterns of rotator cuff tendons</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months postoperatively</time_frame>
    <description>Retear patterns of rotator cuff tendons will be evaluated by using postoperative magnetic resonance images. Detected retears will be classified as type 1 (lateral) or type 2 (medial/musculotendinous) rotator cuff retears/failures.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">104</enrollment>
  <condition>Rotator Cuff Tears</condition>
  <condition>Rotator Cuff Injuries</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Knotless suture-bridge technique</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>All participants in this arm will undergo an arthroscopic rotator cuff repair with knotless suture-bridge technique.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Knot-tying suture-bridge technique</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>All participants in this arm will undergo an arthroscopic rotator cuff repair with knot-tying suture-bridge technique.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Arthroscopic rotator cuff repair with knotless suture-bridge technique</intervention_name>
    <description>A posterior portal will be established to obtain adequate visualization and an anterior portal will be established through rotator interval as a working portal for diagnostic arthroscopy and debridement. Then additional portals will be established and preperation of tendon will be performed and a burr will be used for footprint preperation.
After determination of proper anchor locations, required number of suture anchors will be inserted just lateral to articular margin depending on the tear size. Then limbs of sutures will be passed from the rotator cuff and will be used to create a suture bridge over the tendon. Then these limbs will be loaded to anchors which will form the lateral row without tying the suture limbs at the medial row. These lateral anchors will be inserted to adequate location, just lateral and distal to greater tuberosity with adequate suture-bridge tension over the rotator cuff.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Knotless suture-bridge technique</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Arthroscopic rotator cuff repair with knot-tying suture-bridge technique</intervention_name>
    <description>After the same preparation procedure as in knotless suture-bridge technique, required number of suture anchors will be inserted just lateral to articular margin depending on the tear size. Then limbs of sutures will be passed from the tendon and tied in a horizontal mattress suture pattern. After the establishment of medial row, suture limbs will be used to form a suture bridge over the tendon and will be loaded to lateral row anchors which then will be inserted lateral to greater tuberosity in a similar way to knotless repair technique.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Knot-tying suture-bridge technique</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Full thickness rotator cuff tear repaired by arthroscopic suture-bridge technique

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Partial thickness rotator cuff tear

          -  Presence of a full thickness subscapularis tear that requires a repair

          -  History of a neurological disease

          -  Presence of severe glenohumeral or acromioclavicular arthritis

          -  Presence of a metal implant which prevents magnetic resonance imaging scan

          -  Tears repaired with other techniques

          -  Revision surgeries
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ali Ersen, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Istanbul University Istanbul Medical Faculty</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Istanbul University Istanbul Medical Faculty Department of Orthopedics and Traumatology</name>
      <address>
        <city>Istanbul</city>
        <state>Fatih</state>
        <zip>34093</zip>
        <country>Turkey</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Turkey</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://www.random.org/sequences/</url>
    <description>Web site used for randomization of participants</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Angst F, Schwyzer HK, Aeschlimann A, Simmen BR, Goldhahn J. Measures of adult shoulder function: Disabilities of the Arm, Shoulder, and Hand Questionnaire (DASH) and its short version (QuickDASH), Shoulder Pain and Disability Index (SPADI), American Shoulder and Elbow Surgeons (ASES) Society standardized shoulder assessment form, Constant (Murley) Score (CS), Simple Shoulder Test (SST), Oxford Shoulder Score (OSS), Shoulder Disability Questionnaire (SDQ), and Western Ontario Shoulder Instability Index (WOSI). Arthritis Care Res (Hoboken). 2011 Nov;63 Suppl 11:S174-88. doi: 10.1002/acr.20630. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22588743</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sugaya H, Maeda K, Matsuki K, Moriishi J. Functional and structural outcome after arthroscopic full-thickness rotator cuff repair: single-row versus dual-row fixation. Arthroscopy. 2005 Nov;21(11):1307-16.</citation>
    <PMID>16325080</PMID>
  </reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Rhee YG, Cho NS, Parke CS. Arthroscopic rotator cuff repair using modified Mason-Allen medial row stitch: knotless versus knot-tying suture bridge technique. Am J Sports Med. 2012 Nov;40(11):2440-7. doi: 10.1177/0363546512459170. Epub 2012 Sep 21. Erratum in: Am J Sports Med. 2013 Aug;41(8):NP41.</citation>
    <PMID>23002202</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Kim KC, Shin HD, Cha SM, Park JY. Comparisons of retear patterns for 3 arthroscopic rotator cuff repair methods. Am J Sports Med. 2014 Mar;42(3):558-65. doi: 10.1177/0363546514521577.</citation>
    <PMID>24585674</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Millett PJ, Espinoza C, Horan MP, Ho CP, Warth RJ, Dornan GJ, Katthagen JC. Predictors of outcomes after arthroscopic transosseous equivalent rotator cuff repair in 155 cases: a propensity score weighted analysis of knotted and knotless self-reinforcing repair techniques at a minimum of 2 years. Arch Orthop Trauma Surg. 2017 Oct;137(10):1399-1408. doi: 10.1007/s00402-017-2750-7. Epub 2017 Jul 26. Erratum in: Arch Orthop Trauma Surg. 2017 Dec;137(12 ):1761.</citation>
    <PMID>28748291</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 6, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 7, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 11, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 25, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 25, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">July 28, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Istanbul University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Koray Sahin</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Resident in orthopedics and traumatology department</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>shoulder</keyword>
  <keyword>rotator cuff tear</keyword>
  <keyword>arthroscopic repair</keyword>
  <keyword>suture-bridge technique</keyword>
  <keyword>retear</keyword>
  <keyword>knotless</keyword>
  <keyword>knot-tying</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Rotator Cuff Injuries</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

