<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03989102</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>999919113</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>19-I-N113</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03989102</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Safety, Immunogenicity, and Protective Efficacy of Radiation Attenuated Plasmodium Falciparum NF54 Sporozoites (PfSPZ Vaccine) During Malaria Transmission Season in Healthy African Adult Women of Childbearing Potential in Mali</brief_title>
  <official_title>Randomized, Placebo-Controlled, Double-Blind Study to Assess Safety, Immunogenicity, and Protective Efficacy of Radiation Attenuated Plasmodium Falciparum NF54 Sporozoites (SfSPZ Vaccine) During MaliariaTransmission Season in Healthy African Adult Women of Childbearing Potential in Mali</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      Malaria is a disease spread by mosquitos. Pregnant women are highly susceptible to malaria.
      This can lead to poor health outcomes for pregnant women and their babies. Researchers want
      to test a malaria vaccine in women of child bearing potential (WOCBP) and pregnant women.
      This has not been done before.

      Objective:

      To assess the safety and tolerability of PfSPZ vaccine in healthy Malian WOCBP.

      Eligibility:

      Healthy women ages 18 38 who live in Ouelessebougou, Mali, and surrounding villages

      Design:

      Participants will be screened with:

        -  Physical exam

        -  Medical history

        -  Blood, urine, and heart tests

        -  Multiple-choice test about malaria

      Participants will get 3 injections by needle into a vein of the study vaccine or a placebo.
      All 3 will be within 1 month. They will not know whether they receive the vaccine or placebo.

      Participants will receive treatment to prevent malaria. This will be about 2 weeks before the
      first and third injections.

      After the third injection, participants will be followed for about 1 year. They will be
      tested to see if the vaccine is safe and protects against malaria infection. They will have
      blood tests.

      If participants get a rash or injection site reaction, photos of the site may be taken.

      Any women who become pregnant during the trial will be followed through the end of pregnancy.
      Babies and their mothers will be followed through the first year of life
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Pregnant women are highly susceptible to Plasmodium falciparum malaria, leading to
      substantial maternal, perinatal, and infant mortality. While malaria vaccine development has
      made significant progress in recent years, no trials of malaria vaccines have ever been
      conducted in only women of child bearing potential (WOCBP) or in pregnant women.

      PfSPZ Vaccine (Sanaria, Inc) is an advanced malaria candidate being developed for use in

      pregnant women, owing in part to its highly favorable safety profile. The vaccine is
      comprised of aseptic, metabolically active, non-replicating, purified, cryopreserved P.
      falciparum sporozoites. In multiple double-blind, placebo-controlled trials, there have been
      no differences in adverse events between vaccinees versus controls. PfSPZ Vaccine induces
      immune responses to the sporozoite and liver stages of parasite development in the human host
      and prevents progression to blood stage parasitemia as well as averting disease sequelae; a
      compelling rationale to test PfSPZ Vaccine for its benefits in this proposed population.

      Sanaria has already achieved vaccine efficacy against homologous and heterogenous parasite
      populations in endemic areas following three doses of PfSPZ Vaccine in several studies with
      9.0x10^5 and 1.8x10^6 PfSPZ Vaccine and has explored accelerated regimens, such as 1, 8, 29
      days. Accelerated PfSPZ Vaccine regimens such as this could induce protection earlier in
      pregnancy, minimizing the period at risk and improving pregnancy outcomes over the control
      group.

      Given this, the Malaria Research and Training Center, the Laboratory of Malaria Immunology

      and Vaccinology National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases, and Sanaria, Inc.
      propose to initiate testing of the day 1, 8, and 29 dosing regimen of PfSPZ Vaccine in WOCBP,
      and in subsequent studies, in pregnant women, using doses of 9.0x10^5 and 1.8x10^6 PfSPZ
      Vaccine. This will be the first step in a clinical development plan for PfSPZ Vaccine in
      WOCBP and pregnant women: 1) safety and efficacy studies in non-pregnant WOCBP (this trial),
      2) studies of the safety and efficacy of a primary immunization series in all trimesters, and
      3) studies to evaluate the safety and efficacy of boosting during pregnancy.

      A pregnancy registry study (#17-I-N018) has been ongoing in Mali since 2017 to gain

      background data on maternal/fetal outcomes in the target population in anticipation of this
      study. Women who become pregnant during the course of this study, and their offspring, will
      be followed for maternal clinical outcomes and malaria infection.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 3, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 31, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 31, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of local and systemic adverse events (AEs)graded by severity occurring within 7 days after each vaccine administration.</measure>
    <time_frame>one year</time_frame>
    <description>Assess safety and tolerability of PfSPZ Vaccine primary series in healthy Malian WOCBP when given at 1, 8, 29 days at two doses (9 x10(5); 1.8 x10(6)).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>P. falciparum blood stage infection defined as time to first positive blood smear (detection of at least 2 P. falciparum parasites by microscopic examination of 0.5 microliter) starting immediately following 3rd injection over 24 weeks.</measure>
    <time_frame>24 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Assess the efficacy of PfSPZ Vaccine primary series in healthy Malian WOCBP when given at 1, 8, 29 days at two doses (9 x10(5); 1.8 x10(6)). Exploratory Objectives</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">409</enrollment>
  <condition>Malaria</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Arm 1: (n= 100) will receive 3 doses of PfSPZ Vaccine (9 x10(5)) via direct venous inoculation (DVI) at 1, 8, 29 days.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Arm 2: (n= 100) will receive 3 doses of PfSPZ Vaccine (1.8 x10(6)) via DVI at 1, 8, 29 days.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 3</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Arm 3: (n=100): will receive 3 doses of normal saline (placebo) injection via DVI at 1, 8, 29 days.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>PfSPZ Vaccine/Normal Saline</intervention_name>
    <description>PfSPZ vaccine is comprised of aseptic, metabolically active, non-replicating, purified, cryopreserved P. falciparum sporozoites. Sterile isotonic (0.9%) normal saline is a clear liquid, making it indistinguishable from the study product when drawn up into a syringe; and will be used as a placebo, rather than a comparator vaccine</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 3</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

               1. Females of child bearing potential aged greater than or equal to 18 and less than
                  or equal to 38 years

               2. Able to provide proof of identity to the satisfaction of the study clinician
                  completing the enrollment process

               3. In good general health and without clinically significant medical history

               4. Willing to have blood samples stored for future research

               5. Available for the duration of the study

               6. Must be willing to use reliable contraception (defined as: pharmacologic
                  contraceptives [parental delivery] or pre-existing intrauterine or implantable
                  device) from 21 days prior to study day 1 to 28 days after last vaccination

               7. Report being interested in becoming pregnant within the next 1-2 years

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

          1. Pregnancy at the time of enrollment/vaccination, as determined by a positive urine or
             serum human chorionic gonadotropin (beta-hCG) test

          2. Biologically unable to become pregnant secondary to: surgical sterilization, premature
             ovarian insufficiency (defined as no menses for greater than or equal to 12 months
             without an alternative medical cause)

          3. Behavioral, cognitive, or psychiatric disease that in the opinion of the investigator
             affects the ability of the participant to understand and comply with the study
             protocol

          4. Hemoglobin (Hgb), WBC, absolute neutrophils, and platelets outside the local
             laboratory-defined limits of normal and greater than or equal to Grade 2 (subjects may
             be included at the investigator s discretion for not clinically significant abnormal
             values)

          5. Alanine transaminase (ALT) or creatinine (Cr) level above the local laboratory-defined
             upper limit of normal and greater than or equal to Grade 2 (subjects may be included
             at the investigator s discretion for not clinically significant abnormal values)

          6. Infected with human immunodeficiency virus (HIV)

          7. Known or documented sickle cell disease by history (Note: known sickle cell trait is
             NOT exclusionary)

          8. Clinically significant abnormal electrocardiogram (ECG) such as abnormal QTc.

          9. Evidence of clinically significant neurologic, cardiac, pulmonary, hepatic, endocrine,
             rheumatologic, autoimmune, hematological, oncologic, or renal disease by history,
             physical examination, and/or laboratory studies including urinalysis

         10. History of receiving any investigational product within the past 30 days

         11. Participation or planned participation in a clinical trial with an investigational
             product prior to completion of the follow-up visit 28 days following last vaccination
             OR planned participation in an investigational vaccine study until the last required
             protocol visit

         12. Medical, occupational, or family problems as a result of alcohol or illicit drug use
             during the past 12 months

         13. History of a severe allergic reaction (Grade 2 or higher or per PI discretion) or
             anaphylaxis

         14. Severe asthma (defined as asthma that is unstable or required emergent care, urgent
             care, hospitalization, or intubation during the past two years, or that has required
             the use of oral or parenteral corticosteroids at any time during the past two years)

         15. Pre-existing autoimmune or antibody-mediated diseases including but not limited to:
             systemic lupus erythematosus, rheumatoid arthritis, multiple sclerosis, Sjogren s
             syndrome, or autoimmune thrombocytopenia

         16. Known immunodeficiency syndrome

         17. Known asplenia or functional asplenia

         18. Use of chronic (greater than or equal to 14 days) oral or IV corticosteroids
             (excluding topical or nasal) at immunosuppressive doses (i.e., prednisone greater than
             or equal to 20 mg/day) or immunosuppressive drugs within 30 days of vaccination

         19. Receipt of a live vaccine within the past four weeks or a killed vaccine within the
             past two weeks prior to Vaccination #1 and every subsequent vaccination day

         20. Receipt of immunoglobulins and/or blood products within the past six months

         21. Previous receipt of an investigational malaria vaccine in the last five years

         22. Known allergies or other contraindications against use of artemeter/lumefantrine

         23. Other condition(s) that, in the opinion of the investigator, would jeopardize the
             safety or rights of a participant participating in the trial, interfere with the
             evaluation of the study objectives, or would render the subject unable to comply with
             the protocol
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>38 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Patrick E Duffy, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ouelessebougou Health Research Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ouelessebougou</city>
        <country>Mali</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Mali</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Seder RA, Chang LJ, Enama ME, Zephir KL, Sarwar UN, Gordon IJ, Holman LA, James ER, Billingsley PF, Gunasekera A, Richman A, Chakravarty S, Manoj A, Velmurugan S, Li M, Ruben AJ, Li T, Eappen AG, Stafford RE, Plummer SH, Hendel CS, Novik L, Costner PJ, Mendoza FH, Saunders JG, Nason MC, Richardson JH, Murphy J, Davidson SA, Richie TL, Sedegah M, Sutamihardja A, Fahle GA, Lyke KE, Laurens MB, Roederer M, Tewari K, Epstein JE, Sim BK, Ledgerwood JE, Graham BS, Hoffman SL; VRC 312 Study Team. Protection against malaria by intravenous immunization with a nonreplicating sporozoite vaccine. Science. 2013 Sep 20;341(6152):1359-65. doi: 10.1126/science.1241800. Epub 2013 Aug 8.</citation>
    <PMID>23929949</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sissoko MS, Healy SA, Katile A, Omaswa F, Zaidi I, Gabriel EE, Kamate B, Samake Y, Guindo MA, Dolo A, Niangaly A, Niaré K, Zeguime A, Sissoko K, Diallo H, Thera I, Ding K, Fay MP, O'Connell EM, Nutman TB, Wong-Madden S, Murshedkar T, Ruben AJ, Li M, Abebe Y, Manoj A, Gunasekera A, Chakravarty S, Sim BKL, Billingsley PF, James ER, Walther M, Richie TL, Hoffman SL, Doumbo O, Duffy PE. Safety and efficacy of PfSPZ Vaccine against Plasmodium falciparum via direct venous inoculation in healthy malaria-exposed adults in Mali: a randomised, double-blind phase 1 trial. Lancet Infect Dis. 2017 May;17(5):498-509. doi: 10.1016/S1473-3099(17)30104-4. Epub 2017 Feb 16.</citation>
    <PMID>28216244</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hoffman SL, Billingsley PF, James E, Richman A, Loyevsky M, Li T, Chakravarty S, Gunasekera A, Chattopadhyay R, Li M, Stafford R, Ahumada A, Epstein JE, Sedegah M, Reyes S, Richie TL, Lyke KE, Edelman R, Laurens MB, Plowe CV, Sim BK. Development of a metabolically active, non-replicating sporozoite vaccine to prevent Plasmodium falciparum malaria. Hum Vaccin. 2010 Jan;6(1):97-106. Epub 2010 Jan 21. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19946222</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 5, 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 14, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 15, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 18, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 7, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 7, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 8, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Pregnancy</keyword>
  <keyword>Tolerability</keyword>
  <keyword>Immune</keyword>
  <keyword>Response</keyword>
  <keyword>Vaccination</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Malaria</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

