<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03984565</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2019P001480</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03984565</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Sublingual Cannabidiol for Chronic Pain</brief_title>
  <official_title>Sublingual Cannabidiol for Chronic Pain</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Staci Gruber, Ph.D.</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Mclean Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study involves taking a high-cannabidiol (CBD) sublingual product for 6 weeks in order
      to assess the impact of CBD on chronic pain, conventional medication use, clinical state,
      quality of life, cognition, and where applicable, brain structure and function via
      neuroimaging.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Cannabis sativa has been used medicinally to treat a wide range of disorders for thousands of
      years. Cannabis is comprised of more than 100 cannabinoids, including D9-tetrahydrocannabinol
      (THC), the major psychoactive constituent, and cannabidiol (CBD), the major non-intoxicating
      constituent that has demonstrated significant medicinal properties for a variety of
      disorders. Currently, 33 states and the District of Columbia have enacted full medical
      marijuana (MMJ) programs, and 14 states allow limited access to CBD-containing products. MMJ
      products can vary drastically in their cannabinoid constituent quantities and ratios, ranging
      from high THC products with very little CBD, to 1:1 ratios of THC to CBD, to high CBD
      products with very little THC. Although a wide range of products exist and are being actively
      used by consumers with a variety of medical indications, little is known about the direct
      impact of certain cannabinoids and constituent ratios on the symptoms that cause patients to
      seek treatment.

      Chronic pain is one of the most common indications for MMJ use, and several studies have
      yielded compelling data suggesting that MMJ and its constituents may have analgesic and
      anti-inflammatory properties, suggesting that particular cannabinoids may have the potential
      to treat chronic pain. To date, no clinical trials have been conducted assessing the effects
      of a high-CBD, low-THC product for chronic pain. This investigation will involve a an
      open-label to double-blind, placebo-controlled trial of a high-CBD sublingual product;
      patients will be assessed at baseline and over 6 weeks of treatment with CBD or placebo on
      measures of clinical state, including pain and related symptoms, conventional medication use,
      cognition, and brain imaging (as appropriate).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">August 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 31, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 31, 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>The study consists of two phases: an open-label phase followed by a double-blind, placebo-controlled, randomized trial.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in pain ratings on the Brief Pain Inventory (BPI)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The BPI contains 9 questions that assess the severity of pain, how much relief is provided by treatment, and the functional impact of the pain within the last 24 hours. Lower scores are better.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in ratings on the Pain Self-Efficacy Questionnaire (PSEQ)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The PSEQ contains several questions assessing the patients' confidence in carrying out certain activities despite their pain on a 7-point scale ranging from 0 (not at all confident) to 6 (completely confident). Higher scores are better.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in pain ratings on the Numerical Rating Scale (NRS)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The NRS is an 11-point scale on which subjects rate their pain by choosing a number between 0 (no pain) and 10 (worst possible pain). Lower scores are better.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in ratings on the Pain Distress Scale (PDS)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The PDS is an 11-point scale one where subjects rate their pain by level of distress the pain causes on a scale of 0 to 10. Lower scores are better.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in ratings on the Pain Disability Index (PDI)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>On the PDI, the subject rates how their pain affects 7 different areas of their life on a scale of the level of disability that their pain causes, from &quot;no disability&quot; to &quot;worst disability&quot;. Lower scores are better.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">55</enrollment>
  <condition>Chronic Pain</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cannabidiol Treatment Arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>20mg/ml CBD sublingual product administered twice daily for 6 weeks</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo Treatment Arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Placebo sublingual product administered twice daily for 6 weeks</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cannabidiol</intervention_name>
    <description>Cannabidiol sublingual product formulated in coconut oil</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cannabidiol Treatment Arm</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>CBD</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Placebo sublingual product formulated in coconut oil</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo Treatment Arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Subject has provided informed consent

          -  Subject is 21 or older

          -  Subject is a native English speaker or acquired English prior to age 5

          -  Subject endorses a chronic pain condition including, but not limited to, chronic pain
             due to injury, musculoskeletal pain, arthritis (including osteoarthritis and
             rheumatoid arthritis), fibromyalgia, bursitis, endometriosis, etc.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Non-native English speakers

          -  Estimated IQ &lt; 75

          -  A history of head injury or loss of consciousness greater than 5 minutes

          -  Currently uses marijuana or CBD products

          -  Female subjects will be excluded if they have a positive urine pregnancy test, are
             trying to become pregnant, or are currently breastfeeding

          -  Presence of a serious medical illness, including liver, kidney, or cardiovascular
             disease (hyper/hypotension, cardiac disorders), or neurological disorder (including
             seizure disorder)

          -  Neuropathic pain or cancer-related pain

          -  Disclosure of a genetic polymorphism affecting CYP2C9 function

          -  Coconut allergy, as the product is formulated in coconut oil
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>21 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Staci Gruber, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Mclean Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Staci Gruber, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <phone>617-855-2762</phone>
    <email>gruber@mclean.harvard.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Rosie Smith, B.S.</last_name>
    <phone>617-855-3653</phone>
    <email>brainstudy@mclean.harvard.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <verification_date>February 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 7, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 10, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 13, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 25, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 25, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 27, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Mclean Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Staci Gruber, Ph.D.</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Director, Marijuana Investigations for Neuroscientific Discovery; Director, Cognitive and Clinical Neuroimaging Core; Associate Professor of Psychiatry, Harvard Medical School</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Cannabidiol</keyword>
  <keyword>Medical Marijuana</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Chronic Pain</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Epidiolex</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

