<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03982368</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NGF0118</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03982368</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study to Evaluate Safety and Efficacy of rhNGF Eye Solution vs Vehicle in Patients With Moderate to Severe Dry Eye</brief_title>
  <official_title>A 4 Weeks, Phase II, Multicenter, Randomized, Double-masked, Vehicle-controlled, Parallel Group Study With 12 Weeks of Follow-up to Evaluate Safety and Efficacy of rhNGF Eye Drops Solution vs Vehicle in Moderate to Severe Dry Eye.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Dompé Farmaceutici S.p.A</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Dompé Farmaceutici S.p.A</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The primary objective of this study is to assess the efficacy and safety of rhNGF eye drops
      at 20 μg/ml concentration administered two or three times daily for 4 weeks in patients with
      moderate to severe dry eye. The trial is designed to perform dose ranging.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a 4 weeks, Phase II, multicenter, randomized, double-masked, vehicle-controlled,
      parallel group study with 12 weeks of follow-up to evaluate safety and efficacy of
      recombinant human Nerve Growth Factor (rhNGF) eye drops solution versus vehicle, in patients
      with moderate to severe dry eye (DE).

      Test product is rhNGF 20 μg/ml; reference product is vehicle. Test and reference will be
      instilled in both eyes according to the following scheme:

      Group 1: one drop of rhNGF 20 μg/ml will be instilled in both eyes three times daily (every
      6-8 hours, e.g. 7:00 am, 02:00 pm; 09:00 pm).

      Group 2: one drop of rhNGF 20 μg/ml will be instilled in both eyes two times daily plus one
      drop (40 μL) of vehicle will be instilled in both eyes once daily (every 6-8 hours, e.g. 7:00
      am, 02:00 pm; 09:00 pm).

      NB: rhNGF will be instilled in the morning and in the evening while the vehicle will be
      instilled in the afternoon.

      Group 3: vehicle eye one drop will be instilled in both eyes three times daily (every 6-8
      hours, e.g. 7:00 am, 02:00 pm; 09:00 pm).

      Randomization 1:1:1 of 300 patients to rhNGF eye drops solution 20 μg/ml TID (100 patients)
      or rhNGF eye drops solution 20 μg/ml BID + vehicle eye drop SID (100 patients) or vehicle eye
      drops solution (100 patients) TID for 4 weeks.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 10, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Parallel groups</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>Double masked</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in Schirmer I test (without anesthesia) Vs week 4</measure>
    <time_frame>at week 4</time_frame>
    <description>Without previously instilling anesthetic drops, the Schirmer strips is inserted into the lower conjunctival sac at the junction of the lateral and middle thirds, avoiding touching the cornea, and the length of wetting strips in millimeters is recorded after 5 minutes.
The patients will be instructed to close their eyes gently. After 5 minutes have elapsed, the Schirmer test strip will be removed and the length of the tear absorption on the strip will be measured (millimeters/5 minutes)
Cutoff values:
&lt;5 mm - pathologic dry eye 5-10 mm - marginal dry eye &gt;10 and &lt;30 mm - normal secretion</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in Symptoms questionnaire (SANDE) scores for severity Vs week 4</measure>
    <time_frame>at week 4</time_frame>
    <description>The SANDE score is calculated by taking the square root of the product of the severity of symptoms score. The SANDE scale ranges from 0 to 100 with 100 being the maximal amount of dry eye symptoms and 0 being the minimal amount of dry eye symptoms.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in Symptoms questionnaire (SANDE) scores for frequency Vs week 4</measure>
    <time_frame>at week 4</time_frame>
    <description>The SANDE score is calculated by taking the square root of the product of the frequency of symptoms score. The SANDE scale ranges from 0 to 100 wi.100 being the maximal amount of dry eye symptoms and 0 being the minimal amount of dry eye symptoms</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in Schirmer II test (with anesthesia) Vs week 4;</measure>
    <time_frame>at week 4</time_frame>
    <description>The Schirmer II test is performed as the Schirmer I test after instilling anesthetic drops. The Schirmer strips are inserted into the lower conjunctival sac at the junction of the lateral and middle thirds, avoiding touching the cornea, and the length of wetting strips in millimeters is recorded after 5 minutes.
All patients are seated at rest with their eyes closed, and the lower cul-de-sac is gently dried with a cotton applicator before the placement of strips.
Cutoff values:
&lt;5 mm - pathologic dry eye 5-10 mm - marginal dry eye &gt;10 and &lt;30 mm - normal secretion</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in cornea vital staining with fluorescein (National Eye Institute [NEI] scales) Vs week 4</measure>
    <time_frame>at week 4</time_frame>
    <description>The NEI/Industry Workshop guidelines are used for grading the scale of corneal and conjunctival damage. The cornea is divided into five sectors (central, superior, inferior, nasal and temporal), each of which is scored on a scale of 0-3, with a maximal total corneal staining score of 15.
Briefly, grade 0 reflects normal/healthy situation, whereas grade 3 reflects a severe damage in the considered sector.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in conjunctiva vital staining with fluorescein (National Eye Institute [NEI] scales) Vs week 4;</measure>
    <time_frame>at week 4</time_frame>
    <description>The NEI/Industry Workshop guidelines are used for grading the scale of corneal and conjunctival damage. Both nasally and temporally, the conjunctiva is divided into a superior paralimbal area, an inferior paralimbal area, and a peripheral area with a grading scale of 0-3 and with a maximal total score of 9 for the nasal and temporal conjunctiva (overall the total score ranged from 0-18).
Briefly, grade 0 reflects normal/healthy situation, whereas grade 3 reflects a severe damage in the considered sector.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in Tear Film Break-Up Time (TFBUT) Vs week 4</measure>
    <time_frame>at week 4</time_frame>
    <description>TFBUT is measured by determining the time to tear break-up. The TFBUT is performed after instillation of 5 μL of 2% preservative-free sodium fluorescein solution into the inferior conjunctival cul-de-sac of each eye. The patient is instructed to blink several times to thoroughly mix the fluorescein with the tear film.
A TFBUT greater than 15 &quot; is considered normal, while a break time of less than 10&quot; is to be considered pathological.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of patients who experienced a worsening in symptom scores (SANDE) and/or NEI score ≥ 50% assessed at week 4.</measure>
    <time_frame>at week 4</time_frame>
    <description>The SANDE score is calculated by taking the square root of the product of the severity of symptoms score. The SANDE scale ranges from 0 to 100 with 100 being the maximal amount of dry eye symptoms and 0 being the minimal amount of dry eye symptoms.
The NEI/Industry Workshop guidelines are used for grading the scale of corneal and conjunctival damage.
The cornea is divided into five sectors (central, superior, inferior, nasal and temporal), each of which is scored on a scale of 0-3, with a maximal total corneal staining score of 15.
Both nasally and temporally, the conjunctiva is divided into a superior paralimbal area, an inferior paralimbal area, and a peripheral area with a grading scale of 0-3 and with a maximal total score of 9 for the nasal and temporal conjunctiva (overall the total score ranged from 0-18).
Briefly, grade 0 reflects normal/healthy situation, whereas grade 3 reflects a severe damage in the considered sector.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of life (Impact of Dry Eye on Everyday Life (IDEEL) questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>at baseline and weeks 4, 8, 12 and 16</time_frame>
    <description>IDEEL assesses quality of life, symptoms and treatment effects on patients with dry eye.
The IDEEL contains 3 modules (Daily Activities, Treatment Satisfaction, and Symptom Bother) with a total of 57 questions.
The Daily Activities Module is the quality of life instrument. It is comprised of 27 items.
The IDEEL Treatment Satisfaction and Bother Module is divided into 2 sections, Treatment - In General and Treatment - Eye Drops.
The Symptom Bother Module consists of 20 items in a single content domain, Symptom Bother.
Scores for each dimensions ranged from 0 to 100.
Higher scores for:
dimensions of the Dry Eye Impact on Daily Life module indicates less impact on daily activities; Symptom-Bother dimension indicates greater bother due to symptoms; Satisfaction with Treatment Effectiveness dimension indicates greater satisfaction with treatment effectiveness; Treatment-related Bother/Inconvenience indicates less treatment-related bother or inconvenience.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient global Impression of change (PGIC);</measure>
    <time_frame>at baseline and weeks 4, 8, 12 and 16</time_frame>
    <description>PGIC is a commonly used method of assessing clinically important change. With PGIC the qualitative assessment of meaningful change is determined by the patient on 7-items using a 0 (very much improved) to 10 (very much worse) scale.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>EQ-5D-3L questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>at baseline and weeks 4, 8, 12 and 16</time_frame>
    <description>EQ-5D is a standardised measure of health status.
The EQ-5D 3 level version (EQ-5D-3L) essentially consists of the EQ-5D descriptive system and the EQ visual analogue scale (EQ VAS). The EQ-5D-3L descriptive system comprises the following 5 dimensions:
mobility, self-care, usual activities, pain/discomfort and anxiety/depression. Each dimension has 3 levels: no problems, some problems, extreme problems. The respondent is asked to indicate his/her health state by ticking (or placing a cross) in the box against the most appropriate statement in each of the 5 dimensions. The EQ VAS records the respondent's self-rated health on a vertical, visual analogue scale where the endpoints are labelled 'Best imaginable health state' and 'Worst imaginable health state'. This information can be used as a quantitative measure of health outcome as judged by the individual respondents.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">300</enrollment>
  <condition>Dry Eye Syndrome</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>rhNGF 20 μg/ml TID</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>One drop of rhNGF 20 μg/ml will be instilled in both eyes three times daily (every 6-8 hours)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>rhNGF 20 μg/ml BID + vehicle OD</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>One drop of rhNGF 20 μg/ml will be instilled in both eyes two times daily (BID) plus one drop (40 μL) of vehicle will be instilled in both eyes once daily (OD) (every 6-8 hours)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Vehicle TID</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Vehicle eye one drop will be instilled in both eyes three times daily (every 6-8 hours)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>rhNGF 20 μg/ml</intervention_name>
    <description>one drop of rhNGF 20 μg/ml will be instilled in both eyes three times daily (every 6-8 hours)</description>
    <arm_group_label>rhNGF 20 μg/ml TID</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>cenegermin</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>rhNGF 20 μg/ml + vehicle</intervention_name>
    <description>one drop of rhNGF 20 μg/ml will be instilled in both eyes two times daily plus one drop (40 μL) of vehicle will be instilled in both eyes once daily (every 6-8 hours).
rhNGF will be instilled in the morning and in the evening while the vehicle will be instilled in the afternoon.</description>
    <arm_group_label>rhNGF 20 μg/ml BID + vehicle OD</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>cenegermin + placebo</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Vehicle</intervention_name>
    <description>one drop of vehicle will be instilled in both eyes three times daily (every 6-8 hours)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Vehicle TID</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>placebo</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Male or female aged ≥ 18 years

          2. Patients with moderate to severe dry eye characterized by the following clinical
             features:

               1. Corneal and/or conjunctival staining with fluorescein using National Eye
                  Institute (NEI) grading system &gt; 3

               2. SANDE questionnaire &gt;25 mm

               3. Schirmer test I (without anaesthesia) &gt;2mm &lt;10 mm/5 minutes

               4. Tear film break-up time (TFBUT) &lt; 10 seconds in the worse eye

          3. The same eye (eligible eye) must fulfill all the above criteria

          4. Patients diagnosed with dry eye at least 6 months before enrolment (current use or
             recommended use of artificial tears for the treatment of Dry Eye)

          5. Best corrected distance visual acuity (BCDVA) score of ≥ 0.1 decimal units (20/200
             Snellen value) in both eyes at the time of study enrolment

          6. If a female of childbearing potential, have a negative pregnancy test

          7. Only patients who satisfy all Informed Consent requirements may be included in the
             study. The patient and/or his/her legal representative must read, sign and date the
             Informed Consent document before any study-related procedures are performed. The
             Informed Consent form signed by patients and/or legal representative must have been
             approved by the Institutional Review Board (IRB) / Independent Ethics Committee (IEC)
             for the current study

          8. Patients must have the ability and willingness to comply with study procedures.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Inability to speak and understand the local language sufficiently to understand the
             nature of the study, to provide written informed consent, and to allow the completion
             of all study assessments;

          2. Evidence of an active ocular infection, in either eye

          3. Presence of any other ocular disorder or condition requiring topical medication during
             the entire duration of study

          4. History of severe systemic allergy or of ocular allergy (including seasonal
             conjunctivitis) or chronic conjunctivitis and/or keratitis other than dry eye

          5. Intraocular inflammation defined as Tyndall score &gt;0

          6. History of malignancy in the last 5 years

          7. Systemic disease not stabilized within 1 month before Screening Visit (e.g. diabetes
             with glycemia out of range, thyroid malfunction..) or judged by the investigator to be
             incompatible with the study (e.g. current systemic infections) or with a condition
             incompatible with the frequent assessment required by the study

          8. Patient had a serious adverse reaction or significant hypersensitivity to any drug or
             chemically related compounds or had a clinically significant allergy to drugs, foods,
             amide local anaesthetics or other materials including commercial artificial tears (in
             the opinion of the investigator)

          9. Females of childbearing potential (those who are not surgically sterilized or
             post-menopausal for at least 1 year) are excluded from participation in the study if
             they meet any one of the following conditions:

               1. are currently pregnant or,

               2. have a positive result at the urine pregnancy test (Baseline/Day 0) or,

               3. intend to become pregnant during the study treatment period or,

               4. are breast-feeding or,

               5. are not willing to use highly effective birth control measures, such as: hormonal
                  contraceptives - oral, implanted, transdermal, or injected - and/or mechanical
                  barrier methods - spermicide in conjunction with a barrier such as a condom or
                  diaphragm or Intra Uterine Device (IUD) - during the entire course of and 30 days
                  after the study treatment periods

         10. Any concurrent medical condition, that in the judgment of the PI, might interfere with
             the conduct of the study, confound the interpretation of the study results, or
             endanger the patient's well-being

         11. Use of topical cyclosporine, topical corticosteroids or any other topical drug for the
             treatment of dry eye in either eye within 30 days of study enrolment.

         12. Contact lenses or punctum plug use during the study (previous use not an exclusion
             criteria but must be discontinued at the screening visit)

         13. History of drug addiction or alcohol abuse

         14. Any prior ocular surgery (including refractive palpebral and cataract surgery) if
             within 90 days before the screening visit

         15. Participation in a clinical trial with a new active substance during the past 6 months

         16. Participation in another clinical trial study at the same time as the present study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>85 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mauro Ferrari, Pharm D</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Dompé s.p.a., Milan</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Mauro Ferrari, Pharm D</last_name>
    <phone>+3902583831</phone>
    <email>info@dompe.it</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Elisa Greco, BSc</last_name>
    <phone>+3902583831</phone>
    <email>info@dompe.it</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Global Research Management</name>
      <address>
        <city>Glendale</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>91204</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Lucy Bataneant, MD</last_name>
      <email>lucyb@grmclinical.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Sherif El-Harazi, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Eye Research Foundation</name>
      <address>
        <city>Newport Beach</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>92663</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>David Wirta</last_name>
      <email>david.wirta@drwirta.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Martel Eye Medical Group</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rancho Cordova</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>95670</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Joseph Martel</last_name>
      <email>martelresearch@me.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sierra Clinical Trials &amp; Research Organization</name>
      <address>
        <city>Santa Ana</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>92647</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Michael Sheety</last_name>
      <email>michael.sheety@sierraclinicaltrials.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Michael Sheety, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Clayton Eye Clinical Research, LLC</name>
      <address>
        <city>Morrow</city>
        <state>Georgia</state>
        <zip>30260</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Harvey Dubiner</last_name>
      <email>glaucdocga@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Kentucky Eye Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lexington</city>
        <state>Kentucky</state>
        <zip>40517</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Justin Tincher, MD</last_name>
      <email>justin.tincher@kyeye.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Paul Karpecki, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Tauber Eye Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kansas City</city>
        <state>Missouri</state>
        <zip>64111</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Joseph Tauber, MD</last_name>
      <email>jt@taubereye.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Joseph Tauber, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Moyes Eye Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kansas City</city>
        <state>Missouri</state>
        <zip>64154</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Anthony Verachtert</last_name>
      <email>averachtert@moyeseye.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>SightMD</name>
      <address>
        <city>Babylon</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>11702</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Heather McBride</last_name>
      <email>Singrod1@jhmi.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Alanna Nattis, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Toyos Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nashville</city>
        <state>Tennessee</state>
        <zip>37027</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Melissa Toyos</last_name>
      <email>mtoyos@toyosclinic.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Houston Eye Associates HEA - Gramercy Location</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77025</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>John Goosey</last_name>
      <email>jgoosey@houstoneye.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Advanced Laser Vision Surgical Institute (Study Site) Intouch Clinical Research Center (SMO)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77034</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>William Lipsky</last_name>
      <email>doclipsky@intouchcrc.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 23, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 10, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 11, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 13, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 13, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 14, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Keratoconjunctivitis Sicca</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dry Eye Syndromes</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

