<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03981679</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PROICM 2017-02 DEP</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03981679</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Circulating-free DNA Assessment as a Tool to Predict Colorectal Cancer in Subjects With a Positive Fecal Immunoassay.</brief_title>
  <acronym>DEPLR</acronym>
  <official_title>Prospective, Non-randomized, Open-label and Multi-center Study With the Establishment of a Clinical-biological Database.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Institut du Cancer de Montpellier - Val d'Aurelle</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Institut du Cancer de Montpellier - Val d'Aurelle</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Colorectal cancer (CRC): is one of the most frequent cancers, with almost 42152 new cases
      estimated in France for 2012. There are 3 levels of risk of developing CRC: moderate, high or
      very high. At each level of risk, appropriate follow-up recommendations are made.
      Immunological tests for fecal occult blood tests have emerged in recent years and have
      rapidly become established as benchmark tests in Europe and then in France (OC Sensor test)
      as part of mass screening. In the case of a positive immunological test, a diagnostic
      colonoscopy must be systematically organized in order to characterize the possible
      recto-colic cause of the digestive bleeding thus observed.

      Measurement of the DNA present in the circulating blood (circulating DNA or cfDNA): allowed a
      significant advance in the personalized management of cancers, as a non-invasive test capable
      of producing diagnostic, prognostic, theranostic, and of therapeutic follow-up type.

      The aim of the work is to measure the cfDNA concentration in subjects undergoing colonoscopy
      because of a positive immunological fecal test.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Colorectal cancer (CRC): is one of the most frequent cancers, with almost 42152 new cases
      estimated in France for 2012. The incidence is thus 30 new cases per year per 100 000
      inhabitants in France. It is also a significant cause of death, with 10 deaths per year per
      100,000 inhabitants. More than 8 patients out of 10 are cured by surgery alone in case of
      discovery of an early form with a tumor extension limited to the colonic wall and absence of
      proximal lymph node invasion. Since most of the invasive cancers are preceded by a benign
      precancerous lesion called adenoma, it is well understood that the detection of these
      adenomas (and in particular those at high risk of cancerization: adenomas greater than 10 mm
      or adenomas in severe dysplasia), followed by their endoscopic excision (polypectomy via
      colonoscopy) can prevent the development of invasive CRC and ultimately improve the survival
      of the population thus detected. It is precisely the possibility of intervening on this
      sequence adenomacancer during an asymptomatic phase of the disease that is the basis of the
      offer of screening for CRC. CRC screening: There are 3 levels of risk of developing CRC:
      moderate, high or very high. At each level of risk, appropriate follow-up recommendations are
      made.considered moderate risk of developing CRC, subjects older than 50 years. These patients
      at risk are also the most numerous. They are the ones who are involved in screening for
      occult blood in the stool. Two methods of screening were recommended for moderate-risk
      subjects, left-sided recto-sigmoidoscopy and repeated occult blood tests in the faeces by the
      Gaiac method. The latter method has rapidly became in Europe a reference method for screening
      CRC for reasons of cost and access to care. However, it appears to be a method which is not
      very appreciated by patients (manipulation of several stool samples) and which is not very
      sensitive, and which may also interact with hemoglobin of animal origin. These disadvantages
      have led to an interest in other methods of screening occult blood in stools, such as
      immunological methods. Immunological tests for fecal occult blood tests have emerged in
      recent years and have rapidly become established as benchmark tests in Europe and then in
      France (OC Sensor test) as part of mass screening. Briefly, 2 Dutch randomized studies showed
      that the OC Sensor immunoassay had better screening performance and acceptability than the
      Gaiac test. Overall, the different studies have shown that immunological tests lead to more
      CRCs and more advanced neoplasia than the Gaiac test. According to the studies, the
      positivity rate ranged from 3% to 6% for immunoassays, the positive predictive value of
      advanced neoplasia was about 45% with OC Sensor, and that of invasive cancer was 7%. Thus,
      the OC Sensor fecal immunoassay is the reference screening test, as part of the organized
      screening of subjects at moderate risk of CRC. In the case of a positive immunological test,
      a diagnostic colonoscopy must be systematically organized in order to characterize the
      possible recto-colic cause of the digestive bleeding thus observed. The colonoscopy
      identifies the lesion and the biopsies then performed accurately identify the advanced nature
      (adenoma&gt; 10 mm or adenoma in severe dysplasia or invasive cancer) or not of the neoplasia.
      Colonoscopy is a perfectly controlled medical procedure performed under anesthesia.

      It can, however, exceptionally cause bleeding, perforation of the colon, severe abdominal
      pain, especially when the endoscopic act is associated with an interventional act such as
      biopsy or polypectomy. The practice of colonoscopy is yearly responsible for 3 accidents on
      1000 colonoscopies performed, leading to 1 surgery on 1000 colonoscopy, and unfortunately to
      1 death every 10 000 colonoscopies. Because the colonoscopy is performed under anesthesia,
      this forces the patient to absent himself from work for one day, to call on a third party to
      return home. Finally, although colonoscopy is the most sensitive and specific test for the
      diagnosis of adenomas and CRCs, its diagnostic performance is not absolute: complete colon
      exploration is only possible in 95 % Of cases. Colonoscopy is missing in particular 5% of
      adenomas of more than 1 cm and 4% of colon cancers of the right colon. Colonoscopy also has a
      cost. Thus, any non-invasive test capable of making a diagnosis of invasive cancer or
      discarding the same cancer diagnosis after a positive immunological fecal screening test
      would be able to reduce the use of diagnostic colonoscopy and thus the risks and Associated
      constraints. Measurement of the DNA present in the circulating blood (circulating DNA or
      cfDNA): allowed a significant advance in the personalized management of cancers, as a
      non-invasive test capable of producing diagnostic, prognostic, theranostic, and of
      therapeutic follow-up type. The teams of the IRCM of Montpellier have developed a test called
      IntPlex®, capable of allowing the multiparametric analysis of this cfDNA.

      This innovative technology has been patented and validated technically and clinically on
      large cohorts of patients with different types of cancer and for several types of genetic
      mutations. Briefly, this Intplex® technology enables the simultaneous determination of five
      cfDNA measurement and characterization parameters: total cfDNA concentration, fragmentation,
      point mutation detection, mutant cfDNA concentration and mutational load.

      Plasma cfDNA concentrations in patients with CRC are significantly higher than in healthy
      individuals. These concentrations decrease progressively in patients in remission while they
      increase in the patients evolutionary or in recurrence. This measure also proves to be an
      excellent tool to discriminate patients with metastatic CRC from those with more pejorative
      prognosis. The aim of the work is to measure the cfDNA concentration in subjects undergoing
      colonoscopy because of a positive immunological fecal test.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 5, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Screening</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>AUC</measure>
    <time_frame>Until the study completion of 2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Area under the ROC curve (AUC) of the total cfDNA concentration.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>cfDNA threshold</measure>
    <time_frame>Until the study completion of 2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Optimal threshold of CfDNA (according to Youden Index)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Intplex parameters</measure>
    <time_frame>Until the study completion of 2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Sensitivity, specificity, positive predictive value, negative predictive value of the test Intplex</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">275</enrollment>
  <condition>Colorectal Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Biological collection</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>For all the patients include in the study :
- Blood samples collected before the colonoscopy In parallel to this biological collection, standardized clinical data will be entered into a database</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Biological collection</intervention_name>
    <description>The biological collection will also include samples of blood samples collected before colonoscopy</description>
    <arm_group_label>Biological collection</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age ≥ at 18 years old,

          -  Patient with a positive immunological screening test,

          -  Patient requiring a colonoscopy

          -  Patient having given his informed, written and express consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patient not affiliated to a social security scheme,

          -  Subject under tutelage, curatorship or safeguard of justice,

          -  Patient in an emergency situation,

          -  Acute or chronic inflammatory disease,

          -  Patient having made an intense effort 3 days before sampling.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>ADENIS Antoine, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Institut régional du Cancer de Montpellier</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>BLEUSE Jean-Pierre, MD</last_name>
    <phone>0467613102</phone>
    <phone_ext>+33</phone_ext>
    <email>DRCI-105@icm.unicancer.fr</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>ADENIS Antoine, MD</last_name>
    <phone>0467614701</phone>
    <phone_ext>+33</phone_ext>
    <email>antoine.adenis@icm.unicancer.fr</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>ICM - Institut régional du Cancer Montpellier</name>
      <address>
        <city>Montpellier</city>
        <state>Occ</state>
        <zip>34298</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>ADENIS Antoine, MD</last_name>
      <phone>0467614701</phone>
      <phone_ext>+33</phone_ext>
      <email>antoine.adenis@icm.unicancer.fr</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Segnan N, Armaroli P, Bonelli L, Risio M, Sciallero S, Zappa M, Andreoni B, Arrigoni A, Bisanti L, Casella C, Crosta C, Falcini F, Ferrero F, Giacomin A, Giuliani O, Santarelli A, Visioli CB, Zanetti R, Atkin WS, Senore C; SCORE Working Group. Once-only sigmoidoscopy in colorectal cancer screening: follow-up findings of the Italian Randomized Controlled Trial--SCORE. J Natl Cancer Inst. 2011 Sep 7;103(17):1310-22. doi: 10.1093/jnci/djr284. Epub 2011 Aug 18. Erratum in: J Natl Cancer Inst. 2011 Dec 21;103(24):1903. Fracchia, M [added].</citation>
    <PMID>21852264</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Schoen RE, Pinsky PF, Weissfeld JL, Yokochi LA, Church T, Laiyemo AO, Bresalier R, Andriole GL, Buys SS, Crawford ED, Fouad MN, Isaacs C, Johnson CC, Reding DJ, O'Brien B, Carrick DM, Wright P, Riley TL, Purdue MP, Izmirlian G, Kramer BS, Miller AB, Gohagan JK, Prorok PC, Berg CD; PLCO Project Team. Colorectal-cancer incidence and mortality with screening flexible sigmoidoscopy. N Engl J Med. 2012 Jun 21;366(25):2345-57. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa1114635. Epub 2012 May 21.</citation>
    <PMID>22612596</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Minozzi S, Armaroli P, Segnan N. European guidelines for quality assurance in colorectal cancer screening and diagnosis. First Edition--Principles of evidence assessment and methods for reaching recommendations. Endoscopy. 2012 Sep;44 Suppl 3:SE9-14. Epub 2012 Sep 25.</citation>
    <PMID>23012125</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>US Preventive Services Task Force, Bibbins-Domingo K, Grossman DC, Curry SJ, Davidson KW, Epling JW Jr, García FAR, Gillman MW, Harper DM, Kemper AR, Krist AH, Kurth AE, Landefeld CS, Mangione CM, Owens DK, Phillips WR, Phipps MG, Pignone MP, Siu AL. Screening for Colorectal Cancer: US Preventive Services Task Force Recommendation Statement. JAMA. 2016 Jun 21;315(23):2564-2575. doi: 10.1001/jama.2016.5989. Erratum in: JAMA. 2016 Aug 2;316(5):545. Erratum in: JAMA. 2017 Jun 6;317(21):2239.</citation>
    <PMID>27304597</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Mouliere F, El Messaoudi S, Pang D, Dritschilo A, Thierry AR. Multi-marker analysis of circulating cell-free DNA toward personalized medicine for colorectal cancer. Mol Oncol. 2014 Jul;8(5):927-41. doi: 10.1016/j.molonc.2014.02.005. Epub 2014 Mar 24.</citation>
    <PMID>24698732</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>June 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 7, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 7, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 11, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 7, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 7, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 11, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>colonoscopy</keyword>
  <keyword>CRC screening</keyword>
  <keyword>cfDNA</keyword>
  <keyword>Intplex</keyword>
  <keyword>colorectal cancer</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Colorectal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

