<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03981406</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>STUDY00000753</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03981406</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Palliative Care and Quality of Life in Idiopathic Pulmonary Fibrosis</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Impact of Palliative Care on Quality of Life, Anxiety, and Depression in Patients With Idiopathic Pulmonary Fibrosis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Minnesota</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Minnesota</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to evaluate the effects of adding a palliative care intervention
      for patients with idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis (IPF) to current standard of care.

      Palliative care is comprehensive, coordinated interdisciplinary care for patients and
      families facing a potentially life-threatening illness. This consists of specially trained
      teams of professionals including physicians, nurses, social workers, and chaplains that
      provide care and support in inpatient and outpatient settings. While the specific assistance
      and support provided by the Palliative Care Service depends on individual patient and family
      needs and preferences, it may include:

        1. Pain and symptom management

        2. Psychosocial and spiritual support

        3. Assistance with treatment choices

        4. Help in planning for care in the community
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis (IPF) is a progressive and heterogeneous fibrotic lung disease.
      It is universally fatal, with an average time to death between two to five years.

      Patients with IPF experience significantly diminished quality of life and increased symptom
      burden. Besides dyspnea, cough, fatigue, and deconditioning, patients with IPF experience
      significant depression and anxiety. The benefit of palliative care has been demonstrated in
      several other diseases, notably, in metastatic lung cancer. Patients with metastatic lung
      cancer who were seen by palliative care at the time of their diagnosis and throughout their
      disease course were found to have increased survival, improved quality of life, and received
      less aggressive care at the end of their life. This finding has prompted significant research
      in the role of palliative care in other diseases, including chronic lung disease. A
      non-blinded, randomized trial of a multi-disciplinary breathlessness service intervention in
      patients with advanced disease including cancer, chronic obstructive lung disease (COPD),
      interstitial lung disease (ILD), and congestive heart failure demonstrated improvement in
      breathlessness, anxiety, and even survival. Specific Aim 1: Determine if quality of life is
      improved with a palliative care intervention. Specific Aim 2: Determine if depression and
      anxiety symptoms are decreased with a palliative care intervention. Secondary aims include an
      examination of pulmonary function tests (PFT), number of hospitalizations, and overall
      mortality as an effect of a palliative care intervention.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 15, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 1, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 1, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline respiratory quality of life as measured by SGRQ</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>The Saint George's Respiratory Questionnaire (SGRQ) is 50-item survey with scores ranging from 0 to 100 and with higher scores indicating worse quality of life.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline anxiety and depression symptoms as measured by HADS</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>The Hospital Depression and Anxiety Index (HADS) is a 14-item survey with scores ranging from 0 to 21 and with higher scores indicating greater depression and anxiety.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in prevalence of baseline depression as measured by PHQ-9</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>The Patient Health Questionnaire (PHQ-9) is a 10-item survey with scores ranging from 1 to 27 and with higher scores indicating greater levels of depression.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline of spirometry</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Spirometry is a commonly-used pulmonary function test (PFT) measuring lung function. Greater spirometry output will be considered a measure of greater treatment efficacy.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline of diffusing capacity</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Diffusing capacity is a commonly-used pulmonary function test (PFT) measuring the transfer of gas from air in the lung to the red blood cells in lung blood vessels. Greater diffusing capacity will be considered a measure of greater treatment efficacy.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline of lung volume</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Lung volume is a commonly-used pulmonary function test (PFT) measuring the volume of inhaled or exhaled air. Greater lung volume will be considered a measure of greater treatment efficacy.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline of 6-minute walk distance</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>6-minute walk distance will be considered as a measure of invention efficacy, with an increase in 6-minute walk distance considered a measure of greater treatment efficacy.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Total number of hospitalizations due to any cause</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Total number of hospitalizations due to any cause will be considered as a measure of intervention efficacy, with decrease hospitalizations in the treatment group considered a measure of greater treatment efficacy.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>All-cause mortality</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>All-cause mortality will be considered as a measure of intervention efficacy, with decrease in mortality in the treatment group considered a measure of greater treatment efficacy.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">22</enrollment>
  <condition>Idiopathic Pulmonary Fibrosis</condition>
  <condition>Depression</condition>
  <condition>Anxiety</condition>
  <condition>Depressive Disorder</condition>
  <condition>Anxiety Disorders</condition>
  <condition>Anxiety Depression</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Palliative Care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Palliative care is comprehensive, coordinated interdisciplinary care for patients and families facing a potentially life-threatening illness. This consists of specially trained teams of professionals including physicians, nurses, social workers, and chaplains that provide care and support in inpatient and outpatient settings.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Standard of Care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Standard of care for idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Palliative Care</intervention_name>
    <description>The intervention is one visit to the Fairview Clinics and Surgery Center palliative care clinic, with follow up visits as determined by the palliative care team and the patient.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Palliative Care</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Standard of Care</intervention_name>
    <description>Control group will receive standard of care treatment for IPF.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Standard of Care</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  IPF as diagnosed by chest CT or lung biopsy, and documented by a pulmonologist in the
             patient's medical record

          -  Capacity to provide informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Documented malignancy that would impact mortality within the study enrollment period

          -  Inability to pay for palliative care visit, insurance or personally.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Minnesota</name>
      <address>
        <city>Minneapolis</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55455</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 6, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 6, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 10, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 27, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 27, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 29, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Palliative Care</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pulmonary Fibrosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Idiopathic Pulmonary Fibrosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fibrosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depression</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Anxiety Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

