<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03988855</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>001C16</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03988855</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>An Exploratory, Open-Label, Oligo-Center Study to Evaluate the Safety, Efficacy, and Pharmacokinetics of Intravenous DNV3837 in Subjects With Clostridium Difficile Infection</brief_title>
  <official_title>An Exploratory, Open-Label, Oligo-Center Study to Evaluate the Safety, Efficacy, and Pharmacokinetics of Intravenous DNV3837 in Subjects With Clostridium Difficile Infection</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Deinove</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Deinove</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is an open-label study to evaluate the safety, efficacy, and PK of DNV3837 at a dose of
      6 mg/kg BW/day administered via IV infusion in subjects with CDI. The study will be conducted
      in 2 subsequent parts. In Part 1 of the study, 10 subjects of either sex with non-severe CDI
      will be enrolled to receive DNV3837. In Part 2 of the study, up to 30 subjects with severe
      CDI will be enrolled and randomized in a 2:1 ratio to receive DNV3837 or SOC. In both parts
      of the study, treatment infusions will be administered at a constant rate of 0.5 mg/kg
      BW/hour, resulting in a total IV infusion duration of 12 hours per day, for a total daily
      dose of 6 mg/kg BW DNV3837. Infusions will be administered once daily for 10 consecutive
      days. The objectives of the study are:

        -  To evaluate the safety of intravenous (IV) DNV3837;

        -  To evaluate the efficacy of IV DNV3837 versus standard of care (SOC);

        -  To assess the pharmacokinetics (PK) of DNV3837 and DNV3681 in plasma and of DNV3681 in
           urine and feces;

        -  To assess C. difficile using microbiological assessments;

        -  To assess the proportion of subjects colonized with vancomycin-resistant enterococci
           (VRE), extended-spectrum beta-lactamase (ESBL) organisms, or carbapenem-resistant
           Enterobacteriaceae (CRE) in feces; and

        -  To assess changes in the fecal microbiome using 16S ribosomal ribonucleic acid (RNA)
           analysis
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">August 2, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 17, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 5, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Sequential Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Treatment Success at Test of Cure</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 12</time_frame>
    <description>[Bristol Stool Scale 6 or 7]) that results in the subject receiving antimicrobial treatment active against C. difficile. Confirmed relapse is further defined as a new episode of diarrhea (&gt;3 liquid stools or UBMs [Bristol Stool Scale 6 or 7]) with a positive C. difficile free toxin test and the requirement of antimicrobial treatment active against C. difficile;
Alive;
No additional antimicrobial or anti-diarrheal therapies for CDI</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>All Cause Mortality</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 30</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Clostridium Difficile Infection attributable mortality</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 30</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of relapse at Test of Cure</measure>
    <time_frame>12 Days</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to resolution of diarrhea</measure>
    <time_frame>12 days</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Treatment failure at test of cure</measure>
    <time_frame>12 days</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Clostridium Difficile (C. Difficile)</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Part 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>10 subjects of either sex with severe or non-severe CDI will be enrolled to receive DNV3837. Treatment infusions will be administered at a constant rate of 0.5 mg/kg BW/hour, resulting in a total IV infusion duration of 12 hours per day, for a total daily dose of 6 mg/kg BW DNV3837. Infusions will be administered once daily for 10 consecutive days.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Part 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>30 subjects with severe CDI will be enrolled and randomized in a 2:1 ratio to receive DNV3837 or standard of care. Treatment infusions will be administered at a constant rate of 0.5 mg/kg BW/hour, resulting in a total IV infusion duration of 12 hours per day, for a total daily dose of 6 mg/kg BW DNV3837. Infusions will be administered once daily for 10 consecutive days</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>DNV3837</intervention_name>
    <description>Treatment infusions will be administered at a constant rate of 0.5 mg/kg BW/hour, resulting in a total IV infusion duration of 12 hours per day, for a total daily dose of 6 mg/kg BW DNV3837. Infusions will be administered once daily for 10 consecutive days.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Part 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Part 2</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Standard of Care</intervention_name>
    <description>Standard of care will be administered at the discretion of the Investigator. All regimens according to current guidelines (Infectious Diseases Society of America/Society for Healthcare Epidemiology of America and European Society of Clinical Microbiology and Infectious Diseases guidance on CDI) and bezlotoxumab are acceptable.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Part 2</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        POPULATION:

        Inclusion Criteria:

        Subjects must meet all of the following inclusion criteria to be enrolled in the study:

          1. The subject or a legally authorized representative must sign informed consent;

          2. The subject must be 18 years of age;

          3. Subjects must have a diagnosis of CDI defined as follows:

               1. Diarrhea, defined as a change in bowel habits, with &gt; 3 liquid stools or unformed
                  bowel movements (UBMs) [Bristol Stool Scale 6 or 7] or &gt; 200 mL unformed stool
                  for subjects having rectal collection devices in the 24 hours prior to start of
                  study drug; AND

               2. The subject has the following positive tests on a stool sample produced within 72
                  hours prior to the start of study drug as determined by:

                    -  A positive C. difficile glutamate dehydrogenase (GDH) test by a Food and
                       Drug Administration (FDA)-cleared enzyme immunoassay (EIA); AND

                    -  A positive toxin test (presence of either C. difficile Toxin A [TcdA] and/or
                       C. difficile Toxin B [TcdB]) by an FDA-cleared EIA; OR

                    -  A positive toxin gene test (presence of either C. difficile Toxin A gene
                       [tcdA] and/or C. difficile Toxin B gene [tcdB]) by an FDA-cleared nucleic
                       acid amplification test; OR

                    -  A positive cell cytotoxicity neutralization assay; OR

                    -  positive toxigenic culture;

          4. Subjects with a diagnosis of non-severe CDI must have a white blood cell (WBC) count
             ≤15,000 cells/µL (15 × 10^9 cells/L) and serum creatinine &lt;1.5 mg/dL;

          5. Subjects with a diagnosis of severe CDI must have any of the following criteria:

             a. Criterion 1

             i. WBC count &gt;15,000 cells/µL (15 x 10^9 cells/L); OR

             ii. Serum creatinine 1.5 mg/dL;

             b. Criterion 2

             i. Evidence of pseudomembranous colitis on endoscopy; OR

             ii. Colitis on computed tomography or magnetic resonance imaging scan or ultrasound;

             c. Criterion 3

             i. Severe abdominal pain, vomiting, ileus, temperature &gt;38.9°C, WBC count &gt;15,000
             cells/µL (15 x 10^9 cells/L), or albumin level &lt;2.5 g/dL in which CDI is strongly
             suspected and other non-CDI causes of infection have been ruled out;

          6. The subject has received no more than 24 hours of prior antimicrobial treatment for
             the current episode of CDI with oral/rectal vancomycin, IV/oral metronidazole, or oral
             fidaxomicin prior to Screening;

          7. Female subjects of non-childbearing potential must be either surgically sterile
             (hysterectomy, bilateral tubal ligation, salpingectomy, and/or bilateral oophorectomy
             at least 26 weeks before Screening) or post-menopausal, defined as spontaneous
             amenorrhea for at least 2 years, with follicle-stimulating hormone in the
             post-menopausal range at Screening, based on the central laboratory's ranges;

          8. Women of childbearing potential (ie, not post-menopausal or surgically sterilized)
             must have a negative urine and serum pregnancy test result before randomization.
             Participating women of childbearing potential must agree to use 1 highly effective
             method of contraception AND an acceptable barrier method (condom plus spermicide) OR 2
             highly effective methods of contraception throughout the duration of the study and for
             30 days following the last study drug administration. Highly effective methods of
             contraception that result in a low failure rate (ie, &lt;1% per year) when used
             consistently and correctly include the following:

               1. Combined (estrogen and progestogen containing) hormonal contraception associated
                  with inhibition of ovulation (oral, intravaginal, or transdermal),
                  progestogen-only hormonal contraception associated with inhibition of ovulation
                  (oral, injectable, or implantable), intrauterine device, or intrauterine
                  hormone-releasing system for at least 12 weeks before Screening;

               2. Bilateral tubal occlusion or vasectomized partner at least 26 weeks before
                  Screening;

               3. Sexual abstinence; NOTE: True abstinence, when in line with the preferred and
                  usual lifestyle of the subject, is considered a highly effective method only if
                  defined as refraining from heterosexual intercourse during the entire period of
                  risk associated with the study drug treatment. Periodic abstinence (eg, calendar,
                  ovulation, symptothermal, post ovulation methods) and withdrawal are not
                  acceptable methods of contraception;

          9. Male subjects must agree to abstain from sperm donation and use condoms with
             spermicide during sexual intercourse between Screening and at least 90 days after
             administration of the last dose of study drug. Male subjects must ensure non pregnant
             female partners of childbearing potential comply with the contraception requirements
             in Inclusion Criterion 8.

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Subjects will not be enrolled in the study if they meet any of the following exclusion
        criteria:

          1. The subject is likely to require surgical intervention (eg, subjects with fulminant
             CDI who fail to respond and progress to systemic toxicity, peritonitis, or toxic
             colonic dilatation and bowel perforation) and/or be switched to an already approved
             treatment regimen in the coming 48 hours due to a rapidly degrading condition;

          2. The subject displays evidence of acute renal impairment with a creatinine clearance of
             &lt;50 mL/min as measured by the Cockcroft Gault formula;

          3. The subject is receiving hemodialysis or continuous venous hemofiltration;

          4. The subject has ALT or AST serum levels &gt;3 × ULN, and total bilirubin serum
             concentration &gt;2 × ULN per the testing laboratory;

          5. The subject displays evidence of chronic hepatic impairment (Child-Pugh class B or C);

          6. The subject is pregnant or breastfeeding;

          7. The subject requires the ongoing use of anti-motility agents (eg, anti-diarrheals,
             anti peristaltics) or laxatives, unless approved by the Medical Monitor. Chronic and
             continued use of such products may be permitted during the study if bowel motility has
             stabilized;

          8. The subject requires the ongoing use of concomitant antibiotics to treat CDI (other
             than study drug) (eg, oral/rectal vancomycin, IV/oral metronidazole, oral fidaxomicin)
             or IV immunoglobulin;

          9. The subject has a known hypersensitivity or intolerance to DNV3837 or sorbitol;

         10. The subject has a history of active hepatitis B virus or hepatitis C virus that
             requires ongoing therapy, or human immunodeficiency virus with the most current
             cluster of differentiation 4 (CD4+) &lt;200 copies/mL;

         11. The subject has participated in other clinical research studies using an
             investigational antibacterial or non antibacterial agent within 1 month prior to
             Screening;

         12. The subject is unable or unwilling, in the judgment of the Investigator, to comply
             with the protocol; or

         13. The subject is an employee of the Investigator, study site, Sponsor, or contract
             research organization with direct involvement in the proposed study or other studies
             under the direction of the Investigator, study site, or Sponsor, or a family member of
             the site employee or the Investigator.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Georges Gaudriault</last_name>
    <phone>+33 4 48 19 01 24</phone>
    <email>georges.gaudriault@deinove.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Pinnacle Research Group</name>
      <address>
        <city>Anniston</city>
        <state>Alabama</state>
        <zip>36207</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Pankaj Kashyap</last_name>
      <phone>256-236-0055</phone>
      <email>pkashyap@pinnacletrials.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Phoenix VA Healthcare</name>
      <address>
        <city>Phoenix</city>
        <state>Arizona</state>
        <zip>85012</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Negin Blattman</last_name>
      <email>Negin.Blattman2@va.gov</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of California (UC) Davis Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sacramento</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>95817</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Cohen Stuart, MD</last_name>
      <phone>916-734-5176</phone>
      <email>stcohen@ucdavis.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Snake River Research, PLLC</name>
      <address>
        <city>Idaho Falls</city>
        <state>Idaho</state>
        <zip>83404</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Richard Nathan</last_name>
      <phone>208-535-8404</phone>
      <email>rnathan@snakerr.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Chicago</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chicago</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60637</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Kathleen Mullane</last_name>
      <phone>773-702-3756</phone>
      <email>kmullane@medicine.bsd.uchicago.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Infectious Disease Consultants (IDC) Clinical Research</name>
      <address>
        <city>Wichita</city>
        <state>Kansas</state>
        <zip>67214</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Maha Assi</last_name>
      <phone>316-264-3505</phone>
      <email>massi@idckansas.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Temple University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19140</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Frank Friedenberg</last_name>
      <phone>215-707-9900</phone>
      <email>frank.friedenberg@tuhs.temple.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>MD Anderson Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Pablo Okhuysen</last_name>
      <phone>713-745-6794</phone>
      <email>PCOkhuysen@mdanderson.org</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Southern Star Research Institute, LLC.</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Antonio</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>78229</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jeff Bullock</last_name>
      <phone>210-271-0606</phone>
      <email>js_bull@yahoo.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Utah</name>
      <address>
        <city>Salt Lake City</city>
        <state>Utah</state>
        <zip>84112</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jessica Johnson</last_name>
      <phone>801-585-9155</phone>
      <email>Jessica.johnson@hsc.utah.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 12, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 13, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 18, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 15, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 15, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 17, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Clostridium Infections</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

