<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03987165</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>1043190</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03987165</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Effect of Music Therapy on Newborns</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Effect of Music Therapy on Newborns</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Tulane University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Tulane University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The clinical study is evaluating the impact of music therapy on neonates, specifically
      infants with neonatal opioid withdrawal syndrome (NOWS). The goal is to study the effect of
      music therapy on an infant's behavioral (i.e feeding patterns, sleep patterns, severity of
      withdrawal) and physiological systems (i.e. heart rate, respiratory rate). The investigators
      are also studying the impact of music therapy on the infant's utilization of resources (i.e.
      total opioid usage and total length of stay).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The research will be carried out at the Tulane Lakeside Hospital for Women and Children.
      Caregivers of eligible infants will be approached by the medical team during the infants stay
      at the hospital and asked if they would be willing to hear more about this study. Fliers will
      be provided and also posted so that pregnant mothers or mothers who see the flier can also
      find out more about the study and decide to participate. Mothers may contact the study
      directly. Alternatively the medical team will ask the caregiver if the research team can
      contact them to set up a time to talk to them about the study. If the caregiver agrees then
      the contact information for the caregiver will be provided to the research team who will
      schedule an in person meeting to go over the protocol and obtain consent. The PI or one of
      the research team will meet with the infant's parent/legal guardian, review the study
      explaining all music therapy methods that will be used, explain the risks and benefits of
      participation, answer all questions and ask for consent to allow infant to participate in the
      study, to allow researchers to audio-video record the music therapy session, and to allow
      researchers to review medical records of the parent/legal guardian and infant to obtain
      information for the Data Collection Form regarding the infant's gestational age, race,
      ethnicity, gender, diagnosis, pregnancy and delivery complications, results of the any
      laboratory work, infant medication history, and daily Finnegan Scores over a 2-week period,
      or until infant's medical discharge. Infants will still be able to participate in the study
      if the caregiver does not consent to audio-visual recording.

      After informed consent has been obtained, the parent/legal guardian will complete the
      following questionnaires and surveys: Adverse Childhood Experiences Scale (ACE), Duke
      Functional Support System Questionnaire (FSSQ), Edinburgh Depression Scale (EDS), Postpartum
      Bonding Questionnaire (PBQ), Prenatal Life Events Scale (PLES Revised), Parental Bonding
      Instrument (PBI), Parenting Stress Index (PSI), Maternal Postpartum Attachment Scale (MPAS),
      Infant Behavior Questionnaire (IBQ) and a brief survey about their perceptions and mood
      surrounding music therapy. If the parent/legal guardian is present for any or all of the
      music therapy sessions, they will also be asked to complete a brief survey before and after
      music therapy sessions. The parent/legal guardian does not have to be present, but can be
      present for all music sessions.

      Music therapy interventions will take place over the course of five days. The anticipated
      length of stay in the hospital for infants with NOWS or iatrogenic exposure to opioids is 21
      days and for healthy full term infants is two to three days; however per institutional
      protocol, infants exposed to long-acting opioids in utero could be monitored up to 72-96
      hours prior to discharge to monitor for signs of withdrawal. The investigators will continue
      study procedures until completion of the music therapy treatment schedule, or until infant's
      discharge from the hospital if infant is discharged before completing all music therapy
      sessions. The investigators will not interfere with standard medical care and therefore
      recognize that infants without NOWS will receive less days of music therapy in general,
      however the consistent daily administration of music therapy will provide some ability.

      This study will use a cross-over design with participants undergoing music therapy once daily
      (either morning or afternoon) using a Song of Kin, defined as a familiar song used to lull
      the infant to sleep. If Song of Kin is not provided, the default lullaby will be &quot;Twinkle
      Twinkle Little Star.&quot; In addition, there will be sessions of standard nursing care with no
      treatment intervention (CON). Counterbalancing will be achieved by assigning a different
      order of presentation of conditions for each group. Each day, infants will receive a music
      therapy session lasting up to 20 minutes using the above mentioned technique. The music
      therapy session will be in the morning or afternoon depending upon which treatment group the
      participant is assigned to. There will not be any visits by the music therapist during
      sessions that the infant is to receive standard nursing care with no treatment intervention
      (morning/afternoon). Over the 5 day period (all week, including weekends) participants will
      experience conditions in the following order (with music therapy sessions designated as &quot;MT&quot;
      and control data only designated as &quot;C&quot;):

      Condition A:

      Day 1 (AM - music therapy, PM - control) Day 2 (AM - control, PM - music therapy) Day 3 (AM -
      music therapy, PM - control) Day 4 (AM - control, PM - music therapy) Day 5 (AM - music
      therapy, PM - control)

      Condition B:

      Day 1 (AM - control, PM - music therapy) Day 2 (AM - music therapy, PM - control) Day 3 (AM -
      control, PM - music therapy) Day 4 (AM - music therapy, PM - control) Day 5 (AM - control, PM
      - music therapy)

      The medical team will complete the Finnegan Neonatal Abstinence Scoring Tool (FNAST) for each
      infant with NOWS or suspected to have NOWS following unit policy. Finnegan scales will not be
      collected on newborns who are not thought to have NOWS. Data related to the NOWS symptoms and
      medical conditions will be obtained from medical records. Additional observational data
      before and after the music sessions will be collected by the research assistant, including
      descriptions of where the session is conducted (isolette/bassinette), activity level, vital
      signs, sleep/wake pattern, sucking pattern, and any other observed behaviors throughout the
      session.

      The following research materials and data collection tools are submitted with this IRB
      package: Data Collection Form and Key, Medical Abstraction Form, Music Therapy Session Notes,
      Support System Questionnaire (FSSQ), Edinburgh Depression Scale (EDS), Postpartum Bonding
      Questionnaire (PBQ), Prenatal Life Events Scale (PLES Revised), Adverse Childhood Experiences
      (ACE) Scale, Duke Functional Support System Questionnaire (FSSQ), Parental Bonding Instrument
      (PBI), Parenting Stress Index (PSI), Maternal Postpartum Attachment Scale (MPAS), Infant
      Behavior Questionnaire (IBQ) and Research Code Identification Sheet.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">December 10, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 31, 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 31, 2024</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>cross over design with each baby serving as its own control</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Heart Rate</measure>
    <time_frame>Change in average heart rate over the 20 minute sessions (both control and music therapy)</time_frame>
    <description>Infant's heart rate before, during and after music therapy and during the control session.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Sleeping Patterns</measure>
    <time_frame>Change in phase of sleep over the 20 minute sessions (both control and music therapy)</time_frame>
    <description>Basic parameters of sleeping - Type of sleep during control and intervention periods, including but not limited to, active/alert, quiet alert, sleeping. We will monitor time from end of feeding to start of sleep.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Feeding Patterns</measure>
    <time_frame>Time from feeding to onset of sleep over the 20 minute session (both control and music therapy)</time_frame>
    <description>Time between the end of feeding and the onset of sleeping, with music therapy to be conducted during feeding.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Morphine Utilization</measure>
    <time_frame>From day of birth through day of discharge, up to 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Total cumulative dosage of morphine required during the infant's hospitalization as well as the total number of days on morphine. We will also determine the day of the maximum morphine dosage required by the infant.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Total Length of Stay</measure>
    <time_frame>From day of birth through day of discharge, up to 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>The total number of days the infant was hospitalized, from day of birth to day of discharge from the NICU</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Severity of Withdrawal Symptoms</measure>
    <time_frame>Through day 30 of treatment with oral opioids</time_frame>
    <description>Severity of neonatal withdrawal symptoms as determined by their Finnegan Neonatal Abstinence Scoring Tool (FNAST) scores. This standardized scale is a measure of symptoms of opioid withdrawal experienced by infants with NOWS and scored on a scale from 0 (no symptoms) to 41 (maximum symptoms).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">300</enrollment>
  <condition>Neonatal Abstinence Syndrome</condition>
  <condition>Substance Withdrawal, Neonatal</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Music Therapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Music therapy by a certified music therapist will be delivered to infants over a period of 5 days. There will be two periods of data collection each day, one in the morning and one in the afternoon. Each baby will receive music therapy during one of these time points, with each baby serving as their own control during the second timepoint.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Music Therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>Music therapy will be conducted once daily using a Song of Kin, a familiar song used to lull the infant to sleep. If no Song of Kin is provided, &quot;Twinkle Twinkle Little Star&quot; will be the default lullaby.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Music Therapy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Admitted to the NICU or newborn nursery

          2. Gestational age 28 weeks or older

          3. No identified hearing disorder

          4. Do not have a diagnosed developmental disability (i.e. Down Syndrome)

          5. Do not have Fetal Alcohol Syndrome

          6. Medically cleared to participate in the study

          7. Parent or legal guardian able/willing to give consent &amp; complete surveys.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Gestational age &lt; 28 weeks old

          2. Has an identified hearing disorder

          3. Has diagnosed developmental disability (i.e. Down syndrome)

          4. Has Fetal Alcohol Syndrome

          5. Is not medically cleared to participate in the study

          6. Parent or legal guardian unable/unwilling to give consent
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>1 Month</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Meghan P Howell, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Tulane University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Meghan P Howell, MD</last_name>
    <phone>504-988-2453</phone>
    <email>mhowell2@tulane.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Stacy S Drury, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>504-988-1438</phone>
    <email>sdrury@tulane.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Tulane Lakeside Hospital - Tulane University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Metairie</city>
        <state>Louisiana</state>
        <zip>70001</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Meghan P Howell, MD</last_name>
      <phone>504-988-2453</phone>
      <email>mhowell2@tulane.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Stacy S Drury, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>504-988-1438</phone>
      <email>sdrury@tulane.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 6, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 13, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 14, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 13, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 13, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 14, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Tulane University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Meghan Howell</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Neonatal Opioid Withdrawal Syndrome</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Neonatal Abstinence Syndrome</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

