<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03989440</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>RNX-AX204-101</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03989440</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>AXER-204 in Participants With Chronic Spinal Cord Injury</brief_title>
  <acronym>RESET</acronym>
  <official_title>A Multicenter, Two Part Study to Evaluate the Safety, Tolerability, Pharmacokinetics, and Efficacy of AXER-204 in Subjects With Chronic Spinal Cord Injury</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>ReNetX Bio, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>ReNetX Bio, Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This two-part trial will assess the safety, tolerability, pharmacokinetics, and efficacy of
      AXER-204 administered by lumbar puncture and slow bolus infusion. Part 1 will evaluate the
      safety, tolerability, and pharmacokinetics of single ascending doses of AXER-204. Part 2 will
      evaluate the safety, tolerability, pharmacokinetics, and efficacy of repeated doses AXER-204
      in comparison to placebo.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      AXER-204 is a human fusion protein that acts as a soluble decoy/trap for the
      myelin-associated inhibitors of axonal growth known as Nogo-A, MAG, and OMgp. AXER-204 and a
      surrogate protein used in early preclinical studies have been found to promote axon growth
      and recovery of function in animal models of spinal cord injury.

      Part 1 of the trial is a multicenter, open-label, single ascending dose study in participants
      with chronic cervical spinal cord injury. Four cohorts of 6 participants each are planned,
      with participants within each cohort expected to receive the same dose of AXER-204.

      Part 2 is a multicenter, randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled, repeat dose study in
      chronic cervical spinal cord injury participants. Up to 42 participants will be randomized
      (ratio 1:1) to receive repeated doses of AXER-204 or placebo (a phosphate buffered saline
      formulation). The dose level and dose frequency will be dependent upon outcomes from Part 1.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 16, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Part 1 is open-label single-ascending dose. Part 2 is double-blind, placebo-controlled, repeat dose.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>Part 1 - None; Part 2 - Quadruple</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of treatment-emergent Adverse Events (AEs) and Serious Adverse Events (SAEs)</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 Post-dose to 28-days after last dose</time_frame>
    <description>An AE is any untoward medical occurrence in a patient or clinical investigation participant administered a pharmaceutical product and that does not necessarily have a causal relationship with this treatment. An AE can therefore be any unfavorable and unintended sign (including an abnormal laboratory finding), symptom, or disease temporally associated with the use of a medicinal (investigational) product, whether or not related to the medicinal (investigational) product. An SAE is any untoward medical occurrence that at any dose results in death, is a life-threatening event, requires inpatient hospitalization or prolongation of existing hospitalization, results in a significant disability/incapacity or congenital anomaly, or is a medically important event.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Area Under the Concentration-Time Curve From Time 0 to Time of the Last Measurable Concentration (AUClast) of AXER-204</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 pre-dose up to Day 29</time_frame>
    <description>AXER-204 will be measured in cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) and in serum</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in International Standards for Neurological Classification of SCI (ISNCSCI) Upper Extremity Motor Score (UEMS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Screening to Day 169 or 28 days after last dose and 6 months after last dose</time_frame>
    <description>The ISNCSCI scale includes a Motor and Sensory examination for each side of the body (left/right). The Sensory examination involves 'light touch' and 'pinprick' for each dermatome (28) on both sides of the body (total 56). A score of 0, 1 or 2 can be given to each dermatome resulting in a total max. of 112 points. The Motor level is determined by examining the muscle function within each of the 10 myotomes on each side of the body (20 myotomes in total). A score ranging from 1 to 5 can be given to each myotome tested resulting in a maximum score of 100 (50 for upper extremity and 50 for lower extremity). Higher values indicate better function with the maximum scores corresponding to normal function.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in International Standards for Neurological Classification of SCI (ISNCSCI) motor and sensory scores</measure>
    <time_frame>Screening to Day 169 or 28 days after last dose and 6 months after last dose</time_frame>
    <description>The ISNCSCI scale includes a Motor and Sensory examination for each side of the body (left/right). The Sensory examination involves 'light touch' and 'pinprick' for each dermatome (28) on both sides of the body (total 56). A score of 0, 1 or 2 can be given to each dermatome resulting in a total max. of 112 points. The Motor level is determined by examining the muscle function within each of the 10 myotomes on each side of the body (20 myotomes in total). A score ranging from 1 to 5 can be given to each myotome tested resulting in a maximum score of 100 (50 for upper extremity and 50 for lower extremity). Higher values indicate better function with the maximum scores corresponding to normal function.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Graded Redefined Assessment of Strength, Sensation and Prehension (GRASSP) scores</measure>
    <time_frame>Screening to Day 169 or 28 days after last dose and 6 months after last dose</time_frame>
    <description>The GRASSP is a clinical impairment measure for the upper limb for use after tetraplegia. The measure includes domains which are important in describing hand function: Strength with scores from 0-50 for each side, Sensory testing with scores ranging from 0-12 for each hand, Prehension ability with scores 0-12 for each hand, and Prehension performance with scores from 0-30 for each hand. Higher subscores indicate better function.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in version III of the Spinal Cord Independence Measure (SCIM III) self-care and mobility domain scores</measure>
    <time_frame>Screening to Day 169 or 28 days after last dose and 6 months after last dose</time_frame>
    <description>The SCIM III is a questionnaire that assesses activities of daily living (ADL) regarding self-care, mobility, respiration, and sphincter management. The self-care and mobility domains have scores ranging from 0-20 and 0-40 respectively. Higher scores correspond to better ability to carry out ADL.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Capabilities of Upper Extremity Test (CUE-T) scores</measure>
    <time_frame>Screening to Day 169 or 28 days after last dose and 6 months after last dose</time_frame>
    <description>The CUE-T is a clinical impairment measure for upper limb use after tetraplegia. The test has 19 items (17 unilateral and tested separately for the right and left upper extremities; two bilateral items) that are scored on a five-point scale (0-4) using one of three scoring dimensions (number of times task is completed; amount of weight; amount of time). The total assessment has a possible range in scores from 0 to 144. Higher scores correspond to better function.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Capabilities of Upper Extremity Questionnaire (CUE-Q) scores</measure>
    <time_frame>Screening to Day 169 or 28 days after last dose and 6 months after last dose</time_frame>
    <description>The CUE-Q is a questionnaire to assess arm and hand function comprised of 17 questions with scores of 0-4 assigned to each side for each question resulting in a total score ranging from 0-136. A higher score corresponds to better function.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in SF - 36 v2 Health Survey scores</measure>
    <time_frame>Screening to Day 169 or 28 days after last dose and 6 months after last dose</time_frame>
    <description>The Short Form-36 is a 36-question, 8-domain survey designed to assess physical and emotional health. Raw scores can be converted to normalized values ranging from 0-100 for each domain. Each domain has a normal score of 50 with lower scores indicating progressively poorer health.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Neuro-QOL Item Bank v1.0 - Upper Extremity Function questionnaire scores</measure>
    <time_frame>Screening to Day 169 or 28 days after last dose and 6 months after last dose</time_frame>
    <description>The Neuro-Quality of Life Item Bank v1.0 - Upper Extremity Function questionnaire consists of 20 questions focused on activities of activities of daily living (ADL) requiring use of arms and hands. Scores for each question range from 1-5 resulting in a total maximum score of 100. A higher score corresponds to greater ability to conduct ADL.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Change in International Standards to document remaining Autonomic Function after Spinal Cord Injury (ISAFSCI) scores</measure>
    <time_frame>Screening to Day 169 or 28 days after last dose and 6 months after last dose</time_frame>
    <description>The ISAFSCI consists of patient reported responses on remaining autonomic function regarding regulation of heart rate, blood pressure, sweating, body temperature, breathing, urinary function, bowel function, and sexual function. Scores are assigned as 2=normal, 1=reduced or altered, 0=complete loss of control, or NT=unable to assess for each item.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">66</enrollment>
  <condition>Chronic Spinal Cord Injury</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>AXER-204</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Part 1 - Single ascending doses; Part 2 - Repeated dose</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Part 2 only - Repeated dose</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>AXER-204</intervention_name>
    <description>human NoGo Trap fusion protein</description>
    <arm_group_label>AXER-204</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>human NoGo Trap</other_name>
    <other_name>human Nogo Receptor decoy</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Phosphate buffered saline formulation</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Key Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Traumatic spinal cord injury that occurred ≥ 1 year ago

          2. Cervical spinal cord injury with serious neurologic deficit as evidenced by 1)
             bilateral ISNCSCI UEMS between 4 and 36 points inclusive, and 2) bilateral GRASSP
             Prehension Ability score between 4 and 17 points inclusive

          3. Confirmation by MRI of the following:

               1. Chronic SCI (persistent spinal cord lesion)

               2. For AIS grade of A without sensory or motor zone of partial preservation
                  extending at least two levels caudal to the level of injury, no apparent
                  transection of the cord

               3. CSF space spanning the lesion

        Key Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Penetrating injury to the cord or spinal cord trauma caused by ballistic injury
             including gunshot that did not penetrate the spinal cord

          2. History of stroke, cerebrovascular injury, or elevated intracranial pressure

          3. Contraindications for lumbar puncture

          4. Requiring mechanical ventilatory assistance of any type

          5. Body mass index (BMI) ≥ 35 kg/m2 or body weight &lt;50 kg

          6. History of life threatening allergic or immune-mediated reaction to vaccines, or
             biologic drugs, at any time or any life threatening allergic or immune-mediated
             reaction within the past 12 months

          7. Subjects fitted with an implanted pump or port for delivery of therapeutics to the CSF

          8. Uncontrolled medical condition including but not limited to cardiovascular disease,
             sleep apnea, obstructive lung disease, severe neuropathic or severe chronic pain,
             severe autonomic dysreflexia

          9. Participation in any other investigational drug or device trial within 30 days or
             within 5 half-lives of the investigational drug or any past participation in a SCI
             cellular therapy trial.

        Note: Other protocol defined Inclusion/Exclusion criteria may apply.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>ReNetX Bio</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>ReNetX Bio</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>George Maynard, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>1-203-208-8925</phone>
    <email>info@renetx.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Keck Medicine of USC</name>
      <address>
        <city>Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90033</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sandra Oviedo</last_name>
      <email>sandra.oviedo@med.usc.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Charles Liu, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Shepherd Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Atlanta</city>
        <state>Georgia</state>
        <zip>30309</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Casey Kandilakis, PT,DPT,NCS</last_name>
      <email>casey.kandilakis@shepherd.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Donald Leslie, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Shirley Ryan AbilityLab</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chicago</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60611</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Connie Casale</last_name>
      <phone>312-238-1522</phone>
      <email>ccasale@sralab.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>David Chen, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The Ohio State University Wexner Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Columbus</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>43210</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Amy Bartlett, BA, CCRC</last_name>
      <phone>614-366-9050</phone>
      <email>amy.bartlett@osumc.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jan Schwab, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Thomas Jefferson University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19107</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Marilyn Owens, RN, BSN</last_name>
      <phone>215-955-6579</phone>
      <email>marilyn.owens@jefferson.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ralph Marino, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 11, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 17, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 18, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 14, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 14, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 18, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>myelin-associated inhibitor</keyword>
  <keyword>Nogo-A</keyword>
  <keyword>MAG</keyword>
  <keyword>OMgp</keyword>
  <keyword>Nogo Receptor</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Spinal Cord Injuries</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Wounds and Injuries</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

