<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03987152</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>57911</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2016-002157-38</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03987152</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Treatment of Congenital Vascular Malformations Using Sirolimus: Improving Quality of Life</brief_title>
  <acronym>Sirolimus</acronym>
  <official_title>Treatment of Congenital Vascular Malformations Using Sirolimus: Improving Quality of Life</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Radboud University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Radboud University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Congenital vascular anomalies are uncommon and belong to the group of rare diseases.These
      vascular malformations can cause serious complications including obstruction of vital organs
      and their function, recurrent infection and significantly reduced quality of life of persons
      affected.Treatment options range from conservative to surgical extirpation or intralesional
      embolisation/sclerosis. Unfortunately, this is often not enough. Many patients still have
      complaints like severe pain and invalidation due to the lymphatic or venous malformation
      making a normal functional life impossible. Recent case reports mention the positive effects
      of refractory patients with Sirolimus. Sirolimus, also known as rapamycin, is currently the
      only FDA-approved mammalian target of rapamycin (mTOR) inhibitor.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Congenital vascular anomalies are uncommon and belong to the group of rare diseases. In 1996,
      the International Society of the Study of Vascular Anomalies adopted a new classification,
      distinguishing vascular malformations from vascular tumors. This classification was revised
      in 2014 and newly identified genetic features were taken into account. Vascular malformations
      feature dysplastic malformed vessels and are a consequence of a defective development of the
      embryonic vascular system. Vascular malformations can involve lymphatic vessels, capillaries,
      veins and arteries or even combinations. These vascular malformations are present at birth
      and grow with the child. Treatment options range from conservative to surgical extirpation or
      intralesional embolisation/sclerosis. Unfortunately, this is often not enough. Many patients
      still have complaints like severe pain and invalidation due to the lymphatic or venous
      malformation making a normal functional life impossible. These vascular malformations can
      cause serious complications including obstruction of vital organs and their function,
      recurrent infection and significantly reduced quality of life of persons affected. As the
      natural course of the disease affects multiple body systems, the therapeutic management is
      challenging. To date, no other medical treatment options are available. Although standard
      pain medication is given according the (inter) national pain protocols, patients still suffer
      pain and are not able to function normally in daily life. Majority (60-70% percent of the
      patients) of the patients is not able to have a normal life, with a normal job and normal
      social activities. Children are often not able to go to school normally, cannot play outside
      and have pain at the site of the malformation. The vast majority of literature reporting
      medical therapies for vascular anomalies consists of case reports and small series and is
      complicated by publication bias (negative findings are often not published), inconsistent use
      of nomenclature, and the absence of clinical trials. Recent case reports mention the positive
      effects of refractory patients with Sirolimus. Sirolimus, also known as rapamycin, is
      currently the only FDA-approved mammalian target of rapamycin (mTOR) inhibitor, indicated for
      prevention of kidney allograft rejection in adults and children 13 years or older, but is
      commonly used to manage organ rejection in younger children.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 18, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 1, 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 18, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Sequential Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Challenge-Dechallenge-Rechallenge design All patients receive Sirolimus during challenge phase (6 months), stop Sirolimus during dechallenge phase (12 months), and if pain/symptoms returns Sirolimus intake is restarted during the rechallenge phase.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of life using Sirolimus measured with survey (TAPQOL)</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline Quality of life at 6 months QoL in challenge phase, and 12 months QoL in Rechallenge phase.</time_frame>
    <description>Quality of life: Questionnaire for Preschool Children's Health-Related Quality of Life (TAPQOL). Preschool Children Quality of Life, parent-reported questionnaire clustered into 12 multi-item scales, with higher scores range 0-100) indicating better HRQOL)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of life using Sirolimus measured with survey (PedsQl)</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline Quality of life at 6 months QoL in challenge phase, and 12 months QoL in Rechallenge phase.</time_frame>
    <description>Quality of life: Pediatric Quality of Life Inventory (PedsQl) (children) 23 items questionnaire, 0-100 scale, so that higher scores indicate better HRQOL (Health-Related Quality of Life). Psychosocial Health Summary Score, Physical Health Summary Score and Total score will be measured.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of life using Sirolimus measured with survey (Research and development Rand-36).</measure>
    <time_frame>hange from baseline Quality of life at 6 months QoL in challenge phase, and 12 months QoL in Rechallenge phase</time_frame>
    <description>Quality of life: Rand-36 (adults) eight health domains; physical functioning, social functioning, role limitations due to physical health problems, role limitations due to emotional problems, mental health, vitality, pain and general health perception. Outcomes at each domain will be defined on a scale from a minimum score of 0 to a maximum score of 100. A higher score is equivalent to a better health.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference in pain scores after using Sirolimus measured with VAS score</measure>
    <time_frame>Daily pain scores will be compared after 6 months in Challenge phase, after Challenge phase: starts the phase, and pain during 12 months in the Rechallenge phase</time_frame>
    <description>Daily pain score (daily visual analogue scale (VAS-score 0-10) for children, and numeric rating scale (NRS-score 0-10) for adults)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference in pain scores after using Sirolimus measured with NRS score</measure>
    <time_frame>Daily pain scores will be compared after 6 months in Challenge phase, after Challenge phase: starts the phase without Sirolimus treatment, and pain during 12 months in the Rechallenge phase</time_frame>
    <description>Daily pain score (daily numeric rating scale (NRS-score 0 no pain -10 extreme pain) for adults)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Return of pain after treatment and duration of lowered pain or pain free period in days</measure>
    <time_frame>After 6 months Sirolimus intake till one year follow up.</time_frame>
    <description>Amount of patients who have lowered pain or are pain free. Duration of lowered pain or pain free period in days.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Growth/progression of vascular malformation</measure>
    <time_frame>MRI baseline compared with MRI after 6 months in challenge phase and 12 months in rechallenge phase</time_frame>
    <description>MRI of the vascular malformation will be made at the beginning of the study and after six months of treatment with Sirolimus. An experienced radiologist will evaluate the evolution of the volume of the malformation.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate and occurence of adverse events related to Sirolimus</measure>
    <time_frame>4 years</time_frame>
    <description>Adverse events: short and long term consequences of treatment with Sirolimus according to CTCAE version 5.0.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Severity of adverse events related to Sirolimus</measure>
    <time_frame>4 years</time_frame>
    <description>Adverse events: short and long term consequences of treatment with Sirolimus according to CTCAE version 5.0.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Genetic mutations in the vascular malformation that can predict outcome of treatment with Sirolimus using Single Molecule Molecular Inversion Probes (smMIPs)</measure>
    <time_frame>4 years</time_frame>
    <description>Secondary material that was obtained after surgery, stored in the HECOVAN biobank can be used for analyses. Comprehensive targeted Next Generation Sequencing screen using Unique Molecular Identifiers with a technical sensitivity of 1% mutant alleles was performed for frequently mutated positions using Single Molecule Molecular Inversion Probes. We will investigate if there is a correlation with a possible found mutation and painreduction or improvement of quality of life.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacogenetic profile in the vascular malformation that can predict outcome of treatment with Sirolimus</measure>
    <time_frame>4 years</time_frame>
    <description>Genotyping will be performed using Taqman assays or Kompetitive Allele Specific PCR (KASPTM) assays in saliva swabs. Pharmacogenetic profiles (slow, intermediate, and extensive metabolizer) will be determined. Subjects compared on the outcome of sirolimus effectiveness for pain, and QoL stratified by CYP3A4.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cost-effectiveness of administration of Sirolimus: Quality Adjusted Life Year (QALY) estimate for each patient</measure>
    <time_frame>4 years</time_frame>
    <description>Via standardized questionnaires developed by the iMTA (institute for Medical Technology Assessment). The second part of the cost analysis consists of determining the cost prices for each volume of consumption.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">75</enrollment>
  <condition>Vascular Malformations</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sirolimus</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Sirolimus administration: during Challenge and Rechallenge phase. Compared with the period 2 months before start of Sirolimus.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sirolimus</intervention_name>
    <description>Daily intake of Sirolimus during Challenge and Rechallenge phase</description>
    <arm_group_label>Sirolimus</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>No other treatment</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Diagnosis of Congenital venous malformation, or lymphatic malformation or combined.

          -  Age older than 1 yr.

          -  Patients (or legal guardians for children) have to be able to sign the informed
             consent

          -  Patients are either refractory to standard care such as medical treatment (low
             molecular weight heparins, pain medication etc.), surgical resection and/or
             sclerotherapy/embolization (ineffective or accompanied by major complications) or
             there is no possibility for surgical intervention anymore. Only patients that have a
             normal clinical screening (no signs for infection, normal bone marrow function, normal
             liver and kidney function, normal glucose metabolism etc.) can be included.

          -  Patients included have no cardiac impairment

          -  Patients have no gastrointestinal impairment as Sirolimus is absorbed
             gastro-intestinal and normal function is needed

          -  No other underlying medical disorder like Down syndrome or other syndromes

          -  Women of reproductive age have to be informed that contraceptive methods are

          -  mandatory during the study time, pregnant women are excluded

          -  Karnofsky score &gt; 50

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  No written informed consent

          -  Known hypersensitivity to drugs or metabolites from similar classes as study
             treatment.

          -  Patient has other concurrent severe and /or uncontrolled medical condition that would,
             in the investigator's judgment, contraindicated participation in the clinical study
             (e.g. acute or chronic pancreatitis, liver cirrhosis, active chronic hepatitis,
             severely impaired lung function with a spirometry ≤ 50% of the normal predicted value
             and/or O2 saturation ≤ 88% at rest, etc.)

          -  Recent history of primary malignancy ≤ 5 years

          -  Impaired cardiac function or clinically significant cardiac diseases

          -  Immunocompromised patients, including known seropositivity for HIV

          -  Patient with any other concurrent severe and /or uncontrolled medical condition that
             would,in the investigator's judgment, contraindicated participation in the clinical
             study.

          -  Pregnant or lactating women

          -  Karnofsky score &lt; 50
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>1 Year</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Maroeska Loo, te, Dr.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Radboud University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Maroeska Loo, te, Dr.</last_name>
    <phone>+31243613131</phone>
    <email>Maroeska.teLoo@radboudumc.nl</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Veroniek Harbers, Drs.</last_name>
    <phone>+31243094374</phone>
    <email>Veroniek.Harbers@radboudumc.nl</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Radboudumc, HECOVAN workgroup</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nijmegen</city>
        <state>Gelderland</state>
        <zip>6500HB</zip>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Maroeska te Loo, Dr.</last_name>
      <phone>+312413131</phone>
      <email>Maroeska.teLoo@radboudumc.nl</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Veroniek Harbers, Drs.</last_name>
      <email>veroniek.harbers@radboudumc.nl</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Maroeksa Loo, te, Dr.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Leo Schultze Kool, Prof. dr.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Carine Vleuten, van der, Dr.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Bas Verhoeven, Drs.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Gerard Rongen, Prof. dr.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Peter Laat, de, Dr.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Chantal Horst, van der, Prof. dr.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Netherlands</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 1, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 13, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 14, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 13, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 13, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 14, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Sirolimus</keyword>
  <keyword>mTor inhibitor</keyword>
  <keyword>Quality of life</keyword>
  <keyword>mammalian target of rapamycin (mTOR)</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Vascular Malformations</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Congenital Abnormalities</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Sirolimus</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

