<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03984214</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>AGMT_DISCOVER</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03984214</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Efficacy and Safety of Dronabinol in the Improvement of Chemotherapy-induced and Tumor-related Symptoms in Advanced Pancreatic Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>Multicenter, Randomized, Double-blind, Placebo-controlled, Phase III Clinical Trial to Investigate the Efficacy and Safety of Dronabinol in the Improvement of ChemOthErapy-induced and Tumor-Related Symptoms in Patients With Locally Advanced or Metastatic Pancreatic Cancer During First-line Chemotherapy (DIsCOvER)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Arbeitsgemeinschaft medikamentoese Tumortherapie</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Medical University of Graz</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Unidata Geodesign</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Bionorica SE</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Arbeitsgemeinschaft medikamentoese Tumortherapie</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Aim of this phase III trial is to investigate the efficacy and safety of dronabinol (orally
      administered tetrahydrocannabinol (THC)) as adjuvant therapy to first-line standard
      chemotherapy in patients with metastatic pancreatic cancer for improvement of chemotherapy-
      and tumor-related symptoms applicated by individual titration up to the maximum tolerated
      dose.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Patients with pancreatic cancer suffer from multiple symptoms related to the tumor itself or
      induced by the chemotherapy. The available supportive therapy is still not able to relief all
      symptoms that are caused by the malignancy itself as well as by the antineoplastic therapy.

      Additionally, anorexia and weight loss, that often result in increased morbidity and
      mortality in this patient population as well as in psycho-social burden and suffering in
      patients and their relatives, are unmet needs in pancreatic cancer patients.

      Therapeutic approaches focus on treating the malignancy itself, additional nutritional
      support and physical examination might prevent patients from further side effects such as
      sarcopenia.

      During the last decades a number of appetite-modulating drugs have been under clinical
      investigation. A number of studies focused on the endocannabinoid system, which is involved
      amongst others in appetite-modulating, antiemetic, analgesic and anti-inflammatory processes.

      As dronabinol is already used as magistral formulation, its beneficial effect has often been
      observed in these patients in the clinical routine, especially in patients with
      therapy-refractory nausea and emesis. Due to its broad efficacy it might be of benefit for
      patients suffering from malignancy. Thus, investigators want to evaluate the efficacy of
      dronabinol in the improvement of chemotherapy-induced and tumor-related symptoms in advanced
      pancreatic patients during systemic first-line chemotherapy. However, data on optimal dosage
      are conflicting yet.

      In detail, investigators want to study whether dronabinol has a positive influence on quality
      of life and whether symptoms caused by the tumor or by the chemotherapy itself might be
      palliated by dronabinol. Beneficial and potential harmful side effects and the personal
      perception of advanced pancreatic cancer patients will be documented.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">December 16, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Standardized area under the curve of the European Organisation for Research and Treatment of Cancer (EORTC) quality of life questionnaire (QLQ)-C30 symptom summary score over the on-treatment period.</measure>
    <time_frame>Prior to treatment start until end of 16 weeks maintenance treatment</time_frame>
    <description>The EORTC-QLQ-C30 is an integrated system for assessing the health-related quality of life (QoL) of cancer patients participating in international clinical trials.
The validated QLQ-C30 summary score is calculated as mean score of the 13 of the 15 EORTC QLQ-C30 scales (v3.0), based on 27 of 30 items (the Financial Impact scale and Quality of Life score are not included). A high score for a symptom scale / item (fatigue, nausea and vomiting, pain, dyspnoea, insomnia, appetite loss, constipation, diarrhoea) represents a high level of symptomatology / problems. A high score for a functional scale (physical functioning, role functioning, cognitive functioning, emotional functioning, social functioning) represents a high / healthy level of functioning. Scores for individual items: &quot;Not at All&quot; = 1 point, &quot;A Little&quot; = 2 points, &quot;Quite a Bit&quot; = 3 points, &quot;Very Much&quot; = 4 points.
A linear transformation is used to standardize the raw score, so that overall scores range from 0 to 100.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Standardized area under the curve of the European Organisation for Research and Treatment of Cancer (EORTC) quality of life questionnaire (QLQ)-C30 symptom summary score over the maintenance period</measure>
    <time_frame>After 4 weeks of treatment until week 16</time_frame>
    <description>The European Organisation for Research and Treatment of Cancer (EORTC) quality of life questionnaire (QLQ) is an integrated system for assessing the health-related quality of life (QoL) of cancer patients participating in international clinical trials.
The validated QLQ-C30 summary score is calculated as mean score of items. A high score for a symptom scale / item (fatigue, nausea and vomiting, pain, dyspnoea, insomnia, appetite loss, constipation, diarrhoea) represents a high level of symptomatology / problems.
Scores for individual items: &quot;Not at All&quot; = 1 point, &quot;A Little&quot; = 2 points, &quot;Quite a Bit&quot; = 3 points, &quot;Very Much&quot; = 4 points. A linear transformation is used to standardize the raw score, so that overall scores range from 0 to 100.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of European Organisation for Research and Treatment of Cancer (EORTC) quality of life questionnaire (QLQ)-C30 symptom summary score from baseline to summary score over the maintenance period</measure>
    <time_frame>From treatment start until week 16</time_frame>
    <description>The European Organisation for Research and Treatment of Cancer (EORTC) quality of life questionnaire (QLQ) is an integrated system for assessing the health-related quality of life (QoL) of cancer patients participating in international clinical trials.
The validated QLQ-C30 summary score is calculated as mean score of items. A high score for a symptom scale / item (fatigue, nausea and vomiting, pain, dyspnoea, insomnia, appetite loss, constipation, diarrhoea) represents a high level of symptomatology / problems.
Scores for individual items: &quot;Not at All&quot; = 1 point, &quot;A Little&quot; = 2 points, &quot;Quite a Bit&quot; = 3 points, &quot;Very Much&quot; = 4 points. A linear transformation is used to standardize the raw score, so that overall scores range from 0 to 100.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Symptom scales of European Organisation for Research and Treatment of Cancer (EORTC) quality of life questionnaire (QLQ)-C30</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline and 2-weekly until end of treatment at week 18</time_frame>
    <description>A high score for a symptom scale / item (fatigue, nausea and vomiting, pain, dyspnoea, insomnia, appetite loss, constipation, diarrhoea) represents a high level of symptomatology / problems.
Scores for individual items: &quot;Not at All&quot; = 1 point, &quot;A Little&quot; = 2 points, &quot;Quite a Bit&quot; = 3 points, &quot;Very Much&quot; = 4 points. A linear transformation is used to standardize the raw score, so that overall scores range from 0 to 100.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Global quality of life of the European Organisation for Research and Treatment of Cancer (EORTC) quality of life questionnaire (QLQ)-C30</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline and 2-weekly until end of treatment at week 18</time_frame>
    <description>The European Organisation for Research and Treatment of Cancer (EORTC) quality of life questionnaire (QLQ) is an integrated system for assessing the health-related quality of life (QoL) of cancer patients participating in international clinical trials.
The validated QLQ-C30 summary score is calculated as mean score of items. A high score for the global health status (overall health during the past week) and global QoL (overall quality of life during the past week) represents a high QoL.
Scores: 1 - 7, 1 = very poor and 7 = excellent. A linear transformation is used to standardize the raw score, so that overall scores range from 0 to 100.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Functional scales of the European Organisation for Research and Treatment of Cancer (EORTC) quality of life questionnaire (QLQ)-C30</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline and 2-weekly until end of treatment at week 18</time_frame>
    <description>The European Organisation for Research and Treatment of Cancer (EORTC) quality of life questionnaire (QLQ) is an integrated system for assessing the health-related quality of life (QoL) of cancer patients participating in international clinical trials. A high score for a functional scale (physical functioning, role functioning, cognitive functioning, emotional functioning, social functioning) represents a high / healthy level of functioning.
Scores for individual items: &quot;Not at All&quot; = 1 point, &quot;A Little&quot; = 2 points, &quot;Quite a Bit&quot; = 3 points, &quot;Very Much&quot; = 4 points.
A linear transformation is used to standardize the raw score, so that overall scores range from 0 to 100.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean change from baseline of the Glasgow Prognostic Score</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline and at end of treatment at week 16</time_frame>
    <description>Change of serum levels of the score-defining biomarkers C-reactive protein (CRP) and albumin. Prognostic scores; 0 (CRP ≥ 10 mg/l), 1 (CRP &gt; 10 mg/l and albumin ≥ 35 g/l), 2 CRP &gt; 10 mg/l and albumin &lt; 35g/l). Score 0 indicates good prognosis, score 1 intermediate prognosis and score 2 poor prognosis.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Amount of concomitant medication taken</measure>
    <time_frame>From baseline until end of treatment at week 18</time_frame>
    <description>Special focus on antiemetic, psychotropic and pain medication</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean time to critical weight-loss (5%)</measure>
    <time_frame>From baseline until end of treatment at week 16</time_frame>
    <description>Assessed with a standard scale</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean changes from baseline for Bioelectrical Impedance Analysis (BIA) parameter Lean body mass (LBM)</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline and at end of treatment at week 16</time_frame>
    <description>Mean change of Lean body mass (LBM = Fat free mass FFM) kg</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean changes from baseline for Bioelectrical Impedance Analysis (BIA) parameter Total body water (TBW)</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline and at end of treatment at week 16</time_frame>
    <description>Mean change of Total body water (TBW) kg</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean changes from baseline for Bioelectrical Impedance Analysis (BIA) parameter Fat mass (FM)</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline and at end of treatment at week 16</time_frame>
    <description>Mean change of Fat mass (FM) kg</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean changes from baseline for Bioelectrical Impedance Analysis (BIA) parameter Body cell mass (BCM)</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline and at end of treatment at week 16</time_frame>
    <description>Mean change of Body cell mass (BCM) kg</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean changes from baseline for Bioelectrical Impedance Analysis (BIA) parameter Extracellular mass (EM)</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline and at end of treatment at week 16</time_frame>
    <description>Mean change of Extracellular mass (ECM) kg</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean changes from baseline for Bioelectrical Impedance Analysis (BIA) parameter Phase angle (PA)</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline and at end of treatment at week 16</time_frame>
    <description>Mean change of Phase angle (PA); Phase Angle has long been linked to nutritional status. This marker is fast becoming recognised as a global health marker in total body health assessment. A higher Phase Angle could mean an increase in muscle mass (body cell mass) or a decrease in fluid, either from recovery from infection or injury (a good thing!) or a decrease in fluid from dehydration (a bad thing!). A loss of fat could also increase Phase Angle.
A lower Phase Angle could mean a loss of muscle mass (a bad thing), or an increase of fluid (rehydrating which is a good thing, or sign of inflammation or infection - a bad thing), or gaining fat (which could be a good or bad thing depending on your state of health).
Phase Angle is a direct measurement, (not a calculation using equations) of the cell membrane.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean changes from baseline for Bioelectrical Impedance Analysis (BIA) parameter Resistance (Rz)</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline and at end of treatment at week 16</time_frame>
    <description>Mean change of Resistance (Rz), unit ohm; the resistance reflects the water or fluid in the body</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean changes from baseline for Bioelectrical Impedance Analysis (BIA) parameter Reactance(Xc)</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline and at end of treatment at week 16</time_frame>
    <description>Mean change of Reactance (Xc), unit ohm; reactance reflects the body cell mass.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean change from baseline of muscle strength</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline and at end of treatment at week 16</time_frame>
    <description>To assess physical strength of patient's handgrip strength will be measured prior and after study treatment using a hydraulic hand dynamometer; mean value of three consecutive measurements will be documented</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of patients not adhering to individual baseline chemotherapy regimen</measure>
    <time_frame>From baseline until end of treatment at week 18</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of patients who do not receive full dose of planned chemotherapy regimen and/or within scheduled time frame (interruption or delay)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Chemotherapeutic dose intensity over the treatment period of 18 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>From baseline until end of treatment at week 18</time_frame>
    <description>The total amount of applied chemotherapy over the study treatment phase is documented</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Frequency and severity of (serious) adverse events (S)AE</measure>
    <time_frame>From baseline until safety visit at week 22</time_frame>
    <description>Assessed with Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (NCI-CTCAE V5.0)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of adverse drug reactions (ARs)</measure>
    <time_frame>From baseline until safety visit at week 22</time_frame>
    <description>Frequency and severity of ARs</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression-free survival (PFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>From treatment start until the date of first documented progression or death from any cause assessed up to week 22</time_frame>
    <description>PFS in months; ; patients will be asked to agree on collection of data regarding PFS also after end of trial</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival (OS)</measure>
    <time_frame>From treatment start until death from any cause assessed up to week 22</time_frame>
    <description>OS in months; ; patients will be asked to agree on collection of data regarding PFS also after end of trial</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">140</enrollment>
  <condition>Pancreatic Cancer Non-resectable</condition>
  <condition>Chemotherapy-induced Nausea and Vomiting</condition>
  <condition>Pancreatic Cancer Metastatic</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Dronabinol</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>BX-1 contains 25 mg dronabinol/ml (2.5% delta-9-trans-tetrahydrocannabinol = THC), oral solution; three applications per day from 2.5 mg (3 x 1 droplet) up to 30 mg (3 x 12 droplets)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Placebo: oral solution with cannabis flavor without active substance and otherwise identical to active comparator, three applications per day from 3 x 1 droplet up to 3 x 12 droplets</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Dronabinol in Oral Dosage Form</intervention_name>
    <description>Titration period for 4 weeks: titration according to tolerability from 2.5 mg (3 x 1 droplet) up to 30 mg (3 x 12 droplets) per day; dose increased by 2.5 mg (3 x 1 droplet) every other day Maintenance period for 12 weeks: individually tolerated maximum dose (up to 30 mg ≙ 3 x 12 droplets) at end of titration period will be continued for maintenance treatment Tapering period for 2 weeks: dose is decreased every other day by 5 mg (3 x 2 droplets) Safety follow-up: 4 weeks after end of treatment</description>
    <arm_group_label>Dronabinol</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>BX-1</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo in Oral Dosage Form</intervention_name>
    <description>Titration period for 4 weeks: titration according to tolerability from 3 x 1 droplet up to 3 x 12 droplets per day; dose increased by 3 x 1 droplet every other day Maintenance period for 12 weeks: individually tolerated maximum dose (up to 3 x 12 droplets) at end of titration period will be continued for maintenance treatment Tapering period for 2 weeks: dose is decreased every other day by 3 x 2 droplets Safety follow-up: 4 weeks after end of treatment</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Male and female subjects aged ≥18

          -  Patients with diagnosis of locally advanced, inoperable or metastatic pancreatic
             cancer, eligible for first-line chemotherapy with FOLFIRINOX or gemcitabine+Abraxane®

          -  According to investigator life expectancy of &gt; 4 months at screening

          -  Female patients must either be post-menopausal or surgically sterilized or use a
             highly effective method of birth control (hormonal contraceptives, intra-uterine
             devices, or diaphragms with spermicide) for the duration of the study and/or must have
             a negative pregnancy test (female patients with childbearing potential only)

          -  Willing and able to provide written informed consent.

          -  Written informed consent given prior to any trial-related procedure not part of the
             normal medical practice.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients who are members of the staff of the trial center, staff of the sponsor or
             CRO, the investigator him/herself or close relatives of the investigator.

          -  Simultaneous participation in another interventional clinical trial, participation in
             another trial with less than 30 days or five half-lives of the IMP (whatever is
             longer) to screening, or previous participation in this trial.

          -  Ineligible for chemotherapy treatment with FOLFIRINOX or gemcitabine+Abraxane®

          -  Use of dronabinol or cannabis-based medicine with THC as constituent within 6 months
             before screening. A urine drug test will be performed during screening phase.

          -  Use of marihuana within the last 4 weeks and unwillingness to abstain for the duration
             of the study. A urine drug test will be performed during screening phase.

          -  Currently receiving chemotherapy or anticipated use of chemotherapy due to any
             condition not related to locally advanced or metastatic pancreatic cancer

          -  History of or existing cardiac diseases or pathological findings (e.g. chronic
             insufficiency NYHA III/IV, severe arrhythmia, unstable angina pectoris, myocardial
             infarction within the past 6 months, significant QT-prolongation etc.), which in the
             opinion of the investigator might interfere with the safety or tolerability of the
             study treatment. An ECG has to be done to exclude pathological findings and must not
             be older than 3 months before screening or if none is available, has to be performed
             during the screening phase and assessed prior to randomization

          -  Clinically relevant, severe pulmonary diseases, uncontrolled hypertension, or poorly
             controlled diabetes

          -  History of or existing relevant CNS and/or psychiatric disorders (e.g. schizophrenia,
             psychosis, manic and/or depressive disorders, suicidal ideations, etc) which might
             interfere with the safety or tolerability of the study treatment. Patients with
             reactive depression are not excluded from participation.

          -  Known current or past (within the last year prior to screening) alcohol, narcotics or
             drug abuse

          -  Pregnancy or breast feeding

          -  Known allergy to cannabinoids and other constituents of the investigational medicinal
             product

          -  Intake of prohibited concomitant medication

          -  Any other substantial medical condition that in the opinion of the investigator could
             create undue risk to the subject or could affect adherence with the trial protocol

          -  Legal incapacity, limited legal capacity or any other condition which makes the
             subject unable to understand the subject information and informed consent form (ICF)

          -  Patients unable or unwilling to waive driving motor vehicles or using machines
             especially during titration period

          -  Unable or unwilling to comply with the protocol regulations
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Felix Keil, Prof.MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Med. Dept. III, Hematolog and Oncology</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Richard Greil, Prof.MD</last_name>
    <phone>+43 57255</phone>
    <phone_ext>25801</phone_ext>
    <email>r.greil@agmt.at</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Daniela Wolkersdorfer, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+43 662640</phone>
    <phone_ext>4412</phone_ext>
    <email>d.wolkersdorfer@agmt.at</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Klinikum Wels-Grieskirchen GmbH, Abteilung für Innere Medizin IV</name>
      <address>
        <city>Wels</city>
        <state>Oberösterreich</state>
        <zip>4600</zip>
        <country>Austria</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Gudrun Piringer, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+43 7242 415</phone>
      <phone_ext>3452</phone_ext>
      <email>Gurdrun.Piringer@klinikum-wegr.at</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Mathaeus Muehlberger, BScN</last_name>
      <phone>+43 7242 415</phone>
      <phone_ext>3452</phone_ext>
      <email>Mathaeus.MuehlberMathaeus.Muehlberger@klinikum-wegr.at</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Gudrun Piringer, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>KABEG-Klinikum Klagenfurt am Woerthersee, Abteilung f. Anaesthesie u. Intensivmedizin</name>
      <address>
        <city>Klagenfurt</city>
        <zip>9020</zip>
        <country>Austria</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Rudolf Likar, Prof.MD.MSc</last_name>
      <phone>+43 463 538</phone>
      <phone_ext>26100</phone_ext>
      <email>rudolf.likar@kabeg.at</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Brigitte Trummer</last_name>
      <phone>+43 463 538</phone>
      <phone_ext>35756</phone_ext>
      <email>brigitte.trummer@kabeg.at</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Rudolf Likar, Prof.MD.MSc</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>LKH Hochsteiermark - Leoben, Abt. f. Innere Medizin, Haemato-Onkologie</name>
      <address>
        <city>Leoben</city>
        <zip>8700</zip>
        <country>Austria</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Christoph Tinchon, MD, Lead</last_name>
      <phone>+43 3842 401</phone>
      <phone_ext>2821</phone_ext>
      <email>christoph.tinchon@kages.at</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Manuela Maderdonner, BSc.,MSc.</last_name>
      <phone>+43 3842 401</phone>
      <phone_ext>3402</phone_ext>
      <email>manuela.maderdonner@kages.at</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Christoph Tinchon, MD, Lead</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>IIIrd Medical Department, Private Medical University Hospital Salzburg</name>
      <address>
        <city>Salzburg</city>
        <zip>5020</zip>
        <country>Austria</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Richard Greil, Prof.MD</last_name>
      <phone>+43 57255</phone>
      <phone_ext>25801</phone_ext>
      <email>r.greil@salk.at</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Michaela Schachner, Mag.</last_name>
      <phone>+43 57255</phone>
      <phone_ext>25823</phone_ext>
      <email>m.schachner@salk.at</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Krankenhaus d. Barmherzigen Brüder, Abt. f. Innere Medizin</name>
      <address>
        <city>St. Veit an der Glan</city>
        <zip>9300</zip>
        <country>Austria</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Harald Weiß, Senior MD</last_name>
      <phone>+43 4212 499</phone>
      <email>harald.weiss@bbstveit.at</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Maria Piribauer, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+43 4212 499</phone>
      <email>maria.piribauer@bbstveit.at</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Harald Weiss, Senior MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Landeskrankenhaus Steyr, Interne Medizin II</name>
      <address>
        <city>Steyr</city>
        <zip>A-4400</zip>
        <country>Austria</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Georg Schreil, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+43 50554 66</phone>
      <phone_ext>24208</phone_ext>
      <email>georg.schreil@ooeg.at</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Regina Neuhauser</last_name>
      <phone>+43 50554 66</phone>
      <phone_ext>24202</phone_ext>
      <email>regina.neuhauser@ooeg.at</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Georg Schreil, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Medizinische Univ. Wien, Univ.Klinik f. Innere Medizin I, Onkologie</name>
      <address>
        <city>Vienna</city>
        <zip>1090</zip>
        <country>Austria</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Gerald Prager, Ass.Prof.MD</last_name>
      <phone>+43 1 40400</phone>
      <phone_ext>44450</phone_ext>
      <email>gerald.prager@meduniwien.ac.at</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Susanne Schlagbauer</last_name>
      <email>susanne.schlagbauer@meduniwien.ac.at</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Gerald Prager, Ass.Prof.MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hanusch Krankenhaus der Wiener Gebietskrankenkasse</name>
      <address>
        <city>Vienna</city>
        <zip>1140</zip>
        <country>Austria</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Thamer Sliwa, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+43 1 910 21</phone>
      <phone_ext>57301</phone_ext>
      <email>thamer.sliwa@oegk.at</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Anna Schipany, MSc</last_name>
      <phone>+43 1 910 21</phone>
      <phone_ext>86907</phone_ext>
      <email>anna.schipany@oegk.at</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Thamer Sliwa, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Austria</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.agmt.at</url>
    <description>Sponsor</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>van Amerongen G, Kanhai K, Baakman AC, Heuberger J, Klaassen E, Beumer TL, Strijers RLM, Killestein J, van Gerven J, Cohen A, Groeneveld GJ. Effects on Spasticity and Neuropathic Pain of an Oral Formulation of Δ9-tetrahydrocannabinol in Patients WithProgressive Multiple Sclerosis. Clin Ther. 2018 Sep;40(9):1467-1482. doi: 10.1016/j.clinthera.2017.01.016. Epub 2017 Feb 9.</citation>
    <PMID>28189366</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Davis MP. Cannabinoids for Symptom Management and Cancer Therapy: The Evidence. J Natl Compr Canc Netw. 2016 Jul;14(7):915-22. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>27407130</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cannabis-In-Cachexia-Study-Group, Strasser F, Luftner D, Possinger K, Ernst G, Ruhstaller T, Meissner W, Ko YD, Schnelle M, Reif M, Cerny T. Comparison of orally administered cannabis extract and delta-9-tetrahydrocannabinol in treating patients with cancer-related anorexia-cachexia syndrome: a multicenter, phase III, randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled clinical trial from the Cannabis-In-Cachexia-Study-Group. J Clin Oncol. 2006 Jul 20;24(21):3394-400.</citation>
    <PMID>16849753</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Turgeman I, Bar-Sela G. Cannabis Use in Palliative Oncology: A Review of the Evidence for Popular Indications. Isr Med Assoc J. 2017 Feb;19(2):85-88. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>28457056</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jatoi A, Windschitl HE, Loprinzi CL, Sloan JA, Dakhil SR, Mailliard JA, Pundaleeka S, Kardinal CG, Fitch TR, Krook JE, Novotny PJ, Christensen B. Dronabinol versus megestrol acetate versus combination therapy for cancer-associated anorexia: a North Central Cancer Treatment Group study. J Clin Oncol. 2002 Jan 15;20(2):567-73.</citation>
    <PMID>11786587</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 28, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 11, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 12, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 27, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 27, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 28, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Dronabinol</keyword>
  <keyword>THC</keyword>
  <keyword>Placebo</keyword>
  <keyword>Pancreatic Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Chemotherapy-induced Nausea and Vomiting</keyword>
  <keyword>Tumor related symptoms</keyword>
  <keyword>Quality of life</keyword>
  <keyword>EORTC QLQ-C30</keyword>
  <keyword>FOLFIRINOX</keyword>
  <keyword>Abraxane</keyword>
  <keyword>Gemcitabine</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pancreatic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Nausea</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vomiting</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Dronabinol</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

