<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03982953</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>EA2/040/19</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03982953</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Predicting Cognition After DBS for Parkinson's Disease</brief_title>
  <official_title>Predictors of Cognitive Change After Deep Brain Stimulation in the Subthalmic Nucleus in Parkinson's Disease</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Charite University, Berlin, Germany</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Charite University, Berlin, Germany</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The aim of the study is to improve estimation of cognitive outcome after STN-DBS in PD in
      order to

        -  avoid risk factors by optimizing peri- and intraoperative management

        -  personalize therapeutic strategies for optimal long-term benefit

      The investigators will test possible predictors (clinical, neuropsychological, neuroimaging,
      electrophysiological and molecular) for the risk of cognitive dysfunction after deep brain
      stimulation of the subthalamic nucleus (STN-DBS) in Parkinson's disease (PD) at a single
      center (Charité - Universitätsmedizin Berlin, Germany). Data collection takes place prior to
      as well as 3 and 12 months after the STN-DBS operation. Participation is proposed to all PD
      patients that are planned to undergo STN-DBS after careful examination of eligibility for
      this treatment according to standard operation procedures.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Additionally to clinical routine tests, we will investigate the following possible predictors
      of cognitive dysfunction after STN-DBS in PD:

        -  Imaging biomarkers: volume of the nucleus basalis of Meynert (NBM) measured on
           preoperative MRI and data driven search for unknown MRI characteristics relating to the
           incidence of postoperative neurocognitive disorder by means of Deep Learning
           (Convolutional Neural Networks), test of previously established classification models

        -  Molecular biomarkers in CSF: TAU, phospho-TAU, ß-Amyloid 1-40 and 1-42 measured
           preoperatively

        -  Comorbidity: according to the Charlson Comorbidity Index

        -  Nutritional Status: defined by the Mini Nutritional Assessment (MNA-SF)

        -  Duration of intra-/perioperative brake of dopaminergic medication

        -  Nature and depth of anaesthesia: general or conscious sedation and depth of
           consciousness: as measured by 4 channel electroencephalography (SedLine®) and during
           implantation of impulse generator

        -  Incidence and duration of postoperative delirium: defined according to the Diagnostic
           and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders (DSM-5) and/or as ≥ 2 points in the nursing
           Delirium Screening Scale (Nu-DESC) and/or a positive Confusion Assessment Method for the
           Intensive Care Unit (CAM-ICU) score, assessment three times daily during hospital stay

        -  Length of stay at ICU / hospital

        -  Postoperative organ complications: according to Clavien-Dindo classification

        -  Localisation of bilateral electrodes and active contacts on postoperative imaging

      Substudies

      Correlation of domain specific CANTAB connect test scores with possible predictors and
      incidence of postoperative neurocognitive disorder

      Social Cognition: comparison of pre- and postoperative Theory of Mind (ToM) abilities
      measured by the Yoni-Paradigma (assesses affective and cognitive ToM)

      The resulting multivariate risk model is expected

        -  to improve peri- and intraoperative management by identifying avoidable risk factors for
           the development of postoperative cognitive deficit

        -  to support evidence-based and personalized decision-making when advising PD patients
           considering STN-DBS

        -  to result in the development of future hypothesis-driven interventional trials on the
           basis of biomarker-based sub-grouping of patients

        -  to allow a better understanding of underlying pathophysiological processes both PD and
           surgery-related regarding cognitive effects of STN-DBS
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 12, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 10, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 10, 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in cognitive performance after STN-DBS</measure>
    <time_frame>Difference between pre- and 12 months postoperative testing</time_frame>
    <description>Based on cognitive screening by paper pencil test (MoCA)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of postoperative neurocognitive disorder</measure>
    <time_frame>Difference between pre- and 3 and 12 months postoperative testing</time_frame>
    <description>• According to DSM-5 criteria applying the tablet-based neuropsychological test battery Cambridge Neuropsychological Test Automated Battery (CANTAB connect)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Parkinson's Disease</condition>
  <condition>Deep Brain Stimulation</condition>
  <condition>Postoperativeneurocognitive Deficit</condition>
  <condition>Postoperative Delirium</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>PD patients with STN-DBS</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients with the diagnosis of Levodopa responsive idiopathic Parkinson's Disease that are planned to undergo craniectomy with implantation of bilateral DBS electrodes in the subthalamic nucleus</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Controls - PD patients with medical treatment</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients with the diagnosis of Levodopa responsive idiopathic Parkinson's Disease that do not undergo DBS for personal reasons or contraindications for this treatment. Age, sex and disease-severity matched with PD patients with STN-DBS.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <biospec_retention>Samples Without DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Cholinergic biomarkers in cerebrospinal fluid (CSF)

        -  TAU, phospho-TAU, ß-Amyloid 1-40 and 1-42

        -  measured in CSF preoperatively
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        PD patients that are planned to undergo STN-DBS. Possible contraindications to DBS are
        tested according to clinic-intern standard operation procedures. Tests include

          -  Clinical scales: DemTect, MMST, ADL, MDS-UPDRS I-IV including video documentation of
             MDS-UPDRS III on and off dopaminergic medication

          -  Questionnaires: expectations regarding DBS, PDQ39, BDI, Starkstein-Apathie-Skala,
             QUIP(-RS)

          -  General examinations: Routine laboratory, ECG, TTE, Chest X-Ray, lung function,
             24h-RR, Duplex sonography of extracranial arteries

          -  Expert opinion from related fields: Neuropsychological exam, psychiatric examination,
             neurosurgery and anesthisiologic consultation
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Diagnosis of idiopathic Parkinson's Disease

          -  Indication for STN-DBS

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Internistic, surgical or psychiatric contrainidications with respect to the DBS
             operation or treatment for the STN-DBS group

          -  Dementia

          -  Relevant language barrier
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Andrea A Kühn, Prof. MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Neurology, Head of the Movement Disorders and Neuromodulation Section</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Dorothee Kübler, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+4930450660528</phone>
    <email>dorothee.kuebler@charite.de</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Charité - Universitätsmedizin Berlin</name>
      <address>
        <city>Berlin</city>
        <zip>13351</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Dorothee Kübler, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+4930450660528</phone>
      <email>dorothee.kuebler@charite.de</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Lucia K Feldmann, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+4930450660298</phone>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Germany</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 9, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 9, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 12, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 10, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 10, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 11, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Charite University, Berlin, Germany</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Dorothee Kübler</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Postdoc and MD</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Parkinson Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Delirium</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

