<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03988972</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>27180413</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03988972</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Efficacy of Diathermy on Healing Power of Cesarean Section Scar</brief_title>
  <acronym>EDHPCS</acronym>
  <official_title>Efficacy of Diathermy on Healing Power of Cesarean Section Scar:A Randomized Control Trail</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Ain Shams University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Ain Shams University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To compare the effects of electro-surgery on healing power as a primary outcome (from skin to
      the peritoneum. And volume of blood loss, incision time and postoperative surgical wound pain
      as secondary outcomes.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a prospective study is carried out at Ain Shams University Maternity Hospital,
      Obstetrics and Gynecology Department, Faculty of medicine in women undergoing CS through
      pfannentiel incisions.

      All women will receive intravenous antibiotic prophylaxis according to the Ain Shams
      guideline, 1 g of cefazolin given at the time of incision.

      Diathermy incisions will be carried out using monopolar blade pen electrode, set on cutting
      mode and delivering a 35 continuous current. Electrosurgical cutting will be performed
      without pressure or mechanical displacement.

      'Bleeders' will be controlled by using diathermy, on coagulating mode, and will be applied to
      a hemostat on the vessels.

      Incisions made by the scalpel will be done by the traditional method, with proper hemostasis
      by application of pressure to skin blood vessels and by ligating the subcutaneous bleeders.

      After the operation and during the postoperative period, paracetamol (10mg/mL) 50-mL vial
      will be administered by i.v. infusion for analgesia on demand according to the patient's need
      with a 500-mg dose. And the wound will be sutured subcuticle by a prolene 3.0 sutures.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 6, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">August 1, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">August 1, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>The 180 patients who will be included in our study will be randomized through computer generated system in to 2 groups. Group D (diathermy) and group S (scalpel). Each group will include 90 patients.
Allocation and concealment will be done by sequentially sealed opaque envelopes. 180 envelopes will be numbered serially from 1 to 180, 90 envelopes will contain the letter D and the other 90 will contain the letter S.
In each envelope, the corresponding letter which donates the allocated group will be put according to the randomization table and them all envelopes will be closed and put in one box. When the first patient arrives, the first envelope will be opened and the patient will be allocated according to the letter inside, whom will be allocated by a person not involved in the study.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Care Provider, Investigator)</masking>
    <masking_description>allocation done by a person not involved in the study.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Cosmosis</measure>
    <time_frame>15 days after CS</time_frame>
    <description>The primary objective is to compare healing power between two methods then will be followed at 3, 7, 11, and 15 days post-operative using: Visual Analogue Scale The original VAS consisted of a 100-mm line with &quot;worst scar&quot; at the right end of the line and &quot;best scar&quot; at the left end of the line. In this study, VAS ranged from 0 to 10cm. Using the line as a continuous entity, the patient mark on the line where they thought the scar fit.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Healing power</measure>
    <time_frame>15 days after cs</time_frame>
    <description>The wound score addresses 6 clinical variables: absence of stepoff, contour ir- regularities, wound margin separation &gt;2 mm, edge inversion, excessive distortion, and overall cosmetic appearance. Each of these categories is graded on a O-or-l-point scale. A total cosmetic score is derived by the addition of the scores of the 6 categorical variables. A score of 6 is considered optimal, while a score of ≤5 suboptimal.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>postoperative surgical wound pain: VAS scale</measure>
    <time_frame>24 hours</time_frame>
    <description>postoperative surgical wound pain using visual analogue scale (VAS) after 1, 4,6,12 and 24 hours postoperatively. The visual analogue pain scale is a uni-dimensional measure of pain intensity, which has been used in adults. The visual analogue pain scale is an easy assessment tool consisting of a 10 cm line with 0 on one end, representing no pain, and 10 on the other end, representing the worst pain felt.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">180</enrollment>
  <condition>Healing Surgical Wounds</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>diathermy group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Diathermy incisions will be carried out using monopolar blade pen electrode, set on cutting mode and delivering a 35 continuous current. Electrosurgical cutting was performed without pressure or mechanical displacement.
'Bleeders' will be controlled by using diathermy, on coagulating mode, and will be applied to a hemostat on the vessels</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>scalpel group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Incisions made by the scalpel will be done by the traditional method, with proper hemostasis by application of pressure to skin blood vessels and by ligating the subcutaneous bleeders.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>diathermy</intervention_name>
    <description>In women undergoing C.S, is healing power after diathermy equally to healing power after scalpel?</description>
    <arm_group_label>diathermy group</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>electro-cautrey</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>scalpel</intervention_name>
    <description>Incisions made by the scalpel will be done by the traditional method, with proper hemostasis by application of pressure to skin blood vessels and by ligating the subcutaneous bleeders.</description>
    <arm_group_label>scalpel group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Primi-section

          -  BMI (18-29) kg/m^2.

          -  Age from (18-40).

          -  Women undergoing CS with Pfannenstiel incision.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Women with one of the following conditions:

        Patients requiring midline incision or on anti-coagulant therapy

          -  Cardiac patients on pacemakers and patients with chronic diseases expected to affect
             wound healing, such as diabetes, liver diseases, chronic anemia and renal impairment

          -  Obese patients BMI (&gt;30) kg/m^2.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>40 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mohamed abd elfatah elsenity, lecturer</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Ain Shams University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ain shams maternity teaching hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cairo</city>
        <state>Abbasia</state>
        <zip>11591</zip>
        <country>Egypt</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Egypt</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 11, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 15, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 18, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 19, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 19, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 22, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Ain Shams University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Mohamed abd elfatah elsenity</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Lecturer of obstetrics and gynecology</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Surgical Wound</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>will be shared in amaster sheet</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

