<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03985982</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CPH-303-201400</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03985982</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Botulinum Toxin Treatment of Glabellar Lines: Efficacy and Safety Study III (BLESS III)</brief_title>
  <acronym>BLESS III</acronym>
  <official_title>Randomized Double Blind Phase 3 Study to Assess the Efficacy and Safety of BoNT/A-DP in the Treatment of Glabellar Lines in Comparison With Placebo Followed by an Open Label Extension Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Croma-Pharma GmbH</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Croma-Pharma GmbH</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The aim of this study is to assess the efficacy and safety of BoNT/A-DP in the treatment of
      glabellar lines in comparison with placebo, including efficacy after repeat treatments and
      long term safety.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The study is a parallel-group, randomized, double blind, placebo-controlled study followed by
      an open label extension.

      An interim Analysis will be performed when all subjects finalized the re-evaluation for
      retreatment visit at week 16 of the first treatment cycle or completed the double blind phase
      (whichever occurs earlier).

      The first treatment cycle of the study will comprise two treatment groups as follows:

        -  Group A (active): BoNT/A-DP (20 units, 0.5 mL)

        -  Group B (placebo control): sterile, 0.9% sodium chloride, (0.5 mL). Eligible subjects
           will be randomized at baseline (day 0) to Group A or B to receive the first treatment in
           a 3:1 randomization scheme, respectively. Investigators and subjects will be blinded to
           the treatment administered and will evaluate the severity of glabellar lines
           independently. The subject should perform their assessment independently and ideally
           before the investigator, to ensure they are not biased by the investigator. The same
           investigator should assess the subject at baseline and at the visits at weeks 1, 2 and 4
           in the first treatment cycle.

      After a screening period of up to14 calendar days, subjects will receive the first treatment
      (BoNT/A-DP or placebo) and attend for visits at 1, 2 and 4 weeks after treatment and at 4
      weekly intervals thereafter for evaluation of efficacy and safety (primary and key secondary
      efficacy endpoints are evaluated in the first treatment cycle in comparison with placebo).

      The first treatment cycle will last at least 12 weeks and will end when the subjects qualify
      for re-treatment (in accordance with the &quot;eligibility for re-treatment criteria&quot;). After the
      first treatment cycle is completed, all subjects may enter the open label extension phase and
      will be dosed with BoNT/A-DP (20 U) for subsequent re-treatments.

      Evaluation for re-treatment takes place at the earliest at 12 weeks after the first/previous
      treatment. Subjects who do not qualify for re-treatment at week 12 will have the option
      (pending eligibility) of re-treatment at a later visit (at 4 weekly intervals thereafter)
      until they are eligible for re-treatment or until a total of 48 weeks has elapsed since study
      start. Subjects will attend for visits at 1 and 4 weeks after any re-treatment and at 4
      weekly intervals thereafter. At week 2 and week 8 of each open label cycle a telephone call
      visist will take place. According to the study schedule (Section 2.1 and Section 2.2), a
      maximum of 4 treatments per subject (4 treatment cycles) is permitted during the study time
      frame, with treatments separated by a minimum of 12 weeks.

      The number of treatments administered per subject will depend on the subject's qualification
      for re-treatment; however, the last opportunity for re-treatment is at week 48.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">April 29, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Facial Wrinkle Scale (FWS) score of 0 or 1 and an improvement of ≥ 2 points in FWS score (at maximum frown) at week 4 visit relative to baseline, based on both the investigators´and the subjects´ in-clinic assessments.</measure>
    <time_frame>week 4 relative to baseline</time_frame>
    <description>The primary endpoint is the proportion of subjects among BoNT/A-DP and placebo groups with a Facial Wrinkle Scale (FWS) score of 0 or 1 and an improvement of ≥ 2 points in FWS score (at maximum frown) at week 4 visit (of the first treatment cycle) relative to baseline (responders), based on both the investigators'and the subjects'in-clinic assessments. Thus, the primary endpoint is a composite endpoint comprising investigator and subject assessments of treatment effectiveness.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of responders at maximum frown at week 12</measure>
    <time_frame>week 12</time_frame>
    <description>The percentage of responders at maximum frown at week 12 (after the first treatment with BoNT/A-DP or placebo).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of responders at week 16</measure>
    <time_frame>week 16</time_frame>
    <description>The percentage of responders at week 16 (after the first treatment).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The proportion of subjects with a ≥ 1 point reduction in FWS score at rest at week 4 based separately on the investogators´and the subjects´ in-clinic assessments</measure>
    <time_frame>week 4</time_frame>
    <description>3. The proportion of subjects with a ≥ 1 point reduction in FWS score at rest at week 4 in the first treatment cycle, based separately on the investigators'and the subjects'in-clinic assessments (applicable only for subjects who have a FWS score at rest ≥ 1 at baseline).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of responders at week 20 or up to week 48</measure>
    <time_frame>week 20</time_frame>
    <description>The percentage of responders at week 20 or up to week 48 (after the first treatment)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Frequency, severity and causal relationship of AEs, SAes and AESIs</measure>
    <time_frame>through study completion (60 weeks)</time_frame>
    <description>Frequency, severity and causal relationship of adverse events (AEs), serious adverse events (SAEs) and adverse events of special interest (AESIs) during the entire study period.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">353</enrollment>
  <condition>Glabellar Frown Lines</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Botulinum toxin A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Botulinum Toxin A will be administered in double blind fashion in cycle 1. 20 Units will be administered (divided in five 0.1 mL i.m injections) into glabellar area.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Placebo will be administered in double blind fashion in cycle 1 divided in five 0.1 mL injections into the glabellar area.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Botulinum Toxin A</intervention_name>
    <description>Injection, 20 Units divided in five 0.1 mL i.m injections into the glabellar area</description>
    <arm_group_label>Botulinum toxin A</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>BoNT/A-DP</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>injection, sodium chloride 0.9 % divided in five 0.1 mL i.m injections into the glabellar area</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>sodium chloride 0,9 %</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Ages ≥ 18 years or older at time of screening

          -  Has moderate to severe glabellar fown lines at maximum frown (severity score of 2 or 3
             on FWS) as determinated by in-clinic assessments by both the investigator and the
             subject (where: 0 =´none´, 1= ´mild´, 2= ´moderate´, 3= ´severe´).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Any medical condition that may place the subject at increased risk due to exposure to
             botulinum toxin, including diagnosed myasthenia gravis, Eaton-Lambert syndrome,
             amyotrophic lateral sclerosis, profound atrophy or weakness in the target muscles, or
             any other condition (at the inivestigator´s discretion) that might interfere with
             neuromuscular function or contraindicate botulinum toxin therapy.

          -  Previous treatment with any serotype of botulinum toxin for any indication within the
             12 months prior to screening, or any planned treatment with botulinum toxin of any
             serotype for any reason during the trail (other than the investigational treatment).

          -  Active skin disease/ infection or irritation at the treatment area

          -  Pregnant, breastfeeding or planning to become pregnant during the trial.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jeffrey Adelglass, Dr.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>SKINTASTIC Medical</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Sue Ellen Cox, Dr.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Aesthetic Solutions P.A.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Michael Gold, Dr.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Tennessee Clinical Research Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Joely Kaufman-Janette, Dr.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Skin Research Institute LLC</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Susan Taylor, Dr.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Perelman Center for Advanced Medicine-University of Pennsylvania</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mark Nestor, Dr.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Center for Clinical and Cosmetic Research</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Daniel Mueller, Dr.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Yuvell (Austria)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Sonja Höller, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+43-2262-684-686-0</phone>
    <email>sonja.hoeller@croma.at</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Marion Pucher, Dr.</last_name>
    <phone>+43-2262-684-686-0</phone>
    <email>marion.pucher@croma.at</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Tennessee Clinical Research Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nashville</city>
        <state>Tennessee</state>
        <zip>37215</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Michael Gold</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 12, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 12, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 14, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 14, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 14, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 18, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Botulinum Toxins</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Botulinum Toxins, Type A</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>abobotulinumtoxinA</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>This is not decided yet and will be changed accordingly when the decision has been made</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

