<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02699190</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>16-013213</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02699190</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>LeukoSEQ: Whole Genome Sequencing as a First-Line Diagnostic Tool for Leukodystrophies</brief_title>
  <official_title>LeukoSEQ: Whole Genome Sequencing as a First-Line Diagnostic Tool for Leukodystrophies</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Children's Hospital of Philadelphia</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Illumina, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Children's Hospital of Philadelphia</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Leukodystrophies, and other heritable disorders of the white matter of the brain, were
      previously resistant to genetic characterization, largely due to the extreme genetic
      heterogeneity of molecular causes. While recent work has demonstrated that whole genome
      sequencing (WGS), has the potential to dramatically increase diagnostic efficiency,
      significant questions remain around the impact on downstream clinical management approaches
      versus standard diagnostic approaches.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Leukodystrophies are a group of approximately 30 genetic diseases that primarily affect the
      white matter of the brain, a complex structure composed of axons sheathed in myelin, a glial
      cell-derived lipid-rich membrane. Leukodystrophies are frequently characterized by early
      onset, spasticity and developmental delay, and are degenerative in nature. As a whole,
      leukodystrophies are relatively common (approximately 1 in 7000 births or almost twice as
      prevalent as Prader-Willi Syndrome, which has been far more extensively studied) with high
      associated health-care costs; however, more than half of the suspected leukodystrophies do
      not have a definitive diagnosis, and are generally classified as &quot;leukodystrophies of unknown
      etiology&quot;. Even when a diagnosis is achieved, the diagnostic process lasts an average of
      eight years and results in test expenses in excess of $8,000 on average per patient,
      including the majority of patients who never achieve a diagnosis at all. These diagnostic
      challenges represent an urgent and unresolved gap in knowledge and disease characterization,
      as obtaining a definitive diagnosis is of paramount importance for leukodystrophy patients.
      The diagnostic workup begins with findings on cranial Magnetic Resonance Imaging (MRI)
      followed by sequential targeted genetic testing, however next generation sequencing
      technologies (NGS) offer the promise of rapid and more cost effective approaches.

      Despite significant advances in diagnostic efficacy, there are still significant issues with
      respect to implementation of NGS in clinical settings. First, sample cohorts demonstrating
      diagnostic efficacy are generally small, retrospective, and susceptible to ascertainment
      bias, ultimately rendering them poor candidates for utility analyses (to determine how
      efficient a test is at producing a diagnosis). Second, historic sample cohorts have not been
      examined prospectively for information about impact on clinical management (whether the test
      results in different clinical monitoring, a change in medications, or alternate clinical
      interventions).

      To address these issues, the study team conducted an investigation of patients with suspected
      leukodystrophies or other genetic disorders affecting the white matter of the brain at the
      time of initial confirmation of MRI abnormalities, with prospective collection of patients
      randomly received on a &quot;first come, first served&quot; basis from a network of expert clinical
      sites. Subjects were randomized to receive early (1 month) or late (6 months) WGS, with SoC
      clinical analyses conducted alongside WGS testing. An interim analysis performed in May 2018
      assessed these study outcomes for a cohort of thirty-four (34) enrolled subjects. Two of
      these subjects were resolved before complete enrollment and were retained as controls. Nine
      subjects were stratified to the Immediate Arm, of which 5 (55.6%) were resolved by WGS and 4
      (44.4%) were persistently unresolved. Of the 23 subjects randomized to the Delayed Arm, 14
      (60.9%) were resolved by WGS and 5 (21.7%) by SoC, while the remaining 4 (17.4%) remained
      undiagnosed. The diagnostic efficacy of WGS in both arms was significant relative to SoC
      (p&lt;0.005). The time to diagnosis was significantly shorter in the immediate WGS group
      (p&lt;0.05). The overall diagnostic efficacy of the combination of WGS and SoC approaches was
      26/34 (76.5%; 95% CI = 58.8% to 89.3%) over &lt;4 months, greater than historical norms of &lt;50%
      over more than 5 years.

      The study now seeks to determine whether WGS results in changes to clinical management in
      subjects affected by undiagnosed genetic disorders of the white matter of the brain relative
      to standard diagnostic approaches. We anticipate that WGS will produce measurable downstream
      changes in clinical management, as defined by disease-specific screening for complications or
      implementation of disease-specific therapeutic approaches.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 6, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 11, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 11, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Other</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in Clinical Management (Resulting from WGS)</measure>
    <time_frame>01/06/2017 - 08/26/2019</time_frame>
    <description>The primary objective of this study is to evaluate changes in clinical management between the study cohort, who will undergo whole genome sequencing (WGS) as part of clinical care, and a historical cohort of patients whose diagnoses were established using standard (i.e. non-WGS) diagnostic approaches. Differences in clinical management will be measured at six months following disclosure of results.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to Implementation of Changes in Clinical Management (Resulting from WGS)</measure>
    <time_frame>01/06/2017 - 08/26/2019</time_frame>
    <description>Determine whether time to implementation of clinical management approaches differs between subjects who received whole genome sequencing over standard diagnostic approaches.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">450</enrollment>
  <condition>Leukodystrophy</condition>
  <condition>White Matter Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Prospective Study Cohort</arm_group_label>
    <description>This cohort comprises recently identified individuals for whom a clinical decision has been made to pursue whole genome sequencing (WGS) as a first-line diagnostic test. The cohort also includes each subject's biological parents.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Historical Study Cohort</arm_group_label>
    <description>This cohort comprises approximately 50 historical controls who received either whole genome sequencing (WGS) or standard diagnostic testing as part of their participation in a previous version of this protocol, which used a randomized controlled design to assess diagnostic efficacy of WGS. This cohort is closed to new enrollment, and exists for statistical analysis purposes only.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        We expect participants to be identified during their initial presentation and preliminary
        diagnostic workup. Leukodystrophies are heritable conditions that - with only few
        exceptions - are not gender-specific. We therefore expect males and females to be equally
        represented in the study population. The age of presentation is variable ranging from
        infancy to adulthood, though enrollment for the study is limited to individuals who have
        not yet reached the age of 18. All ethnicities are equally represented in these disorders,
        and we expect ethnicities to be represented based on US census data of population
        distribution.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Abnormalities of the white matter signal on neuroimaging (MRI) with T2 hyperintensity
             which must be diffuse or involve specific anatomical tracts consistent with a genetic
             diagnosis;

          2. No pre-existing genetic diagnosis;

          3. A clinical decision has been made to perform WGS;

          4. Less than 18 years of age;

          5. Availability of both biologic parents for blood sampling;

          6. Availability both biological parents to provide informed consent;

          7. Concurrently enrolled in CHOP IRB 14-011236 (New Diagnostic Approaches in
             Leukodystrophy - The Myelin Disorders Biorepository Project)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Candidates with acquired disorders, including infection, acute disseminated
             encephalomyelitis (ADEM), multiple sclerosis, vasculitis or toxic
             leukoencephalopathies;

          2. Patients who have had previous genetic testing*, including WES or WGS;

          3. Those with no third-party payer insurance, unable to receive standard of care
             diagnosis and therapeutic approaches;

          4. Candidates who have already received a diagnosis.

               -  Note: Karyotype or microarray testing that did not yield a definitive diagnosis
                  should not be considered as an excluding factor.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>18 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Adeline Vanderver, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Children's Hospital of Philadelphia</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Omar Sherbini, MPH</last_name>
    <phone>215-590-3068</phone>
    <email>sherbinio@email.chop.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The Children's Hospital of Philadelphia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19104</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Omar Sherbini, MPH</last_name>
      <phone>215-590-3068</phone>
      <email>sherbinio@email.chop.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Adeline Vanderver, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://www.chop.edu/centers-programs/leukodystrophy-center/research</url>
    <description>CHOP Leukodystrophy Center Research Portal</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Costello DJ, Eichler AF, Eichler FS. Leukodystrophies: classification, diagnosis, and treatment. Neurologist. 2009 Nov;15(6):319-28. doi: 10.1097/NRL.0b013e3181b287c8. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19901710</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bonkowsky JL, Nelson C, Kingston JL, Filloux FM, Mundorff MB, Srivastava R. The burden of inherited leukodystrophies in children. Neurology. 2010 Aug 24;75(8):718-25. doi: 10.1212/WNL.0b013e3181eee46b. Epub 2010 Jul 21.</citation>
    <PMID>20660364</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Vanderver A, Hussey H, Schmidt JL, Pastor W, Hoffman HJ. Relative incidence of inherited white matter disorders in childhood to acquired pediatric demyelinating disorders. Semin Pediatr Neurol. 2012 Dec;19(4):219-23. doi: 10.1016/j.spen.2012.10.001.</citation>
    <PMID>23245555</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Richards J, Korgenski EK, Srivastava R, Bonkowsky JL. Costs of the diagnostic odyssey in children with inherited leukodystrophies. Neurology. 2015 Sep 29;85(13):1167-70. doi: 10.1212/WNL.0000000000001974. Epub 2015 Aug 28.</citation>
    <PMID>26320197</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Richards J, Korgenski EK, Taft RJ, Vanderver A, Bonkowsky JL. Targeted leukodystrophy diagnosis based on charges and yields for testing. Am J Med Genet A. 2015 Nov;167A(11):2541-3. doi: 10.1002/ajmg.a.37215. Epub 2015 Jul 16.</citation>
    <PMID>26183797</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bamshad MJ, Ng SB, Bigham AW, Tabor HK, Emond MJ, Nickerson DA, Shendure J. Exome sequencing as a tool for Mendelian disease gene discovery. Nat Rev Genet. 2011 Sep 27;12(11):745-55. doi: 10.1038/nrg3031. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21946919</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Srivastava S, Cohen JS, Vernon H, Barañano K, McClellan R, Jamal L, Naidu S, Fatemi A. Clinical whole exome sequencing in child neurology practice. Ann Neurol. 2014 Oct;76(4):473-83. doi: 10.1002/ana.24251. Epub 2014 Aug 30.</citation>
    <PMID>25131622</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Vanderver A, Simons C, Helman G, Crawford J, Wolf NI, Bernard G, Pizzino A, Schmidt JL, Takanohashi A, Miller D, Khouzam A, Rajan V, Ramos E, Chowdhury S, Hambuch T, Ru K, Baillie GJ, Grimmond SM, Caldovic L, Devaney J, Bloom M, Evans SH, Murphy JLP, McNeill N, Fogel BL; Leukodystrophy Study Group, Schiffmann R, van der Knaap MS, Taft RJ. Whole exome sequencing in patients with white matter abnormalities. Ann Neurol. 2016 Jun;79(6):1031-1037. doi: 10.1002/ana.24650. Epub 2016 May 9.</citation>
    <PMID>27159321</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schiffmann R, van der Knaap MS. Invited article: an MRI-based approach to the diagnosis of white matter disorders. Neurology. 2009 Feb 24;72(8):750-9. doi: 10.1212/01.wnl.0000343049.00540.c8.</citation>
    <PMID>19237705</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>November 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 16, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 1, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 4, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 29, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 29, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">December 2, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Children's Hospital of Philadelphia</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Adeline Vanderver, MD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Leukodystrophy</keyword>
  <keyword>White Matter Disease</keyword>
  <keyword>Whole Genome Sequencing</keyword>
  <keyword>WGS</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Leukoencephalopathies</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Individual participant data (IPD) only available to principal investigator, co-investigators, and trial staff.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <provided_document_section>
    <provided_document>
      <document_type>Informed Consent Form</document_type>
      <document_has_protocol>No</document_has_protocol>
      <document_has_icf>Yes</document_has_icf>
      <document_has_sap>No</document_has_sap>
      <document_date>December 14, 2018</document_date>
      <document_url>https://ClinicalTrials.gov/ProvidedDocs/90/NCT02699190/ICF_000.pdf</document_url>
    </provided_document>
  </provided_document_section>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

