<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02690714</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2002C011G</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02690714</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study of Prometic Plasminogen IV Infusion in Subjects With Hypoplasminogenemia</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase 2/3, Open-Label, Repeat-Dose Study of the Pharmacokinetics, Efficacy, and Safety of Prometic Plasminogen Intravenous Infusion in Subjects With Hypoplasminogenemia</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Prometic Biotherapeutics, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Prometic Biotherapeutics, Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a Phase 2/3 pivotal study to evaluate pharmacokinetics (PK), efficacy, and safety of
      Prometic Plasminogen (Human) Intravenous Lyophilized Solution, the investigational medicinal
      product (IMP), in pediatric and adult subjects with hypoplasminogenemia.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a Phase 2/3, open-label, repeat-dose study of the PK, efficacy, and safety of the
      IMP, in pediatric and adult subjects with hypoplasminogenemia. The study consists of a
      screening period and 3 treatment segments (Segment 1,2, and 3). Subjects who have documented
      individual PK profiles do not need to undergo Segment 1 and can proceed directly to Segment
      2. Subjects in Segment 1 will receive a single dose of 6.6 mg/kg IMP infusion. Blood samples
      for PK analysis will be drawn prior to infusion and subsequently through 96 hours after the
      infusion to establish individual PK profiles. The sample drawn prior to infusion will be used
      to measure the subject's baseline anti-plasminogen antibody, plasminogen activity and antigen
      as well as D-dimer levels. The resulting PK profile will be used to determine each subject's
      dosing interval in Segment 2.

      Based on individual PK profiles from Segment 1 subjects will receive 6.6 mg/kg IMP infusion
      every second, third, or fourth day for 12 weeks in Segment 2. For subjects who directly enter
      Segment 2, baseline assessments will be conducted before the first dose of IMP, including a
      blood sample to measure the baseline anti-plasminogen antibody, plasminogen activity and
      antigen as well as D-dimer levels. Subjects will visit the study sites on Week 1 and
      subsequently every 4 weeks, and receive the IMP infusion at the study site. Blood samples
      will be obtained at each study visit at Weeks 4, 8 and 12 and by a home health nurse at Weeks
      2, 6 and 10. Subjects will undergo clinical assessments of the disease, including but not
      limited to: photographic measurements of visible lesions, spirometry for subjects with
      pulmonary involvement, and imaging study of nonvisible lesions, as applicable. Plasma samples
      will be drawn before IMP administration every 2 weeks to measure the trough levels of
      plasminogen activity and antigen, and D-dimer.

      At the end of Segment 2, subjects will have the option to participate in Segment 3 where they
      will continue to receive IMP for an additional 36 weeks in Norway, and until product
      licensing or study termination by the sponsor for subjects in the United States. Subjects
      will return to the study sites for assessments every 3 months to monitor subjects' clinical
      status and plasminogen trough levels. Subjects at the Norway site in Segment 3 should return
      to the study site for a safety follow-up visit 30 days after the final IMP dose. Due to the
      delay in product approval, subjects at the US site in Segment 3 will be allowed to enroll in
      treatment protocol 2002C018G and continue ongoing IMP treatment without any break in
      treatment. If subjects decide to not enter treatment protocol 2002C018G, then they will stop
      IMP and return to the study site for a safety follow-up visit 30 days after the final IMP
      dose.

      The primary objective of this study is to achieve an increase of individual trough
      plasminogen activity by at least an absolute 10% (i.e., 10 U/dL) from baseline during the 12
      weeks of plasminogen replacement therapy in Segment 2; and to evaluate the efficacy of
      plasminogen replacement therapy on clinically evident or visible symptoms of
      hypoplasminogenemia during the 48 weeks of dosing in Segments 2 and 3.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 4, 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">October 8, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 17, 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2/Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>Yes</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Trough plasminogen activity levels during 12 weeks of study drug treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Blood samples are collected before the first dose of the study drug to establish the baseline levels and every 2 weeks thereafter prior to study drug administration through Week 12 to measure trough levels of plasminogen activity.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of lesions after 48 weeks of study drug treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>48 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Clinical success is defined as 50% of subjects with visible or other measureable lesions achieving at least a 50% improvement in lesion number/size or functionality impact from baseline.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Size of lesions after 48 weeks of study drug treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>48 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Clinical success is defined as 50% of subjects with visible or other measurable lesions achieving at least a 50% improvement in lesion size from baseline.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Spirometry results after 48 weeks of study drug treatment in subjects with bronchial lesions of hypoplasminogenemia.</measure>
    <time_frame>48 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Clinical success is defined as 50% of subjects with visible or other measurable lesions achieving at least a 50% improvement in affected organ functionality (e.g., spirometry) from baseline.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of treatment emergent adverse events (TEAEs)</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 53 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The relatedness and severity of all TEAEs will be summarized
Numbers of subjects who had changes from baseline in viral tests will be summarized
Number of subjects who had changes from baseline in immunogenicity tests will be summarized</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Trough plasminogen activity levels after 24, 36, and 48 weeks of study drug treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>24-48 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Blood samples are collected before the first dose of the study drug to establish the baseline levels and at 24, 36, and 48 weeks thereafter prior to study drug administration to measure trough levels of plasminogen activity.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of lesions after 12 weeks of study drug treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Clinical success is defined as 50% of subjects with visible or other measurable lesions achieving at least a 50% improvement in lesion number from baseline.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Size of lesions after 12 weeks of study drug treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Clinical success is defined as 50% of subjects with visible or other measurable lesions achieving at least a 50% improvement in lesion size from baseline.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in spirometry after 12 weeks of study drug treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Clinical success is defined as 50% of subjects with visible or other measurable lesions achieving at least a 50% improvement in affected organ functionality (e.g., spirometry) from baseline.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical Global Impression-Global Improvement (CGI-I) scores after 12 and 48 weeks of study drug treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>12 and 48 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>CGI-I scores are measured at baseline and at 12 and 48 weeks after study drug treatment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of life score after 12 and 48 weeks of study treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>12 and 48 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Quality of life scores are measured at baseline and at 12 and 48 weeks after study drug treatment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean baseline-adjusted mean plasminogen activity levels after the first and Week 12 dose of study drug treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Blood samples are collected prior to the first and Week 12 dose and at 0.167, 6, 24, 48, 72, and 96 hours after the first and Week 12 dose of study drug to measure plasminogen activity.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean area under the concentration-time curve, from time 0 to the last measured time point (AUCLAST) of baseline-adjusted plasminogen activity after the first and Week 12 dose of study drug treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>To determine the mean AUCLAST of baseline-adjusted plasminogen activity in subjects with hypoplasminogenemia</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean extrapolated area under the concentration-time curve, from time 0 to infinity (AUCINF) of baseline-adjusted plasminogen activity after the first and Week 12 dose of study drug treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>To determine the mean AUCINF of baseline-adjusted plasminogen activity in subjects with hypoplasminogenemia</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean clearance (CL) of baseline-adjusted plasminogen activity after the first and Week 12 dose of study drug treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>To determine the mean CL of baseline-adjusted plasminogen activity in subjects with hypoplasminogenemia</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean MRT of baseline-adjusted plasminogen activity after the first and Week 12 dose of study drug treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>To determine the mean MRT of baseline-adjusted plasminogen activity in subjects with hypoplasminogenemia</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean Vd of baseline-adjusted plasminogen activity after the first and Week 12 dose of study drug treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>To determine the mean Vd of baseline-adjusted plasminogen activity in subjects with hypoplasminogenemia</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean terminal half-life (t1/2) of baseline-adjusted plasminogen activity after the first and Week 12 dose of study drug treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>To determine the mean t1/2 of baseline-adjusted plasminogen activity in subjects with hypoplasminogenemia</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean Cmax of baseline-adjusted plasminogen activity after the first and Week 12 dose of study drug treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>To determine the mean t1/2 of baseline-adjusted plasminogen activity in subjects with hypoplasminogenemia</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean baseline-adjusted mean plasminogen antigen levels after the first and Week 12 dose of study drug treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Blood samples are collected prior to the first and Week 12 dose and at 0.167, 6, 24, 48, 72, and 96 hours after the first and Week 12 dose of study drug to measure plasminogen antigen levels.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean AUCLAST of baseline-adjusted plasminogen antigen after the first and Week 12 dose of study drug treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>To determine the mean AUCLAST of baseline-adjusted plasminogen antigen in subjects with hypoplasminogenemia</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean AUCINF of baseline-adjusted plasminogen antigen after the first and Week 12 dose of study drug treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>To determine the mean AUCINF of baseline-adjusted plasminogen antigen in subjects with hypoplasminogenemia</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean CL of baseline-adjusted plasminogen antigen after the first and Week 12 dose of study drug treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>To determine the mean CL of baseline-adjusted plasminogen antigen in subjects with hypoplasminogenemia</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean MRT of baseline-adjusted plasminogen antigen after the first and Week 12 dose of study drug treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>To determine the mean MRT of baseline-adjusted plasminogen antigen in subjects with hypoplasminogenemia</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean Vd of baseline-adjusted plasminogen antigen after the first and Week 12 dose of study drug treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>To determine the mean Vd of baseline-adjusted plasminogen antigen in subjects with hypoplasminogenemia</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean t1/2 of baseline-adjusted plasminogen antigen after the first and Week 12 dose of study drug treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>To determine the mean t1/2 of baseline-adjusted plasminogen antigen in subjects with hypoplasminogenemia</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean Cmax of baseline-adjusted plasminogen antigen after the first and Week 12 dose of study drug treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>To determine the mean t1/2 of baseline-adjusted plasminogen antigen in subjects with hypoplasminogenemia</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Abnormal D-dimer levels after study drug treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>48 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Abnormal D-dimer levels in subjects with hypoplasminogenemia</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">15</enrollment>
  <condition>Hypoplasminogenemia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>6.6 mg/kg Plasminogen (Human) Intravenous</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>6.6 mg/kg Plasminogen (Human) Intravenous given every 2 to 4 days by a 10- to 30-minute intravenous infusion for 48 weeks (Norway) and longer until product licensing or study termination by the Sponsor (US).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Plasminogen (Human) intravenous</intervention_name>
    <description>Prometic Plasminogen (Human) intravenous infusion given as single dose of 6.6 mg/kg in Segment 1 and repeat doses in Segments 2 and 3.</description>
    <arm_group_label>6.6 mg/kg Plasminogen (Human) Intravenous</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Subject is a male or female between the ages of 2 and 80 years (inclusive), is able to
             provide informed consent or assent, and agrees to use contraceptive methods during the
             study (unless documented as biologically or surgically sterile or has not reached
             reproductive age).

          -  Subject has documented history of hypoplasminogenemia and has plasminogen activity
             level ≤ 45%.

          -  Subject has documented vaccination to hepatitis A virus (HAV) and hepatitis B virus
             (HBV), or has received the first dose of HAV and HBV vaccine prior to the first dose
             of IMP and is scheduled to receive the second vaccine dose.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Subject has uncontrolled hypertension; clinical or laboratory evidence of an
             intercurrent infection; a malignancy within 3 years, except for basal or squamous cell
             skin cancer; a psychiatric disorder; chronic or acute clinically significant
             inter-current illness; or evidence of renal and hepatic dysfunction.

          -  Subject is pregnant or lactating

          -  Subject has a history of anaphylactic reactions to blood or blood products that may
             interfere with participation in study in the opinion of the investigator.

          -  Subject is a previous organ transplant recipient; has received exogenous plasminogen
             within 2 weeks of the screening; has a history of anaphylactic reactions to blood or
             blood products; or has received another IRB-approved interventional clinical trial of
             a drug, biologic, or device within 30 days before the first dose of the IMP.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>2 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Amy Shapiro, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Indiana Hemophilia &amp; Thrombosis Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Indiana Hemophilia and Thrombosis Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Indianapolis</city>
        <state>Indiana</state>
        <zip>46260</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Oslo University Hospital HF</name>
      <address>
        <city>Oslo</city>
        <state>Sognsvannvejen 20</state>
        <zip>0372</zip>
        <country>Norway</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Norway</country>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shapiro AD, Nakar C, Parker JM, Albert GR, Moran JE, Thibaudeau K, Thukral N, Hardesty BM, Laurin P, Sandset PM. Plasminogen replacement therapy for the treatment of children and adults with congenital plasminogen deficiency. Blood. 2018 Mar 22;131(12):1301-1310. doi: 10.1182/blood-2017-09-806729. Epub 2018 Jan 10.</citation>
    <PMID>29321155</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>December 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 12, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 19, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 24, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <disposition_first_submitted>December 4, 2019</disposition_first_submitted>
  <disposition_first_submitted_qc>December 5, 2019</disposition_first_submitted_qc>
  <disposition_first_posted type="Actual">December 9, 2019</disposition_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 6, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 6, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">December 10, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Coagulation Protein Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Plasminogen</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted, but a results disposition has been submitted           -->
</clinical_study>

