<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03686865</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>4597 bis</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03686865</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Peri-implant Marginal Bone and Soft Tissue Conditions Around Single Laser-Lok Implants Placed in Regenerated Extraction Sockets and in Native Bone: A 2-years Results of RCT</brief_title>
  <official_title>Peri-implant Marginal Bone and Soft Tissue Conditions Around Single Laser-Lok Implants Placed in Regenerated Extraction Sockets and in Native Bone: A 2-years Results of RCT</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Roma La Sapienza</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Roma La Sapienza</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The aim of present study was to compare peri-implant marginal bone loss and soft tissues
      conditions around single Laser-Lok implants placed in alveolar
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Records of 20 consecutive patients treated with dental implants placed in post-extraction
      sockets augmented with porcine derived bone and 20 consecutive patients with implants placed
      in native bone were reviewed. For each implant, the radio- graphs from the surgical
      appointment were compared to those from the last follow-up visit and evaluated regarding
      changes of marginal bone level over time.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 18, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">September 18, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">September 18, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>peri-implant marginal bone loss</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>peri-implant soft tissue conditions</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Partially Edentulous Maxilla, Partially Edentulous Mandible</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>dental implants</arm_group_label>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>dental implants</intervention_name>
    <description>extraction sockets regenerated with xenograft</description>
    <arm_group_label>dental implants</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>porcine derived bone</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        patients with monoedentulism
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  mono-edentulism, age ≥ 18 years, good general health, without contraindications to
             implant surgery

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  lack of a periodontal chart and periapical radiograph at the beginning and at the end
             of follow-up period, alcohol and drug abuse, pregnancy, or uncontrolled metabolic
             disorders, tobacco smoking (&gt; 10 cigarettes/day), full mouth plaque score (FMPS), and
             full mouth bleeding score /FMBS) ≥25%, teeth adjacent to the implant area (mesial and
             distal) affected by untreated periodontal and/or endodontic infections.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Universita la Sapienza</name>
      <address>
        <city>Roma</city>
        <zip>00100</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Italy</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>1. Carlsson GE, Bergman B, Hedega ̊rd B. Changes in contour of the maxillary alveolar process under im- mediate dentures. A longitudinal clinical and x-ray cephalometric study covering 5 years. Acta Odontol Scand 1967;25:45-75. 2. Arau ́jo MG, Lindhe J. Dimensional ridge alterations following tooth extraction. An experimental study in the dog. J Clin Periodontol 2005;32:212-218. 3. Pietrokovski J, Massler M. Alveolar ridge resorption following tooth extraction. J Prosthet Dent 1967;17: 21-27. 4. Johnson K. A study of the dimensional changes occurring in the maxilla following tooth extraction. Aust Dent J 1969;14:241-244. 5. Schropp L, Wenzel A, Kostopoulos L, Karring T. Bone healing and soft tissue contour changes following single-tooth extraction: A clinical and radiographic 12- month prospective study. Int J Periodontics Restor- ative Dent 2003;23:313-323. 6. Arau ́jo MG, Carmagnola D, Berglundh T, Thilander B, Lindhe J. Orthodontic movement in bone defects augmented with Bio-Oss. An experimental study in dogs. J Clin Periodontol 2001;28:73-80. 7. Carmagnola D, Berglundh T, Lindhe J. The effect of a fibrin glue on the integration of Bio-Oss with bone tissue. An experimental study in Labrador dogs. J Clin Periodontol 2002;29:377-383. 8. Cardaropoli G, Arau ́jo M, Hayacibara R, Sukekava F, Lindhe J. Healing of extraction sockets and surgically produced - augmented and non-augmented - defects in the alveolar ridge. An experimental study in the dog. J Clin Periodontol 2005;32:435-440. 9. Becker W, Clokie C, Sennerby L, Urist MR, Becker BE. Histologic findings after implantation and evaluation of different grafting materials and titanium micro screws into extraction sockets: Case reports. J Periodontol 1998;69:414-421. 10. Artzi Z, Tal H, Dayan D. Porous bovine bone mineral in healing of human extraction sockets. Part 1: Histo- morphometric evaluations at 9 months. J Periodontol 2000;71:1015-1023. 11. Artzi Z, Tal H, Dayan D. Porous bovine bone mineral in healing of human extraction sockets: 2. Histochemical observations at 9 months. J Periodontol 2001;72:152- 159. 12. Iasella JM, Greenwell H, Miller RL, et al. Ridge preservation with freeze-dried bone allograft and a col- lagen membrane compared to extraction alone for implant site development: A clinical and histologic study in humans. J Periodontol 2003;74:990-999. 13. Carmagnola D, Adriaens P, Berglundh T. Healing of human extraction sockets filled with Bio-Oss. Clin Oral Implants Res 2003;14:137-143. 14. Becker W, Urist M, Becker BE, et al. Clinical and histologic observations of sites implanted with intrao- ral autologous bone grafts or allografts. 15 human case reports. J Periodontol 1996;67:1025-1033. 15. Froum S, Cho SC, Rosenberg E, Rohrer M, Tarnow D. Histological comparison of healing extraction sockets implanted with bioactive glass or demineralized freeze-dried bone allograft: A pilot study. J Periodontol 2002;73:94-102. 16. Barone A, Aldini NN, Fini M, Giardino R, Calvo Guirado JL, Covani U. Xenograft versus extraction alone for ridge preservation after tooth removal: A clinical and histomorphometric study. J Periodontol 2008;79:1370-1377. 17. Lekovic V, Kenney EB, Weinlaender M, et al. A bone regenerative approach to alveolar ridge maintenance following tooth extraction. Report of 10 cases. J Periodontol 1997;68:563-570. 18. Lekovic V, Camargo PM, Klokkevold PR, et al. Pres- ervation of alveolar bone in extraction sockets using bioabsorbable membranes. J Periodontol 1998;69: 1044-1049. 19. Nevins M, Camelo M, De Paoli S, et al. A study of the fate of the buccal wall of extraction sockets of teeth with prominent roots. Int J Periodontics Restorative Dent 2006;26:19-29. 20. Albrektsson T, Bra ̊ nemark PI, Hansson HA, Lindstro ̈ m J. Osseointegrated titanium implants. Requirements for ensuring a long-lasting, direct bone-to-implant anchorage in man. Acta Orthop Scand 198</citation>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>September 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 25, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 25, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 27, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 25, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 25, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">September 27, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Roma La Sapienza</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Renzo Guarnieri</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>adjunct professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>regenerated bone, native bone, dental implant</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Mouth, Edentulous</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

