<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03681639</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>09-H00</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03681639</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Metasul Monoblock Component™ Cup in a Hip Resurfacing Application With the Durom® Hip Resurfacing Femoral Component</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Multi-Centre, Prospective Study to Obtain Survival and Clinical Outcome Data on the Zimmer Hip Resurfacing System Utilising the Metasul Monoblock Component™ Cup in a Hip Resurfacing Application With the Durom® Hip Resurfacing Femoral Component</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Zimmer Biomet</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Zimmer Biomet</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The Zimmer Hip Resurfacing System Post-Market Clinical Follow-up study will examine the
      safety and efficacy of this device in the young and/or active patient with advanced hip
      disease.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a multi-center, prospective, non-controlled post market surveillance study. The
      objective of this study is to obtain survival and outcome data on the Zimmer Hip Resurfacing
      System. This will be assessed by analysis of standard scoring systems, radiographs and
      adverse event records. Data will be used to monitor pain, mobility and survivorship, and to
      confirm the safety and efficacy of the Zimmer Hip Resurfacing System. Serum metal ion levels
      (cobalt and chromium) will also be collected pre-operatively and again at 6 months, 1 year, 2
      years and 5 years. This procedure will offer an option to these patients who would otherwise
      require and likely outlive a conventional total hip replacement.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">August 1, 2009</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 31, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 31, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Implant survival based on removal or intended removal of the device and determined using the Kaplan-Meier method</measure>
    <time_frame>10 years post-surgery</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pain and functional performance based on the Harris Hip Score</measure>
    <time_frame>10 years post-surgery</time_frame>
    <description>The Harris Hip Score is a questionnaire filled by the surgeon with the patient who received a hip implant. The domains covered are pain, function, absence of deformity, and range of motion. The pain domain measures pain severity and its effect on activities and need for pain medication.
The function domain consists of daily activities (stair use, using public transportation, sitting, and managing shoes and socks) and gait (limp, support needed, and walking distance). Deformity takes into account hip flexion, adduction, internal rotation, and extremity length discrepancy. Range of motion measures hip flexion, abduction, external and internal rotation, and adduction.
There are 10 items. The score has a maximum of 100 points (best possible outcome) covering pain (1 item, 0-44 points), function (7 items, 0-47 points), absence of deformity (1 item, 4 points), and range of motion (2 items, 5 points).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Subject quality-of-life determined by the SF-12 questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>10 years post-surgery</time_frame>
    <description>The SF-12 Questionnaire (form 7) is a 12-item questionnaire in accordance with the &quot;quality of life&quot; questioning standards of the American Academy of Orthopaedic Surgeons (AAOS) Committee for Outcomes Research. The questions determine the patient's physical, emotional and social health and will be used to calculate a physical and mental functional score.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient's activity level determined by UCLA Score</measure>
    <time_frame>10 years post-surgery</time_frame>
    <description>The University of California at Los Angeles (UCLA) Score surveys a patient's hip and knee pain and function on a 10-point scale from a 1 - &quot;wholly inactive: dependent upon others; cannot leave residence,&quot; to a 5 - &quot;sometimes participate in moderate activities,&quot; to a 10 - &quot;regularly participate in impact sports, such as jogging, tennis, skiing, acrobatics, ballet, heavy labor, or backpacking.&quot;</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety based on eventual complications occurred including dislocations and revisions/removals</measure>
    <time_frame>10 years post-surgery</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>X-rays evaluated for radiolucencies, osteolysis, hypertrophy, subsidence, heterotopic ossification, etc</measure>
    <time_frame>10 years post-surgery</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Metal ion (whole blood cobalt and chromium) determined by blood analysis</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years post-surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Metal ion levels (cobalt and chromium) content will be evaluated for all study subjects enrolled in this study. To prevent intra-observer variation, an approved Central Laboratory will provide specimen collection kits for the transfer of blood specimens and will analysed the metal ion concentrations. The cobalt and chromium contents will be measured by induced coupled plasma mass spectrometry (ICP-MS). The Blood Analysis Form will then be completed by the Investigator or his/her designee from the results of the blood analysis.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Renal function (BUN) determined by blood analysis</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years post-surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Renal function (BUN) will be evaluated for all study subjects enrolled in this study. Phlebotomy (blood drawing), and evaluation of BUN content will be conducted locally. The Blood Analysis Form will then be completed by the Investigator or his/her designee from the results of the blood analysis.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Renal function (Creatinine) determined by blood analysis</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years post-surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Renal function (Creatinine) will be evaluated for all study subjects enrolled in this study. Phlebotomy (blood drawing), and evaluation of Creatinine content will be conducted locally. The Blood Analysis Form will then be completed by the Investigator or his/her designee from the results of the blood analysis.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Renal function (GFR) determined by blood analysis</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years post-surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Renal function (GFR) will be evaluated for all study subjects enrolled in this study. Phlebotomy (blood drawing), and evaluation of GFR content will be conducted locally. The Blood Analysis Form will then be completed by the Investigator or his/her designee from the results of the blood analysis.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Subject quality-of-life determined by the EQ-5D (EuroQoI) score</measure>
    <time_frame>10 years post-surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Optional: EQ-5D is a standardized instrument for measuring health status. It is made up for two components.
The description part: health status is measured in five dimensions (5D); mobility, self-care, usual activities, pain/discomfort, and anxiety/depression. Mobility dimension asks about the person's walking ability. Self-care dimension asks about the ability to wash or dress by oneself. Usual activities dimension measures performance in &quot;work, study, housework, family or leisure activities&quot;. In pain/discomfort dimension, it asks how much pain or discomfort they have. In anxiety/depression dimension, it asks how anxious or depressed they are.
Visual analogue scale: The patient marks his health status on the day of the interview on a 20 cm vertical scale with end points of 0 and 100. The bottom rate (0) corresponds to &quot; the worst health you can imagine&quot;, and the highest rate (100) corresponds to &quot;the best health you can imagine&quot;.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Pain and functional performance based on the Oxford Patient Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>10 years post-surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Optional: the Oxford Hip Score Form consists of 12 questions relative to the function and pain associated of the hip and completed by the patient.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Pain and functional performance based on the Western Ontario and McMaster Universities Osteoarthritis Index (WOMAC)</measure>
    <time_frame>10 years post-surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Optional: the WOMAC Score is a patient completed questionnaire developed to assess pain and functional ability in patients suffering from osteoporosis.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">225</enrollment>
  <condition>Avascular Necrosis of Hip</condition>
  <condition>Osteoarthritis, Hip</condition>
  <condition>Rheumatoid Arthritis</condition>
  <condition>Inflammatory Arthritis</condition>
  <condition>Post-traumatic; Arthrosis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Patients who received Metasul Monoblock in hip resurfacing</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients who received the Zimmer Hip Resurfacing System utilising the Metasul Monoblock Component™ Cup in a Hip Resurfacing Application with the Durom® Hip Resurfacing Femoral Component and whose Serum metal ion levels is being measured.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Serum Metal ion levels determined to monitor changes in chromium and cobalt levels</intervention_name>
    <description>Analyses will be performed pre-operatively, 6 months, 1 year, 2 years and 5 years postoperatively for all study subjects enrolled in this study, as well as, all revision study subjects receiving the Metasul® LDH™ total hip system. To prevent intra-observer variation the metal ion concentrations will be analysed by an approved Central Laboratory. The Central Laboratory will provide specimen collection kits for the transfer of blood specimens to the Laboratory for analysis. The Laboratory will provide the results to the Investigators. The cobalt and chromium will be measured by induced coupled plasma mass spectrometry (ICP-MS). BUN, creatinine and GFR will be determined locally.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Patients who received Metasul Monoblock in hip resurfacing</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Patient selection without bias to race or gender.

          2. Patient is ≥ 18 and ≤ 65 years of age.

          3. Female patients only, if

               1. Actively practicing a contraceptive method, or

               2. Surgically sterilized, or

               3. Post-menopausal

          4. Pre-operative Harris Hip Score ≤ 70.

          5. Primary surgical hip candidate, suffering from hip pain and/or disability due to
             degenerative joint disease (inflammatory or non-inflammatory), based on physical
             examination and history, which may include the following diagnosis:

               1. Non-inflammatory degenerative joint disease (NIDJD), e.g. avascular necrosis or
                  osteoarthritis

               2. Inflammatory joint disease (IJD), e.g., rheumatoid arthritis

          6. Patient is willing and able to cooperate in prescribed post-operative therapy.

          7. Patient is willing and able to complete scheduled follow-up evaluations as described
             in the Informed Consent.

          8. Patient has participated in the Informed Consent process and has signed an Ethics
             Committee approved Informed Consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Patient has an acute, chronic, local or systemic infection.

          2. Patient is skeletally immature.

          3. Patient is known to be pregnant.

          4. Patient has a severe muscular, neural or vascular disease that endangers the involved
             extremity.

          5. Patient has an insufficient acetabular or femoral bone stock in which good anchorage
             of the implants are unlikely or impossible, including, but not limited to:

               1. patient with severe osteopenia,

               2. patients with a family history of severe osteoporosis or osteopenia,

               3. patients with osteonecrosis or avascular necrosis (AVN) with &gt;50% involvement of
                  the femoral head (regardless of FICAT grade), or

               4. patients with local bone tumors and/or cysts of the femoral head &gt; 1 cm

          6. Patient has a total or partial absence of the muscular or ligamentous apparatus.

          7. Patient has known moderate to severe renal insufficiency.

          8. Patient has a known clinical condition which may interfere with the patient's outcome,
             including but not limited to:

               1. immunocompromised conditions (AIDS),

               2. organ transplant,

               3. high doses of corticosteroids etc

          9. Patient is severely overweight (BMI &gt; 40)

         10. Patient is scheduled for simultaneous bilateral total hip replacement.

         11. OPERATIVE (IPSILATERAL) HIP: Patient has a total prosthetic hip replacement device,
             surface arthroplasty, endoprosthesis or femoral and/or acetabular osteosynthesis.

         12. CONTRALATERAL HIP: Patient has had a hip replacement, surface arthroplasty or
             endoprosthesis, within the past 12 months, unless previously enrolled in this clinical
             study.

         13. Patient is:

               1. a prisoner,

               2. mentally incompetent,

               3. a known alcohol or drug abuser,

               4. anticipated to be non-compliant

         14. Patient has participated in a study of any other investigational device (drug, device
             or biologic) within the past 12 months. Exception: previous enrollment in the Zimmer
             Hip Resurfacing clinical study.

         15. Patient has a known allergy to one of the constituents of the implant, e.g. cobalt,
             chromium, nickel, etc.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Paola Vivoda</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Zimmer Biomet</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Medizinische Fakultàt Carl Gustav Carus der Technischen Universität Dresden</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dresden</city>
        <zip>01307</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Germany</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 13, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 20, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 24, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 17, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 17, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 21, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Hip resurfacing</keyword>
  <keyword>Medical Device</keyword>
  <keyword>Safety</keyword>
  <keyword>Hip prosthesis</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Arthritis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Osteoarthritis, Hip</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Joint Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Necrosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cobalt</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Chromium</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

