<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03688061</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PEACHI-03</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2016-000983-41</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03688061</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Class II Invariant Chain HCV Vaccine Study</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase-I Dose-Escalation Study to Evaluate the Safety and Immunogenicity of Prime-Boost Immunisations With Candidate HCV Vaccines, ChAd3-hliNSMut and MVA-hliNSMut in Healthy Volunteers and Patients Previously Chronically Infected With HCV</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Oxford</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Oxford University Hospitals NHS Trust</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>ReiThera Srl</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>European Commission</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>GlaxoSmithKline</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Oxford</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The study is aimed at assessing the safety and immunogenicity of HCV prime-boost vaccinations
      ChAd3-hliNSmut and MVA-hliNSmut, administered intramuscularly in healthy volunteers and DAA
      treated patients.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Hepatitis C currently infects more than 180 million people worldwide and is associated with
      the development of liver cancer, liver failure and liver cirrhosis. Although drug treatments
      are available these are expensive and prolonged. Furthermore patients often only present to
      health care professionals at late stages when liver disease has already progressed.
      Therefore, vaccination remains the optimal method of preventing infection. To date this has
      proved extremely difficult due to the enormous variation in HCV strains around the world.

      Researchers at the University of Oxford in collaboration with industry, have developed novel
      candidate vaccines against HCV ('NSmut'). These vaccines have been inserted into the carrier
      viruses Chimpanzee Adenovirus (ChAd) and modified vaccinia virus Ankara (MVA), both of which
      have excellent safety records. These vaccines have been given to hundreds of healthy
      volunteers and are now being tested for effectiveness.

      In this study we are hoping to increase the immune response against the HCV virus. We will do
      this by inserting a gene in the vaccine (class-II invariant gene). In animal studies, this
      approach has been shown to be safe and to significantly to enhance the immune response
      against HCV.

      During this study 15 healthy adults and 10 volunteers who were previously treated for HCV
      infection, aged 18-65 years, will receive either two intramuscular injections over a period
      of two months. All participants will be followed up for a further 6 months (12 visits in
      total) and will be asked to give a blood sample at each clinic visit.

      The aims of the study are to assess the safety of the vaccine and to see if the vaccine can
      induce a strong immune response against the hepatitis C Virus.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">December 4, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 4, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 4, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Sequential Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Each group will be sequentially recruited over a period of two months to allow for safety review.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of volunteers who develop a grade 3 local and systemic reactions</measure>
    <time_frame>Actively collected throughout the study until 6 months after the last vaccination</time_frame>
    <description>To evaluate the safety of administering HCV prime-boost vaccinations, ChAd3-hliNSmut and MVA-hilNSmut intramuscularly in healthy volunteers and DAA treated volunteers that were previously infected with HCV</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of volunteers who develop T cell responses to HCV epitopes, as determined by INF-gamma ELISpot assay</measure>
    <time_frame>Actively collected throughout the study until 6 months after the last vaccination</time_frame>
    <description>To assess the cellular immune response generated by HCV prime-boost vaccinations, ChAd3-hliNSmut and MVA-hliNSmut administered intramuscularly to healthy volunteers and DAA treated volunteers that were previously infected with HCV</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">25</enrollment>
  <condition>Hepatitis C</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group 1 (low dose/healthy volunteers)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>5 healthy volunteers receiving 1 dose ChAd3-hliNSmut (5x10*9 vp) IM at week 0 and 1 dose of MVA-hliNSmut (5 X10*7 pfu) IM at week 8</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group 2 (higher dose/healthy volunteers)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>10 healthy volunteers receiving 1 dose ChAd3-hliNSmut (2.5 x10*10 vp) IM at week 0 and 1 dose of MVA-hliNSmut (2 X 10*8 pfu) IM at week 8</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group 3 (higher dose/HCV cured volunteers)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>10 DAA treated volunteers (previously HCV positive) receiving 1 dose ChAd3-hliNSmut (2.5 x10*10 vp) IM at week 0 and 1 dose of MVA-hliNSmut (2 X10*8 pfu) IM at week 8</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ChAd3-hliNSmut</intervention_name>
    <description>Attenuated chimpanzee adenovirus (ChAd) vectored vaccine against HCV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group 1 (low dose/healthy volunteers)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Group 2 (higher dose/healthy volunteers)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Group 3 (higher dose/HCV cured volunteers)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>MVA-hliNSmut</intervention_name>
    <description>Modified Vaccinia Ankara (MVA) vectored vaccine against HCV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group 1 (low dose/healthy volunteers)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Group 2 (higher dose/healthy volunteers)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Group 3 (higher dose/HCV cured volunteers)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Aged at least 18 years on the day of screening and no greater than 65 years on the day
             of the first vaccination

          -  Resident in or easy access to the trial site for the duration of the study

          -  Available for follow-up for the planned duration of the study

          -  Able and willing (in the CI's opinion) to comply with all study requirements

          -  Willing to allow the investigators to discuss the volunteer's medical history with
             their General Practitioner

          -  For heterosexual females, willingness to practice continuous effective contraception
             from screening until 4 months after the last immunisation

          -  All female volunteers must be willing to undergo urine pregnancy tests at the time
             points specified in the Schedule of Procedures and must have a negative pregnancy test
             on the day(s) of vaccination

          -  For sexually active men, willingness to use condoms from screening until 4 months
             after the last vaccination

          -  Agreement to refrain from blood donation during the course of the study

          -  In the opinion of the Chief Investigator or designee, the volunteer has understood the
             information provided. Written informed consent must be given before any study-related
             procedures are performed

          -  Willing to undergo HCV and HIV testing, counselling and receive test results

        Specific for Groups 1 and 2:

        • Healthy males or females, as assessed by medical history, physical examination and
        laboratory tests

        Specific for Group 3:

          -  A previous diagnosis of chronic HCV infection (any HCV genotype) successfully treated
             with all oral DAA therapy.

          -  Minimum duration of six months between last dose of DAA treatment and planned
             vaccination date

          -  SVR 12 following last DAA treatment course

          -  Fibroscan score of &lt;12.5kPa within 6 months of screening.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Participation in another research study involving an investigational product in the 30
             days preceding enrolment, or planned used during the study period

          -  Prior receipt of a recombinant simian adenoviral vaccine

          -  Receipt of any investigational HCV vaccine within the last 6 years

          -  Administration of immunoglobulins and/or any blood products within the last three
             months preceding the planned administration of the vaccine candidate

          -  Receipt of live attenuated vaccine within the previous 60 days or planned receipt
             within 60 days after vaccination with the IMP

          -  Receipt of other vaccine, including influenza vaccine, within the previous 14 days or
             planned receipt within 14 days after vaccination with the IMP

          -  Any confirmed or suspected immunosuppressive or immunodeficient state, including HIV
             infection; asplenia; recurrent, severe infections and chronic (more than 14 days)
             immunosuppressive medication within the last 6 months (inhaled and topical steroids
             are allowed)

          -  History of allergic disease or reactions likely to be exacerbated by any component of
             the vaccine

          -  Any history of anaphylaxis in reaction to vaccination

          -  Pregnancy, lactation or willingness/intention to become pregnant during the study

          -  Personal history of autoimmune disease

          -  History of major autoimmune disease in first degree relative, e.g. Type 1 diabetes,
             Graves' Disease, Systemic Lupus Erythematosus (SLE) or Spondyloarthropathy (AS).

          -  HLA type B27 positive individuals

          -  History of cancer (except basal cell carcinoma of the skin and cervical carcinoma in
             situ)

          -  History of serious psychiatric condition

          -  Any other serious chronic illness requiring hospital specialist supervision

          -  Suspected or known current alcohol abuse as defined by an alcohol intake of greater
             than 42 units every week

          -  Suspected or known current injecting drug use

          -  Seropositive for hepatitis B surface antigen (HBsAg)

          -  Any clinically significant acute or chronic medical condition that is considered
             unstable/progressive, or in the opinion of the Chief Investigator, may either put the
             volunteer at risk because of participation in the study, or may influence the result
             of the study, or the volunteer's ability to participate in the study

          -  Any clinically significant abnormal finding on screening biochemistry or haematology
             blood test or urinalysis

          -  Any other finding which in the opinion of the investigators would significantly
             increase the risk of having an adverse outcome from participating in the protocol

          -  Vulnerable subjects (according to ICH GCP)

        Specific for groups 1 and 2:

          -  Previous HCV infection

          -  Reported current or previous high-risk behaviour for HCV infection (including IVDU)

          -  Seropositive for hepatitis C virus (antibodies to HCV) at screening

        Specific for group 3:

          -  Reported current high-risk behaviour for HCV infection (previous IVDU is not an
             exclusion criteria for this group)

          -  HCV RNA positive following DAA treatment

          -  Cirrhosis or severe fibrosis (Ishak 5 or 6) as previously defined by any of the
             following:

               -  Radiological findings on CT, MR or USS

               -  Abnormal biochemical parameters (PT, albumin and bilirubin)

               -  clinical signs of liver decompensation (ascites, varices, encephalopathy)

               -  Ishak score 5 on liver biopsy

               -  Fibroscan at any time point in the past &gt;12.5kPa
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Eleanor Barnes, Professor</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>University of Oxford</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Lucy Dorrell, Professor</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Oxford</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Eleanor Barnes, Professor</last_name>
    <phone>01865 281547</phone>
    <email>ellie.barnes@ndm.ox.ac.uk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Centre for Cinical Vaccinology and Tropical Medicine, Univeristy of Oxford</name>
      <address>
        <city>Oxford</city>
        <state>Oxfordshire</state>
        <zip>OX3 7LJ</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Eleanor Barnes, Prof</last_name>
      <email>ellie.barnes@ndm.ox.ac.uk</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hepatology Clinical Trial Unit, John Radcliffe Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Oxford</city>
        <state>Oxfordshire</state>
        <zip>OX3 9DU</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Eleanor Barnes, Prof</last_name>
      <email>ellie.barnes@ndm.ox.ac.uk</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 19, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 26, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 27, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 26, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 26, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">September 27, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Hepatitis</keyword>
  <keyword>Vaccine</keyword>
  <keyword>Adenoviral-vector</keyword>
  <keyword>human invariant chain</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis C</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

