<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03688880</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>KF7021-04</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>1012937</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03688880</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Clinical Study to Compare MAR-CUTIS With Dermabond Advanced</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized, Open-label, Multi-center, Controlled Clinical Study to Compare MAR-CUTIS With Dermabond Advanced in Closure of Surgical Incisions and Lacerations up to 15 Centimeters</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Grünenthal GmbH</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Syneos Health</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Grünenthal GmbH</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_unapproved_device>Yes</is_unapproved_device>
    <is_us_export>Yes</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a randomized, open-label, multicenter, comparator-controlled clinical study to
      compare MAR-CUTIS with Dermabond Advanced in closure of surgical incisions and lacerations
      ≤15 cm. Eligible subjects will be randomized 2:1 to MAR-CUTIS or Dermabond Advanced.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Sponsor decision
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 30, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">September 4, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">July 17, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Total dehiscence rate of the target incision/laceration at Day 10</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Day 10 (+/- 2 days)</time_frame>
    <description>Only one incision/laceration will be treated with the Investigational Medical Device. The total dehiscence rate of the target incision/laceration will be compared between MAR-CUTIS and Dermabond Advance.
The dehiscence will be defined as &quot;yes&quot; if the wound show dehiscence or &quot;No&quot; if the wound remains closed.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of adverse events reported within 1 month after closure of the surgical incision/laceration</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Month 1 (+/- 7 days)</time_frame>
    <description>Adverse events reported within 1 month after treatment will be classified by severity and relatedness to the treatment. The incidences of mild, moderate, and severe and of related adverse events will be compared between MAR-CUTIS and Dermabond Advanced.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Total dehiscence rate of the target incision/laceration at 1 month after closure of the surgical incision/laceration</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Month 1 (+/- 7 days)</time_frame>
    <description>Only one incision/laceration will be treated with the Investigational Medical Device. The total dehiscence rate of the target incision/laceration will be compared between MAR-CUTIS and Dermabond Advance.
The dehiscence will be defined as &quot;yes&quot; if the wound show dehiscence or &quot;No&quot; if the wound remains closed.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Subject-completed Patient and Observer Scar Assessment Scale at 1 month after closure of the surgical incision/laceration</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Month 1 (+/- 7 days)</time_frame>
    <description>To assess the subjects' satisfaction with the cosmetic outcome, subjects will complete the patient scale of the Patient and Observer Scar Assessment Scale (POSAS) at 1 month after treatment with MAR-CUTIS or Dermabond Advance. The POSAS is a questionnaire that was developed to assess scar quality. It consists of 2 separate 6-item scales (Patient Scale and Observer Scale), both of which are scored on a 10-point rating scale. In addition, each scale has an overall &quot;opinion&quot; with 1 being no pain, no itching, or normal skin and 10 being worst scar imaginable with pain and itching.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Subject-completed Patient and Observer Scar Assessment Scale at 3 months after closure of the surgical incision/laceration</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Month 3 (+/- 14 days)</time_frame>
    <description>To assess the subjects' satisfaction with the cosmetic outcome, subjects will complete the patient scale of the POSAS at 3 months after treatment with MAR-CUTIS or Dermabond Advance. The POSAS is a questionnaire that was developed to assess scar quality. It consists of 2 separate 6-item scales (Patient Scale and Observer Scale), both of which are scored on a 10-point rating scale. In addition, each scale has an overall &quot;opinion&quot; with 1 being no pain, no itching, or normal skin and 10 being worst scar imaginable with pain and itching.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Wound infection incidence at Day 10</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Day 10 (+/- 2 days)</time_frame>
    <description>The wound infection incidence will be assessed at the Day 10 scheduled visit (diagnosed according to the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention [CDC] criteria for surgical site infection) and will be compared between both treatment groups.
Wound infection will be assessed on a binary scale (&quot;1 - yes&quot; or &quot;0 - no&quot;) for the following criteria:
Presence of erythema
Presence of edema
Presence of pain at rest
Presence of elevated temperature
A total score will be calculated for each subject.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Wound infection incidence at 1 month after closure of the surgical incision/laceration</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Month 1 (+/- 7 days)</time_frame>
    <description>The wound infection incidence will be assessed at the 1-month follow-up visit (diagnosed according to the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention [CDC] criteria for surgical site infection) and will be compared between both treatment groups. Wound infection will be assessed on a binary scale (&quot;1 - yes&quot; or &quot;0 - no&quot;) for the following criteria:
Presence of erythema
Presence of edema
Presence of pain at rest
Presence of elevated temperature
A total score will be calculated for each subject.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Wound infection incidence at 3 months after closure of the surgical incision/laceration</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Month 3 (+/- 14 days)</time_frame>
    <description>The wound infection incidence will be assessed at the Month 3 visit (diagnosed according to the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention [CDC] criteria for surgical site infection) and will be compared between both treatment groups.
Wound infection will be assessed on a binary scale (&quot;1 - yes&quot; or &quot;0 - no&quot;) for the following criteria:
Presence of erythema
Presence of edema
Presence of pain at rest
Presence of elevated temperature
A total score will be calculated for each subject.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Investigator-completed Patient and Observer Scar Assessment Scale at 1 month after closure of the surgical incision/laceration</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Month 1 (+/- 7 days)</time_frame>
    <description>To assess the medical practitioner satisfaction with the cosmetic outcome, the investigator will complete the observer scale of the POSAS after 1 month of treatment with MAR-CUTIS or Dermabond Advance. The POSAS is a questionnaire that was developed to assess scar quality. It consists of 2 separate 6-item scales (Patient Scale and Observer Scale), both of which are scored on a 10-point rating scale. In addition, each scale has an overall &quot;opinion&quot; with 1 being no pain, no itching, or normal skin and 10 being worst scar imaginable with pain and itching.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Investigator-completed Patient and Observer Scar Assessment Scale at 3 months after closure of the surgical incision/laceration</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Month 3 (+/- 14 days)</time_frame>
    <description>To assess the medical practitioner satisfaction with the cosmetic outcome, the Investigator will complete the observer score of the POSAS at 3 months after treatment with MAR-CUTIS or Dermabond Advance. The POSAS is a questionnaire that was developed to assess scar quality. It consists of 2 separate 6-item scales (Patient Scale and Observer Scale), both of which are scored on a 10-point rating scale. In addition, each scale has an overall &quot;opinion&quot; with 1 being no pain, no itching, or normal skin and 10 being worst scar imaginable with pain and itching.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Investigator-completed Modified Hollander Cosmesis Scale at Day 10</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Day 10 (+/- 2 days)</time_frame>
    <description>The investigator's satisfaction with the cosmetic outcome will be assessed using the Modified Hollander Cosmesis Scale (mHCS). The mHCS consists of 6 wound characteristics, evaluated as &quot;poor&quot; or &quot;good&quot;. Each of the characteristics is graded on a 0 (no/good) or 1 (yes/poor) point scale. A total cosmetic score is derived by the addition of the scores.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Investigator-completed Modified Hollander Cosmesis Scale at 1 month after closure of the surgical incision/laceration</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Month 1 (+/- 7 days)</time_frame>
    <description>The investigator's satisfaction with the cosmetic outcome will be assessed using the mHCS. The mHCS consists of 6 wound characteristics, evaluated as &quot;poor&quot; or &quot;good&quot;. Each of the characteristics is graded on a 0 (no/good) or 1 (yes/poor) point scale. A total cosmetic score is derived by the addition of the scores.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Subject comfort with the device at Day 10</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Day 10 (+/- 2 days)</time_frame>
    <description>A questionnaire related to subject experience and satisfaction with the treatment they received will be used. The questionnaire consists of 5 yes/no questions that evaluate the subject's experience with the adhesive, 1 question that rates the effect of the closed wound on several daily activities (i.e., showering, getting dressed), 1 question that evaluates satisfaction with the wound closure, and visual analog scales which rate pain and scarring.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Subject comfort with the device at 1 month after closure of the surgical incision/laceration</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Month 1 (+/- 7 days)</time_frame>
    <description>A questionnaire related to subject experience and satisfaction with the treatment they received will be used. The questionnaire consists of 5 yes/no questions that evaluate the subject's experience with the adhesive, 1 question that rates the effect of the closed wound on several daily activities (i.e., showering, getting dressed), 1 question that evaluates satisfaction with the wound closure, and visual analog scales which rate pain and scarring.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Medical practitioner overall satisfaction and ease of use with the device during and after the closure of the target surgical incision/laceration</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Month 1 (+/- 7 days)</time_frame>
    <description>A questionnaire for investigators will be completed at the Month 1 visit. This questionnaire consists of 5 yes/no questions that assess the investigator's experience applying the adhesive (i.e., easy to use, fast, without complications), a visual scale that rates the usability of the product from 1 to 100, and 1 question that evaluates satisfaction with the adhesive.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">101</enrollment>
  <condition>Wounds and Injuries</condition>
  <condition>Lacerations</condition>
  <condition>Surgical Incision</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>MAR-CUTIS</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>MAR-CUTIS is a polyurethane-based skin adhesive. At the time of use, the 2 components, prepolymer and curing agent, in the syringe are mixed in the mixing cannula. MAR-CUTIS is distributed sterile and is intended for single use.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Dermabond Advanced</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Dermabond Advanced adhesive is supplied sterile, in a prefilled, single-use applicator. The pen-style applicator consists of a crushable ampoule contained within a plastic applicator. The active ingredient in Dermabond Advanced is 2-Octyl Cyanoacrylate.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>MAR-CUTIS</intervention_name>
    <description>MAR-CUTIS will be applied in one 1 to 2 mm thick layer, ensuring that at least 1 cm of the glue is applied over the length of the wound on each side. The amount of the glue applied will be calculated such that one 5-mL syringe covers approximately 8 cm of wound length (giving a total of 10 cm per syringe). For wounds &gt;8 cm, 2 syringes will be required. The wound will be held for approximately 30 seconds to allow for initial polymerization.</description>
    <arm_group_label>MAR-CUTIS</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Dermabond Advanced</intervention_name>
    <description>Dermabond Advanced will be applied in 1 continuous layer onto a dry wound through painting motions, taking care not to apply adhesive between the wound edges. The wound will be held for 60 seconds to allow for complete polymerization.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Dermabond Advanced</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        For subjects with surgical incisions:

          1. Subject undergoing closure of surgical incision 6 to 15 centimeters following
             laparotomy, abdominal hysterectomy, or laparoscopic intervention.

             For subjects with lacerations:

          2. Subject requiring closure of a laceration on face (avoiding the immediate area around
             the eye) or extremities. In subjects with multiple lacerations, one will be selected
             as the target wound (i.e., greatest length and meets the study entry criteria).

             For all subjects:

          3. Subject has given written informed consent/assent to participate.

          4. Male and female subjects at least 2 years of age and body weight 10 kg or greater.

          5. Subject willing and capable of following instructions for wound care provided by the
             investigator and agreeing to return for all treatment control visits specified in this
             clinical study.

        Exclusion Criteria:

        For subjects with lacerations:

          1. Wounds on mucosal surfaces or across mucocutaneous junctions (e.g., oral cavity, lips,
             eyes).

          2. Wounds which may be regularly exposed to body fluids or with dense natural hair (e.g.,
             scalp); wounds on ears.

          3. Wounds on palms and feet.

          4. Animal or human bites.

          5. Lacerations that are heavily contaminated.

          6. Punctured or crushed wounds.

          7. Subjects with lacerations having wound treatment more than 6 hours after the trauma.

             For all subjects:

          8. Subjects requiring suturing with sutures greater than 5 mm thickness.

          9. Subject with documented skin disease or skin conditions (e.g., excessive hair at the
             site of surgery, scar tissue, wound, tattoo, coloration, or pre-existing open sores at
             the site of surgery that would interfere with the application of Investigational
             Medical Device or the skin assessment, as judged by the investigator).

         10. Subject with any factors that may have an adverse effect on wound healing (e.g.,
             previous history of keloid formation or hypertrophy [as well in the family]), history
             of immunosuppression, chronic systemic infection, or poor general health.

         11. Subjects with known blood clotting disorders.

         12. Subjects receiving steroids, immunosuppressants, chemotherapy, or anticoagulants.

         13. Subject having known or suspected allergy or sensitivity to polyurethane,
             cyanoacrylates, formaldehyde, tapes or adhesives, or benzalkonium chloride.

         14. Subject participating in any current clinical study with a non-CE (&quot;Conformitee
             Europeene&quot;) marked device or investigational product.

         15. Subject who is pregnant or breastfeeding.

         16. Subject with history of a significant dermatologic disease or condition, such as
             atopic dermatitis, psoriasis, lichen ruber planus, vitiligo or conditions known to
             alter the skin appearance or physiologic response (e.g., decompensated diabetes
             mellitus, porphyria) that involves the investigative site.

        Removal of Subjects From Therapy or Assessments:

        Only subjects that are withdrawn from the study due to product failure at the time of
        application will be replaced.

        Subjects may stop the study for any of the following reasons:

          1. Subject request.

          2. Use of non-permitted concurrent therapy.

          3. Lost to follow-up (considered lost to follow-up only before Day 10).

          4. Occurrence of adverse events not compatible with the continuation of subject
             participation in the study, in the investigator's opinion, or unacceptable to the
             subject to continue.

               -  Investigator request

               -  Inter-current illness
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>2 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Study Director</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Grünenthal GmbH</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>004 - CHU Amiens-Picardie</name>
      <address>
        <city>Amiens</city>
        <zip>80054</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>005 - Hôpital Privé Paul d'Egine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Champigny-sur-Marne</city>
        <zip>94500</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>010 - Charité Berlin</name>
      <address>
        <city>Berlin</city>
        <zip>13353</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>006 - Universitätsklinikum Heidelberg</name>
      <address>
        <city>Heidelberg</city>
        <zip>69120</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>009 - Klinikum Magdeburg</name>
      <address>
        <city>Magdeburg</city>
        <zip>39130</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>001 - Hospital Universitari Vall d'Hebron</name>
      <address>
        <city>Barcelona</city>
        <zip>08035</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>022 - Hospital General Universitario Gregorio Maranon</name>
      <address>
        <city>Madrid</city>
        <zip>28007</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>003 - University Hospital Virgen del Rocío</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seville</city>
        <zip>41013</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>019 - Barnsley Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Barnsley</city>
        <zip>S75 2EP</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>017 - Birmingham Children's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Birmingham</city>
        <zip>B4 6NH</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>018 - Bristol Royal Hospital for Children</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bristol</city>
        <zip>BS2 8AE</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>021 - University Hospital of Wales</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cardiff</city>
        <zip>CF14 4XW</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>013 - The Princess Alexandra Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Harlow</city>
        <zip>CM20 1QX</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>011 - Leeds Teaching Hospitals</name>
      <address>
        <city>Leeds</city>
        <zip>LS9 7TF</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>016 - St George's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>London</city>
        <zip>SW17 0QT</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>014 - Queen Elizabeth the Queen Mother Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Margate</city>
        <zip>CT9 4AN</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>020 - Royal Gwent Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Newport</city>
        <zip>NP20 2UB</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>012 - Peterborough City Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Peterborough</city>
        <zip>PE3 9GZ</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>015 - Musgrove Park Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Taunton</city>
        <zip>TA1 5DA</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
    <country>Germany</country>
    <country>Spain</country>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 26, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 26, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 28, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 16, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 16, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">September 17, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Wounds</keyword>
  <keyword>Injuries</keyword>
  <keyword>Surgery</keyword>
  <keyword>Lacerations</keyword>
  <keyword>Wound healing</keyword>
  <keyword>Surgical Wounds</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Surgical Wound</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lacerations</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Wounds and Injuries</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <pending_results>
    <submitted>July 12, 2020</submitted>
  </pending_results>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

