<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03684408</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2011684</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03684408</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Radiofrequency Chip for Localization of Non-Palpable Breast Lesions</brief_title>
  <official_title>Use of a Radiofrequency Chip for Localization of Non-Palpable Breast Lesions: A Comparison to Wire Localization</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Missouri-Columbia</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Health Beacons</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Missouri-Columbia</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>Yes</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of the project is to compare Radiofrequency identification device (RFID)
      localization technique with the current clinical standard wire localization technique. The
      Investigator's hypotheses is that the RFID localization technique is non-inferior to wire
      localization for breast lesions (tumors).

      The study will be conducted in two parts. The purpose of Part A is for physician training
      with the RFID device. Nine subjects will undergo RFID and wire localization prior to breast
      lesion excision. This will allow the breast radiologists and surgeons to become comfortable
      with RFID device placement and retrieval. Additionally, the investigators will pilot the data
      collection surveys and chart review methodology to be used in Part B.

      The purpose of Part B is to conduct a randomized clinical trial to assess whether RFID
      localization is non-inferior to wire localization for breast lesions. For this part, sixty
      subjects will be randomized to RFID (N=30) or wire localization (N=30) at time of enrollment.
      Surveys will be used to gather data from participants, radiologists, surgeons, and
      technologists/mammography nurses. A variety of data will be collected including, but not
      limited to, information on tumor size, location, depth; subject demographics; adequacy of
      tumor margins, re-excision rates, accuracy of wire or chip placement, and surgical
      complications.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      As part of standard of care, participants will receive: an ultrasound (US) or mammographic
      guided localization; excisional breast surgery; and a follow-up visit in breast surgery
      clinic.

      As part of the research protocol, participants will receive a RFID chip for the localization
      procedure and complete surveys.

      Part A of this project is for physician training to master the technique of RFID placement
      and retrieval. On the day of surgery prior to going to the operating room, all participants
      will have the RFID placed first to allow radiologists to become familiar with placement of
      the RFID localizer. Participants will then immediately undergo wire localization. Either
      ultrasound or mammogram guidance will be used for the localization at the discretion of the
      performing radiologist. Surgeons will use a reader to locate the RFID chip during surgery.
      The wire will be present in the event the area of concern cannot be adequately located with
      the reader. Participants, radiologists, surgeons, breast surgery and radiology staff will
      complete surveys.

      Part B of this project is a prospective trial to examine safety, efficacy, operating room
      utilization patterns, and satisfaction with RFID versus wire localization. Participants will
      be stratified based on technique of localization (either US guidance or mammographic
      guidance). Participants will then be randomized to receive either the wire or RFID
      localization. There will be four visits: one pre-op breast surgery visit in which enrollment
      will occur, one radiology procedure visit for localization, one surgical visit, and one
      post-operative visit. This is the same number of visits as standard of care. Participants,
      radiologists, surgeons, breast surgery and radiology staff will complete surveys.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 18, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 31, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Success of localization</measure>
    <time_frame>From the date of localization through the date of surgery up to 4 weeks; data collected during Visit 3</time_frame>
    <description>Whether the surgeon was able to identify and remove the tumor</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Surveys of Satisfaction</measure>
    <time_frame>From the date of consent through the date of the final follow up visit up to 10 weeks; data collected during Visits 1, 2, and 4</time_frame>
    <description>Surveys of patient satisfaction with the localization procedure</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Surveys of Satisfaction</measure>
    <time_frame>From the date of consent through the date of the final follow up visit up to 10 weeks; data collected during Visit 1</time_frame>
    <description>Surveys of staff satisfaction with the localization procedure</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Surveys of Satisfaction</measure>
    <time_frame>From the date of localization to the date of surgery up to 4 weeks; data collected during Visits 2 and 3</time_frame>
    <description>Surveys of physician satisfaction with the localization procedure</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Size of Tumor Margins</measure>
    <time_frame>From the date of localization through the date of surgery up to 4 weeks; specimen collected during Visit 3</time_frame>
    <description>Size of tumor margins on pathology in mm</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">84</enrollment>
  <condition>Breast Tumor</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>RFID and Wire Localization</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Part A of this project is for physician training to master the technique of RFID placement and retrieval. On the day of surgery prior to going to the operating room, all participants will have the RFID placed first to allow radiologists to become familiar with placement of the RFID localizer. Participants will then immediately undergo wire localization. Either ultrasound or mammogram guidance will be used for the localization at the discretion of the performing radiologist. Surgeons will use a reader to locate the RFID chip during surgery. The wire will be present in the event the area of concern cannot be adequately located with the reader.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>RFID Localization</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will be stratified based on technique of localization (either US guidance or mammographic guidance). They will then be randomized to receive either the wire or RFID localization. There will be four visits: one pre-op breast surgery visit in which enrollment will occur, one radiology procedure visit for localization, one surgical visit, and one post-operative visit. This is the same number of visits as standard of care.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Wire Localization</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will be stratified based on technique of localization (either US guidance or mammographic guidance). They will then be randomized to receive either the wire or RFID localization. There will be four visits: one pre-op breast surgery visit in which enrollment will occur, one radiology procedure visit for localization, one surgical visit, and one post-operative visit. This is the same number of visits as standard of care.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>RFID Localization</intervention_name>
    <description>The RFID and wire localization devices used in this study are FDA approved for the image guided localization of breast tumors prior to surgical excision. The two techniques for localization will be compared in this trial.</description>
    <arm_group_label>RFID Localization</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Wire Localization</intervention_name>
    <description>The RFID and wire localization devices used in this study are FDA approved for the image guided localization of breast tumors prior to surgical excision. The two techniques for localization will be compared in this trial.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Wire Localization</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>RFID and Wire Localization</intervention_name>
    <description>Both RFID and the standard of care wire localization will be performed for physician training.</description>
    <arm_group_label>RFID and Wire Localization</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Women requiring image guided pre-operative breast tumor localization

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Tumors deeper than 6 cm from the skin surface

          -  More than one tumor requiring localization

          -  Tumors requiring bracketing

          -  Tumors requiring Magnetic Resonance Imaging localization

          -  Inability to complete survey

          -  Pregnancy
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Megha Garg, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Missouri-Columbia</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Joanne Cassani, RN, CCRC</last_name>
    <phone>573-882-3677</phone>
    <email>cassanij@health.missouri.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Megha Garg, MD</last_name>
    <phone>573-882-1026</phone>
    <email>gargmeg@health.missouri.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Missouri</name>
      <address>
        <city>Columbia</city>
        <state>Missouri</state>
        <zip>65212</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Joanne Cassani, RN</last_name>
      <phone>434-825-0494</phone>
      <email>cassanij@health.missouri.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Megha Garg, M.D.</last_name>
      <phone>5738821026</phone>
      <email>gargmeg@health.missouri.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dauphine C, Reicher JJ, Reicher MA, Gondusky C, Khalkhali I, Kim M. A prospective clinical study to evaluate the safety and performance of wireless localization of nonpalpable breast lesions using radiofrequency identification technology. AJR Am J Roentgenol. 2015 Jun;204(6):W720-3. doi: 10.2214/AJR.14.13201.</citation>
    <PMID>26001262</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Reicher JJ, Reicher MA, Thomas M, Petcavich R. Radiofrequency identification tags for preoperative tumor localization: proof of concept. AJR Am J Roentgenol. 2008 Nov;191(5):1359-65. doi: 10.2214/AJR.08.1023.</citation>
    <PMID>18941069</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>November 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 27, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 21, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 25, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 1, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 1, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 5, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Missouri-Columbia</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Megha Garg</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor of Clinical Radiology</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

