<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03688295</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PI2017_843_0002</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2017-000334-59</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03688295</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Value of Post-operative Antibiotic Therapy After Laparoscopic Appendectomy for Complicated Acute Appendicitis (Other Than for Generalized Peritonitis)</brief_title>
  <acronym>ABAP</acronym>
  <official_title>The Value of Post-operative Antibiotic Therapy After Laparoscopic Appendectomy for Complicated Acute Appendicitis (Other Than for Generalized Peritonitis): a Prospective, Randomized, Placebo-controlled Phase III Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Centre Hospitalier Universitaire, Amiens</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Centre Hospitalier Universitaire, Amiens</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Around 30% of appendectomies are performed for complicated acute appendicitis (CAA, i.e.
      cases with perforated appendicitis, extraluminal fecaliths, abscesses, or local or
      generalized peritonitis). The treatment of these complicated forms involves the following
      steps: initiation of antibiotic treatment at the time of the diagnosis, appendectomy and
      post-operative antibiotic therapy that continues for 3 days for localized forms of CAA and
      for 5 days for generalized peritonitis (according to the guidelines issued by the French
      Society for Anaesthesia and Critical Care Medicine (SFAR)). The results of a Cochrane
      meta-analysis published in 2005 suggested that the post-operative infection rate was lower in
      patients having receiving antibiotic therapy after surgery for AA. When only cases of CAA
      were considered, the difference was no longer significant. However, it should be noted that
      the studies included in the meta-analysis are now rather old (published before 1995, with
      open procedures) and no longer provide valid data for answering this question because most
      appendectomies (80%) are now performed using laparoscopy. Furthermore, a recent cohort study
      compared a short (3-day) course of antibiotics with a long course (at least 5 days) in
      patients with CAA having undergone laparoscopic or open appendectomy. There was no
      significant intergroup difference in the post-operative complication rate. One can thus
      legitimately question whether post-operative antibiotic therapy is required after
      laparoscopic appendectomy for CAA.

      The purpose of the present study is to evaluate the impact of the absence of post-operative
      antibiotic therapy on the organ space surgical site infection (SSI) rate in patients
      presenting with CAA (other than cases of generalized peritonitis) by comparing a group of
      patients having undergone a conventional strategy of post-operative antibiotic therapy for
      three days after appendectomy for CAA (the control group) with a group of patients having
      received a post-operative placebo for three days after appendectomy for CAA (the experimental
      group). The primary endpoint will be evaluated at one month after randomization.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">February 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 1, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 1, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>proportion of patients having developed organ space surgical site infections (SSIs) by postoperative day (POD)30</measure>
    <time_frame>postoperative day 30</time_frame>
    <description>primary outcome is the proportion of patients with deep SSIs by POD30. Deep SSIs are officially defined by the CDCcentre of disease control and prevention (CDC) as infections that occur within 30 days of surgery AND appear to be related to the surgery AND affect the organ or the cavity around the surgical site (i.e. any anatomical structure - other than the incision - that is opened or handled during surgery) AND for which at least one of the following signs is observed: pus coming from a drain placed in the organ or cavity; germs isolated from a liquid or tissue sample collected aseptically from the organ or cavity; an abscess or another obvious sign of infection of the organ or cavity found by macroscopic examination during subsequent surgery or in a radiological or histopathological examination.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of life post surgery using the 36-Item Short Form Health Survey</measure>
    <time_frame>day 0 and day 30</time_frame>
    <description>Quality of life on day 0 and day 30 post surgery, with the 36-Item Short Form Health Survey questionnaires (0 = very bad, 100 = very good)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>proportion of patients with superficial SSIs</measure>
    <time_frame>postoperative day 30</time_frame>
    <description>The proportion of patients with superficial SSIs, defined as infections that occur within 30 days of the intervention AND affect the skin and subcutaneous tissue AND or which at least one of the following signs is observed: pus coming from the superficial part of the incision, germs isolated from a liquid or tissue sample collected aseptically from the superficial part of the incision, a sign of infection (pain, tenderness, redness, burning, etc.) associated with deliberate opening of the superficial part of the incision by the surgeon (except if the culture is negative). Infection of the superficial part of the incision is diagnosed by the surgeon (or the physician attending to the patient).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>post-operative infection rates</measure>
    <time_frame>postoperative day 30</time_frame>
    <description>post-operative infection rates by POD30, including SSIs and remote infections.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>number of antibiotic-free days</measure>
    <time_frame>postoperative day 30</time_frame>
    <description>number of antibiotic-free days between randomization and POD30</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Description of the microbial flora</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 0</time_frame>
    <description>Description of the microbial flora found in the antibiogram of the per-operative sample collected in all cases</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>balance between antibiotic therapy and microbial resistance</measure>
    <time_frame>postoperative day 30</time_frame>
    <description>balance between antibiotic therapy and microbial resistance</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluation of morbidity and mortality</measure>
    <time_frame>postoperative day 30</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluation of morbidity and mortality (according to the Dindo-Clavien classification and the Comprehensive Complication Index (CCI)).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Length of hospital stay</measure>
    <time_frame>postoperative day 30</time_frame>
    <description>Length of hospital stay, defined as the number of days of hospitalization between surgery and discharge</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>rehospitalization rate</measure>
    <time_frame>postoperative day 30</time_frame>
    <description>rehospitalization rate, defined as the proportion of patients rehospitalized during the study</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">1476</enrollment>
  <condition>Complicated Acute Appendicitis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>experimental group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>no antibiotherapy post surgery for complicated acute appendicitis (CAA)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>control group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>antibiotherapy post surgery for complicated acute appendicitis (CAA)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>No antibiotics</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients will not receive antiobitherapy post surgery for CAA</description>
    <arm_group_label>experimental group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Antibiotics</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients will receive antiobitherapy post surgery for CAA</description>
    <arm_group_label>control group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. CAA suspected pre-operatively through a Saint-Antoine score ≤3 and confirmed
             peroperatively by the presence of a perforated appendicitis, extraluminal fecaliths,
             abscesses and/or localized peritonitis (pus in one or two abdominal quadrants).

          2. Laparoscopic appendectomy.

          3. Aged 18 or over

          4. Written, informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Pre-operative exclusion criteria:

               -  Patients with cardiac valvulopathy

               -  Immunodepressed patients

               -  Diabetic patients

               -  Patients who have received an antibiotic treatment within 3 months before the
                  surgery (and having a potential impact on the intestinal flora)

               -  Related to the diagnosis: other diseases (Crohn's disease, ulcerative colitis,
                  treatment with an immunosuppressive therapy).

               -  Related to the severity of the appendicitis:

               -  A Saint-Antoine score of 4 or 5 (non-complicated acute appendicitis)

               -  Severe sepsis, septic shock, generalized peritonitis

               -  Related to the treatment:

                    -  A decision to perform open appendectomy.

                    -  Patients who received an adaptive dose of Levofloxacine 250 mg/24H instead
                       of 500 mg/24H in pre-operative or in per-operative (notably for patients
                       with creatinine clearance ≤ 50 ml/min)

                    -  allergy to metronidazole or to one of the excipient

                    -  Contra-indication to the use of ceftriaxone (hypersensibility to the active
                       substance, to another cephalosporin, to the excipient of the used
                       speciality), history of severe hypersesibility (as anaphylactic shock),
                       history of hypersensibility to another antibiotic of the beta-lactamin
                       family (penicillin, monobactam, carbapénèmes)

                    -  Contra-indication to the use of levofloxacin, hypersensibility to
                       levofloxacin, to another quinolone or to the excipient of one of the use
                       speciality, hypersensibility to levofloxacine ou any other quinolone or to
                       any excipient, epilepsia, history of tendinitis when injection of
                       fluoroquinolones.

               -  Related to the patient

                    -  Living at more than one hour from an hospital

                    -  Patient who has no relative or other third person who could be present at
                       home and provide assistance in case of any problem for the discharged
                       patient

          2. Per-operative exclusion criteria (related to the severity of appendicitis):

               -  Non-complicated forms (catarrhal appendicitis or the absence of extraluminal
                  fecaliths, abscess or peritonitis).

               -  Generalized purulent or stercoral peritonitis (the presence of pus or faeces in
                  more than two quadrants of the abdomen).

        In order to assess the reproducibility of the inclusion criteria in the various centres and
        to avoid variations due to the lack of an official definition for localized peritonitis,
        all centres will receive a video tutorial on localized peritonitis before the start of the
        study.

          -  Pregnancy or breastfeeding.

          -  Patients under guardianship.

          -  Patients unable to provide informed consent.

          -  Patient lacking social security coverage

          -  Allergy to metronidazole
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Jean-Marc Regimbeau, PD</last_name>
    <phone>33 3.22.08.88.93</phone>
    <email>Regimbeau.Jean-Marc@chu-amiens.fr</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Charles Sabbagh, MD</last_name>
    <email>Sabbagh.Charles@chu-amiens.fr</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <verification_date>September 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 7, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 27, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 28, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 27, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 27, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">September 28, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>complicated acute appendicitis</keyword>
  <keyword>post-operative antibiotic therapy</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Appendicitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Peritonitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Acute Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Anti-Bacterial Agents</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Antibiotics, Antitubercular</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

