<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03685422</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2018/2200</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03685422</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Preoperative Virtual Reality to Reduce Pain on Gynaecologic Patients Undergoing Surgery</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Use of Preoperative Virtual Reality to Reduce Anxiety and Pain on Gynaecologic Patients Undergoing Surgery</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>KK Women's and Children's Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>KK Women's and Children's Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      In the perioperative setting, distraction therapies have been used as a technique to reduce
      anxiety and pain in the perioperative period. Measures employed in the local restructured
      hospitals include television, magazines, and newspapers. Tablet-based activity, music and
      video distraction therapy have also been shown to be useful to reduce preoperative anxiety.
      The investigators propose a prospective study to implement and evaluate the use of Virtual
      Reality (VR) in decreasing in anxiety and pain undergoing gynaecological surgery.

      The investigators will administer VR in 100 female adults undergoing day surgery or
      same-day-admission gynecologic surgery in KK Women's and Children's Hospital (KKH). The VR
      will be administered using a Samsung Gear VR3 headset fitted with a smartphone. VR images and
      sound with calming effect will be delivered to the patients for a short duration of about 10
      minutes. This low-intensity activity offers soothing experience to distract the patients from
      any pain and anxiety.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Studies have shown that the majority of patients undergoing selective surgery experience
      different levels of anxiety. The degree of anxiety is influenced by factors such as patient
      demographic characteristics, type of surgery, previous experiences with operational
      procedures, willingness to undergo the proposed intervention, perceived rapport with hospital
      personnel and personal stress threshold. This anxiety has been shown to be correlated with
      acute postoperative pain and chronic postsurgical pain, which leads to an increased use of
      postoperative analgesic, slow recovery, and other maladaptation behaviours in paediatric
      patient like eating disorders. The link between greater preoperative anxiety and the risk for
      developing chronic postsurgical pain has been documented in a variety of surgical procedures,
      including elective abdominal hysterectomy, radical mastectomy, breast cancer surgery, and
      arthroscopic knee surgery. While pharmacological interventions such as opioid-based analgesic
      are available, other methods to manage anxiety and distract patients from stressors - such as
      music, television, and virtual reality - have become more popular in the recent years due to
      their safety, low cost and effectiveness in improving overall patient experience and outcome.

      Virtual reality (VR) is a promising new technology that offers opportunities to modulate pain
      experience and cognition. Patients received VR treatment reported a reduction in pain and
      anxiety, faster wound healing, decreased chronic pain intensity and other neurorehabilitation
      improvements. The recent advent of inexpensive consumer VR system has also made VR more
      accessible to the mass, especially those by Samsung available locally. In SingHealth, VR has
      been used in neurosurgery for individualized surgery planning for patients with brain
      tumours, vascular malfunction and skull based tumours. However, there has been little done to
      investigate the effectiveness of VR during the preoperative period especially in local
      setting. Therefore, the investigators will investigate the feasibility and practicability of
      employing VR in anxiety and pain management in patients undergoing same day admission or day
      surgery. The proposed intervention may not only be implemented in the preoperative
      environment but also be in other settings such as before diagnostic screening or minor
      treatments done during inpatient stay or outpatient visit. The use of VR is suitable for
      those who are preparing for procedures in clinic or ward as an alternative anxiety management
      without prolonging the preparation time.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 26, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 31, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Pain score as assessed by Numeric Rating Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day (before and after surgery)</time_frame>
    <description>Difference of pain score before and after surgery. Pain scores (on a numeric rating scale 0-10) will be given to patients, with 0 being no pain and 10 being the worst pain possible.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Total consumption of morphine</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day (after surgery)</time_frame>
    <description>Morphine (in milligrams) used after surgery will be recorded.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Patient satisfaction as assessed by ordinal scale</measure>
    <time_frame>5 minutes (before and after surgery)</time_frame>
    <description>Patient will be asked on their satisfaction level before and after the use of VR based on ordinal scale (excellent, good, fair, poor).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale (HADS) score</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day (Before surgery and after patient is discharged from recovery room)</time_frame>
    <description>HADS score will be collected before and after surgery to assess patients' level of anxiety and depression. Each item on the questionnaire is scored from 0 to 3, thus a patient might have a total score from 0 to 21 for the overall questionnaire. A score of 0-7 indicates normal level of anxiety/depression while 8-10 indicates borderline abnormal (borderline case) and 11-21 indicates abnormal case.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in EQ-5D-3L score</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day (Before surgery and after patient is discharged from recovery room)</time_frame>
    <description>EQ-5D-3L is a standardized instrument for measuring generic health status. The two components of the Score are health state description and evaluation. The health status is measured in terms of five dimensions (5D): mobility, self-care, usual activities, pain/discomfort, and anxiety/depression; each dimension ranges from 1 to 3. From these dimensions, EQ-5D index is calculated, having a value between 0 and 1. The evaluation component involves an analogue scale, asking to mark health status on the day of interview on a 20 cm vertical scale with end point of 0 and 100. Zero corresponds to &quot;the worst health you can imagine&quot; and hundred corresponds to &quot;the best health you can imagine&quot;.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">110</enrollment>
  <condition>Pain, Postoperative</condition>
  <condition>Anxiety</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Virtual Reality</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patient will be given a Samsung Gear VR3 headset fitted with a smartphone. She will choose the desired playlist on calming scenario and experience the Virtual Reality (VR) for about 10 minutes, seated in a quiet environment in pre-operative waiting area before her turn for the scheduled surgery. Patient will be asked on their satisfaction on the VR experience after the intervention. Questionnaires will be conducted during this period. During and after the gynecologic surgery, baseline demographic data and analgesia usage will be recorded. Patient will be sent to the recovery room after the surgery, and the study team members will collect their questionnaire scorings. All the headsets will be disinfected following the hospital's infection control guideline.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Virtual Reality</intervention_name>
    <description>Before surgery, consented patients are given a Virtual Reality headset with pre-installed relaxation apps to choose a preferred scenario. Patient will be asked on their satisfaction on the VR experience after the intervention. Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale (HADS), Spielberger State-Trait Anxiety Inventory (STAI) and EQ-5D-3L questionnaires will be conducted during this period.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Virtual Reality</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Healthy participants who are ASA 1 &amp; 2 (with well-controlled medical problems)

          -  Undergo day surgery or same-day -admission gynecologic surgery

          -  Have no visual impairment

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with significant respiratory disease and obstructive sleep apnea

          -  Patient who are unable to understand questionnaire

          -  Obstetric patients

          -  Patients with motion sickness in 3D environment
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <gender_based>Yes</gender_based>
    <gender_description>Only females undergoing gynecologic surgery in KKH will be recruited</gender_description>
    <minimum_age>21 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ban Leong Sng, MBBS, MMED</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>KK Women's and Children's Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>KK Women's and Children's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Singapore</city>
        <zip>229899</zip>
        <country>Singapore</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Singapore</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 22, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 24, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 26, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 24, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 24, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 26, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Virtual Reality</keyword>
  <keyword>Pain</keyword>
  <keyword>Anxiety</keyword>
  <keyword>Analgesia</keyword>
  <keyword>Patient satisfaction</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pain, Postoperative</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Anxiety Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <provided_document_section>
    <provided_document>
      <document_type>Study Protocol and Statistical Analysis Plan</document_type>
      <document_has_protocol>Yes</document_has_protocol>
      <document_has_icf>No</document_has_icf>
      <document_has_sap>Yes</document_has_sap>
      <document_date>August 23, 2018</document_date>
      <document_url>https://ClinicalTrials.gov/ProvidedDocs/22/NCT03685422/Prot_SAP_000.pdf</document_url>
    </provided_document>
  </provided_document_section>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

