<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03687424</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>01-285/8-3-17-B</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03687424</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Can High-flow Nasal Oxygenation Improve Oxygen Saturation During Analgo-sedation in Obese Adults?</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Effect of High-flow Nasal Oxygenation vs. Low-flow Nasal Oxygenation on Oxygen Saturation During Analgo-sedation in Obese Adult Patients, Randomized Controlled Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Split, School of Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>General Hospital Dubrovnik</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Split, School of Medicine</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Obesity is omnipresent problem in everyday anesthesiology practice associated with low level
      of blood oxygen (hypoxemia) during analgo-sedation. Overweight outpatients are often
      scheduled for colonoscopy usually undergo analgo-sedation. In obese patients, intravenous
      analgo-sedation often diminish respiratory drive causing hypoxemia. To avoid hypoxemia,
      low-flow nasal oxygenation (LFNO) of 2-6 L/min is applied via standard nasal catheter to
      provide maximum 40 % of inspired fraction of oxygen (FiO2). LFNO comprises applying cold and
      dry oxygen which causes discomfort to nasal mucosa of patient. LFNO is often insufficient to
      provide satisfying oxygenation. Insufficient oxygenation adds to circulatory instability -
      heart rate (HR) and blood pressure (BP) disorder.

      On the other side, high-flow nasal oxygenation (HFNO) brings 20 to 70 L/min of heated and
      humidified of O2/air mixture up to 100% FiO2 via specially designed nasal cannula. Heated and
      humidified O2/air mixture is much more agreeable to patient. HFNO brings noninvasive support
      to patients' spontaneous breathing by producing continuous positive pressure of 3-7 cmH2O in
      upper airways consequently enhancing oxygenation.

      Investigators intend to analyze effect of HFNO vs. LFNO on oxygen saturation during
      procedural analgo-sedation for colonoscopy in obese adult patients.

      Investigators expect that obese patients with preserved spontaneous breathing, oxygenized by
      HFNO vs. LFNO, will be less prone to hypoxemia thus more respiratory and circulatory stable
      during procedural analgo-sedation for colonoscopy.

      Obese patients with applied HFNO should longer preserve: normal oxygen saturation, normal
      level of CO2 and O2, reflecting better respiratory stability. Investigators expect obese
      participnts to have more stable HR and BP, reflecting improved circulatory stability. There
      will be less interruption of breathing pattern of obese patients and less necessity for
      attending anesthesiologist to intervene.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Obese patients are often scheduled for colonoscopy under analgo-sedation. Analgo-sedation is
      characterized by deep conscious sedation and preserved spontaneous breathing. Continuous
      intravenous application of sedatives favors patients' circulatory stability and application
      of oxygenation contributes to maintaining adequate patients' oxygenation. Typically, low-flow
      nasal oxygenation (LFNO) of 2-6 L/min is applied via standard nasal catheter to provide
      maximum 40% of inspired fraction of oxygen (FiO2) before (preoxygenation), during (procedural
      oxygenation) and after (postprocedural oxygenation) until patient regains consciousness.

      During analgo-sedation obese patients are prone to intervals of bradypnea and
      hypoventilation. Transitory apnea in obese patients could lead to hypoxemia, hypoxia,
      hypercapnia and hemodynamic insufficiency despite LFNO application. Fatal outcome may occur,
      especially at higher risk overweight patients (ASA III class). Respiratory and hemodynamic
      stability of morbidly obese outpatients during analgo-sedation for endoscopic procedures
      represent challenge to anesthesiologists. There is no generally accepted protocol of
      preoxygenation and intraoperative ventilatory management for obese patients. Obese (30&lt;BMI&lt;40
      kg/m2, BMI= body mass index) and morbidly obese patients (BMI ≥40 kg/m2) are classified to
      higher anesthesia risk groups, even if obese patients may not have other comorbidities
      (30&lt;BMI&lt;40 kg/m2 = ASA II, BMI ≥40 kg/m2 = ASA III).

      Partial relaxation of pharyngeal muscles characteristic for analgo-sedation in overweight
      patients causes prolapse of fatty tissue that partially obstructs pharynx and can cause
      obstructive sleep apnoea (OSA). Although OSA is not related to obesity, OSA can accompany
      obesity. Besides perioperatively, hypoxia and bradypnoea episodes occur postoperatively in
      obese patients, which makes additional observation of obese patients necessary. More frequent
      hypoxia and bradypnoea during awakening require additional respiratory effort. Ventilation
      strategies in obese patients are necessary to optimize gas exchange and pulmonary mechanics
      in order to reduce pulmonary complications.

      High-flow nasal oxygenation (HFNO) brings 20 to 70 L/min heated and humidified O2/air mixture
      up to 100% FiO2 via specially designed, soft nasal cannula. HFNO brings non-invasive support
      to patients' inspiratory effort by developing 3-7 cmH2O of continuous pressure in upper
      airway, decreasing it's resistance and dead space. Also, heated and humidified oxygen/air
      mixture with possibility to bring higher FiO2 adds to better patients' oxygenation
      preservation and improved patients' comfort during procedure.

      AIM of this study is to compare effect of HFNO vs. LFNO during standardized procedure of
      intravenous analgo-sedation on periprocedural oxygenation maintenance in patients of
      different weight groups: 18&lt;BMI&lt;30 kg/m2, 30&lt;BMI&lt;40 kg/m2 and BMI ≥40 kg/m2.

      Investigators hypothesized that application of HFNO compared to LFNO, in obese patients with
      preserved spontaneous breathing during procedural analgo-sedation, contributes to maintaining
      adequate oxygenation, consequently adding to greater peri-procedural circulatory and
      respiratory stability of obese patients. Investigators expect that HFNO will ensure reduced
      bradypnoea intervals (frequency of breathing, FoB 1/min), longer maintenance of adequate
      oxygenation, shorter intervals of desaturation (SpO2 ≤ 92%), reducing hypercapnia (PaCO2 ≥ 6
      kPa) and less airway - opening maneuvers performed by attending anesthesiologist (Aom). These
      will prevent partial respiratory insufficiency detected by low SpO2 or low PaO2 ≤ 11 kPa
      accompanied by normal or low PaCO2 ≤ 6 kPa, and global respiratory insufficiency detected by
      decreased SpO2 ≤ 92% and PaO2 ≤ 11 kPa with increased PaCO2 ≥ 6 kPa.

      Investigators plan to conduct prospective, parallel group, randomized controlled clinical
      trial. Trial will be managed according to principles of Declaration of Helsinki for
      scientific clinical research and will be planned and guided according to CONSORT guidelines
      (Consolidated Standards of Reporting Trials). The trial has been approved by hospital's Ethic
      Committee.

      The source of information are going to be 126 adult patients scheduled for colonoscopy under
      analgo-sedation in the setting of daily outpatient gastroenterology ambulance. Eligible
      participants will be interviewed and examined ambulatory by anesthesiologist together with
      evaluation of ASA status, difficulty of airway management and BMI. After initial examination
      inclusive and exclusive criteria will be distinguished. Eligible participants who give
      written consent of participation will be included in this trial. After that, participants
      will be assigned to equal normal weight (18&lt;BMI&lt;30 kg/m2), obese (30&lt;BMI&lt;40 kg/m2) or
      morbidly obese (BMI ≥40 kg/m2) group. Each group will be randomized to intervention (HFNO)
      and control (LFNO) subgroup by random numbers generator. Randomization will be used until
      adequate number of participants in every group is reached.

      Interventions: intervention subgroups participants will be oxygenated via nasal cannula using
      high flow (40 L/min) of humidified and heated oxygen in air mixture (FiO2 40%). HFNO will be
      applied by oxygenator (AirVO™2, Fisher and Paykell, New Zealand, Technomedika Croatia d.o.o.)
      during procedural analgo-sedation for colonoscopy with maintained spontaneous breathing. In
      control subgroups, oxygenation will be applied via nasal catheter (Bauerfeind d.o.o, Zagreb,
      Croatia) using standard low flow oxygen (5 L/min, FiO2 40%) LFNO. In both groups
      concentration of oxygen delivered depends on oxygen flow which is regulated by standard
      flow-regulator (flowmeter). Oxygen is delivered through pipelines from central hospital gas
      supply or from portable cylinder gas supply.

      Anesthesia procedure will be uniformed for all participants. Integrated noninvasive
      monitoring of vital functions will be set: EKG - (heart rate/min), SpO2 (%), blood pressure
      (mmHg), indirect respiration (number of breaths/min) (Compact 7; Medical Econet GmbH,
      Germany).

      Every participant will have established intravenous infusion of 250 ml NaCl 0.9% through
      intravenous cannula regulated by continuous flow (Extension set/CONTROL-A-FLO Regulator 19&quot;
      Male Luer Lock Adapter, Baxter/Agmar d.o.o. United States of America/Croatia).

      Arterial cannula (REF30401, 20 G - 1,10 mm x 45 mm 49 ml, atraumatic needle tip, Medbar LTD,
      Izmir, Turkey) will be placed in radial artery in a previously anesthetized area with local
      anesthetic (EMLA).

      Oxygenation (HFNO or LFNO) will be administrated in continuity until patients' awakening.
      Oxygenation will be started 3 minutes before starting analgo-sedation (preoxygenation),
      continued during analgo-sedation and procedure of colonoscopy (perioperative oxygenation) and
      up to five minutes after colonoscopy and until patient is awaken (postprocedural
      oxygenation).

      Intravenous analgo-sedation will be started through continuous infusions of propofol and
      fentanyl. Induction of sedation will be guided by TCI (Target control Infusion) (B. Braun
      Melsungen, Germany) with initial target propofol concentration of 6 micrograms/minute.
      Expected time of induction with this concentration is 60-120 seconds. This target
      concentration allows hemodynamic and respiratory stability. Required analgesia will be
      simultaneously applied through slow continuous infusion in dose of 0.05 mcg/kg/min in order
      to preserve spontaneous breathing. Slow infusion will be applied through perfusor (B.Braun,
      Melsungen, Germany). Analgo-sedation will be discontinued immediately after end of the
      procedure.

      Control of nasopharyngeal airway passage during procedure is achieved by using oropharyngeal
      airway, if necessary. Oropharyngeal airway (Airway; Vigon-Medicpro d.o.o.) will be inserted
      after achieving moderate sedation, and only if base of tongue is closing airway by dropping
      on posterior pharyngeal wall. Every manipulation of patients' airway by anesthesiologist will
      be documented (insertion of airway, jaw thrust maneuver).

      Sampling: one milliliter of arterial blood will be collected as three consecutive samples
      from arterial cannula before, during and after analgo-sedation. Sample of arterial blood will
      be drawn from left radial or cubital artery.

      Measurements: measurement of oxygenation will be done using two methods: indirect
      (noninvasive) method using pulse oxymeter (Compact 7, Medical ECONET GmbH, Germany) and
      direct (invasive) method from obtained arterial blood sample. Measurement of SpO2 and drawing
      arterial blood sample will be done simultaneously. Direct measurements of SpO2 and PaO2 will
      be taken in intervals of time. SpO2 will be measured on the left-hand index finger. Data will
      be uniformly collected through indirect - noninvasive (SpO2, heart rate, blood pressure,
      respiratory rate) and direct - invasive (arterial blood gas analysis - pH, PaO2, PaCO2, SaO2)
      measurements.

      Possible biases and confounding variables could be caused by hypothermia of participant, by
      sphygmomanometer cuff pressure on the same arm where blood samples are drawn and by prolonged
      time of arterial blood analysis. These difficulties can be bypassed by: adjustment of room
      temperature where analgo-sedation is performed, blood pressure measuring on opposite arm from
      where samples of blood are taken and by arterial blood gas analysis without delay.

      Basic data analyses will be performed by statistician. Sample size is determined by statistic
      computing web program: http://www.stat.ubc.ca/~rollin/stats/ssize used statistic test
      Inference for Proportions: Comparing Two Independent Samples. Assessment of sample size is
      computed for two independent samples with assumption of clinically significant difference in
      patients' oxygenation: ≤11 and ≥14.4 kPa with delta 4.4. Statistical significance of
      difference will be inferred with 5% α-error, 50% β-error and study power 0.80. Calculated
      size of sample is: 21 participant pro subgroup (total of 126 participants).

      Investigators expect no changes to methods after trial commencement. All potential unwanted
      events which may happen during analgo-sedation and colonoscopy that could cause deviation
      from this trial's protocol will be reason for exclusion of participant from this trial. If
      circumstances change, anesthesiologist responsible for application of anesthesia will carry
      out procedure in way which is in patients' best interest.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">October 30, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 30, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 30, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>We plan to conduct prospective, parallel group, randomized controlled clinical trial.
In total, 126 participants will be included in this trial. These participants are patients scheduled for outpatient colonoscopy in analgo-sedation.
This study includes 126 patients divided in 3 groups of according to BMI: 18&lt;BMI&lt;30 kg/m2, 30&lt;BMI&lt;40 kg/m2 or BMI ≥40 kg/m2. Each group will be divided in control groups of 21 patients who will receive LFNO and intervention groups of 21 patients who will receive HFNO during standardized intravenous analgo-sedation.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>Anesthesiologist who interviews and examines patients scheduled for colonoscopy under analgo-sedation will enroll eligible participants and will offer procedure explanation and possibility to sign uniformed written consent. Unique personal hospital admission number (UPHAN) will be assigned to all eligible participants. After that, they will be randomized to control or intervention group by using random numbers generator. Anesthesiologist who implements anesthesia will receive nontransparent envelope with assigned intervention provided by independent investigator and will not decide which participant will receive LFNO or HFNO. However, attending anesthesiologist and participants will unavoidably be aware of type of oxygenation applied. Investigator who collects data after procedure will be unaware of study protocol and will enter data to formatted database. Participants' data will be noted under UPHAN. Outcome assessors will be unaware of intervention applied.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of peripheral blood oxygenation (SpO2),</measure>
    <time_frame>Before procedure: 1 minute before start of analgo-sedation and oxygenation, During procedure: 15 minutes from beginning of oxygenation and analgo-sedation, After procedure: 5 minutes after discontinuing oxygenation and analgo-sedation</time_frame>
    <description>Peripheral blood saturation (SpO2):
Normal range ≥ 92% Acceptable deflection from normal values of peripheral blood saturation (SpO2) significant for hypoxemia is &lt; 92%, while all values above will be considered normal.
Above-mentioned parameter will be observed during procedure so that we can confirm or exclude differences connected with practical application of LFNO and HFNO.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of arterial blood saturation (PaO2)</measure>
    <time_frame>Before procedure: 1 minute before start of analgo-sedation and oxygenation, During procedure: 15 minutes from beginning of oxygenation and analgo-sedation, After procedure: 5 minutes after discontinuing oxygenation and analgo-sedation</time_frame>
    <description>Partial pressure of oxygen (PaO2):
Normal range: ≥11 kPa Partial pressure of oxygen (PaO2), ≥ 11 kPa PaO2 will be considered normal, while all values below are considered significant for hypoxemia.
Above-mentioned parameter will be observed during procedure so that we can confirm or exclude differences connected with practical application of LFNO and HFNO.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of pH (pH)</measure>
    <time_frame>Before procedure: 1 minute before start of analgo-sedation and oxygenation, During procedure: 15 minutes from beginning of oxygenation and analgo-sedation, After procedure: 5 minutes after discontinuing oxygenation and analgo-sedation</time_frame>
    <description>pH value of arterial blood sample :
Normal values: 7.35 - 7.45. Acceptable deflection from normal values significant for acidosis: pH &lt;7.35.
Above-mentioned parameter will be observed during procedure so that we can confirm or exclude differences connected with practical application of LFNO and HFNO.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of partial pressure of CO2 (PaCO2)</measure>
    <time_frame>Before procedure: 1 minute before start of analgo-sedation and oxygenation, During procedure: 15 minutes from beginning of oxygenation and analgo-sedation, After procedure: 5 minutes after discontinuing oxygenation and analgo-sedation</time_frame>
    <description>Partial pressure of CO2 (PaCO2):
Normal range: 4.7 - 6.4 kPa. Acceptable deflection from normal values significant for hypercapnia: PaCO2 ≥ 6 kPa
Above-mentioned parameter will be observed during procedure so that we can confirm or exclude differences connected with practical application of LFNO and HFNO.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of normopnea (FoB)</measure>
    <time_frame>From the beginning of oxygenation and analgo-sedation till the end of analgo-sedation and oxygenation - complete procedure duration estimated: 35 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>Frequency of breathing. (FoB/min - number of breaths per minute). Normal range: 12 - 20 breaths per minute. Bradypnoea will be noted when number of breaths is less than 12 breaths/min.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of frequency of desaturation (fDE)</measure>
    <time_frame>From the beginning of oxygenation and analgo-sedation till the end of analgo-sedation and oxygenation - complete procedure duration estimated: 35 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>Frequency of desaturation during time of analgo-sedation: (fDE/min, SpO2&lt;92%). Normal range: fDE ≤1/30, up to one episode of desaturation from the start to the end of analgo-sedation. Acceptable deflection from normal range: more than one desaturation in 30 minutes.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of duration of desaturation (DE/min)</measure>
    <time_frame>From the beginning of oxygenation and analgo-sedation till the end of analgo-sedation and oxygenation - complete procedure duration estimated: 35 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>Duration of desaturation (DE/min). Normal range: up to one minute. Duration of desaturation longer then one minute will be considered as insufficient ventilation.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of frequency of bradypnoea during analgo-sedation (fBRP/min)</measure>
    <time_frame>From the beginning of oxygenation and analgo-sedation till the end of analgo-sedation and oxygenation - complete procedure duration estimated: 35 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>Frequency of bradypnoea during analgo-sedation (fBRP/min), Normal range: fBRP ≤1/30, up to one episode of bradypnoea from the start to the end of analgo-sedation. Acceptable deflection from normal range: &gt; one episode of bradypnoea during 30 minutes.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of heart rate (HR/min)</measure>
    <time_frame>Before procedure: 1 minute before start of analgo-sedation and oxygenation, During procedure: 15 minutes from beginning of oxygenation and analgo-sedation, After procedure: 5 minutes after discontinuing oxygenation and analgo-sedation</time_frame>
    <description>Heart rate (HR/min): normal range 60 -100/min. Acceptable deflection from normal values is &lt; 60 heartbeats/min significant for bradycardia, while all values up to 100 heartbeats per minute will be considered normal.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of mean arterial pressure (MAP)</measure>
    <time_frame>Before procedure: 1 minute before start of analgo-sedation and oxygenation, During procedure: 15 minutes from beginning of oxygenation and analgo-sedation, After procedure: 5 minutes after discontinuing oxygenation and analgo-sedation</time_frame>
    <description>Mean arterial pressure (MAP): normal range: 65 -110 mmHg Acceptable deflection from normal values is &lt; 65 mmHg - significant for hypotension.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>6</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">126</enrollment>
  <condition>Noninvasive Ventilation</condition>
  <condition>Respiratory Insufficiency</condition>
  <condition>Obesity</condition>
  <condition>Deep Sedation</condition>
  <condition>Hypoxia</condition>
  <condition>Airway Management</condition>
  <condition>Colonoscopy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Normal weight 18&lt;BMI&lt;30 kg/m2 LFNO</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Low-flow nasal oxygenation (LFNO) O2 flow 5L/min, FiO2 40%</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Obese 30&lt;BMI&lt;40 kg/m2 LFNO</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Low-flow nasal oxygenation (LFNO) O2 flow 5L/min, FiO2 40%</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Morbidly obese BMI ≥40 kg/m2 LFNO</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Low-flow nasal oxygenation (LFNO) O2 flow 5L/min, FiO2 40%</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Normal weight 18&lt;BMI&lt;30 kg/m2 HFNO</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>High-flow nasal oxygenation (HFNO) O2 flow 40L/min, FiO2 40%</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Obese 30&lt;BMI&lt;40 kg/m2 HFNO</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>High-flow nasal oxygenation (HFNO) O2 flow 40L/min, FiO2 40%</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Morbidly obese BMI ≥40 kg/m2 HFNO</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>High-flow nasal oxygenation (HFNO) O2 flow 40L/min, FiO2 40%</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>high-flow nasal oxygenation (HFNO)</intervention_name>
    <description>Experimental HFNO: O2 flow 40L/min, FiO2 40%</description>
    <arm_group_label>Morbidly obese BMI ≥40 kg/m2 HFNO</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Normal weight 18&lt;BMI&lt;30 kg/m2 HFNO</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Obese 30&lt;BMI&lt;40 kg/m2 HFNO</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>low-flow nasal oxygenation (LFNO)</intervention_name>
    <description>Active comparator (LFNO): O2 flow 5L/min, FiO2 40%</description>
    <arm_group_label>Morbidly obese BMI ≥40 kg/m2 LFNO</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Normal weight 18&lt;BMI&lt;30 kg/m2 LFNO</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Obese 30&lt;BMI&lt;40 kg/m2 LFNO</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  normal weight (18&lt;BMI&lt;30 kg/m2)

          -  obese patients (30&lt;BMI&lt;40 kg/m2)

          -  morbidly obese patients (BMI≥40 kg/m2)

          -  intravenous analgo-sedation

          -  elective colonoscopy

          -  colorectal tumors.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  emergency colonoscopy

          -  diseases of peripheral blood vessels

          -  hematological diseases

          -  psychiatric diseases

          -  sideropenic anemia

          -  patients' refusal

          -  ongoing chemotherapy or irradiation

          -  propofol allergies

          -  fentanyl allergies.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Anita Vukovic, MD</last_name>
    <phone>0989264821</phone>
    <phone_ext>+385</phone_ext>
    <email>anita_vukovic1@yahoo.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <link>
    <url>https://www.asahq.org/resources/clinical-information/asa-physical-status-classification-system</url>
    <description>American Society of Anesthesiologists (ASA). ASA physical status classification system 2014 Oct [internet]. Schaumburg, Illinois, USA: ASA;2014.</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://statpages.info/#Power</url>
    <description>I Interactive Statistical Pages [internet].USA: Statpages.net; c2018 [cited 2018 Sept17].Available from:</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.programiz.com/article/flowchart-programming</url>
    <description>Programiz [internet].Kupandole, Nepal: Parewa Labs Pvt. Ltd. [cited 2018 Sept17]. Flowchart in programming. Available from:</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Becker DE, Haas DA. Management of complications during moderate and deep sedation: respiratory and cardiovascular considerations. Anesth Prog. 2007 Summer;54(2):59-68; quiz 69.</citation>
    <PMID>17579505</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Anand GW, Heuss LT. Feasibility of breath monitoring in patients undergoing elective colonoscopy under propofol sedation: A single-center pilot study. World J Gastrointest Endosc. 2014 Mar 16;6(3):82-7. doi: 10.4253/wjge.v6.i3.82.</citation>
    <PMID>24634712</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lee CC, Perez O, Farooqi FI, Akella T, Shaharyar S, Elizee M. Use of high-flow nasal cannula in obese patients receiving colonoscopy under intravenous propofol sedation: A case series. Respir Med Case Rep. 2018 Feb 3;23:118-121. doi: 10.1016/j.rmcr.2018.01.009. eCollection 2018.</citation>
    <PMID>29719796</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Frieling T, Heise J, Kreysel C, Kuhlen R, Schepke M. Sedation-associated complications in endoscopy--prospective multicentre survey of 191142 patients. Z Gastroenterol. 2013 Jun;51(6):568-72. doi: 10.1055/s-0032-1330441. Epub 2013 Jun 5. Erratum in: Z Gastroenterol. 2013 Jun;51(6):E1.</citation>
    <PMID>23740356</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Frat JP, Goudet V, Girault C. [High flow, humidified-reheated oxygen therapy: a new oxygenation technique for adults]. Rev Mal Respir. 2013 Oct;30(8):627-43. doi: 10.1016/j.rmr.2013.04.016. Epub 2013 May 29. Review. French.</citation>
    <PMID>24182650</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nagata K, Morimoto T, Fujimoto D, Otoshi T, Nakagawa A, Otsuka K, Seo R, Atsumi T, Tomii K. Efficacy of High-Flow Nasal Cannula Therapy in Acute Hypoxemic Respiratory Failure: Decreased Use of Mechanical Ventilation. Respir Care. 2015 Oct;60(10):1390-6. doi: 10.4187/respcare.04026. Epub 2015 Jun 23.</citation>
    <PMID>26106206</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ni YN, Luo J, Yu H, Liu D, Ni Z, Cheng J, Liang BM, Liang ZA. Can High-flow Nasal Cannula Reduce the Rate of Endotracheal Intubation in Adult Patients With Acute Respiratory Failure Compared With Conventional Oxygen Therapy and Noninvasive Positive Pressure Ventilation?: A Systematic Review and Meta-analysis. Chest. 2017 Apr;151(4):764-775. doi: 10.1016/j.chest.2017.01.004. Epub 2017 Jan 13. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>28089816</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nathanson V. Revising the Declaration of Helsinki. BMJ. 2013 May 8;346:f2837. doi: 10.1136/bmj.f2837.</citation>
    <PMID>23657182</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schulz KF, Altman DG, Moher D; CONSORT Group. CONSORT 2010 statement: updated guidelines for reporting parallel group randomized trials. Obstet Gynecol. 2010 May;115(5):1063-70. doi: 10.1097/AOG.0b013e3181d9d421.</citation>
    <PMID>20410783</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Groves N, Tobin A. High flow nasal oxygen generates positive airway pressure in adult volunteers. Aust Crit Care. 2007 Nov;20(4):126-31. Epub 2007 Oct 10.</citation>
    <PMID>17931878</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gotera C, Díaz Lobato S, Pinto T, Winck JC. Clinical evidence on high flow oxygen therapy and active humidification in adults. Rev Port Pneumol. 2013 Sep-Oct;19(5):217-27. doi: 10.1016/j.rppneu.2013.03.005. Epub 2013 Jul 8. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23845744</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jirapinyo P, Thompson CC. Sedation Challenges: Obesity and Sleep Apnea. Gastrointest Endosc Clin N Am. 2016 Jul;26(3):527-37. doi: 10.1016/j.giec.2016.03.001. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>27372775</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bignami E, Saglietti F, Girombelli A, Briolini A, Bove T, Vetrugno L. Preoxygenation during induction of anesthesia in non-critically ill patients: A systematic review. J Clin Anesth. 2019 Feb;52:85-90. doi: 10.1016/j.jclinane.2018.09.008. Epub 2018 Sep 15.</citation>
    <PMID>30227319</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shah U, Wong J, Wong DT, Chung F. Preoxygenation and intraoperative ventilation strategies in obese patients: a comprehensive review. Curr Opin Anaesthesiol. 2016 Feb;29(1):109-18. doi: 10.1097/ACO.0000000000000267. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26545146</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>September 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 22, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 25, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 27, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 25, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 25, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">September 27, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Split, School of Medicine</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Anita Vukovic</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>MD, specialist of anesthesiology, reanimatology and intensive care</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>&quot;Noninvasive Ventilation&quot;[Mesh]</keyword>
  <keyword>&quot;Obesity&quot;[Mesh]</keyword>
  <keyword>&quot;Deep Sedation&quot;[Mesh]</keyword>
  <keyword>&quot;Hypoxia&quot;[Mesh]</keyword>
  <keyword>&quot;Adult&quot;[Mesh]</keyword>
  <keyword>&quot;Airway management&quot;[Mesh]</keyword>
  <keyword>&quot;Colonoscopy&quot;[Mesh]</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Respiratory Insufficiency</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pulmonary Valve Insufficiency</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hypoxia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

