<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03686748</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CIN_TPD_001</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03686748</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Two Point Discrimination</brief_title>
  <acronym>TPD</acronym>
  <official_title>Retuning the Nervous System in Youth With Chronic Pain</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Children's Hospital Medical Center, Cincinnati</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Children's Hospital Medical Center, Cincinnati</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      SPECIFIC AIMS

      Pain in both youth and adults is a complex, subjective and personal experience, and remains
      poorly understood. One particularly perplexing dimension of some forms of pain is the
      tendency of pain to spread outside of an affected body site to adjacent location, and then to
      unaffected body sites. Such widespread pain may reflect an altered spatial tuning of
      somatosensory processing, such that lateral inhibition is diminished, thereby allowing pain
      to spread. To date, no therapies exist which are designed specifically to diminish or even
      reverse the spatial spread of pain. However, training in two-point discrimination holds the
      potential to retune spatial aspects of somatosensory processing and may represent a novel
      therapy for widespread pain. Thus, the present investigation will test the following aims:

      Aim 1. Do youth with chronic pain have disrupted spatial tuning of somatosensory processing?
      Deficits in two point tactile discrimination have long been noted in adults with chronic
      pain, but such deficits remain poorly documented in pediatric chronic pain patients. In order
      to determine if such deficits exist, youth with both chronic pain and healthy youth will
      undergo assessment of two point discrimination thresholds.

      Aim 2. Does two-point discrimination training result in diminished pain and disability in
      youth with somatic pain? After initial characterization of tactile discrimination thresholds,
      youth with chronic pain will participate in multiple sessions of either two-point
      discrimination training or a single-point spatially-directed attentional control condition.
      Training will involve up to 9 additional sessions. Efficacy of training will be assessed by
      1) reductions in the spatial extent of pain, 2) reductions in pain intensity and
      unpleasantness, and 3) reductions in pain-related disability.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      STUDY DESIGN Prior to commencing this investigation, investigators will optimize the tactile
      discrimination threshold testing (i.e. as per baseline visit, below), and the training
      conditions, in up to ten participants (patients and/or healthy controls). This will serve as
      a pilot to refine operational aspects of study procedures before investigators commence the
      main investigation proposed herein. Following this, youth with either chronic pain (ages
      10-17, n=40) or healthy youth (ages 10-17, n=20) will undergo assessments of two-point and
      single-point discrimination thresholds in an initial session (Aim 1). After this initial
      session, youth with chronic pain will participate in up to 9 additional sessions of
      attentional training (Aim 2). These chronic pain patients will be randomized to either
      two-point discrimination training (n=20) or a single-point spatially-directed attentional
      control condition (n=20). Participants will not be informed of which intervention they will
      receive (single-blind study). Psychological questionnaires will be completed in the first and
      last sessions in order to determine how these variables relate to tactile discrimination and
      response to training.

      STUDY INTERVENTIONS 5.1 Two Point Discrimination Training: Two-point discrimination threshold
      (TPD) training may be performed 1) at spatial locations remote from pain, 2) at spatial
      locations adjacent to the region of pain, and/or 3) at spatial locations in the site of pain,
      if the participant will tolerate it. TPD is defined as the smallest distance between two
      points at which someone can recognize two points, and not one, touching their skin. As such
      this is a test of one's ability to identify separate stimulation of two discrete areas, and
      relies heavily on lateral inhibition. Highly precise mechanical calipers will be gently
      placed onto the skin and the distance between the prongs will be increased/decreased. After
      repeated decreases and increases in the distance between the prongs, the TPD will be deemed
      as the distance at which participants consistently report two points instead of one.
      One-point stimuli will be interleaved to serve as a control condition. Participants will be
      informed immediately of correct and incorrect responses as part of the discrimination
      training.

      5.2 Control Stimulation: Participants will undergo a single-point discrimination training at
      the same sites as described above. Probes of different sizes will be used for this portion -
      a small diameter probe (~1-5 mm) and a large diameter probe (~6-50mm). The probes will be
      gently placed in contact with the participants' skin, and the participant will be instructed
      to respond if they were contacted with the small or large probe. Participants will be
      informed immediately of correct and incorrect responses as part of the discrimination
      training.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 21, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 16, 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 17, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Early Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Two group, single blind for chronic pain patients receiving intervention, additional basic science component with baseline comparisons between patients and healthy controls.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
    <masking_description>Participant in the Chronic Pain Group are initially blinded to the intervention they will be receiving in the study.
Healthy participants under go all assessments in the study.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in spatial extent of pain from baseline visit to final visit</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline to final visit which is up to 5 weeks from baseline</time_frame>
    <description>total area of body affected by pain</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in pain ratings from baseline visit to final visit</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline to final visit which is up to 5 weeks from baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Ratings of current pain intensity on a non-numerical visual analog scale ranging from &quot;not at all intense&quot; to &quot;most intense pain sensation imaginable&quot; and of pain unpleasantness on a non-numerical visual analog scale ranging from &quot;not at all unpleasant&quot; to &quot;most unpleasant pain imaginable&quot;.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in pain-related disability from baseline visit to final visit</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline to final visit which is up to 5 weeks from baseline</time_frame>
    <description>pain-related disability as assessed by the Functional Disability Index</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in two point discrimination threshold from baseline visit to final visit</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline to final visit which is up to 5 weeks from baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Calipers moving at fixed distances to determine threshold of two point detection</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Ehlers-Danlos Syndrome (EDS)</condition>
  <condition>Complex Regional Pain Syndrome (CRPS)</condition>
  <condition>Amplified Musculoskeletal Pain Syndrome (AMPS)</condition>
  <condition>Low Back Pain</condition>
  <condition>Fibromyalgia</condition>
  <condition>Chronic Widespread Pain</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Two-point intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Two point discrimination training.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>One-point intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>One point discrimination of size of probe</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Healthy Controls</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Observational component of differences in discrimination between chronic pain patients and healthy controls.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Two-point discrimination training</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients will undergo multiple sessions of two-point discrimination training.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Two-point intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>One-point discrimination training</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients will undergo multiple sessions of one-point discrimination training.</description>
    <arm_group_label>One-point intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Chronic Pain Patients:

          -  Somatically located chronic pain

          -  amplified musculoskeletal pain syndrome

          -  complex regional pain syndrome

          -  low back pain

          -  fibromyalgia

          -  other forms of chronic, widespread pain

          -  Male or female, 10-17 years

          -  High fluency in written and oral English language

        Control Participants:

          -  Youth in good general health

          -  Male or female, 10-17 years

          -  High fluency in written and oral English language

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Present significant mental health disorder as defined by DSM V (e.g. psychosis,
             bipolar disorder, major depression),

          -  alcohol or drug dependence

          -  documented developmental delays or impairments (e.g., autism, cerebral palsy, or
             mental retardation) of a magnitude that would interfere with adherence to study
             requirements or safe participation in the study

          -  Primary complaint of migraine or visceral (abdominal) pain, with minimal somatic
             involvement.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>10 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>17 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Robert C Coghill, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Children's Hospital Medical Center, Cincinnati</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Geraldine C Schulze</last_name>
    <phone>513-978-3007</phone>
    <email>geraldine.schulze@cchmc.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Eric Leon</last_name>
    <email>eric.leon@cchmc.org</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cincinnati Children's Hospital Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cincinnati</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>45229</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Geraldine C Schulze, BS</last_name>
      <phone>513-517-0593</phone>
      <email>Geraldine.Schulze@cchmc.org</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Eric Leon, BA</last_name>
      <phone>513-517-0594</phone>
      <email>Eric.Leon@cchmc.org</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Robert C Coghill, PHD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Flor H, Nikolajsen L, Staehelin Jensen T. Phantom limb pain: a case of maladaptive CNS plasticity? Nat Rev Neurosci. 2006 Nov;7(11):873-81. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>17053811</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Defrin R, Pope G, Davis KD. Interactions between spatial summation, 2-point discrimination and habituation of heat pain. Eur J Pain. 2008 Oct;12(7):900-9. doi: 10.1016/j.ejpain.2007.12.015. Epub 2008 Feb 14.</citation>
    <PMID>18280188</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Flor H, Denke C, Schaefer M, Grüsser S. Effect of sensory discrimination training on cortical reorganisation and phantom limb pain. Lancet. 2001 Jun 2;357(9270):1763-4.</citation>
    <PMID>11403816</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gardner EP, Martin JH, Jessell TM, Kandel ER, Schwartz JH (2000) Principles of neural science. New York: McGraw-Hill.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Groenewald CB, Essner BS, Wright D, Fesinmeyer MD, Palermo TM. The economic costs of chronic pain among a cohort of treatment-seeking adolescents in the United States. J Pain. 2014 Sep;15(9):925-33. doi: 10.1016/j.jpain.2014.06.002. Epub 2014 Jun 19.</citation>
    <PMID>24953887</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hechler T, Wager J, Zernikow B. Chronic pain treatment in children and adolescents: less is good, more is sometimes better. BMC Pediatr. 2014 Oct 13;14:262. doi: 10.1186/1471-2431-14-262.</citation>
    <PMID>25308551</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hestbaek L, Leboeuf-Yde C, Kyvik KO, Manniche C. The course of low back pain from adolescence to adulthood: eight-year follow-up of 9600 twins. Spine (Phila Pa 1976). 2006 Feb 15;31(4):468-72.</citation>
    <PMID>16481960</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Huguet A, Miró J. The severity of chronic pediatric pain: an epidemiological study. J Pain. 2008 Mar;9(3):226-36. Epub 2007 Dec 21.</citation>
    <PMID>18088558</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>King S, Chambers CT, Huguet A, MacNevin RC, McGrath PJ, Parker L, MacDonald AJ. The epidemiology of chronic pain in children and adolescents revisited: a systematic review. Pain. 2011 Dec;152(12):2729-38. doi: 10.1016/j.pain.2011.07.016. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22078064</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lotze M, Moseley GL. Role of distorted body image in pain. Curr Rheumatol Rep. 2007 Dec;9(6):488-96. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18177603</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Maihöfner C, Handwerker HO, Neundörfer B, Birklein F. Patterns of cortical reorganization in complex regional pain syndrome. Neurology. 2003 Dec 23;61(12):1707-15.</citation>
    <PMID>14694034</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Maihöfner C, Handwerker HO, Neundörfer B, Birklein F. Cortical reorganization during recovery from complex regional pain syndrome. Neurology. 2004 Aug 24;63(4):693-701.</citation>
    <PMID>15326245</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Moseley GL, Zalucki NM, Wiech K. Tactile discrimination, but not tactile stimulation alone, reduces chronic limb pain. Pain. 2008 Jul 31;137(3):600-8. Epub 2007 Dec 3.</citation>
    <PMID>18054437</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>O'Sullivan PB, Beales DJ, Smith AJ, Straker LM. Low back pain in 17 year olds has substantial impact and represents an important public health disorder: a cross-sectional study. BMC Public Health. 2012 Feb 5;12:100. doi: 10.1186/1471-2458-12-100.</citation>
    <PMID>22304903</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Price DD (1999) Psychological mechanisms of pain and analgesia, 0 Edition. Seattle: IASP Press.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Price DD, McHaffie JG, Larson MA. Spatial summation of heat-induced pain: influence of stimulus area and spatial separation of stimuli on perceived pain sensation intensity and unpleasantness. J Neurophysiol. 1989 Dec;62(6):1270-9.</citation>
    <PMID>2600624</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Price DD, Bush FM, Long S, Harkins SW. A comparison of pain measurement characteristics of mechanical visual analogue and simple numerical rating scales. Pain. 1994 Feb;56(2):217-26.</citation>
    <PMID>8008411</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Quevedo AS, Coghill RC. Attentional modulation of spatial integration of pain: evidence for dynamic spatial tuning. J Neurosci. 2007 Oct 24;27(43):11635-40.</citation>
    <PMID>17959806</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Quevedo AS, Mørch CD, Andersen OK, Coghill RC. Lateral inhibition during nociceptive processing. Pain. 2017 Jun;158(6):1046-1052. doi: 10.1097/j.pain.0000000000000876.</citation>
    <PMID>28195854</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wand BM, Di Pietro F, George P, O'Connell NE. Tactile thresholds are preserved yet complex sensory function is impaired over the lumbar spine of chronic non-specific low back pain patients: a preliminary investigation. Physiotherapy. 2010 Dec;96(4):317-23. doi: 10.1016/j.physio.2010.02.005.</citation>
    <PMID>21056167</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 27, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 25, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 27, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 29, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 29, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 31, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Children's Hospital Medical Center, Cincinnati</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Robert Coghill</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Director of Research</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Pain</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Fibromyalgia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Musculoskeletal Pain</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Complex Regional Pain Syndromes</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Reflex Sympathetic Dystrophy</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ehlers-Danlos Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Low Back Pain</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Somatoform Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>All collected deidentified IPD that underlie results in a publication</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Statistical Analysis Plan (SAP)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Informed Consent Form (ICF)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Clinical Study Report (CSR)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Analytic Code</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>Immediately after publication with no end date.</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>Researchers who provide a methodologically sound proposal and who sign a data sharing agreement.</ipd_access_criteria>
  </patient_data>
  <provided_document_section>
    <provided_document>
      <document_type>Informed Consent Form: Healthy Control</document_type>
      <document_has_protocol>No</document_has_protocol>
      <document_has_icf>Yes</document_has_icf>
      <document_has_sap>No</document_has_sap>
      <document_date>October 8, 2017</document_date>
      <document_url>https://ClinicalTrials.gov/ProvidedDocs/48/NCT03686748/ICF_000.pdf</document_url>
    </provided_document>
    <provided_document>
      <document_type>Informed Consent Form: Patient Population</document_type>
      <document_has_protocol>No</document_has_protocol>
      <document_has_icf>Yes</document_has_icf>
      <document_has_sap>No</document_has_sap>
      <document_date>October 8, 2017</document_date>
      <document_url>https://ClinicalTrials.gov/ProvidedDocs/48/NCT03686748/ICF_001.pdf</document_url>
    </provided_document>
    <provided_document>
      <document_type>Study Protocol</document_type>
      <document_has_protocol>Yes</document_has_protocol>
      <document_has_icf>No</document_has_icf>
      <document_has_sap>No</document_has_sap>
      <document_date>November 16, 2017</document_date>
      <document_url>https://ClinicalTrials.gov/ProvidedDocs/48/NCT03686748/Prot_002.pdf</document_url>
    </provided_document>
  </provided_document_section>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

