<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03681925</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>STUDY00142818</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03681925</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Measuring Nutrition Literacy in Clinical Practice: Evaluating Effects Upon Providers and Patients</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Effects of Nutrition Literacy Assessment on Patient-Centered Nutrition Education Provided by Dietitians</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Kansas Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Kansas Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study evaluates the effects of assessing patient nutrition literacy prior to an initial
      session with an outpatient dietitian on the patient-centeredness of the session. We will
      randomize 6 dietitians, 4 of whom will have access to their participating patients' nutrition
      literacy scores. These dietitians will use this information to better inform their
      interventions, and hopefully improve their patients' nutrition literacy as a result.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Nutrition Literacy Assessment Tool (NLit): a validated, 64-question survey that assesses
      nutrition literacy across 6 subscales:

        -  Nutrition and Health

        -  Energy Sources in Food

        -  Household Food Measurement

        -  Food Label and Numeracy

        -  Food Groups

        -  Consumer Skills

      Dietitians who work within 6 different outpatient clinics (1 dietitian per clinic) will be
      recruited to the study; each dietitian will recruit 19 patients from their clinic. All
      patient participants will take the NLit survey prior to an initial visit with their
      dietitian. Dietitians randomized to the intervention arm (n=4) will have access to their
      participating patients' NLit results, and tailor their intervention to the patient's
      nutrition literacy weaknesses. Dietitians randomized to the control group (n=2) will not have
      access to their participating patients' NLit scores, and will provide the same
      standard-of-care intervention usually provided.

      All participating patients will then re-take the NLit a month after their initial session
      with their dietitian, and we will examine the results to see if a) nutrition literacy
      improved within groups, and b) if the patients of the intervention dietitians showed more
      improvement in nutrition literacy than their counterparts being treated by the control
      dietitians.

      We will also collect dietary pattern information from participating patients before their
      initial session with their dietitian, and again one month after their initial session with
      their dietitian. We will examine the results to see if a) dietary patterns improve with
      increased nutrition literacy, and b) if the dietary patterns of patients in the intervention
      group improve more than patients in the control group.

      Finally, we will collect survey information from patients pertaining to the perceived
      patient-centeredness of the session with their dietitian. We will also collect audio
      recordings of the sessions between patients and dietitians, which will be analyzed for
      patient-centeredness. We will also analyze readability and clearness of printed materials
      used by dietitians during their interventions with patients.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 15, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 6, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 6, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>6 dietitians will be randomized in a 2:1 intervention:control fashion. Each dietitian will recruit 19 patient participants, for 114 total patient participants.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Screening</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
    <masking_description>Patient participants will be unaware of which arm their dietitian has been randomized to.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Nutrition Literacy Assessment Instrument (NLit) score from baseline to post-session.</measure>
    <time_frame>Nutrition literacy will be measured prior to the patients' initial session with a dietitian, then again one month after the session.</time_frame>
    <description>Nutrition literacy will be assessed with the Nutrition Literacy Assessment Instrument (NLit)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in BRFSS 2011 Fruit and Vegetable Module scores from baseline to one month post-session.</measure>
    <time_frame>BRFSS 2011 Fruit and Vegetable Module scores will be measured prior to the patients' initial session with a dietitian, then again one month after the session.</time_frame>
    <description>Dietary patterns will be assessed using the BRFSS 2011 Fruit and Vegetable Module.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Rapid Eating Assessment for Patients (REAP) score from baseline to one month post-session</measure>
    <time_frame>BRFSS 2011 Fruit and Vegetable Module scores will be measured prior to the patients' initial session with a dietitian, then again one month after the session.</time_frame>
    <description>Dietary patterns will be assessed using the Rapid Eating Assessment for Patients (REAP)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient view of patient-centeredness of the session with a dietitian</measure>
    <time_frame>Patients will complete the survey up to two months after they complete their session with a dietitian.</time_frame>
    <description>Patient view of patient-centeredness of the session will be assessed using a modified version of the Consumer Assessment of Healthcare Providers and Systems-Clinician and Group Survey (CAHPS), v.3.0</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient-centeredness of the session between patient and dietitian</measure>
    <time_frame>One month post-session</time_frame>
    <description>Patient-centeredness of the session between patient and dietitian will be assessed using the Teach back Loop Score, a validated tool used to examine the use of teach back, an essential part of patient-centered care.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Readability of printed materials used by dietitians during interventions</measure>
    <time_frame>One month prior to first patient session with a dietitian</time_frame>
    <description>Reading level of all printed materials will be assessed using the Flesch-Kincaid Readability score.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clearness of printed materials used by dietitians during interventions</measure>
    <time_frame>One month prior to first patient session with a dietitian</time_frame>
    <description>Clearness of printed materials will be assessed using the Center for Disease Control Clear Communications Index</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">95</enrollment>
  <condition>Health Knowledge, Attitudes, Practice</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Dietitians randomized to the intervention arm will have access to their participating patients' Nutrition Literacy Assessment Instrument (NLit) scores, and base their intervention on these results.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Dietitians randomized to the control arm will not have access to their participating patients' Nutrition Literacy Assessment Instrument (NLit) scores, and will provide the standard-of-care intervention for their patients.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Nutrition Literacy Assessment Instrument (NLit)</intervention_name>
    <description>The NLit is a 64-question survey broken into 6 subscales. each subscale examines a different aspect of nutrition literacy (Nutrition and Health, Energy Sources in Food, Household Food Measurement, Food Label and Numeracy, Food Groups, and Consumer Skills). Global and subscale NLit scores will be generated for each participating patient.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  subjects must be at least 18 years old

          -  subjects must be able to read English

          -  subjects must be scheduled with a participating dietitian

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  subjects with cognitive disabilities or overt mental illnesses

          -  subjects with vision issues severe enough to disrupt reading of the NLit.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Heather D Gibbs, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Kansas Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The University of Kansas Health System Family Medicine and Internal Medicine Clinics</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kansas City</city>
        <state>Kansas</state>
        <zip>66160</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Kansas Medical Center Student Health Services</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kansas City</city>
        <state>Kansas</state>
        <zip>66160</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Kansas Medical Center, Center for Physical Activity and Weight Management</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kansas City</city>
        <state>Kansas</state>
        <zip>66160</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Kansas Medical Center Bariatric and Weight Loss Surgery Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Overland Park</city>
        <state>Kansas</state>
        <zip>66211</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Encompass Medical Group</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kansas City</city>
        <state>Missouri</state>
        <zip>64131</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gibbs HD, Ellerbeck EF, Gajewski B, Zhang C, Sullivan DK. The Nutrition Literacy Assessment Instrument is a Valid and Reliable Measure of Nutrition Literacy in Adults with Chronic Disease. J Nutr Educ Behav. 2018 Mar;50(3):247-257.e1. doi: 10.1016/j.jneb.2017.10.008. Epub 2017 Dec 12.</citation>
    <PMID>29246567</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 14, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 20, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 24, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 19, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 19, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 20, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Patient-centered care</keyword>
  <keyword>Dietitian</keyword>
  <keyword>Nutrition literacy</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

