<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03682562</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>N1P1H1D1</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03682562</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Diagnostic Accuracy of Salivary DNA Integrity Index in Oral Malignant and Premalignant Lesions</brief_title>
  <official_title>Diagnostic Accuracy of Salivary DNA Integrity Index in Oral Malignant and Premalignant Lesions</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Cairo University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Cairo University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study aims to identify the accuracy of DNA integrity index in differentiating between
      oral premalignant lesions and oral cancer.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      As stated by the U.S. Preventive Services Task Force and the National Institute of Dental and
      Craniofacial Research, the main screening test for oral cancer remains conventional oral
      examination of the oral cavity. Most cases of oral cancer are preceded by a clinically
      visible lesion. These lesions are called oral potentially malignant disorders. These are
      leukoplakia, erythroplakia, oral submucous fibrosis, oral lichen planus and discoid lupus
      erythematosis. Leukoplakia has a reported annual transformation rate of 2-3%, while OLP has a
      rate of 0.5% .

      Full thickness tissue biopsy is the &quot;gold standard&quot; for diagnosing suspicious lesions should
      they be encountered during COE. However, oral biopsy is an invasive technique that can be
      challenging in sites as the floor of the mouth or the soft palate . The invasive nature of a
      biopsy also makes it unsuitable for cancer screening in high-risk populations.

      Thus there is a need for a diagnostic aid that can help primary care providers determine
      which patients need to be biopsied or referred to a specialist.

      Nucleic acids can be released actively or passively into the circulation by both living and
      dead cells, where the latter is considered the predominant source. Programmed cell death
      gives neatly digested DNA fragments of approximately 180 bp in length. In case of solid
      tumors, cell-free DNA is released through necrosis which generates longer DNA fragments due
      to haphazard and incomplete digestion of DNA. Thus, the integrity of the DNA fragment can
      determine its origin making DNA integrity a potential marker for oral cancer.

      The DNA integrity index (DII) is the ratio between the longer DNA fragments to the shorter
      ones. A higher index has been reported in breast, prostate, liver and cervical cancer. Jiang
      et al. 2006 found that the DNA integrity index was significantly higher in oral cancer
      patients than in normal ones and reported a sensitivity and specificity values of 84.5% 83%
      respectively . The next step for such a marker would be early quantification of performance
      in clinical settings to determine if it is possible to extrapolate cut off values.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 15, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 10, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 10, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Control</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference in DNA Integrity Index</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month after the end of patient recruitment</time_frame>
    <description>The DNA integrity will be compared between the three group to determine whether there is a difference between them in that aspect or not</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>3</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">93</enrollment>
  <condition>Oral Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Oral Lichen Planus</condition>
  <condition>Oral Leukoplakia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Oral Cancer</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients diagnosed clinically and histopathologically as having oral cancer.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Premalignant Oral Lesions</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients diagnosed clinically and histopathologically with either leukoplakia or oral lichen planus as stated by modified WHO criteria</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Normal Subjects</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients who give a history of:
No smoking
No alcohol
No systemic disease; and who on conventional oral examination have:
No visible oral lesions on conventional oral examination .
Good oral hygiene.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>DNA Integrity Index</intervention_name>
    <description>This test will be performed for ALL three groups:
Sample collection:
Patients will be given a sterile cup containing 5mL saline solution with which they will vigorously rinse their mouth while rubbing their tongues against the oral mucosa for 30 seconds, then spit it back into the cup. The solution will then be used for DNA extraction.
DNA integrity analysis:
The DNA integrity will be done through measuring a housekeeping gene using competitive polymerase chain reaction where the isolated DNA will be combined with DNA capture probes for sequence-specific DNA fragments. The DNA integrity index will be calculated as the ratio of the concentration of longer DNA fragments to the ratio of shorter ones.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Normal Subjects</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Oral Cancer</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Premalignant Oral Lesions</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Salivary Samples will be obtained for DNA extraction, Biosamples will be stored in -80
      degrees after patient's consent
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Group I: (Clinical examination and Biopsy) Patients diagnosed clinically and
        histopathologically as having oral cancer. Group II: (History and Clinical examination)

        Patients who give a history of:

          -  No smoking

          -  No alcohol

          -  No systemic disease; and who on conventional oral examination(National Institute of
             Dental and Craniofacial Research, 2013b) have:

          -  No visible oral lesions on conventional oral examination .

          -  Good oral hygiene. Group III: (Clinical examination and Biopsy) Patients diagnosed
             clinically and histopathologically with oral lichen planus as stated by modified WHO
             criteria (van der Meij and van der Waal, 2003).
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Patients in this study will be divided into three groups:

        Group I: Patients diagnosed histopathologically with oral cancer recruited from the
        National Cancer Institute, who have yet to receive treatment.

        Group II: Healthy Controls

        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  No visible oral lesions as detected by conventional oral examination

          -  Good oral hygiene, with healthy gingival tissues

          -  Non-smokers

          -  No systemic disease Group III: Patients diagnosed with oral lichen planus according to
             the modified WHO (van der Meij and van der Waal, 2003)diagnostic criteria not
             receiving treatment at least 8 weeks prior to enrollment.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>20 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Faculty of Dentistry - Cairo University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cairo</city>
        <zip>11553</zip>
        <country>Egypt</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Egypt</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 21, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 21, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 24, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 13, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 13, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 15, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Cairo University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Noha Adel Azab</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Researcher</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Mouth Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukoplakia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Precancerous Conditions</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukoplakia, Oral</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lichen Planus, Oral</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lichen Planus</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>According to the mode of data entry, if it is solely numerical it can be more easily shared and deposited on repositories, however patient clinical photos may not be possible to share</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

