<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03680872</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>17-0840</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03680872</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Restoring Motor and Sensory Hand Function in Tetraplegia Using a Neural Bypass System</brief_title>
  <official_title>Restoring Motor and Sensory Hand Function in Tetraplegia Using a Neural Bypass System</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Chad Bouton</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Northwell Health</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_unapproved_device>Yes</is_unapproved_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a single-cohort early feasibility trial to determine whether an investigational
      device called the Bidirectional Neural Bypass System can lead to the restoration of movement
      and sensation in the hand and wrist of up to three individuals with tetraplegia.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study consists of the following three phases: baseline visit, surgical procedure, and
      restoration sessions.

      At the baseline visit, participants will undergo a medical history review, physical and
      neurological examination, functional assessment of motor and sensory capabilities, a
      functional magnetic resonance image (fMRI), diffusion tensor image (DTI), and a neuromuscular
      stimulation test.

      Participants deemed eligible for continued participation will then undergo a craniotomy under
      anesthetic sedation to implant the investigational device. The surgeon will implant
      microelectrode arrays into the primary motor cortex to record neural activity associated with
      desired movements and into the primary somatosensory cortex to deliver stimulation in order
      to provide sensory perception.

      While in surgical recovery, participants will have their vital signs monitored, be provided
      pain medication and antibiotics, and undergo a computed tomography (CT). The participants may
      also undergo electromyography and microneurography while in recovery. After being evaluated
      by a physician, the participants will be discharged from the hospital to continue their
      recovery.

      After fully recovering, participants will attend restoration sessions at the Feinstein
      Institute for Medical Research's Center for Bioelectronic Medicine. Participants will attend
      up to 3 study sessions a week for approximately 12 months, with each session lasting up to 4
      hours. The sessions will progressively focus on identifying neural activity related to
      desired movements, restoring volitional control of the hand and wrist, restoring tactile
      perception, and then restoring volitional control and tactile perception of the hand and
      wrist simultaneously.

      The study will be considered complete after completion of enrollment (up to 3 participants),
      completion of study procedures by all participants, and the completion of analysis of
      identifiable study data.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 30, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>This is a single-cohort early feasibility trial to determine whether an investigational device called the Bidirectional Neural Bypass System can lead to the restoration of movement and sensation in the hand and wrist of up to three individuals with tetraplegia.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Restoration of Movement</measure>
    <time_frame>The primary outcome will be assessed over the course of 12 months during the study's restoration sessions.</time_frame>
    <description>The primary outcome of restoring movement will be evaluated through Graded Redefined Assessment of Strength, Sensibility &amp; Prehension. The performance will be graded on a numeric scale from 0-92, where a higher number indicates a better outcome.
Participants will complete 10 distinct arm, wrist, and finger movements. The movements will be evaluated on a 5-point scale ranging from no movement to normal movement for a total of 0-50.
Participants will be asked to perform a cylindrical grasp, key pinch, and a thumb-index pinch. The movements will be evaluated on a 4-point scale ranging from an inability to position wrist and fingers to able to perform movement with normal force for a total of 0-12.
Participants will be asked to pour water, unscrew lids, place pegs on a board, open a lock, drop coins in a slot, and screw nuts. The movements will be evaluated on a 5-point scale ranging from 0% completed to 100% completed with expected grasp and no difficulties for a total of 0-30.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Restoration of Sensation</measure>
    <time_frame>The primary outcome will be assessed over the course of 12 months during the study's restoration sessions.</time_frame>
    <description>The primary outcome of restoring the perception of tactile sensation of the hand will be evaluated through the 5-Point Likert Scale. Participants will be asked whether they perceive sensation in response to objects being placed against the hand and fingertips. Participants will indicate whether they feel the object by selecting either strongly disagree (1), disagree (2), neutral (3), agree (4), or strongly agree (5). A higher total response score indicates an improvement in outcome.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">3</enrollment>
  <condition>Spinal Cord Injuries</condition>
  <condition>Spinal Cord Injury Cervical</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Spinal Cord Injury Participants</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>This group consists of individuals with tetraplegia receiving an investigational device called the Bidirectional Neural Bypass System.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Bidirectional Neural Bypass System</intervention_name>
    <description>These participants will receive the investigational device called the Bidirectional Neural Bypass System. The study intends to use this device to restore volitional movement and sensation to the hand and wrist of an individual during its use in the laboratory.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Spinal Cord Injury Participants</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Males and females between 22 and 65 years of age

          2. Individuals with a stable cervical spinal cord injury that have International
             Standards for the Neurological Classification of SCI (ISNCSCI) motor scores for
             fingers of 0 - 2 (non-functional) and ISNCSCI sensory scores of 0 - 2 (not normal) on
             the palmar side

          3. Individuals at least one year from initial spinal cord injury

          4. Individuals that are considered English Proficient due to the study requirements to
             follow verbal commands during testing sessions

          5. Individuals that are able to comprehend the study goals and procedures, and are able
             to provide informed consent for participation.

          6. Individuals that are willing and able to visit the study center for study procedures
             that will be 1-3 sessions a week for up to 12 months at 1-4 hours per session.

          7. Have the ability and willingness to undergo upper limb electrodiagnostic and nerve
             conduction studies

          8. Demonstrate typical amplitude, latency, and conduction velocity in the distal median,
             ulnar, and radial nerves of at least one upper limb

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Individuals participating in another research study that may affect the conduct or
             results of this study

          2. Individuals having or exhibiting any of the following:

               1. Medical contraindications for diffusion tensor imaging, functional magnetic
                  resonance imaging, electromyography, computed tomography, cortical stimulation,
                  or craniotomies/surgeries

               2. Prior difficulties or allergy to general anesthesia

               3. Active wound healing or skin breakdown issues

               4. Stage III-IV pressure ulcers

               5. Chronically-implanted electronic medical device (e.g. baclofen pump, deep brain
                  stimulator, epidural stimulator, cardiac pacemaker, vagus nerve stimulator, or
                  other)

               6. Prior tendon transfer to enhance hand function

               7. History of autoimmune disease

               8. Cancer

               9. Biochemical abnormalities of the liver, kidney, or pancreas

              10. Ventilator dependence

              11. History of serious mood or thought disorder

              12. Significant residual clinically evident traumatic brain injury or cognitive
                  impairment

              13. Uncontrolled autonomic dysreflexia

              14. Spasticity in the upper extremities that is uncontrolled by pharmacological
                  methods

              15. Diagnosis of acute myocardial infarction or cardiac arrest within previous 6
                  months

              16. Individuals with any type of destruction and/or damage to the motor cortex region
                  as determined by fMRI.

              17. History of a neurological ablation procedure

              18. History of hemorrhagic stroke

              19. History of infectious or chronic diseases, such as HIV or tuberculosis

          3. Individuals with any of the following co-morbid conditions that would interfere with
             study activities or response to treatment:

               1. Life expectancy &lt; 3 years

               2. Severe chronic pulmonary disease

               3. Intractable seizure disorders

               4. Local, systemic acute or chronic infectious illness

               5. Life threatening cardiac arrhythmias

               6. Severe collagen vascular disorder

               7. Kidney failure or other major organ systems failures

          4. Individuals with a substance abuse (alcoholism or other) problem

          5. Pregnant women

          6. Prisoners
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>22 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Chad E Bouton, MS</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Northwell Health</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Richard D Ramdeo</last_name>
    <phone>516-562-3634</phone>
    <email>rramdeo1@northwell.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Northwell Health's The Feinstein Institute for Medical Research</name>
      <address>
        <city>Manhasset</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>11030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Richard D Ramdeo</last_name>
      <phone>516-562-3634</phone>
      <email>rramdeo1@northwell.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Chad E Bouton</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://www.nature.com/articles/nature17435</url>
    <description>Restoring Cortical Control of Functional Movement in a Human with Quadriplegia</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bouton CE, Shaikhouni A, Annetta NV, Bockbrader MA, Friedenberg DA, Nielson DM, Sharma G, Sederberg PB, Glenn BC, Mysiw WJ, Morgan AG, Deogaonkar M, Rezai AR. Restoring cortical control of functional movement in a human with quadriplegia. Nature. 2016 May 12;533(7602):247-50. doi: 10.1038/nature17435. Epub 2016 Apr 13.</citation>
    <PMID>27074513</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sharma G, Friedenberg DA, Annetta N, Glenn B, Bockbrader M, Majstorovic C, Domas S, Mysiw WJ, Rezai A, Bouton C. Using an Artificial Neural Bypass to Restore Cortical Control of Rhythmic Movements in a Human with Quadriplegia. Sci Rep. 2016 Sep 23;6:33807. doi: 10.1038/srep33807.</citation>
    <PMID>27658585</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>November 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 27, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 19, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 21, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 18, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 18, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 19, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Northwell Health</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Chad Bouton</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Vice President, Advanced Engineering; Managing Director, Center for Bioelectronic Medicine</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Physical and Rehabilitation Medicine</keyword>
  <keyword>Biomedical Engineering</keyword>
  <keyword>Paralysis</keyword>
  <keyword>Tetraplegia</keyword>
  <keyword>Quadriplegia</keyword>
  <keyword>Movement Restoration</keyword>
  <keyword>Muscle Stimulation</keyword>
  <keyword>Tactile Sensation</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Spinal Cord Injuries</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Quadriplegia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Wounds and Injuries</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Currently, there are no plans to make individual participant data available.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

