<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03681431</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ENDOKINETIC-CEF</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03681431</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluation of an Antibiotic Regimen Pharmacokinetic Applicable to Enterococcus Faecalis Infective Endocarditis</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase II Clinical Trial to Evaluate an Antibiotic Regimen Pharmacokinetic Applicable to Outpatient Parenteral Antimicrobial Therapy in Enterococcus Faecalis Infective Endocarditis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Fundación Pública Andaluza para la gestión de la Investigación en Sevilla</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Fundación Pública Andaluza para la gestión de la Investigación en Sevilla</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The clinical trial is designed as a phase II, crossover clinical trial. It will be carried
      out in healthy volunteers, who will receive two different antibiotic regimen based on
      ceftriaxone. One of the regimens had shown clinical effectiveness in this scenario, but it is
      not suitable for OPAT programs. In the other hand, a new treatment schema useful in OPAT
      programs is proposed, but there is still a lack of pharmacokinetic data to support it. The
      plasma drug concentrations will be measured in both cases, comparing the minimal drug
      concentration observed and the pharmacokinetic profiles of the two regimens.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Infective endocarditis (IE) is an uncommon but virulent infection disease. One of the most
      frequent etiology for this infection is Enterococcus faecalis. IE treatment is difficult due
      to the characteristics of the infection itself, the bacterial species and the frequent
      comorbidities of the patients. A bactericidal antimicrobial treatment is mandatory for the
      resolution of this disease, but most antibiotics do not exhibit this effect against E.
      faecalis and have prompted the combination of an aminoglycoside and a cell-wall active agent
      (generally a β-lactam) as the standard treatment. This is a lengthy treatment (4-6 weeks) and
      its primary side effect is nephrotoxicity. Furthermore, aminoglycoside resistant strain's
      rates are increasing in USA and Europe, getting more complicated to establish an effective
      antibiotic regimen. Nowadays, patients with E. faecalis IE are old and often have significant
      underlying comorbidities with an increased risk of developing nephrotoxicity with
      aminoglycoside treatment. For this reason, and for the relevance of high-level
      aminoglycoside-resistant strains, some alternatives have been explored. A double β-lactam
      regimen is an option, despite the intrinsically resistance of E. faecalis to cephalosporins.
      The most studied combination is a regimen based on ampicillin plus ceftriaxone, which has
      shown a synergistic effect in vitro. This combination is as effective as ampicillin plus
      gentamycin, but with lower nephrotoxicity. Those patients need at least 4-6 weeks of
      treatment with a prolonged hospitalization. However, after 2 week of treatment some patients
      are clinically stabilized and could be benefit of an outpatient parenteral antibiotic therapy
      (OPAT) program. For that purpose, it is essential to design a treatment regimen, which
      ensures the effectiveness and safety of the treatment, based on stability and pharmacokinetic
      and pharmacodynamics (PK/PD) studies of the administered drugs. Furthermore, the logistic and
      schedule should be simple enough to enable the inclusion in an OPAT program. In order to
      design an antibiotic regimen suitable for OPAT programs and as effective as the standard
      therapies for E. faecalis IE, we decided to start clinical trial.

      The clinical trial is designed as a phase II, crossover clinical trial. It will be carried
      out in healthy volunteers, who will receive two different antibiotic regimen based on
      ceftriaxone. One of the regimens had shown clinical effectiveness in this scenario, but it is
      not suitable for OPAT programs. In the other hand, a new treatment schema useful in OPAT
      programs is proposed, but there is still a lack of pharmacokinetic data to support it. The
      plasma drug concentrations will be measured in both cases, comparing the minimal drug
      concentration observed and the pharmacokinetic profiles of the two regimens.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">April 23, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 23, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 23, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>A phase II, single-centre, open, non-randomized, cross-over, clinical trial.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Serum levels after 24 hours</measure>
    <time_frame>24 hours</time_frame>
    <description>To determinate whether 24 hours after the administration of 4 grams of ceftriaxone in a single short infusion, serums levels would be higher than 5 micrograms per millilitre</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>AUC 24 hours</measure>
    <time_frame>24 hours</time_frame>
    <description>To compare the 24 hours area under the curve (AUC) after the administration of 4 grams of ceftriaxone in a single short infusion and the administration of 2 grams of ceftriaxone in a two short infusions separated for 12 hours.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Plasma Clearance</measure>
    <time_frame>24 hours</time_frame>
    <description>To determinate ceftriaxone plasma clearance after the administration of 4 grams of ceftriaxone in a single short infusion.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Elimination Half-life</measure>
    <time_frame>24 hours</time_frame>
    <description>To determinate ceftriaxone elimination half-life after the administration of 4 grams of ceftriaxone in a single short infusion.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Volume of Distribution</measure>
    <time_frame>24 hours</time_frame>
    <description>To determinate ceftriaxone volume of distribution after the administration of 4 grams of ceftriaxone in a single short infusion.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum Plasma Concentration</measure>
    <time_frame>24 hours</time_frame>
    <description>To determinate ceftriaxone maximum plasma concentration after the administration of 4 grams of ceftriaxone in a single short infusion.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety: Number, frequency and importance of adverse reactions.</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month</time_frame>
    <description>To determinate the safety (number, frequency and importance of adverse reactions) of the administration of 4 grams of ceftriaxone in a single short infusion</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">12</enrollment>
  <condition>Infectious Endocarditis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Ceftriaxone 4g/ 24h</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Single intravenous dose of Ceftriaxone 4g/ 24h</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Ceftriaxone 2g/ 12h</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Two intravenous doses of Ceftriaxone 2g/ 12h</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ceftriaxone 4g/ 24h</intervention_name>
    <description>Each individual will be administrated 2 doses of 2 g of ceftriaxone separated for 12 hours. After a wash-out period (5-7 days) the same individuals will receive a single dose 4 g of ceftriaxone. In both cycles, plasma drug concentrations will be measure during 24 hours.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Ceftriaxone 4g/ 24h</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ceftriaxone 2g/ 12h</intervention_name>
    <description>Each individual will be administrated 2 doses of 2 g of ceftriaxone separated for 12 hours. After a wash-out period (5-7 days) the same individuals will receive a single dose 4 g of ceftriaxone. In both cycles, plasma drug concentrations will be measure during 24 hours.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Ceftriaxone 2g/ 12h</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Male and female adults subjects.

          2. Weight between 40 and 105 kilograms, both included, and body mass index lower than 34
             kilograms per square meter.

          3. The subject (or his/her &quot;trusted representative&quot;) must have given his/her informed and
             signed consent approved by an Ethical Committee.

          4. The subject must have normal analytical values or abnormal without clinical
             significance of biochemical parameters, liver and kidney function panel test, hemogram
             and album level. A medical check will be run by workers of Infectious Diseases
             Department.

          5. The subject must have a normal physical examination or abnormal without clinical
             significance. A medical check will be run by workers of Infectious Diseases
             Department.

          6. The medication taken usually by the subjects will be check by the Pharmacy Department
             in order to find possible interactions with ceftriaxone.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Subjects with clinically significant abnormalities in laboratory test or physical
             exploration. A medical check will be run by workers of Infectious Diseases Department.

          2. Subjects undergoing an active infection find at the screening.

          3. Subjects with any clinical or surgery condition which contraindicate his/her
             inclusion, check by workers of Infectious Diseases Department.

          4. Subjects who has received treatment with cephalosporins 21 days before the trial
             starts or during the trial (apart from the protocol treatment).

          5. Subjects hypersensitive or allergic to cephalosporines or penicillins.

          6. Subjects undergoing chronic or acute cutaneous diseases which prevent the treatment
             administration.

          7. Subjects not giving his/her informed and signed consent approved by an Ethical
             Committee.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Maria Victoria H Gil Navarro</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University Hospital Virgen del Rocio/ Institute of Biomedicine of Seville</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Hospital Virgen del Rocio</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sevilla</city>
        <zip>41013</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Spain</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 3, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 21, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 24, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 21, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 21, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">September 24, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Pharmacokinetic</keyword>
  <keyword>Ceftriaxone</keyword>
  <keyword>Enterococcus faecalis</keyword>
  <keyword>Infectious Endocarditis</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Communicable Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Infection</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Endocarditis, Bacterial</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Endocarditis, Subacute Bacterial</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Endocarditis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Ceftriaxone</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <provided_document_section>
    <provided_document>
      <document_type>Study Protocol</document_type>
      <document_has_protocol>Yes</document_has_protocol>
      <document_has_icf>No</document_has_icf>
      <document_has_sap>No</document_has_sap>
      <document_date>January 11, 2018</document_date>
      <document_url>https://ClinicalTrials.gov/ProvidedDocs/31/NCT03681431/Prot_000.pdf</document_url>
    </provided_document>
  </provided_document_section>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

