<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03683069</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2018P001888</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03683069</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>MR Antagonist and STRIATIN</brief_title>
  <official_title>Salt Sensitive Hypertension and Striatin</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Brigham and Women's Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Brigham and Women's Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Salt sensitivity of blood pressure is a substantial risk factor for cardiovascular morbidity
      and mortality. Inappropriate increases in renal sodium reabsorption lead to volume expansion,
      hypertension and salt sensitive blood pressure. Key homeostatic mechanisms that regulate
      renal sodium reabsorption are: first, hormonal, e.g., renin-angiotensin-aldosterone system
      and second, vascular, e.g., renal vasculature. Dysfunction in one or both mechanisms leads to
      hypertension and salt sensitive blood pressure. The investigators recently documented that
      striatin plays a novel role in the development of salt sensitive blood pressure. However, the
      mechanisms that lead to striatin-mediated salt sensitive blood pressure are not clear;
      defining these mechanisms is the overall goal of this proposal.

      Striatin is a calmodulin- and caveolin-binding protein that can function as either a
      scaffolding and/or signaling protein, specifically in relation to the mechanism of action of
      steroids. In a large study of well characterized subjects from the HyperPATH cohort, the
      investigators documented that hypertensive and normotensive humans who are striatin risk
      allele carriers have salt sensitive blood pressure.

      The investigators then developed a striatin heterozygous knockout mouse as a tool to identify
      potential mechanisms for the salt sensitive blood pressure. The investigators documented that
      these mice also have salt sensitive blood pressure with higher blood pressure levels and
      inappropriately increased aldosterone levels on a liberal salt diet.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      HYPOTHESIS:

      Hypertensive striatin risk allele carriers will show significantly greater reductions in
      blood pressure with a specific aldosterone mediated treatment approach (mineralocorticoid
      receptor blockade) than with a non-specific approach (amlodipine).

      RATIONALE:

      Striatin deficient versus wild-type mice have salt sensitive blood pressure and
      inappropriately increased aldosterone levels on a liberal salt diet. In observational
      studies, the investigators documented that in humans, striatin risk allele carriers also have
      salt sensitive blood pressure. Since aldosterone increases sodium retention, excess
      aldosterone levels could be one mechanism for their salt sensitive blood pressure. The goal
      of this project is to document that a genetic marker identifies individuals who are uniquely
      responsive to mineralocorticoid receptor blockade - personalized, precision medicine. The
      investigators will perform a novel two-limb, proof-of-principle, randomized, double-blind,
      active controlled study contrasting a mineralocorticoid receptor antagonist versus a calcium
      channel blocker in hypertensive striatin risk allele carriers. Our primary outcome will be
      systolic blood pressure assessed on a liberal salt diet with our secondary outcome being salt
      sensitive blood pressure.

      PRELIMINARY RESULTS:

      The investigators recently reported that in two large cohorts from HyperPATH, the striatin
      risk allele carriers have increased blood pressure on a liberal salt diet and salt sensitive
      blood pressure. The link between striatin risk allele and salt sensitive blood pressure was
      seen in ALL participant groups - hypertensives, Caucasians, Africans, males, females, old and
      young. The investigators then created a striatin deficient mouse. It also had salt sensitive
      blood pressure. Furthermore, compared to wild-type mice, the striatin deficient mice had
      increased aldosterone levels on a liberal salt diet. An inappropriate aldosterone level for
      the level of sodium intake is a well-known and important mediator of salt sensitive blood
      pressure and hypertension. Thus, if human striatin risk allele carriers have dysregulated
      aldosterone production, this genetic biomarker could identify subjects at increased risk for
      aldosterone-mediated salt sensitive blood pressure and hypertension.

      SUBJECT POPULATION:

      It is estimated that most of the striatin rs2540923 risk allele carriers will come from our
      HyperPATH cohort. Because there are no racial, age or ethnic differences in the salt
      sensitive blood pressure responses observed, an equal number of females and males and the
      same proportion of Africans as in the HyperPATH cohort will be studied. Additional subjects
      will be recruited from the West Roxbury VA Health Care System and/or BWH and Partners
      Healthcare's Research Patient Data Registry. As an example of the richness of these sources,
      Research Patient Data Registry contains over 90,000 hypertensive patients, ages 17-65 years
      with 13.5 % of African descent and 52.8 % women. The investigators will recruit approximately
      105 individuals to have 45 individuals in each drug group for analyses. This assumes that the
      investigators will have 10-15% non-completers. Based on our previous studies the
      investigators estimated that approximately 10% of hypertensives will be carriers of the
      rs2540923 risk allele. The investigators have DNA, history, screening laboratory tests, and
      physical examinations on 4000 individuals in HyperPATH. Approximately 60% have hypertension
      and 10% carry the risk allele, i.e., approximately 250 individuals. The investigators
      estimate from our previous use of this cohort that the investigators will be able to recruit
      75-80 individuals during the 4 years of this project. Thus, the investigators will need to
      recruit 25-30 new subjects over four years, i.e., 6-8 per year. The research Patient Data
      Registry is the source from which the investigators have the most success. Approximately 20%
      of those to whom the investigators send requests to participate in the study enter the
      electronic screening phase. Approximately 50% of these subjects enter the clinic screening
      phase and about 25% of them are enrolled in a study that is comparable or more time consuming
      than the one proposed in this project. Thus, the investigators will need to invite each month
      approximately 200 of the 90,000 hypertensives in the Research Patient Data Registry to
      participate in our study. All subjects will be genotyped at rs2540923, and the risk allele
      carriers will be entered into the protocol and randomized blindly into one or the other
      treatment arms.

      PROTOCOL:

        1. The screened, eligible hypertensives will enter a two-week single blind placebo washout
           phase. Pill count will be used to determine compliance. Those with blood pressure
           between 145-170/90-109 mmHg and pill count between 80-100% will enter the randomized
           phase and counseled regarding salt intake.

        2. The first step: subjects will be counseled regarding liberal salt dietary intake to
           ensure similar intakes in all subjects [Na+ (200 mEq), potassium (K+, 100 mEq) and
           calcium (800 mg)]. This or a greater level of Na+ intake was consumed by 60-70% of
           subjects before entering the HyperPATH protocol. After completion of this diet for 7
           days, the subject will come to the Center for Clinical Investigation (CCI) Ambulatory
           Clinical Center between 7-8 AM, fasting, and after remaining supine for 60-90 mins will
           have blood samples obtained for future analyses, and their BP measured using an
           automatic recording sphygmomanometer (Space Labs, Snoqualmie, WA). Readings will be
           obtained every 2 mins for 20 mins with the highest and lowest values discarded and the
           rest averaged. From the morning of the 6th to the morning of the 7th day, a 24-hr. urine
           will be collected for creatinine and Na+ as a check on balance and stored for future
           analyses.

        3. The second step: subjects will then be fed a 10 mEq Na+, 100 mEq K+ calculated diet for
           7 days. The meals will be provided by the CCI Dietary Core. On the morning of the 7th
           day, the subjects will come fasting to the CCI Ambulatory Clinical Center between 7-8
           AM. After remaining supine for 60-90 minutes, the subjects will have blood samples
           obtained for future analyses and their blood pressure measured using an automatic
           recording sphygmomanometer (Space Labs, Snoqualmie, WA). Readings will be obtained every
           2 minutes for 20 minutes with the highest and lowest values discarded and the rest
           averaged. From the morning of the 6th to the morning of the 7th day a 24-hr. urine will
           be collected for creatinine and sodium as a check on balance and stored for future
           analyses. Creatinine and Na+ in urine from both days will be measured in the BWH
           clinical laboratory. The BP data from 2) and 3) will allow us to calculate SSBP, an
           approach performed successfully more than 500 times in the HyperPATH cohort.

        4. The hypertensive striatin risk carrier subjects will be randomized, double blinded to
           one of two primary treatment groups and titrated to effect every four weeks, as was
           previously reported (1, 2), eplerenone 50, 100 and 200 mg daily or amlodipine 2.5, 5 and
           10 mg daily. Study duration will be sixteen weeks.

        5. Participants will be randomized in blocks of two to 1 of 2 study drugs (amlodipine and
           eplerenone). The drug class assignment will remain the same throughout the study for
           each subject. The PI or Co-PI will notify The Brigham and Womens Hospital
           Investigational Drug Pharmacy Service to escalate or maintain current dose on each of
           the three visits. The Brigham and Womens Hospital Investigational Drug Pharmacy Service
           will be responsible for the randomization schema, recording of study drug assignment,
           and dispensing of prescriptions. All others (PI, Co-PI, research staff, subject) will be
           blinded as to drug assignment.

        6. Home seated, morning cuff blood pressure and pulse will be obtained daily and monitored
           by study staff weekly as a safety check with the information provided to the study staff
           by email or phone. A member of the research team will contact the subject if the blood
           pressure data are not received within 24-hr of the designated time. If the cuff blood
           pressure is greater than 170/109 mmHg on two consecutive occasions 24 hours apart, or
           the subject develops cardiovascular symptoms, the subject will be terminated from the
           study and re-started on medications used before the washout period. The subject's
           physician will be contacted.

        7. Serum K+ will be obtained 1 week after each titration in dose. If serum K+ is greater
           than 5.5 mM on two consecutive occasions 24 hours apart, the subject will be terminated
           from the study. If unexpected adverse event is noted The Brigham and Women's Hospital
           Investigational Drug Pharmacy Service will be notified so as to break code and identify
           agent.

        8. At the end of four weeks since randomization and the subjects have completed the first
           dose of the agent, the subject will be counseled regarding a 24-hour dietary intake of
           sodium (200 mEq), potassium (100 mEq) and calcium (800 mg). After completion of this
           diet for 5 days, the subject returns to Center for Clinical Investigation - Ambulatory
           Clinical Center between 7-8 AM, fasting, and after remaining supine for 60-90 minutes
           again will have blood samples obtained for future analyses and their blood pressure
           measured using an automatic recording sphygmomanometer. Readings will be obtained every
           2 minutes for 20 minutes with the highest and lowest values discarded and the rest
           averaged. This measurement will be used to assess the blood pressure response to a
           single dose of each agent and to determine if the subject has reached goal blood
           pressure (less than or equal to140/90 mmHg). If not, the subject's dose is up titrated
           as per protocol; otherwise the subject is maintained on his/her current dose.

        9. Home seated, morning cuff blood pressure and pulse will be obtained daily and monitored
           by study staff weekly as a safety check with the information provided to the study staff
           by email or phone. A member of the research team will contact the subject if the blood
           pressure data are not received within 24-hr of the designated time. If the cuff blood
           pressure is greater than 170/109 mmHg on two consecutive occasions 24 hours apart, or
           the subject develops cardiovascular symptoms, the subject will be terminated from the
           study and re-started on medications used before the washout period. The subject's
           physician will be contacted.

       10. Serum K+ will be obtained 1 week after each titration in dose. If serum K+ is greater
           than 5.5 mM on two consecutive occasions 24 hours apart, the subject will be terminated
           from the study. If unexpected adverse event is noted The Brigham and Women's Hospital
           Investigational Drug Pharmacy Service will be notified so as to break code and identify
           agent.

       11. At the end of eight weeks since randomization and the subjects have completed the second
           dose of the agent, the subject will be counseled regarding a 24-hour dietary intake of
           sodium (200 mEq), potassium (100 mEq) and calcium (800 mg). After completion of this
           diet for 5 days, the subject returns to Center for Clinical Investigation - Ambulatory
           Clinical Center between 7-8 AM, fasting, and after remaining supine for 60-90 minutes
           again will have blood samples obtained for future analyses and their blood pressure
           measured using an automatic recording sphygmomanometer. Readings will be obtained every
           2 minutes for 20 minutes with the highest and lowest values discarded and the rest
           averaged. This measurement will be used to assess the blood pressure response to a
           single dose of each agent and to determine if the subject has reached goal blood
           pressure (less than or equal to140/90 mmHg). If not, the subjects dose is up titrated as
           per protocol; otherwise the subject is maintained on his/her current dose.

       12. Home seated, morning cuff blood pressure and pulse will be obtained daily and monitored
           by study staff weekly as a safety check with the information provided to the study staff
           by email or phone. A member of the research team will contact the subject if the blood
           pressure data are not received within 24-hr of the designated time. If the cuff blood
           pressure is greater than 170/109 mmHg on two consecutive occasions 24 hours apart, or
           the subject develops cardiovascular symptoms, the subject will be terminated from the
           study and re-started on medications used before the washout period. The subject's
           physician will be contacted.

       13. Serum K+ will be obtained 1 week later. If serum K+ is greater than 5.5 mM on two
           consecutive occasions 24 hours apart the subject will be terminated from the study. If
           unexpected adverse event is noted The Brigham and Women's Hospital Investigational Drug
           Pharmacy Service will be notified so as to break code and identify agent.

       14. At the end of twelve weeks since randomization and the subjects have completed the
           second dose of each agent, the subject will be counseled regarding a 24-hour dietary
           intake of sodium (200 mEq), potassium (100 mEq) and calcium (800 mg). After completion
           of this diet for 5 days, the subject returns to Center for Clinical Investigation -
           Ambulatory Clinical Center between 7-8 AM, fasting, and after remaining supine for 60-90
           minutes again will have blood samples obtained for future analyses and their blood
           pressure measured using an automatic recording sphygmomanometer. Readings will be
           obtained every 2 minutes for 20 minutes with the highest and lowest values discarded and
           the rest averaged. This measurement will be used to assess the blood pressure response
           to a single dose of each agent and to determine if the subject has reached goal blood
           pressure (less than or equal to140/90 mmHg). If not, the subject's dose is up titrated
           as per protocol; otherwise the subject is maintained on his/her current dose.

       15. Home seated, morning cuff blood pressure and pulse will be obtained daily and monitored
           by study staff weekly as a safety check with the information provided to the study staff
           by email or phone. A member of the research team will contact the subject if the blood
           pressure data are not received within 24-hr of the designated time. If the cuff blood
           pressure is greater than 170/109 mmHg on two consecutive occasions 24 hours apart, or
           the subject develops cardiovascular symptoms, the subject will be terminated from the
           study and re-started on medications used before the washout period. The subject's
           physician will be contacted.

       16. Serum K+ will be obtained 1 week. If serum K+ is greater than 5.5 mM on two consecutive
           occasions 24 hours apart the subject will be terminated from the study. If unexpected
           adverse event is noted The Brigham and Women's Hospital Investigational Drug Pharmacy
           Service will be notified so as to break code and identify agent.

       17. At the end of the study, sixteen weeks after randomization, the subjects will repeat the
           liberal salt / low salt study performed at randomization. Subjects will be counseled
           regarding liberal salt dietary intake to ensure similar intakes in all subjects [Na+
           (200 mEq), potassium (K+, 100 mEq) and calcium (800 mg)]. This or a greater level of Na+
           intake was consumed by 60-70% of subjects before entering the HyperPATH protocol. After
           completion of this diet for 7 days, the subject will come to the Center for Clinical
           Investigation (CCI) Ambulatory Clinical Center between 7-8 AM, fasting, and after
           remaining supine for 60-90 mins will have blood samples obtained for future analyses,
           and their BP measured using an automatic recording sphygmomanometer (Space Labs,
           Snoqualmie, WA). Readings will be obtained every 2 mins for 20 mins with the highest and
           lowest values discarded and the rest averaged. From the morning of the 6th to the
           morning of the 7th day, a 24-hr. urine will be collected for creatinine and Na+ as a
           check on balance and stored for future analyses.

       18. Subjects will then be fed a 10 mEq sodium, 100 mEq potassium calculated diet for 7 days.
           The meals will be provided by the Center for Clinical Investigation - Dietary Core. On
           the morning of the 7th day, the subjects will come fasting to the Center for Clinical
           Investigation - Ambulatory Clinical Center between 7-8 AM. After remaining supine for
           60-90 minutes, the subjects will have blood samples obtained for future analyses and
           their blood pressure measured using an automatic recording sphygmomanometer. Readings
           will be obtained every 2 minutes for 20 minutes with the highest and lowest values
           discarded and the rest averaged. From the morning of the 6th to the morning of the 7th
           day a 24-hr. urine will be collected for creatinine and sodium as a check on balance and
           stored for future analyses. The blood pressure data from 2) and 3) will allow us to
           calculate salt sensitive blood pressure. This approach has been performed successfully
           more than 500 times in some subjects in the HyperPATH cohort.

       19. The subject then will have completed the study and will be re-started on medications
           used before the washout period. The subject's physician will be contacted.

      ANTICIPATED RESULTS:

      Based on our Preliminary Results, the investigators anticipate that: 1) in response to the
      first dose of each agent, the risk allele carriers will have significantly greater BP
      reductions with eplerenone than with amlodipine; 2) a significantly lower dose of eplerenone
      will be required to achieve goal BP than with amlodipine; and 3) greater reduction in SSBP
      will occur with eplerenone than with amlodipine. If proven, these results will support: a)
      proof of principle that an activated MR, likely secondary to increased ALDO, is contributing
      to the HTN in STRN risk allele carriers, a conclusion inferred from HET-KO studies described
      in our Preliminary Results; b) that genotype can be used to predict therapeutic response in
      HTN -a positive application of pharmacogenetics to a complex, common condition; and c)
      provide specific information necessary to appropriately statically power and design a
      definitive clinical trial. The investigators also will draw on data obtained from the studies
      performed in AIMS 2 and 3 in designing this new trial. The investigators anticipate that this
      new treatment trial will contrast not only BP and SSBP responses to specific treatments in
      carriers versus non-carriers (a control group) of the STRN risk allele, but also will assess
      the human relevance of the likely mechanisms linking STRN to SSBP, as will be suggested by
      the data generated in the mechanistic studies (AIMS 2 and 3 of this project). For example, if
      AIM 3 shows that STRN deficiency results in decreased RBF response to a liberal salt intake,
      then in addition to measuring the response of BP and SSBP to specific therapy, the
      investigators will measure the treatment's effect on RBF.

      ALTERNATIVE RESULTS AND POTENTIAL PITFALLS:

      First, a negative outcome may not be a true treatment failure, but secondary to: 1) the
      length of treatment being too short; 2) an ALDO mediated effect not blocked by eplerenone; or
      3) an ALDO mediated effect whose mechanism is made worse by blocking the MR. These
      possibilities, in part will be addressed in AIM 2 where the investigators are determining the
      mechanism(s) underlying the STRN/ALDO interaction. Second, a positive outcome could indicate
      that an activated MR is a proximate mediator of the increased liberal salt BP and SSBP
      associated with STRN's risk allele carriers. However, since the investigators did not include
      a control group (non-risk allele carriers), a future study would need to be performed as
      outlined in the Anticipated Results above. Third, the STRN risk allele carriers do have
      increased liberal salt BP and SSBP but the primary mechanism is dysfunction in the renal
      vasculature. This possibility will be addressed in AIM 3. Fourth, the study's length could
      lead to a false positive, i.e. the length is not long enough to see an initial difference
      disappearing with longer therapeutic exposure. However, the investigators believe the trial
      length is appropriate because: 1) most clinical trials using these agents achieve stable BP
      responses during this time interval; 2) with eplerenone treatment, BP nadirs after three
      months with no significant changes even if therapy is extended to a year. Finally, the study
      is too complicated. The investigators will have too many dropouts. The investigators have
      completed this and even more complicated studies in more than 1000 subjects and achieved the
      completion rate assumed for this study.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 15, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 31, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 1, 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Parallel Design</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>The screened, eligible hypertensives will enter a two-week single blind placebo washout phase.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Systolic supine morning liberal salt automated blood pressure</measure>
    <time_frame>Change in blood pressure between baseline and 16 weeks of randomized drug therapy</time_frame>
    <description>Subjects will be counseled regarding liberal salt dietary intake to ensure similar intakes in all subjects [Na+ (200 mEq), potassium (K+, 100 mEq) and calcium (800 mg)]. This or a greater level of Na+ intake was consumed by 60-70% of subjects before entering the HyperPATH protocol. After completion of this diet for 7 days, the subject will come to the Center for Clinical Investigation (CCI) Ambulatory Clinical Center between 7-8 AM, fasting, and after remaining supine for 60-90 mins will have blood samples obtained for future analyses, and their BP measured using an automatic recording sphygmomanometer. Readings will be obtained every 2 mins for 20 mins with the highest and lowest values discarded and the rest averaged. From the morning of the 6th to the morning of the 7th day, a 24-hr. urine will be collected for creatinine and Na+ as a check on balance and stored for future analyses. Procedure will be performed before randomization and at the completion of 16 weeks of therapy.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Systolic salt sensitive blood pressure</measure>
    <time_frame>Change in blood pressure between baseline and 16 weeks of randomized drug therapy</time_frame>
    <description>First step: subjects will ingest a liberal salt intake [Na+ (200 mEq/day)] for 7 days. The subject will come to the study unit between 7-8 AM, fasting. After remaining supine for 60-90 mins, their BP will be measured using an automatic recording sphygmomanometer. Readings will be obtained every 2 mins for 20 mins with the highest and lowest values discarded and the rest averaged. From the morning of the 6th to the morning of the 7th day, a 24-hr. urine will be collected for creatinine and Na+ as a check on balance and stored for future analyses. Second step: subjects will then be fed a restricted salt diet (10 mEq Na+/day) for 7 days. On the morning of the 7th day, the subjects will come fasting to the study unit between 7-8 AM, and the studies performed as detailed above. The BP data from the two diet studies will allow us to calculate SSBP. The procedures will be performed before randomization and at the completion of 16 weeks of therapy.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">250</enrollment>
  <condition>Hypertension</condition>
  <condition>Genetics Hypertension</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Epleronone Arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Amlodipine Arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Eplerenone vs Amlodipine</intervention_name>
    <description>We posit that decreases in striatin activity/levels increases aldosterone secretion resulting in hypertension and salt sensitive blood pressure. Thus, our mechanistic clinical study will assess whether hypertensive striatin risk allele carriers will show significantly greater reductions in blood pressure with a specific aldosterone mediated treatment approach (mineralocorticoid receptor blockade) than with a non-specific approach (amlodipine). To test this hypothesis, we will perform a randomized, double-blind, active controlled study in hypertensive carriers of the striatin risk allele using a novel two-limb, proof-of-principle study. Our primary outcome will be a liberal salt diet systolic blood pressure with a secondary outcome of salt sensitive blood pressure. Therefore, this mechanistic trial will provide support for using a genetic marker that identifies individuals who are uniquely responsive to mineralocorticoid receptor blockade--personalized, precision medicine.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Amlodipine Arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Epleronone Arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        The subjects evaluated in this protocol are hypertensive and carry the Striatin rs254093
        risk allele. Most will be recruited from the HyperPATH cohort. The HyperPATH cohort was
        developed under a SCOR in Hypertension program. This program has demographic data and DNA
        on more than 4000 subjects. Currently, nearly 2000 of them have undergone an extensive
        phenotyping protocol. All hypertensive medications have been stopped for 3 weeks before
        study except agents that interfere with the renin-angiotensin-aldosterone system (RAAS) are
        stopped for three months and amlodipine and/or hydrochlorothiazide is added if necessary
        for blood pressure control until one month before study initiation. Then each subject is
        studied twice on a diet consisting of 100 mmol potassium, 800 mg calcium, isocaloric, 2500
        ml. The two times they are studied are after one week of a liberal sodium diet (200 mmol)
        and after one week of a low sodium diet (10 mmol). Blood is obtained supine, upright and
        after a 3 ng Ang II infusion and a norepinephrine dose response curve. BP and renal plasma
        flow are assessed in response to the diet and the Ang II infusion and 24 hour urines are
        collected on each diet. An oral glucose tolerance test is performed on each subject and
        blood is obtained for DNA. In addition to hypertensives, the nearly 2000 intensively
        studied cohort consists of 75 individuals in 10 families, 225 sibling pairs with
        hypertension, 525 normotensive individuals without a family history of hypertension or
        diabetes before the age of 60, and 250 type II diabetic subjects with or without
        hypertension. On most of the 4000 subjects serum, plasma, urine and DNA is available for
        measurements and analyses. Currently the data set consists of approximately 2100 data
        points of demographic data, family history, biomarkers, and genotypes. The subjects have
        been recruited from Boston MA, Salt Lake City UT, Paris France, Rome Italy and Nashville
        TN. The demographics consists of the following: 52% male, 18% of African descent, 3% Asian
        descent, age 17-66, hypertension stage 1-2, diet or oral medication controlled diabetes
        (80% of the total diabetics). A few subjects will be recruited from advertisements on the
        Internet and in local newspapers, from fliers and postings in the hospital, through
        mailings to households located in the Boston areas and through patient registries at
        Brigham and Womens Hospital. As an example of the richness of these sources is the Research
        Patient Data Registry (RPDR). RPDR is a centralized clinical data registry of 2.8 million
        Brigham and Womens Hospital and Massachusetts General Hospital patients. With approval of
        the Institutional Review Board, investigators may use the RPDR Data Acquisition Engine to
        obtain medical record information for patients with a specific diagnosis. Patients who meet
        inclusion criteria for a specific study can be identified. Potential research subjects may
        be contacted by his/her physician to inform the patient of the possibility of participating
        in a research study and to provide the patient with the information for contacting the
        study personnel. Investigators from Brigham and Womens Hospital may apply to use the RPDR.
        RPDR contains over 90,000 hypertensives, ages 17-65 years with 13.5 % of African descent
        and 52.8 % women.

        We reported in our studies using the HyperPATH cohort that there was no racial, age or
        ethnic differences in the salt sensitive blood pressure responses related to Striatin
        allele variants. Thus, an equal number of females and males and the same proportion of
        Africans as in the HyperPATH cohort will be studied. Subjects in HyperPATH and those
        recruited for the new study in this project will have the similar characteristics. The
        range in age is &gt;17; however, it is anticipated that the clear majority will be between the
        ages of 40 and 60 years.

        Hypertensive patients previously treated will be weaned off medications for two-three weeks
        except agents that interfere with the renin-angiotensin-aldosterone system (RAAS) are
        stopped for three months and amlodipine and/or hydrochlorothiazide is added if necessary
        for blood pressure control until one month before study initiation. Thus, these subjects
        will match the characteristics of subjects recruited in HyperPATH. They must have a
        diastolic blood pressure between 95 and 105 mm Hg off medication in each of three screening
        visits. Subjects with diastolic blood pressures greater than 105 mm Hg or systolic blood
        pressures greater than 180 mm Hg will be excluded. Subjects with only elevated systolic
        blood pressure (but diastolic less than 95 mm Hg) will be excluded because such subjects
        were not in the HyperPATH cohort.

        Based on individual statements, subjects with current excessive alcohol use (greater than
        12 oz/ETOH/week) or recreational drug use will be excluded. Subjects taking other
        medications (except thyroid supplements) or weighing more than 150% of an ideal body weight
        will be excluded. Subjects with other major cardiovascular diseases, diabetes, asthma, or
        other major medical illness will be excluded. Subjects who smoke will be excluded. In
        addition, subjects must have normal values for the following screening tests: CBC, serum
        electrolytes, liver enzymes, TSH, urinalysis, 24-hour urine excretion of catecholamines and
        cortisol, and ECG. Specifically, estimated GFR must be &gt; 60 ml/min and serum potassium &lt;
        5.0 mmol/l. Subjects with hypokalemia while on diuretics will be evaluated for
        hyperaldosteronism before inclusion in this study. Cushings syndrome will be ruled out
        clinically, and with a 24-hour urine cortisol if there is clinical uncertainty. For the
        more difficult question of renal artery stenosis, we will perform renal artery digital
        subtraction angiogram in patients with hypertension and a two-component abdominal bruit.
        Patients with greater than 50% renal artery stenosis will be further evaluated, but
        excluded from this study. Subjects with a known sensitivity to any of the agents, such as
        amlodipine or eplerenone will be excluded. Women who are pregnant will be excluded and will
        be dropped from the study if they become pregnant during the study because eplerenone has
        not been approved for use in pregnancy and the activity of the RAAS is dramatically altered
        by pregnancy.

        The screened, eligible hypertensives will enter a two-week single blind placebo washout
        phase. Pill count will be used to determine compliance. Those with BP between
        145-170/90-109 mmHg and pill count between 80-100% will enter the randomized phase,
        counseled regarding salt intake, and randomized double blindly into one of our two
        treatment arms. We will recruit approximately 105 individuals to have 45 individuals in
        each drug group for analyses. This assumes that we will have 10-15% non-completers.

        INCLUSION CRITERIA:

          1. rs2540923A allele carrier

          2. ages &gt;17 years;

          3. hypertension as defined by primary physician;

          4. not on more than two anti-hypertensives;

          5. normal renal, metabolic, electrolyte, complete blood cell count, and lipid profile
             laboratory tests;

          6. if on an angiotensin converting enzyme inhibitor, angiotensin receptor blocker or
             mineralocorticoid receptor antagonist, needs to be washed out for 3 months.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

          1. known cardiac disease other than hypertension

          2. renal, circulatory or neurologic diseases

          3. diabetes; smoking

          4. secondary hypertension as indicated by history, physical examination or screening
             blood and urine tests; any drug therapy, except for anti-hypertensives and replacement
             thyroid medication.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Haris Lefteri, BA</last_name>
    <phone>6175257288</phone>
    <email>hlefteri@bwh.harvard.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Rebecca Easly</last_name>
    <phone>6175258867</phone>
    <email>reasly@bwh.harvard.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Brigham and Women's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02115</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Haris Lefteri, BA</last_name>
      <phone>617-732-7288</phone>
      <email>hlefteri@bwh.harvard.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Coutinho P, Vega C, Pojoga LH, Rivera A, Prado GN, Yao TM, Adler G, Torres-Grajales M, Maldonado ER, Ramos-Rivera A, Williams JS, Williams G, Romero JR. Aldosterone's rapid, nongenomic effects are mediated by striatin: a modulator of aldosterone's effect on estrogen action. Endocrinology. 2014 Jun;155(6):2233-43. doi: 10.1210/en.2013-1834. Epub 2014 Mar 21.</citation>
    <PMID>24654783</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Garza AE, Rariy CM, Sun B, Williams J, Lasky-Su J, Baudrand R, Yao T, Moize B, Hafiz WM, Romero JR, Adler GK, Ferri C, Hopkins PN, Pojoga LH, Williams GH. Variants in striatin gene are associated with salt-sensitive blood pressure in mice and humans. Hypertension. 2015 Jan;65(1):211-217. doi: 10.1161/HYPERTENSIONAHA.114.04233. Epub 2014 Nov 3.</citation>
    <PMID>25368024</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Pojoga LH, Coutinho P, Rivera A, Yao TM, Maldonado ER, Youte R, Adler GK, Williams J, Turchin A, Williams GH, Romero JR. Activation of the mineralocorticoid receptor increases striatin levels. Am J Hypertens. 2012 Feb;25(2):243-9. doi: 10.1038/ajh.2011.197. Epub 2011 Nov 17.</citation>
    <PMID>22089104</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Garza AE, Pojoga LH, Moize B, Hafiz WM, Opsasnick LA, Siddiqui WT, Horenstein M, Adler GK, Williams GH, Khalil RA. Critical Role of Striatin in Blood Pressure and Vascular Responses to Dietary Sodium Intake. Hypertension. 2015 Sep;66(3):674-80. doi: 10.1161/HYPERTENSIONAHA.115.05600. Epub 2015 Jul 13.</citation>
    <PMID>26169051</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Baudrand R, Pojoga LH, Romero JR, Williams GH. Aldosterone's mechanism of action: roles of lysine-specific demethylase 1, caveolin and striatin. Curr Opin Nephrol Hypertens. 2014 Jan;23(1):32-7. doi: 10.1097/01.mnh.0000436543.48391.e0. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24275769</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Vaidya A, Underwood PC, Hopkins PN, Jeunemaitre X, Ferri C, Williams GH, Adler GK. Abnormal aldosterone physiology and cardiometabolic risk factors. Hypertension. 2013 Apr;61(4):886-93. doi: 10.1161/HYPERTENSIONAHA.111.00662. Epub 2013 Feb 11.</citation>
    <PMID>23399714</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Brown JM, Williams JS, Luther JM, Garg R, Garza AE, Pojoga LH, Ruan DT, Williams GH, Adler GK, Vaidya A. Human interventions to characterize novel relationships between the renin-angiotensin-aldosterone system and parathyroid hormone. Hypertension. 2014 Feb;63(2):273-80. doi: 10.1161/HYPERTENSIONAHA.113.01910. Epub 2013 Nov 4.</citation>
    <PMID>24191286</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Baudrand R, Pojoga LH, Vaidya A, Garza AE, Vöhringer PA, Jeunemaitre X, Hopkins PN, Yao TM, Williams J, Adler GK, Williams GH. Statin Use and Adrenal Aldosterone Production in Hypertensive and Diabetic Subjects. Circulation. 2015 Nov 10;132(19):1825-33. doi: 10.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.115.016759. Epub 2015 Oct 2.</citation>
    <PMID>26432671</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Bentley-Lewis R, Adler GK, Perlstein T, Seely EW, Hopkins PN, Williams GH, Garg R. Body mass index predicts aldosterone production in normotensive adults on a high-salt diet. J Clin Endocrinol Metab. 2007 Nov;92(11):4472-5. Epub 2007 Aug 28.</citation>
    <PMID>17726083</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Garg R, Williams GH, Hurwitz S, Brown NJ, Hopkins PN, Adler GK. Low-salt diet increases insulin resistance in healthy subjects. Metabolism. 2011 Jul;60(7):965-8. doi: 10.1016/j.metabol.2010.09.005. Epub 2010 Oct 30.</citation>
    <PMID>21036373</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Pojoga LH, Underwood PC, Goodarzi MO, Williams JS, Adler GK, Jeunemaitre X, Hopkins PN, Raby BA, Lasky-Su J, Sun B, Cui J, Guo X, Taylor KD, Chen YD, Xiang A, Raffel LJ, Buchanan TA, Rotter JI, Williams GH. Variants of the caveolin-1 gene: a translational investigation linking insulin resistance and hypertension. J Clin Endocrinol Metab. 2011 Aug;96(8):E1288-92. doi: 10.1210/jc.2010-2738. Epub 2011 May 25.</citation>
    <PMID>21613355</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Underwood PC, Sun B, Williams JS, Pojoga LH, Chamarthi B, Lasky-Su J, Raby BA, Hopkins PN, Jeunemaitre X, Brown NJ, Adler GK, Williams GH. The relationship between peroxisome proliferator-activated receptor-gamma and renin: a human genetics study. J Clin Endocrinol Metab. 2010 Sep;95(9):E75-9. doi: 10.1210/jc.2010-0270. Epub 2010 Jul 14.</citation>
    <PMID>20631015</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Underwood PC, Sun B, Williams JS, Pojoga LH, Raby B, Lasky-Su J, Hunt S, Hopkins PN, Jeunemaitre X, Adler GK, Williams GH. The association of the angiotensinogen gene with insulin sensitivity in humans: a tagging single nucleotide polymorphism and haplotype approach. Metabolism. 2011 Aug;60(8):1150-7. doi: 10.1016/j.metabol.2010.12.009. Epub 2011 Feb 8.</citation>
    <PMID>21306748</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Pojoga LH, Romero JR, Yao TM, Loutraris P, Ricchiuti V, Coutinho P, Guo C, Lapointe N, Stone JR, Adler GK, Williams GH. Caveolin-1 ablation reduces the adverse cardiovascular effects of N-omega-nitro-L-arginine methyl ester and angiotensin II. Endocrinology. 2010 Mar;151(3):1236-46. doi: 10.1210/en.2009-0514. Epub 2010 Jan 22.</citation>
    <PMID>20097717</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Chong C, Hamid A, Yao T, Garza AE, Pojoga LH, Adler GK, Romero JR, Williams GH. Regulation of aldosterone secretion by mineralocorticoid receptor-mediated signaling. J Endocrinol. 2017 Mar;232(3):525-534. doi: 10.1530/JOE-16-0452. Epub 2017 Jan 17.</citation>
    <PMID>28096435</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Pojoga LH, Yao TM, Sinha S, Ross RL, Lin JC, Raffetto JD, Adler GK, Williams GH, Khalil RA. Effect of dietary sodium on vasoconstriction and eNOS-mediated vascular relaxation in caveolin-1-deficient mice. Am J Physiol Heart Circ Physiol. 2008 Mar;294(3):H1258-65. doi: 10.1152/ajpheart.01014.2007. Epub 2008 Jan 4.</citation>
    <PMID>18178722</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 17, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 21, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 25, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 10, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 10, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 12, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Brigham and Women's Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Gordon H. Williams, MD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor of Medicine</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hypertension</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Amlodipine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Eplerenone</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

