<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03684720</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>GDL-Efficacy</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03684720</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Using 'Guided-Discovery-Learning' to Optimize and Maximize Transfer of Surgical Simulation</brief_title>
  <acronym>GDLEFFICACY</acronym>
  <official_title>Using 'Guided-Discovery-Learning' to Optimize and Maximize Transfer of Surgical Simulation</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Copenhagen Academy for Medical Education and Simulation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Copenhagen Academy for Medical Education and Simulation</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The study is a randomized experimental study comparing two forms of learning;
      guided-discovery-learning and traditional instructional learning. Recruiting sixty-four
      participants, the investigators plan on comparing these two groups through a procedural skill
      in the form of suturing. In the case of guided-discovery-learning, the group will be allowed
      a discovery phase before instruction. In contrast, the control group will receive traditional
      instruction-lead-learning, in which a teacher teaches the participants a skill, and
      afterwards the participants practice it. After the teaching session, both groups will
      undertake a post-test of skill-level. A week later both groups will undertake a test for the
      execution of the learned suturing skill to a more complex version of the original task
      (Near-transfer). They will also undergo a test for the ability to transfer their learning to
      a new skill (i.e. preparation for future learning), in this case a new suture (Far-transfer).
      By filming these tests and having a blinded expert rater score them, the investigators will
      be able to get a measurement of attained transfer of skill-level throughout the procedures.
      The investigators hypothesis is that, the participants in the Guided-discovery-group will
      have an equal score to that of the traditional-learning group in the ability to obtain a
      skill and transfer it to a more complex version. Furthermore, the investigators hypothesize
      that the Guided-discovery-group will score better than the traditional-learning group in the
      case of transferring the procedural knowledge to learning a new skill.

      As well as testing the efficacy of guided-discovery-learning on a procedural skill, the
      investigators wish to investigate how and why it works. By filming a subset of participants
      in each group, as well as using questionnaires, and focus-group interviews the investigators
      will explore how participants interact in this different learning-environment compared to the
      traditional instructional learning-environment.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      BACKGROUND AND RATIONALE:

      Technical skills are a core competency in surgical specialties. The level of technical skills
      is directly linked to patient outcomes and it is an absolute requirement that surgical
      trainees learn to master basic surgical skills. It is therefore a necessity that medical
      students also become well equipped with these skills, such as suturing. During the last
      decade, minimally invasive techniques have made their way to the operating room and improved
      patient outcomes. Despite these advances it is still necessary for surgeons to master the
      open surgical skills. Unexpected complication can arise in minimally invasive procedures that
      require conversion to open access surgery. Furthermore, there are procedures where you cannot
      use minimally invasive techniques. Because of the extensive use of minimally invasive
      surgery, it is becoming more difficult for doctors as well as medical students in surgical
      departments to gain the level of experience needed, to become proficient in open surgical
      techniques. Pre-clinical teaching and simulation training is a possible solution to this
      problem For novice learners, simulation training is an opportunity to acquire fundamental
      skills such as suturing in a safe and high-feedback environment and without the difficulties
      of acquiring these skills in the workplace. For more advanced trainees, simulation affords
      the practice of difficult and complex procedures which may be otherwise too unsafe to acquire
      during patient care. But, merely implementing simulation training is no guarantee of
      educational utility, and instead thoughtful curricular integration of simulation requires
      considering the role and purpose of the simulator, the student experience, debriefing, and
      the intended outcomes to evaluate success.

      One potential area for optimizing simulation-based training is to clarify instructors' roles
      when providing guidance and direct supervision. One of the challenges with simulation
      training is the amount of resources this sort of education requires. Especially the amount of
      time a student spends interacting with an instructor. Supervision and instruction are key to
      an effective simulation-based training, and there is mounting evidence, which suggest, that
      the community needs to reconsider the balance between instruction and discovery, allowing for
      a good interaction between student and teacher, encouraging learning. Therefore the question
      is; on what level should simulation-based teaching be instructor-orientated? When teaching
      technical medical skills, the answer to the question, whether the training should be
      discovery-orientated or instructor-orientated has been thoroughly researched. Medical
      Education literature has long moved away from the question of either or, and is now more
      focused on, in which order discovery- and instruction-teaching should be, to provide the best
      learning outcome. Recent studies has shown some positive results of
      guided-discovery-learning, which in its simple form, combines both elements from discovery
      and instruction-based teaching. Especially the ability to 'transfer' learning seems vastly
      improved, with this teaching method. Transfer tasks faced by learners exist on spectrum with
      a common challenge being new problems which are more complex or in new contexts but
      essentially require replication of previously learned skills, i.e. near transfer. While near
      transfer can be difficult for learners, even more challenging is transfer that requires they
      apply their previous skills and understanding to learn new skills or concepts, i.e. far
      transfer. Guided-discovery learning has been shown to especially positively impact this
      latter type of transfer task. Thus guided-discovery may promote student-autonomy and
      self-learning which subsequently enables students to take responsibility for their own future
      learning.

      In a pilot-study completed by the investigators research-partners at the Wilson-Centre in
      Toronto, Canada, they compared groups of discovery followed by direct discovery (DD) with
      instruction followed by discovery (IP). In the case of DD, the participants, where given the
      materials needed to complete a simple suture, and a finished suture to look at. After the
      discovery-phase, they were parred with an instructor who demonstrated how it was to be
      performed. In the IP-case they were first instructed on how to perform the suture, and were
      afterwards allowed to practice it. At the end of the course both groups were given a
      post-test of ability, and a week-later both groups were given a retention test as well as a
      transfer test. The pilot-study included 26 participants in total, divided in two groups of
      13. The participants were randomized, and everything was filmed and scored by blinded raters
      after an international standard. There were no significant results for the immediate
      post-test as well as the retention test. But in the case of the transfer test, the DD-group
      was far superior.

      The investigators study will expand on the pilot-study to provide a comparison of guided
      discovery to traditional instruction for the learning of suturing tasks in surgery, seeing if
      Guided-discovery-learning works in a much larger research group. Using a double randomized,
      mixed-methods experimental design, the investigators will investigate the effect of discovery
      followed by direct instruction (DD) vs. instruction followed by practice (IP) for the
      acquisition and two types of transfer of surgical skills.

      The investigators hypothesize that:

        1. Participants in the DD condition will be better able to transfer their knowledge to
           learning a new skill (i.e., preparation for future learning).

        2. Participants in the DD condition will have equivalent performance to IP on post-test,
           but a similar or slightly improved performance on transfer of suturing skill to a more
           complex task (near-transfer).

        3. Participants in the DD condition will interact differently with instructors and will use
           their learnings from the discovery phase to scaffold their learning during the direct
           instruction phase as well as interacting differently with the task at hand.

      EXPERIMENTAL DESIGN:

      The study will be performed at CAMES, including n=64 pre-clinical medical students from the
      Copenhagen University. The investigators are targeting undergraduate students, rather than
      surgical residents, because they want novice learners, and they believe it is worthwhile to
      establish efficacy of the intervention group using simpler tasks which can be feasibly
      studied. The investigators based their sample size on the previous pilot-study which suggests
      that detecting a large effect on a global rating scale (Hedges g of &gt;0. with an alpha of 0.05
      and power of 80% requires at least 13 participants per group with additional participants
      recruited for potential loss to follow-up for a total of 16 per group. Participants will
      receive a certificate showing completed suturing course, as an honorarium to compensate for
      their time in the study.

      Part 1 of this study is an experimental design with two phases that will test the efficacy of
      guided discovery: Phase 1 will be a learning phase with the experimental manipulations, and
      Phase 2 will take place one week later and be outcome assessment for near- and far transfer.
      Part 2 of this study will be explorative seeking answers to how and why guided-discovery
      works.

      For Phase 1, participants will be enrolled and randomly allocated to either the DD or IP
      groups. Each group consists of 8 participants. Participants will be randomized and the method
      of teaching allocated on the date of teaching. This will ensure generalization and ease of
      statistical analysis. In the DD group, participants will be given an example of a completed
      simple interrupted suture and their own skin pad, and suturing kit. They will then attempt to
      replicate the suture using the equipment and their own knowledge over 30 minutes. During the
      same period of time, the IP group will be taught using an instructor. The instructor will
      provide two demonstrations and explanations of the simple interrupted suture following which
      the participants will attempt the suture individually on their own skin pads and suturing kit
      (Modifications will be made by an experienced surgical instructor on our team ST). The
      instructor will be told to provide feedback and guidance to the participants as well as
      answer any questions that participants may have. After the initial time, the DD group will be
      paired with an instructor who will provide two demonstrations and explanations of the suture
      and then interact with participants as they attempt the suture. The IP group will practice
      the suture without any further instructor guidance. At the end of the teaching session, all
      participants will complete a post-test requiring them to complete two simple interrupted
      sutures. Afterwards participants willing will be interview in short focus-group interviews.
      This entire session is expected to last 2 hours including consent and setup time.

      After a 1-week delay, participants will return for Phase 2 for the tests of near- and far
      transfer. Each group will again be randomly allocated a transfer task. Two transfer tasks
      will be used in this study: To test Hypothesis 1, (the impact on transfer to future
      learning), participants will be taught the interrupted vertical mattress suture. To ensure
      equivalency of design and to prevent biasing in favor of one group, all participants will be
      taught didactically, which will involve viewing a 15-minute video designed by an expert
      surgeon on our team (ST) to teach the novel suturing task. Participants will then be given
      20-30 minutes to practice the suture following which they will perform two vertical matrass
      sutures on a typical skin pad.

      To test Hypothesis 2 (the impact on transfer of learning to a more complex version of the
      initial task) participants will perform two simple interrupted sutures on a suturing pad
      representing in an abdominal simulator with the added contextual change of different
      instruments and suture. In both groups, participants willing, will afterwards be recorded for
      a 'Think-Aloud' interview, in which they describe their approach to the suturing task
      out-loud. This phase is expected to last 1.5 hours.

      PERSPECTIVES:

      Faculty instructors are a limited resource in formal simulation-based training during
      post-graduate training. The rise of structured learning activities such as surgical boot
      camps and the emphasis on greater feedback and support for trainees means that instructor
      time is at a greater premium than ever before. Instructors must take time away from their
      busy clinical and workplace-based education activities in order to teach. Not only does this
      cost the healthcare system, the time commitment can reduce willingness to participate in
      education. Additional costs may be incurred by programs that must offer financial incentives
      for instructors. This trade-off between education and clinical work occurs in all academic
      postgraduate programs. Given the cost and investment required to recruit faculty for
      training, research is needed to maximize the efficiency of faculty involvement. The
      investigators work directly contributes to this goal by identifying how instructor guidance
      is most helpful to trainees. Guided-discovery may be one approach to reducing the cost of
      training and instructor time in both post-graduate as well as pre-graduate learning courses.

      Post-graduate training also requires that trainees develop autonomy and are able to learn new
      skills or concepts effectively (stresses trainees' abilities to transfer their training when
      faced with uncertainty and or complexity in future scenarios. Guided-discovery may be an
      effective organizing principle for educational design that can achieve these competencies
      across a wide range of disciplines and training environments. The investigators proposal
      would thus establish evidence of efficacy for guided-discovery for these competency roles.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 2, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 31, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">November 5, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>The study is a randomized experimental study comparing 2 groups, a control and an intervention. One group will receive traditional instructional teaching (control) and the other will receive guided-discovery-learning (intervention). Both groups will undertake the same tests after the teaching session.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>The groups will be masked, until the day of the teaching session, so the investigator won't know, which group he assigns participants to, when enrolling them. The raters who will score the participants, will have no knowledge of which group the participant belongs to.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Effects of Guided-Discovery-Learning in the Far Transfer of Simple Surgical Skills.</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion on average 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Comparison of far transfer-test between control and intervention group as assessed by OSATS: Global Rating Scale of Performance. OSATS is short for: Objective Structured Assessment of Technical Skills. It consists of 7 subsets of which 5 are relevant to the study. Each participant is rated from 1(minimum) to 5(maximum) in each subset, and all subsets are added together by simple summation. This gives the participants a total score of out of 25 points, where the higher the number the better the performance.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Effects of Guided-Discovery-Learning on the Near Transfer of Simple Surgical Skills.</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion on average 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Comparison of near transfer-test between control and intervention group as assessed by OSATS: Global Rating Scale of Performance. OSATS is short for: Objective Structured Assessment of Technical Skills. It consists of 7 subsets of which 5 are relevant to the study. Each participant is rated from 1(minimum) to 5(maximum) in each subset, and all subsets are added together by simple summation. This gives the participants a total score of out of 25 points, where the higher the number the better the performance.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Effects of Guided-Discovery-Learning immediately after a training-session in simple surgical skills.</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion on average 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Comparison of post-test skill level between control and intervention group as assessed by OSATS: Global Rating Scale of Performance. OSATS is short for: Objective Structured Assessment of Technical Skills. It consists of 7 subsets of which 5 are relevant to the study. Each participant is rated from 1(minimum) to 5(maximum) in each subset, and all subsets are added together by simple summation. This gives the participants a total score of out of 25 points, where the higher the number the better the performance.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Impact Difference on near and far transfer using Guided-Discovery-Learning</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion on average 10 months</time_frame>
    <description>Comparison of near and far transfer scores in both control and intervention groups [change from baseline post-test to near- and far transfer tests] using OSATS: Global Rating Scale of Performance. OSATS is short for: Objective Structured Assessment of Technical Skills. It consists of 7 subsets of which 5 are relevant to the study. Each participant is rated from 1(minimum) to 5(maximum) in each subset, and all subsets are added together by simple summation. This gives the participants a total score of out of 25 points, where the higher the number the better the performance.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">64</enrollment>
  <condition>Humans</condition>
  <condition>Simulation Training</condition>
  <condition>Problem-Based Learning</condition>
  <condition>Clinical Competence</condition>
  <condition>Education, Medical</condition>
  <condition>Learning</condition>
  <condition>Surgical Procedure, Unspecified</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Discover followed by direct instruction [DD]</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The intervention group which will be taught suturing using guided-discovery-learning</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Instruction followed by practice [IP]</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>The control group which will be taught suturing using traditional instructional teaching.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Discover followed by direct instruction [DD]</intervention_name>
    <description>The intervention group will be taught suturing using the principles of guided-discovery-learning. In its simplest form, this means allowing the participants to practice placing a simple interrupted suture using the materials needed, as well as a picture of a finished suture. They must then draw from their own learning experiences, as well as discover for themselves how to do it. After a discovery period, an instructor will then teach them, how to place a simple interrupted suture, and will them guide them, as they begin to practice again.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Discover followed by direct instruction [DD]</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Guided-discovery-learning</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Participant are students currently attending a Danish medical bachelor and who are
             willing and consent to participation in the study.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Participants who have received prior suturing education are excluded from
             participating in the study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Andreas H Aagesen</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Copenhagen Academy for Medical Education and Simulation</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Copenhagen Academy of Medical Education and Simulation</name>
      <address>
        <city>Copenhagen</city>
        <state>Kbh Ø</state>
        <zip>2100</zip>
        <country>Denmark</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Denmark</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Reznick RK, MacRae H. Teaching surgical skills--changes in the wind. N Engl J Med. 2006 Dec 21;355(25):2664-9.</citation>
    <PMID>17182991</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dawe SR, Pena GN, Windsor JA, Broeders JA, Cregan PC, Hewett PJ, Maddern GJ. Systematic review of skills transfer after surgical simulation-based training. Br J Surg. 2014 Aug;101(9):1063-76. doi: 10.1002/bjs.9482. Epub 2014 May 15. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24827930</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zendejas B, Brydges R, Hamstra SJ, Cook DA. State of the evidence on simulation-based training for laparoscopic surgery: a systematic review. Ann Surg. 2013 Apr;257(4):586-93. doi: 10.1097/SLA.0b013e318288c40b. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23407298</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zendejas B, Cook DA. Reply to Letter: &quot;Surgical Simulation: Seeing the Bigger Picture and Asking the Right Questions&quot;. Ann Surg. 2015 Aug;262(2):e51-2. doi: 10.1097/SLA.0000000000001138.</citation>
    <PMID>25607763</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Brydges R, Nair P, Ma I, Shanks D, Hatala R. Directed self-regulated learning versus instructor-regulated learning in simulation training. Med Educ. 2012 Jul;46(7):648-56. doi: 10.1111/j.1365-2923.2012.04268.x.</citation>
    <PMID>22691145</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Brydges R, Dubrowski A, Regehr G. A new concept of unsupervised learning: directed self-guided learning in the health professions. Acad Med. 2010 Oct;85(10 Suppl):S49-55. doi: 10.1097/ACM.0b013e3181ed4c96. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20881703</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lee HS, Anderson JR. Student learning: what has instruction got to do with it? Annu Rev Psychol. 2013;64:445-69. doi: 10.1146/annurev-psych-113011-143833. Epub 2012 Jul 12. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22804771</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mylopoulos M, Brydges R, Woods NN, Manzone J, Schwartz DL. Preparation for future learning: a missing competency in health professions education? Med Educ. 2016 Jan;50(1):115-23. doi: 10.1111/medu.12893.</citation>
    <PMID>26695471</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>DeCaro MS, Rittle-Johnson B. Exploring mathematics problems prepares children to learn from instruction. J Exp Child Psychol. 2012 Dec;113(4):552-68. doi: 10.1016/j.jecp.2012.06.009. Epub 2012 Jul 31.</citation>
    <PMID>22849809</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Grierson LE. Information processing, specificity of practice, and the transfer of learning: considerations for reconsidering fidelity. Adv Health Sci Educ Theory Pract. 2014 May;19(2):281-9. doi: 10.1007/s10459-014-9504-x. Epub 2014 Apr 2.</citation>
    <PMID>24691891</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hatala R, Cook DA, Brydges R, Hawkins R. Constructing a validity argument for the Objective Structured Assessment of Technical Skills (OSATS): a systematic review of validity evidence. Adv Health Sci Educ Theory Pract. 2015 Dec;20(5):1149-75. doi: 10.1007/s10459-015-9593-1. Epub 2015 Feb 22. Review. Erratum in: Adv Health Sci Educ Theory Pract. 2015 Dec;20(5):1177-8.</citation>
    <PMID>25702196</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Devine LA, Donkers J, Brydges R, Perelman V, Cavalcanti RB, Issenberg SB. An Equivalence Trial Comparing Instructor-Regulated With Directed Self-Regulated Mastery Learning of Advanced Cardiac Life Support Skills. Simul Healthc. 2015 Aug;10(4):202-9. doi: 10.1097/SIH.0000000000000095.</citation>
    <PMID>26154249</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Brydges R, Manzone J, Shanks D, Hatala R, Hamstra SJ, Zendejas B, Cook DA. Self-regulated learning in simulation-based training: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Med Educ. 2015 Apr;49(4):368-78. doi: 10.1111/medu.12649. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25800297</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 24, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 24, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 26, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 5, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 5, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 6, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Copenhagen Academy for Medical Education and Simulation</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Andreas Höier Aagesen</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principle Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Medical education</keyword>
  <keyword>Basic Science</keyword>
  <keyword>Procedural skills</keyword>
  <keyword>Simulation</keyword>
  <keyword>Transfer</keyword>
  <keyword>Instructional design</keyword>
  <keyword>Guided Discovery Learning</keyword>
  <keyword>Retention</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <provided_document_section>
    <provided_document>
      <document_type>Study Protocol, Statistical Analysis Plan, and Informed Consent Form</document_type>
      <document_has_protocol>Yes</document_has_protocol>
      <document_has_icf>Yes</document_has_icf>
      <document_has_sap>Yes</document_has_sap>
      <document_date>September 19, 2018</document_date>
      <document_url>https://ClinicalTrials.gov/ProvidedDocs/20/NCT03684720/Prot_SAP_ICF_002.pdf</document_url>
    </provided_document>
  </provided_document_section>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

