<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03680781</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IRB-44150</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03680781</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Accelerated Theta Burst in Treatment-Resistant Depression: A Dose Finding and Biomarker Study</brief_title>
  <official_title>Accelerated Theta Burst in Treatment-Resistant Depression: A Dose Finding and Biomarker Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Stanford University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Stanford University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study evaluates the effectiveness of re-treatment using accelerated schedule of
      intermittent theta-burst stimulation for treatment-resistant depression. This is an open
      label study.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Repetitive transcranial magnetic stimulation (rTMS) is an established technology as therapy
      for treatment-resistant depression. The approved method for treatment is 10Hz stimulation for
      40 min over the left dorsolateral prefrontal cortex (L-DLPFC). This methodology has been very
      successful. The limitations of this approach include the duration of the treatment
      (approximately 40 minutes per treatment session). Recently, researchers have aggressively
      pursued modifying the treatment parameters to reduce treatment times with some preliminary
      success. This study will investigate the efficacy of a further modified protocol, creating a
      more rapid form of the treatment and look at the change in neuroimaging biomarkers. In
      particular, this study will determine the efficacy of re-treatment in individuals who have
      already experienced benefit of the accelerated protocol to ensure results can be repeated.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Enrolling by invitation</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">April 13, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage change in Hamilton Depression Rating Scale 21-Item score</measure>
    <time_frame>Difference between baseline and one month after aiTBS treatment</time_frame>
    <description>A 21 item clinical assessment tool used to rate a patient's level of depression</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Hamilton Rating Scale for Depression (HAMD-17)</measure>
    <time_frame>Pretreatment, immediately posttreatment, 2 weeks posttreatment, 4 weeks posttreatment</time_frame>
    <description>A provider administered questionnaire used to assess remission and recovery from depression.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Columbia Suicide Severity Rating Scale (C-SSRS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Pretreatment, immediately posttreatment, 2 weeks posttreatment, 4 weeks posttreatment</time_frame>
    <description>A suicidal ideation rating scale created by researchers at Columbia University.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Hamilton Rating Scale for Depression (HAMD-6)</measure>
    <time_frame>Every day of stimulation, follow-up every 2 weeks after treatment for 6 months by telephone]</time_frame>
    <description>A 6 item questionnaire used to score the severity of depression.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline functional connectivity</measure>
    <time_frame>Pretreatment, immediately post-treatment, 4 weeks post-treatment</time_frame>
    <description>We will assess functional connectivity as seen on resting state fMRI, between the subcallosal cingulate to the default mode network and within the default mode network.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in heart rate variability</measure>
    <time_frame>Pretreatment, during treatment, immediately post-treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Heart rate variability measures will be compared pre-treatment, during and post-treatment</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Beck Depression Inventory (BDI)</measure>
    <time_frame>Pretreatment, immediately post-treatment, 4 weeks post-treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Self-report measure of depressive symptoms</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Quick Inventory of Depressive Symptoms (QIDS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Pretreatment, immediately post-treatment, 4 weeks post-treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Self-report measure of depressive symptoms</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Montgomery-Åsberg Depression Rating Scale (MADRS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Pretreatment, immediately post-treatment, 4 weeks post-treatment</time_frame>
    <description>A 10 item clinician rated measure of depressive symptoms</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">90</enrollment>
  <condition>Treatment Resistant Depression</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Accelerated theta burst treatment</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>All participants will receive theta-burst TMS.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Intermittent theta-burst stimulation (iTBS)</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will receive iTBS to the left DLPFC or bilateral DLPFC, to the right and left DLPFC. The DLPFC will be targeted utilizing either Localite's neuronavigation system or Nexstim's eField neuronavigation system. Stimulation intensity will be standardized at 90% of RMT and adjusted to the skull to cortical surface distance (see Nahas 2004).
Stimulation will be delivered to the L-DLPFC or bilateral DLPFC using either a MagVenture MagPro X100 or a Nexstim TMS device.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Accelerated theta burst treatment</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Male or female, 18 to 75 years of age.

          -  Able to provide informed consent.

          -  Diagnosed with Major Depressive Disorder (MDD) or bipolar affective disorder 2 and
             currently experiencing a Major Depressive Episode (MDE).

          -  prior exposure to rTMS

          -  Participants must qualify as &quot;moderate or severe treatment refractory&quot; using the
             Maudsley staging method.

          -  Participants may continue antidepressant regimen, but must be stable for 6 weeks prior
             to enrollment in the study. They must maintain that same antidepressant regimen
             throughout the study duration.

          -  Participants are required to have a stable psychiatrist for the duration of study
             enrollment.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  History of MI, CABG, CHF, or other cardiac history

          -  Any neurological conditions

          -  History of epilepsy

          -  OCD

          -  Independent sleep disorder

          -  Autism Spectrum Disorder
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Nolan Williams, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Stanford University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of Psychiatry and Behavioral Sciences, Stanford School of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Palo Alto</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94305</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>George MS, Lisanby SH, Avery D, McDonald WM, Durkalski V, Pavlicova M, Anderson B, Nahas Z, Bulow P, Zarkowski P, Holtzheimer PE 3rd, Schwartz T, Sackeim HA. Daily left prefrontal transcranial magnetic stimulation therapy for major depressive disorder: a sham-controlled randomized trial. Arch Gen Psychiatry. 2010 May;67(5):507-16. doi: 10.1001/archgenpsychiatry.2010.46.</citation>
    <PMID>20439832</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>George MS, Wassermann EM, Williams WA, Callahan A, Ketter TA, Basser P, Hallett M, Post RM. Daily repetitive transcranial magnetic stimulation (rTMS) improves mood in depression. Neuroreport. 1995 Oct 2;6(14):1853-6.</citation>
    <PMID>8547583</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pascual-Leone A, Rubio B, Pallardó F, Catalá MD. Rapid-rate transcranial magnetic stimulation of left dorsolateral prefrontal cortex in drug-resistant depression. Lancet. 1996 Jul 27;348(9022):233-7.</citation>
    <PMID>8684201</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chung SW, Hill AT, Rogasch NC, Hoy KE, Fitzgerald PB. Use of theta-burst stimulation in changing excitability of motor cortex: A systematic review and meta-analysis. Neurosci Biobehav Rev. 2016 Apr;63:43-64. doi: 10.1016/j.neubiorev.2016.01.008. Epub 2016 Feb 3. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26850210</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jelić MB, Milanović SD, Filipović SR. Differential effects of facilitatory and inhibitory theta burst stimulation of the primary motor cortex on motor learning. Clin Neurophysiol. 2015 May;126(5):1016-23. doi: 10.1016/j.clinph.2014.09.003. Epub 2014 Sep 16.</citation>
    <PMID>25281475</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chung SW, Hoy KE, Fitzgerald PB. Theta-burst stimulation: a new form of TMS treatment for depression? Depress Anxiety. 2015 Mar;32(3):182-92. doi: 10.1002/da.22335. Epub 2014 Nov 28. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25450537</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 10, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 20, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 21, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 25, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 25, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 28, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Stanford University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Nolan R</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor, Department of Psychiatry &amp; Behavioral Sciences, Director of the Brain Stimulation Laboratory at Stanford University School of Medicine, Stanford University</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Depression</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder, Treatment-Resistant</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

