<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04179006</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>B-BR-108-032</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04179006</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effects of Nutrients Supplementation in Antidepressant Treated Depressive Disorder Patients</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effects of Nutrients Supplementation in Antidepressant Treated Depressive Disorder Patients</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Cheng-Kung University Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Grape King Bio Ltd.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Cheng-Kung University Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled to evaluate the potential role of
      nutrients supplementation (LF chocolate /Erinacine A-enriched Hericium Erinaceus chocolate)
      on the therapeutic efficacy of antidepressants in major depressive disorder(MDD).

      120 subjects who meet all the inclusion and exclusion criteria will be randomized into three
      categories, receiving 3 pieces of supplement nutrients-added or plain chocolates per day for
      a period of 24 weeks in total. The three categories are as follow:

        1. LF chocolate

        2. Erinacine A-enriched Hericium Erinaceus chocolate

        3. Plain chocolate without any supplementary nutrients added (placebo group) These MDD
           patients will continue their antidepressant regimen throughout the study.

      Symptom rating, blood samples for antidepressant-related/depressive disorder-related genome
      profiles identification, as well as for biomarkers assessment for metabolic indices,
      questionnaires and tests for psychosocial variables identification and patient's cognitive
      and social cognitive function or performance determination, will be carried out before and at
      certain time points within the 24-week tracking period. Patient's fecal samples will be
      acquired to recognize and to distinguish the alterations of these MDD patients microbiota
      profiles over the 24-week period.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Major depressive disorder (MDD) is a common, severe, and often life-threatening illness that
      involves the body, mood, and thoughts. Recent reports suggested that immune dysfunction could
      be linked with cognitive impairment and metabolic comorbidities, and accumulating evidence
      suggested that the regulation of the microbiota- gut-brain axis has been shown to impact
      inflammation and to affect brain function.

      This randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled is to evaluate the potential role of
      nutrients supplementation (LF chocolate /Erinacine A-enriched Hericium Erinaceus chocolate)
      on the therapeutic efficacy of antidepressants in major depressive disorder(MDD). 120 MDD
      outpatients (aged 20-70 years) from the National Cheng Kung University Hospital who meet the
      Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of mental disorders, Fifth Edition (DSM-5) and Hamilton
      Rating Scale for Depression (HAMD) scores ≥ 7, receiving fluoxetine or venlafaxine so as SSRI
      or SNRI antidepressants will be enrolled.

      Subjects who meet all the inclusion and exclusion criteria will be randomized into three
      categories, with 40 subjects each, receiving 3 pieces of supplement nutrients-added or plain
      chocolates (placebo) manufactured by GRAPE KING BIO LTD per day for a period of 24 weeks in
      total. The three categories are as follow:

        1. LF chocolate

        2. Erinacine A-enriched Hericium Erinaceus chocolate

        3. Plain chocolate without any supplementary nutrients added (placebo group) These MDD
           patients will continue their antidepressant regimen throughout the study. Follow-up
           visits will be arranged at week no. 0, 2, 4, 8, 12, 16, 20 and 24, in which week no. 0,
           4, 12 and 24 will be the four most important re-visit timing.

      Various assessments or tests will be arranged in these 24-week period. Symptom rating with
      17-item Hamilton Rating Scale for Depression (HAM-D) by psychiatrist will be done at every
      visits. Blood samples for antidepressant-related/depressive disorder-related genome profiles
      identification, as well as for biomarkers assessment for metabolic indices, will be obtained
      at week no. 0, 4, 12 and 24. Questionnaires aimed for psychosocial variables (environmental
      factors) identification including social support scales (SSS), quality of life scale (QOLs)
      and Recent life changes questionnaire (RCLQ) will be self-answered by patients. Continuous
      Performance Test (CPT), finger-Tapping Test (FPT) and Wisconsin Card Sorting Test (WCST) will
      be utilized to evaluate their cognitive performance. Mayer-Salovey-Caruso emotional
      Intelligent Test (MSCEIT) will help in social cognitive function assessment. Patient's fecal
      samples will be acquired at week no. 0, 4, 12 and 24 to recognize and to distinguish the
      alterations in MDD patients microbiota profiles.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 14, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in participant's Hamilton Rating Scale for Depression (HAM-D) score</measure>
    <time_frame>week no. 0, 2, 4, 8, 12, 16, 20, 24</time_frame>
    <description>Depressive symptom rating; 21 items int total, eight items are scored on a 5-point scale, ranging from 0 = not present to 4 = severe, while nine are scored from 0-2; [higher scores denote worse symptoms/signs of depression]</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in participant's BW(kg), Height(cm), Waist circumference(cm), BMI (kg/m2)</measure>
    <time_frame>week no. 0, 2, 4, 8, 12, 16, 20, 24</time_frame>
    <description>Metabolic indices; BW (to the nearest 0.1 kg), height (to the nearest 0.1 cm), and waist circumference (to the nearest 0.1 cm), weight and height will be combined to report BMI in kg/m^2</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in participant's Glucose profiles</measure>
    <time_frame>week no. 0, 4, 12, 24</time_frame>
    <description>Metabolic indices; HbA1c(%)+Fasting plasma glucose (mg/dl)+Fasting serum insulin concentrations (uIU/ml)+Homeostasis model assessment-estimated insulin resistance (HOMA-IR) index+Homeostasis model of assessment for pancreatic β-cell secretory function (HOMA-β) {HOMA- IR= [fasting plasma insulin level (uIn/ml)*fasting plasma glucose level (mg/dl)/405]; HOMA- IR ≥2.5 =&gt; Insulin resistance (+)} {HOMA-β= (360× fasting serum insulin [uIn/ml]) / (fasting plasma glucose [mg/dL] -63)}</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in participant's Fasting serum leptin level (ng/mL)</measure>
    <time_frame>week no. 0, 4, 12, 24</time_frame>
    <description>Metabolic indices</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in participant's Fasting serum lipid profiles</measure>
    <time_frame>week no. 0, 4, 12, 24</time_frame>
    <description>Metabolic indices; including Fasting total cholesterol(mg/dL), High density lipoprotein (HDL) cholesterol(mg/dL), Low-density lipoprotein (LDL) cholesterol(mg/dL), Triglyceride (TG) concentration(mg/dL)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in participant's Cortisol(ug/dL) level</measure>
    <time_frame>week no. 0, 4, 12, 24</time_frame>
    <description>Metabolic indices</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in participant's C-peptide(ng/dL)</measure>
    <time_frame>week no. 0, 4, 12, 24</time_frame>
    <description>Metabolic indices</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in participant's Inflammatory cytokines levels</measure>
    <time_frame>week no. 0, 4, 12, 24</time_frame>
    <description>Metabolic indices; Fasting plasma C-reactive protein (CRP) level (pg/mL) + Oxytocin(pg/mL) + Leptin(mg/mL)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in participants's Quality of life scale (QOLs) scores [WHOQOL-BREF]</measure>
    <time_frame>week no. 0, 4, 12, 24</time_frame>
    <description>Psychosocial variables as environment factors; Quality of Life Scale developed through the World Health Organization (WHOQOL-BREF) &amp; Health-Related Quality of Life (HRQOL) questionnaires will be used as assessment tools WHOQOL-BREF: 4 domains will be assessed, consists of 1. Physical Health 2. Psychological 3. Social Relationship 4. Environment; [higher scores in each domains denote higher quality of life]</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in participants's Quality of life scale (QOLs) scores [HRQOL]</measure>
    <time_frame>week no. 0, 4, 12, 24</time_frame>
    <description>Psychosocial variables as environment factors; Quality of Life Scale developed through the World Health Organization (WHOQOL-BREF) &amp; Health-Related Quality of Life (HRQOL) questionnaires will be used as assessment tools HRQOL: 4 domains will be assessed, consists of 1. Physical Health 2. Psychological 3. Level of independence 4. Social Relationship [higher scores in each domains denote higher quality of life]</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in participant's Cognitive performance</measure>
    <time_frame>week no. 0, 12, 24</time_frame>
    <description>Continuous Performance Test (CPT)[visual information processing &amp; attentive capacity], Finger Tapping Test (FPT), Wisconsin Card-Sorting Test (WCST)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in participant's Social cognitive functional performance</measure>
    <time_frame>week no. 0, 12, 24</time_frame>
    <description>Mayer-Salovey-Caruso emotional Intelligence Test (MSCEIT) scores; perceiving + facilitating + understanding + managing emotion</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in participant's Microbiota profiles</measure>
    <time_frame>week no. 0, 12, 24</time_frame>
    <description>Fecal samples; Types of microorganisms + no. of colonies (colony-forming unit, CFU)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">120</enrollment>
  <condition>Depressive Disorder, Major</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>LF chocolate + antidepressant(s)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants with LF chocolate add-on to their antidepressants regimen.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Erinacine A-enriched Hericium chocolate + antidepressant(s)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants with Erinacine A-enriched Hericium chocolate add-on to their antidepressants regimen.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Plain chocolate + antidepressant(s)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants with plain chocolate add-on to their antidepressants regimen.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>LF/Erinacine A-enriched Hericium/Plain chocolate + antidepressant(s)</intervention_name>
    <description>3 pieces per day</description>
    <arm_group_label>Erinacine A-enriched Hericium chocolate + antidepressant(s)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>LF chocolate + antidepressant(s)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Plain chocolate + antidepressant(s)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Major depressive disorder (MDD) outpatients meet DSM- criteria

          -  Hamilton Rating Scale for Depression (HAM-D) ≥ 7

          -  Start to receive fluoxetine or venlafaxine or those who have received the SSRI or SNRI
             antidepressants

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  (A) had DSM-5 diagnosis for substance abuse within the past three months;

          -  (B) had taken monoamine oxidase inhibitors;

          -  (C) had an organic mental disorder, mental retardation, dementia, or other diagnosed
             neurological illness;

          -  (D) had a surgical condition or a major physical illness;

          -  (E) pregnant or breast-feeding.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>20 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Po-See Chen, Professor</last_name>
    <phone>866-6-2353535</phone>
    <phone_ext>5189</phone_ext>
    <email>chenps@mail.ncku.edu.tw</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Hui-Hua Chang, Professor</last_name>
    <phone>886-6-2353535</phone>
    <phone_ext>5683</phone_ext>
    <email>huihua@mail.ncku.edu.tw</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Cheng-Kung University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tainan</city>
        <zip>704</zip>
        <country>Taiwan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Po-See Chen, Professor</last_name>
      <phone>886-6-2353535</phone>
      <phone_ext>5189</phone_ext>
      <email>chenps@mail.ncku.edu.tw</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Hui-Hua Chang, Professor</last_name>
      <phone>886-6-2353535</phone>
      <phone_ext>5683</phone_ext>
      <email>huihua@mail.ncku.edu.tw</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Taiwan</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Byers AL, Yaffe K. Depression and risk of developing dementia. Nat Rev Neurol. 2011 May 3;7(6):323-31. doi: 10.1038/nrneurol.2011.60. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21537355</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gorska-Ciebiada M, Saryusz-Wolska M, Ciebiada M, Loba J. Mild cognitive impairment and depressive symptoms in elderly patients with diabetes: prevalence, risk factors, and comorbidity. J Diabetes Res. 2014;2014:179648. doi: 10.1155/2014/179648. Epub 2014 Nov 9.</citation>
    <PMID>25431771</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chang HH, Chi MH, Lee IH, Tsai HC, Gean PW, Yang YK, Lu RB, Chen PS. The change of insulin levels after six weeks antidepressant use in drug-naïve major depressive patients. J Affect Disord. 2013 Sep 5;150(2):295-9. doi: 10.1016/j.jad.2013.04.008. Epub 2013 May 9.</citation>
    <PMID>23664565</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Howren MB, Lamkin DM, Suls J. Associations of depression with C-reactive protein, IL-1, and IL-6: a meta-analysis. Psychosom Med. 2009 Feb;71(2):171-86. doi: 10.1097/PSY.0b013e3181907c1b. Epub 2009 Feb 2. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19188531</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chang HH, Lee IH, Gean PW, Lee SY, Chi MH, Yang YK, Lu RB, Chen PS. Treatment response and cognitive impairment in major depression: association with C-reactive protein. Brain Behav Immun. 2012 Jan;26(1):90-5. doi: 10.1016/j.bbi.2011.07.239. Epub 2011 Aug 4.</citation>
    <PMID>21839826</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hiles SA, Baker AL, de Malmanche T, Attia J. Interleukin-6, C-reactive protein and interleukin-10 after antidepressant treatment in people with depression: a meta-analysis. Psychol Med. 2012 Oct;42(10):2015-26. doi: 10.1017/S0033291712000128. Epub 2012 Feb 16.</citation>
    <PMID>22336436</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fabbri C, Porcelli S, Serretti A. From pharmacogenetics to pharmacogenomics: the way toward the personalization of antidepressant treatment. Can J Psychiatry. 2014 Feb;59(2):62-75. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24881125</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Antypa N, Drago A, Serretti A. Genomewide interaction and enrichment analysis on antidepressant response. Psychol Med. 2014 Mar;44(4):753-65. doi: 10.1017/S0033291713001554. Epub 2013 Jul 1.</citation>
    <PMID>23809733</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Biernacka JM, Sangkuhl K, Jenkins G, Whaley RM, Barman P, Batzler A, Altman RB, Arolt V, Brockmöller J, Chen CH, Domschke K, Hall-Flavin DK, Hong CJ, Illi A, Ji Y, Kampman O, Kinoshita T, Leinonen E, Liou YJ, Mushiroda T, Nonen S, Skime MK, Wang L, Baune BT, Kato M, Liu YL, Praphanphoj V, Stingl JC, Tsai SJ, Kubo M, Klein TE, Weinshilboum R. The International SSRI Pharmacogenomics Consortium (ISPC): a genome-wide association study of antidepressant treatment response. Transl Psychiatry. 2015 Apr 21;5:e553. doi: 10.1038/tp.2015.47. Erratum in: Transl Psychiatry. 2016 Nov 1;6(11):e937.</citation>
    <PMID>25897834</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rogers GB, Keating DJ, Young RL, Wong ML, Licinio J, Wesselingh S. From gut dysbiosis to altered brain function and mental illness: mechanisms and pathways. Mol Psychiatry. 2016 Jun;21(6):738-48. doi: 10.1038/mp.2016.50. Epub 2016 Apr 19. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>27090305</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Soto M, Herzog C, Pacheco JA, Fujisaka S, Bullock K, Clish CB, Kahn CR. Gut microbiota modulate neurobehavior through changes in brain insulin sensitivity and metabolism. Mol Psychiatry. 2018 Dec;23(12):2287-2301. doi: 10.1038/s41380-018-0086-5. Epub 2018 Jun 18.</citation>
    <PMID>29910467</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jiang H, Ling Z, Zhang Y, Mao H, Ma Z, Yin Y, Wang W, Tang W, Tan Z, Shi J, Li L, Ruan B. Altered fecal microbiota composition in patients with major depressive disorder. Brain Behav Immun. 2015 Aug;48:186-94. doi: 10.1016/j.bbi.2015.03.016. Epub 2015 Apr 13.</citation>
    <PMID>25882912</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>November 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 19, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 24, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">November 26, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 25, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 25, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 27, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>National Cheng-Kung University Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Po-See, Chen</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator, Professor, Visiting Staff Psychiatrist of Department of Psychiatry, Professor (joint appointment) of Institute of Behavioral Medicine</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Major depressive disorder</keyword>
  <keyword>Supplement nutrients</keyword>
  <keyword>Antidepressants</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depression</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder, Major</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Antidepressive Agents</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

