<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04175587</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>RIF &amp; ATRA in NHR APL</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04175587</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Randomized,International Multi-center Clinical Trial of RIF Plus RA for Non-high-risk APL</brief_title>
  <acronym>RIF</acronym>
  <official_title>Implement Randomized, Controlled, International Multi-center Clinical Trial of Compound Realgar-Indigo Naturalis Formula Plus Retinoic Acid for Non-high-risk Acute Promyelocytic Leukaemia</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Peking University People's Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Ministry of Science and Technology of the People´s Republic of China</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Peking University People's Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Acute Promyelocytic Leukaemia (APL) has been known as a type of cancer, which is of great
      significance to improve its eradication rate. Recent clinical trials show that ATRA plus ATO
      treatment regimen can result in complete response (CR) in 90-94% of patients and 5-year
      disease-free survival (DFS) in more than 90% of patients. However, the ATRA plus ATO
      treatment regimen can achieve considerate survival rate, patients still need to receive
      infusion therapy in hospital. If oral arsenic can replace intravenous ATO without reduction
      of the efficacy, patients would not need to be administered to receive treatment, which would
      highly increase their quality of lives. Phase I, II Clinical trials have verified the
      security and efficacy of the Compound Realgar-Indigo Naturalis Formula. Compound
      Realgar-Indigo Naturalis Formula was approved by the China Food and Drug Administration in
      2009. Investergators have done a multi-centre, randomized, controlled, non-inferiority phase
      3 clinical trial in China. And the result showed that oral arsenic plus retinoic acid has an
      anti-leukaemic efficacy similar to the intravenous arsenic treatment. So Investigators
      performed an international multi-center, Randomized controlled clinical trialsto compare the
      efficacy of oral RIF plus ATRA with intravenous arsenic trioxide plus ATRA in patients with
      non-high-risk APL in different racial types.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Acute Promyelocytic Leukaemia (APL) has been known as a type of cancer, seriously endangering
      human health especially for young adults. It is of great significance to improve its
      eradication rate. Recent clinical trials show that ATRA plus ATO treatment regimen can result
      in complete response (CR) in 90-94% of patients and 5-year disease-free survival (DFS) in
      more than 90% of patients.

      However, the ATRA plus ATO treatment regimen can achieve considerate survival rate, patients
      still need to receive infusion therapy in hospital. If oral arsenic can replace intravenous
      ATO without reduction of the efficacy, patients would not need to be administered to receive
      treatment, which would highly increase their quality of lives. The research and development
      of oral arsenic has therefore become a hotpoint. Professor Huang, Shilin from he 210th
      Hospital of PLA, according to the Prescription Theory &quot;Jun Chen Zuo Shi&quot;, developed and
      designed an oral arsenic, the Compound Realgar-Indigo Naturalis Formula. Phase I, II Clinical
      trials have verified the security and efficacy of the Compound Realgar-Indigo Naturalis
      Formula. Research Team led by Professor Huang, Saijun, Shanghai Institute of Haematology
      (China), studied Compound Realgar-Indigo Naturalis Formula's mechanism of action from vitro
      cell lines and mice.

      In the following Phase II clinical trial, APL patients received Compound Realgar-Indigo
      Naturalis Formula solo treatment regime. It resulted in 96.7% of CR and high safety rate
      Compound Realgar-Indigo Naturalis Formula was approved by the China Food and Drug
      Administration in 2009. Investigators have done a multi-centre, randomized, controlled,
      non-inferiority phase 3 clinical trial in China. 242 newly diagnosed APL patients (with newly
      diagnosed WBC&lt;50×10^9/L) were enrolled. And the result showed that oral arsenic plus retinoic
      acid has an anti-leukaemic efficacy similar to the intravenous arsenic treatment.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">December 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 31, 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 31, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>This study is a prospective, non-inferiority, randomized controlled clinical trial. The non-inferiority is concluded if the lower limit of the 95% CI for the difference in proportion of patients achieving EFS is greater than the -10% non-inferiority margin. The survival curves are estimated by using the Kaplan-Meier method and will be compared by using the log-rank test.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>2-year Event-free Survival (EFS) rate</measure>
    <time_frame>2 year after diagnosis</time_frame>
    <description>treatment failure (no CR after 45-day induction therapy, or no molecular complete remission after 3-month consolidation therapy), relapse (molecular relapse, or haematological relapse); or death from any cause.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">109</enrollment>
  <condition>Acute Promyelocytic Leukaemia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Compound Realgar-Indigo Naturalis Formula Plus Retinoic Acid</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Induction: a) RIF: 60 mg/kg daily until CR, b) ATRA: 25 mg/m² daily until CR; Consolidation: a) RIF: 60 mg/kg daily, in a 4-week on 4-week off regimen for four cycles in a 4-week on 4-week off regimen for four cycles b) ATRA: 25 mg/m² daily, in a 2-week on 2-week off regimen for seven cycles</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arsenic trioxide Plus Retinoic Acid</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Induction: a) Arsenic trioxide: 0·15 mg/kg daily until CR, b) ATRA: 25 mg/m² daily until CR Consolidation: a) Arsenic trioxide: 0.15mg/kg daily, in a 4-week on 4-week off regimen for four cycles b) ATRA: 25 mg/m² daily, in a 2-week on 2-week off regimen for seven cycles Expected Efficacy: Oral RIF plus ATRA is not inferior to intravenous arsenic trioxide plus ATRA for achieving 2-year EFS.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Compound Realgar-Indigo Naturalis Formula Plus Retinoic Acid</intervention_name>
    <description>Randomization is done centrally according to trial centers Eligible patients are randomly assigned (2:1) to the Treatment Group or the Control Group, with a 24-month follow-up.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arsenic trioxide Plus Retinoic Acid</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Compound Realgar-Indigo Naturalis Formula Plus Retinoic Acid</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>intravenous arsenic trioxide plus Retinoic Acid</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Newly diagnosed APL patient (with WHO performance status)

          2. Age 18-70

          3. ALT and AST of maximum 2·5 times the ULN, and bilirubin concentration of maximum two
             times the ULN

          4. Creatinine concentration of maximum three times the ULN

          5. Performance status of 0-2 grade (ECOG)

          6. WBC ≤ 10 x 109/L before the treatment

          7. Informed Consent Paper signed

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Cerebral hemorrhage

          2. Pregnancy

          3. Concomitant severe psychiatric condition or anything else against the fulfillment of
             the plan

          4. Clinically significant arrhythmias or electrocardiogram abnormalities (QT&gt;500ms)

          5. Refusal to sign off the Informed Consent Paper
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Xiao-Jun Huang, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Peking University People's Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Hao Jiang, MD</last_name>
    <phone>13601164350</phone>
    <email>2516735116@qq.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Sheng ye Lu, PhD &amp; MD</last_name>
    <phone>15810723933</phone>
    <email>lushengye01@126.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <verification_date>November 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 21, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 21, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">November 25, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 26, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 26, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 29, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Peking University People's Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Xiaojun Huang,MD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Director of Hematology Department</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Realgar-Indigo Naturalis Formula, Retinoic Acid</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Leukemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Promyelocytic, Acute</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Tretinoin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Arsenic Trioxide</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

