<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04179409</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>SRPT-Dup-US-001</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04179409</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A 48-Week, Open Label, Study to Evaluate the Efficacy and Safety of Casimersen, Eteplirsen and Golodirsen in Subjects With Duchenne Muscular Dystrophy Carrying Eligible DMD Duplications</brief_title>
  <official_title>A 48-Week, Open Label, Study to Evaluate the Efficacy and Safety of Casimersen, Eteplirsen and Golodirsen in Subjects With Duchenne Muscular Dystrophy Carrying Eligible DMD Duplications</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Kevin Flanigan</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Sarepta Therapeutics, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Nationwide Children's Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is an 48-week open-label study to determine the efficacy and safety of casimersen,
      eteplirsen, or golodirsen for the treatment of boys with duchenne muscular dystrophy who have
      a single exon duplication of either exon 45, 51 or 53, respectively. There will be weekly
      infusions and two muscle biopsies at baseline and at month 12.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      DMD is a rare, serious, debilitating, and ultimately fatal, disease for which there is an
      urgent need to develop safe and effective therapies. In order to efficiently meet this
      urgency and the needs of the subject community, the study evaluates the efficacy and safety
      of casimersen, eteplirsen, and of golodirsen administration over approximately 1 year in DMD
      subjects with duplication mutations amenable to treatment by exon 45, 51 or exon 53 skipping.
      Skipping of a single copy of the duplicated exon is expected to result in a wild-type (WT)
      DMD transcript allowing the expression of a WT, full length dystrophin protein. Successful
      skipping of a single copy of the duplicated exon in in vitro and in vivo models has been
      reported in the literature. Casimersen, eteplirsen, and golodirsen have the potential to be
      disease-modifying treatments for boys with DMD mutations amenable to exon 45, 51 and exon 53
      skipping, respectively.

      The totality of the non-clinical data with these PMOs as well as AVI-4225 (targeting exon 23)
      and eteplirsen suggests that PMOs are well tolerated in the non-clinical setting. Moreover,
      treatment with eteplirsen (at 30 mg/kg and 50 mg/kg) has been well-tolerated by boys with DMD
      deletion mutations amenable to skipping exon 51. The relatively low expected risk for
      subjects exposed to casimersen, eteplirsen, or golodirsen and the urgent medical need for a
      treatment for this subject population support the conclusion that the potential benefits of
      exposing subjects to casimersen, eteplirsen, or golodirsen outweigh the potential risks.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Enrolling by invitation</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 18, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 15, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 15, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in dystrophin expression from baseline following treatment with either casimersen (previously SRP-4045), eteplirsen (previously AVI-4658), or golodirsen (previously SRP-4053).</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>This will be assessed by quantification of protein in muscle biopsy tissue by western blot.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Monitoring for the development of unacceptable toxicity.</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>This will be measured by capturing and reviewing Adverse Events ad defined by CTCAE v4.0.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in dystrophin expression from baseline following treatment with either casimersen (previously SRP-4045), eteplirsen (previously AVI-4658), or golodirsen (previously SRP-4053).</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Expression of dystrophin will be measured by immunofluorescent staining in muscle tissue sections in comparison to baseline values</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">6</enrollment>
  <condition>Duchenne Muscular Dystrophy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Casimersen</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>This arm will involve the treatment of boys with DMD who have a duplication of exon 45, for which casimersen will target skipping of this exon.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Eteplirsen</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>This arm will involve the treatment of boys with DMD who have a duplication of exon 51, for which eteplirsen will target skipping of this exon.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Golodirsen</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>This arm will involve the treatment of boys with DMD who have a duplication of exon 53, for which golodirsen will target skipping of this exon.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Casimersen</intervention_name>
    <description>This drug is used to target skipping of exon 45 of the dystrophin gene.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Casimersen</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>SRP-4045</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Eteplirsen</intervention_name>
    <description>This drug is used to target skipping of exon 51 of the dystrophin gene.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Eteplirsen</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>EXONDYS 51®</other_name>
    <other_name>AVI-4658</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Golodirsen</intervention_name>
    <description>This drug is used to target skipping of exon 53 of the dystrophin gene.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Golodirsen</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>SRP-4053</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Is a male with DMD and has an out-of-frame duplication of either exon 45, 51, or 53,
             with a normal copy number of all other DMD exons.

          -  Is above age 6 months of age.

          -  Has sufficient muscle mass in a pair of bilateral muscles that will allow for pre- and
             post-treatment muscle biopsies per PI discretion.

          -  If the subject is ambulant and 4 years old or greater and has been on a stable dose or
             dose equivalent of oral corticosteroids for at least 12 weeks prior to Week 1 the dose
             is expected to remain constant (except for modifications to accommodate changes in
             weight) throughout the study.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Any additional missing exon for DMD that cannot be treated with study drugs.

        Other inclusion/exclusion criteria apply
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>6 Months</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Kevin Flanigan, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Nationwide Children's Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Nationwide Children's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Columbus</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>43205</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Aartsma-Rus A, Fokkema I, Verschuuren J, Ginjaar I, van Deutekom J, van Ommen GJ, den Dunnen JT. Theoretic applicability of antisense-mediated exon skipping for Duchenne muscular dystrophy mutations. Hum Mutat. 2009 Mar;30(3):293-9. doi: 10.1002/humu.20918. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19156838</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Greer KL, Lochmüller H, Flanigan K, Fletcher S, Wilton SD. Targeted exon skipping to correct exon duplications in the dystrophin gene. Mol Ther Nucleic Acids. 2014 Mar 18;3:e155. doi: 10.1038/mtna.2014.8.</citation>
    <PMID>24643206</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mendell JR, Rodino-Klapac LR, Sahenk Z, Roush K, Bird L, Lowes LP, Alfano L, Gomez AM, Lewis S, Kota J, Malik V, Shontz K, Walker CM, Flanigan KM, Corridore M, Kean JR, Allen HD, Shilling C, Melia KR, Sazani P, Saoud JB, Kaye EM; Eteplirsen Study Group. Eteplirsen for the treatment of Duchenne muscular dystrophy. Ann Neurol. 2013 Nov;74(5):637-47. doi: 10.1002/ana.23982. Epub 2013 Sep 10.</citation>
    <PMID>23907995</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mendell JR, Goemans N, Lowes LP, Alfano LN, Berry K, Shao J, Kaye EM, Mercuri E; Eteplirsen Study Group and Telethon Foundation DMD Italian Network. Longitudinal effect of eteplirsen versus historical control on ambulation in Duchenne muscular dystrophy. Ann Neurol. 2016 Feb;79(2):257-71. doi: 10.1002/ana.24555. Epub 2016 Jan 8.</citation>
    <PMID>26573217</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 12, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 25, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">November 27, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 18, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 18, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 20, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Nationwide Children's Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Kevin Flanigan</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor of Neurology</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>DMD</keyword>
  <keyword>Exon Skipping</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Muscular Dystrophies</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Muscular Dystrophy, Duchenne</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

