<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04178798</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>GLLC-EARLY</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04178798</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study to Investigate the Use of Acalabrutinib in the Treatment of Patients With Chronic Lymphocytic Leukemia</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase III Randomized Study to Investigate the Use of Acalabrutinib in the Treatment of Patients With Early Stage CLL With High Risk of Early Disease Progression</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>PETHEMA Foundation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>PETHEMA Foundation</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Study Phase III Randomized Study to Investigate the Use of Acalabrutinib in the Treatment of
      Patients with Early Stage CLL With High Risk of Early Disease Progression.

      The study will consist of a screening phase, a treat¬ment/observation phase until
      progression, and a follow-up phase for progression in patients who discontinue treatment with
      Acalabrutinib without confirmed progression. Patients who progress will be followed for
      survival and initiation of subsequent antileukemic therapy. In the study, 130 patients from
      20 centers in Spain with intermediate, high or very high risk will be randomized (1:1) to
      receive Acalabrutinib (n=65) or clinical observation (n=65). Acalabrutinib will be
      administered orally 100 mg twice daily on a continuous schedule.

      Even though the majority of patients with CLL are currently diagnosed at early stages of the
      disease, there is a consensus that the standard of care in these patients is clinical
      observation (watch &amp; wait) despite of the presence of risk factors for premature disease
      progression. Early treatment in patients with adverse prognostic parameters could prevent a
      disease evolving to a more advanced stage, and therefore more difficult to treat. So far,
      conventional chemotherapy did not show any benefit in terms of overall survival in patients
      with early stage CLL. (Dighiero 1998, Hoechstetter Leukemia 2017) Alongside this, treatment
      with chemotherapy may provoke two undesired effects: first, the occurrence of bone marrow
      toxicity that may hamper the subsequent administration of other treatments during the course
      of the disease; second, but not less relevant, genotoxic drug delivery may elicit a
      phenomenon of clonal selection leading to the appearance of CLL cells with genetic
      aberrations associated with refractoriness and aggressive outcome (i.e., TP53).

      Against this background, it is of interest to investigate the role of new non-genotoxic drugs
      in the treatment of patients with CLL in early stages. Among different scores for selecting
      cases that are likely to progress rapidly, the German CLL Study Group (GCLLSG) risk score
      that includes 8 independent predictors for OS and PFS, differentiates patients with low-risk
      PFS vs. those with risk of early disease progression (median PFS 87 months vs. less than 27
      months), allowing for a risk-adapted treatment approach in early stage CLL. (Pflug 2014,
      Langerbeins 2015).

      Acalabrutinib, a second-generation, selective inhibitor of BTK, has shown substantial
      activity in patients with CLL. Acalabrutinib is a non-genotoxic drug active in cases with
      genetic lesions associated with chemorefratoriness and adverse outcome, including patients
      with alterations of TP53. Therefore, acalabrutinib represents a suitable compound for the
      treatment of patients with CLL in early stages with risk of early disease progression,
      including the high-risk CLL patient population with TP53 alterations.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Randomized, open-label, parallel-group, multicenter, phase III trial with two arms, one with
      acalabrutinib (Arm A) and the other with the standard of care for the management of early
      Binet stage A patients &quot;clinical observation (watch &amp; wait)&quot; (Arm B) in patients with
      untreated early stage CLL and risk factors for early disease progression. Early risk of
      disease progression will be defined by the GCLLSG prognostic index: intermediate (3-5), high
      (6-10) or very high (11-14) risk scores are required to be included in the study.
      Randomization will be managed through an IRT system:

        -  Arm A (65 patients): Patients assigned to arm A, will receive acalabrutinib as one
           capsule of 100 mg orally twice daily on a continuos schedule until disease progression,
           unacceptable toxicity or early withdrawal.

        -  Arm B (65 patients): Patients assigned to arm B, will remain on the w&amp;w approach until
           disease progression or early withdrawal.

      The enrolment period is estimated in 24 months. A treatment cycle is defined as lasting 28
      days.

      The duration of the study will be of 60 months from the inclusion of the first patient to the
      last patient has completed the last follow up visit.

        1. Periods of patient participation in the study

             -  Screening Phase: After providing the written Informed Consent Form (ICF) to
                participate in the study, patients will be evaluated for eligibility, baseline
                characteristics and risk factors, during a screening period up to 28 days prior to
                randomization.

             -  Treatment/Observation Phase: The treatment/observation Phase extends from
                randomization until symptomatic disease progression, unacceptable toxicity or early
                withdrawal. A treatment cycle is defined as lasting 28 days.

             -  Suspected Disease Progression Visit: A visit should be performed at any time when
                disease progression is suspected. If progression is confirmed, the patient will be
                followed every 6 months to assess survival status and receipt of subsequent
                antileukemic therapy until death, patient withdrawal, loss to follow-up, or study
                termination, whichever comes first. The subsequent treatment decision will be up to
                the investigator and should generally follow the routine practice.

             -  End-of-Treatment/Observation Visit: For patients receiving acalabrutinib, the
                End-of-Treatment Visit will be performed within 30 days (± 3 days) after the last
                dose of treatment administration or progression. For patients remaining in the w&amp;w
                approach, the End-of- Observation Visit will be performed within 30 days of
                progression.

             -  Follow-up for Progression (Pre-PD FU): Patients who discontinue the study treatment
                without confirmed progression (according to iwCLL guidelines) will continue to be
                followed for progression every 4 months (±7 days) for the first 24 months of study,
                then every 6 months (±7 days) until progression or study closure.

           Study visits will no longer be carried out for patients who have withdrawn their
           informed consent, have died or have been lost to follow-up.

        2. Study drug - dosage and administration:

           Acalabrutinib is orally administered and is suitable for formulating in capsules.
           Acalabrutinib will be supplied by ASTRAZENECA FARMACÉUTICA SPAIN, S.A., on behalf of the
           Sponsor, as hard gelatin capsules of 100 mg for oral administration. Acalabrutinib can
           be taken with or without food. As acalabrutinib is metabolized by CYP3A, subjects should
           be cautioned against using herbal remedies or dietary supplements (in particular, St
           John's wort, which is a potent CYP3A inducer). Otherwise, subjects should maintain a
           normal diet unless modifications are required to manage an AE such as diarrhea, nausea
           or vomiting.

        3. Description of Procedures

             -  Confirmation of Eligibility: Perform all necessary procedures and evaluations to
                document that the patient meets each eligibility criterion.

             -  Medical History: will include concurrent medical signs and symptoms based upon
                available documents and patient history.

             -  Adverse Events: All medical occurrences that meet the accepted regulatory
                definition of AE must be recorded from the time the informed consent form is signed
                until 30 days after the last dose of study drug (in Arm A) or progression (in both
                arms).

             -  Physical Examination, Vital Signs, Height and Weight, ECOG. This will include the
                lymphatic system, spleen and liver examination as well. will be performed at every
                visit during the study.

             -  Clinical Stage Rai/Binet: A Binet or Rai staging system will be used at every study
                visit (except on Day 15 Cycle 1 and Day 15 Cycle 2) to stratify patients according
                to the disease risk.

             -  Disease-related symptoms will be assessed and collected at every study visit.

             -  Electrocardiogram (ECG) done only at Screening.

             -  Concomitant Medication: All medications from 14 days before the start of study drug
                administration through 30 days after the last dose of study drug or progression.

             -  German CLL Study Group (GCLLSG) prognostic index will be determined for each
                patient only at screening.

             -  Cumulative Illness Rating Scale is a measure of comorbid medical conditions that
                help to characterize patients with concomitant morbidity and fit.

             -  Hepatitis Serologies: Hepatitis serologies include Hepatitis C antibody, Hepatitis
                B surface antigen, Hepatitis B surface antibody, and Hepatitis B core antibody.

             -  Hematology: will be performed at every visit by local laboratory and will include a
                complete blood cell count.

             -  Coagulation Panel: Measurement of prothrombin time /INR, and activated partial
                thromboplastin time will be performed at Screening.

             -  Serum chemistry will be locally performed at every visit (except on Day 15 of
                Cycles 1 and 2)

             -  Creatinine clearance (Cockcroft-Gault) will be evaluated (only at screening) by
                local laboratory.

             -  Cytogenetic, CLL FISH Panel within 90 days prior to the inclusion in the study to
                detect abnormalities in chromosomes 13q, 12, 11q, and 17p must be evaluated.

             -  Blood for immunophenotyping (for diagnosis), IGVH mutation status, and serum
                markers (B2-microglobulin and thymidine kinase) will be centralized in the
                department of Hematology of the University Hospital of Vall d'Hebron. Blood samples
                will be collected for all patients at Screening.

             -  Serum quantitative immunoglobulin (IgG, IgM, IgA) levels will be evaluated by local
                laboratory at screening, on Day 1 of every odd cycle from Cycles 3 through 12, on
                Day 1 of every odd cycle (for Cycles 13, 15, 17, 19, 21 and 23), and then every 3
                cycles until progression or study closure.

             -  Coombs test will be performed (only at screening) by local laboratory.

             -  CT scans of the neck, chest, abdomen, and pelvis.

             -  Bone Marrow Aspirate and/or Biopsy should be obtained to confirm CR, or confirm
                cytopenic progression and distinguish autoimmune versus treatment-related causes.
                In addition, a further marrow assessment should be performed at any time during
                follow-up when the patient has cleared MRD from the peripheral blood. Marrow
                aspirate to confirm CR should have a flow-cytometry-based MRD; MRD should be also
                analysed in peripheral blood .

             -  Overall response assessment will include evaluation of physical exams, recording of
                symptoms, and hematological evaluations. OR will be assessed on Day 1 Cycle 2, on
                Day 1 of Cycles 3 to 12, and on Day 1 of Cycles 13, 15, 17, 19, 21, and 23, and
                then every 3 cycles to disease progression or study closure. For patients in Arm B,
                response assessment will be performed on Day 1 of every 3 cycles to progression or
                study termination.

             -  Overall Survival: After progression, patients will be followed every 6 months to
                assess survival status and the start of subsequent cancer therapies until death,
                patient withdrawal, loss to follow-up, or study termination, whichever comes first.

             -  Biomarkers: Blood samples will be collected for an exploratory biomarker assessment
                at baseline and at progression. Samples at month 3, 6 and 12 will be optional and
                will collected in patients who have accepted in the inform consent form.

        4. Main Efficacy Evaluations Suspected Disease Progression: should be confirmed with a CT
           scan (or MRI, if CT is contraindicated).

           Disease Evaluation: Objective response will be categorized as CR, CR with incomplete
           bone marrow recovery (CRi), nodular partial remission (nPR), partial response (PR),
           stable disease, or progressive disease-all based upon IWCLL criteria (Hallek 2018).
           Patients who achieve PR in all parameters except lymphocyte count will be considered a
           PR with lymphocytosis, for the purposes of the Protocol. CRs must be confirmed by bone
           marrow biopsy/aspirate.

           Given the known mechanism of action of BCR-inhibiting agents, including acalabrutinib,
           and the treatment-related lymphocytosis frequently observed during treatment with
           acalabrutinib, isolated treatment-related lymphocytosis (in absence of other clinical,
           CT, or laboratory evidence of disease progression) will not be considered progressive
           disease. This approach is supported by the IWCLL guidelines (Hallek 2018).

        5. Safety, Monitoring and Reporting: An adverse event (AE) is any untoward medical
           occurrence in a patient or clinical investigation subject administered a medicinal
           product and which does not necessarily have a causal relationship with the treatment. An
           AE can therefore be any unfavourable and unintended sign, symptom, or disease temporally
           associated with the use of a medicinal product, whether or not considered related to the
           medicinal product.

           PETHEMA Foundation has delegated Pharmacovigilance functions to the Pharmacovigilance
           Department of the CRO Dynamic Science S.L.

        6. Warnings, Precautions, and Adverse Effects: Acalabrutinib is contraindicated in subjects
           with clinically significant hypersensitivity to the compound itself or to the excipients
           in its formulation.

           Hemorrhagic events, including CNS, respiratory, and gastrointestinal hemorrhage, have
           been reported in clinical trials with acalabrutinib. The mechanism for hemorrhage is not
           well understood.

           Serious infections, including fatal events, have been reported in clinical studies with
           acalabrutinib. The most frequently reported Grade 3 or 4 infection was pneumonia. Cases
           of hepatitis B virus reactivation (resulting in liver failure and death in 1 case) and
           cases of progressive multifocal leukoencephalopathy have occurred in subjects with
           hematologic malignancies.

           Cytopenias: treatment-emergent Grade 3 or 4 cytopenias including neutropenia, anemia,
           and thrombocytopenia have occurred in clinical studies with acalabrutinib.

           Events of second primary malignancies, including non-skin carcinomas, have been reported
           in clinical studies with acalabrutinib. The most frequently reported was skin cancer.

           Events of atrial fibrillation/flutter have been reported in clinical studies with
           acalabrutinib, particularly in subjects with cardiac risk factors, hypertension,
           diabetes mellitus, acute infections, and a previous history of atrial fibrillation. The
           mechanism for atrial fibrillation is not well understood.

           Subjects should be managed per institutional guidelines with supportive care and
           diagnostic evaluations as clinically indicated.

        7. Drug-drug Interactions: Acalabrutinib is partially metabolized by CYP3A; its exposure is
           affected when coadministered with strong CYP3A inducers or inhibitors. Consequently, the
           concomitant use of strong inhibitors/inducers of CYP3A should be avoided when possible.
           Subjects who require therapy with strong inhibitors of CYP3A should not be enrolled into
           the study.

           Subjects should avoid the use of calcium carbonate containing drugs or supplements for a
           period of at least 2 hours before and 2 hours after taking acalabrutinib. Use of
           omeprazole, esomeprazole, lansoprazole or any other proton pump inhibitors while taking
           acalabrutinib is not recommended due to a potential decrease in study drug exposure. For
           subjects who require H2 antagonists, the recommendation is that acalabrutinib is taken
           at least 2 hours before the H2 antagonist.

        8. Treatment-related lymphocytosis, for the purposes of this Protocol, is defined as an
           elevation in blood lymphocyte count of ≥50% compared to baseline. Acalabrutinib
           associated treatment-related lymphocytosis generally occurs within the first weeks of
           therapy, peaks within the first few months, and resolves slowly. Patients with
           treatment-related lymphocytosis should remain on study treatment and continue with all
           study-related procedures.

        9. Once the complete study is explained, written Informed Consent will be obtained from the
           patient, legal guardian or representative before starting participation in the study.

       10. In order to respect patient privacy, patients will be identified by patient number in
           all case report forms, study drug accountability logs, study reports and communications.
           Confidentiality of patients will be kept and their identity will not be disclosed as far
           as permitted by the law and relevant regulations. Regulation (EU) 2016/679 of the
           European Parliament and of the Council, of 27 April 2016, on the protection of natural
           persons with regard to the processing of personal data and the free movement of such
           data, and Organic Law 3/2018 of December 5, on the Protection or Personal Data and
           guarantee of digital rights.

       11. Early study discontinuation: This study may be discontinued early if, in the Sponsor's
           opinion, there is sufficient reasonable cause.

       12. Data registering and storage: The investigator will keep all study records in compliance
           with ICH-GCP requirements and current regulations.

       13. Responsibility and insurance: The Sponsor has taken out an insurance policy covering, in
           its terms and conditions, the liability for damages caused to participants and derived
           from this research, performed fully in compliance with both the scientific Protocol and
           the applicable law and professional standards.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">December 9, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 1, 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 1, 2024</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Arm A (65 patients): Patients assigned to arm A, will receive acalabrutinib as one capsule of 100 mg orally twice daily on a continuos schedule until disease progression, unacceptable toxicity or early withdrawal.
Arm B (65 patients): Patients assigned to arm B, will remain on the w&amp;w approach until disease progression or early withdrawal.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Event-Free Survival (EFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>From randomization to 60 months</time_frame>
    <description>EFS is defined as the time between the date of randomization and time point of symptomatic disease progression with treatment indication according to the iwCLL-Guidelines, initiation of subsequent treatment for CLL or death by any cause, whichever occurs first.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression-Free Survival (PFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>From randomization to 60 months</time_frame>
    <description>Time between the date of randomization and progression of disease or death from any cause, whichever occurs first.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall Survival (OS)</measure>
    <time_frame>From randomization to 60 months</time_frame>
    <description>Time between the date of randomization and death from may cause.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time To Next Treatment (TTNT)</measure>
    <time_frame>From randomization to 60 months</time_frame>
    <description>Time from randomization until the date of initiation of subsequent treatment for CLL or death from any cause.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Objetive Response Rate (ORR)</measure>
    <time_frame>From randomization to 60 months</time_frame>
    <description>Is defined as the proportion of patients who achieve a CR (Complete Remission), CRi (CR with incomplete bone marrow recovery), nPR (nodular Partial Remission) or PR (Partial Response) over the course of the study. Patients who achieve a PR with lymphocytosis will be included in the ORR. The rate of MRD-negative disease (MRD: Minimal Residual Disease) will also be calculated. The IWCLL guidelines (Hallek, 2018) will be used to measure response in CLL.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">130</enrollment>
  <condition>Chronic Lymphocytic Leukemia- Binet Staging System</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm A_Acalabrutinib</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients assigned to arm A, will receive acalabrutinib as one capsule of 100 mg orally twice daily on a continuos schedule until disease progression, unacceptable toxicity or early withdrawal.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B_Standard of care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients assigned to arm B, will receive standard of care for the management of early Binet stage A patients &quot;clinical observation (watch &amp; wait)&quot; until disease progression or early withdrawal.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Acalabrutinib 100 MG Oral Capsule</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients in Arm A will receive acalabrutinib as one capsule of 100 mg orally twice daily on a continuos Schedule.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm A_Acalabrutinib</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Adult patients with previously untreated CLL according to IWCLL criteria (Hallek,
             2018).

          2. Must understand and voluntarily sign an informed consent form.

          3. Age ≥ 18 years at the time of signing the informed consent form and must be able to
             adhere to the study visit schedule and other Protocol requirements.

          4. Diagnosis of CLL &lt; 6 months prior to inclusion in the study.

          5. Binet clinical stage A and Rai 0 or 1.

          6. Absence of criteria for the initiation of chemotherapy, defined by the IWCLL
             guidelines for diagnosis and treatment of CLL (Hallek, 2018):

               -  Evidence of progressive marrow failure as manifested by the development of, or
                  worsening of, anemia and/or thrombocytopenia.

               -  Massive (i.e. ≥6 cm below the left costal margin) or progressive or symptomatic
                  splenomegaly.

               -  Massive nodes (i.e. ≥10 cm in longest diameter) or progressive or symptomatic
                  lymphadenopathy.

               -  Progressive lymphocytosis with an increase of ≥50% over a 2-month period, or
                  lymphocyte doubling time (LDT) of less than 6 months.

               -  A minimum of any one of the following disease-related symptoms: unintentional
                  weight loss ≥10% within the previous 6 months, significant fatigue (i.e., ECOG PS
                  2 or worse; cannot work or unable to perform usual activities), fevers of ≥38.0°C
                  for 2 or more weeks without other evidence of infection, or night sweats for more
                  than 1 month without evidence of infection.

               -  Autoimmune complications including anemia or thrombocytopenia poorly responsive
                  to corticosteroids.

               -  Symptomatic or functional extranodal involvement (e.g., skin, kidney, lung,
                  spine).

          7. GCLLSG prognostic index with intermediate (3-5), high (6-10) or very high (11-14) risk
             scores.

          8. Must have an Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status score of ≤1.

          9. All sexually active subjects with the capacity to reproduce (male and female) must use
             high-efficacy contraceptive methods during the course of the study. These restrictions
             apply for 3 months after the last dose of acalabrutinib. High-efficacy contraceptive
             methods include:

               -  Total abstinence when consistent with the subject's typical and preferred
                  lifestyle (periodic abstinence [e.g. calendar methods, ovulation, symptothermal
                  and post-ovulation methods] and the withdrawal method are not acceptable
                  contraceptive methods).

               -  Female sterilisation defined as surgical hysterectomy, bilateral oophorectomy, or
                  tubal ligation at least six weeks prior to the study treatment (a simple
                  oophorectomy does not meet the definition of female sterilisation).

               -  Male sterilisation (at least six months before screening). A man who has
                  undergone a vasectomy must be the only partner who is a study subject.

               -  Combination of two of the following methods (a+b or a+c or b+c):

                    1. Use of oral, injected or implanted hormonal contraceptives, or other
                       hormonal contraceptive methods that have a comparable efficacy (failure rate
                       &lt; 1%), for example, hormonal vaginal ring or transdermal hormonal
                       contraceptive. If an oral contraceptive is used, women must use the same
                       pill for a minimum of three months before taking the study treatment.

                    2. Placement of an intrauterine device (IUD) or an intrauterine system (IUS).

                    3. Barrier contraceptive methods: condom or cervical cap (cervical/vault
                       diaphragm or cap) with foam/gel/film/spermicidal cream/vaginal suppository.

         10. Female subjects of childbearing potential must have a negative serum pregnancy test at
             screening. Females of child bearing potential are defined as sexually mature women
             without prior hysterectomy or who have had any evidence of menses in the past 12
             months. However, women who have been amenorrheic for 12 or more months are still
             considered to be of childbearing potential if the amenorrhea is possibly due to other
             causes, including prior chemotherapy, anti-estrogens, or ovarian suppression.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Prior treatment for CLL.

          2. Meets any criteria for the initiation of treatment defined by the IWCLL guidelines for
             diagnosis and treatment of CLL (Hallek, 2018).

          3. Known Human Immunodeficiency Virus (HIV), Hepatitis B Virus (HBV) and/or Hepatitis C
             Virus (HCV) infection. Subjects who are hepatitis B core antibody (anti-HBc) positive
             and who are surface antigen negative will need to have a negative polymerase chain
             reaction (PCR). Those who are hepatitis B surface antigen (HbsAg) positive or
             hepatitis B PCR positive will be excluded. Subjects who are hepatitis C antibody
             positive will need to have a negative PCR result. Those who are hepatitis C PCR
             positive will be excluded.

          4. Estimated Glomerular Filtration Rate (Cockcroft-Gault Appendix C) ≤ 40 mL/min/1.73m2.

          5. Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) &lt; 1.0 X 109/L.

          6. Platelet count &lt; 100 X 109/L.

          7. Serum aspartate aminotransferase (AST)/serum glutamic-oxaloacetic transaminase (SGOT)
             or alanine transaminase (ALT)/serum glutamate pyruvate transaminase (SGPT) &gt;2.5 x
             upper limit of normal (ULN).

          8. Serum total bilirubin &gt;1.5 x ULN, except in cases of Gilbert's syndrome.

          9. Prothrombin time/INR or aPTT (in the absence of Lupus anticoagulant) &gt;2 x ULN.

         10. Active bleeding, history of bleeding diathesis (e.g., hemophilia or von Willebrand
             disease).

         11. Requires treatment with proton pump inhibitors (e.g., omeprazole, esomeprazole,
             lansoprazole, dexlansoprazole, rabeprazole, or pantoprazole). Subjects receiving
             proton pump inhibitors who switch to H2-receptor antagonists or antacids are eligible
             for enrolment to this study.

         12. Unable to swallow capsules, or has disease significantly affecting gastrointestinal
             function that would limit absorption of oral medication.

         13. Currently active, clinically significant cardiovascular disease or a history of
             myocardial infarction within 3 months prior to enrolment. Exception: Subjects with
             controlled, asymptomatic atrial fibrillation during screening can enrol on study.

         14. Requires or receiving anticoagulation with warfarin or equivalent vitamin K
             antagonists (e.g., phenprocoumon) within 7 days of first dose of study drug.

         15. Systemic infection that has not resolved prior to initiating study treatment in spite
             of adequate anti-infective therapy.

         16. Pregnant or lactating females.

         17. Participation in any clinical study or having taken any investigational therapy within
             28 days prior to initiating study therapy.

         18. Prior history of malignancies, other than CLL, unless the patient has been free of the
             disease for ≥ 3 years. Exceptions include the following:

               -  Basal cell carcinoma of the skin

               -  Squamous cell carcinoma of the skin

               -  Carcinoma in situ of the cervix

               -  Carcinoma in situ of the breast

               -  Incidental histologic finding of prostate cancer (TNM stage of T1a or T1b)

         19. Presence of autoimmune haemolytic anaemia or autoimmune thrombocytopenia, or a
             positive direct antiglobulin test result.

         20. Chronic use of steroids in excess of prednisone 20mg/day or its equivalent.

         21. Major surgery within the last 28 days prior to registration.

         22. History of stroke or intracranial hemorrhage within 6 months prior to enrolment.

         23. Requires treatment with strong CYP3A4/5 Inhibitors.

         24. Known history of drug-specific hypersensitivity or anaphylaxis to study drug
             (including active product or excipient components).

         25. Any life-threatening illness, medical condition, or organ system dysfunction which, in
             the investigator's opinion, could compromise the subject's safety, interfere with the
             absorption or metabolism of acalabrutinib, or put the study outcomes at undue risk.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Pau Abrisqueta Costa, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University Hospital of Vall d'Hebron</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Francesc Bosch Albareda, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University Hospital of Vall d'Hebron</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Carmen López Carrero</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Fundación Pethema</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Olga García Calduch</last_name>
    <phone>0034 609 128 678</phone>
    <email>olga.garcia.calduch@fundacionpethema.es</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Carina Fernandez Mondino</last_name>
    <phone>0034 91 456 11 05</phone>
    <email>ensayosclinicos@dynasolutions.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Complejo Hospitalario Universitario A Coruña</name>
      <address>
        <city>A Coruña</city>
        <zip>15010</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ana María Vale López, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>ICO Badalona (Hospital Universitari Germans Trias i Pujol)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Badalona</city>
        <zip>08916</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Christelle Ferra Coll, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital de la Santa Creu i Sant Pau</name>
      <address>
        <city>Barcelona</city>
        <zip>08025</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Carol Moreno Atanasio, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Universitari Vall d'Hebron</name>
      <address>
        <city>Barcelona</city>
        <zip>08035</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Pau Abrisqueta Costa, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Clínic de Barcelona</name>
      <address>
        <city>Barcelona</city>
        <zip>08036</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Julio Delgado González, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>ICO L´Hospitalet - Hospital Duran i Reynals</name>
      <address>
        <city>Barcelona</city>
        <zip>08908</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ana Carla de Oliveira Ramos, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Universitario Reina Sofía</name>
      <address>
        <city>Córdoba</city>
        <zip>14004</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Margarita Fernández de la Mata, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Universitario de La Princesa</name>
      <address>
        <city>Madrid</city>
        <zip>28006</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Javier Loscertales Pueyo, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Universitario Infanta Leonor</name>
      <address>
        <city>Madrid</city>
        <zip>28031</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jose Angel Hernandez Rivas, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Universitario Fundación Jiménez Díaz</name>
      <address>
        <city>Madrid</city>
        <zip>28040</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Raul Cordoba Mascuñano, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Universitario 12 de Octubre</name>
      <address>
        <city>Madrid</city>
        <zip>28041</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Javier de la Serna Torroba</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Universitario La Paz</name>
      <address>
        <city>Madrid</city>
        <zip>28046</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Patricia Baltasar Tello, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Costa del Sol</name>
      <address>
        <city>Marbella</city>
        <zip>29603</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ángeles Medina Pérez, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Universitario Central de Asturias</name>
      <address>
        <city>Oviedo</city>
        <zip>33011</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Angel Ramírez Páyer, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Universitario Son Espases</name>
      <address>
        <city>Palma De Mallorca</city>
        <zip>07120</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Carmen Ballester Ruiz, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Universitario Salamanca</name>
      <address>
        <city>Salamanca</city>
        <zip>37007</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Marcos González Díaz, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Universitario Marqués de Valdecilla</name>
      <address>
        <city>Santander</city>
        <zip>39009</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Lucrecia Yáñez San Segundo, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Universitario Virgen de Valme</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sevilla</city>
        <zip>41014</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Eduardo Ríos Herranz, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Virgen de la Salud (Complejo Hospitalario de Toledo)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toledo</city>
        <zip>45004</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Luis Felipe Casado Montero, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>H Clínico Universitario Valencia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Valencia</city>
        <zip>46010</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>María José Terol Casterá, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Universitari i Politecnic La Fe</name>
      <address>
        <city>Valencia</city>
        <zip>46026</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Rafael Andreu Lapiedra, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Spain</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Abrisqueta P, Pereira A, Rozman C, Aymerich M, Giné E, Moreno C, Muntañola A, Rozman M, Villamor N, Hodgson K, Campo E, Bosch F, Montserrat E. Improving survival in patients with chronic lymphocytic leukemia (1980-2008): the Hospital Clinic of Barcelona experience. Blood. 2009 Sep 3;114(10):2044-50. doi: 10.1182/blood-2009-04-214346. Epub 2009 Jun 24.</citation>
    <PMID>19553638</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Advani RH, Buggy JJ, Sharman JP, Smith SM, Boyd TE, Grant B, Kolibaba KS, Furman RR, Rodriguez S, Chang BY, Sukbuntherng J, Izumi R, Hamdy A, Hedrick E, Fowler NH. Bruton tyrosine kinase inhibitor ibrutinib (PCI-32765) has significant activity in patients with relapsed/refractory B-cell malignancies. J Clin Oncol. 2013 Jan 1;31(1):88-94. doi: 10.1200/JCO.2012.42.7906. Epub 2012 Oct 8.</citation>
    <PMID>23045577</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Barrientos JC, Barr PM, Flinn I, Burger JA, Salman Z, Clow F et al. Ibrutinib in combination with bendamustine and rituximab is active and tolerable in patients with relapsed/refractory CLL/SLL: final results of a phase 1b study. Blood 2013; 122: 525.[Abstract].</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Beum PV, Lindorfer MA, Beurskens F, Stukenberg PT, Lokhorst HM, Pawluczkowycz AW, Parren PW, van de Winkel JG, Taylor RP. Complement activation on B lymphocytes opsonized with rituximab or ofatumumab produces substantial changes in membrane structure preceding cell lysis. J Immunol. 2008 Jul 1;181(1):822-32.</citation>
    <PMID>18566448</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bishop GA, Haxhinasto SA, Stunz LL, Hostager BS. Antigen-specific B-lymphocyte activation. Crit Rev Immunol. 2003;23(3):149-97. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>14584878</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bleeker WK, Munk ME, Mackus WJ, van den Brakel JH, Pluyter M, Glennie MJ, van de Winkel JG, Parren PW. Estimation of dose requirements for sustained in vivo activity of a therapeutic human anti-CD20 antibody. Br J Haematol. 2008 Feb;140(3):303-12. Epub 2007 Nov 27.</citation>
    <PMID>18045353</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bojarczuk K, Siernicka M, Dwojak M, Bobrowicz M, Pyrzynska B, Gaj P, Karp M, Giannopoulos K, Efremov DG, Fauriat C, Golab J, Winiarska M. B-cell receptor pathway inhibitors affect CD20 levels and impair antitumor activity of anti-CD20 monoclonal antibodies. Leukemia. 2014 May;28(5):1163-7. doi: 10.1038/leu.2014.12. Epub 2014 Jan 10.</citation>
    <PMID>24492323</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bosch F, Abrisqueta P, Villamor N, Terol MJ, González-Barca E, Ferra C, González Diaz M, Abella E, Delgado J, Carbonell F, García Marco JA, Escoda L, Ferrer S, Monzó E, González Y, Estany C, Jarque I, Salamero O, Muntañola A, Montserrat E. Rituximab, fludarabine, cyclophosphamide, and mitoxantrone: a new, highly active chemoimmunotherapy regimen for chronic lymphocytic leukemia. J Clin Oncol. 2009 Sep 20;27(27):4578-84. doi: 10.1200/JCO.2009.22.0442. Epub 2009 Aug 24.</citation>
    <PMID>19704063</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Brenner H, Gondos A, Pulte D. Trends in long-term survival of patients with chronic lymphocytic leukemia from the 1980s to the early 21st century. Blood. 2008 May 15;111(10):4916-21. doi: 10.1182/blood-2007-12-129379. Epub 2008 Feb 28.</citation>
    <PMID>18309034</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Burger JA. Nurture versus nature: the microenvironment in chronic lymphocytic leukemia. Hematology Am Soc Hematol Educ Program. 2011;2011:96-103. doi: 10.1182/asheducation-2011.1.96. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22160019</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Burger JA, Keating MJ, Wierda WG, Hartmann E, Hoellenriegel J, Rosin NY, de Weerdt I, Jeyakumar G, Ferrajoli A, Cardenas-Turanzas M, Lerner S, Jorgensen JL, Nogueras-González GM, Zacharian G, Huang X, Kantarjian H, Garg N, Rosenwald A, O'Brien S. Safety and activity of ibrutinib plus rituximab for patients with high-risk chronic lymphocytic leukaemia: a single-arm, phase 2 study. Lancet Oncol. 2014 Sep;15(10):1090-9. doi: 10.1016/S1470-2045(14)70335-3. Epub 2014 Aug 20.</citation>
    <PMID>25150798</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Burger JA, Tedeschi A, Barr PM, Robak T, Owen C, Ghia P, Bairey O, Hillmen P, Bartlett NL, Li J, Simpson D, Grosicki S, Devereux S, McCarthy H, Coutre S, Quach H, Gaidano G, Maslyak Z, Stevens DA, Janssens A, Offner F, Mayer J, O'Dwyer M, Hellmann A, Schuh A, Siddiqi T, Polliack A, Tam CS, Suri D, Cheng M, Clow F, Styles L, James DF, Kipps TJ; RESONATE-2 Investigators. Ibrutinib as Initial Therapy for Patients with Chronic Lymphocytic Leukemia. N Engl J Med. 2015 Dec 17;373(25):2425-37. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa1509388. Epub 2015 Dec 6.</citation>
    <PMID>26639149</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Byrd JC, Furman RR, Coutre SE, Flinn IW, Burger JA, Blum KA, Grant B, Sharman JP, Coleman M, Wierda WG, Jones JA, Zhao W, Heerema NA, Johnson AJ, Sukbuntherng J, Chang BY, Clow F, Hedrick E, Buggy JJ, James DF, O'Brien S. Targeting BTK with ibrutinib in relapsed chronic lymphocytic leukemia. N Engl J Med. 2013 Jul 4;369(1):32-42. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa1215637. Epub 2013 Jun 19. Erratum in: N Engl J Med. 2014 Feb 20;370(8):786.</citation>
    <PMID>23782158</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Byrd JC, Brown JR, O'Brien S, Barrientos JC, Kay NE, Reddy NM, Coutre S, Tam CS, Mulligan SP, Jaeger U, Devereux S, Barr PM, Furman RR, Kipps TJ, Cymbalista F, Pocock C, Thornton P, Caligaris-Cappio F, Robak T, Delgado J, Schuster SJ, Montillo M, Schuh A, de Vos S, Gill D, Bloor A, Dearden C, Moreno C, Jones JJ, Chu AD, Fardis M, McGreivy J, Clow F, James DF, Hillmen P; RESONATE Investigators. Ibrutinib versus ofatumumab in previously treated chronic lymphoid leukemia. N Engl J Med. 2014 Jul 17;371(3):213-23. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa1400376. Epub 2014 May 31.</citation>
    <PMID>24881631</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Byrd JC, Harrington B, O'Brien S, Jones JA, Schuh A, Devereux S, Chaves J, Wierda WG, Awan FT, Brown JR, Hillmen P, Stephens DM, Ghia P, Barrientos JC, Pagel JM, Woyach J, Johnson D, Huang J, Wang X, Kaptein A, Lannutti BJ, Covey T, Fardis M, McGreivy J, Hamdy A, Rothbaum W, Izumi R, Diacovo TG, Johnson AJ, Furman RR. Acalabrutinib (ACP-196) in Relapsed Chronic Lymphocytic Leukemia. N Engl J Med. 2016 Jan 28;374(4):323-32. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa1509981. Epub 2015 Dec 7.</citation>
    <PMID>26641137</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Campo E, Swerdlow SH, Harris NL, Pileri S, Stein H, Jaffe ES. The 2008 WHO classification of lymphoid neoplasms and beyond: evolving concepts and practical applications. Blood. 2011 May 12;117(19):5019-32. doi: 10.1182/blood-2011-01-293050. Epub 2011 Feb 7. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21300984</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cheson BD, Byrd JC, Rai KR, Kay NE, O'Brien SM, Flinn IW, Wiestner A, Kipps TJ. Novel targeted agents and the need to refine clinical end points in chronic lymphocytic leukemia. J Clin Oncol. 2012 Aug 10;30(23):2820-2. doi: 10.1200/JCO.2012.43.3748. Epub 2012 Jul 9.</citation>
    <PMID>22778323</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chiorazzi N, Rai KR, Ferrarini M. Chronic lymphocytic leukemia. N Engl J Med. 2005 Feb 24;352(8):804-15. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>15728813</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Coiffier B, Lepretre S, Pedersen LM, Gadeberg O, Fredriksen H, van Oers MH, Wooldridge J, Kloczko J, Holowiecki J, Hellmann A, Walewski J, Flensburg M, Petersen J, Robak T. Safety and efficacy of ofatumumab, a fully human monoclonal anti-CD20 antibody, in patients with relapsed or refractory B-cell chronic lymphocytic leukemia: a phase 1-2 study. Blood. 2008 Feb 1;111(3):1094-100. Epub 2007 Nov 14.</citation>
    <PMID>18003886</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Craxton A, Jiang A, Kurosaki T, Clark EA. Syk and Bruton's tyrosine kinase are required for B cell antigen receptor-mediated activation of the kinase Akt. J Biol Chem. 1999 Oct 22;274(43):30644-50.</citation>
    <PMID>10521450</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Da Roit F, Engelberts PJ, Taylor RP, Breij EC, Gritti G, Rambaldi A, Introna M, Parren PW, Beurskens FJ, Golay J. Ibrutinib interferes with the cell-mediated anti-tumor activities of therapeutic CD20 antibodies: implications for combination therapy. Haematologica. 2015 Jan;100(1):77-86. doi: 10.3324/haematol.2014.107011. Epub 2014 Oct 24.</citation>
    <PMID>25344523</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dighiero G, Maloum K, Desablens B, Cazin B, Navarro M, Leblay R, Leporrier M, Jaubert J, Lepeu G, Dreyfus B, Binet JL, Travade P. Chlorambucil in indolent chronic lymphocytic leukemia. French Cooperative Group on Chronic Lymphocytic Leukemia. N Engl J Med. 1998 May 21;338(21):1506-14.</citation>
    <PMID>9593789</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Eichhorst BF, Busch R, Hopfinger G, Pasold R, Hensel M, Steinbrecher C, Siehl S, Jäger U, Bergmann M, Stilgenbauer S, Schweighofer C, Wendtner CM, Döhner H, Brittinger G, Emmerich B, Hallek M; German CLL Study Group. Fludarabine plus cyclophosphamide versus fludarabine alone in first-line therapy of younger patients with chronic lymphocytic leukemia. Blood. 2006 Feb 1;107(3):885-91. Epub 2005 Oct 11.</citation>
    <PMID>16219797</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Flinn IW, Neuberg DS, Grever MR, Dewald GW, Bennett JM, Paietta EM, Hussein MA, Appelbaum FR, Larson RA, Moore DF Jr, Tallman MS. Phase III trial of fludarabine plus cyclophosphamide compared with fludarabine for patients with previously untreated chronic lymphocytic leukemia: US Intergroup Trial E2997. J Clin Oncol. 2007 Mar 1;25(7):793-8. Epub 2007 Feb 5.</citation>
    <PMID>17283364</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Flinn IW, Byrd JC, Morrison C, Jamison J, Diehl LF, Murphy T, Piantadosi S, Seifter E, Ambinder RF, Vogelsang G, Grever MR. Fludarabine and cyclophosphamide with filgrastim support in patients with previously untreated indolent lymphoid malignancies. Blood. 2000 Jul 1;96(1):71-5.</citation>
    <PMID>10891432</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gribben JG, O'Brien S. Update on therapy of chronic lymphocytic leukemia. J Clin Oncol. 2011 Feb 10;29(5):544-50. doi: 10.1200/JCO.2010.32.3865. Epub 2011 Jan 10. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21220603</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gururajan M, Jennings CD, Bondada S. Cutting edge: constitutive B cell receptor signaling is critical for basal growth of B lymphoma. J Immunol. 2006 May 15;176(10):5715-9. Erratum in: J Immunol. 2006 Jun 15;176(12):7789.</citation>
    <PMID>16670274</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hagenbeek A, Gadeberg O, Johnson P, Pedersen LM, Walewski J, Hellmann A, Link BK, Robak T, Wojtukiewicz M, Pfreundschuh M, Kneba M, Engert A, Sonneveld P, Flensburg M, Petersen J, Losic N, Radford J. First clinical use of ofatumumab, a novel fully human anti-CD20 monoclonal antibody in relapsed or refractory follicular lymphoma: results of a phase 1/2 trial. Blood. 2008 Jun 15;111(12):5486-95. doi: 10.1182/blood-2007-10-117671. Epub 2008 Apr 4.</citation>
    <PMID>18390837</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hallek M, Cheson BD, Catovsky D, Caligaris-Cappio F, Dighiero G, Döhner H, Hillmen P, Keating M, Montserrat E, Chiorazzi N, Stilgenbauer S, Rai KR, Byrd JC, Eichhorst B, O'Brien S, Robak T, Seymour JF, Kipps TJ. iwCLL guidelines for diagnosis, indications for treatment, response assessment, and supportive management of CLL. Blood. 2018 Jun 21;131(25):2745-2760. doi: 10.1182/blood-2017-09-806398. Epub 2018 Mar 14.</citation>
    <PMID>29540348</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hallek M, Fischer K, Fingerle-Rowson G, Fink AM, Busch R, Mayer J, Hensel M, Hopfinger G, Hess G, von Grünhagen U, Bergmann M, Catalano J, Zinzani PL, Caligaris-Cappio F, Seymour JF, Berrebi A, Jäger U, Cazin B, Trneny M, Westermann A, Wendtner CM, Eichhorst BF, Staib P, Bühler A, Winkler D, Zenz T, Böttcher S, Ritgen M, Mendila M, Kneba M, Döhner H, Stilgenbauer S; International Group of Investigators; German Chronic Lymphocytic Leukaemia Study Group. Addition of rituximab to fludarabine and cyclophosphamide in patients with chronic lymphocytic leukaemia: a randomised, open-label, phase 3 trial. Lancet. 2010 Oct 2;376(9747):1164-74. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(10)61381-5.</citation>
    <PMID>20888994</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Herman SE, Gordon AL, Hertlein E, Ramanunni A, Zhang X, Jaglowski S, Flynn J, Jones J, Blum KA, Buggy JJ, Hamdy A, Johnson AJ, Byrd JC. Bruton tyrosine kinase represents a promising therapeutic target for treatment of chronic lymphocytic leukemia and is effectively targeted by PCI-32765. Blood. 2011 Jun 9;117(23):6287-96. doi: 10.1182/blood-2011-01-328484. Epub 2011 Mar 21.</citation>
    <PMID>21422473</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hoechstetter MA, Busch R, Eichhorst B, Bühler A, Winkler D, Eckart MJ, Vehling-Kaiser U, Schimke H, Jäger U, Hurtz HJ, Hopfinger G, Hartmann F, Fuss H, Abenhardt W, Blau I, Freier W, Müller L, Goebeler M, Wendtner CM, Bahlo J, Fischer K, Bentz M, Emmerich B, Döhner H, Hallek M, Stilgenbauer S. Early, risk-adapted treatment with fludarabine in Binet stage A chronic lymphocytic leukemia patients: results of the CLL1 trial of the German CLL study group. Leukemia. 2017 Dec;31(12):2833-2837. doi: 10.1038/leu.2017.246. Epub 2017 Aug 14.</citation>
    <PMID>28804126</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Honigberg LA, Smith AM, Sirisawad M, Verner E, Loury D, Chang B, Li S, Pan Z, Thamm DH, Miller RA, Buggy JJ. The Bruton tyrosine kinase inhibitor PCI-32765 blocks B-cell activation and is efficacious in models of autoimmune disease and B-cell malignancy. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2010 Jul 20;107(29):13075-80. doi: 10.1073/pnas.1004594107. Epub 2010 Jul 6.</citation>
    <PMID>20615965</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kohrt HE, Sagiv-Barfi I, Rafiq S, Herman SE, Butchar JP, Cheney C, Zhang X, Buggy JJ, Muthusamy N, Levy R, Johnson AJ, Byrd JC. Ibrutinib antagonizes rituximab-dependent NK cell-mediated cytotoxicity. Blood. 2014 Mar 20;123(12):1957-60. doi: 10.1182/blood-2014-01-547869.</citation>
    <PMID>24652965</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Küppers R. Mechanisms of B-cell lymphoma pathogenesis. Nat Rev Cancer. 2005 Apr;5(4):251-62. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>15803153</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Langerbeins P, Bahlo J, Rhein C, Cramer P, Pflug N, Fischer K, Stilgenbauer S, Kreuzer KA, Wendtner CM, Eichhorst B, Hallek M. The CLL12 trial protocol: a placebo-controlled double-blind Phase III study of ibrutinib in the treatment of early-stage chronic lymphocytic leukemia patients with risk of early disease progression. Future Oncol. 2015;11(13):1895-903. doi: 10.2217/fon.15.95.</citation>
    <PMID>26161926</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Meeker T, Lowder J, Cleary ML, Stewart S, Warnke R, Sklar J, Levy R. Emergence of idiotype variants during treatment of B-cell lymphoma with anti-idiotype antibodies. N Engl J Med. 1985 Jun 27;312(26):1658-65.</citation>
    <PMID>3923352</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Miller MD, Paradis CF, Houck PR, Mazumdar S, Stack JA, Rifai AH, Mulsant B, Reynolds CF 3rd. Rating chronic medical illness burden in geropsychiatric practice and research: application of the Cumulative Illness Rating Scale. Psychiatry Res. 1992 Mar;41(3):237-48.</citation>
    <PMID>1594710</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>National Comprehensive Cancer Network (NCCN). NCCN Clinical Practice Guidelines in Oncology (NCCN Guidelines) Non-Hodgkin's Lymphomas. Version I.2012. NCCN.org</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>O'Brien SM, Kantarjian HM, Cortes J, Beran M, Koller CA, Giles FJ, Lerner S, Keating M. Results of the fludarabine and cyclophosphamide combination regimen in chronic lymphocytic leukemia. J Clin Oncol. 2001 Mar 1;19(5):1414-20.</citation>
    <PMID>11230486</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>O'Brien S, Furman RR, Coutre SE, Sharman JP, Burger JA, Blum KA, Grant B, Richards DA, Coleman M, Wierda WG, Jones JA, Zhao W, Heerema NA, Johnson AJ, Izumi R, Hamdy A, Chang BY, Graef T, Clow F, Buggy JJ, James DF, Byrd JC. Ibrutinib as initial therapy for elderly patients with chronic lymphocytic leukaemia or small lymphocytic lymphoma: an open-label, multicentre, phase 1b/2 trial. Lancet Oncol. 2014 Jan;15(1):48-58. doi: 10.1016/S1470-2045(13)70513-8. Epub 2013 Dec 10.</citation>
    <PMID>24332241</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pawluczkowycz AW, Beurskens FJ, Beum PV, Lindorfer MA, van de Winkel JG, Parren PW, Taylor RP. Binding of submaximal C1q promotes complement-dependent cytotoxicity (CDC) of B cells opsonized with anti-CD20 mAbs ofatumumab (OFA) or rituximab (RTX): considerably higher levels of CDC are induced by OFA than by RTX. J Immunol. 2009 Jul 1;183(1):749-58. doi: 10.4049/jimmunol.0900632. Epub 2009 Jun 17.</citation>
    <PMID>19535640</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Petro JB, Rahman SM, Ballard DW, Khan WN. Bruton's tyrosine kinase is required for activation of IkappaB kinase and nuclear factor kappaB in response to B cell receptor engagement. J Exp Med. 2000 May 15;191(10):1745-54.</citation>
    <PMID>10811867</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Petro JB, Khan WN. Phospholipase C-gamma 2 couples Bruton's tyrosine kinase to the NF-kappaB signaling pathway in B lymphocytes. J Biol Chem. 2001 Jan 19;276(3):1715-9. Epub 2000 Oct 19.</citation>
    <PMID>11042193</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pflug N, Bahlo J, Shanafelt TD, Eichhorst BF, Bergmann MA, Elter T, Bauer K, Malchau G, Rabe KG, Stilgenbauer S, Döhner H, Jäger U, Eckart MJ, Hopfinger G, Busch R, Fink AM, Wendtner CM, Fischer K, Kay NE, Hallek M. Development of a comprehensive prognostic index for patients with chronic lymphocytic leukemia. Blood. 2014 Jul 3;124(1):49-62. doi: 10.1182/blood-2014-02-556399. Epub 2014 May 5.</citation>
    <PMID>24797299</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ponader S, Chen SS, Buggy JJ, Balakrishnan K, Gandhi V, Wierda WG, Keating MJ, O'Brien S, Chiorazzi N, Burger JA. The Bruton tyrosine kinase inhibitor PCI-32765 thwarts chronic lymphocytic leukemia cell survival and tissue homing in vitro and in vivo. Blood. 2012 Feb 2;119(5):1182-9. doi: 10.1182/blood-2011-10-386417. Epub 2011 Dec 16.</citation>
    <PMID>22180443</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Satterthwaite AB, Witte ON. The role of Bruton's tyrosine kinase in B-cell development and function: a genetic perspective. Immunol Rev. 2000 Jun;175:120-7. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>10933597</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shaffer AL, Rosenwald A, Staudt LM. Lymphoid malignancies: the dark side of B-cell differentiation. Nat Rev Immunol. 2002 Dec;2(12):920-32. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>12461565</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Smith TJ, Khatcheressian J, Lyman GH, Ozer H, Armitage JO, Balducci L, Bennett CL, Cantor SB, Crawford J, Cross SJ, Demetri G, Desch CE, Pizzo PA, Schiffer CA, Schwartzberg L, Somerfield MR, Somlo G, Wade JC, Wade JL, Winn RJ, Wozniak AJ, Wolff AC. 2006 update of recommendations for the use of white blood cell growth factors: an evidence-based clinical practice guideline. J Clin Oncol. 2006 Jul 1;24(19):3187-205. Epub 2006 May 8.</citation>
    <PMID>16682719</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Spaargaren M, Beuling EA, Rurup ML, Meijer HP, Klok MD, Middendorp S, Hendriks RW, Pals ST. The B cell antigen receptor controls integrin activity through Btk and PLCgamma2. J Exp Med. 2003 Nov 17;198(10):1539-50. Epub 2003 Nov 10.</citation>
    <PMID>14610042</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Surveillance Epidemiology and End Results (SEER), NCI, US National Institutes of Health, Fast Stats; Statistics Stratified by Cancer Site, 2010.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tam CS, O'Brien S, Wierda W, Kantarjian H, Wen S, Do KA, Thomas DA, Cortes J, Lerner S, Keating MJ. Long-term results of the fludarabine, cyclophosphamide, and rituximab regimen as initial therapy of chronic lymphocytic leukemia. Blood. 2008 Aug 15;112(4):975-80. doi: 10.1182/blood-2008-02-140582. Epub 2008 Apr 14.</citation>
    <PMID>18411418</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Teeling JL, French RR, Cragg MS, van den Brakel J, Pluyter M, Huang H, Chan C, Parren PW, Hack CE, Dechant M, Valerius T, van de Winkel JG, Glennie MJ. Characterization of new human CD20 monoclonal antibodies with potent cytolytic activity against non-Hodgkin lymphomas. Blood. 2004 Sep 15;104(6):1793-800. Epub 2004 Jun 1.</citation>
    <PMID>15172969</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Teeling JL, Mackus WJ, Wiegman LJ, van den Brakel JH, Beers SA, French RR, van Meerten T, Ebeling S, Vink T, Slootstra JW, Parren PW, Glennie MJ, van de Winkel JG. The biological activity of human CD20 monoclonal antibodies is linked to unique epitopes on CD20. J Immunol. 2006 Jul 1;177(1):362-71.</citation>
    <PMID>16785532</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tomlinson MG, Woods DB, McMahon M, Wahl MI, Witte ON, Kurosaki T, Bolen JB, Johnston JA. A conditional form of Bruton's tyrosine kinase is sufficient to activate multiple downstream signaling pathways via PLC Gamma 2 in B cells. BMC Immunol. 2001;2:4. Epub 2001 Jun 8.</citation>
    <PMID>11410123</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Welch HG, Albertsen PC, Nease RF, Bubolz TA, Wasson JH. Estimating treatment benefits for the elderly: the effect of competing risks. Ann Intern Med. 1996 Mar 15;124(6):577-84.</citation>
    <PMID>8597322</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wierda WG, Kipps TJ, Mayer J, Stilgenbauer S, Williams CD, Hellmann A, Robak T, Furman RR, Hillmen P, Trneny M, Dyer MJ, Padmanabhan S, Piotrowska M, Kozak T, Chan G, Davis R, Losic N, Wilms J, Russell CA, Osterborg A; Hx-CD20-406 Study Investigators. Ofatumumab as single-agent CD20 immunotherapy in fludarabine-refractory chronic lymphocytic leukemia. J Clin Oncol. 2010 Apr 1;28(10):1749-55. doi: 10.1200/JCO.2009.25.3187. Epub 2010 Mar 1. Erratum in: J Clin Oncol. 2010 Aug 1;28(22):3670.</citation>
    <PMID>20194866</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wierda WG, Kipps TJ, Dürig J, Griskevicius L, Stilgenbauer S, Mayer J, Smolej L, Hess G, Griniute R, Hernandez-Ilizaliturri FJ, Padmanabhan S, Gorczyca M, Chang CN, Chan G, Gupta I, Nielsen TG, Russell CA; 407 Study Investigators. Chemoimmunotherapy with O-FC in previously untreated patients with chronic lymphocytic leukemia. Blood. 2011 Jun 16;117(24):6450-8. doi: 10.1182/blood-2010-12-323980. Epub 2011 Apr 15.</citation>
    <PMID>21498674</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 8, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 25, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">November 26, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 10, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 10, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 11, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>CLL</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Leukemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Lymphoid</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Lymphocytic, Chronic, B-Cell</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

