<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04176341</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>38RC19.143</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04176341</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Feasability and Clinical Impact Study of Non Pharmacological Interventions in Management of Chronic Pain</brief_title>
  <acronym>ELISAD</acronym>
  <official_title>Feasibility and Clinical Impact Study of Non Pharmacological Interventions Targeting the Subject's Empowerment Among Slackline, Mindfulness, Adapted Physical Activity, Self-hypnosis, Qi Gong Versus Usual Care in Management of Chronic Pain</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University Hospital, Grenoble</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Hospices Civils de Lyon</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Groupe Hospitalier Mutualiste de Grenoble</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University Hospital, Grenoble</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This feasability study aims to compare the 6-month success rate of a systematic proposal for
      non pharmacological interventions targeting the subject's empowerment among slackline,
      mindfulness, adapted physical activity, self-hypnosis, and Qi Gong versus usual care in the
      management of chronic pain.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Chronic pain management is complex. 27.2 to 43.5 % of general population suffers from it.
      Opoid crisis has shown the limit of the WHO 3 step analgesic ladder. Multidisciplinary pain
      management programs, shared decision making and non pharmacological interventions targeting
      subject's empowerment are needed. Among these non pharmacological interventions, patients are
      increasingly turning to traditional and complementary medicines. Evidence about their safety
      and efficacy is hard to build. Thus our study aims to assess the feasibility of a systematic
      proposal for non pharmacological interventions targeting the subject's empowerment.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">December 18, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 15, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 15, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Intervention group : chronic pain patient consulting in Grenoble Alps University Hospital and Grenoble Hospital Mutualist Group who will one non pharmacological intervention between slackline, mindfulness, adapted physical activity, self-hypnosis, Qi Gong during 6 to 8 weeks.
Control group : chronic pain patient consulting in Lyon University Hospital who will receive usual care.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Compare the 6-month success rate of a systematic proposal for non pharmacological interventions targeting the subject's empowerment versus usual care in the management of chronic pain</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>The success of the intervention will be defined as a reduction of 30% or more of the average daily Visual Analog Score [0-10] for pain collected the 7 days prior to the M6 visit, compared to baseline status before intervention.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Compare the effectiveness of the intervention versus usual care between M6-M3-M0</measure>
    <time_frame>3 and 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Average daily pain visual analogue scale collected the 7 days prior to the visit of M0, M3 and M6.
We will perform a subgroup analysis per workshop if n ≥ 25 in this one.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Describe adherence of the intervention</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Number of participated workshops by patients</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Describe side effects of the intervention</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Report eventuels side effects occuring during interventions</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Compare changes in quality of life at 3 and 6 months compared to baseline.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 and 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Evolution of the generic quality of life measured by the EQ5D-3L questionnaire at 3 and 6 months compared to baseline</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluate the evolution of the overall motivation of the subjects of the Intervention group at different times of the study: before, during, just after the intervention, and at 3 and 6 months.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 and 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluate the evolution of the overall motivation (EMG-28 scale) at 3 and 6 months compared to baseline for the subjects of the Intervention group.
To evaluate the motivation of the subjects of the intervention group with Likert scales (importance / confidence / disposition) before, during, just after the intervention, and at 3 and 6 months.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluate the evolution of the detailed motivation of the subjects of the Intervention group at different times of the study: before, during, just after the intervention, and at 3 and 6 months.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 and 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluate motivation of the subjects of the intervention group with Likert scales (importance / confidence / disposition) before, during, just after the intervention, and at 3 and 6 months.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Compare the evolution of the health care consumption of the subjects at 3 and 6 months compared to baseline.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 and 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Count drug consumption, herbal medicine, homeopathy, food supplements, use of care (medical consultations, hospitalization, use of complementary medicines (acupuncture, osteopathy, micro physiotherapy, chiropractic ...), professional absenteeis that occurs to patient during the study.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluate the success of the intervention (intervention group) or the conventional follow-up (control group) from the patient's point of view at 3 and 6 months compared to baseline.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 and 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Binary success / failure criterion chosen by the patient during the inclusion visit among 5 criteria previously defined by a focus group of chronic pain patients upstream of the study, at 3 and 6 months compared to baseline.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Sub-group analysis for healthcare professionals : compare the 6-month success rate of a systematic proposal for non pharmacological interventions targeting the subject's empowerment versus usual care in the management of chronic pain</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Sub-group analysis for healthcare professionals of the success of the intervention defined as a reduction of 30% or more of the average daily Visual Analog Score [0-10] for pain collected the 7 days prior to the M6 visit, compared to baseline status before intervention.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Compare the evolution of the ability to cope with subjects at 3 and 6 months compared to baseline.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 and 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Evolution of the Ways of Coping Checklist on the patient's ability to cope at 3 and 6 months compared to baseline</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Compare the evolution of the catastrophism of the subjects at 3 and 6 months compared to baseline.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 and 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Evolution of the PCS-CF Pain Catastrophism Scale [0-52] at 3 and 6 Months compared to baseline</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">155</enrollment>
  <condition>Chronic Pain</condition>
  <condition>Slackline</condition>
  <condition>Mindfulness</condition>
  <condition>Adapted Physical Activity</condition>
  <condition>Self-hypnosis</condition>
  <condition>Qi Gong</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>chronic pain patient consulting in Grenoble Alps University Hospital, and Hospital Mutualist Group who will one non pharmacological intervention between slackline, mindfulness, adapted physical activity, self-hypnosis, Qi Gong during 6 to 8 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>chronic pain patient consulting in Lyon University Hospital who will receive usual care.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>a systematic proposal for non pharmacological interventions targeting the subject's empowerment among slackline, mindfulness, adapted physical activity, self-hypnosis, and Qi Gong</intervention_name>
    <description>chronic pain patient consulting in Grenoble Alps University Hospital, and Hospital Mutualist Group who will one non pharmacological intervention between slackline, mindfulness, adapted physical activity, self-hypnosis, Qi Gong during 6 to 8 weeks.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention group</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>non pharmacological interventions</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patient with stable chronic pain defined by the presence of pain for more than 3
             months and without substantial change in management in the month prior to inclusion

          -  Patient with a mean EVA maximum daily pain over 7 days greater than or equal to 4/10

          -  Patient aged 18 and over

          -  Informed and written consent signed by the patient (or his / her legal
             representative).

          -  Person affiliated with social security or beneficiary of such a scheme

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patient with a cluster headache

          -  Patient followed for 7 years or more by a pain center

          -  Patient treated with adjuvant or neo-adjuvant chemotherapy or radiotherapy for the
             primary tumor

          -  Patient with a decompensated psychiatric condition

          -  Patient currently participating or having participated in the month prior to inclusion
             in another interventional clinical research that may impact the study; this impact is
             left to the investigator's discretion

          -  Protected persons
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Caroline Maindet, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University Hospital, Grenoble</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Caroline Maindet, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+33476765213</phone>
    <email>Cmaindetdominici@chu-grenoble.fr</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Gilliane Lalami</last_name>
    <phone>+33476766729</phone>
    <email>GLalami@chu-grenoble.fr</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CHU de GRENOBLE ALPES</name>
      <address>
        <city>Grenoble</city>
        <zip>38000</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shipton EA, Shipton EE, Shipton AJ. A Review of the Opioid Epidemic: What Do We Do About It? Pain Ther. 2018 Jun;7(1):23-36. doi: 10.1007/s40122-018-0096-7. Epub 2018 Apr 6. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>29623667</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Skelly AC, Chou R, Dettori JR, Turner JA, Friedly JL, Rundell SD, Fu R, Brodt ED, Wasson N, Winter C, Ferguson AJR. Noninvasive Nonpharmacological Treatment for Chronic Pain: A Systematic Review [Internet]. Rockville (MD): Agency for Healthcare Research and Quality (US); 2018 Jun. Available from http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK519953/</citation>
    <PMID>30179389</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Devan H, Hale L, Hempel D, Saipe B, Perry MA. What Works and Does Not Work in a Self-Management Intervention for People With Chronic Pain? Qualitative Systematic Review and Meta-Synthesis. Phys Ther. 2018 May 1;98(5):381-397. doi: 10.1093/ptj/pzy029.</citation>
    <PMID>29669089</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dworkin RH, Turk DC, McDermott MP, Peirce-Sandner S, Burke LB, Cowan P, Farrar JT, Hertz S, Raja SN, Rappaport BA, Rauschkolb C, Sampaio C. Interpreting the clinical importance of group differences in chronic pain clinical trials: IMMPACT recommendations. Pain. 2009 Dec;146(3):238-44. doi: 10.1016/j.pain.2009.08.019. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19836888</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Olsen MF, Bjerre E, Hansen MD, Tendal B, Hilden J, Hróbjartsson A. Minimum clinically important differences in chronic pain vary considerably by baseline pain and methodological factors: systematic review of empirical studies. J Clin Epidemiol. 2018 Sep;101:87-106.e2. doi: 10.1016/j.jclinepi.2018.05.007. Epub 2018 May 21. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>29793007</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 15, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 21, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">November 25, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 19, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 19, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 20, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>non pharmacological interventions</keyword>
  <keyword>chronic pain</keyword>
  <keyword>slackline</keyword>
  <keyword>mindfulness</keyword>
  <keyword>adapted physical activity</keyword>
  <keyword>self-hypnosis</keyword>
  <keyword>Qi Gong</keyword>
  <keyword>shared decision making</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Chronic Pain</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

