<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04171050</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Pudendal Enhancement of ERAS</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04171050</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Pudendal Enhancement of Enhanced Recovery After Surgery (ERAS) for Reconstructive Surgery (PEERS)</brief_title>
  <official_title>Pudendal Enhancement of Enhanced Recovery After Surgery (ERAS) for Reconstructive Surgery (PEERS)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of California, Los Angeles</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of California, Los Angeles</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Patients will undergo their vaginal reconstructive surgery in the usual manner, but will also
      be randomly assigned on the day of surgery to either receive the extra injection of numbing
      medication at the onset of surgery or not. The chances they will be assigned to the
      additional injection is 50%. Their care in the hospital and after surgery will be the same.
      They will participate in the study for a total of 6 weeks during which time they will be
      asked to complete two phone surveys, during which a provider will check in on pain level and
      pain medication use, and one office visit at 6 weeks. The office visit is part of their
      routine care and would be a scheduled visit regardless if they participated in the study or
      not. If they are unable to return to the office for a postoperative visit at 6 weeks, they
      will be contact by phone instead to obtain information on satisfaction with postoperative
      care, any complications after surgery, and overall how they are doing after surgery.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PROTOCOL SUMMARY AND/OR SCHEMA

      To determine whether administration of a PNB at time of vaginal reconstructive surgery can
      reduce use of narcotics and reported pain scores in the immediate postoperative period within
      the setting of multimodal postoperative pain control of ERAS. Women &gt;18yo undergoing vaginal
      reconstructive surgery without a hysterectomy will be randomized to either standard of care
      with typical use of local anesthetic during their surgery versus perioperative PNB in
      addition to typical use of local anesthetic during their surgery. PNB will be performed with
      0.5% bupivacaine and 10cc will be injected bilaterally. All patients will be on a standard
      preoperative and postoperative multimodal pain regimen. Patients will be followed until 6
      weeks after surgery.

      OVERVIEW OF STUDY DESIGN/INTERVENTION

      This will be a prospective blinded randomized controlled trial. We will recruit women who are
      undergoing vaginal prolapse repair surgery with a Female Pelvic Medicine and Reconstructive
      Surgery fellowship-trained provider within the UCLA Health System. Women will be recruited
      prior to undergoing vaginal reconstructive surgery. They will then be randomized to control
      group with standard of care with local anesthesia used during surgery (Group 1) or PNB in
      addition to use of local anesthesia typically used during surgery (Group 2).

      All pain medication will be standardized. Preoperative medications per our ERAS protocol will
      include oral acetaminophen 1000mg, gabapentin 600mg, and celecoxib 400mg. During surgery the
      patient will undergo their randomized intervention as either Group 1 or Group 2.
      Postoperative medications per our ERAS protocol including scheduled acetaminophen 1,000mg PO
      every 6 hours and ketorolac 30mg IV every 6 hours. For supplemental pain medication patients
      will have the following available: tramadol 50mg PO every 6 hours as needed for moderate pain
      (pain 4-6/10 on NRS scale), tramadol 100mg PO every 6 hours as needed for severe pain (pain
      7-10/10 on NRS scale), and oxycodone 5mg PO every 4 hours as needed for breakthrough pain as
      supplemental pain medication. If the above regimen does not allow for sufficient pain control
      then additional hydromorphone IV 0.2mg or morphine IV 2mg can be ordered by the provider as
      needed, but will not be standard in the postoperative order set. The providers will know what
      intervention the patients underwent, but the patients and the care team obtaining pain scores
      in the hospital will be blinded to the intervention.

      The patients' pain scores on the numeric rating scale (NRS) and supplemental opioid use
      measured in morphine milligram equivalent (MME) will be tracked during their hospitalization,
      which is typically a 23-hour observation. They will then be called at 48 hours for further
      follow-up on pain score by NRS and asked how much opioid medication they have taken since
      leaving the hospital and their overall satisfaction with their pain control. To help with the
      determination of supplemental pain medication used and pain scores, the patients will be
      provided a worksheet upon discharge that outlines their recommended medication routine,
      allows them to record their supplemental opioid medication use with dose and time, and also
      provides space for them to record their pain score at 48 hours post operatively. The patient
      will then be contacted at 2 weeks after surgery to determine if they have returned to normal
      activities (walking, sitting, and performing daily household tasks comfortably) and if so at
      what point this occurred, as well as their overall satisfaction with their postoperative pain
      control again. The two week contact will be either a phone call or clinic visit depending on
      the provider's preference for patient follow-up. The last point of contact will be at 6 weeks
      to determine time to return to normal activities, if they had not met this milestone at the
      2-week contact, and again assess their overall satisfaction with their postoperative pain
      control. If a patient is discharge same day instead of admitted for 23-hour observation they
      will also receive a call at 24 hours postoperative to check on pain score and supplemental
      pain medication used.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 14, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 1, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 1, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>This will be a prospective blinded randomized controlled trial. We will recruit women who are undergoing vaginal prolapse repair surgery with a Female Pelvic Medicine and Reconstructive Surgery fellowship-trained provider within the University of California, Los Angeles (UCLA) Health System.
Women will be recruited prior to undergoing vaginal reconstructive surgery. They will then be randomized to control group with standard of care with local anesthesia used during surgery (Group 1) or PNB in addition to use of local anesthesia typically used during surgery (Group 2).</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Care Provider)</masking>
    <masking_description>The providers will know what intervention the patients underwent, but the patients and the care team obtaining pain scores in the hospital will be blinded to the intervention</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Narcotic use</measure>
    <time_frame>24 hours after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Measured in MME at 24 hours</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Narcotic use</measure>
    <time_frame>48 hours after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Measured in MME at 48 hours</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pain scores</measure>
    <time_frame>0-2 hours, 2-4 hours, 4-8 hours, 8-12 hours, 12-24 hours, and 48 hours after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Average pain score by Numerical Rating Scale (NRS). The scale is composed of 0 (no pain at all) to 10 (worst imaginable pain).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Return to normal daily activities</measure>
    <time_frame>2 weeks after surgery and 6 weeks after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Days to return</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient satisfaction with postoperative recovery</measure>
    <time_frame>48 hours after surgery, 2 weeks after surgery, and 6 weeks after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Questionnaire</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Length of hospital stay</measure>
    <time_frame>Tracked by hour through time of patient discharge (0 - 72 hours)</time_frame>
    <description>Tracked in hours</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">80</enrollment>
  <condition>Pain Management</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group 1: Local Anesthesia</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Standard of care with local anesthesia used during surgery</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group 2: Local Anesthesia plus Pudendal Nerve Block</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Pudendal Nerve Block (PNB) in addition to local anesthesia used during surgery</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Local anaesthetic</intervention_name>
    <description>Local anesthesia injections</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group 1: Local Anesthesia</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pudendal Nerve Block plus anesthesia</intervention_name>
    <description>Local anesthesia injections plus a pudendal nerve block</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group 2: Local Anesthesia plus Pudendal Nerve Block</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Female

          -  Age &gt; 18 years old

          -  English speaking

          -  Undergoing vaginal reconstructive surgery of at least 2 compartments (anterior vaginal
             wall, posterior vaginal wall, and/or apical suspension including hysteropexy,
             uterosacral ligament suspension, or sacrospinous ligament fixation)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Hysterectomy at time of surgery—is variable in duration which may affect response to
             PNB

          -  Inability to tolerate opioids—allergy or medical contraindication

          -  Inability to tolerate local anesthetic agents—allergy or medical contraindication

          -  Inability to tolerate NSAIDS—allergy or medical contraindication

          -  Inability to tolerate acetaminophen—allergy or medical contraindication

          -  Coagulation disorder

          -  Chronic pain syndrome using opioid medication on a regular basis prior to surgery
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <gender_based>Yes</gender_based>
    <gender_description>Women over the age of 18 undergoing vaginal reconstructive surgery without a hysterectomy</gender_description>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>99 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Tamara Grisales, MD</last_name>
    <phone>310-983-1023</phone>
    <email>Tgrisales@mednet.ucla.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Sonali Namiranian</last_name>
    <phone>310-794-9095</phone>
    <email>snamiranian@mednet.ucla.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of California, Los Angeles</name>
      <address>
        <city>Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90095</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sonali Namiranian</last_name>
      <phone>310-794-9095</phone>
      <email>snamiranian@mednet.ucla.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 15, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 18, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">November 20, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 18, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 18, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 20, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of California, Los Angeles</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Tamara Grisales</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Pain Management</keyword>
  <keyword>Pudendal Nerve Block (PNB)</keyword>
  <keyword>Vaginal Reconstruction</keyword>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Anesthetics</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Anesthetics, Local</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

