<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04173481</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>RiphahIUAroosaTariq</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04173481</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>ROOD's Sensory Motor Training in Sub-acute Stroke</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effects of ROOD's Sensory Motor Training Along With Constraint Induced Movement Therapy in Sub-acute Stroke</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Riphah International University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Riphah International University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The aim of this randomized controlled trial is to determine the effects of ROOD's sensory
      motor training along with Constraint Induced Movement Therapy (CIMT) in sub-acute stroke. Two
      randomized groups of patients with stroke were treated with conservative physical therapy and
      the experimental group was given ROOD's SMT and CIMT in conjunction with conservative
      rehabilitation. Both, male and female patients meeting the inclusion criteria were included.
      Patients having other neurological disease, chronic disease, not compatible being
      participates in CIMT or with any surgical intervention were excluded.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The study is aimed at determining the effects of ROOD's sensory motor training along with
      constraint induced movement therapy in sub-acute stroke and is being conducted in National
      Institute of Rehabilitation Medicine Islamabad and Pakistan Railway General Hospital,
      Rawalpindi (Feb 2019-July 2019). Sample size of the study is 36 patients, 36 were included in
      the study on the basis of inclusion criteria, 18 for each group. Patients were allocated
      randomly and equally in each group. Similar conservative rehabilitation protocol was designed
      for both control and experimental group except for experimental group had ROOD's sensory
      motor training and CIMT training. Patients were examined at 1st visit before administration
      of any treatment and at 6th week which was also the last one (after completing 6 weeks
      sessions at alternate days). Baseline evaluation for demographics and assessment was taken.
      Fugyl-meyer assessment scale(FMA) and Wolf motor function test(WMFT) as measuring tools were
      used for first and 6th week assessment. 29 patients completed the study while 4 patient from
      control group and 3 patients from experiment group were lost to follow up and were considered
      drop outs.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">July 30, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 30, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Wolf Motor Function Test</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Changes from the baseline, Wolf motor function test is a test of motor ability that is use to evaluate the speed and coordination.
Total of 17 tasks performed by the patient.
Scoring:
The items are rated on a 6-point scale as 0-6.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Fugyl-meyer motor assessment scale</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Changes from the baseline, Fugyl-meyer assessment scale is use to assess voluntary movements, reflex activity, grasping and coordination of affected limb in stroke. FMA upper extremity portion contain 33 tasks with a scale 0 to 2 with maximum scoring of 66.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">29</enrollment>
  <condition>Stroke</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Rood's Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Rood's sensory motor training along with CIMT</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Conventional Physical Therapy Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Conventional Physical Therapy including Proprioceptive Neuromuscular Facilitation technique.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Rood's Group</intervention_name>
    <description>ROOD'S sensory motor training
Brushing &amp; strokings 3-5 strokings after 30sec, joint compressions and slow stretch 10 rep of 3 sets on alternative days for consecutive 6 weeks CIMT training
Writing, combing hairs and using spoon activity 1 hour training concentrated on affected limb along with restraint of non affected limb by cotton sling under supervision of therapist and 5 hours training in home plan 3 times a week on alternative days for consecutive 6 weeks along with conventional physical therapy.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Rood's Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Conventional Physical Therapy Group</intervention_name>
    <description>Conventional training Proprioceptive neuromuscular facilitations (PNF) Combination of Isotonics technique 10 rep 3 sets 10 sec hold on alternative days for consecutive 6 weeks Stretching's 10 rep 3 sets on alternative days for consecutive 6 weeks Joint approximation 10 rep of 3 sets on alternative days for 6 weeks</description>
    <arm_group_label>Conventional Physical Therapy Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Right &amp; Left hemiplegia

          -  Ischemic &amp; Hemorrhagic stroke

          -  Compatible with being participate in CIMT i.e. 10ºwrist extension,10ºany two fingers
             extension,10ºthumb abduction

          -  Duration of stroke between 6 weeks to 6 months

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Not compatible with being participate in CIMT

          -  Any other neurological disease e.g. Parkinson's disease, brain tumors

          -  Chronic disease e.g. Ischemic Heart Disease, tumors, Diabetes Mellitus

          -  Behaviors issues, not willing to participate

          -  Surgical intervention that hinders treatment and assessment

          -  Not well oriented to follow designed motor task
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>45 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mir Arif Hussain, PhD*</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Riphah International University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Riphah International University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Islamabad</city>
        <zip>440000</zip>
        <country>Pakistan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Pakistan</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sacco RL, Kasner SE, Broderick JP, Caplan LR, Connors JJ, Culebras A, Elkind MS, George MG, Hamdan AD, Higashida RT, Hoh BL, Janis LS, Kase CS, Kleindorfer DO, Lee JM, Moseley ME, Peterson ED, Turan TN, Valderrama AL, Vinters HV; American Heart Association Stroke Council, Council on Cardiovascular Surgery and Anesthesia; Council on Cardiovascular Radiology and Intervention; Council on Cardiovascular and Stroke Nursing; Council on Epidemiology and Prevention; Council on Peripheral Vascular Disease; Council on Nutrition, Physical Activity and Metabolism. An updated definition of stroke for the 21st century: a statement for healthcare professionals from the American Heart Association/American Stroke Association. Stroke. 2013 Jul;44(7):2064-89. doi: 10.1161/STR.0b013e318296aeca. Epub 2013 May 7. Erratum in: Stroke. 2019 Aug;50(8):e239.</citation>
    <PMID>23652265</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Redon J, Olsen MH, Cooper RS, Zurriaga O, Martinez-Beneito MA, Laurent S, Cifkova R, Coca A, Mancia G. Stroke mortality and trends from 1990 to 2006 in 39 countries from Europe and Central Asia: implications for control of high blood pressure. Eur Heart J. 2011 Jun;32(11):1424-31. doi: 10.1093/eurheartj/ehr045. Epub 2011 Apr 12.</citation>
    <PMID>21487117</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Umar M, Badshah M, Baig MS. Frequency of Dystonia Among Post Stroke Patients in Pakistan. Annals of PIMS ISSN. 2016;1815:2287.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Langhorne P, Bernhardt J, Kwakkel G. Stroke rehabilitation. Lancet. 2011 May 14;377(9778):1693-702. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(11)60325-5. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21571152</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Doyle S, Bennett S, Fasoli SE, McKenna KT. Interventions for sensory impairment in the upper limb after stroke. Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2010 Jun 16;(6):CD006331. doi: 10.1002/14651858.CD006331.pub2. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20556766</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lang CE, Bland MD, Bailey RR, Schaefer SY, Birkenmeier RL. Assessment of upper extremity impairment, function, and activity after stroke: foundations for clinical decision making. J Hand Ther. 2013 Apr-Jun;26(2):104-14;quiz 115. doi: 10.1016/j.jht.2012.06.005. Epub 2012 Sep 10. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22975740</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sawaki L, Butler AJ, Leng X, Wassenaar PA, Mohammad YM, Blanton S, Sathian K, Nichols-Larsen DS, Wolf SL, Good DC, Wittenberg GF. Constraint-induced movement therapy results in increased motor map area in subjects 3 to 9 months after stroke. Neurorehabil Neural Repair. 2008 Sep-Oct;22(5):505-13. doi: 10.1177/1545968308317531.</citation>
    <PMID>18780885</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kwakkel G, Veerbeek JM, van Wegen EE, Wolf SL. Constraint-induced movement therapy after stroke. Lancet Neurol. 2015 Feb;14(2):224-34. doi: 10.1016/S1474-4422(14)70160-7. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25772900</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shi YX, Tian JH, Yang KH, Zhao Y. Modified constraint-induced movement therapy versus traditional rehabilitation in patients with upper-extremity dysfunction after stroke: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Arch Phys Med Rehabil. 2011 Jun;92(6):972-82. doi: 10.1016/j.apmr.2010.12.036. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21621674</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schriner M, Thome J, Carrier M. Rehabilitation of the upper extremity after stroke: current practice as a guide for curriculum. The Open Journal of Occupational Therapy. 2014;2(1):6.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pollock A, Baer G, Campbell P, Choo PL, Forster A, Morris J, Pomeroy VM, Langhorne P. Physical rehabilitation approaches for the recovery of function and mobility following stroke. Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2014 Apr 22;(4):CD001920. doi: 10.1002/14651858.CD001920.pub3. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24756870</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nijland R, van Wegen E, Verbunt J, van Wijk R, van Kordelaar J, Kwakkel G. A comparison of two validated tests for upper limb function after stroke: The Wolf Motor Function Test and the Action Research Arm Test. J Rehabil Med. 2010 Jul;42(7):694-6. doi: 10.2340/16501977-0560.</citation>
    <PMID>20603702</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sullivan KJ, Tilson JK, Cen SY, Rose DK, Hershberg J, Correa A, Gallichio J, McLeod M, Moore C, Wu SS, Duncan PW. Fugl-Meyer assessment of sensorimotor function after stroke: standardized training procedure for clinical practice and clinical trials. Stroke. 2011 Feb;42(2):427-32. doi: 10.1161/STROKEAHA.110.592766. Epub 2010 Dec 16.</citation>
    <PMID>21164120</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Beekhuizen KS, Field-Fote EC. Sensory stimulation augments the effects of massed practice training in persons with tetraplegia. Arch Phys Med Rehabil. 2008 Apr;89(4):602-8. doi: 10.1016/j.apmr.2007.11.021.</citation>
    <PMID>18373988</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>November 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 20, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 20, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">November 22, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 23, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 23, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 26, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Stroke</keyword>
  <keyword>Proprioceptive Neuromuscular Facility</keyword>
  <keyword>Hemiplegia</keyword>
  <keyword>Neurorehabilitation</keyword>
  <keyword>Neural Plasticity</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Stroke</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

