<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04179422</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IS002377</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04179422</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Nutritional Status and Family Strategies in Children With Cerebral Palsy.</brief_title>
  <official_title>Nutritional Status and Family Strategies Linked to Feeding in Children and Adolescents With Cerebral Palsy.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Council of Scientific and Technical Research, Argentina</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Council of Scientific and Technical Research, Argentina</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Cerebral palsy (CP) is one of the neurological disorders that most often generates disability
      in pediatric age. Children with CP have a very high nutritional risk since their motor
      dysfunction causes coordination dysfunction in the processes of sucking, chewing and
      swallowing, which lead to insufficient intake. There are other difficulties in relation to
      feeding, such as the time required for feeding and the presence of gastrointestinal
      disorders. In addition, the families of children with CP develop different strategies that
      allow them to face reality. This research plan seeks to investigate the relationships between
      the nutritional status of children and adolescents with CP, food intake and family behavior
      according to the strategies they develop. This study will be observational, cross-sectional
      descriptive. The population will consist of children and adolescents from 2 to 18 years with
      a diagnosis of CP and their families attending health institutions in Córdoba. The minimum
      sample size in 187 subjects was calculated for an expected prevalence of 30% of feeding
      difficulties for an alpha 0.05 and a beta 0.20. It will be a successive sampling, until the
      desired sample is completed. The variables studied will be: age, weight, height, nutritional
      status, sex, type of CP, caloric and macro nutrient intake, type and feeding time, clinical
      difficulties related to feeding and family strategies For data analysis, normal continuous
      variables will be described in means with their standard deviations, with non-normal
      distribution in medians with their interquartile ranges. The daily food intake and macro
      nutrients will be calculated using the Food Analysis and Registration System software
      (SARA1.2.25). The relationship between the average energy intake, the nutritional status of
      children with CP and family strategies will be described. Interpretation of the data will be
      carried out, showing the relationship between the different areas, analyzing the connectivity
      of the ideas with the nutritional status. The study of nutrition in patients with CP is an
      emerging field that has not yet been developed in our country, for which this work plan seeks
      to develop methodologies that promote social inclusion by making substantial and necessary
      contributions to improve the treatment and quality of life of children and adolescents with
      CP.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 30, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 1, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Other</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Nutritional status</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Weigth (Kg), height (cm), BMI (Kg/cm2)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>feeding disorders</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Questionnaire: number of participants with dysphagia, number of participants with sialorrhea, number of participants with constipation, number of participants with gastroesophageal reflux</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Cerebral Palsy</condition>
  <condition>Nutrition Disorders</condition>
  <condition>Child</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>anthropometric measurement</intervention_name>
    <description>weight, height, BMI</description>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>nutritional questionnaire</intervention_name>
    <description>24hs food recall, presence of feeding disorders</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        The population of this study will be made up of children aged 2 to 18 years with a
        diagnosis of CP who attend public and private health institutions in Argentina.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Children with diagnosis of cerebral palsy

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  children with endocrine or metabolic disorders, genetic diseases and other congenital
             anomalies that affect or have affected their growth or nutritional status.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>2 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>18 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Instituto de Investigaciones en Ciencias de la Salud,</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cordoba</city>
        <state>Córdoba</state>
        <zip>5000</zip>
        <country>Argentina</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Eduardo Cuestas, Prof. Dr</last_name>
      <phone>+54 0351 433-4021</phone>
      <email>inicsa@conicet.gov.ar</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Argentina</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Day SM, Strauss DJ, Vachon PJ, Rosenbloom L, Shavelle RM, Wu YW. Growth patterns in a population of children and adolescents with cerebral palsy. Dev Med Child Neurol. 2007 Mar;49(3):167-71.</citation>
    <PMID>17355471</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bell KL, Davies PS. Prediction of height from knee height in children with cerebral palsy and non-disabled children. Ann Hum Biol. 2006 Jul-Aug;33(4):493-9.</citation>
    <PMID>17060071</PMID>
  </reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Brooks J, Day S, Shavelle R, Strauss D. Low weight, morbidity, and mortality in children with cerebral palsy: new clinical growth charts. Pediatrics. 2011 Aug;128(2):e299-307. doi: 10.1542/peds.2010-2801. Epub 2011 Jul 18.</citation>
    <PMID>21768315</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>November 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 17, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 25, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">November 27, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 25, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 25, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 27, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>National Council of Scientific and Technical Research, Argentina</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Eduardo Cuestas</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cerebral Palsy</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Nutrition Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>the research group is yet not decided to make individual participant data available, we wont to have a bigger data base to decide.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

