<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04171401</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>S57757</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04171401</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Limits of Stability in Sitting in Healthy Controls and Participants Post Stroke</brief_title>
  <official_title>Maximum Weight-shifts in Sitting in Non-ambulatory People With Stroke Are Related With Trunk Control and Balance in Sitting and Standing</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>KU Leuven</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Universitaire Ziekenhuizen Leuven</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>KU Leuven</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      In this cross-sectional study we will compare the limits of stability in non-ambulatory
      participants post stroke compared to healthy controls. This will be done by placing
      participants in a seated position on a force platform, that will measure centre of pressure
      displacements during a leaning task in multiple directions. The results of the limits of
      stability test will be compared to standard clinical Measures of trunk control and functional
      balance, to see if there is a relationship between both ways of measuring. And how balance
      and trunk control are affected in the subacute stroke population.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 11, 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">January 27, 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">January 27, 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Control</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Cross-Sectional</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Limits of Stability Testing</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline</time_frame>
    <description>The centre of pressure(COP) movement is measured while the patient is seated on a force platform and is asked by the software that is projected on a screen, to lean with the trunk in a certain direction and hold this position before going back to the starting position. The COP distance between start and end position is calculated, as well as the COP length of the trajectory that it takes the participant to reach his or her maximum leaning position.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Berg Balance Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline</time_frame>
    <description>The Berg Balance Scale (BBS) is used to assess functional balance. The scale consists of 14 items, for each item the minimum score is 0 points, the maximum score is 4 points. A total amount of 56 points can be achieved on the Berg Balance Scale which indicates a normal balance for adults. A score lower than 45 points in elderly indicates that individuals may be at greater risk of falling.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Trunk Impairment Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline</time_frame>
    <description>The Trunk Impairment Scale (TIS) assesses static and dynamic sitting balance and coordination of trunk movement. The test consists of 17 items with a minimum score of 0 and a maximum score of 23 points, which is calculated by adding up the scores from the subscales (0-7 Points for static sitting Balance, 0-10 Points for dynamic sitting Balance, 0-6 Points for coordination), with a higher scores for better trunk control.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Trunk Control Test</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline</time_frame>
    <description>The Trunk Control Tests consists of four items with a maximum score of 100 points. The patient is asked to turn in bed, come from lying to sitting at the bedside and stay seated at the bedside. A higher score shows better functioning.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">49</enrollment>
  <condition>Stroke</condition>
  <condition>Balance; Distorted</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Participants post stroke</arm_group_label>
    <description>Severly affected patients in the subacute phase post stroke that are unable to walk without the help of one or two therapists to assist for balance and weight-carrying. Participants were able to sit independently for two minutes. Participants post stroke performed limits of stability testing in sitting, and tests for trunk control and functional balance.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Healthy controls</arm_group_label>
    <description>Healthy control subjects who matched patients post stroke for age and gender, and had no limitations to perform measurements. Healthy controls performed limits of stability measurements and a clinical measurements for balance.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>In-patient stroke rehabilitation.</intervention_name>
    <description>An in-patient multi-disciplinary stroke rehabilitation program was performed.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Participants post stroke</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        The study population consists of patients post stroke which are severly affected and are
        unable to walk without help of one or two persons who help cary their weight or control
        their balance. Participants are in the subacute phase post stroke and are admitted to a
        rehabilitation programme at the UZ Pellenberg.

        Healthy controls were also included in this study.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria Participants post Stroke:

          -  a stroke with clear hemiplegia (a previous stroke is accepted when complete recovery
             was achieved)

          -  being a patient at the UZ Pellenberg

          -  Functional Ambulation Catergory of two or less

          -  to be able to sit independently for 2 minutes

          -  to be cooperative enough to fulfill multiple Evaluations and tests

          -  to be able to understand simple instructions and be able to execute those.

        Exclusion Criteria Participants post Stroke:

          -  to have musculoskeletal and/or other neurological disorders that could influence the
             protocol

          -  severe communication, memory or language disorders that could disturb the
             understanding of the research protocol.

          -  no signed informed consent

        Inclusion criteria healthy controls:

          -  Age above 50

          -  to be able to stand independently for 2 minutes

        Exclusion criteria healthy controls:

          -  a disorder that could influence balance capabilities

          -  Berg Balance Scale less than 50 Points

          -  no signed informed consent
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Geert Verheyden</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>KU Leuven</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <verification_date>November 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 18, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 19, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">November 20, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 19, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 19, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 20, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>KU Leuven</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Evelien Wiskerke</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Physiotherapist and Researcher, MSc, PhD Candidate</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Stroke</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

