<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04175301</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IRB2019-00236</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04175301</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effect H2 Water on QoL of Patients Receiving Radiotherapy for High Grade Gliomas.</brief_title>
  <official_title>Pilot Study on Effects of Hydrogen Rich Water on Quality of Life of Patients Treated With Radiotherapy for High Grade Gliomas.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Stony Brook University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Stony Brook University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a pilot randomized control trial (RCT) to explore the effects of hydrogen rich water
      on quality of life in patients with high grade gliomas, receiving focal radiation therapy to
      the brain concurrent with chemotherapy with Temozolomide.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This will be a pilot trial exploring the ability of molecular hydrogen to improve quality of
      life in patients with high grade gliomas, receiving focal radiation therapy to the brain
      concurrent with chemotherapy with Temozolomide. Hydrogen has an excellent safety profile, has
      antioxidant properties and reduces inflammatory events in the tissues. It has been postulated
      in previous studies that continuous consumption of hydrogen water reduces oxidative stress in
      the brain by lowering the concentration of the reactive oxygen species, resulting in the
      improvement of adult neurogenesis or the stimulation of neural proliferation, leading to the
      prevention of the decline in the learning and memory.

      This will be a double blinded, placebo-controlled trial. Eligible and willing subjects will
      be randomly assigned in a 2:1 ratio to be treated with either hydrogen or placebo, to receive
      hydrogen or placebo, additionally to all standard-of-care treatments. The treatment with
      hydrogen or placebo will start the day before chemoradiation therapy starts, and continue for
      six weeks. The effects of drinking hydrogen water on the quality of life will be assessed
      using the EORTC QLQ-C30 and the EORTC QLQ-BN20 questionnaires at baseline, at 6 weeks, 6
      months, 12 months, 18 months and 24 months.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 31, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 31, 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 31, 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>The subjects will be randomly assigned in a 2:1 ratio to receive hydrogen or placebo, additionally to all standard-of-care treatments by the SB Research Pharmacy. Masking of active and placebo treatments will be preserved by creating study medication containers that appear identical.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient enrollment statistics</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Feasibility of recruitment, assessment procedures, treatment, and outcome measures will be evaluated. Number of screened / eligible / enrolled patients, treatment adherence, assessment completion, subject dropout, data completeness, and data variability.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>European Organisation for Research and Treatment of Cancer (EORTC) Quality of Life (QLQ) C30 score</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Change in health related quality of life from baseline to week 6, month 6, month 12, month 18, and month 24, as assessed by the EORTC QLQ-C30 score. The score range from 0 to 100; a higher score represents a higher (&quot;better&quot;) level of functioning, or a higher (&quot;worse&quot;) level of symptoms.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>European Organisation for Research and Treatment of Cancer (EORTC) Quality of Life (QLQ) BN20 score</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Change in health related quality of life from baseline to week 6, month 6, month 12, month 18, and month 24, as assessed by the EORTC QLQ-BN20 score. The score range from 0 to 100; a higher score represents a higher (&quot;better&quot;) level of functioning, or a higher (&quot;worse&quot;) level of symptoms.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Memory</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Change in memory from baseline to week 6, month 6, month 12, month 18, and month 24, as assessed by the Mini-Mental State Examination (MMSE).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Karnofsky performance score (KPS)</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Change in Karnofsky performance score (KPS) from baseline to week 6, month 6, month 12, month 18, and month 24.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival and progression free survival (PFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Overall survival is defined as the time from randomization until death from any cause. PFS is defined as the time from randomization until tumor progression (defined by McDonald's criteria).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">15</enrollment>
  <condition>Malignant Glioma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Hydrogen</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Five times per day for 6 weeks subjects will dissolve a hydrogen generating tablet into water and drink the effervescent water. Dissolving one tablet in 250 mL of water will achieve a saturating hydrogen concentration of approximately 1.6 ppm.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Five times per day for 6 weeks subjects will dissolve an placebo tablet into water and drink the effervescent water. The effervescent placebo tablet does not generate hydrogen-enriched water.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Hydrogen</intervention_name>
    <description>Each hydrogen tablet contains 80 mg magnesium</description>
    <arm_group_label>Hydrogen</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>H2</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo oral tablet</intervention_name>
    <description>Matching placebo tablet also contains 80 mg magnesium</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Aged 18 years old or over

          -  New diagnosis of a malignant glioma (HGG) either by a biopsy or craniotomy

          -  KPS of at least 70

          -  Being able to fill out quality of life questionnaire

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Other major diseases of the central nervous system, including history of prior brain
             tumors, Alzheimer's disease, Parkinson's disease, demyelinating disease, inflammatory
             brain or vascular disease, traumatic encephalopathy, or idiopathic intracranial
             hypertension, anxiety/depression.

          -  Pre-existing neurological disability, unable to read or write

          -  Severe comorbidities likely to result in patient dying within 3 months

          -  Prior history of radiation therapy

          -  Prior use of chemotherapy

          -  History of other cancers

          -  Inability to safely tolerate the 1500 ml- 2000ml fluid load (po water) associated with
             study medication*

          -  Pregnancy or nursing.

          -  Treatment with another investigational drug within the last 30 days that may interfere
             with this study's medications*

          -  Hypersensitivity to Temozolomide and or it's active agent- Dacarbazine
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Agnieszka Kowalska, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Stony Brook Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Christine Pol, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>6314449083</phone>
    <email>christiana.pol@stonybrookmedicine.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Agnieszka Kowalska, MD</last_name>
    <phone>631-444-2599</phone>
    <email>agnieszka.kowalska@stonybrookmedicine.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Stony Brook University Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Stony Brook</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>11794-8121</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Christine Pol, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>631-444-9083</phone>
      <email>christiana.pol@stonybrookmedicine.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Agnieszka Kowalska, MD</last_name>
      <phone>631-444-2599</phone>
      <email>agnieszka.kowalska@stonybrookmedicine.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Dennis Choi, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Samuel Ryu, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 20, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 21, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">November 25, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 21, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 21, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 25, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Stony Brook University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Agnieszka Kowalska</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>neuroprotection</keyword>
  <keyword>hydrogen</keyword>
  <keyword>antioxidant</keyword>
  <keyword>malignant glioma</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Glioma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

