<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04176978</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CREC 2019.063T</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04176978</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>PsA T2T Statin Trial on Carotid and Coronary Atherosclerosis</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effects of Tight-control Strategy With and Without Rosuvastatin on Progression of Subclinical Carotid and Coronary Atherosclerosis in Psoriatic Arthritis- a Randomized Controlled Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Chinese University of Hong Kong</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Chinese University of Hong Kong</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Psoriatic arthritis (PsA) is a chronic inflammatory disease associated with an increased risk
      of myocardial infarction (MI). Using coronary computer tomography angiogram (CCTA), it is
      found that a significantly higher prevalence of high-risk coronary plaque (non-calcified
      plaque [NCP]), supporting the notion that more aggressive cardiovascular (CV) evaluation
      strategy should be considered in these patients.

      Carotid ultrasound screening in this population may be a better alternative than traditional
      risk score to identify patients at high CV risk as the latter underestimated CV risk.
      Previous study from our group have demonstrated that achieving treatment target (minimal
      disease activity [MDA]) can prevent progression of carotid atherosclerosis. Nevertheless, 38%
      of this Treat to Target (T2T) cohort still had carotid plaque progression.

      Project description

      it is hypothesized that combination of a T2T stratgy together with high-intensity
      rosuvastatin treatment (Group 1: T2T-statin group) is more effective in preventing
      progression of coronary and carotid atherosclerosis than T2T stratgy alone (Group 2: T2T-only
      group) in high-risk PsA patients with carotid plaque.

      The primary outcome is to ascertain the effect of T2T strategy with high-intensity
      rosuvastain (Group 1: T2T-statin group) on the change in CIMT over a period of 12 months
      compared with T2T strategy alone (Group 2: T2T-only group)
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Treatment protocol This is a 1-year prospective, hospital-based, open-label, randomized,
      controlled trial. The trial comprised two arms. Group 1 will receive T2T strategy together
      with rosuvastain 20mg daily (T2T-statin group). Group 2 will receive T2T strategy only
      (T2T-only group). The method of concealed random allocation will be used. Simple
      randomization will be conducted by a computer-generated random list.

      Use of statins The patients will be given the necessary number of rosuvastatin tablets at
      each visit. At the following visits, surplus medication will be returned to the investigator.
      Compliance is calculated as a percentage, based on the number of tablets returned.

      No trials to date that have evaluated effects on CVD events have tested any medication in
      combination with statins or treatment to specific LDL-C goals, therefore we do not intensify
      the regimen for any particular level of LDL-C response. Measuring LDL-C response after
      initiating therapy in this study is mainly to assess adherence. In this primary prevention
      trial, in patients who do not tolerate statins, no lipid-lowering therapy will be
      administered. Potential interventions include lifestyle modification.

      Use of DMARDs All participants will receive a 1-year protocolized treatment with the aim to
      achieve MDA. A predefined treatment protocol is developed based on the EULAR recommendations
      and the Hong Kong guideline for the use of bDMARDs. Patients fulfilling the criteria for
      bDMARDs can either pay out of pocket or can apply for the Samaritan Fund for financial
      assistance, provided they must pass a household-based financial assessment
      (http://www.ha.org.hk/visitor/ha_visitor_index.asp?content_id=212020). When patient cannot
      achieve treatment goal within 3-6 months of therapy, the treatment therapy will be escalated
      to the next step according to the protocol, unless the patient declined or toxic effects
      preclude this approach. For the introduction of DMARD only joint involvement is taken into
      account. The participants with active disease who failed non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drug
      (NSAID) or those with poor prognostic factor will start with methotrexate monotherapy, which
      is increased to 20mg/week or maximum tolerated dose. Subsequent steps for patients who fail
      to achieve treatment goal include switching to other conventional synthetic DMARDs
      (csDMARDs), combination csDMARD therapy or TNFi, ustekinumab, secukinumab or tofacitinib.
      Intra-articular steroid or local steroid injection to enthesitis and dactylitis are allowed
      during the study but will be forbidden in the 4 weeks before assessment.

      Clinical Assessment Assessment performed at each visit include pain, physicians' and
      patients' global assessments, number of tender joints count (TJC) and swollen joints count
      (SJC) (using the 68 tender/66 SJC), Maastricht Ankylosing Spondylitis Enthesitis Score
      (MASES), number of digits with dactylitis; ankylosing spondylitis disease activity score
      (ASDAS), modified health assessment questionnaire (M-HAQ); Disease Activity index for
      Psoriatic Arthritis (DAPSA), Psoriasis Area (BSA), Psoriasis Activity and Severity Index
      (PASI) were used to measure joint and skin disease activity.(31) MDA was used for assessment
      of treatment efficacy endpoint. The MDA criteria assess 7 domains [TJC ≤ 1, SJC ≤ 1,
      enthesitis count ≤ 1, skin (≤ 1 or BSA ≤ 3%), function (measured by the Health Assessment
      Questionnaire), ≤ 0.5, patient's global VAS on a 100-mm scale ≤ 20, and patient pain VAS on a
      100 mm scale ≤ 15]. If 5 of 7 of the cutoffs for these domains are met, then the patient is
      deemed to be in MDA.

      Cardiovascular assessments The following anthropomorphic assessment will be performed at each
      visit. Anthropomorphic measurements include body heights, body weight, waist and hip
      circumferences, two consecutive blood pressure readings in sitting position and heart rate.
      Hypertension status is defined as systolic blood pressure (SBP) ≥140mmHg or diastolic blood
      pressure (DBP) ≥90mmHg or the use of antihypertensive agents. Other data include menopausal
      status, smoking and drinking habits, history of DM, hypertension, hypercholesterolemia, overt
      CVD, and family history of CVD, DM in first-degree male relatives &lt;55 years of age or
      first-degree female relatives &lt;65 years of age. Drug history is retrieved from case notes or
      elicited during the clinical assessment.

      Laboratory assessments and inflammatory markers Laboratory assessments at each visit include
      complete blood count, liver and renal function tests, creatine kinase (CK), ESR and
      C-reactive protein (CRP), fasting blood glucose, lipid profile (total cholesterol [TC],
      LDL-C, high-density lipoprotein-cholesterol [HDL-C], triglycerides), fibrinogen and uric
      acid.

      Carotid intima-media thickness (CIMT) and plaque CIMT and plaque will be assessed at baseline
      and 12 months.CIMT will be measured using a high-resolution B-mode ultrasound machine
      (Philips EPIQ7) by an experienced sonographer blinded to all clinical information using a
      30-MHz linear vascular probe (Philips L12-3 broadband linear array transducer). The CIMT will
      be measured offline in the distal common carotid artery, bulb, and proximal internal carotid
      artery using dedicated software (Philips Xcelera Cardiology Enterprise Viewer Client 4). The
      mean and maximal IMT values of 6 arterial segments will be calculated for further analysis.
      Plaque is defined as a localized thickening &gt;1.2 mm that do not uniformly involve the whole
      artery. Progression of plaque is defined as an increase in region harboring plaque or number
      of plaque. Reproducibility of IMT was 0.97. Total plaque area (TPA) will be measured as
      described before. The plane for measurement of each plaque will be chosen by reviewing the
      video of the scan to find the largest extent of plaque as seen on the longitudinal view. TPA
      will be recorded as the sum of the areas of all plaques in the right and left carotid
      arteries. Reading of the ultrasound scans obtained at baseline and follow-up will be
      performed concurrently by a single reader (ITC) who is aware of the temporal order of the
      images but is blinded to all clinical data. The change in TPA will be calculated by
      subtracting the baseline TPA from the follow-up TPA. The intraobserver intraclass correlation
      coefficient for TPA was 0.94.

      Coronary atherosclerosis assessment CCTA scans will be performed at baseline and 12 months
      256-rows multidetector CT (General Electric (GE) Revolution CT) in accordance with the
      protocol employed in the ACCURACY trial, and will be analysed by an experienced radiologist
      blinded to clinical data (PT). Coronary artery calcium score (CAC) will be quantified by the
      Agatston method. The presence, site, stenosis level of plaques will be recorded. Coronary
      arteries will be standardised to American Heart Association 15-segment model. Segment
      involvement score (SIS) represented the total number of segments harbouring plaque. Lesions
      rendering over 50% stenosis of the lumen will be considered as obstructive. For multiple
      plaques, the most stenotic one will be recorded. Voxels with attenuation less than 130 HU
      will be assigned to the non-calcified volume of the plaque. For each segment, the presence or
      absence of 4 coronary artery high risk plaque features will be assessed: positive remodeling,
      low attenuation plaque, spotty calcification, and the &quot;napkin ring&quot; sign. Positive remodeling
      is defined as an outer vessel diameter that is 10% greater than the mean of the diameter of
      the segments immediately proximal and distal to the plaque. Low-attenuation plaque is defined
      as a focal central area of plaque with an attenuation density of &lt;30 HU. Spotty calcification
      is defined as focal calcification within the coronary artery wall &lt;3 mm in maximum diameter.
      The &quot;napkin ring&quot; sign is defined as a central area of low attenuation plaque that had a
      peripheral rim of high attenuation. Observer agreement for the assessment of coronary artery
      plaque characteristics has overall been shown to be fair. Plaque volume will be measured
      automatically based on attenuation (CardIQ Xpress 2.0 Reveal, General Electic).

      Toxicity monitoring To monitor the possible side effect of the statin and DMARDs, complete
      blood count, CK, liver and renal function tests will be performed every visit. Chest X-rays
      will be obtained at baseline and at the end of the study. The treating physician record all
      adverse events and serious adverse events and, if necessary, make treatment adjustments in
      accordance with the protocol. Serious adverse events are defined as any adverse reaction
      resulting in any of the following outcomes: a life-threatening condition or death, a
      significant or permanent disability, a malignancy, hospitalization or prolongation of
      hospitalization, a congenital abnormality, or a birth defect.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Suspended</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Lack of funding
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">April 1, 2021</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>change in CIMT over a period of 12 months between two groups</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>The change in carotid IMT will be compared between 2 groups. A higher increment indicate greater progression of atherosclerosis</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression of carotid plaque at 12 months between the two groups.</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Progression of carotid plaque at 12 months between the two groups will be analyzed. Plaque progression is an indicator of worsening of carotid atherosclerosis.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percent change in indexed volume of noncalcified coronary plaque by CCTA over a period of 12 months between the two groups.</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Percent change in indexed volume of noncalcified coronary plaque detected by CCTA indicate the coronary atherosclerosis condition in the patient.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percent change in indexed volume of the sum of fatty plaque and fibrous plaque detected by CCTA over a period of 12 months between the two groups.</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Percent change in indexed volume of the sum of fatty and fibrous plaque detected by CCTA indicate the coronary atherosclerosis condition in the patient.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">142</enrollment>
  <condition>Psoriatic Arthritis</condition>
  <condition>Atherosclerosis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>T2T + statin</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patient in this arm will receive treat-to-target strategy with rousavastin 20mg</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>T2T only</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patient in this arm will receive treat-to-target strategy only.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Rosuvastatin</intervention_name>
    <description>Patient in this group will receive Rosuvastatin 20mg daily.</description>
    <arm_group_label>T2T + statin</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Statin</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Treat-to-target strategy</intervention_name>
    <description>Patient will receive treat-to-target strategy aiming at minimal disease activity (MDA). If patient cannot achieve MDA, treatment will be escalated.</description>
    <arm_group_label>T2T + statin</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>T2T only</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>T2T</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Fulfilled the Classification of Psoriatic Arthritis (CASPAR) criteria

          2. With asymptomatic carotid plaques with &lt;50% stenosis

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. History of overt CVD (including myocardial infarction, angina, stroke, and transient
             ischemic attack)

          2. Currently on antiplatelet agents (including aspirin, Clopidogrel etc), or HMG-CoA
             reductase inhibitors (statins);

          3. FRS &gt; 10% at screening visit who are indicated to start statins;

          4. had contraindication for statin medication (hypersensitivity to statins, liver disease
             with transaminase levels of ≥ 2 times the upper limit of normal [ULN], previous
             statin-induced myopathy or severe hypersensitivity, reactions to other statins

          5. Female of childbearing potential who are unwilling to use adequate contraception

          6. Pregnant or breastfeeding women

          7. Cyclosporine treatment

          8. Treatment with medicinal products that have a known interaction with rosuvastatin

          9. Uncontrolled hypothyroidism defined as thyroid-stimulating hormone level of &gt;1.5 times
             the ULN at the first visit [due to the connection between myopathy and hypothyroidism
             with statin treatment]

         10. Secondary hyperlipidemia (primary hypothyroidism, nephrotic syndrome, creatinine level
             of &gt; 120µmol/l], uncontrolled diabetes mellitus [DM] [glycated hemoglobin &gt;10%], or
             plasma triglyceride level of &gt;6.8 mmoles/liter [602.3 mg/dl])

         11. Other diseases or treatment that reduces the safety of rosuvastatin or treatment that
             would interfere with use of rosuvastatin (gastrointestinal disease/treatment that may
             cause malabsorption of rosuvastatin, cancer, severe psychiatric disease,
             life-threatening ventricular arrhythmias, other medication that increases the risk of
             rhabdomyolysis, known alcohol abuse, or participation in other studies).

         12. Currently on glucocorticoids at a dose &gt;10mg/day.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Lai Shan Tam, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Chinese University of Hong Kong</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of Medicine and Therapeutics</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hong Kong</city>
        <country>Hong Kong</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Hong Kong</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 21, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 22, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">November 26, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 14, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 14, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 16, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Chinese University of Hong Kong</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Lai-Shan Tam</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Arthritis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Arthritis, Psoriatic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Atherosclerosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Coronary Artery Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myocardial Ischemia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Rosuvastatin Calcium</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

