<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04175392</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2019-129</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04175392</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effect of Probiotics in Non-alcoholic Fatty Liver Disease and Steatohepatitis</brief_title>
  <acronym>PRONE</acronym>
  <official_title>Effect of Probiotics in Non-Alcoholic Fatty Liver Disease and Steatohepatitis Measured by Transient Elastography (PRONE Study).</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>William Beaumont Hospitals</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>William Beaumont Hospitals</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>Yes</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will evaluate the effect of probiotics, a beneficial intestinal bacteria
      supplement, if it will cause improvement of the non-alcoholic fatty liver disease (NAFLD) and
      or non-alcoholic steatohepatitis (NASH- an inflammation with concurrent fatty accumulation of
      the liver) as measured by transient elastography - an ultrasound of the liver that assess the
      elastic properties (density) and stiffness of the liver tissue. This study will enroll
      patients 18 years and older with diagnosis of NAFLD and or NASH.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Non-Alcoholic Fatty Liver Disease (NAFLD) and Non-Alcoholic Steatohepatitis (NASH) are
      conditions without symptoms where inflammation in the liver can progress to end-stage liver
      disease (cirrhosis). Current standard of care for these conditions include control of
      metabolic syndrome which includes but is not limited to a patient's high blood pressure
      (hypertension), high cholesterol (hyperlipidemia), high blood sugar (hyperglycemia) and
      excess fat around the waist (central obesity and waist circumference) with lifestyle
      modifications including diet, exercise and medications. While the mechanism for inflammation
      on the liver in NAFLD and NASH is not completely understood, the American Association for the
      Study of Liver Diseases currently suspects it may be connected with the metabolism in the
      bowel and subsequent hepatic (liver) circulation. The bacteria of the intestines (microbiome
      or gut flora) may play a role in the inflammatory cascade through the bloodstream that
      affects the liver.

      The World Health Organization (WHO) and the Food and Agricultural Organization (FAO) of the
      United Nations define Probiotics as a &quot;live microorganism&quot; which, when taken in adequate
      amounts confer a health benefit in the gastrointestinal tract. This study will be done to
      determine if probiotic use may be a viable treatment option for NAFLD and NASH and to
      establish a link that the intestinal microbiome or gut flora plays a role in liver
      inflammation which will be measured by elastography.

      Patients with NAFLD and NASH seen in office consultation of the investigator will be
      approached to participate in the randomized like a flip of a coin, double-blind (patients and
      researchers will be blinded), placebo controlled study. Participant will be counseled on diet
      and exercise. The participants will receive information on a standardized Mediterranean diet
      based nutrition program as well as direction for recommended 30 minutes of aerobic exercise 3
      times weekly. A baseline transient elastography, blood test such as liver enzymes (Aspartate
      Aminotransferase [AST] and Alanine Aminotransferase [ALT]) will be drawn, including
      hemoglobin A1C (diabetic marker), cholesterol in the form of Low-Density Lipoprotein (LDL/bad
      cholesterol) and assessment of Body Mass Index (BMI).

      Participants will be randomized by pharmacy into 2 groups, a control group and a treatment
      group. The treatment group will be provided with a 6 month supply of Align probiotic once
      daily supplementation; the control group will be given a placebo for 6 months along with both
      groups given instructions on how to take the supplement. Subjects will receive a 1 month
      phone call follow up to ensure adherence to study instructions and daily oral intake of
      supplement, and again at 3 months. Study participation will end at 6 months after the repeat
      of liver enzymes, hemoglobin A1C, lipid panel, assessment of BMI and transient elastography
      as completed at scheduled clinical appointment.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">July 30, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 1, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 1, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Prospective, randomized, double-blind study. Participant will be randomized to either the Treatment (Probiotic) Group or the Control (Placebo) Group.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
    <masking_description>Both Participants and Researchers will not know which treatment group assigned to.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Probiotic effects on liver fibrosis</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Probiotic effects on liver fibrosis as measured by transient elastography, as a change from baseline to 6 months, measured in kilopascals (KPa). Positive numbers indicate an increase in fibrosis; negative numbers indicate decrease in fibrosis</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Probiotic effects on Liver enzymes, AST</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Probiotic effects on Liver enzymes, AST as a change from baseline to 6 months, measured in units per liter. Positive numbers indicate an increase in AST; negative numbers indicate decrease in AST</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Probiotic effects on Liver enzymes, ALT</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Probiotic effects on Liver enzymes, ALT as a change from baseline to 6 months, measured in units per liter. Positive numbers indicate an increase in ALT; negative numbers indicate decrease in ALT</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Probiotic effects on Diabetic Markers</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Probiotic effects on Diabetic Markers as measured by hemoglobin A1C blood test as a change from baseline to 6 months, measured in percent. Positive numbers indicate an increase in hemoglobin A1c; negative numbers indicate decrease in hemoglobin A1c</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Probiotic effects on BMI</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Probiotic effects on Body Mass Index (BMI) wherein weight and height will be combined to report BMI in kg/m^2 as a change from baseline to 6 months. Positive numbers indicate an increase in BMI; negative numbers indicate decrease in BMI.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Probiotic effects on LDL</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Probiotic effects on Low-density Lipoprotein (LDL) as a change from baseline to 6 months, measured in milligrams per deciliter. Positive numbers indicate an increase in LDL; negative numbers indicate decrease in LDL</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">80</enrollment>
  <condition>Fatty Liver Disease</condition>
  <condition>Fibrosis, Liver</condition>
  <condition>Cirrhosis, Liver</condition>
  <condition>Steatohepatitis, Nonalcoholic</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment Group: Probiotic</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Probiotic 1 billion units Supplement Once Daily</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control Group: Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Placebo Capsule Once Daily</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Align Probiotic Supplement Capsule</intervention_name>
    <description>Align Probiotic 1 billion units, 1 capsule once daily</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment Group: Probiotic</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Probiotic</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebos</intervention_name>
    <description>Placebos capsule 1 capsule Once daily</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control Group: Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Placebo</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Diagnosis of NAFLD and/or NASH

          -  Subject aged 18 and older

          -  Non-pregnant - Self-reported

          -  Subject with decision making capacity to understand and consent to study procedures

          -  Ability to follow study related activities regarding medications, diet and exercise

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Without diagnosis of NAFLD or NASH

          -  History of liver disease from other causes, including but not limited to hepatitis,
             autoimmune, alcohol use, fatty liver of pregnancy, Wilson's disease, primary or
             secondary hemochromatosis

          -  Patients aged less than 18 years

          -  Self-reported pregnant patients

          -  Inability to understand, follow and consent to study procedures

          -  Hepatic decompensation defined as gastrointestinal bleeding, ascites, hepatic
             encephalopathy

          -  Inability to engage in exercise

          -  Currently immunocompromised or taking immunosuppressive drugs

          -  Milk protein allergy

          -  Recent or active chemotherapy for malignancy

          -  Gastrointestinal malignancy

          -  Gastrointestinal disease such as Ulcerative Colitis, Crohn's Disease as these alter
             the microbiome

          -  Recent antibiotic therapy (within 6 months)

          -  Known allergy to probiotics

          -  History of major gastrointestinal surgery such as resection of the colon

          -  No concomitant use of probiotic from any source (i.e., kefir, certain yogurts, live
             culture, sauerkraut)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mariquit Sendelbach, DO</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>William Beaumont Hospitals</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Mark Anthony Raphael, DO</last_name>
    <phone>586-604-2810</phone>
    <email>mark.raphael@beaumont.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Evie Russell, RN.</last_name>
    <phone>947-521-8136</phone>
    <email>evie.russell@beaumont.org</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Beaumont Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Farmington Hills</city>
        <state>Michigan</state>
        <zip>48336</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Evie Russell, RN.</last_name>
      <phone>248-471-8136</phone>
      <email>evie.russell@beaumont.org</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Mariquit Sendelbach, DO</last_name>
      <phone>248 579 9220</phone>
      <email>mariquit.sendelbach@beaumont.org</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 21, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 21, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">November 25, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 23, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 23, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 24, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>William Beaumont Hospitals</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Mariquit Sendelbach</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Fatty Liver</keyword>
  <keyword>Fibrosis</keyword>
  <keyword>Cirrhosis</keyword>
  <keyword>Probiotic</keyword>
  <keyword>Steatohepatitis</keyword>
  <keyword>Elastography</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Liver Cirrhosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Liver Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fatty Liver</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Non-alcoholic Fatty Liver Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fibrosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

