<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04172909</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2019-10682</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04172909</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>LEGO MRI: Decreasing the Need for Sedation, and Improving Patient Anxiety.</brief_title>
  <acronym>LEGO MRI</acronym>
  <official_title>LEGO MRI: Decreasing the Need for Sedation, and Improving Patient Anxiety.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Montefiore Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Montefiore Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The objective of the LEGO®Bricks MRI project is to study a new play-based tool for use in
      children preparing to undergo MRI and evaluate its ability to reduce the need for anesthesia.

      A randomized study design will be employed in the experimental &quot;Child Life&quot; (CL) group, in
      regard to which Child Life intervention patients will have. Age matched controls will be
      found retrospectively, and will be patients of the same age, undergoing their first
      non-contrast brain MRI with no Child Life intervention.

      Patients in the CL group will be prepped by a Certified Child Life Specialist with the use of
      one of the following 2 tools, to be randomly selected:

        1. LEGO Bricks model MRI (A model of the MRI machine and adjacent control room made out of
           LEGO bricks)

        2. Mock MRI tube (A six foot long pop-out play tunnel for children, with a diameter of
           around 17 inches to simulate the MRI magnet bore)
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Diagnostic imaging is frequently utilized in modern medical practice, and various imaging
      modalities are routinely utilized in the care of pediatric patients. Magnetic resonance
      imaging (MRI) is an advanced imaging modality that is utilized to evaluate many conditions in
      pediatric patients. MRI is frequently favored over other imaging modalities in pediatrics
      since it allows for high-quality cross sectional imaging without the use of potentially
      harmful ionizing radiation, to which children are more sensitive than adults. However, MRI
      quality is highly dependent on patients' ability to hold still and follow instructions, which
      is often challenging in pediatric patients. Young and uncooperative children often require
      anesthesia to successfully complete MRI. Anesthesia can often be avoided with the assistance
      of Certified Child Life Specialists, who use techniques to reduce patient anxiety and improve
      children's ability to follow instructions during MRI. For example, children may visit the MRI
      unit or a simulator prior to the examination to contextualize the procedure1-3. Preparation,
      in the form of play, has been proven to reduce anxiety in children prior to scans and
      invasive medical procedures. Children who are prepared for medical procedures experience less
      fear and anxiety and will have better long term adjustment to medical challenges (Koller,
      2008).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 24, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 1, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 1, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>There will be two experimental groups including the LEGO Bricks group, and the Mock MRI tube group, as well as a retrospective age matched control group.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants who need anesthesia - Comparing CL groups ((1) LEGO Bricks model MRI and (2) mock MRI tube groups) and Control group</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 90 minutes (duration of MRI exam)</time_frame>
    <description>Monitor whether or not the child needs anesthesia to successfully complete MRI exam</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Anxiety Scores -Comparing CL groups (1) LEGO Bricks model MRI and (2) mock MRI tube -- Control group will not have Anxiety Scores available, and will not be assessed on this secondary outcome measure.</measure>
    <time_frame>At time of enrollment (Baseline) and at the end of MRI exam, which typically ranges from 15-90 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>Anxiety score will be measured by response to a series of questions using an anxiety self rating scale where for each questions particpants need to decide if Not at all applies (mark 1) Somewhat (mark 2) Moderately (mark 3) Very much (mark 4).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in quality of MRI image- Comparing CL groups ((1) LEGO Bricks model MRI and (2) mock MRI tube groups) and Control group using image quality and motion artifact grading scale</measure>
    <time_frame>1-2 weeks (average time to get MRI results)</time_frame>
    <description>This will be assessed by blinded attending radiologist/ resident radiologist. The above mentioned grading scale scores motion artifact and image quality on a 1 to 4 and 0 to 3 scales as follows:
Image quality:
1 (excellent images, with very high confidence in diagnostic content), 2 (good images, with confidence in diagnostic content), 3 (fair images, with reservations about diagnostic content), 4 (poor nondiagnostic image),
Motion artifact:
0 (no motion artifact)
(minimal motion artifact not interfering with diagnostic content)
(moderate motion artifact degrading diagnostic content)
(severe motion artifact resulting in non diagnostic image)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in duration of MRI exam-Comparing time stamp (ending time of exam minus beginning time of exam) of MRI in CL groups ((1) LEGO Bricks model MRI and (2) mock MRI tube groups) and Control group</measure>
    <time_frame>At the end of MRI exam, which typically ranges from 15-90 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>Total length of time from beginning to end of MRI scan will be recorded and compared between groups, by subtracting the start time of the exam from the end time of the exam.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">200</enrollment>
  <condition>Stress</condition>
  <condition>Anesthesia</condition>
  <condition>Children, Only</condition>
  <condition>Anxiety</condition>
  <condition>MRI</condition>
  <condition>Sedation</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Child life group with LEGO bricks</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients in this group will be prepped by a Certified Child Life Specialist with the use of LEGO bricks model MR</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Age matched controls will be found retrospectively, and will be patients of the same age, undergoing their first non-contrast brain MRI with no Child Life intervention.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Child life group with Mock MRI tube</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients in this group will be prepped by a Certified Child Life Specialist with the use of a Mock MRI tube</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>LEGO Bricks MRI</intervention_name>
    <description>LEGO Bricks model MRI (A model of the MRI machine and adjacent control room made out of LEGO bricks) will be used by the child life specialist to prepare the child for MRI</description>
    <arm_group_label>Child life group with LEGO bricks</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Mock MRI tube</intervention_name>
    <description>Mock MRI tube will be used by the child life specialist to prepare the child for MRI</description>
    <arm_group_label>Child life group with Mock MRI tube</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Between 4 and 10 years of age

          -  Undergoing first MRI

          -  MRI brain without contrast

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Diagnosed serious illness/mental disability

          -  Have undergone prior MRI
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>4 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>10 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mark Liszewski, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Montefiore Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Mark Liszewski, MD</last_name>
    <phone>718-920-7748</phone>
    <email>mliszews@montefiore.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Faraz Ahmed, MD</last_name>
    <phone>5165077344</phone>
    <email>faraz.ahmed1222@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Montefiore Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bronx</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10467</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Faraz Ahmed</last_name>
      <phone>516-507-7344</phone>
      <email>faraz.ahmed1222@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Saleh RS, Patel S, Lee MH, Boechat MI, Ratib O, Saraiva CR, Finn JP. Contrast-enhanced MR angiography of the chest and abdomen with use of controlled apnea in children. Radiology. 2007 Jun;243(3):837-46.</citation>
    <PMID>17517937</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 10, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 19, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">November 21, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 24, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 24, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 25, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Montefiore Medical Center</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Mark Liszewski</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Anxiety Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

