<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04176549</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>18HH4883</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04176549</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Assessment of Biomarkers in Ectopic Pregnancy</brief_title>
  <acronym>AMBER</acronym>
  <official_title>The Assessment of Biomarkers in Ectopic Pregnancy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Imperial College London</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Imperial College Healthcare NHS Trust</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Imperial College London</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To further develop a patient care pathway (incorporating a statistical model which uses the
      values of biomarkers) in routine clinical practice that will aid the diagnosis and management
      of women with an ectopic pregnancy.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Purpose and design-There is a need for the patient care pathway to evolve in order to aid and
      improve the diagnosis and management of women with a pregnancy of unknown location (PUL) and
      ectopic pregnancy (EP). There is potential for this to be achieved by the incorporation of a
      statistical model that uses one or more novel markers identified by this study. These markers
      may replace or add to the effectiveness of markers used in the current statistical model.

      Recruitment-200 patients. Inclusion: Patients attending the Early Pregnancy Unit (EPU) in the
      first trimester with a PUL or ectopic pregnancy on trans-vaginal ultrasound scan between the
      ages of 18-50 years. Exclusion: Patients diagnosed with cancer, presence of acute medical
      condition, patients aged less than 18 years, patients who cannot give fully informed study
      consent.

      Consent - Posters will advertise the study. Patients in EPU will be invited to the study by a
      member of the clinical care team. Written consent will be required for all aspects of the
      study other than for 3-dimensional scanning of PUL and EP patients, where verbal consent will
      be obtained. Patients will be given at least 24 hours to consider whether they wish to
      participate.

      Confidentiality - The Chief Investigator will preserve the confidentiality of participants
      taking part in the study and is registered under the Data Protection Act. Patient consent
      forms will be stored securely within the study file. All patient identifiable information,
      where required, will be stored electronically on National Health Service (NHS) approved
      computers, accessible only by personnel involved in the study via password.

      Conflict of interest - None involved in the study have a conflict of interest.

      Dissemination of results - No patient identifiable information will be included in the
      research report or publication. Anonymised results will be disseminated to scientific
      community by means of publication in peer-reviewed literature and presented at national and
      international meetings.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 18, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 8, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 8, 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Novel biomarkers for Ectopic Pregnancy prediction and diagnosis</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Identification of microRNA and microbiome markers identified in blood, urine, swabs, fallopian tubes, peritoneal washings and trophoblastic tissue that have predictive value in identifying ectopic pregnancies as well as high and low risk pregnancy of unknown location. microRNA will be assessed using blood and trophoblast using cell free profiling assays and quantitative reverse transcription polymerase chain reaction and microbiome will be assessed using Illumina microbiome genomic sequencing.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>microRNA as a biomarker</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Identification of novel microRNA markers from blood and trophoblast tissue samples associated with ectopic pregnancy and high-risk pregnancy of unknown location. MicroRNA will be assessed using blood and trophoblast using cell free profiling assays and quantitative reverse transcription polymerase chain reaction.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Microbiome as a biomarker</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Identification of novel microbiome markers from blood and trophoblast tissue samples associated with ectopic pregnancy and high-risk pregnancy of unknown location. Microbiome will be assessed using Illumina microbiome genomic sequencing.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>3</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">200</enrollment>
  <condition>Ectopic Pregnancy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Ectopic Pregnancy</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients diagnosed with ectopic pregnancy Samples collected: Plasma, Serum, Urine, Oral swab, Vaginal Swab If surgery required for tubal ectopic: Fallopian tube, peritoneal washing, trophoblast</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Surgical termination of pregnancy</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients undergoing elective surgical termination of pregnancy Samples collected: Plasma, Serum, Urine, Oral swab Vaginal swab, Trophoblast</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Elective hysterectomy and salpingo-oophorectomy</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients undergoing elective hysterectomy and salpingo-oophorectomy Samples collected: Fallopian tube, peritoneal washing</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Management of Ectopic Pregnancy</intervention_name>
    <description>Expectant, Medical or Surgical management of Ectopic Pregnancy</description>
    <arm_group_label>Ectopic Pregnancy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Management of termination of pregnancy</intervention_name>
    <description>Surgical termination of pregnancy</description>
    <arm_group_label>Surgical termination of pregnancy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Elective management of gynaecology patients</intervention_name>
    <description>Elective hysterectomy and salpingo-oophorectomy</description>
    <arm_group_label>Elective hysterectomy and salpingo-oophorectomy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Plasma samples Serum samples Urine samples Oral swabs Vaginal swabs Fallopian tube samples
      Peritoneal washing samples Trophoblast tissue samples
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        -  Pregnant women attending the Early Pregnancy Unit (EPU) within a hospital in the first
             trimester (up to 14 weeks gestation) with a PUL or ectopic pregnancy on trans-vaginal
             ultrasound scan between the ages of 18 and 50 years.

          -  Women attending the gynaecology unit for a surgical termination of pregnancy or for a
             salpingo-oophorectomy.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients attending the Early Pregnancy Unit (EPU) in the first trimester (up to 14
             weeks gestation) with a PUL or ectopic pregnancy on trans-vaginal ultrasound scan
             between the ages of 18 and 50 years.

          -  Patients attending the gynaecology unit for a surgical termination of pregnancy or for
             a salpingo-oophorectomy.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients diagnosed with cancer, presence of an acute medical condition, patients aged
             less than 18 years, patients who cannot give fully informed study consent (language or
             learning impairment), presence of a viable intrauterine pregnancy and presence of
             miscarriage.

          -  Exclusion to fallopian tube samples - presence of any ectopic pregnancy that does not
             require operative salpingectomy.

          -  Exclusion to peritoneal washings - presence of any ectopic pregnancy that does not
             require access to the peritoneal cavity as part of management.

          -  Exclusion to trophoblast tissue sampling - presence of an ectopic pregnancy that does
             not require surgical removal.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>50 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Tom Bourne, MBBS, PhD, MRCOG</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Imperial College London</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Tom Bourne, MBBS, PhD, MRCOG</last_name>
    <phone>0044 203 313 5131</phone>
    <email>t.bourne@ic.ac.uk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Christopher Kyriacou, MBBS, BSc</last_name>
    <phone>0044 203 313 5131</phone>
    <email>christopher.kyriacou@nhs.net</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Imperial College Healthcare NHS Trust</name>
      <address>
        <city>London</city>
        <zip>W12 0HS</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Tom Bourne, MBBS, PhD, MRCOG</last_name>
      <phone>0044 203 313 5131</phone>
      <email>t.bourne@ic.ac.uk</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Christopher Kyriacou, MBBS, BSc</last_name>
      <phone>0044 203 313 5131</phone>
      <email>christopher.kyriacou@nhs.net</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Tom Bourne, MBBS, PhD, MRCOG</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bobdiwala S, Al-Memar M, Farren J, Bourne T. Factors to consider in pregnancy of unknown location. Womens Health (Lond). 2017 Aug;13(2):27-33. doi: 10.1177/1745505717709677. Epub 2017 Jun 29. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>28660799</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Senapati S, Barnhart KT. Biomarkers for ectopic pregnancy and pregnancy of unknown location. Fertil Steril. 2013 Mar 15;99(4):1107-16. doi: 10.1016/j.fertnstert.2012.11.038. Epub 2013 Jan 3. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23290746</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Van Calster B, Bobdiwala S, Guha S, Van Hoorde K, Al-Memar M, Harvey R, Farren J, Kirk E, Condous G, Sur S, Stalder C, Timmerman D, Bourne T. Managing pregnancy of unknown location based on initial serum progesterone and serial serum hCG levels: development and validation of a two-step triage protocol. Ultrasound Obstet Gynecol. 2016 Nov;48(5):642-649. doi: 10.1002/uog.15864. Epub 2016 Oct 9.</citation>
    <PMID>26776599</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bobdiwala S, Christodoulou E, Farren J, Mitchell-Jones N, Kyriacou C, Al-Memar M, Ayim F, Chohan B, Kirk E, Abughazza O, Guruwadahyarhalli B, Guha S, Vathanan V, Bottomley C, Gould D, Stalder C, Timmerman D, van Calster B, Bourne T. Triaging women with pregnancy of unknown location using two-step protocol including M6 model: clinical implementation study. Ultrasound Obstet Gynecol. 2020 Jan;55(1):105-114. doi: 10.1002/uog.20420.</citation>
    <PMID>31385381</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cook J, Bennett PR, Kim SH, Teoh TG, Sykes L, Kindinger LM, Garrett A, Binkhamis R, MacIntyre DA, Terzidou V. First Trimester Circulating MicroRNA Biomarkers Predictive of Subsequent Preterm Delivery and Cervical Shortening. Sci Rep. 2019 Apr 10;9(1):5861. doi: 10.1038/s41598-019-42166-1.</citation>
    <PMID>30971726</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>November 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 20, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 21, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">November 25, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 21, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 21, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 25, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Ectopic Pregnancy</keyword>
  <keyword>Biomarker</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pregnancy, Ectopic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cardiac Complexes, Premature</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

