<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04067973</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>RC19_0026</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04067973</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Impact of Prematurity on the Optic Nerve</brief_title>
  <official_title>Impact of Prematurity on the Morphological and Tomographic Aspect of the Papilla</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Nantes University Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Nantes University Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this protocol is to study the consequences of prematurity on the optic nerve.
      Indeed, the work already carried out on the subject suggests that prematurity induces
      suffering of the optic nerve with a loss of optical fibre, an essential element in the
      transmission of the visual nerve signal to the brain.

      The investigators will therefore study two populations: a population of premature infants
      aged 5 to 10 years, and a control population of term infants.

      The examinations performed are painless, non-invasive and non-irradiating. To date, there are
      no known adverse reactions to these tests. These examinations are a photo of the fundus
      (retinophotography), a pachymetry (measurement of the thickness of the non-contact cornea),
      an OCT RNFL (optical coherence tomography, scanner of the non-irradiating non-painful optical
      nerve) and the taking of the IOP (intraocular pressure).

      They aim to measure the main morphological characteristics of the eye and the optic nerve.

      This is a prospective observational study. The inclusion and measurements necessary for the
      study are made on the day of the consultation.

      The expected results will provide new data on this population of premature infants, allowing
      for better management if a pathology involving the optic nerve were to occur at any age in
      these patients.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The prematurity of the newborn is now a major theme in medical research. Indeed,
      technological progress makes it possible to revive increasingly premature children. But being
      born premature also brings many complications, some of which are already well known
      (pulmonary, cardiac, digestive complications, etc....). At the ophthalmological level, the
      retinopathy of the premature child is an entity already well described, this retinal
      vascularization anomaly leads to many complications on the child's visual future. The optic
      nerves of premature infants are described as larger than those of normal children.

      Recently, a new ophthalmological condition has been described. This is the damage to the
      optic nerve of the premature baby, characterized by a loss of optical fibres, of major
      importance in the transmission of the visual signal to the brain.

      The aim of this study is to characterize the particularities of the optic nerve of the
      premature child, as there is currently very little data available on it in this context. Some
      studies have reported this, but with results that are not always homogeneous. For example,
      some studies report a lack of optic fiber in the temporal area of the optic nerve, while
      others find more pronounced atrophy on the nasal side, which has practical consequences in
      the examination and monitoring of these children.

      A better understanding of these disorders would make it possible to establish monitoring
      protocols for these children born with nerve fibre deficiency, especially to prevent
      subsequent fibre loss due to any pathology of ocular tone, the best known of which is
      glaucoma.

      The purpose of this prospective study is to compare the aspects of optic nerves in premature
      infants compared to those of optic nerves in non-premature infants. This aspect changes with
      age, with a progressive physiological decrease in the thickness of optic fiber within the
      optic nerve over time. It is therefore essential to match the two age groups to exploit this
      data.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">September 2, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational [Patient Registry]</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Control</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <target_duration>1 Day</target_duration>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Compare the thickness of the optical fibres measured in OCT RNFL between premature subjects and controls.</measure>
    <time_frame>10 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>The examinations performed are painless, non-invasive and non-irradiating. To date, there are no known adverse reactions to these tests. These examinations are a photo of the fundus (retinophotography), a pachymetry (measurement of the thickness of the non-contact cornea), an OCT RNFL (optical coherence tomography, scanner of the non-irradiating non-painful optical nerve) and the taking of the IOP (intraocular pressure).
They aim to measure the main morphological characteristics of the eye and the optic nerve.
We will therefore study two populations: a population of premature infants aged 5 to 10 years, and a control population of term infants.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Compare the cup/disc ratio</measure>
    <time_frame>20 seconds</time_frame>
    <description>Compare the cup/disc ratio (optic nerve excavation, a criterion well used in the study of glaucoma) between the premature population and the control population.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>eye length</measure>
    <time_frame>10 seconds</time_frame>
    <description>compare the measurement of the axial eye length (eye length) between the two populations.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Intraocular tension</measure>
    <time_frame>20 seconds</time_frame>
    <description>compare the intraocular tension (which can lead to a loss of optical fibre if too high, a criterion measured to avoid any bias induced by hypertonia on the thickness of the optical fibres) between the two populations.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pachymetry</measure>
    <time_frame>20 seconds</time_frame>
    <description>compare pachymetry (corneal thickness, measurement that may interfere with intraocular pressure measurement) between premature born patients and controls</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>refractive measurements</measure>
    <time_frame>20 seconds</time_frame>
    <description>compare refractive measurements (myopia, hyperopia, astigmatism) between the two populations</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Ocular Surface Disease</condition>
  <condition>Premature</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>patients</arm_group_label>
    <description>Premature subjects benefit from the examinations described in the protocol, namely automated refractometry, intraocular air pressure, biometrics (with axial length and pachymetry (corneal thickness) performed by the same machine at the same time), a photo of the fundus (retinophotography) and an OCT RNFL. These examinations are necessary for the follow-up of premature children.
All children examined at Nantes University Hospital benefit systematically from: automated refractometry, intraocular pressure in the air and a photo of the fundus.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>control</arm_group_label>
    <description>controls benefit from two additional tests: RNFL OCT and biometrics. The duration of the RNFL OCT is about 2 minutes, with a total of 10 seconds per eye, the rest being computer manipulation.
The biometrics take about 2 minutes to complete, with a total of 30 seconds per eye, the rest being computer manipulation.
These two reviews are conducted on the same day as the initial consultation and directly following the consultation.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Prospective monocentric case-control study, based on the use of data recovered after a
        single patient visit.

        Conduct of a visit for the patient (case control):

          -  Reception of the patient and his parents or legal representatives

          -  Information to the patient and his parents or legal representatives of the study

          -  Carrying out the standard consultation (optical correction most often) then carrying
             out additional examinations necessary for the study.

          -  This visit is unique, there will be no further visits.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  For patients:

          -  between 5 and 10 years old

          -  Premature births: before 37 weeks of amenorrhea

          -  To be able to benefit from the examinations necessary for the study (being able to set
             a target, to install correctly on the machines)

        For control:

          -  Aged between 5 and 10 years old

          -  Born after 37 SA

          -  No known ophthalmological pathologies

          -  To be able to benefit from the examinations necessary for the study (being able to set
             a target, to install correctly on the machines)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients who cannot benefit from the examinations (patients in wheelchairs, whose
             psychomotor delay prevents a good understanding of the examination and the need to set
             a target)

          -  patient under the protection of justice.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>5 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>10 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <verification_date>August 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 22, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 23, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 28, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 23, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 23, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">August 28, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>optic nerve</keyword>
  <keyword>premature</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Premature Birth</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

