<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04064216</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ATADEK-2018/8</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04064216</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Comparison of Cosmesis, Patient Satisfaction and Quality of Life in Patients Undergoing Laparoscopic Surgery</brief_title>
  <official_title>Comparison of Cosmesis, Patient Satisfaction and Quality of Life in Patients Undergoing Robot Assisted Versus Conventional Laparoscopic Surgery for Bening Gynecologic Disorders: a Prospective Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Acibadem University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Acibadem University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To compare robot assisted versus conventional laparoscopic surgery performed for bening
      gynecologic disorders regarding cosmesis, patient satisfaction and quality of life
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      30 patients undergoing robot assisted laparoscopic surgery for bening gynecologic disorders
      and 30 patients undergoing conventional laparoscopic surgery for bening gynecologic disorders
      will be included in the study. All surgeries will be performed in the same hospital by the
      same surgeon. 6 months after the surgery the patients will be called and will be informed
      about the trial. After confirming that the questionnaires can be sent to them by e-mail, 4
      questionnaires will be sent to the patients via e-mail. To evaluate cosmesis, patient
      satisfaction and quality of life VAS (visual analogue scale), SF-12 (short form-12) health
      survey, BIQ (body image questionnaire) and POSAS (the patient and observer scar assessment
      scale) will be sent to the patients 6 months after the surgery. Patients who have not
      completed the questionnaires will be called for reminders after 1 week. Patients will be
      expected to complete the questionnaire completely and accurately.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 16, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 16, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 16, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational [Patient Registry]</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <target_duration>9 Months</target_duration>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient-perceived cosmesis</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months after the surgery</time_frame>
    <description>The primary outcome is to evaluate patient's satisfaction about their laparoscopic incision scars 6 months after the surgery. 6 months after the surgery the patients will be called and will be informed about the trial. After confirming that the questionnaires can be sent to them by e-mail, questionnaires will be sent to the patients. BIQ (body image questionnaire) multiple choice questionnaire to evaluate their scar will be sent to the patients 6 months after the surgery. Patients who have not completed the questionnaires will be called for reminders after 1 week. Patients will be expected to complete the questionnaires completely and accurately.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient and observer scar assessment</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months after the surgery</time_frame>
    <description>The primary outcome is to evaluate patient's satisfaction about their laparoscopic incision scars 6 months after the surgery. 6 months after the surgery the patients will be called and will be informed about our trial. After confirming that the questionnaires can be sent to them by e-mail, questionnaires will be sent to the patients. POSAS (the patient and observer scar assessment scale) multiple choice questionnaires to evaluate their scar will be sent to the patients 6 months after the surgery. Patients who have not completed the questionnaires will be called for reminders after 1 week. Patients will be expected to complete the questionnaires completely and accurately.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient satisfaction</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months after the surgery</time_frame>
    <description>To compare patient-reported satisfaction using a scale called visual analogue scale (VAS) will be send to the patients via e-mail. This is a 100-mm long scale with adjectival descriptions at both end positions. There will be a statement explaining what was intended to measure. Participants will be asked to mark the VAS 6 months after the surgery. On this scale 0 representing the worst and 10 the best expected appearance of their scars.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of life after robot assisted versus conventional laparoscopic surgery</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months after the surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Quality of life will be measured using SF-12 (short form 12) health questionnaire. This is a 12-Item Short-form Health Survey. 6 months after the surgery the patients will be called and will be informed about our trial. After confirming that the questionnaire can be sent to them by e-mail, questionnaire will be sent to the patients. Patients who have not completed the questionnaires will be called for reminders after 1 week. Patients will be expected to complete the questionnaires completely and accurately.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Gynecologic Disease</condition>
  <condition>Cosmesis</condition>
  <condition>Patient Satisfaction</condition>
  <condition>Quality of Life</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Robot assisted laparoscopic surgery</arm_group_label>
    <description>This group will be consisted of patients that will undergo robot assisted laparoscopic surgery for benign gynecologic disorders</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Conventional laparoscopic surgery</arm_group_label>
    <description>This group will be consisted of patients that will undergo conventional laparoscopic surgery for benign gynecologic disorders</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Laparoscopic surgery</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients that will undergo robot assisted laparoscopic surgery and conventional laparoscopic surgery for benign gynecologic disorders will answer 4 questionnaires to assess patient satisfaction, quality of life and cosmesis</description>
    <arm_group_label>Conventional laparoscopic surgery</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Robot assisted laparoscopic surgery</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        30 patients undergoing robot assisted laparoscopic surgery for bening gynecologic disorders
        and 30 patients undergoing conventional laparoscopic surgery for bening gynecologic
        disorders will be included in our study.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with a diagnosis of being gynecologic disorders

          -  Patients undergoing conventional laparoscopic surgery

          -  Patients undergoing robot assisted laparoscopic surgery

          -  Patients undergoing surgery in our hospital by the same surgeon

          -  Patients willing to participate in the study

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Malignancy

          -  Requirement of emergency procedure

          -  Pregnancy

          -  Visible previous abdominal scars or keloid

          -  Inability of patient to tolerate Trendelenburg position or pneumoperitoneum

          -  Patients undergoing surgery by another surgeon or in an another hospital

          -  Mental impairment that would preclude giving informed consent
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <gender_based>Yes</gender_based>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mete Gungor, MD,Prof.</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Acibadem Mehmet Ali Aydinlar University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Acibadem Maslak Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Istanbul</city>
        <state>Sariyer</state>
        <zip>34457</zip>
        <country>Turkey</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Turkey</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Van Loey NE, Van Son MJ. Psychopathology and psychological problems in patients with burn scars: epidemiology and management. Am J Clin Dermatol. 2003;4(4):245-72. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>12680803</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Korolija D, Sauerland S, Wood-Dauphinée S, Abbou CC, Eypasch E, Caballero MG, Lumsden MA, Millat B, Monson JR, Nilsson G, Pointner R, Schwenk W, Shamiyeh A, Szold A, Targarona E, Ure B, Neugebauer E; European Association for Endoscopic Surgery. Evaluation of quality of life after laparoscopic surgery: evidence-based guidelines of the European Association for Endoscopic Surgery. Surg Endosc. 2004 Jun;18(6):879-97. Epub 2004 Apr 27. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>15108103</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Corrado G, Calagna G, Cutillo G, Insinga S, Mancini E, Baiocco E, Zampa A, Bufalo A, Perino A, Vizza E. The Patient and Observer Scar Assessment Scale to Evaluate the Cosmetic Outcomes of the Robotic Single-Site Hysterectomy in Endometrial Cancer. Int J Gynecol Cancer. 2018 Jan;28(1):194-199. doi: 10.1097/IGC.0000000000001130.</citation>
    <PMID>29040189</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yeung PP Jr, Bolden CR, Westreich D, Sobolewski C. Patient preferences of cosmesis for abdominal incisions in gynecologic surgery. J Minim Invasive Gynecol. 2013 Jan-Feb;20(1):79-84. doi: 10.1016/j.jmig.2012.09.008.</citation>
    <PMID>23312246</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 7, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 20, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 21, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 10, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 10, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 13, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Acibadem University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Esra Ozbasli</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Ass. Prof.</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Cosmesis</keyword>
  <keyword>Laparoscopic surgery</keyword>
  <keyword>Patient satisfaction</keyword>
  <keyword>Scar assessment</keyword>
  <keyword>Quality of life</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Genital Diseases, Female</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>It will be shared upon request.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

