<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04065256</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>N201905008</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04065256</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effects of Music Therapy on Reducing Delirium in Mechanically Ventilated Adults in Intensive Care Unit</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effects of Music Therapy on Reducing Delirium in Mechanically Ventilated Adults in Intensive Care Unit: a Randomized Controlled Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Taipei Medical University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Taipei Medical University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background: Delirium is a common acute confusion state in patients in intensive care units
      (ICUs). It has been linked to poor clinical prognoses (e.g., prolonged ICU stay) in critical
      patients. Furthermore, it might connect with long-term cognitive dysfunction. Mostly,
      pharmacological treatments have been frequently prescribed for preventing ICU delirium;
      however, their side effects might subsequently increase the risks of ICU delirium. Therefore,
      developing an effective non-pharmacological intervention of preventing delirium among
      critically mechanical ventilated patients is of clinical relevance. Purposes: To examine the
      effects of music intervention on reducing delirium in mechanically ventilated critical
      patients, to determine its beneficial effects on delirium-related outcomes, including
      sedation dosage and time, the duration of mechanical ventilation, and the length of ICU stay,
      and to compare the change of heart rate variability, electroencephalography and serum
      biomarkers after music therapy between groups.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Delirium is a common acute confusion state among critical patients in intensive care units
      (ICUs). The symptoms are serious disturbance in mental abilities which may cause inattention,
      confused thinking, agitated mood, and fluctuated consciousness. Delirium also lead to higher
      mortality, longer hospital stay, higher cost of healthcare and poor recovery. However, the
      mechanism of delirium still not fully understand. Imbalanced neurotransmitters may be one of
      the possible explain for such situation. It is related to increased level of dopamine and
      acetylcholine deficiency. In addition, the relation between low level of melatonin and
      postoperative delirium was also reported. Glucocorticoid which represent the stress response
      is also related to postoperative delirium. Both changes of neurotransmitters and hormone
      levels would affect sleep-awake cycle. It is observed that patients who is delirium show a
      relative higher EEG theta power and a reduced alpha power than non-delirious patients.
      Several modifiable risk factors, such as noise, light, physical restrain, pain, anxiety, and
      sedatives, may contribute to poor sleep quality or sleep disruption and further delirium
      occurrence. Effectiveness interventions are extremely important when patients are inevitably
      exposed to such risk factors.

      Pharmacological interventions are rapid and effective way for delirium management. However,
      the concern about side effect and increased mortality among high risk patients are needed.
      According to 2018 Clinical Practice Guidelines for the Prevention and Management of Pain,
      Agitation/Sedation, Delirium, Immobility, and Sleep Disruption in Adult Patients in the ICU,
      non-pharmacological intervention was suggested for delirium management firstly.
      Non-pharmacological interventions, such as using earplug or eye mask at night, music therapy
      or early mobilization, should be safe, less side effect and widely applicable for first-line
      healthcare providers. In addition, multicomponent interventions should be more effective than
      single component intervention. However, the evidence of direct comparison is limited.

      Music intervention is a non-invasive, low-cost and non-pharmacological intervention. Several
      clinical trials were proved that music therapy could reduce the pain and anxiety among
      postoperative and old age population for better clinical progress. Listening to soft music
      can enhance brain alpha wave, and there is a negative correlation between alpha wave of EEG
      and sympathetic excitation. The preference of music also influences power of alpha wave.
      Recent studies report that implying music intervention on postoperative patients could lead
      to fewer acute confusion status, however, the incidence and potential exposed risk factors of
      delirium between medical and surgical populations were different. The effect of music
      intervention on medical critical patients and the related mechanism still need further
      investigation. In addition, whether the multicomponent intervention could obtain greater
      effect than single component intervention still not ascertained. Furthermore, the evidences
      of music intervention in decreasing the duration of mechanical ventilation, length of ICU
      stay, sedation time and mortality were still lacking. The mechanism between music
      intervention and delirium occurrence also need to further investigate.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 5, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 31, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 31, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Care Provider, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Delirium incidence</measure>
    <time_frame>Date of study enrollment through 8th day, or date of discharge from ICU.</time_frame>
    <description>The number of patients who with delirium. The delirium event is assessed by Intensive Care Delirium Screening Checklist (ICDSC).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Sedation level</measure>
    <time_frame>Date of study enrollment through 8th day, or date of discharge from ICU.</time_frame>
    <description>Sedation level is assessed by Richmond Agitation-Sedation Scale (RASS). It is a ranking scale with 10-level (+4 &quot;combative&quot; to −5 &quot;unarousable&quot;) used to measure the agitation or sedation level of a person. RASS score will be reported.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pain score</measure>
    <time_frame>Date of study enrollment through 8th day, or date of discharge from ICU.</time_frame>
    <description>Pain score is assessed by Critical-Care Pain Observation Tool (CPOT). CPOT score will be reported.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Sleep quality</measure>
    <time_frame>Date of study enrollment through 8th day, or date of discharge from ICU.</time_frame>
    <description>Sleep parameters are measured by mini motionlogger actigraph. Sleep parameters will be reported.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline on heart rate variability (HRV)</measure>
    <time_frame>The date of enrollment, the 4th day, and the 8th day.</time_frame>
    <description>Heart rate variability is measured by portable ECG recorder and analyzer.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline on electroencephalography</measure>
    <time_frame>The date of enrollment, the 4th day, and the 8th day.</time_frame>
    <description>Electroencephalography is measured by Neurosky mindwave mobile 2</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline on serum cortisol over time</measure>
    <time_frame>The date of enrollment, the 4th day, and the 8th day.</time_frame>
    <description>Change in serum cortisol (pmol/L) from baseline</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline on serum Adrenocorticotropic Hormone(ACTH) over time</measure>
    <time_frame>The date of enrollment, the 4th day, and the 8th day.</time_frame>
    <description>Change in ACTH (pmol/L) from baseline</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline on serum melatonin over time</measure>
    <time_frame>The date of enrollment, the 4th day, and the 8th day.</time_frame>
    <description>Change in melatonin (pg/ml) from baseline</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline on serum C-reactive protein (CRP) over time</measure>
    <time_frame>The date of enrollment, the 4th day, and the 8th day.</time_frame>
    <description>Change in CRP(mg/dl) from baseline</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline on serum interleukin-6 over time</measure>
    <time_frame>The date of enrollment, the 4th day, and the 8th day.</time_frame>
    <description>Change in interleukin-6 (pg/ml) from baseline</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline on serum epinephrine over time</measure>
    <time_frame>The date of enrollment, the 4th day, and the 8th day.</time_frame>
    <description>Change in epinephrine (pmol/L) from baseline</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline on serum norepinephrine over time</measure>
    <time_frame>The date of enrollment, the 4th day, and the 8th day.</time_frame>
    <description>Change in norepinephrine (pmol/L) from baseline</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of mechanical ventilation</measure>
    <time_frame>Date of study enrollment through weaning from mechanical ventilation, or date of study enrollment up to 90 days.</time_frame>
    <description>The total days of mechanical ventilation.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Length of ICU stay</measure>
    <time_frame>Date of study enrollment through discharge from ICU, or date of study enrollment up to 90 days.</time_frame>
    <description>The total days of ICU stay.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Sedation time</measure>
    <time_frame>Date of study enrollment through discharge from ICU, or date of study enrollment up to 90 days.</time_frame>
    <description>The total days of sedation drug used.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mortality</measure>
    <time_frame>The time points of measurement are 30th and 90th days.</time_frame>
    <description>The number of death in a period of time.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">90</enrollment>
  <condition>Critical Illness</condition>
  <condition>Mechanical Ventilation</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Personalized music intervention group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will receive a personalized music session for forty minutes twice a day for consecutive seven days or until discharge from ICU. A total treatment dosage of 560 minutes is required.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Personalized music plus earplug group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will receive a personalized music session for forty minutes twice a day for consecutive seven days or until discharge from ICU. In addition, using earplug during night time sleep. The music intervention total treatment dosage of 560 minutes is required.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>The control group involves neither music intervention nor using earplug at night.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Personalized music</intervention_name>
    <description>Personalized music intervention will be conducted by research nurse independently. Firstly, the music preference will be confirmed by using predesigned music list. After confirming the music preference, participants will receive a music session for forty minutes through headphone and MP3 player.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Personalized music intervention group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Personalized music plus earplug</intervention_name>
    <description>Personalized music intervention will be conducted by research nurse independently. Firstly, the music preference will be confirmed by using predesigned music list. After confirming the music preference, participants will receive a music session for forty minutes through headphone and MP3 player. In addition, participants will be worn earplug during night time sleep for decreasing the noise until next morning.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Personalized music plus earplug group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Age from 20 to 85 years

          2. Expected to receive mechanical ventilation more than 24 hours

          3. Be able to communicate with others using verbal or non-verbal (such as paper and
             pencil) approaches when enrollment.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Dementia

          2. Psychiatric illness

          3. Suspected or confirmed drug or alcohol intoxication/overdose or withdrawal

          4. Severe or uncorrected hearing impairment

          5. Coma status after cardiac arrest or/and hypothermia treatment

          6. Deep sedation needed (RASS=-4~-5 or SAS=1~2)

          7. Expected death within 24h

          8. Delirium history during this admission

          9. Attending physician or healthcare team refusal
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>20 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>85 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Hsiao-Yean Chiu, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+886-2-27361661</phone>
    <phone_ext>6329</phone_ext>
    <email>hychiu0315@tmu.edu.tw</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Taipei Medical University-Shuang Ho Hospital, Ministry of Health and Welfare</name>
      <address>
        <city>Taipei</city>
        <zip>110</zip>
        <country>Taiwan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Hisao Yean Chiu, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>886227361661</phone>
      <phone_ext>6329</phone_ext>
      <email>hychiu0315@tmu.edu.tw</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Taiwan</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 16, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 20, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 22, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 22, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 22, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 24, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Taipei Medical University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Hsiao-Yean Chiu</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associated professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>music therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>intensive care unit</keyword>
  <keyword>delirium</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Delirium</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Critical Illness</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

