<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04060901</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IRB00112957</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04060901</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Compassion-Centered Spiritual Health for Faculty and Staff</brief_title>
  <official_title>Compassion-Centered Spiritual Health (CCSH) Interventions for Teams With Faculty and Staff</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Emory University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Emory University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Compassion-Centered Spiritual Health (CCSH) at Emory University was launched as a joint
      creation by Spiritual Health and the Center for Contemplative Science and Compassion-Based
      Ethics in 2018. The program enhances the practice of spiritual health through CCSH
      Interventions, which are a Cognitively-Based Compassion Training (CBCT)-based approach to
      support the practices of spiritual health clinicians. CBCT is a research-based contemplative
      program developed at Emory University in 2004. CCSH Interventions are provided by spiritual
      health clinicians across Emory's inpatient and outpatient facilities and beyond, and offer a
      method to alleviate distress in patients and families and to mitigate burnout in healthcare
      professionals. While the intervention will be required for some staff and provider
      populations, Spiritual Health proposes to pilot a voluntary systematic implementation of CCSH
      Interventions for Teams (CCSH-TI) to clinical research teams at Winship Cancer Institute.
      Clinical Research Coordinators (CRCs) experience significant emotional and spiritual burden
      through exposure to patients living with cancer and undergoing clinical trials for cancer
      treatment. As individuals and teams, CRCs face multiple work-related challenges known to
      cause distress, including experiences of secondary trauma, exposure to emotional and
      spiritual suffering of patients and families, and experiences of loss of patients. The
      researchers of this study hope that offering CCSH Interventions for Teams to CRCs will
      increase their resilience, wellbeing and compassion toward self and others, with a secondary
      benefit that burnout will be reduced. By conducting this pilot project, the researchers hope
      to gain a better understanding of how to optimally implement CCSH for CRC teams at the
      Winship Cancer Institute.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Previous research indicates that Cognitively-Based Compassion Training (CBCT) improves
      empathic accuracy, enhances well-being, and attenuates the pro-inflammatory response to
      psychosocial stress. CBCT is a secularized compassion meditation program adapted from the
      Tibetan Buddhist mind training (lojong) tradition, and it may be an ideal addendum to the
      spiritual caregiving provided by Emory University hospital chaplains and chaplain residents
      to approximately 100,000 patients, staff, and faculty members each year.

      With this in mind, The Emory University Spiritual Health department now incorporates CBCT
      into their training curriculum using a phased approach that began in Fall 2017. The Spiritual
      Health department also developed an adapted program based on CBCT principles that chaplains
      can then deliver to patients and staff, called Compassion-Centered Spiritual Health (CCSH).
      Spiritual Health proposes to pilot a systematic implementation of CCSH Interventions for
      Teams (CCSH-TI) to clinical research teams at the Winship Cancer Institute.

      This is a randomized trial of CCSH Interventions for Teams versus a wait list control
      condition. CRC teams will be randomized to receive CCSH-TI during a first cohort or to a
      wait-list group that will receive CCSH-TI during the second cohort. CRCs (n = 93) will be
      randomized by team to receive CCSH Interventions for Teams either in the fall or in the
      spring. Participating CRCs will complete self-report measures at 4 timepoints throughout the
      year: (1) Prior to randomization, (2) immediately upon completion of CCSH Interventions for
      Teams for cohort 1 (3) prior to CCSH Interventions for Teams for cohort 2, and (4)
      immediately upon completion of CCSH Interventions for Teams for cohort 2.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">August 23, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">February 7, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">February 7, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>CRC teams will be randomized to one of two cohorts; the first cohort will receive the intervention during the first period while the second cohort waits to receive the intervention during the second period.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Professional Quality of Life (ProQOL) Score</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Week 5, Week 24, Week 29</time_frame>
    <description>The Professional Quality of Life Scale (ProQOL) is a 30-item inventory and is the most commonly used measure of the negative and positive effects of helping others who experience suffering. It has sub-scales for compassion satisfaction, burnout, and compassion fatigue. The sub-scales are summed and converted to t-scores with a mean of 50 and standard deviation of 10. Scores higher than 57 indicate professional satisfaction while scores below 40 indicate possible problems with feeling satisfied professionally.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Staff Retention</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Week 29</time_frame>
    <description>Staff retention (number of employees not resigning) will be compared between the teams completing the intervention and those who have not yet participated.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Staff Absenteeism</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Week 29</time_frame>
    <description>Staff absenteeism (number of missed work days) will be compared between the teams completing the intervention and those who have not yet participated.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Depression Anxiety and Stress Scale (DASS) Short Form Score</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Week 5, Week 24, Week 29</time_frame>
    <description>The Depression Anxiety and Stress Scale (DASS) short form is a 21-item likert-scale measure that assesses the frequency of symptoms of depression, anxiety and stress during the past week. Respondents indicate the degree to which they agree with each statement on a scale of 0 to 3 where 0 = does not apply to me at all and 3 = applied to me very much, or most of the time. Total scores range from 0 to 63 and higher scores indicate increased feelings of depression, anxiety and stress.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Revised University of California, Los Angeles (UCLA) Loneliness Scale (R-UCLA) Score</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Week 5, Week 24, Week 29</time_frame>
    <description>The Revised UCLA Loneliness Scale (R-UCLA) is a 20-item questionnaire measuring general feelings of social isolation and dissatisfaction with one's social interactions. Participants rate each item on a scale from 1 (never) to 4 (often). When scoring the scale, certain items are reversed so that low scores correspond with low loneliness. Total scores range from 20 to 80, where higher scores indicate increased feelings of loneliness.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Patient-Reported Outcomes Measurement Information System (PROMIS) Sleep Disturbance Short Form Score</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Week 5, Week 24, Week 29</time_frame>
    <description>The PROMIS Sleep Disturbance Short Form is an 8-item scale assessing self-reported perceptions of sleep quality, sleep depth, and restoration associated with sleep. This includes perceived difficulties and concerns with getting to sleep or staying asleep, as well as perceptions of the adequacy of and satisfaction with sleep. Responses are given on a 5-point scale where 1 = no problems and 5 = very problematic. Total raw scores range from 8 to 40 where higher scores indicate greater sleep disturbances.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Connor-Davidson Resilience Scale 25 (CD-RISC-25) Score</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Week 5, Week 24, Week 29</time_frame>
    <description>The CD-RISC-25 is a 25-item inventory measuring resilience. Responses are on a 5-point scale where 0 = rarely true and 4 = true nearly all of the time. Total scores range from 0 to 100 and higher scores indicate greater resilience.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Nursing Incivility Scale (General, Nurse, and Patient subscales)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Week 5, Week 24, Week 29</time_frame>
    <description>The Workplace Incivility Scale is a 43-item instrument assessing perceived disrespect, condescension, or degradation in the healthcare environment. Responses are on a 5-point scale where 1 = strongly disagree and 5 = strongly agree. Total scores for the 3 subscales used here range from 0 to 116 and higher scores indicate greater perceived incivility in the workplace.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Interest in the CCSH Intervention Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline or Week 24</time_frame>
    <description>Prior to beginning the CCSH intervention, participants will complete a 6-item questionnaire assessing their interest in learning CBCT. Responses are given on a 7-point scale where 7-point scale where 0 = strongly disagree and 6 = strongly agree. Total scores range from 0 to 36 with higher scores indicating greater interest in the intervention. Participants in Cohort 1 will complete the questionnaire at the Baseline visit and participants in Cohort 2 will complete this questionnaire at the Week 24 visit (prior to beginning the second session of the intervention).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Experiences with the CCSH Intervention Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 5 or Week 29</time_frame>
    <description>Upon completion of the CCSH intervention the participant's experiences with the intervention will be assessed with a 7-item scale asking questions about how beneficial the intervention was. Responses are given on a 7-point scale where 0 = strongly disagree and 6 = strongly agree. Total scores range from 0 to 42 with higher scores indicating greater satisfaction with the intervention. Participants in Cohort 1 will complete the questionnaire at the Week 5 visit and participants in Cohort 2 will complete this questionnaire at the Week 29 visit.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">58</enrollment>
  <condition>Health Behavior</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>CCSH Interventions for Teams in Cohort 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants in the first cohort will receive the CCSH Interventions for Teams during the fall session (first intervention period).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>CCSH Interventions for Teams in Cohort 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants in the second cohort will receive the CCSH Interventions for Teams during the spring session (second intervention period).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>CCSH Intervention for Teams</intervention_name>
    <description>CCSH Interventions for Teams will be a six session intervention. The groups meet once per week for 60 minutes for 4 weeks, coupled with 2 booster sessions over the following 2 months. Participants will receive the CCSH interventional approach, adapted for a group setting, which follows four stages: 1) Preparing the care responder; 2) Attuning to the Relationship; 3) Accessing Compassion, and 4) Entrusting the Careseeker.
The CCSH approach will be used to assess group dynamics, individual member sources of distress, as well as existing resources for resilience and compassion. Through the intervention, resources will then be identified and accessed in order to respond to team (and individual) sources of distress with greater resilience and increased compassion toward self and others. CCSH clinicians will utilize group process skills to encourage team communication about work-related challenges, enhance team cohesion, and enable interpersonal support among members of the team.</description>
    <arm_group_label>CCSH Interventions for Teams in Cohort 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>CCSH Interventions for Teams in Cohort 2</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Emory staff, clinical research coordinators

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  None
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jennifer Mascaro, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Emory University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Emory University, Winship Cancer Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Atlanta</city>
        <state>Georgia</state>
        <zip>30322</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 16, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 16, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 19, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 12, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 12, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 14, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Emory University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Jennifer Mascaro</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Spiritual health clinician</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

