<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04067492</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CL04018054</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04067492</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Safety, Tolerability, Pharmacokinetics and Pharmacodynamics Evaluation of RPH-104 Administered at Different Doses to Patients With Acute Gout Attack</brief_title>
  <official_title>An Open-label, Single-dose, Active-controlled Randomized Phase IIa Clinical Study to Evaluate the Safety, Tolerability, Pharmacokinetics and Pharmacodynamics of RPH-104 (RPH-104/L04018) Administered at Different Doses to Patients With Acute Gout Attack</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>R-Pharm</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Covance</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>ZAO Unimed Laboratories</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Data Matrix Solutions</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>R-Pharm</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The primary goal of the study is to evaluate the parameters of efficacy, pharmacokinetics,
      pharmacodynamics, safety and tolerability of a single dose of RPH-104 in adult patients with
      acute gout attack.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The study will consist of two periods:

      Period 1. During Period 1 of the study, the patients who meet the eligibility criteria are
      enrolled to cohorts consisting of 22 patients and randomized to receive either RPH-104 4 mg
      or Voltaren® (diclofenac) in the 15:7 ratio (15 RPH-104: 7 Voltaren® (diclofenac)). In order
      to prevent damage to the gastric or duodenal mucosa, the patients receiving Voltaren®
      (diclofenac) will also be given Ortanol® (omeprazole) as a concomitant therapy agent.

      Period 2. Period 2 begins after 22 patients in period 1 have been enrolled. During Period 2,
      the enrolled patients are randomly distributed to one of five treatment groups: four groups
      to receive RPH-104 in different doses :20 mg, 40 mg, 80 mg and 160 mg and one active control
      group to receive Voltaren® (diclofenac). During Period 2, it is planned to enroll 14 patients
      into each of the RPH-104 -treatment groups and 7 patients into the Voltaren® (diclofenac)
      group.

      Subject enrolment during Periods 1 and 2 is successive. No intervals between enrolment of
      subjects in the dose cohorts are envisaged. Thus, the subjects in Period 2 will start to be
      enrolled immediately after the end of enrolment of the subjects in Period 1.

      Total number of patients which are planned to be enrolled for the study: 85 (15 patients in
      the group of treatment with RPH-104 4 mg and 14 patients in the each of the other treatment
      groups)

      For patients who cannot endure pain, a rescue therapy agent (Triamcinolone 40 mg) is
      administered intramuscularly 2 hours after the first dose of the test drug in order to
      enhance the treatment. If the disease attack relapses after using the rescue therapy,
      treatment of acute gout attack shall be conducted in accordance with routine practice adopted
      at the healthcare institution.

      The primary efficacy endpoints are evaluated 72 hours after the end of administration of the
      test drug. The secondary efficacy endpoints are evaluated for 45 days of the treatment period
      and follow-up. The safety parameters are evaluated for 60 days of the treatment period and
      follow-up. Total duration of the study for a volunteer is not more than 70 days.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 26, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 31, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 31, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in pain intensity in the assessed joint 72 hours after the initiation of treatment in comparison to baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 72 hours after the initiation of treatment with the test drug</time_frame>
    <description>Change in pain intensity in the assessed joint 72 hours after the initiation of treatment with the test drug measured using the Visual Analogue Scale (VAS) in comparison to baseline. VAS is a hard copy 100 mm scale with the indications:&quot;Absence of pain&quot; on the left side of the scale (0 mm point) and &quot;The most severe pain ever experienced&quot; on the right side of the scale (100 mm point)) The better outcome would be &quot;Absence of pain&quot;, the worse outcome would be &quot;The most severe pain ever experienced&quot;.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in pain intensity in the assessed joint in 15, 30, 45 minutes, 1, 1.5, 2, 4, 8, 24, 48, 72 hours, on Days 5, 6, 10, 15, 18, 22, 29 and 45 following the initiation of treatment and compared to baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 15, 30, 45 minutes, 1, 1.5, 2, 4, 8, 24, 48, 72 hours, on Days 5, 6, 10, 15, 18, 22, 29 and 45 after the initiation of treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Change in pain intensity in the assessed joint in 15, 30, 45 minutes, 1, 1.5, 2, 4, 8, 24, 48, 72 hours, on Days 5, 6, 10, 15, 18, 22, 29 and 45 following the initiation of treatment with the test drug measured using the Visual Analogue Scale (VAS) and compared to baseline</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of patients who assessed the response to therapy with the test drug as &quot;Excellent&quot; or &quot;Good&quot;</measure>
    <time_frame>15, 30, 45 minutes, 1, 1.5, 2, 4, 8, 24, 48, 72 hours, on Days 5, 6, 10, 15, 18, 22, 29 and 45 after the initiation of treatment with the test drug</time_frame>
    <description>Proportion of patients who assessed the response to therapy with the test drug as &quot;Excellent&quot; or &quot;Good&quot; in 15, 30, 45 minutes, 1, 1.5, 2, 4, 8, 24, 48, 72 hours, on Days 5, 6, 10, 15, 18, 22, 29 and 45 following the initiation of treatment with the test drug</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in the rate of swelling and erythema of the assessed joint evaluated after the initiation of treatment with the test drug</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 24, 48, 72 hours, on Days 5, 6, 10, 15, 18, 22, 29 and 45 following the initiation of treatment with the test drug</time_frame>
    <description>Change in the rate of swelling and erythema of the assessed joint evaluated in 24, 48, 72 hours, on Days 5, 6, 10, 15, 18, 22, 29 and 45 following the initiation of treatment with the test drug compared to baseline. For the assessment, the categorical scales consistent with the Form for evaluation (Investigator's Assessment) of the rate of edema, tenderness, erythema, restriction of movements will be used. The rates of swelling are specified in the evaluation form as &quot;no&quot;, &quot;mild&quot;, &quot;moderate&quot; and &quot;severe&quot;; the rates of &quot;erythema&quot; are specified as &quot;no&quot;, &quot;yes&quot;, &quot;impossible to evaluate&quot;.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in the rate of movement restrictions in the specified timeframes after initiation of treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and in 24, 48, 72 hours, on Days 5, 6, 10, 15, 18, 22, 29 and 45 following the initiation of treatment with the test drug</time_frame>
    <description>Change in the rate of movement restrictions in the assessed joint evaluated in 24, 48, 72 hours, on Days 5, 6, 10, 15, 18, 22, 29 and 45 following the initiation of treatment with the test drug compared to baseline. For the assessment, the categorical scales consistent with the Form for evaluation (Investigator's Assessment) of the rate of edema, tenderness, erythema, restriction of movements will be used. The rates of movement restrictions (amplitide of movements) are specified in the evaluation form as &quot;Normal amplitude&quot;, &quot; slightly restricted amplitude&quot;, &quot; moderately restricted amplitude&quot; ,&quot;severely restricted amplitude&quot; and &quot;movements in the joints are impossible &quot;.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to achieve the 50% decrease in pain intensity in the assessed joint relative to the baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and one of the pain intensity measurements in accordance with the schedule: 15, 30, 45 minutes, 1, 1.5, 2, 4, 8, 24, 48, 72 hours, on Days 5, 6, 10, 15, 18, 22, 29 and 45 after the initiation of treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Time to achieve the 50% decrease in pain intensity in the assessed joint relative to the baseline VAS level</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of patients who received a rescue therapy agent</measure>
    <time_frame>72 hours prior to the initiation of treatment with the test drug and during the entire course of treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Proportion of patients who received a rescue therapy agent within 72 hours prior to the initiation of treatment with the test drug and during the entire course of treatment</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in the Health Assessment Questionnaire (HAQ) parameters within the specified timeframes after the start of the treatment with the test drug</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 15, 29 and 45 days following the initiation of treatment with the test drug</time_frame>
    <description>Changes in the Health Assessment Questionnaire (HAQ) parameters in 15, 29 and 45 days following the initiation of treatment with the test drug as compared to baseline. HAQ is a hard copy Questionnaire to be completed by patient in order to discover how partient's illness affects his/her ability to function in daily life. The better outcome would be &quot;Without any difficulty&quot;, the worse outcome would be &quot;Unable to do&quot;.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetics (PK) - area under the plasma concentration-of RPH-104 under the subcutaneous administration</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and in 2,8,24,48,72 hours,on Days 5,6,10,15,18,22,29,45 following the initiation of treatment with the test drug and on the follow-up visit (in case of premature withdrawal of patient)</time_frame>
    <description>Including area under the plasma concentration-time curve over the dosing interval (AUC0-tau)</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetics (PK) - Area under the active substance concentration- of RPH-104 under the subcutaneous administration</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and in 2,8,24,48,72 hours,on Days 5,6,10,15,18,22,29,45 following the initiation of treatment with the test drug and on the follow-up visit (in case of premature withdrawal of patient)</time_frame>
    <description>Including Area under the active substance concentration-time curve from zero (before drug administration) to infinity (AUC0-∞)</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetics (PK) - Maximum concentration of the active substance -of RPH-104 under the subcutaneous administration</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and in 2,8,24,48,72 hours,on Days 5,6,10,15,18,22,29,45 following the initiation of treatment with the test drug and on the follow-up visit (in case of premature withdrawal of patient)</time_frame>
    <description>Including Maximum concentration of the active substance (Cmax)</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetics (PK) of RPH-104 under the subcutaneous administration</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and in 2,8,24,48,72 hours,on Days 5,6,10,15,18,22,29,45 following the initiation of treatment with the test drug and on the follow-up visit (in case of premature withdrawal of patient)</time_frame>
    <description>Including elimination constant (Kel)</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetics (PK) -Time to reach maximum concentration of the active substance - of RPH-104 under the subcutaneous administration</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and in 2,8,24,48,72 hours,on Days 5,6,10,15,18,22,29,45 following the initiation of treatment with the test drug and on the follow-up visit (in case of premature withdrawal of patient)</time_frame>
    <description>Including Time to reach maximum concentration of the active substance (tmax)</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetics (PK) - terminal half-life -of RPH-104 under the subcutaneous administration</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and in 2,8,24,48,72 hours,on Days 5,6,10,15,18,22,29,45 following the initiation of treatment with the test drug and on the follow-up visit (in case of premature withdrawal of patient)</time_frame>
    <description>Including terminal half-life (T 1/2)</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Change in the serum rate of high-sensitive CRP (hs-CRP) in specified timeframes</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and in 24, 72 hours, on Days 5, 6, 15, 29 and 45 after the initiation of treatment with the test drug</time_frame>
    <description>Change in the serum rate of high-sensitive CRP (hs-CRP) in 24, 72 hours, on Days 5, 6, 15, 29 and 45 following the initiation of treatment with the test drug compared to baseline</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Change in the rate of serum amyloid protein A in the specified timeframes</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and in 24, 72 hours and on Day 5, 6, 15, 29 and 45 following the initiation of treatment with the test drug</time_frame>
    <description>Change in the rate of serum amyloid protein A in 24, 72 hours and on Day 5, 6, 15, 29 and 45 following the initiation of treatment with the test drug as compared to baseline</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Change in the serum rates of cytokines (IL-1α, IL-1β, Interleukin -1 Receptor Antagonist (IL-1RA), IL-6, IL-8, Tumor Necrosis Factor (TNF-α))</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and in 24, 72 hours and on Days 5, 6, 15, 29 and 45 following the initiation of treatment with the test drug</time_frame>
    <description>Change in the serum rates of cytokines (IL-1α, IL-1β, IL-1RA, IL-6, IL-8, TNF-α) in 24, 72 hours and on Days 5, 6, 15, 29 and 45 following the initiation of treatment with the test drug as compared to baseline</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Immunogenicity evaluation of blood samples</measure>
    <time_frame>before administration of RPH-104, on Day 15 and Day 45</time_frame>
    <description>Concentrations of anti-RPH-104 antibodies, including neutralizing antibodies, will be assessed before administration of RPH-104, on Day 15 and Day 45</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>6</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">85</enrollment>
  <condition>Gout Attack</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>RPH - 4 mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects randomized to receive RPH-104, 4 mg, subcutaneous single-dose injection. In order to administer RPH-104 at the dose of 4 mg, 0.1 mL of RPH-104 solution is injected.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>RPH - 20 mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects randomized to receive RPH-104, 20 mg, subcutaneous single-dose injection. In order to administer RPH-104 at the dose of 20 mg, 0.5 mL of RPH-104 solution is injected.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>RPH - 40 mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects randomized to receive RPH-104, 40 mg, subcutaneous single-dose injection. In order to administer RPH-104 at the dose of 40 mg, 1 mL of RPH-104 solution is injected.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>RPH - 80 mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects randomized to receive RPH-104, 80 mg, subcutaneous single-dose injection. In order to administer RPH-104 at the dose of 80 mg, 2 mL (whole vial) of RPH-104 solution is injected.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>RPH - 160 mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects randomized to receive RPH-104, 160 mg, two subcutaneous injections of 80 mg administered at different injection sites. (1 vial of 2mL solution per each site)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Voltaren® (diclofenac)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects randomized to receive Voltaren® (diclofenac) orally with water at the dose 50 mg thrice daily for 3 days (150 mg total daily dose), then 25 mg thrice daily for 9 days (75 mg total daily dose)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>RPH - 104</intervention_name>
    <description>solution for subcutaneous administration 40 mg/mL, 2 mL in the 4-mL glass vial</description>
    <arm_group_label>RPH - 160 mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>RPH - 20 mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>RPH - 4 mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>RPH - 40 mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>RPH - 80 mg</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Voltaren®</intervention_name>
    <description>Enteric-coated tablets, 25 mg and 50 mg</description>
    <arm_group_label>Voltaren® (diclofenac)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Diclofenac</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  1. The subject has given his / her informed consent to participate in this study; the
             Informed Consent Form has been signed both by the patient and the Investigator;

          -  2. Established diagnosis of gout according to Gout Classification Criteria established
             by the American College of Rheumatology (ACR) and European League against Rheumatism
             (EULAR) in 2015;

          -  3. Pain in at least one joint at the screening and immediately prior to initiation of
             therapy with the study drugs, with intensity 50 mm to 100 mm according to the Visual
             Analogue Scale (VAS);

          -  4. Development of acute gout attack within 120 hours (5 days) prior to the
             randomization date;

          -  5. History of 1 or more acute gout attacks prior to the Screening Visit;

          -  6.The patients receiving uric acid-lowering drugs should continue receiving these
             drugs at a constant dose for at least 4 weeks prior to enrolment to the study and
             throughout the entire study period; the patients not receiving uric acid-lowering
             drugs may start receiving this treatment after the end of the study;

          -  7. Body mass index ≤40 kg/m2;

          -  8. QTcF interval ≤450 msec for male subjects and ≤470 msec for females on ECG at the
             screening;

          -  9. For women of child-bearing potential: negative result of the serum pregnancy test
             performed at the screening;

          -  10. The consent of a woman of child-bearing potential, as well as of a man who has
             female partners of child-bearing potential, to abstain from sexual intercourses or to
             use effective birth control methods throughout the entire study period and for 60 days
             after RPH-104 administration (if RPH-104 is administered);

          -  11. The patient is able to fulfil the requirements of the Study Protocol as judged by
             the Investigator

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  1. The patient received therapy with ibuprofen in a dose of up to 400 mg inclusive
             within 4 hours or &gt;400 mg within 8 hours prior to randomization.

          -  2. The patient received therapy with diclofenac in a dose of up to 50 mg inclusive
             within 8 hours or &gt;50 mg within 24 hours prior to randomization.

          -  3. The patient received any other non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drug (NSAID) within
             24 hours prior to the randomization;

          -  4.The patient received opioids within 48 hours prior to the randomization;

          -  5. The patient received metamizole or metamizole-containing drugs within 12 hours
             prior to the randomization;

          -  6. The patient received any drug with analgesic activity (including paracetamol)
             within 6 hours prior to the randomization;

          -  7. The patient received a long-acting NSAID (half-life ≥24 hours) within 5 half-life
             periods or 1 month prior to the randomization whichever is longer;

          -  8. The patient received naproxen, meloxicam, nabumetone, celecoxib, etoricoxib or
             extended-release indomethacin within 5 days prior to the randomization;

          -  9 . The patient received corticosteroids (including their intra-articular
             administration and inhalations) within 4 weeks prior to the randomization;

          -  10. The patient received colchicine within 7 days prior to the randomization;

          -  11. Intolerance or contraindications for NSAID use;

          -  12. Contraindications for the use of Ortanol® capsules 20 mg;

          -  13. Chronic heart failure functional class II-IV (classification of NYHA);

          -  14. History of clinically significant ventricular arrhythmias or clinically
             significant atrial tachy-arrhythmias or presence of these arrhythmias at the moment of
             evaluation;

          -  15. Unstable angina or stable exercise-induced angina of functional class III or IV;

          -  16. Secondary gout, chemotherapy-induced gout, lead- or transplantation-induced gout;

          -  17. Rheumatoid arthritis, confirmed or suspected infectious septic arthritis or any
             other type of acute inflammatory arthritis;

          -  18. Clinically significant renal impairment determined based on creatinine clearance
             (estimated using the Cockcroft-Gault equation) &lt;60 mL/min, or patients on
             hemodialysis;

          -  19. Blood coagulation disorders; history of gastrointestinal bleedings or perforation;

          -  20. Pregnant or nursing women;

          -  21. Scheduled surgical treatment or performed major surgical procedure (minor surgical
             procedures, such as catheter placement are not considered non-inclusion criteria)
             within 14 days prior to the first dose of the test drug;

          -  22. Current or suspected HIV-infection, HBsAg, Hepatitis C Virus antibodies (HCVAb),
             other acute or chronic bacterial, fungal or viral infections at the moment of
             subject's enrolment to the study;

          -  23. Presence of any risk factors for tuberculosis based on the results of assessment
             using Tuberculosis Risk Assessment Questionnaire at the screening or confirmed
             tuberculosis or any other infectious disease of the lungs or bronchi based on findings
             of the chest X-ray exam in two views performed within 3 months prior to the screening
             visit, or the need for using therapy with tuberculosis medications, such as isoniazid
             in the course of the study;

          -  24. Neutropenia, leukopenia, or thrombocytopenia determined based on the following
             laboratory parameters assessed during the screening:

               1. Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) &lt;1.5 x 10^9/L;

               2. White blood cell count &lt;4.0 х 10^9/L

               3. Platelet count &lt;150 х 10^9/L;

          -  25. Immunization with live vaccines within 3 months prior to the subject's enrolment
             to the study or planned vaccination within 60 days after the expected date of the
             first dose of the test drug;

          -  26. History of allergic reactions to biologicals, Voltaren® (diclofenac) or Ortanol®
             (omeprazole);

          -  27. Contraindications for subcutaneous, intramuscular, intravenous or intra-articular
             injections;

          -  28. History of malignancy (except for patients with localized in situ basal cell
             carcinoma of the skin or in situ cervical cancer, who can be enrolled to the study
             immediately after the therapy for this disease), unless it is in remission for ≥5
             years, as well as patients who are being examined for cancer or patients with
             suspected malignancy;

          -  29. A condition or disease, which, in the Investigator's opinion, could put the
             patient's safety at risk or affect the test drug safety assessment;

          -  30. Any other conditions and diseases, such as uncontrolled diabetes mellitus,
             uncontrolled hypertension, congestive heart failure, exacerbation of peptic ulcer
             disease, clinically significant liver diseases, kidney diseases, uncontrolled thyroid
             dysfunction, unhealed wounds, ulcers or bone fractures, psychiatric disorders,
             uncontrolled epilepsy, drug dependence, which could prevent the patient from complying
             with the requirements of this Study Protocol.

          -  31. The patient received biologicals or investigational medicinal products within 5
             half-life periods of these drugs or 3 month prior to the randomization whichever is
             longer;

          -  32. Blood donation or blood loss of ≥400 mL within 8 weeks prior to the randomization.

          -  33. The patient has already been randomized in this clinical study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mikhail Samsonov</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>R-Pharm</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Moscow City State Healthcare Institution &quot;O.M. Filatov Municipal Clinical Hospital No. 15&quot; of the Moscow Department of Healthcare</name>
      <address>
        <city>Moscow</city>
        <zip>111539</zip>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ivan G. Gordeev</last_name>
      <phone>+7 (495) 918 72 84</phone>
      <email>cardio-15@yandex.ru</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ivan G. Gordeev</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>State Budgetary Healthcare Institution of Moscow City &quot;Municipal Clinical Hospital No.1 named after N.I. Pirogov&quot; of Moscow Department of Healthcare</name>
      <address>
        <city>Moscow</city>
        <zip>119049</zip>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Evgeniya I. Shmidt</last_name>
      <phone>+7 (495) 536 92 33</phone>
      <email>jenny.smidt@gmail.ru</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Evgeniya I. Shmidt</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Federal State Autonomous Educational Institution of Higher Education &quot;I.M. Sechenov First Moscow State Medical University of the Ministry of Health of the Russian Federation (Sechenov University)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Moscow</city>
        <zip>119991</zip>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Suspended</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>State Budgetary Healthcare Institution of Moscow City &quot;Municipal Clinical Hospital No.52&quot; of Moscow Department of Healthcare</name>
      <address>
        <city>Moscow</city>
        <zip>123182</zip>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Natalia G. Poteshkina</last_name>
      <phone>+7 (910) 442 22 16</phone>
      <email>podagra2019@mail.ru</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Natalia G. Poteshkina</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>State Budgetary Institution of Healthcare of Nizhny Novgorod region &quot;City Clinical hospital #13 of Avozavodskiy district&quot;</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nizhny Novgorod</city>
        <zip>603018</zip>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Galina V. Shestakova</last_name>
      <phone>+7 (831) 255 67 71</phone>
      <email>gvshestakova@yandex.ru</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Galina V. Shestakova</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Federal State Budgetary Education Institution of Higher Education &quot;Orenburg State Medical University&quot; under Ministry of Healthcare of Russian Federation</name>
      <address>
        <city>Orenburg</city>
        <zip>460000</zip>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Oga V. Bugrova</last_name>
      <phone>+7(3532) 76 58 42</phone>
      <email>ov.bugrova@yandex.ru</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Olga V. Bugrova</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>St. Petersburg State Budgetary Healthcare Institution &quot;Clinical Rheumatological Hospital No.25&quot;</name>
      <address>
        <city>Saint Petersburg</city>
        <zip>190068</zip>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Marianna S. Petrova</last_name>
      <phone>+7 (812) 310 99 24</phone>
      <email>podagra@bk.ru</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Marianna S. Petrova</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>State Budget Institution &quot;Saint Petersburg Research Insitute of emergency care named after I.I. Dzhanelidze</name>
      <address>
        <city>Saint Petersburg</city>
        <zip>192242</zip>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Anton S. Povzun</last_name>
      <phone>+7(812) 709 61 57</phone>
      <email>a.s.povzun@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Anton S. Povzun</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Limited Liability company &quot;Scientific Research Center Eco-safety&quot;</name>
      <address>
        <city>Saint Petersburg</city>
        <zip>196143</zip>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Konstantin A. Zakharov</last_name>
      <phone>+7(812) 500 52 03</phone>
      <email>letuchih_as@ecosafety.ru</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Konstantin A. Zakharov</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>State Insitution of healthcare &quot;Tula regional clinical dermatovenerologic dispensary&quot;</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tula</city>
        <zip>300053</zip>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Valentina N. Sorotskaya</last_name>
      <phone>+7(4872) 48 66 21</phone>
      <email>svnreum1@rambler.ru</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Valentina N. Sorotskaya</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>State Autonomous Healthcare Institution of the Yaroslavl Region &quot;N.V. Solovyev Clinical Emergency Hospital&quot;</name>
      <address>
        <city>Yaroslavl</city>
        <zip>150003</zip>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Olga B. Ershova</last_name>
      <phone>+7 (4852) 73 71 03</phone>
      <email>yarosteoporosis@list.ru</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Olga B. Ershova</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Russian Federation</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>August 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 5, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 22, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 26, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 22, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 22, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">August 26, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>hyperuricemia</keyword>
  <keyword>acute arthritis</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Gout</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Arthritis, Gouty</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Diclofenac</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

