<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04061018</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>STU 042016-020</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>1R01HL136724-01A1</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04061018</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Genetic, Protein, and Lipid Basis of Variation in Cholesterol Efflux</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Genetic, Protein, and Lipid Basis of Variation in Cholesterol Efflux</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Texas Southwestern Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Texas Southwestern Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The rationale of this research is that deep phenotyping of individuals at the extremes of
      cholesterol efflux will identify key determinants of efflux that are potential novel
      therapeutic targets to prevent or reverse Atherosclerotic Cardiovascular Disease (ASCVD). The
      investigators propose to carry out the objective by studying participants at extreme low and
      high cholesterol efflux identified from the investigator's study in the population-based
      Dallas Heart Study by accomplishing the following aims: 1) determine the heritability of and
      genomic factors associated with cholesterol efflux by establishing a family pedigree of
      extreme low and high efflux and sequencing candidate genes involved in HDL metabolism; and 2)
      identify the protein and lipid signature of extreme low and high cholesterol efflux in a sex-
      and ethnicity-specific manner using mass spectroscopy and ELISA in FPLC-derived fractions.
      The investigators expect to identify genetic variants and sex- and ethnicity-specific
      combinations of proteins and lipids in participants with extreme low and high efflux that may
      lead to novel ways to modulate efflux. This proposal leverages a well-phenotyped
      population-based study to characterize the gene-protein-lipid signature of 1) extremes of
      cholesterol efflux in a sex- and ethnicity-specific manner. Successful completion of these
      aims will have immediate and direct impact on the use of cholesterol efflux as a clinically
      relevant biomarker of therapeutic benefit and are necessary for the clinical development of
      appropriate new targets for manipulation of the key atheroprotective function of cholesterol
      efflux to reduce ASCVD.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The mechanisms that underlie variation in cholesterol efflux are unknown. There is a critical
      need to identify factors that regulate cholesterol efflux to effectively advance the clinical
      development of cholesterol efflux as both a risk prediction marker and as a target of
      therapy. The investigator's long-term goal is to determine whether modulating cholesterol
      efflux prevents or reverses cardiovascular disease. The overall objective of this study is to
      systematically create a family pedigree and biobank repository of blood and DNA from
      participants from the Dallas Heart Study with extreme low or high cholesterol efflux, with
      the specific aims of : 1) determining the heritability of and genomic factors associated with
      cholesterol efflux, and 2) identifying the protein and lipid signature of extreme low and
      high cholesterol efflux in a sex- and ethnicity-specific manner. The investigator's central
      hypothesis is that a combination of genetic variation in lipid transporters as well as
      proteins and lipids will be most strongly correlated with variation in efflux.

      DHS probands and their relatives (parents, siblings, adult children, grandparents,
      aunts/uncles, cousins) with extreme low or high cholesterol efflux will be recruited to
      establish a prospective family pedigree cohort and understand the heritability of extreme
      cholesterol efflux. Investigators will collect the following information from all
      participants: demographics, health history, lifestyle measures, and medications. Blood will
      be collected on-site by venipuncture and plasma, serum, and cells will be stored at -80o
      Celsius. All efflux measurements will be completed in the investigator's laboratory.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Suspended</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    The study is temporarily suspended due to covid-19 policy.
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date type="Actual">December 1, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Cross-Sectional</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Contribution of genetic factors to variability in cholesterol efflux</measure>
    <time_frame>Anticipated completion date - November 2022</time_frame>
    <description>The expected outcome is establishing the degree of heritability of the extreme low or high cholesterol efflux phenotype, specific for sex and ethnicity and the contribution of common and rare genetic variants to cholesterol efflux. This will establish for the first time to what degree inherited verses environmental factors associate with variation in cholesterol efflux.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Circulating metabolites and proteins linked to variation cholesterol efflux</measure>
    <time_frame>Anticipated completion date - November 2022</time_frame>
    <description>The investigators will measure circulating metabolites and proteins and identify the most relevant to the high/low cholesterol efflux phenotype, offering the potential to focus future studies targeting metabolic regulators of efflux.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">180</enrollment>
  <condition>Lipid Metabolism Disorders</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>High Cholesterol Efflux</arm_group_label>
    <description>Dallas Heart Study participants who are above the sex and ethnicity specific 90th % of cholesterol efflux</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Low Cholesterol Efflux</arm_group_label>
    <description>Dallas Heart Study participants who are below the sex and ethnicity specific 10th % of cholesterol efflux</description>
  </arm_group>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Plasma, Serum, DNA
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Participants from the Dallas Heart Study (DHS) with extreme low or high cholesterol efflux
        will be recruited in this study. DHS is a multi-ethnic, population based probability sample
        of Dallas County designed to define the social and the biological variables contributing to
        ethnic differences in cardiovascular health at the community level.

        https://www.utsouthwestern.edu/edumedia/edufiles/research/center_translational_medicine/dal
        las_heart_study/dhs-study-overview.pdf
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Dallas Heart Study (DHS) Participants who are above or below the sex- and
             ethnicity-specific 10th and 90th% of cholesterol efflux.

          -  Family members of the DHS participants are also eligible

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  HIV

          -  Cancer

          -  Autoimmune diseases

          -  Pregnancy
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>89 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Anand Rohatgi, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>UT Southwetsern Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UT Southwestern Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dallas</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>75390</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 26, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 14, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 19, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 12, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 12, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 14, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>HDL</keyword>
  <keyword>Atherosclerotic Cardiovascular Disease</keyword>
  <keyword>Cholesterol efflux</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Metabolic Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lipid Metabolism Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

