<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04063566</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>123874</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04063566</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>ReIMAGINE Prostate Cancer Screening</brief_title>
  <official_title>ReIMAGINE Prostate Cancer Screening - Inviting Men for Prostate Cancer Screening Using MRI</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University College, London</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Medical Research Council</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Cancer Research UK</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Imperial College London</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>King's College London</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University College, London</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Single site study to assess the feasibility of prostate cancer screening using an invitation
      for a prostate MRI scan via GP practices. This feasibility study will assess the
      acceptability of an MRI as a prostate cancer screening assessment and assess the prevalence
      of MRI defined suspicious lesions and cancer in men across a spectrum of PSA results.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      ReIMAGINE Prostate cancer screening is a single site screening study to assess the
      feasibility of MRI as a screening tool for prostate care and determine the prevalence of MRI
      defined suspicious lesions and cancer in men across a spectrum of PSA results.

      Men with no previous prostate cancer diagnosis, but deemed suitable based on age will be
      identified through general practitioner (GP) practices who will act as participant
      identification centres (PIC's). Potential participants will be identified through screening
      of existing patient databases at multiple London GP surgeries participating in the study, and
      randomly selected for invitation. The ReIMAGINE study team will link with London cancer
      networks and Noclor research support (https://www.noclor.nhs.uk/) who will make first contact
      with potentially eligible men.

      A personalised invitation letter from each man's own GP will be sent to him. Invitation
      letters will be sent in batches so to limit the time between the invitation and their study
      visit. Batched invitations will be prepared using an iterative process so to allow the study
      team to assess uptake rates and limit the gap between invitation and study visits.

      Invitation letters will include contact details for the ReIMAGINE study team who will
      coordinate bookings for research visits for all responders.

      All consented men will have a blood test for PSA and a screening MRI scan. This will take a
      maximum of 20 minutes, and will include T2, diffusion and research specific sequences.

      Two radiologists will report the MRI blinded to the PSA result, with a third reviewer when
      there is disagreement between reporters. Men in whom a suspicious lesion is seen (MRI screen
      positive) or who have a suspicious PSA density (&gt;0.12ng/ml) will be recommended to have an
      National Health Service (NHS) referral for suspected prostate cancer as per National
      Institute for Health and Care Excellence (NICE) guidelines.

      Screen negative men will at this point exit the study. Screen positive men will be followed
      up to gather data from any investigations (mpMRI +/- prostate biopsy) that may occur as a
      result of the NHS referral. No formal visits will be required to collect this data.
      Participant consent will be sought to approach GP or other secondary care centre.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">September 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 31, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 31, 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Single site screening study to assess the feasibility of MRI as a screening tool for prostate care and determine the prevalence of MRI defined suspicious lesions and cancer in men across a spectrum of PSA results.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Screening</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The acceptance rate of an invitation for a screening prostate MRI in men who have not had a prostate cancer diagnosis</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Proportion of men who accept the invitation for prostate screening</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The prevalence of MRI defined suspicious lesions in men accepting a screening invitation</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>The prevalence of MRI defined suspicious lesions in men accepting a screening invitation</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Presence of cancer in men who have biopsy as a result of their MRI findings</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>The prevalence of men being diagnosed with prostate cancer who have biopsy as a result of their MRI findings</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The proportion of men ineligible due to prior prostate cancer diagnosis</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>The proportion of men ineligible due to prior prostate cancer diagnosis</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The proportion of men who screen negative on MRI</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>The proportion of men who screen negative on MRI</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The proportion of men who screen negative on PSA density</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>The proportion of men who screen negative on PSA density</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The proportion of men who screen positive on MRI alone</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>The proportion of men who screen positive on MRI alone</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The proportion of men who screen positive on PSA density alone</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>The proportion of men who screen positive on PSA density alone</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">300</enrollment>
  <condition>Prostate Cancer Screening</condition>
  <condition>Prostate Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Total cohort</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>The study will consist of one group, one arm, all receiving the same screening procedures.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Magnetic Resonance Imaging (MRI)</intervention_name>
    <description>Prostate cancer screening MRI</description>
    <arm_group_label>Total cohort</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Prostate-specific antigen (PSA) test</intervention_name>
    <description>Blood test for PSA levels</description>
    <arm_group_label>Total cohort</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Men aged 50-75

          2. No prior prostate cancer diagnosis / treatment

          3. Willing and able to provide written informed consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Contraindication for MRI scanning (as assessed by the MRI safety questionnaire of the
             PET/MRI department) which includes but is not limited to: Intracranial aneurysm clips
             or other metallic objects; Intra-orbital metal fragments that have not been removed;
             Pacemakers or other implanted cardiac rhythm management devices and non-MRI compatible
             heart valves; Inner ear implants; and History of claustrophobia

          2. Men who require assisted living e.g. care home living

          3. Dementia or other neurological condition meaning participant lacks the capacity to
             consent.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>50 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Caroline Moore, FRCS</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>univeristy college london</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Neil McCartan, MSc</last_name>
    <phone>+44 (0)20 7679 9280</phone>
    <phone_ext>09280</phone_ext>
    <email>situ.reimagine@ucl.ac.uk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <verification_date>August 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 15, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 20, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 21, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 20, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 20, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">August 21, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Prostate Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>MRI</keyword>
  <keyword>PSA</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Prostatic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

