<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04064892</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>181367</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04064892</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Physical Activity Intervention for Young Cancer Survivors</brief_title>
  <official_title>Physical Activity Interventions for Young Cancer Survivors</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of California, San Diego</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Haus of Volta</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of California, San Diego</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The proposed mixed methods pilot study will enroll 20 young breast cancer survivors into a
      12-week technology-based, remotely-delivered, peer-moderated physical activity program to
      examine the effects of the intervention on objectively measured physical activity and
      multiple aspects of quality of life; and conduct qualitative analyses to refine the
      intervention for a future randomized controlled trial.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Young breast cancer survivors (i.e. those &lt; 50 years old) have lower survival rates than
      their older counterparts and experience unique physical and mental challenges associated with
      their cancer treatments. Depression, anxiety, and poor body image are common in young breast
      cancer survivors. Research in older breast cancer survivors has shown that physical activity
      can decrease cancer recurrence and mortality, and improve many aspects of quality of life.
      Few physical activity intervention studies have been conducted in young breast cancer
      survivors, despite the fact that young survivors would be best served by age-specific
      interventions designed to target their needs. Remotely-delivered, technology-based
      interventions may be important to help young breast cancer survivors overcome unique barriers
      to increasing physical activity and improving quality of life.

      The study aims are: 1) Explore the feasibility and acceptability of a technology-based,
      remotely-delivered, peer-moderated physical activity intervention for young breast cancer
      survivors; 2a) Assess the invention's impact on change in physical activity; and 2b) Measure
      the intervention's effect on multiple aspects of quality of life
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Physical Activity</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The ActiGraph GT3X+ accelerometer will be used to measure change in minutes of moderate to vigorous physical activity from baseline to 12 weeks. For 7 days around each assessment time point, participants will wear the accelerometer.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Body Image Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The Body Image Scale will be used to measure changes in perceptions of body image from baseline to 12 weeks. Scores range from 0 to 30. A higher score indicates more distress.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Female Sexual Function Index</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The Female Sexual Function Index will be used to measure change in self-reported sexual functioning from baseline to 12 weeks. Scores range from 2 to 36. A higher score indicates fewer problems with sexual functioning.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PROMIS Cancer - Fatigue</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Change in fatigue from baseline to 12 weeks will be assessed via a Patient-Reported Outcome Measurement Information System (PROMIS) computer adaptive test (CAT), PROMIS Cancer- Fatigue. CAT items are dynamically selected for administration from an item bank based upon the respondent's previous answers. Participants will complete 4-12 items. This measure yields a T-Score with a mean of 50 and a standard deviation of 10. Higher scores indicate higher levels of fatigue.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Breast Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Quality of Life</condition>
  <condition>Physical Activity</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Exercise Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will receive a 12-week, individually-tailored, video conference-based physical activity intervention</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Exercise Intervention</intervention_name>
    <description>The intervention will use peer mentors, motivational interviewing, and technology (Fitbit, Fitbit Coach App, &amp; Fitbit message board) to support behavior change. All participants will receive phone or video calls from their peer mentors every other week, and interact with their peer mentor and other participants through a private Fitbit message board at least weekly. Peer mentors will use Fitbit data to identify participants who need additional support to increase their activity.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Exercise Intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Diagnosed with breast cancer between 18-49 years old

          -  Completed active treatment (chemotherapy, radiation) at least 6 months prior to
             enrollment

          -  Self-report low levels of moderate to vigorous physical activity each week

          -  Accessible by phone or video chat

          -  Have a Fitbit compatible cellphone, tablet, or laptop with Internet

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  medical condition that could make it potentially unsafe to be in an unsupervised
             physical activity intervention

          -  currently pregnant

          -  unable to commit to intervention schedule

          -  prisoner
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>55 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of California, San Diego</name>
      <address>
        <city>La Jolla</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>92093</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 19, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 19, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 22, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 5, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 5, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 6, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of California, San Diego</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Sheri Hartman</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

