<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04065568</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>DISKO/STRADA</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04065568</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>An Interactive Distance Solution for Stroke Rehabilitation in the Home Setting</brief_title>
  <official_title>An Interactive Distance Solution for Stroke Rehabilitation in the Home Setting</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Danderyd Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Karolinska Institutet</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Danderyd Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Equal access to evidence based rehabilitation in the stroke population is a challenge. Home
      based solutions including telerehabilitation is a promising strategy to meet these needs.
      However, the tools must be customized for persons with stroke and the technologies developed
      to serve rehabilitation purposes. The DISKO-tool was developed to enable efficient,
      continuous training in the home setting with health professional follow ups of training and
      training results after stroke via video link. The tool has in a preliminary study proved
      feasible and safe in different phases after stroke. The functional effect of using the
      DISKO-tool added to conventional rehabilitation in the home setting is yet to be explored.
      Thus, the aim of this study is to explore the added value of using the DISKO-tool during
      rehabilitation in the home setting.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Aim:The DISKO-tool was developed to enable efficient, continuous training in the home setting
      with health professional follow ups of training and training results after stroke via video
      link. The tool has in a preliminary study proved feasible and safe in different phases after
      stroke. The functional effect of using the DISKO-tool added to conventional rehabilitation in
      the home setting is yet to be explored. Thus, the aim of this study is to explore the added
      value of using the DISKO-tool during rehabilitation in the home setting.

      Hypothesis to be tested: Participants who perform 6 weeks of intensive training supported by
      the DISKO-tool in addition to the regular stroke rehabilitation interventions, gain a higher
      level of functioning compared to the control group with regular rehabilitation interventions.

      Study design: A randomized controlled intervention study.

      Participants and methods: 100 participants will be included in the study 3-6 months after
      stroke and after informed consent. The participants are recruited from primary care i.e.
      neuroteam and out-patient rehabilitation in Stockholm, Sweden. The included patients will be
      randomized to either 1) the intervention group (n=50) or 2) the control group (n=50). Based
      on previously published results on the BESTtest [14], a significance level of 5% and a power
      of 80%, 41 patients/treatment arm need to be included. With an expected minimal loss of
      participants per treatment arm, the study will require 50 patients/treatment arm.

      After the baseline assessment, the patients will receive a first introduction to the
      DISKO-tool. Thereafter the DISKO-tool system is set up at the patients' home by the
      physiotherapist. For safety reasons, space requirements and convenience of the patients, the
      physiotherapist in dialogue with the patients will select the placement of the screen. During
      the home visit, the patients will receive a manual and are instructed and guided in how to
      use the DISKO-tool including turning on the screen, controlling the user interface and
      performing test exercises. Dates and times for follow-ups by video communication with the
      physiotherapist are scheduled. After the installation, the physiotherapist will design an
      individualized training program for each of the patients. The training program will be based
      on the initial assessments of functioning and disability and the patients' performance of the
      test exercises. Type and number of exercises per session, level of difficulty and number of
      repetitions (including proportion of repetitions to the right and left side of the body) will
      be set. The set training program is thereafter introduced and evaluated during the first
      follow-up by video communication with the patients. In both groups, patients are instructed
      to train self-sufficiently 5 days a week and will be supervised by the treating
      physiotherapist. The intervention will last for 6 weeks. The baseline and final testing will
      both be performed at the rehabilitation clinics.

      The follow-ups, by video communication, will be registered by the physiotherapists in
      standardised logbooks. Data on conventional interventions will be retrieved from medical
      records. From the DISKO-tool, data regarding number of performed self-training sessions will
      be retrieved.

      After the intervention, the physiotherapist's (also after informed consent) and patient's
      experience and perception of using the DISKO-tool will be assessed in a study specific
      questionnaire based on the results of the semi-structured interviews performed in the
      feasibility study that preceded this study.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">April 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 1, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 1, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>A randomized controlled intervention study.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>Baseline and outcome will be assessed by blinded physiotherapists not involved in the intervention, who will be trained to be synchronized in the assessment procedures and to follow the same standardised protocol to assure consistency both at the Danderyd Hospital and Stockholm Sjukhem site.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>BESTest -to assess change</measure>
    <time_frame>T1 (baseline, before start of intervention) T2 (after completion of the 6 week intervention) and T3 (6 months after completion of the intervention)</time_frame>
    <description>Assesses balance</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>National Institute of Health Stroke Scale- to assess change</measure>
    <time_frame>T1 (baseline, before start of intervention) T2 (after completion of the 6 week intervention) and T3 (6 months after completion of the intervention)</time_frame>
    <description>Assesses stroke-related neurologic impairments (0p no detected impairment, summed up to 34p max impairment)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Montreal Cognitive Assessment- to assess change</measure>
    <time_frame>T1 (baseline, before start of intervention) T2 (after completion of the 6 week intervention) and T3 (6 months after completion of the intervention)</time_frame>
    <description>Assesses mental function (0p max impairment summed up to 30p no detected impairment)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Modified Ashworth Scale- to assess change</measure>
    <time_frame>T1 (baseline, before start of intervention) T2 (after completion of the 6 week intervention) and T3 (6 months after completion of the intervention)</time_frame>
    <description>Assesses spasticity on a 6 point scale/muscle (0p no impairment, 5p max impairment/muscle)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Fugle-Meyr for lower and upper extremity- to assess change</measure>
    <time_frame>T1 (baseline, before start of intervention) T2 (after completion of the 6 week intervention) and T3 (6 months after completion of the intervention)</time_frame>
    <description>Assesses sensory and movement related functions in lower and upper extremity (0p max impairment summed up to 86p max no detected impairment (lower extremity) 126p max no detected impairment (upper extremity)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Functional Ambulation Category- to assess change</measure>
    <time_frame>T1 (baseline, before start of intervention) T2 (after completion of the 6 week intervention) and T3 (6 months after completion of the intervention)</time_frame>
    <description>Assesses independence in walking 0p nonfunctional, 5p independent Total score 0-5p</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>6 minutes walk test combined with the RPE-scale- to assess change</measure>
    <time_frame>T1 (baseline, before start of intervention) T2 (after completion of the 6 week intervention) and T3 (6 months after completion of the intervention)</time_frame>
    <description>Assesses walking endurance in meters walked</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Timed Up and Go Test- to assess change</measure>
    <time_frame>T1 (baseline, before start of intervention) T2 (after completion of the 6 week intervention) and T3 (6 months after completion of the intervention)</time_frame>
    <description>Assesses gait and mobility (timed sek)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Falls Efficacy Scale- to assess change</measure>
    <time_frame>T1 (baseline, before start of intervention) T2 (after completion of the 6 week intervention) and T3 (6 months after completion of the intervention)</time_frame>
    <description>Assesses self perceived balance in every day life activities rated on an 11 point scale (0p not safe at all 10p completely safe). Total score: 0- 130 p</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Barthel Index- to assess change</measure>
    <time_frame>T1 (baseline, before start of intervention) T2 (after completion of the 6 week intervention) and T3 (6 months after completion of the intervention)</time_frame>
    <description>Assesses independence in mobility and personal care (0p dependent 10/15p independent) Total score 0-100p</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Stroke Impact Scale- to assess change</measure>
    <time_frame>T1 (baseline, before start of intervention) T2 (after completion of the 6 week intervention) and T3 (6 months after completion of the intervention)</time_frame>
    <description>Assesses self perceived impact of stroke on functioning and disability (domains: strength, hand function, ADL/IADL, Mobility, Commnication, Emotion, Memory/thinking, Participation rated on a 5 point scale (1p maximum impairment/limitation/restriction, 5p minimum impairment/limitation/restriction) Total score 0-100 p/domain calculated using an algorithm</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Stroke Rehabilitation</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The patient will receive conventional out patient rehabilitation after discharge to the home after stroke. In addition an individualized training program with gamified excercises for motor function will be set and followed up by clincians using video communication, as part of the DISKO-tool. Patients are instructed to train self sufficiently 5 days a week and will be supervised by the treating physiotherapist. The intervention will last for 6 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Conventional rehabilitation in primary care after discharge to the home after stroke.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>DISKO-tool</intervention_name>
    <description>The training program will be based on the initial assessments of functioning and disability and the patients' performance of the test exercises. Type and number of exercises per session, level of difficulty and number of repetitions (including proportion of repetitions to the right and left side of the body) will be set. The set training program is thereafter introduced and evaluated during the first follow-up by video communication with the patients.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  impaired motor function after stroke limiting activities of daily living but can walk
             indoors with or without supervision (functional ambulation category[ &gt;FAC 3), can
             stand without support &gt;2 min and are able to perform a forward reach of &gt;12 cm in
             standing position,

          -  referred to a neuroteam for rehabilitation interventions in the home setting and/or
             out- patient rehabilitation at Stockholms sjukhem or Rehab Nordost Täby

          -  motivated to perform exercises in the home setting with the DISKO-tool and with
             recurrent supervision by a physiotherapist through video communication.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  cognitive and/or speech impairment, limiting the ability to follow verbal and written
             training instruction or study information

          -  other disabling neurological disorder or other diagnosis prohibiting physical activity
             necessary when utilizing the DISKO tool

          -  impaired vision preventing orientation and reading instructions on a screen

          -  sufficient internet access in the home to participate in the intervention
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Susanne Palmcrantz, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Danderyd Hosptial</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jorgen Borg, Prof</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Danderyd Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Elisabet Akesson, Assoc Prof</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Karolinska Institutet</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Erika Franzén, Assoc Prof</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Karolinska Institutet</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Susanne Palmcrantz, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+46(0)709567653</phone>
    <email>susanne.palmcrantz@ki.se</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Elisabet Akesson, Assoc Prof</last_name>
    <phone>+46 (0)73-057 31 57</phone>
    <email>elisabet.akesson@stockholmssjukhem.se</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of Rehabilitation Medicine, Danderyd Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Danderyd</city>
        <state>Stockholm</state>
        <zip>SE18288</zip>
        <country>Sweden</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Susanne Palmcrantz, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>+46 (0)70-9567653</phone>
      <email>susanne.palmcrantz@ki.se</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Jorgen Borg, Prof</last_name>
      <phone>+46 (0)70-1684213</phone>
      <email>jorgen.borg@ki.se</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Stockholms sjukhem</name>
      <address>
        <city>Stockholm</city>
        <zip>SE112 19</zip>
        <country>Sweden</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Elisabet Akesson, Assoc Prof</last_name>
      <email>elisabet.akesson@stockholmssjukhem.se</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Erika Franzén, Assoc Prof</last_name>
      <email>erika.franzén@ki.se</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Sweden</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ehn M, Hansson P, Sjölinder M, Boman IL, Folke M, Sommerfeld D, Borg J, Palmcrantz S. Users perspectives on interactive distance technology enabling home-based motor training for stroke patients. Stud Health Technol Inform. 2015;211:145-52.</citation>
    <PMID>25980861</PMID>
  </reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Palmcrantz S, Borg J, Sommerfeld D, Plantin J, Wall A, Ehn M, Sjölinder M, Boman IL. An interactive distance solution for stroke rehabilitation in the home setting - A feasibility study. Inform Health Soc Care. 2017 Sep;42(3):303-320. doi: 10.1080/17538157.2016.1253015. Epub 2016 Dec 5.</citation>
    <PMID>27918220</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>August 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>April 9, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 20, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 22, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 20, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 20, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">August 22, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Stroke</keyword>
  <keyword>Rehabilitation</keyword>
  <keyword>Medical technology</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Stroke</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

