<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04060030</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>AS Leucovorin</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04060030</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Treatment of Social and Language Deficits With Leucovorin for Young Children With Autism</brief_title>
  <official_title>Treatment of Social and Language Deficits With Leucovorin for Young Children With Autism</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Phoenix Children's Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Autism Speaks</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>State University of New York - Downstate Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Arizona</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>New York State Institute for Basic Research</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Phoenix Children's Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The primary objective of this study is to evaluate the cognitive and behavioral effects of
      liquid leucovorin calcium on young children with autism spectrum disorder (ASD) and determine
      whether it improves social communication as well as the core and associated symptoms of ASD.
      The investigators will enroll 80 children across two sites, between the ages of 2.5 and 5
      years, with confirmed ASD and known social and communication delays. Participation will last
      approximately 26 weeks, from screening visit to end of treatment.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Autism spectrum disorder (ASD) is a heterogeneous neurodevelopmental disorder with life-long
      consequences that affects young children during critical times in their development. ASD is
      defined by impairments in social-communication as well as the presence of restricted
      interests and repetitive behaviors. ASD is frequently associated with co-occurring language
      delays. Currently the only well-accepted treatment for core ASD symptoms is behavior therapy
      such as Applied Behavioral Analysis and Early Intensive Behavioral Intervention. There is no
      US Food and Drug Administration approved medical therapy that addresses core ASD symptoms or
      the pathophysiological processes that underlie ASD.

      The primary aim of this study is to evaluate the effect of a liquid form of leucovorin
      calcium on social and communication impairments in very young children with ASD. Participants
      entered into the trial will have delayed language and moderate ASD symptoms. The
      investigators hypothesize that leucovorin calcium will significantly improve social
      communication as well as core and associated behavioral symptoms of ASD, and be
      well-tolerated with no significant adverse effects, in young children with ASD.

      To assess whether the liquid form of leucovorin calcium is superior to placebo, the
      investigators will study 80 children across two sites, between the ages of 2.5 and 5 years,
      with confirmed ASD and known social and communication delays at baseline. Participants will
      be randomly assigned to receive active treatment or placebo for 12 weeks under double-blind
      conditions. At the end of 12 weeks, all participants will receive active treatment for 12
      weeks. Language skills and social communication abilities will be measured at screening and
      after each treatment arm in order to determine if the supplement positively influences social
      communication. Additionally, the investigators will measure changes in neural pathways using
      either magnetoencephalography at Phoenix Children's Hospital or functional Near Infrared
      Spectroscopy at State University of New York, Downstate. While these measures will be
      considered exploratory, they will be important to begin to elucidate the neuronal mechanisms
      underlying leucovorin's impact.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">May 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Prospective randomized 12-week double-blind placebo-controlled study followed by 12-week open label</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>Quadruple masking during blinded phase, followed by unblinding during open label phase</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluate the overall change in core ASD symptoms of social communication</measure>
    <time_frame>Screening, Week 6, Week 12, Week 24</time_frame>
    <description>Brief Observation of Social Communication Change: a 16-item scale that rates social interactions between children with ASD and their interactive rater. Each item is rated on a scale of 0-5, wherein 0 indicates the least severe behavior and 5 indicates the most severe behavior. A higher score is indicative of more severe social communication deficits.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluate the safety and tolerability of L-leucovorin calcium in young children with ASD</measure>
    <time_frame>Screening, Baseline, Week 2, Week 4, Week 6, Week 8, Week 10, Week 12, Week 16, Week 20, Week 24</time_frame>
    <description>Modified Dosage Record and Treatment Emergent Symptoms: treating clinician will perform a review of medical and behavioral history at each visit to assess incidence of treatment-emergent adverse events. The treating clinician will use the scale to record presence and intensity of adverse effects. Intensity is rated on a scale of 0 (Not present) to 3 (Severe). The treating clinician will also judge the adverse effects' relatedness to treatment. Relatedness is rated on a scale of 1 (None) to 4 (Defined). The treating clinician will denote action taken. Action taken is rated on a scale of 0 (None) to 5 (Discontinue Treatment). No total score is calculated. However, higher ratings on any individual item indicate greater severity of adverse effects.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluate the safety of L-leucovorin calcium in young children with ASD</measure>
    <time_frame>Screening, Baseline, Week 2, Week 4, Week 6, Week 8, Week 10, Week 12, Week 16, Week 20, Week 24</time_frame>
    <description>Columbia-Suicide Severity Rating Scale: a suicide risk assessment that identifies presence and severity of suicidal ideation, planning, and behavior, as well as non-suicidal self-harm behaviors. Presence of any of these behaviors during the course of study enrollment will be considered an adverse event.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluate the safety of L-leucovorin calcium in young children with ASD</measure>
    <time_frame>Screening, Week 12, Week 24</time_frame>
    <description>Routine complete blood counts will be collected to determine whether treatment-emergent basic blood chemistry is altered. Presence of any changes during the course of study enrollment will be evaluated by the treating physician and determined clinically significant or not clinically significant. If determined by the treating physician, a change will be considered an adverse event.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluate the safety of L-leucovorin calcium in young children with ASD</measure>
    <time_frame>Screening, Week 12, Week 24</time_frame>
    <description>Routine comprehensive blood panels will be collected to determine whether treatment-emergent basic blood chemistry is altered. Presence of any changes during the course of study enrollment will be evaluated by the treating physician and determined clinically significant or not clinically significant. If determined by the treating physician, a change will be considered an adverse event.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluate the safety of L-leucovorin calcium in young children with ASD</measure>
    <time_frame>Screening, Week 12, Week 24</time_frame>
    <description>For children using antiepileptic drugs, the level of that drug will be measured. If determined by the treating physician, a change will be considered an adverse event.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Examine the change in measures of language</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Week 12, Week 24</time_frame>
    <description>Mullen Scales of Early Learning: a scale of cognitive abilities across core domains: visual reception, fine motor, expressive language, receptive language. Expressive language domain: 28-item scale with a raw score range of 0-50, t score range of 20-80. Receptive language domain: 33-item scale with a raw score range of 0-48, t score range of 20-80.
Change in domain ability will be measured by the change in domain t score. T scores are calculated from raw scores and based on age norms. A higher domain t score indicates a higher level of ability in that domain.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluate the change in effects of autism symptoms on family members</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Week 6, Week 12, Week 24</time_frame>
    <description>Parent Target Problems: a parent-nominated list of 2 most problematic core autism symptoms. Responses are documented in a brief narrative and detail frequency, constancy, intensity, and impact of behavior on the family. Subjective reports of frequency, constancy, intensity, and impact on family will be rated by a blinded statistician at the conclusion of the study. Higher scores indicate more severe impact on family.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluate the change in stereotypical autism symptoms</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Week 6, Week 12, Week 24</time_frame>
    <description>Aberrant Behavior Checklist-2: a 58-item parent-reported measure of stereotypical autism behaviors with ratings in the following domains: irritability, social withdrawal, stereotypic behavior, hyperactivity, and inappropriate speech. Each item is rated from 0 (Not a Problem) to 3 (Severe Problem). The raw score will be reported. The total raw score is the sum of the domain raw scores. A higher raw score in any of the domains indicates more severe problems in that domain; a higher total raw score indicates more severity of stereotypical autism symptoms overall.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluate change in overall autism severity</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Week 6, Week 12, Week 24</time_frame>
    <description>Clinical Global Impression Scale: The Clinical Global Impression Scale-Severity is a 7-point measure of overall symptom severity, ranging from 1 (Normal) to 7 (Extreme), with a raw score range of 1-7. The raw score will be reported. The Clinical Global Impression Scale-Improvement is a measure in change of symptom severity, ranging from 1 (Very Much Improved) to 7 (Very Much Worse). A Score of 4 indicates no change in symptom severity.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluate change in overall autism severity</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Week 6, Week 12, Week 24</time_frame>
    <description>Ohio State University Clinical Impressions Scale: a clinical rating of severity and improvement of 10 autism domains: social interaction, aberrant/abnormal behavior, repetitive/ritualistic behavior, verbal communication, non-verbal communication, hyperactivity/inattention, anxiety/fears, sensory sensitivities, restricted/narrow interests, autism. Severity will be measured at baseline. Each item is rated from 1 (Normal) to 7 (Among the most severe) with a raw score range of 10-70. The raw score will be reported. Higher scores indicate more severe impairment. At the following time points, improvement will be measured. Each item is rated from 1 (Very much improved) to 7 (Very much worse) with a raw score range of 10-70. The raw score will be reported. Higher scores indicate more severe impairment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluate the change in overall cognitive ability</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Week 12, Week 24</time_frame>
    <description>Mullen Scales of Early Learning: a scale of cognitive abilities across core domains: visual reception, fine motor, expressive language, receptive language. Expressive language domain: 28-item scale with a raw score range of 0-50, t score range of 20-80. Receptive language domain: 33-item scale with a raw score range of 0-48, t score range of 20-80. Visual reception domain: 33-item scale with a raw score range of 0-50, t score range of 20-80. Fine motor domain: 33-item scale with a raw score range of 0-50, t score range of 20-80.
Change in domain ability will be measured by the change in domain t score. T scores are calculated from raw scores and based on age norms. A higher domain t score indicates a higher level of ability in that domain. Domain t scores will be used to get a standard composite score. Change in cognition will be measured by change in the standard score. A higher composite score indicates higher overall cognitive ability.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluate the change in adaptive functioning</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Week 12, Week 24</time_frame>
    <description>Vineland Adaptive Behavior Scale-II Domain LevelI: a scale to assess adaptive behavior in children with developmental/intellectual disabilities. This is a 135-item parent-reported measure with ratings in the following domains: communication, daily living skills, and socialization. The frequency of each item is scaled from 0 (Never) to 2 (Usually). For each domain, there are 45 items with a maximum score of 90. Change in each domain will be measured by the change in standard score. Standard scores are calculated from the raw scores and based on age norms. A higher standard score in any domain indicates a higher level of adaptive behavior in that domain. Domain standard scores will be used to get a standard composite score. Change in adaptive behavior will be measured by the change in the standard score. A higher composite score indicates higher overall adaptive behavior ability.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Demonstrate changes in neuronal activation and connectivity associated with treatment response using non-invasive neuroimaging methods</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Week 12, Week 24</time_frame>
    <description>Using magnetoencephalography at Phoenix Children's Hospital and functional near-infrared spectroscopy and the State University of New York, the investigators will assess whether the following pathways are altered by leucovorin calcium treatment: M100 auditory evoked gamma-band power, connectivity, and coherence. Both the magnetoencephalography and functional near-infrared spectroscopy will be able to capture these same values. Treatment-emergent change in these values will indicate that a change has occurred in the neural pathway.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluate the effect of L-leucovorin on cellular regulatory pathways known to be implicated in social communication</measure>
    <time_frame>Screening, Week 12, Week 24</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluate changes in the following cellular regulatory pathways known to be implicated in social communication: peripheral blood mononuclear cell, plasma, DNA, red blood cells, and oxidative stress rates. Treatment-emergent change in these biomarkers will indicate that a change has occurred at the cellular level.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Test if biomarkers (single nucleotide polymorphisms) predict clinical response to L-leucovorin</measure>
    <time_frame>Screening, Week 12</time_frame>
    <description>Saliva will be collected to determine presence of the following single nucleotide polymorphisms: MTR, MTHFR6, DHFR, GCH1, MTHFR12, RFC, FOLH, COMT. Presence or absence of these genetic polymorphisms will be analyzed to assess correlation with response to L-leucovorin treatment.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">80</enrollment>
  <condition>Autism Spectrum Disorder</condition>
  <condition>Language Disorders</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>L-leucovorin calcium</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The liquid form of leucovorin calcium will be dosed by weight, with a target dose of 1mg/kg/day, divided into two daily doses. This product may be taken alone or mixed with liquid. Participants randomized to this arm will receive active treatment for both 12-week phases of the study.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The placebo will mimic the experimental treatment in flavor, odor, packaging, and dosing instructions. Participants randomized to this arm will receive placebo for the first 12 weeks of the study, then active treatment for the remaining 12 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Levoleucovorin Calcium</intervention_name>
    <description>Liquid leucovorin calcium dosed by weight</description>
    <arm_group_label>L-leucovorin calcium</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>L-leucovorin</other_name>
    <other_name>L-leucovorin calcium</other_name>
    <other_name>L-folinic acid, calcium salt</other_name>
    <other_name>L-folinate, calcium salt</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Placebo</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Autism Spectrum Disorder (as defined below).

          2. Between 2.5 and 5 years of age

          3. FRAA+ status

          4. Language impairment (Ages and Stages Questionnaire between -1 and -3 SD for Language)

          5. English included in the languages in which the child is being raised

          6. Moderate level of autism symptoms (Clinical Global Impression Grade 4 or above)

          7. Ability to maintain all ongoing complementary, traditional and behavioral treatments
             constant for the study period

          8. Unchanged complementary, traditional and behavioral treatments for two months prior to
             study entry

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Mineral or vitamin supplementation that exceeds the Recommended Daily Allowance limit
             set by the FDA and Institute of Medicine

          2. Significant self-abusive or violent behavior or evidence of suicidal ideation, plan or
             behavior

          3. Severely low functioning (Defined a Mullen Scales of Early Learning Composite &lt;55)

          4. Severe prematurity (&lt;34 weeks gestation) as determined by medical history

          5. Current uncontrolled gastroesophageal reflux

          6. Current or history of liver or kidney disease as determined by medical history and
             safety labs

          7. Genetic syndromes

          8. Congenital brain malformations

          9. Epilepsy

         10. Any medical condition that the PI determines could jeopardize the safety of the study
             subject or compromise the integrity of the data

         11. Significant negative reaction (i.e. fainting, vomiting, etc.) as a result of a
             previous blood draw.

         12. Failure to thrive or Body Mass Index &lt; 5%ile.

         13. Concurrent treatment with drug that would significantly interact with leucovorin such
             as specific chemotherapy agents, antimalarial and immune suppressive agents and select
             antibiotics
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>30 Months</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>60 Months</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Richard E Frye, MD, Phd</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Phoenix Children's Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Richard E Frye, MD, Phd</last_name>
    <phone>(602) 933-2680</phone>
    <email>rfrye@phoenixchildrens.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Sarah G Vassall, BS, BA</last_name>
    <phone>(602) 933-0853</phone>
    <email>svassall@phoenixchildrens.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Phoenix Children's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Phoenix</city>
        <state>Arizona</state>
        <zip>85016</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Richard E Frye, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>602-933-2680</phone>
      <email>rfrye@phoenixchildrens.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Sarah G Vassall, BS, BA</last_name>
      <phone>(602) 933-0853</phone>
      <email>svassall@phoenixchildrens.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>State University of New York, Downstate</name>
      <address>
        <city>Brooklyn</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>11203</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Harris Huberman, MD</last_name>
      <phone>718-270-2272</phone>
      <email>harris.huberman2@downstate.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Khadija Sikriti</last_name>
      <phone>(718) 270-4657</phone>
      <email>khadija.sikriti@downstate.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 13, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 15, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 16, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 2, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 2, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 3, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Phoenix Children's Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Richard Frye, MD, PhD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Language Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Autistic Disorder</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Autism Spectrum Disorder</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Calcium, Dietary</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leucovorin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Calcium</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Levoleucovorin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>The investigators plan to publish the results of the study in an academic journal. Results may also be shared at conferences and presentations.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

