<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04061239</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PALOMA</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04061239</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Comparison of Therapies Before Stem Cell Transplantation in Patients With Higher Risk MDS and Oligoblastic AML</brief_title>
  <acronym>PALOMA</acronym>
  <official_title>Primary Comparison of Liposomal Anthracycline Based Treatment Versus Conventional Care Strategies Before Allogeneic Stem Cell Transplantation in Patients With Higher Risk MDS and Oligoblastic AML</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>GWT-TUD GmbH</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>GWT-TUD GmbH</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To compare the event-free survival at 2 years of CPX-351 vs. conventional care regimens
      before allogeneic blood cell transplantation as first line treatment in patients with higher
      risk MDS and oligoblastic AML.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Allogeneic stem cell transplantation (alloHCT) is considered the only potentially curative
      treatment option for MDS patients and is therefore often considered the standard treatment
      for mainly higher-risk MDS patients up to the age of 75 years. One common approach to
      &quot;bridge&quot; higher-risk MDS from the time of diagnosis to transplantation is a treatment with
      hypomethylating agents such as azacitidine due to its anticipated low toxicity profile.
      Alternative strategies are intensive 7+3 chemotherapy with anthracycline and cytarabine or
      direct and immediate transplantation. By this strategy the time interval for donor search can
      be significantly prolonged leading to a higher proportion of success.Nevertheless, not every
      patient initially eligible for transplantation undergoes this procedure subsequently. A
      direct prospective comparison of different therapeutic approaches as outlined above versus
      CPX-351 prior to alloHCT has not been performed so far and is subject of the PALOMA trial. We
      hypothesize that CPX-351 will lead to higher and more durable response rates including a more
      favourable safety profile and long-term outcome compared to currently used conventional care
      regimens approaches prior to alloHCT.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">August 19, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2024</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>2-year EFS in both arms</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>To compare the event-free survival (EFS) at 2 years of CPX-351 vs. CCR before allogeneic blood cell transplantation (alloHCT) as first line treatment in patients with higher risk MDS and oligoblastic AML.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Response rate</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>To compare best and overall response rate of CPX-351 vs. CCR according to AML-ELN and MDS-IWG criteria</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Toxicity Assessment</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>To compare the safety and tolerability of CPX-351 vs. CCR measured by NCI CTCAE v5.0</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of patients proceeding to alloHCT</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>To compare the effects of CPX-351 vs. CCR on the proportion of patients proceeding to alloHCT</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Minimal residual disease</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>To compare the effect of CPX-351 vs. CCR on minimal residual disease which will be assessed at all times of bone marrow puncture</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient's quality of life</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>To compare the effect of CPX-351 vs. CCR on the quality of life. It will be measured using the EORTC-QLQ30 questionnaire</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">150</enrollment>
  <condition>MDS</condition>
  <condition>AML</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>CPX-351 Arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>CPX-351 is a liposomal formulation with a fixed 5:1 molar ratio of cytarabine and daunorubicin. It will be administered as a 90-minute intravenous infusion.
The treatment includes up to 2 cycles of induction as follows:
1 x CPX-351 1st induction: daunorubicin 44 mg/m² and cytarabine 100 mg/m² in liposomes on days 1, 3, and 5
1 x CPX-351 2nd induction: daunorubicin 44 mg/m² and cytarabine 100 mg/m² in liposomes on days 1 and 3
Each induction cycle will last 28 days. Depending on the type and extent of response as well as toxicity, the patient may continue on to consolidation therapy after induction or be discontinued from the treatment phase and transferred directly to alloHCT, if applicable. CPX-351 consolidation is with daunorubicin 29 mg/m² and cytarabine 65 mg/m² in liposomes on days 1 and 3. For patients &lt; 60 years up to 3 consolidation cycles and for patients ≥ 60 years up to 2 consolidation cycles are allowed.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>CCR Arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>The conventional care regimens (CCR) arm has 2 options according to the discretion of the investigator:
conventional &quot;7+3&quot; cytarabine/daunorubicin chemotherapy regimen
treatment with s.c. Azacitidine</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>CPX-351</intervention_name>
    <description>CPX-351 is a liposomal formulation with a fixed 5:1 molar ratio of cytarabine and daunorubicin. It will be administered as a 90-minute intravenous infusion.</description>
    <arm_group_label>CPX-351 Arm</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Vyxeos</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Daunorubicin</intervention_name>
    <description>Daunorubicin is commercially available as a powder for reconstitution in 20 mg vials. In this trial, daunorubicin should be administered as an IV infusion over 60 min.</description>
    <arm_group_label>CCR Arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cytarabine</intervention_name>
    <description>Cytarabine is commercially available as vials/bottles for preparation of diluted infusion solution. Cytarabine will be administrated intravenously. In this trial, cytarabine is administered as a continuous infusion.</description>
    <arm_group_label>CCR Arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Azacitidine</intervention_name>
    <description>Azacitidine at 75mg/m² for 7 days. Patients should receive a minimum of 2 and up to 6 cycles.</description>
    <arm_group_label>CCR Arm</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Vidaza</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Male and female adult patients, 18-75 years of age

          -  Diagnosis of high risk MDS including oligoblastic non-proliferative (WBC &lt;13 Gpt/l)
             AML up to 29% of bone marrow blasts

          -  Availability of BM blast count from central morphology

          -  Bone marrow blasts ≥ 5%

          -  IPSS score intermediate or high

          -  alloHCT intended within the next 6 months

          -  ECOG performance status of 0 or 1

          -  Signed informed consent

          -  Laboratory values fulfilling the following:

          -  Serum creatinine &lt; 2.0 mg/dL

          -  Serum total bilirubin &lt; 2.0 mg/dL

          -  Serum alanine aminotransferase or aspartate aminotransferase &lt; 3 times the ULN

          -  Cardiac ejection fraction (LVEF) ≥ 50% by echocardiography

          -  Contraception:

          -  Female subjects of childbearing potential† must agree to use a medically acceptable
             method of contraception for at least 2 months prior to the first dose of CPX-351 and
             consent of female patients to use a medically acceptable method of contraception
             throughout the entire study period and for 6 months following the last dose of
             CPX-351. Medically acceptable methods of contraception that may be used by the patient
             include abstinence, diaphragm and spermicide, intrauterine device (IUD), condom and
             vaginal spermicide, hormonal contraceptives (patients must be stable on hormonal
             contraceptives for at least the prior 3 months), surgical sterilization, or
             post-menopausal (≥2 years of amenorrhea). Medically acceptable methods of
             contraception that may be used by the male partner of a female patient are condom and
             spermicide or vasectomy (&gt;6 months prior to Day-1) and are to be used throughout the
             entire study period and for 6 months following the last dose of CPX-351.

          -  Male patients must be willing to refrain from sperm donation for 6 months following
             the last dose of CPX-351 and must use adequate contraception throughout the entire
             study period and for 6 months following the last dose of CPX-351.

          -  Combined oral contraceptive pills are not recommended. It is recommended that during
             the study two medically accepted methods of contraception (e.g. as hormonal
             contraceptive methods along with a condom) apply.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with history of myeloproliferative neoplasms (MPN) (defined as a history of
             essential thrombocytosis or

          -  polycythemia vera, or idiopathic myelofibrosis prior to the diagnosis of AML) or
             combined MDS/MPN are not eligible.

          -  WHO-2016 defined AML entities: AML with t(15;17), PML-RARA; AML with t(8;21),
             RUNX1-RUNX1T1, AML with inv(16)/t(16;16), CBFβ-MYH11; AML with biallelic CEBPA
             mutation; AML with mutated FLT3 or NPM1.

          -  Clinical evidence of active CNS leukemia.

          -  Patients with a &quot;currently active&quot; second malignancy other than non-melanoma skin
             cancers. Patients are not considered to have a &quot;currently active&quot; malignancy if they
             have completed therapy and are considered by their physician to be at less than 30%
             risk of relapse within one year.

          -  Any major surgery or radiation therapy within four weeks prior screening.

          -  Patients with prior treatment of either CPX-351, hypomethylating agents, cytarabine or
             intensive chemotherapy for high-risk MDS or AML.

          -  Patients with prior cumulative anthracycline exposure of greater than 368 mg/m2
             daunorubicin (or equivalent).

          -  Any serious medical condition, laboratory abnormality or psychiatric illness that
             would prevent obtaining informed consent.

          -  Patients with myocardial impairment of any cause (e.g. cardiomyopathy, ischemic heart
             disease, significant valvular dysfunction, hypertensive heart disease, and congestive
             heart failure) resulting in heart failure by New York Heart Association Criteria (NYHA
             Class III or IV staging).

          -  Active or uncontrolled infection. Patients with an infection receiving treatment
             (antibiotic, antifungal or antiviral treatment) may be entered into the study but must
             be afebrile and hemodynamically stable for ≥72 hrs.

          -  Current evidence of invasive fungal infection (blood or tissue culture); patients with
             recent fungal infection must have a subsequent negative cultures to be eligible; known
             HIV (new testing not required) or evidence of active hepatitis B or C infection (with
             rising transaminase values).

          -  Hypersensitivity to cytarabine, daunorubicin or liposomal products.

          -  History of Wilson's disease or other copper-metabolism disorder.

          -  Female patients who are pregnant or lactating.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Uwe Platzbecker, Prof.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Universitätsklinikum Leipzig AöR</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Martin Puttrich</last_name>
    <phone>+49 351 25933</phone>
    <phone_ext>193</phone_ext>
    <email>Martin.Puttrich@gwtonline.de</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Universitätsklinikum Leipzig AöR</name>
      <address>
        <city>Leipzig</city>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Uwe Platzbecker, Prof.</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Germany</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 15, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 16, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 19, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 20, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 20, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">September 23, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cytarabine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Azacitidine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Daunorubicin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

