<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04066764</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>SAHZhejiangU-002</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04066764</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Rivaroxaban and Vitamin K Antagonists for the Anticoagulation for the Implantation of Vena Cava Filters</brief_title>
  <acronym>EPICT</acronym>
  <official_title>An Efficacy and Safety Study of New Oral Anticoagulants and Vitamin K Antagonists for the Anticoagulation for the Implantation of Vena Cava Filters: A Prospective Randomized Controlled Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Second Affiliated Hospital, School of Medicine, Zhejiang University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Sir Run Run Shaw Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Huadong Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Shanghai Zhongshan Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Shanghai 5th People's Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Yantai Yuhuangding Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Anhui Provincial Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Second Affiliated Hospital, School of Medicine, Zhejiang University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to evaluate the efficacy and safety of new oral anticoagulants
      and vitamin K antagonists for the anticoagulation for the implantation of vena cava filters
      in patients with deep venous thrombosis.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Deep vein thrombosis (DVT) of lower extremities is a venous reflux disorder caused by
      abnormal coagulation of deep vein blood. The main adverse consequences of DVT are pulmonary
      embolism (PE) and post-thrombotic syndrome, which can significantly affect the quality of
      life of patients and even lead to death. Anticoagulation is the basic treatment of DVT, which
      can inhibit the spread of thrombus, facilitate thrombus autolysis and recanalization of the
      lumen, and reduce the incidence and mortality of PE. For patients with contraindications or
      complications of anticoagulation therapy, the implantation of inferior vena cava filter may
      be considered. At the same time, patients with the following conditions may be considered for
      the implantation of inferior vena cava filter: PE is still present in the case of adequate
      anticoagulant therapy, floating thrombus in the iliac, femoral or inferior vena cava,
      thrombectomy is planned for acute DVT, and abdominal, pelvic or lower extremity surgery with
      high risk factors for PE and acute DVT. The current standard treatment regimen for venous
      thromboembolism (VTE) anticoagulation is low molecular weight heparin (LMWH) combined with or
      followed by vitamin K antagonist warfarin. It has been proved that low molecular weight
      heparin has good safety and effectiveness in the prevention and initial treatment of VTE,
      especially for VTE prevention and treatment in cancer patients and pregnant patients. As a
      standard oral anticoagulant, warfarin has definite anticoagulant effect and is cheap.
      However, low molecular weight heparin needs subcutaneous injection, which can cause adverse
      reactions such as pain, itching, subcutaneous hemorrhage and nodules at the injection site,
      and some complications such as heparin-induced thrombocytopenia (HIT). Warfarin
      anticoagulation therapy requires long-term laboratory monitoring of international
      standardized ratio (INR) and timely adjustment of warfarin dosage according to INR, which
      will result in difficult follow-up management, poor compliance, uncertainty of warfarin
      treatment effect, and even serious bleeding complications. According to relevant studies, the
      incidence of warfarin-related major bleeding is about 1%-2%, and the recurrence or
      aggravation of thrombus is also high. Rivaroxaban can simplify treatment, and is safe. It's
      also not easy to interact with food or drugs. Previous studies have shown that rivaroxaban is
      effective in preventing deep venous thrombosis after orthopaedic surgery. Rivaroxaban has
      also been shown to be safe and effective in anticoagulation therapy for patients with deep
      venous thrombosis and pulmonary embolism, and repeated coagulation monitoring is not
      required. However, Rivaroxaban lacks sufficient clinical data for perioperative adjuvant
      anticoagulation therapy of filter implantation. Therefore, this study should be carried out
      to provide the basis for DVT treatment guidelines and explore the clinical indications of
      rivaroxaban.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 8, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 1, 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 1, 2024</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Participants With Symptomatic Recurrent Venous Thromboembolism</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months after the filter is retrieved</time_frame>
    <description>the Composite of Recurrent Deep Vein Thrombosis [DVT] or Fatal or Non-fatal Pulmonary Embolism [PE]</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Participants With Hemorrhage due to Anticoagulation</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months after the filter is retrieved</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Participants with Filter-related thrombosis which leads to retrieval failure</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months after the filter is retrieved</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>All cause mortality</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months after the filter is retrieved</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of participants with all deaths</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Participants With an Event for Net Clinical Benefit</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months after the filter is retrieved</time_frame>
    <description>composite of primary efficacy outcomes and major bleeding, assessed in the intention-to-treat population.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Participants With Other Vascular Events</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months after the filter is retrieved</time_frame>
    <description>All pre-defined vascular events (ST segment elevation myocardial infarction, non ST segment elevation myocardial infarction, acute coronary syndrome, unstable angina, ischemic stroke, transient ischemic attack, pulmonary embolism, non-central nervous system systemic embolism or vascular death) will be assessed based results/films/images of confirmatory testing, and/or case summaries.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">200</enrollment>
  <condition>Venous Thromboembolism</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Rivaroxaban</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will receive rivaroxaban 15mg oral twice daily for 3 weeks after operation, later rivaroxaban 20mg oral once daily until 3 months after the filter is retrieved.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Warfarin/ Nadroparin</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will receive Nadroparin 1mg/kg twice daily (subcutaneous), plus warfarin 3mg oral once daily for 5 days after the operation, later warfarin(oral) at individually titrated doses(0.75mg to 18mg) to achieve a target international normalized ratio (INR) of 2.0 to 3.0, once daily until 3 months after the filter is retrieved.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Rivaroxaban</intervention_name>
    <description>15mg twice daily for 3 weeks after operation, later 20mg once daily until 3 months after the filter is removed. Application: oral</description>
    <arm_group_label>Rivaroxaban</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Xarelto</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Warfarin</intervention_name>
    <description>3mg for 5 days after the operation, later 0.75mg to 18mg depending on INR (2.0-3.0) until until 3 months after the filter is removed. Frequency: once daily Application: oral</description>
    <arm_group_label>Warfarin/ Nadroparin</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>coumadin</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Nadroparin</intervention_name>
    <description>Dose: 1mg/kg Duration: 5 days after the operation Frequency: twice daily Application: subcutaneous</description>
    <arm_group_label>Warfarin/ Nadroparin</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Fraxiparin</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients who was diagnosed with deep venous thrombosis of the lower extremity and
             implanted with a retrievable inferior vena cava filter.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Age &lt; 18 years or age &gt; 75 years,

          -  With obvious contraindications for anticoagulation therapy,

          -  Allergic to iodine contrast agents in the past,

          -  Pregnant or breastfeeding women,

          -  With malignant tumors and life expectancy &lt; 1 year,

          -  Severe liver diseases (such as acute hepatitis, chronic active hepatitis or cirrhosis)
             or alanine aminotransferase levels were higher than three times the upper limit of
             normal.

          -  With other diseases that need anticoagulation,

          -  With previous heparin‐induced thrombocytopenia,

          -  Bacterial endocarditis,

          -  Systolic blood pressure &gt; 180 mmHg or diastolic blood pressure &gt; 110 mmHg,

          -  Taking cytochrome P450 3A4(CYP-450 3A4) inhibitors or inducers

          -  With severe renal insufficiency (creatinine clearance &lt;30 mL/min)

          -  Allergic to the drug used in this study

          -  With permanent filter implantation
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Zhejie Liu</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Second Affiliated Hospital, School of Medicine, Zhejiang University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Li s Yin</last_name>
    <phone>86-0571-87913706</phone>
    <phone_ext>15268135830</phone_ext>
    <email>lawson4001@zju.edu.cn</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Zhejie s Liu</last_name>
    <phone>15268135830</phone>
    <phone_ext>15268135830</phone_ext>
    <email>lawson3001@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Anhui Provincial Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hefei</city>
        <state>Anhui</state>
        <zip>230000</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Zhengdong Fang, MD</last_name>
      <phone>15256990126</phone>
      <phone_ext>15256990126</phone_ext>
      <email>fangzhengdong@126.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Yantai Yuhuangding Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Yantai</city>
        <state>Shangdong</state>
        <zip>264000</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Lubin Li, MD</last_name>
      <phone>18653587255</phone>
      <phone_ext>18653587255</phone_ext>
      <email>278468192@qq.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Huadong Hospital affiliated to Fudan University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Shanghai</city>
        <state>Shanghai</state>
        <zip>200000</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Wan Zhang, MD</last_name>
      <phone>13916056910</phone>
      <phone_ext>13916056910</phone_ext>
      <email>ant0930@163.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Shanghai 5th People's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Shanghai</city>
        <state>Shanghai</state>
        <zip>200000</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Bin Gao, MD</last_name>
      <phone>13764979078</phone>
      <phone_ext>13764979078</phone_ext>
      <email>doctorgaobin@163.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Zhongshan Hospital affiliated to Fudan University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Shanghai</city>
        <state>Shanghai</state>
        <zip>200000</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jianing Yue, MD</last_name>
      <phone>13564788422</phone>
      <phone_ext>86</phone_ext>
      <email>yuejianing@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sir Run Run Shaw Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hangzhou</city>
        <state>Zhejiang</state>
        <zip>310000</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Yuefeng R Zhu, MD</last_name>
      <phone>13868101010</phone>
      <phone_ext>13868101010</phone_ext>
      <email>drzyf@hotmail.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The second affiliated hospital of zhejiang university school of medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hangzhou</city>
        <state>Zhejiang</state>
        <zip>310000</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Zhejie Liu, MD,PhD</last_name>
      <phone>15268135830</phone>
      <phone_ext>86</phone_ext>
      <email>lawson3001@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kearon C, Akl EA, Ornelas J, Blaivas A, Jimenez D, Bounameaux H, Huisman M, King CS, Morris TA, Sood N, Stevens SM, Vintch JRE, Wells P, Woller SC, Moores L. Antithrombotic Therapy for VTE Disease: CHEST Guideline and Expert Panel Report. Chest. 2016 Feb;149(2):315-352. doi: 10.1016/j.chest.2015.11.026. Epub 2016 Jan 7. Erratum in: Chest. 2016 Oct;150(4):988.</citation>
    <PMID>26867832</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jain A, Cifu AS. Antithrombotic Therapy for Venous Thromboembolic Disease. JAMA. 2017 May 16;317(19):2008-2009. doi: 10.1001/jama.2017.1928.</citation>
    <PMID>28510665</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Breddin HK, Hach-Wunderle V, Nakov R, Kakkar VV; CORTES Investigators. Clivarin: Assessment of Regression of Thrombosis, Efficacy, and Safety. Effects of a low-molecular-weight heparin on thrombus regression and recurrent thromboembolism in patients with deep-vein thrombosis. N Engl J Med. 2001 Mar 1;344(9):626-31.</citation>
    <PMID>11228276</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schulman S, Zondag M, Linkins L, Pasca S, Cheung YW, de Sancho M, Gallus A, Lecumberri R, Molnar S, Ageno W, Le Gal G, Falanga A, Hulegårdh E, Ranta S, Kamphuisen P, Debourdeau P, Rigamonti V, Ortel TL, Lee A. Recurrent venous thromboembolism in anticoagulated patients with cancer: management and short-term prognosis. J Thromb Haemost. 2015 Jun;13(6):1010-8. doi: 10.1111/jth.12955. Epub 2015 May 9.</citation>
    <PMID>25851122</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Turpie AG, Lassen MR, Davidson BL, Bauer KA, Gent M, Kwong LM, Cushner FD, Lotke PA, Berkowitz SD, Bandel TJ, Benson A, Misselwitz F, Fisher WD; RECORD4 Investigators. Rivaroxaban versus enoxaparin for thromboprophylaxis after total knee arthroplasty (RECORD4): a randomised trial. Lancet. 2009 May 16;373(9676):1673-80. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(09)60734-0. Epub 2009 May 4.</citation>
    <PMID>19411100</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lassen MR, Ageno W, Borris LC, Lieberman JR, Rosencher N, Bandel TJ, Misselwitz F, Turpie AG; RECORD3 Investigators. Rivaroxaban versus enoxaparin for thromboprophylaxis after total knee arthroplasty. N Engl J Med. 2008 Jun 26;358(26):2776-86. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa076016.</citation>
    <PMID>18579812</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Prins MH, Lensing AW, Brighton TA, Lyons RM, Rehm J, Trajanovic M, Davidson BL, Beyer-Westendorf J, Pap ÁF, Berkowitz SD, Cohen AT, Kovacs MJ, Wells PS, Prandoni P. Oral rivaroxaban versus enoxaparin with vitamin K antagonist for the treatment of symptomatic venous thromboembolism in patients with cancer (EINSTEIN-DVT and EINSTEIN-PE): a pooled subgroup analysis of two randomised controlled trials. Lancet Haematol. 2014 Oct;1(1):e37-46. doi: 10.1016/S2352-3026(14)70018-3. Epub 2014 Sep 28.</citation>
    <PMID>27030066</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>EINSTEIN Investigators, Bauersachs R, Berkowitz SD, Brenner B, Buller HR, Decousus H, Gallus AS, Lensing AW, Misselwitz F, Prins MH, Raskob GE, Segers A, Verhamme P, Wells P, Agnelli G, Bounameaux H, Cohen A, Davidson BL, Piovella F, Schellong S. Oral rivaroxaban for symptomatic venous thromboembolism. N Engl J Med. 2010 Dec 23;363(26):2499-510. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa1007903. Epub 2010 Dec 3.</citation>
    <PMID>21128814</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>EINSTEIN–PE Investigators, Büller HR, Prins MH, Lensin AW, Decousus H, Jacobson BF, Minar E, Chlumsky J, Verhamme P, Wells P, Agnelli G, Cohen A, Berkowitz SD, Bounameaux H, Davidson BL, Misselwitz F, Gallus AS, Raskob GE, Schellong S, Segers A. Oral rivaroxaban for the treatment of symptomatic pulmonary embolism. N Engl J Med. 2012 Apr 5;366(14):1287-97. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa1113572. Epub 2012 Mar 26.</citation>
    <PMID>22449293</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 22, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 22, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 26, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 8, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 8, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 11, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Second Affiliated Hospital, School of Medicine, Zhejiang University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Zhenjie Liu</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>venous thromboembolism</keyword>
  <keyword>rivaroxaban</keyword>
  <keyword>vena cava filters</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Thromboembolism</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Venous Thromboembolism</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Nadroparin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Warfarin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Rivaroxaban</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

