<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04064853</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>GT dental pain Malmo U</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04064853</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Childrens' Experiences of Pain in Conjunction With Tooth Extraction - a Grounded Theory Study</brief_title>
  <official_title>Childrens' Experiences of Pain in Conjunction With Tooth Extraction - a Grounded Theory</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Malmö University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Malmö University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a qualitative study, using Grounded Theory. The aim is to deepen our knowledge about
      how children perceive pain in conjunction with dental treatment; tooth extractions in
      particular. What increases, and what decreases, the risk of children experiencing pain; and
      how do they perceive dental treatments where pain might occur, either as procedural pain, or
      postoperatively?
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      BACKGROUND: Pain in conjunction with dental treatment should be avoided as much as possible,
      when treating children. Many dental procedures may result in procedural and/or postoperative
      pain. There is a well-documented relationship between perceived pain during/after dental
      treatment, and the development of dental fear and anxiety. This may lead to suffering for the
      patient and accelerating treatment-costs for society. Despite this, research on children and
      pain is scarce. Systematic review shows a lack of studies on oral analgesics and their
      possibility to reduce/prevent pain. There is a need for randomized clinical trials regarding
      different treatments and effect of analgesics. However, before such research can be
      undertaken, one important piece is missing; an understanding on how children and adolescents
      perceive dental treatment and the possible pain afterwards. The aim of this study is to
      elucidate how children perceive dental treatment and pain after tooth extractions.

      METHODS: This is a qualitative study using Grounded Theory (GT). Children aged 10-15 years,
      who needs teeth extracted prior orthodontic treatment, will be consecutively enrolled if the
      legal guardians signs the informed consent-form and the child assents to participate. Tooth
      extractions will then be performed by another dentist than the one doing the interviews with
      the children. A treatment protocol, in accordance with today standardized practice, for the
      extractions will be followed. No extra dental treatment is performed, rather this is a part
      of the whole treatment plan for orthodontic treatment. In-depth interview will be performed
      with the children 1-2 weeks after tooth extraction, at a place convenient for the
      child/family. If the participant wishes to, they can be accompanied by their legal guardian
      during the interview. The questions will focus on their experiences of the tooth extraction,
      perceived pain, pain management, coping strategies, and previous experiences of pain and how
      they handled it then. Each interview is calculated to take approximately one hour. In
      Grounded Theory no sample size calculation is applicable. Participants will be included until
      saturation in data is reached, i.e. no new information can be obtained. In GT this is often
      achieved after 10-15 interviews, but when it involves children it is not unlikely that the
      number of participants will be closer to 20, since there is a risk of the interviews not
      being so &quot;rich&quot;. All interviews will be tape recorded, and without further delay, the
      interviews will be transcribed. Data analyses and data collection will be done parallel with
      each other. The transcribed interviews will be analyzed, where codes will be identified.
      These codes will then merge into different preliminary categories. In the following axial
      coding process, each category will be further developed by identifying dimensions and
      characteristics (sub-categories). Relations between data and categories is sought for, and
      hereby a new whole is created. Selective coding will lead to data saturation and validation.
      Saturation can also be achieved by already retrieved data being re-coded.

      KNOWLEDGE GAINS: GT is a theory generating method. This is especially suitable for research
      areas where theories are scarce or completely lacking. A lot of research within the medical
      and dental field today, takes the perspective of the investigator, and far too seldom is
      those directly affected (i.e. the patient), involved. From an ethical point of view, it is
      important to include children and adolescents if the research is targeting this group. If
      knowledge about how children and adolescents perceive pain is gained, this will be an
      important piece in assembling the puzzle of research strategies related to pain.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">April 5, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 27, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Cross-Sectional</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Children's experiences during and after tooth extraction, and it's consequences</measure>
    <time_frame>Fall 2019</time_frame>
    <description>After tooth extraction, on orthodontic indications, participants, 10-15 years of age, are interviewed. The interviews are transcribed and analyzed, identifying codes, which will be clustered into categories. Through different types of methods, used in Grounded Theory, core categories will be identified which together with other categories and sub-categories, will answer the question &quot;what is all this about?&quot;.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">25</enrollment>
  <condition>Attitude</condition>
  <condition>Pain, Postoperative</condition>
  <condition>Pain, Procedural</condition>
  <condition>Child</condition>
  <condition>Adolescent</condition>
  <condition>Tooth Extraction</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Children aged 10-15 years of age, identified as eligable according to inclusion and
        exclusion criteria, during first visit to orthodontist, working in city of Malmö, Sweden.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Healthy individuals

          -  In need of extraction of permanent premolars prior orthodontic treatment

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  If sedation is needed to be able to comply with dental treatment

          -  Do not understand Swedish language
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>10 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>15 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Henrik Berlin, DDS</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Malmö University, Faculty of Odontology</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Henrik Berlin, DDS</last_name>
    <phone>0046 40 665 84 88</phone>
    <email>henrik.berlin@mau.se</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Gunilla Klingberg, Dean</last_name>
    <phone>0046 40 665 84 85</phone>
    <email>gunilla.klingberg@mau.se</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Faculty of Odontology, Malmö University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Malmö</city>
        <state>Scania</state>
        <zip>SE-20506</zip>
        <country>Sweden</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Henrik Berlin, DDS</last_name>
      <phone>0046 40665 84 88</phone>
      <email>henrik.berlin@mau.se</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Gunilla Klingberg, Professor</last_name>
      <phone>0046 40 665 84 85</phone>
      <email>gunilla.klingberg@mau.se</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Sweden</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Berlin H, List T, Ridell K, Davidson T, Toft D, Klingberg G. Postoperative pain profile in 10-15-year-olds after bilateral extraction of maxillary premolars. Eur Arch Paediatr Dent. 2019 Dec;20(6):545-555. doi: 10.1007/s40368-019-00425-9. Epub 2019 Apr 8.</citation>
    <PMID>30963511</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Berlin H, List T, Ridell K, Klingberg G. Dentists' attitudes towards acute pharmacological pain management in children and adolescents. Int J Paediatr Dent. 2018 Mar;28(2):152-160. doi: 10.1111/ipd.12316. Epub 2017 Jul 10.</citation>
    <PMID>28691744</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Charmaz K. Grounded theory. In: Smith JA, Harre R, van Langenhove L, eds. Rethinking methods in psychology, 2nd ed. London: Sage Publications, 1995; 27-49.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Charmaz K. Grounded theory. Objectivist and constructivist methods. In: Denzin NK, Lincoln YS, eds. Handbook of qualitative research, 2nd ed. Thousand Oaks, CA: Sage, 2000; 509-535.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dellve L, Henning Abrahamsson K, Trulsson U, Hallberg LR-M. Grounded theory in public health research. In: Hallberg LR-M, ed. Qualitative methods in public health research: theoretical foundations and practical examples. Lund: Studentlitteratur, 2002; 137-173.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Glaser B, Strauss A. The discovery of grounded theory: strategies for qualitative research. New York: Aldine de Gruyter, 1967.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ashley PF, Parekh S, Moles DR, Anand P, MacDonald LC. Preoperative analgesics for additional pain relief in children and adolescents having dental treatment. Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2016 Aug 8;(8):CD008392. doi: 10.1002/14651858.CD008392.pub3. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>27501304</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>August 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 20, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 20, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 22, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 20, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 20, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">August 22, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Malmö University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Henrik Berlin</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>DDS, senior lecturer</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>grounded theory</keyword>
  <keyword>child</keyword>
  <keyword>adolescent</keyword>
  <keyword>postoperative pain</keyword>
  <keyword>procedural pain</keyword>
  <keyword>tooth extraction</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pain, Postoperative</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pain, Procedural</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Individual participant data (IPD) will not be shared.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

