<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04066829</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HUM00159821</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>1K08DA048110</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04066829</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Default Dosing Settings for Opioid Prescriptions to Adolescents and Young Adults After Tonsillectomy</brief_title>
  <official_title>Default Dosing Settings for Opioid Prescriptions to Adolescents and Young Adults After Tonsillectomy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Michigan</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute on Drug Abuse (NIDA)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Michigan</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will evaluate whether lowering the default number of doses for opioid
      prescriptions written in an electronic health record system can decrease opioid prescribing
      without causing unintended consequences such as worsened pain control.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Suspended</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Enrollment is temporarily paused due to COVID-19; interactions/interventions with current
    participants continue. This is not a suspension of IRB approval
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 30, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 30, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Health Services Research</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
    <masking_description>Intervention is assigned based on location. Participants and providers are 'nudged' but not masked.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of doses in the initial discharge opioid prescription</measure>
    <time_frame>Day of discharge, approximately 1 day</time_frame>
    <description>Detailed in electronic health record</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of patients for whom the number of doses in the discharge opioid prescription equals the number of doses in the new default settings</measure>
    <time_frame>Day of discharge, approximately 1 day</time_frame>
    <description>Detailed in electronic health record</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of patients who had at least one opioid prescription refill from University of Michigan during the two weeks after surgery</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 14</time_frame>
    <description>Detailed in electronic health record</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of patients who saw a University of Michigan provider in an office due to pain during the two weeks after surgery</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 14</time_frame>
    <description>Detailed in electronic health record</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of patients with at least one emergency department and/or hospitalization at University of Michigan for pain during the two weeks after surgery</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 14</time_frame>
    <description>Detailed in electronic health record</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall satisfaction score on pain control during the two weeks after surgery as measured by the post-operative survey.</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 14</time_frame>
    <description>Pain control satisfaction is on a scale of 1-10 with higher scores indicating higher satisfaction</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of patients who reported that their pain was well-controlled as measured by the post-operative survey.</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 14</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of patients whose overall pain control was rated as much worse or worse than expected as measured by the post-operative survey.</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 14</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of patients whose pain has resolved by day 14 after surgery as measured by the post-operative survey.</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 14</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pain in the throat and/or mouth over the past 7 days at its worst as measured by the post-operative survey.</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 14</time_frame>
    <description>Pain control is on a scale of 0-10 with higher scores indicating more pain.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pain in the throat and/or mouth over the past 7 days on average as measured by the post-operative survey.</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 14</time_frame>
    <description>Pain control is on a scale of 0-10 with higher scores indicating worse pain.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of patients with leftover doses of opioids as measured by the post-operative survey.</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 14</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of opioid doses taken during the two weeks after surgery as measured by the post-operative survey.</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 14</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of patients who misused opioids prescribed to others or who misused opioids prescribed to them at least once during the two weeks after surgery as measured by the post-operative survey.</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 14</time_frame>
    <description>Includes any use of opioids prescribed to others or taking one's own opioids in greater amounts, more often, or longer than directed by a doctor</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of patients who misused opioids prescribed to others at least once during the two weeks after surgery as measured by the post-operative survey.</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 14</time_frame>
    <description>Includes any use of opioids prescribed to others</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of patients who misused opioids prescribed to them at least once during the two weeks after surgery as measured by the post-operative survey.</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 14</time_frame>
    <description>Includes taking one's own opioids in greater amounts, more often, or longer than directed by a doctor.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient Health Questionnaire 8-item (PHQ-8) score (depression) as measured by the post-operative survey.</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 14</time_frame>
    <description>This is an 8-item self-report scale, all items are rated on a score of 0-3, for a total range of 0-24. Higher scores indicate more depressive symptoms</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient-Reported Outcomes Measurement Information System (PROMIS)- Pediatric Anxiety - Short Form 8a score as measured by the post-operative survey.</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 14</time_frame>
    <description>This measure is 8 items each scored from 1 to 5 points, with the lowest possible raw score being 8 and the highest possible raw score being 40. Higher scores indicate greater anxiety,</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient-Reported Outcomes Measurement Information System (PROMIS)- Sleep Disturbance - Short Form 8a score as measured by the post-operative survey.</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 14</time_frame>
    <description>This measure is 8 items each scored from 1 to 5 points, with the lowest possible raw score being 8 and the highest possible raw score being 40. Higher scores indicate greater sleep disturbance, i.e. worse sleep.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of patients who saw their primary care doctor (or a colleague) in the office due to pain at least once during the two weeks after surgery as measured by the post-operative survey.</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 14</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of patients who visited a retail clinic due to pain at least once during the two weeks after surgery as measured by the post-operative survey.</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 14</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of patients who visited an urgent care center due to pain at least once during the two weeks after surgery as measured by the post-operative survey.</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 14</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of patients who visited an emergency department and/or were hospitalized due to poorly controlled pain at least once during the two weeks after surgery as measured by the post-operative survey.</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 14</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">450</enrollment>
  <condition>Tonsillectomy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Default setting intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The arm will include all patients undergoing tonsillectomy at C.S. Mott Hospital by a pediatric otolaryngology faculty member at the University of Michigan.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control (Usual Care)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>The arm will include all patients undergoing tonsillectomy at University Hospital, Brighton Center for Specialty Care, or Livonia Center for Specialty Care by a general otolaryngology faculty member at the University of Michigan.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Default setting intervention</intervention_name>
    <description>All patients in the treatment group (patients undergoing tonsillectomy at Mott by pediatric otolaryngology attendings) will have clinicians who are exposed to the new default settings.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Default setting intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Adolescents and young adults aged 12-25 years undergoing tonsillectomy at C.S. Mott
             Hospital, University Hospital, Brighton Center for Specialty Care, or Livonia Center
             for Specialty Care.

          -  Surgeon belongs to the Department of Otolaryngology at the University of Michigan
             Medical School

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with prescription opioid use prior to surgery

          -  Patients undergoing additional procedures at the same time as tonsillectomy (other
             than minor procedures such as tympanostomy tube placement)

          -  Patients enrolled in another study

          -  Patients who are not prescribed opioids post-operatively at discharge

          -  Patients who are enrolled in the Michigan Pain-control Optimization Pathway (M-POP),
             which includes education about pain management and a small initial opioid prescription
             (10 doses)

          -  Patients with hospitalization with length of stay &gt; 1 day after surgery

          -  Patients who do not give consent (cannot reach them to enroll, decline to enroll, or
             non-English speaking)

          -  Additional exclusion criteria for secondary analysis: Patients who do not complete the
             baseline and post-operative day 14 surveys
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>12 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>25 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Kao-Ping Chua</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Michigan</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The University of Michigan</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ann Arbor</city>
        <state>Michigan</state>
        <zip>48109</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 22, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 22, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 26, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 5, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 5, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 7, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Michigan</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Kao-Ping Chua</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor of Pediatrics</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Default settings</keyword>
  <keyword>Opioid prescribing</keyword>
  <keyword>Electronic Health Record</keyword>
  <keyword>Opioid</keyword>
  <keyword>Opioid Use</keyword>
  <keyword>Behavioral intervention</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

