<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04066127</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2018/941</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04066127</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Non-ischaemic Heart Preservation Versus Standard Cold Storage in Human Heart Transplantation</brief_title>
  <acronym>NIHP2</acronym>
  <official_title>A Randomized Controlled Trial Comparing a New State-of-the-art Non Ischemic Heart Preservation Method With the Standard Ischemic Cold Static Storage Method of Donor Hearts in Adult Heart Transplantation</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Region Skane</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Lund University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Skane University Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Region Skane</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The overall aim of this study is to compare a new state-of-the-art ex-vivo organ preservation
      method with standard ischemic cold static storage of donor hearts in adult cardiac
      transplantation.

      Standard heart preservation before transplantation consists of cold ischemic storage of the
      heart. Clinical studies have shown that the morbidity and mortality risk increases with the
      extension of the allograft ischemic time over four hours. For each additional hour the
      mortality risk increase with 25% the first year. This time constraint is costly and results
      in severe logistical problems, leading to loss of transplantable organs. The preliminary
      results from our safety study, where six patients transplanted with the new state-of-the-art
      ex-vivo organ preservation method, have shown promising results.

      The study is a multicenter, prospective, open, blinded endpoint, randomized, controlled
      clinical trial. The primary end-point is survival free of acute cellular rejection (ACR) and
      retransplantation within 1-year post-transplant. ACR will be assessed blinded. The secondary
      end-points are ischemia/reperfusion injury, early graft dysfunction, and QoL.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      SURVEY OF THE FIELD Ischemia and reperfusion (I/R) - elicited tissue injury contributes to
      morbidity and mortality. In organ transplantation, it is a major challenge. The imbalance in
      metabolic supply and demand within the ischemic organ results in tissue hypoxia and
      microvascular dysfunction. The following reperfusion enhances the activation of innate and
      adaptive immune responses resulting in a cell death program.

      A damaged endothelium increases the risk of allograft rejection within 1-year after
      transplantation and a drug treated rejection increases the risk of chronicle rejection and
      five-year mortality. An improved preservation of the endothelium of the coronary arteries is
      therefore instrumental to achieve an improved short- and long-term outcome for the
      transplanted patients.

      Standard heart preservation before transplantation consists of cold ischemic storage of the
      heart. Clinical studies have shown that the mortality risk increases sharply with extension
      of the allograft ischemic time over four hours. For each additional hour, the mortality risk
      increases with 25% the first year. Different myocardial cardioplegic preservation solutions
      and ex-vivo perfusion machines have been developed. Despite some promising experimental
      results, no consistent differences in outcome have been found. Our first-in-man pilot study,
      including 6 NIHP cases, show the device's feasibility and provide the first pieces of
      evidence that machines improves outcome of heart transplantation. However, as these results
      are based on a non-randomized study design with a few patients, a randomized study is needed
      to ensure the effect.

      PURPOSE AND AIMS The purpose of this study is to compare a new state-of-the-art non ischemic
      heart preservation (NIHP) method, on heart allograft function, rejection episodes, and
      quality of life, with the standard ischemic cold static storage (SCS) method of donor hearts
      in adult heart transplantation.

      STUDY DESIGN The study is a multicentre, prospective, randomized, open, blinded endpoint,
      controlled clinical trial. The study will randomly assign eligible patients to be
      transplanted with a donor heart preserved with either a new ex-vivo perfusion method (NIHP)
      or the standard cold static storage (SCS). The study will be performed at Skane University
      Hospital, Karolinska University Hospital, Linköping University Hospital, and Uppsala
      University Hospital, which cover two-thirds of the population in Sweden. Patients listed at
      these centres will be transplanted at Skane University Hospital and then returned to their
      centre for post-transplant care. The data collection, statistical analysis, and presentation
      of results will be done according to the CONSORT criteria. The main outcomes will be reported
      on intention to treat basis.

      PICO Population: Adult patients with end-stage heart failure eligible for heart
      transplantation.

      Intervention: Recipient transplanted with a donor heart preserved using NIHP. Control:
      Recipient transplanted with a donor heart preserved using SCS. Outcome: Survival, rejection,
      graft function, and quality-of-life.

      STATISTICAL ANALYS PLAN Populations for analysis The full analysis set will consist of all
      randomized patients. Following the intent-to-treat principle, patients will be analyzed
      according to the preservation methods (NIHP and SCS, respectively) to which they were
      assigned at randomization. Efficacy variables will be analyzed based on all randomized
      patients as the primary population.

      Patient demographics/other baseline characteristics Baseline value is defined as the last
      non-missing assessment prior to the transplantation. Summary statistics will be provided by
      treatment group for demographics and baseline characteristics, including age, sex, weight,
      height, body mass index (BMI), diagnosis, prior hospitalization, need for inotropic support
      pre-transplant and/or ECMO, CK-MB, TnI, proBNP, and vital signs. Continuous variables will be
      summarized using n, mean, standard deviation, median, minimum, and maximum. Categorical
      variables will be summarized using frequency and percentage. The difference between treatment
      groups will be compared using the Chi-square test for categorical variables or using
      Mann-Whitney U-test for continuous variables. The p-values will be provided for descriptive
      purposes and will not be considered to define any formal basis for determining factors to be
      included in statistical models.

      Analysis of the primary efficacy variable and outcomes The primary objective of this study is
      to evaluate the survival free of allograft rejection and re-transplantation after heart
      transplantation comparing two preservation methods (NIHP versus SCS).

      Time-to-event variables (primary efficacy variable) will be analyzed using the Cox
      proportional hazard model. The estimated hazards ratio and the corresponding two-sided 95%
      confidence interval will be provided. A supplemental log-rank test will be performed.
      Survival function for each treatment group will be estimated by Kaplan-Meier method and the
      Kaplan-Meier curves will be presented. The frequency and percentage of patients who reach the
      primary composite endpoint will be provided by treatment group for the population.

      Analysis of secondary efficacy, exploratory, and safety variables and outcomes The secondary
      objects of this study are to test if the new preservation technique (NIHP) is superior to
      standard preservation technique (SCS) in I/R injury (cTnI and CK-MB), immediate graft
      function, QoL and severe adverse events. Furthermore we will analyse the postoperative renal
      function (minimum creatinine clearance, need for CRRT), postoperative liver function (ASAT,
      ALAT), postoperative pulmonary function (hours in ventilator), SAE, time to no improvement in
      physical activity, resource utilizations (length of stay, and number of visits to
      professional healthcare).

      Continues variables (cTnI, CK-MB, inotrope score, minimum creatinine clearance, hours of
      ventilator, physical activity (calorie use), length of stay, and number of visits to
      professional healthcare, EQ-5D index and EQ VAS) will be analysed using Mann-Witney U-test.
      Additionally, the baseline value of the corresponding variable may be included as a covariate
      if appropriate. The estimated treatment effect and the corresponding two-sided 95% confidence
      interval will be provided.

      Binary variables (primary graft dysfunction, LVEF&lt;40%, RVEF&lt;40%, severe adverse events) will
      be analysed using logistic regression. Additionally, the baseline value of the corresponding
      variable may be included as a covariate if appropriate. The estimated treatment effect and
      the corresponding two-sided 95% confidence interval will be provided. EQ-5D descriptive
      system will be analysed by using χ2-test and Fisher's exact test.

      SAFETY The assessment of safety will be based primarily on the frequency of adverse events
      and laboratory abnormalities. Other safety data will be summarized as appropriate. Laboratory
      data will be summarized by presenting shift tables using extended normal ranges (baseline to
      most extreme post-baseline value), by presenting summary statistics of raw data and change
      from baseline values (mean, medians, standard deviations, ranges). An interim assessment of
      the initial 10 patients in the intervention group will be performed when all of them has
      passed 30-days post-transplant or expired.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">October 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>Acute cellular rejection assessment will be performed by a blinded access</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Survival free of acute cellular rejection and re-transplantation</measure>
    <time_frame>One year</time_frame>
    <description>The primary end-point is defined as the difference between the two treatment arms in survival free of acute cellular rejection ≥1R and re-transplantation within one year. Acute cellular rejection assessment is based on post-transplant myocardial biopsy information and standard clinical evaluation.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>I/R-tissue injury</measure>
    <time_frame>72 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Cardiac troponin I and T, and kinase-muscle/brain measured at end of preservation and 6, 12, 24, 32, 48, and 72 hours after cross-clamp release.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Early allograft dysfunction</measure>
    <time_frame>24 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Moderate or severe primary graft dysfunction (PGD) within 24 hours after x-clamp release. PGD is measured and defined according to Kobashigawa.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Measuring health status</measure>
    <time_frame>One year</time_frame>
    <description>The EQ-5D-5L instrument will be used. This instrument assesses morbidity, self-care, usual activity, pain, and anxiety and depression of patients. The EQ-5D-5L will be completed pre-transplant and at 1, 3, 6, and 12 months visits.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Organ discard rate</measure>
    <time_frame>24 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Number of donor heart which was discarded after retrieval to the transplant unit</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Heart function</measure>
    <time_frame>One year</time_frame>
    <description>An echo is performed day 1, 7, and 3 months and one year post transplant daily to monitor the heart function. Ejection fraction, ventricular dimensions, valve competence TAPSE.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Cardiovascular magnetic resonance</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days</time_frame>
    <description>Patient will be examined by CMR at 21 ±7 days post transplantation with a 1.5 Tesla MR scanner with measurements of cardiac dimensions, cardiac output, local and global myocardial perfusion, tissue characterization, and extracellular volume measurements.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Acute cellular rejection</measure>
    <time_frame>One year</time_frame>
    <description>A national protocol for surveillance and monitoring the patients, including collecting 14 endomyocardial biopsies during the first year. The endomyocardial biopsies will be used to measure grade of acute cellular rejection. Assessment of the biopsies will be performed blinded by three independent pathologists</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Functional capacity</measure>
    <time_frame>One year</time_frame>
    <description>Recording the patient's activity. Patient will carry an activity monitor (step gauge, accelerator, calorie meter) for the whole day, except when sleeping. The activity clock will also collect information about the patient's heart rhythm. Patient retains the activity meter throughout the study period.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Resource use</measure>
    <time_frame>One year</time_frame>
    <description>Length of Stay at Intensive Care Unit (ICU) calculated from time patient arrives into the ICU until the patient is discharged from the ICU. Length of Stay at hospital calculated from date and time of surgery until date and time that the patient is discharged from the hospital. Number of visits to professional healthcare within first year post-transplant.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Costs for organ procurement</measure>
    <time_frame>24 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Defined as cost for personality, transportation and equipment</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Severe adverse events - Cardiac failure</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days</time_frame>
    <description>Cardiac failure is determined as the need for intra-aortic balloon pump (IABP) and/or mechanical circulatory extra corporal support (ECMO) within seven days or need for re-transplantation due to graft failure</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Severe adverse events - Acute bleeding</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days</time_frame>
    <description>Acute bleeding is defined according to the BARC type IV criteria (&gt;2000 ml/24 h and/or requiring re-operation for bleeding, and/or intracranial bleeding, and/or transfusion of &gt;5 red blood cell concentrates/48 h)</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Severe adverse events - Respiratory failure</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days</time_frame>
    <description>Respiratory failure is defined as impairment of respiratory function requiring re-intubation, tracheostomy, vvECMO or the inability to discontinue invasive ventilator support within 48 h after CPB due to respiratory issues and not due to sedation issues.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Severe adverse events - Acute kidney failure</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days</time_frame>
    <description>Acute kidney failure is defined according to the KDIGO criteria as an increase in serum creatinine of &gt;27 μmol/L within 48 hours or 1.5 times baseline within seven days.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Severe adverse events - Permanent stroke</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days</time_frame>
    <description>Permanent stroke is defined as an episode of a computer tomography (CT) verified acute neurological dysfunction to be caused by ischemia or haemorrhage, persisting ≥24 hours or until death.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Severe adverse events - Permanent pacemaker</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days</time_frame>
    <description>Permanent pacemaker is defined as need for a permanent pacemaker implantation two weeks after transplantation</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Transplant; Failure, Heart</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Non-ischemic heart preservation (NIHP)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Non-ischemic hypothermic perfusion (NIHP): The donor heart is preserved using a portable heart-lung machine. The device perfuse the heart continuously with a a new preservation solution at a temperature of 8°C.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Standard cold storage (SCS)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Standard cold static storage (SCS): The donor heart is preserved using a standard crystalloid cardioplegia. The heart is in then storage i a transport box containing ice to keep the temperature around 4-8°C. The device does not perfuse the heart.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Non-ischemic heart preservation (NIHP)</intervention_name>
    <description>The device is a miniaturized and fully automated heart-lung machine, housed in a portable device (weight 32 kg), that enables transportation between hospitals. The reservoir is filled with 2.5 liters of the perfusion solution plus approximately 500 mL compatible washed and leucocyte-filtered red blood cells from the hospital blood bank. The NIHP system software is adjusted to maintain a mean blood pressure of 20-25 mmHg in the aortic root, giving a coronary flow between 150 mL/min and 250 mL/min.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Non-ischemic heart preservation (NIHP)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Standard ischemic cold static storage (SCS)</intervention_name>
    <description>The device is a cool box that enables transportation between hospitals. The heart is stored on ice slush in the box at a temperature of approximately 4-8 °C.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Standard cold storage (SCS)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria recipient:

          -  Age ≥18 years

          -  Signed informed consent form

          -  Listed for heart transplantation

        Exclusion Criteria recipient:

          -  Previous solid organ transplantation

          -  Grown-up congenital heart disease (GUCH)

          -  Kidney failure eGFR&lt;40, calculated by CDK-EPI Creatinine, or ultrafiltration or
             dialysis or rapidly deteriorating kidney function due to a diagnosed renal disease

          -  Coagulopathy due to known hepatic disease or heparin induced thrombocytopenia

          -  Ongoing septicemia defined as positive blood culture (including with a durable VAD)

          -  Incompatible blood group

          -  Not able to understand the information provided during the informed consent procedure

          -  Patients under pre-transplant desensitization protocol

          -  Short term mechanical support pre-transplant (ECMO)

        Inclusion criteria donor:

          -  Age ≤70 years

          -  Accepted as heart donor by the transplant team (research consent from the donor if
             required in country)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Johan Nilsson, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+46 46171000</phone>
    <email>johan.nilsson@med.lu.se</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Skane University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lund</city>
        <state>Skane</state>
        <zip>22185</zip>
        <country>Sweden</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Johan Nilsson, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>171000</phone>
      <phone_ext>46</phone_ext>
      <email>johan.nilsson@med.lu.se</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Sweden</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Steen S, Paskevicius A, Liao Q, Sjöberg T. Safe orthotopic transplantation of hearts harvested 24 hours after brain death and preserved for 24 hours. Scand Cardiovasc J. 2016 Jun;50(3):193-200. doi: 10.3109/14017431.2016.1154598. Epub 2016 Apr 4.</citation>
    <PMID>26882241</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nilsson J, Jernryd V, Qin G, Nozohoor S, Goncalves DC, Ragnarsson S, Paskevicius A, Johansson M, Warheim J, Hoglund P, Sjoberg T, Steen S. Non Ischemic Heart Preservation. J Heart Lung Transpl 2018;37:S13-S.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jernryd V, Metzsch C, Andersson B, Nilsson J. Organ Preservation and Reperfusion Influence on Outcome after Heart Transplantation. The Journal of Heart and Lung Transplantation 2016;35:S193-S.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nilsson J, Ohlsson M, Stehlik J, Lund L, Andersson B. Prediction of Primary Graft Dysfunction After Heart Transplantation. J Heart Lung Transpl 2015;34:S35-S.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Qin G, Sjöberg T, Liao Q, Sun X, Steen S. Intact endothelial and contractile function of coronary artery after 8 hours of heart preservation. Scand Cardiovasc J. 2016 Oct - Dec;50(5-6):362-366. Epub 2016 Aug 3.</citation>
    <PMID>27420646</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Steen S. Preservation of the endothelium in cardiovascular surgery-some practical suggestions--a review. Scand Cardiovasc J. 2001 Oct;35(5):297-301. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>11771819</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nilsson J, Jernryd V, Qin G, Paskevicius A, Sjoberg T, Hoglund P, Steen S. Non Ischemic Heart Preservation - Results from the Safety Study. J Heart Lung Transpl 2019;38:S26-S.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Steen S, Sjöberg T, Pierre L, Liao Q, Eriksson L, Algotsson L. Transplantation of lungs from a non-heart-beating donor. Lancet. 2001 Mar 17;357(9259):825-9.</citation>
    <PMID>11265950</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>August 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 21, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 21, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 26, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 21, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 21, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">August 26, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Region Skane</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Johan Nilsson, MD, PhD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Heart preservation</keyword>
  <keyword>Ex-vivo perfusion</keyword>
  <keyword>Heart transplantation</keyword>
  <keyword>Acute cellular rejection</keyword>
  <keyword>Survival</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Heart Failure</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

