<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04069507</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>201807150</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>1K23AR074520-01A1</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04069507</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Healthy Hip Study: Conservative Management for Pre-arthritic Hip Disorders</brief_title>
  <acronym>HHS</acronym>
  <official_title>Healthy Hip Study: Predictors of Successful Conservative Management for Pre-arthritic Hip Disorders: Prospective Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Washington University School of Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Arthritis and Musculoskeletal and Skin Diseases (NIAMS)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Washington University School of Medicine</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Pre-arthritic hip disorders can cause pain, interfere with daily activities and exercise, and
      lead to the development of osteoarthritis in young adults. Surgical and conservative
      treatment options are being developed and studied, but it is currently unclear why some
      patients improve with a particular treatment plan while others do not. The goal of this
      research project is to develop a tool that predicts which combination of treatment options
      will be most effective for each individual patient.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Significance: Pre-arthritic hip disorders (PAHD) are bony and soft tissue hip morphologies
      that predispose adolescents and young adults to developing hip pain, chronic impairment, and
      early osteoarthritis (OA). Proper management may prevent these sequelae, but current
      evidence, especially regarding non-operative treatment options, is limited.

      Innovation: The majority of PAHD has so far addressed identification and correction of
      abnormal hip anatomy via surgical management. However, a growing body of evidence suggests
      that several other variables including patients' functional goals, movement patterns, and
      psychological profiles also affect their symptomatology. These risk factors are modifiable
      but are not routinely or adequately addressed. The innovation of this project is to improve
      patient outcomes by evaluating patients with a more comprehensive, patient-specific approach
      than is currently the standard of care.

      Purpose: The purpose of this project is to identify predictors of response to non-operative
      PAHD treatment options and to synthesize these predictors into a clinical prediction tool
      that informs non-operative one-year outcomes using data available during patients' initial
      evaluation. In this prospective observational study, patients who present to an orthopedic
      physician for PAHD will be provided instruction on movement pattern training, which is a
      standardized activity modification protocol that addresses how patients perform routine and
      strenuous activities in order to reduce hip pain. It has proven to be efficacious in a
      randomized trial setting, but it is not yet widely discussed by physicians in the clinic
      setting. Patients will report adherence and response to the movement pattern training at
      scheduled intervals for 12 weeks, and they will also report persistent hip-related
      dysfunction and/or progression to surgery at 6 and 12 months. A clinical prediction tool of
      one-year outcomes will be developed using patients' demographics, biopsychosocial profile,
      movement and activity patterns, and anatomy as candidate predictors. The analysis will also
      determine a minimum combination of patient-reported outcome measures (PROMs) that reduces
      survey burden while maintaining similar predictive utility when compared to administration of
      a full battery of hip-specific and general health PROMs.

      Impact: This study is the first step in creating and validating a clinical prediction tool
      which will guide management for patients with pre-arthritic hip disorders. This line of
      research will equip clinicians to provide more accurate prognostic counseling at initial
      evaluation so that an informed shared decision can be made with the patient and initiation of
      an appropriate comprehensive management plan can be expedited.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 15, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 22, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 22, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of successful conservative management</measure>
    <time_frame>1 Year</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of participants who self-report satisfactory overall hip symptoms and no plan to proceed with surgery. The rate will be adjusted for patients' baseline demographics, severity of hip symptoms, biopsychosocial profile, hypermobility profile, movement and activity patterns, and hip anatomy.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of adherence and symptom response to movement pattern training</measure>
    <time_frame>12 Weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of participants who are adherent to the movement pattern training protocol for at least one study interval and who report at least moderate symptomatic improvement on a Global Rating of Change scale as a result of adherence</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of clinically meaningful improvement with conservative management</measure>
    <time_frame>1 Year</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of participants who do not proceed to hip surgery and who either self-report satisfactory overall hip symptoms or meet the minimal clinically important difference (MCID) on the International Hip Outcome Tool-12 (iHOT-12)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">250</enrollment>
  <condition>Femoroacetabular Impingement</condition>
  <condition>Acetabular Dysplasia</condition>
  <condition>Acetabular Labrum Tear</condition>
  <condition>Hip Pain</condition>
  <condition>Rehabilitation</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Participants will be recruited from patients who present to a single tertiary care academic
        orthopedic department. Potentially eligible patients will have presented to an orthopedic
        surgeon or sports medicine physiatrist for a new evaluation of hip pain.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Clinically suspected intra-articular hip joint pain

          -  One or more of the following radiographic/MRI findings: Femoroacetabular impingement,
             acetabular dysplasia, acetabular labral tear, acetabular retroversion, femoral
             anteversion, hip microinstability, and/or normal radiographs

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Surgery recommended and/or scheduled at initial clinic evaluation

          -  &quot;At-risk&quot; acetabular dysplasia (Lateral center edge angle &lt; 15 degrees)

          -  Other intra-articular hip diagnoses including: Slipped capital femoral epiphysis,
             Legg-Calve-Perthes disease, Avascular necrosis

          -  Moderate or severe hip osteoarthritis (Tonnis grade 2 or 3)

          -  Hip/pelvis weakness from brain/nerve disorder (Ex: lumbosacral radiculopathy with
             weakness, cerebral palsy)

          -  Previous same-side hip surgery, hip fracture, hip infection, and/or hip tumor

          -  Inflammatory arthropathy

          -  Known pregnancy
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>15 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>40 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Abby L Cheng, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Washington University School of Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Melissa Armbrecht</last_name>
    <phone>314-747-2828</phone>
    <email>armbrechtm@wustl.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Abby L Cheng, MD</last_name>
    <phone>314-747-2828</phone>
    <email>ChengAL@wustl.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Washington University School of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Saint Louis</city>
        <state>Missouri</state>
        <zip>63110</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Melissa Armbrecht</last_name>
      <phone>314-747-2828</phone>
      <email>ArmbrechtM@wustl.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Harris-Hayes M, Czuppon S, Van Dillen LR, Steger-May K, Sahrmann S, Schootman M, Salsich GB, Clohisy JC, Mueller MJ. Movement-Pattern Training to Improve Function in People With Chronic Hip Joint Pain: A Feasibility Randomized Clinical Trial. J Orthop Sports Phys Ther. 2016 Jun;46(6):452-61. doi: 10.2519/jospt.2016.6279. Epub 2016 Apr 26.</citation>
    <PMID>27117727</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Prather H, Creighton A, Sorenson C, Simpson S, Reese M, Hunt D, Rho M. Anxiety and Insomnia in Young and Middle-Aged Adult Hip Pain Patients With and Without Femoroacetabular Impingement and Developmental Hip Dysplasia. PM R. 2018 May;10(5):455-461. doi: 10.1016/j.pmrj.2017.10.007. Epub 2017 Oct 27.</citation>
    <PMID>29111466</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hunt D, Prather H, Harris Hayes M, Clohisy JC. Clinical outcomes analysis of conservative and surgical treatment of patients with clinical indications of prearthritic, intra-articular hip disorders. PM R. 2012 Jul;4(7):479-87. doi: 10.1016/j.pmrj.2012.03.012. Epub 2012 May 16.</citation>
    <PMID>22595328</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Prather H, Decker G, Bonnette M, Simpson S, Hunt D, Sahrmann S, Cheng A, Nepple J. Hip Radiograph Findings in Patients Aged 40 Years and Under with Posterior Pelvic Pain. PM R. 2019 Aug;11 Suppl 1:S46-S53. doi: 10.1002/pmrj.12180. Epub 2019 Jul 25. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>31059595</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Prather H, Cheng A, Steger-May K, Maheshwari V, VanDillen L. Association of Hip Radiograph Findings With Pain and Function in Patients Presenting With Low Back Pain. PM R. 2018 Jan;10(1):11-18. doi: 10.1016/j.pmrj.2017.06.003. Epub 2017 Jun 16.</citation>
    <PMID>28629805</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Prather H, Cheng A, Steger-May K, Maheshwari V, Van Dillen L. Hip and Lumbar Spine Physical Examination Findings in People Presenting With Low Back Pain, With or Without Lower Extremity Pain. J Orthop Sports Phys Ther. 2017 Mar;47(3):163-172. doi: 10.2519/jospt.2017.6567. Epub 2017 Feb 3.</citation>
    <PMID>28158964</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>October 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 21, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 23, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 28, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 17, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 17, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 21, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Washington University School of Medicine</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Abby Cheng</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Biopsychosocial health</keyword>
  <keyword>Clinical prediction tool</keyword>
  <keyword>Patient-reported outcomes</keyword>
  <keyword>Movement pattern training</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Femoracetabular Impingement</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hip Dislocation, Congenital</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>The investigators are amenable to sharing individual participant data (IPD) when all anticipated data analyses are complete. However, the data generated from this study may be used for future validation efforts of new versions of the clinical prediction tool. The IPD will likely not be made available until there is reasonable confidence that no further data analyses are planned.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

