<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04065776</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HALGG</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04065776</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluation of Hippocampal-Avoidance Using Proton Therapy in Low-Grade Glioma</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase II Study of Hippocampal-Avoidance Using Proton Therapy in Low-Grade Glioma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>St. Jude Children's Research Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>St. Jude Children's Research Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>Yes</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Low-grade gliomas (LGGs) are the most common brain tumors in children, and a subset of these
      tumors are treated definitively with focal radiation therapy (RT). These patients often
      survive for many years after receiving RT and experience late deficits in memory. Verbal
      recall is an important measure of memory and is associated with other important functional
      outcomes, such as problem-solving, independence of every-day functioning, and quality of
      life. Decline in memory, as measured by verbal recall, is associated with RT dose to the
      hippocampi. Therefore, this phase II study investigates the feasibility of reducing RT doses
      to the hippocampi (i.e., hippocampal avoidance [HA]) by using proton therapy for midline or
      suprasellar LGGs.

      Primary Objective:

        -  To determine the feasibility of HA with proton therapy in suprasellar or midline LGGs.
           Feasibility will be established if 70% of plans meet the first or second dose
           constraints shown below.

             1. First priority RT dose constraints for bilateral hippocampi: volume receiving 40
                CGE (V40CGE) ≤ 25%, dose to 100% of Hippocampus (D100%) ≤ 5CGE.

             2. Second priority RT dose constraints for bilateral hippocampi: V40CGE ≤ 35%, D100% ≤
                10 CGE.

                Secondary Objectives:

        -  To estimate the 3-year event-free-survival (EFS) for LGGs treated with HA.

        -  To estimate the change in California Verbal Learning Test short-term delay (CVLT-SD)
           from baseline to 3 years and from baseline to 5 years

        -  To compare CVLT-SD and Cogstate neurocognitive scores in patients with proton therapy
           plans that: (1) meet first priority RT dose constraints, (2) meet second priority RT
           dose constraints but not first priority RT dose constraints, and (3) that did not meet
           either first or second RT priority dose constraints

      Exploratory Objectives:

        -  To describe the change in overall cognitive performance from baseline to 3 years and
           from baseline to 5 years with an age appropriate battery, including gold standard
           measures shown in the published studies to be sensitive to attention, memory processing
           speed and executive function that will afford comparison to historical controls.

        -  To characterize longitudinal changes in connection strength within brain networks in the
           first 3 years after proton therapy and to investigate associations between these changes
           and neurocognitive performance with focus on the hippocampi.

        -  To correlate the distribution and change in L-methyl-11C-methionine positron emission
           tomography (MET-PET) uptake to tumor progression and from baseline to 3 years and to
           investigate whether cases of pseudoprogression exhibit a differential pattern of uptake
           and distribution compared to cases of true progression after controlling for histology.

        -  To investigate the effect of BRAF alteration, tumor histology and tumor location on PFS
           and OS in a prospective cohort of patients treated in a homogenous manner.

        -  To investigate whether the methylation profiles of LGGs differ by tumor location
           (thalamic/midbrain vs. hypothalamic/optic pathway vs. others) and histologies (pilocytic
           astrocytoma vs. diffuse astrocytoma vs. others), which, in conjunction with specific
           genetic alterations, may stratify patients into different subgroups and highlight
           different therapeutic targets.

        -  To record longitudinal measures of circulating tumor DNA (ctDNA) in plasma and correlate
           these measures with radiographic evidence of disease progression.

        -  To bank formalin-fixed, paraffin-embedded (FFPE)/frozen tumors and whole blood from
           subjects for subsequent biology studies not currently defined in this protocol.

        -  To quantify and characterize tumor infiltrating lymphocytes (TILs) and to characterize
           the epigenetics of T cells and the T cell receptor repertoire within the tumor
           microenvironment.

        -  To estimate the cumulative incidence of endocrine deficiencies, vision loss, hearing
           loss and vasculopathy after proton therapy and compare these data to those after photon
           therapy.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      All patients will receive HA proton therapy to 52.2 CGE or 54 CGE in 29 or 30 fractions,
      depending on tumor location. Patients will receive weekly magnetic resonance imaging (MRI)
      scans during the course of proton therapy to monitor changes in solid tumor or cystic volume.
      Such changes may prompt adaptive therapy to improve coverage or minimize the RT dose to
      healthy structures. Neurocognitive outcomes, sensitive to measures of memory and learning,
      will be collected at baseline and continue to 5 years post therapy. Disease evaluation will
      be monitored with brain MRI.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">August 28, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2028</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of plans meet the first or second dose constraints.</measure>
    <time_frame>4 years after activation</time_frame>
    <description>To determine the feasibility of HA with proton therapy in suprasellar or midline LGGs. Feasibility will be established if 70% of plans meet the first or second dose constraints. First RT dose constraints for bilateral hippocampi: volume receiving 40 CGE (V40CGE) ≤ 25%, dose to 100% of hippocampus (D100%) ≤ 5CGE. Second RT dose constraints for bilateral hippocampi: V40CGE ≤ 35%, D100% ≤ 10 CGE.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>EFS of LGGs treated with HA</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>EFS will be calculated from the date of RT starts until disease progression, second malignancy, death of any cause or last follow up date.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The change in CVLT-SD scores from baseline to 3 years</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline evaluation date, 3 years after treatment</time_frame>
    <description>CVLT-SD scores change of patients with HA feasible from baseline evaluation date to 3 years after treatment</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The change in CVLT-SD scores from baseline to 5 years</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline evaluation date, 5 years after treatment</time_frame>
    <description>CVLT-SD scores change from baseline evaluation date to 5 years after treatment</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cogstate neurocognitive scores</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline evaluation date</time_frame>
    <description>Cogstate neurocognitive scores in patients with proton therapy plans</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cogstate neurocognitive scores</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years after treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Cogstate neurocognitive scores in patients with proton therapy plans</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cogstate neurocognitive scores</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years after treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Cogstate neurocognitive scores in patients with proton therapy plans</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>CVLT-SD neurocognitive scores</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline evaluation date</time_frame>
    <description>CVLT-SD neurocognitive scores in patients with proton therapy plans</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>CVLT-SD neurocognitive scores</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years after treatment</time_frame>
    <description>CVLT-SD neurocognitive scores in patients with proton therapy plans</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>CVLT-SD neurocognitive scores</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years after treatment</time_frame>
    <description>CVLT-SD neurocognitive scores in patients with proton therapy plans</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">74</enrollment>
  <condition>Glioma</condition>
  <condition>Pilocytic Astrocytoma</condition>
  <condition>Pilomyxoid Astrocytoma</condition>
  <condition>Pleomorphic Xanthoastrocytoma</condition>
  <condition>Ganglioglioma</condition>
  <condition>Optic Pathway Glioma</condition>
  <condition>Diffuse Astrocytoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Hippocampal-avoidance proton therapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Hippocampal-avoidance proton therapy</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Radiation</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Hippocampal-avoidance proton therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>Hippocampal-avoidance proton therapy</description>
    <arm_group_label>Hippocampal-avoidance proton therapy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients must have a diagnosis of pilocytic astrocytoma, pilomyxoid astrocytoma,
             pleomorphic xanthoastrocytoma, ganglioglioma, optic pathway glioma, diffuse
             astrocytoma, low-grade neuroepithelial tumor, low-grade glioneuronal tumor or LGG, or
             not otherwise specified (NOS).

          -  Patient with eligible diagnosis other than optic pathway glioma or tumors of the
             brainstem/midbrain/tectum has histologic verification of disease at diagnosis or
             recurrence OR

          -  Patient with optic pathway glioma or tumors of the brainstem/midbrain/tectum has
             radiologic verification of disease at diagnosis or recurrence

          -  A repeat biopsy was done because the recurrent tumor was enhancing but did not
             originally enhance because there was a high index of suspicion regarding high-grade
             transformation

          -  Tumor must be located in the suprasellar region or midline structures. Midline
             structures include, but are not limited to, the thalamus, basal ganglia, internal
             capsule, midbrain, tectum, third ventricle, fourth ventricle, cerebellum, pons, and
             medulla. Tumors may involve the optic pathway. For questions about tumor locations
             that are not specified on this list, please contact the Study PI.

          -  Patients must be at least 6 years but less than 22 years of age at the time of
             enrollment.

          -  Patients must have a performance status greater or equal to 70 (use Karnofsky scale
             for patients aged 16 years and older and Lansky scale for patients aged less than 16
             years).

          -  Patients may not receive concurrent chemotherapy or targeted therapy, including but
             not limited to BRAF-inhibitors and MEK-inhibitors.

          -  All patients must be able to undergo contrast-enhanced brain MRI.

          -  All patients must have adequate organ function as described below.

               -  Peripheral absolute neutrophil count (ANC) ≥ 1000/µL

               -  Platelet count ≥ 10,000/µL (transfusion independent)

               -  Patients with seizures may be enrolled if well controlled on anticonvulsants

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients may not have received prior CNS radiation.

          -  Patients with gross total resection and no measurable disease via MRI are not
             eligible. Patients must have measurable disease of at least 1 cm via MRI.

          -  Patients with evidence of metastatic disease are not eligible.

          -  Patients with WHO grade II midline tumors that harbor the H3K27M mutation, IDH-mutant
             gliomas, grade II ependymomas and subependymomas, pituicytomas, spindle cell
             oncocytomas, or granular cell tumors of the sellar region are not eligible.

          -  Patients with tumors that directly invade the hippocampus or with gross tumor volumes
             that extend into the hippocampus are not eligible.

          -  Patients with tumors in the spine or cervicomedullary junction.

          -  Females of child-bearing potential cannot be pregnant or breast feeding. Female
             participants &gt; 10 years of age or post menarche must have a negative serum or urine
             pregnancy test before enrollment. Males and females of reproductive potential may not
             participate unless they have agreed to use an effective contraceptive method.

          -  Patients who are status post resection of bilateral hippocampi. Patients who are
             status post resection of one hippocampus will be eligible for the study and the
             hippocampal dose constraints will be applied to the intact hippocampus.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>6 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>21 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Sahaja Acharya, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>St. Jude Children's Research Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Sahaja Acharya, MD</last_name>
    <phone>866-278-5833</phone>
    <email>referralinfo@stjude.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>St. Jude Children's Research Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Memphis</city>
        <state>Tennessee</state>
        <zip>38105</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sahaja Acharya, MD</last_name>
      <phone>866-278-5833</phone>
      <email>referralinfo@stjude.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Sahaja Acharya</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.stjude.org</url>
    <description>St. Jude Children's Research Hospital</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.stjude.org/protocols</url>
    <description>Clinical Trials Open at St. Jude</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 20, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 20, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 22, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 8, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 8, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 10, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Glioma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Astrocytoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ganglioglioma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

