<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04068506</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>123</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04068506</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Analgesic Effects of Gabapentin and Paracetamol</brief_title>
  <acronym>GABA</acronym>
  <official_title>Comparison of Analgesic Effects of Gabapentin and Paracetamol in Patients With Hand Injury</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Dow University of Health Sciences</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Dow University of Health Sciences</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This research is about the effects of drug gabapentin; which is an amino acid that is
      structurally similar to neurotransmitter GABA. It is a novel drug used for the treatment of
      postoperative pain with analgesic properties having unique mechanism of action. This study
      reviews clinical effects of this agent in hand injury patients managed at the Department of
      Plastics &amp; Reconstructive Surgery, Dow University of Health Sciences &amp; Dr. Ruth KM Pfau Civil
      Hospital Karachi.

      This study aims to inquire the analgesic properties of gabapentin in the patients and to
      further investigate its comparison with the equivalent dose of paracetamol given 6 hours
      after undergoing operative procedure. Acetaminophen is well tolerated when administered in
      therapeutic dose for pain management. It is a principal drug used as pain reliever and as an
      antipyretic regimen.

      This is an experimental study in which a pre-coded questionnaire would be approved in the
      research for appraising the intensity of pain after intervening operative procedure using
      visual analogue scale, measuring the pain intensity from 0-10. The questions regarding pain
      intensity will be inquired after administrating the drug six hours postoperatively. The drug
      will be prescribed by the doctor on duty having no knowledge regarding the given drug or the
      group in which he/she is administrating the drug; further questionnaire will be filled by the
      two co-investigators who will be trained by principal investigator, how to take correct
      information.

      Sample size was calculated using www.openepi.com using the previous literature searches of
      similar research and 50 patients (25 in each group) will be randomly selected from the ward
      of a known case of hand injury. Group A patients will receive 600 mg of gabapentin post
      operatively while group B will receive 1 g of paracetamol for management of pain
      postoperatively orally.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Gabapentin is an anti-convulsion medication and has a high affinity for voltage-gated calcium
      channel throughout the brain, acts by inhibition of release of excitatory neurotransmitters.
      As a lipophilic substance, it shows linear pharmacokinetics and has oral bioavailability
      greater than 90%. Gabapentin is used in a variety of condition as a therapeutic measure
      involving diabetic neuropathy, post-herpetic neuralgia, in partial seizures, restless leg
      syndrome, post-menopausal hot flashes, anxiety, resistant mood disorders, essential tremors,
      and numerous other modalities. Gabapentin is a muscle relaxant and anti-spasmodic, its
      analgesic effect has also be identified for moderate to severe pain.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">January 21, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">January 7, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>A total of 50 patients who fulfill the inclusion criteria will be approached and written consent will be signed by the participants prior to the interview. Participants will be divided into two groups divided equally i.e. gabapentin group and paracetamol group. Gabapentin group received 600 mg dose while the control/other group received 1 gram (1000 mg) of paracetamol as a postoperative analgesic agent.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>Investigators will divide the calculated sample size into two groups A and B in which all the participants have the same probability of being included in the study. Two unrecognizable envelopes separating both drugs gabapentin and paracetamol with equivalent dose will be administered with the specific code number labeled by the principal investigator and will be prescribed by the on-duty doctor to the patients in tablet form once orally allowed after surgery. Analgesic effects will be inquired after 6 hours of drug administration. Further questions will be asked according to the questionnaire by the co-investigators having no knowledge of the given drug to participant.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Comparison of analgesic effects of Gabapentin and paracetamol in patients with hand injury</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>The outcome of this study will be finding that how much gabapentin is effective in improving pain over paracetamol by simply inquiring about the analgesic effect of both drugs with the help of Visual analogue scale measuring pain intensity from 1 - 10 and how much each drug adversely effects individual's health by assessment of any unwanted symptoms like: nausea, vomiting, headache, dizziness, etc. So, that certainty about its effect and efficacy over paracetamol in relieving pain can be assessed.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">68</enrollment>
  <condition>Hand Injuries</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Gabapentin 600 mg Tab</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group B</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Paracetamol 1000 mg Tab</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Gabapentin 600 mg Tab</intervention_name>
    <description>Gabapentin 600 mg Tab is a drug of choice for treating postoperative pain.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Group B</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Neurontin</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        1. Inclusion Criteria:

               1. Patients between 18-60 years of age

               2. Patients Undergoing hand surgery in the Department of Plastics and Reconstructive
                  Surgery, Dr. Ruth KM Pfau Civil Hospital Karachi, Dow University of Health
                  Sciences

          2. Exclusion criteria:

               1. Pregnant women

               2. Any patient presenting with the signs of:

                    -  Arrhythmia

                    -  Myocardial ischemia

                    -  Cognitive impairment

                    -  Psychiatric disorders

                    -  Drug abuse

               3. Patients sensitive to any epileptic drug or taking any anti-epileptic drug

               4. Having severe and multiple injuries.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>60 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Hyder Ali, MBBS,FCPS</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Assistant professor at Dr.Ruth K.M pfau Civil Hospital Karachi,DUHS</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Dr. Ruth K.M. Pfau Civil Hospital Karachi</name>
      <address>
        <city>Karachi</city>
        <state>Sindh</state>
        <country>Pakistan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Pakistan</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK2658/</url>
    <description>Improving the Quality of Care Through Pain Assessment and Management.</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.onlinejets.org/article.asp?issn=0974-2700;year=2017;volume=10;issue=1;spage=19;epage=25;aulast=Ghiya</url>
    <description>A descriptive study of hand injuries presenting to the adult emergency department of a tertiary care center in urban India.</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/12873949</url>
    <description>Postoperative pain experience: results from a national survey suggest postoperative pain continues to be undermanaged.</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4009126/</url>
    <description>Gabapentin in Acute Postoperative Pain Management</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/12198050</url>
    <description>Pain as a factor complicating recovery and discharge after ambulatory surgery.</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://jpet.aspetjournals.org/content/298/1/15.long</url>
    <description>The Anticonvulsant, Antihyperalgesic Agent Gabapentin Is an Agonist at Brain γ-Aminobutyric Acid Type B Receptors Negatively Coupled to Voltage-Dependent Calcium Channels</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC3567599/</url>
    <description>Prescribing gabapentin off label: Perspectives from psychiatry, pain and neurology specialists</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>https://www.jmcp.org/doi/10.18553/jmcp.2003.9.6.559</url>
    <description>Examination of the evidence for off-label use of gabapentin.</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC5346867/</url>
    <description>Randomized, controlled, multicentre clinical trial of the antipyretic effect of intravenous paracetamol in patients admitted to hospital with infection</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>January 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 11, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 23, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 28, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 22, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 22, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 27, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Dow University of Health Sciences</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Hyder Ali</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>assistant professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hand Injuries</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Gabapentin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <pending_results>
    <submitted>February 4, 2020</submitted>
    <returned>February 20, 2020</returned>
    <submitted>February 25, 2020</submitted>
    <returned>March 6, 2020</returned>
    <submitted>March 20, 2020</submitted>
    <returned>April 1, 2020</returned>
  </pending_results>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

