<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04066699</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>VMT-01-003</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04066699</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Percutaneous Localization: Open-label Registry of Thoracic Surgery</brief_title>
  <acronym>PLOTS</acronym>
  <official_title>Intraoperative, Percutaneous Localization of Peripheral Pulmonary Nodules for Resection: a Prospective, Open-Label, Multi-Center Registry Study of Thoracic Surgery Outcomes.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Veran Medical Technologies</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Veran Medical Technologies</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>Yes</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The objectives of this study are to evaluate intraoperative percutaneous lung lesion marking
      assisted by electromagnetic guided percutaneous navigation and related tools.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The Intraoperative, Percutaneous Localization of Peripheral Pulmonary Nodules for Resection:
      a Prospective, Open-Label, Multi-Center Registry Study of Thoracic Surgery Outcomes (PLOTS)
      registry is aimed at developing a high quality set of data regarding intraoperative
      percutaneous localization of peripheral pulmonary nodules (PPNs), and then identifying and
      promulgating efficient, evidence-based best practices for this technique. The resection
      procedure itself is standard of care and follows the investigator's standard protocol.

      Successful localization of PPNs is a challenge involving multiple factors, beginning with the
      subjects' health, lung function and also factors specific to the nodule including location
      within the lung, size, distance from the lung surface, whether solid or ground glass and
      proximity to a fissure. Hard to see or palpate nodules are currently localized with dye
      and/or hook wires or fiducials, either endoscopically or percutaneously. Successful, large,
      prospective studies have not been reported using modern electro-magnetic navigation
      (EMN)-guided percutaneous intraoperative localization, and different techniques (dye vs.
      fiducial vs. hook wire etc.) have not been broadly evaluated. It is for these reasons that
      the different localization techniques used with EMN-guided percutaneous localization will be
      collected for patients having a suspicious nodule and who undergo percutaneous
      intra-operative localization and immediate resection.

      This registry aims to record the localization techniques used by thoracic surgeons and
      IP/surgical teams to identify PPNs using the SPiN Thoracic Navigation System™ in the hands of
      trained physicians. The objectives of this study will be to accomplish the primary and
      secondary objectives listed below, and to observe localization in a real world context of
      pulmonary resection.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 10, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational [Patient Registry]</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <target_duration>6 Weeks</target_duration>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of successful percutaneous localization and removal of PPN.</measure>
    <time_frame>Duration of procedure.</time_frame>
    <description>Successful percutaneous localization of PPN defined as the percentage of subjects in whom the nodule is successfully localized and removed in the first resected specimen.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Collect safety data for localization procedure.</measure>
    <time_frame>Duration of procedure.</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Report localization method and technique.</measure>
    <time_frame>Duration of procedure.</time_frame>
    <description>Details regarding the localization technique will be collected, including the materials used. If dye (methylene blue, ICG etc.) is used the volume will be collected. Other materials include microcoils, hook wires, etc..</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Collect data on intraoperative percutaneous localization time and duration of total surgical procedure.</measure>
    <time_frame>Duration of procedure.</time_frame>
    <description>The time of the localization procedure will be recorded. The length of the entire surgical procedure will also be recorded.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Record nodule characteristics, including location in the lobe, distance from pleura, distance from surface of skin to target, morphological appearance, solid vs. ground glass etc.</measure>
    <time_frame>Duration of procedure.</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Record weight of excised tissue and margin.</measure>
    <time_frame>Duration of procedure.</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Report type of surgical resection performed and the resection technique used.</measure>
    <time_frame>Duration of procedure.</time_frame>
    <description>The surgical resection may include segmentectomy or wedge using the VATS, RATS, or thoracotomy techniques.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Lung Lesion(s) Requiring Evaluation</condition>
  <condition>Pulmonary Metastasis</condition>
  <condition>Pulmonary Nodule, Solitary</condition>
  <condition>Peripheral Lung Lesions</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Localization</arm_group_label>
    <description>Electromagnetic navigation (EMN) guided percutaneous localization of suspicious lung lesion(s).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Percutaneous localization of suspicious lung lesion(s) using electromagnetic navigation and tools.</intervention_name>
    <description>Transthoracic localization of suspicious lung lesion(s) in preparation for subsequent resection.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Localization</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>SPiN Thoracic Navigation System™</other_name>
    <other_name>Veran System</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        The target subject population includes adult subjects (18 years - 85 years), with small,
        suspicious lung lesions. Patients with small, indeterminate PPNs that, in the judgment of
        the thoracic surgeon, based on surgical risk and risk of malignancy, warrant lung resection
        via a percutaneous localization approach. Data will be collected from study subjects having
        a PPN between 0.4 cm and 3.2 cm in greatest dimension, that are accessible to percutaneous
        localization, who consent to and undergo intraoperative dye/wire localization procedure
        followed by surgical lung resection.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Subject's physician and/or thoracic surgeon have deemed/has deemed that the surgical
             removal of the PPN is appropriate.

          -  A clinical decision has been made to use the SPiN Thoracic Navigation System™.

          -  Subject is at least 18 years of age at time of study entry.

          -  Subject is able to read, understand, and voluntarily sign the IRB-approved informed
             consent document prior to the performance of any study-specific procedures. IRB-
             approved translation may be used if indicated. Reasonable accommodation of visually
             impaired subjects will be allowed.

          -  Subject is able to tolerate general anesthesia.

          -  Subject has a target nodule between 0.4 cm and 3.2 cm in greatest dimension;

          -  The target nodule is in a location that is accessible for percutaneous localization in
             the judgement of the surgeon.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects with any other concomitant treatment or medical condition that, in the
             opinion of the clinician, would render peripheral nodule resection more hazardous than
             beneficial.

          -  Subject is pregnant.

          -  Pulmonary nodule is greater than 3.2 cm.

          -  Subjects with significant coagulopathy having INR &gt; 2.0 or PTT &gt; 2x normal.

          -  Subject is unable to tolerate general anesthesia.

          -  Obese subject, impacting percutaneous access (BMI &gt; 50).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Faiz Bhora, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Vassar Brothers Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Susan Shelby, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>314-659-8500</phone>
    <email>PLOTS@veranmedical.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Kaiser Permanente</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lone Tree</city>
        <state>Colorado</state>
        <zip>80124</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Lanny Dunham, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>MedStar Washington Hospital Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Washington</city>
        <state>District of Columbia</state>
        <zip>20010</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>John Lazar, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Northern Light Eastern Maine Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bangor</city>
        <state>Maine</state>
        <zip>04401</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jawad Latif, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Vassar Brothers Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Poughkeepsie</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>12601</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Faiz Bhora, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Houston Methodist Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Min Kim, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Wisconsin</name>
      <address>
        <city>Madison</city>
        <state>Wisconsin</state>
        <zip>53792</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Malcolm DeCamp, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Semaan RW, Lerner AD, Lee HJ, Feller-Kopman D, Yarmus LB. Electromagnetic Guidance for the Diagnosis of Pulmonary Nodules: Don't Put the Nail in the Coffin. Am J Respir Crit Care Med. 2016 Jul 1;194(1):121. doi: 10.1164/rccm.201602-0243LE.</citation>
    <PMID>27367891</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mallow C, Lee H, Oberg C, Thiboutot J, Akulian J, Burks AC, Luna B, Benzaquen S, Batra H, Cardenas-Garcia J, Toth J, Heidecker J, Belanger A, McClune J, Osman U, Lakshminarayanan V, Pastis N, Silvestri G, Chen A, Yarmus L. Safety and diagnostic performance of pulmonologists performing electromagnetic guided percutaneous lung biopsy (SPiNperc). Respirology. 2019 May;24(5):453-458. doi: 10.1111/resp.13471. Epub 2019 Jan 24.</citation>
    <PMID>30675961</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Thiboutot J, Lee HJ, Silvestri GA, Chen A, Wahidi MM, Gilbert CR, Pastis NJ, Los J, Barriere AM, Mallow C, Salwen B, Dinga MJ, Flenaugh EL, Akulian JA, Semaan R, Yarmus LB. Study Design and Rationale: A Multicenter, Prospective Trial of Electromagnetic Bronchoscopic and Electromagnetic Transthoracic Navigational Approaches for the Biopsy of Peripheral Pulmonary Nodules (ALL IN ONE Trial). Contemp Clin Trials. 2018 Aug;71:88-95. doi: 10.1016/j.cct.2018.06.007. Epub 2018 Jun 7.</citation>
    <PMID>29885373</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>December 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 21, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 21, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 26, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 3, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 3, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">December 4, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Surgical Lung Resection</keyword>
  <keyword>Percutaneous Localization</keyword>
  <keyword>Electromagnetic Navigation</keyword>
  <keyword>Transthoracic Localization</keyword>
  <keyword>Peripheral Pulmonary Nodule(s)</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Multiple Pulmonary Nodules</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Solitary Pulmonary Nodule</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

