<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04068025</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>16.01.2018 18/10</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04068025</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Information, Motivation, Behavioral Skills Model on Urinary Incontinence and Quality of Life in Men</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Effect of Information, Motivation, Behavioral Skills Model on Urinary Incontinence and Quality of Life in Men With Overactive Bladder: A Randomized Controlled Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Ankara Yildirim Beyazıt University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Ankara Yildirim Beyazıt University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Multiple studies have shown that education based on the IMB model is effective at bringing
      about health-related behavior change. The IMB model was found to be effective in developing
      healthy behaviors aimed at maintaining heart health, providing behavior to prevent smoking
      addiction, diabetes management, correct nutrition in iron deficiency anemia, and using
      condoms to prevent HIV. There are no studies in the literature regarding the adaptation of
      the IMB model to behavioral therapy in patients with OAB or urinary incontinence. To address
      this, there we aimed to investigate the effect of the IMB model on urinary incontinence and
      quality of life in men with OAB.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study aimed to investigate the effect of the Information, Motivation, Behavioral Skills
      Model (IMB) on urinary incontinence and quality of life in men with overactive bladder.

      This is a single-center, parallel-group, open-label, randomized controlled clinical trial.

      This study was conducted between February 2018 and February 2019, with a total of 60 male
      patients admitted to the urology clinic of a training and research hospital. Patients over
      the age of 18, male, and with overactive bladder were included in the study.

      Participants were randomized into two equal groups: the intervention group (n=30) and control
      group (n=30). Structured bladder training with the IMB model was applied to the intervention
      group. This model was not applied to the control group. The primary outcome was the mean
      score change over the severity of incontinence measured by the International Consultation on
      Incontinence Questionnaire-Short Form (ICIQ-SF). The other outcomes were measured by the
      Urogenital Distress Inventory (UDI-6), Incontinence Impact Questionnaire-7 (IIQ-7), and
      Urinary Incontinence Information Rating scores. All outcome measures were evaluated before
      and 6 months after the training. Bladder training with IMB model was found to be effective at
      ameliorating urinary incontinence and improving quality of life in patients with an
      overactive bladder.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 1, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">February 1, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">August 1, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>A Change on Incontinence Severity Measured by The International Consultation on Incontinence Questionnaire-Short Form (ICIQ-SF)</measure>
    <time_frame>20 minutes before and 6 months after the training</time_frame>
    <description>The primary outcome measure was the mean score change from baseline incontinence severity at 6 months measured by the International Consultation on Incontinence Questionnaire-Short Form (ICIQ-SF). The ICIQ-SF consists of a total of six items, including the birth date, gender and urinary incontinence characteristics. The score range of this scale is 0-21. High scores indicate increased urinary incontinence severity.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The Urogenital Distress Inventory (UDI-6)</measure>
    <time_frame>20 minutes before and 6 months after the training</time_frame>
    <description>UDI-6 is short forms of the scales developed by Uebersax et al. with six and seven questions, respectively. The Turkish validity study of these forms was made by Cam et al., who reported a Cronbach's alpha coefficient for UDI-6 as 0.74. In this study, the Cronbach's alpha coefficient for UDI-6 was 0.786 before training and 0.746 after the training implementations. Each item was scored between zero and 3, and the total score was calculated in the range of zero to 100. Higher scores obtained from these scales indicate that bladder function is worse.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The Incontinence Impact Questionnaire-7 (IIQ-7)</measure>
    <time_frame>20 minutes before and 6 months after the training</time_frame>
    <description>IIQ-7 is short forms of the scales developed by Uebersax et al. with six and seven questions, respectively. The Turkish validity study of these forms was made by Cam et al., who reported a Cronbach's alpha coefficient for IIQ-7 as 0.87. In this study, the Cronbach's alpha coefficient for IIQ-7 was 0.933 before training and 0.902 after the training implementations. Each item was scored between zero and 3, and the total score was calculated in the range of zero to 100. Higher scores obtained from these scales indicate that bladder function is worse.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>The Urinary Incontinence Information Evaluation Form (UIIEF)</measure>
    <time_frame>20 minutes before and 6 months after the training</time_frame>
    <description>Urinary Incontinence Information Evaluation Form (UIIEF) is an information form consisting of 10 multiple choice questions prepared by researchers literature-based and expert opinions. Each item is scored between 0-10 and the total score is calculated in the range of 0-100. The scores obtained from this form provide information about the change of information score means.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Overactive Bladder</condition>
  <condition>Quality of Life</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>No Intervention: Control group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients in the control group were given usual care by a health professional who was not involved in the study and who worked in the Department of Urology. After the end of the study, the patients in the control group were also given structured bladder training similar to the patients in the intervention group.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>the IMB model</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Structured bladder training was applied to the patients in the intervention group via the IMB model.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Assigned Interventions</intervention_name>
    <description>Information: In the information step of the bladder training program given through the IMB model, training was given about pelvic floor muscle exercises, bladder program formation, and lifestyle change. The training was conducted face-to-face by the nurse researcher for about 15-20 min, and the training booklet was given to the patients.
Motivation: The patients in the intervention group were interviewed by the nurse researcher by phone or face-to-face in the 1st, 3rd, and 6th months after the training. The patients were motivated by providing information and counseling on the necessary issues. This process was carried out using motivational interviewing principles. Patients were given positive behavioral feedback and encouraged to control urinary incontinence.
Behavioral Skills: Behavioral skills related to urinary incontinence were evaluated 6 months after the training,together with their effects on urinary incontinence symptom score and quality of life.</description>
    <arm_group_label>the IMB model</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Male patient

          -  Over 18 years old

          -  Overactive Bladder

          -  Urge urinary incontinence

          -  Voluntarily agreed to participate in the research

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Benign prostatic hyperplasia

          -  Prostate cancer

          -  Congenital urinary anomalies

          -  Neurological or spinal cord injury,

          -  Diabetes mellitus

          -  Hypertension

          -  A mental disability

          -  Receive medical treatment for incontinence
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Hilal Tüzer, RN, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Ankara Yildirim Beyazıt University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Elif Gezginci, RN, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Saglik Bilimleri Universitesi</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Tuba Yılmazer, RN, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Ankara Yildirim Beyazıt University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ankara Yildirim Beyazit University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ankara</city>
        <zip>06010</zip>
        <country>Turkey</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Turkey</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.auanet.org/guidelines/overactive-bladder-(oab)-guideline</url>
    <description>American Urological Association (AUA) (2019). Diagnosis and Treatment of Non-Neurogenic Overactive Bladder (OAB) in Adults (2019)</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.k4health.org/sites/default/files/peyman_and_abdollahi_2016.pdf</url>
    <description>Peyman N, Abdollahi M. Using of information-motivation-behavioral skills model on nutritional behaviors in controlling anemia among girl students. J Research&amp;Health. 2016; 12</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1877042810017544</url>
    <description>Gavgani RM, Poursharifi H, Aliasgarzadeh A. Effectiveness of Information-Motivation and Behavioral skill (IMB) model in improving self-care behaviors &amp; Hba1c measure in adults with type2 diabetes in Iran-Tabriz. Procedia Social and Behavioral Sciences.</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Abrams P, Cardozo L, Fall M, Griffiths D, Rosier P, Ulmsten U, van Kerrebroeck P, Victor A, Wein A; Standardisation Sub-committee of the International Continence Society. The standardisation of terminology of lower urinary tract function: report from the Standardisation Sub-committee of the International Continence Society. Neurourol Urodyn. 2002;21(2):167-78.</citation>
    <PMID>11857671</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Stewart WF, Van Rooyen JB, Cundiff GW, Abrams P, Herzog AR, Corey R, Hunt TL, Wein AJ. Prevalence and burden of overactive bladder in the United States. World J Urol. 2003 May;20(6):327-36. Epub 2002 Nov 15.</citation>
    <PMID>12811491</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Irwin DE, Milsom I, Hunskaar S, Reilly K, Kopp Z, Herschorn S, Coyne K, Kelleher C, Hampel C, Artibani W, Abrams P. Population-based survey of urinary incontinence, overactive bladder, and other lower urinary tract symptoms in five countries: results of the EPIC study. Eur Urol. 2006 Dec;50(6):1306-14; discussion 1314-5. Epub 2006 Oct 2.</citation>
    <PMID>17049716</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Irwin DE, Abrams P, Milsom I, Kopp Z, Reilly K; EPIC Study Group. Understanding the elements of overactive bladder: questions raised by the EPIC study. BJU Int. 2008 Jun;101(11):1381-7. doi: 10.1111/j.1464-410X.2008.07573.x. Epub 2008 Mar 10.</citation>
    <PMID>18336602</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Eapen RS, Radomski SB. Gender differences in overactive bladder. Can J Urol. 2016 Feb;23(Suppl 1):2-9. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26924589</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jeon E, Park HA. Development of the IMB Model and an Evidence-Based Diabetes Self-management Mobile Application. Healthc Inform Res. 2018 Apr;24(2):125-138. doi: 10.4258/hir.2018.24.2.125. Epub 2018 Apr 30.</citation>
    <PMID>29770246</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zarani F, Besharat MA, Sarami G, Sadeghian S. An information-motivation-behavioral skills (IMB) model-based intervention for CABG patients. Int J Behav Med. 2012 Dec;19(4):543-9. doi: 10.1007/s12529-011-9193-2.</citation>
    <PMID>21948041</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kiene SM, Fisher WA, Shuper PA, Cornman DH, Christie S, Macdonald S, Pillay S, Mahlase G, Fisher JD. Understanding HIV transmission risk behavior among HIV-infected South Africans receiving antiretroviral therapy: an information--motivation--behavioral skills model analysis. Health Psychol. 2013 Aug;32(8):860-8. doi: 10.1037/a0030554. Epub 2013 Mar 11.</citation>
    <PMID>23477576</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Konkle-Parker DJ, Amico KR, McKinney VE. Effects of an intervention addressing information, motivation, and behavioral skills on HIV care adherence in a southern clinic cohort. AIDS Care. 2014;26(6):674-83. doi: 10.1080/09540121.2013.845283. Epub 2013 Oct 14.</citation>
    <PMID>24116922</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Uebersax JS, Wyman JF, Shumaker SA, McClish DK, Fantl JA. Short forms to assess life quality and symptom distress for urinary incontinence in women: the Incontinence Impact Questionnaire and the Urogenital Distress Inventory. Continence Program for Women Research Group. Neurourol Urodyn. 1995;14(2):131-9.</citation>
    <PMID>7780440</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cam C, Sakalli M, Ay P, Cam M, Karateke A. Validation of the short forms of the incontinence impact questionnaire (IIQ-7) and the urogenital distress inventory (UDI-6) in a Turkish population. Neurourol Urodyn. 2007;26(1):129-33.</citation>
    <PMID>17083117</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Aydın Sayılan A, Özbaş A. The Effect of Pelvic Floor Muscle Training On Incontinence Problems After Radical Prostatectomy. Am J Mens Health. 2018 Jul;12(4):1007-1015. doi: 10.1177/1557988318757242. Epub 2018 Mar 14.</citation>
    <PMID>29540090</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shell DF, Newman IM, Perry CM, Folsom AR. Changing intentions to use smokeless tobacco: an application of the IMB model. Am J Health Behav. 2011 Sep;35(5):568-80.</citation>
    <PMID>22040618</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Walsh JL, Senn TE, Scott-Sheldon LA, Vanable PA, Carey MP. Predicting condom use using the Information-Motivation-Behavioral Skills (IMB) model: a multivariate latent growth curve analysis. Ann Behav Med. 2011 Oct;42(2):235-44. doi: 10.1007/s12160-011-9284-y.</citation>
    <PMID>21638196</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Osborn CY, Egede LE. Validation of an Information-Motivation-Behavioral Skills model of diabetes self-care (IMB-DSC). Patient Educ Couns. 2010 Apr;79(1):49-54. doi: 10.1016/j.pec.2009.07.016. Epub 2009 Aug 21.</citation>
    <PMID>19699601</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mittal M, Senn TE, Carey MP. Intimate partner violence and condom use among women: does the information-motivation-behavioral skills model explain sexual risk behavior? AIDS Behav. 2012 May;16(4):1011-9. doi: 10.1007/s10461-011-9949-3.</citation>
    <PMID>21484278</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Malow RM, Dévieux JG, Stein JA, Rosenberg R, Lerner BG, Attonito J, Villalba K. Neurological function, information-motivation-behavioral skills factors, and risk behaviors among HIV-positive alcohol users. AIDS Behav. 2012 Nov;16(8):2297-308. doi: 10.1007/s10461-012-0246-6.</citation>
    <PMID>22767030</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ndebele M, Kasese-Hara M, Greyling M. Application of the information, motivation and behavioural skills model for targeting HIV risk behaviour amongst adolescent learners in South Africa. SAHARA J. 2012 Dec;9 Suppl 1:S37-47. doi: 10.1080/17290376.2012.744903.</citation>
    <PMID>23234378</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kudo Y. Effectiveness of a condom use educational program developed on the basis of the Information-Motivation-Behavioral Skills model. Jpn J Nurs Sci. 2013 Jun;10(1):24-40. doi: 10.1111/j.1742-7924.2012.00207.x. Epub 2012 Mar 30.</citation>
    <PMID>23735087</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ybarra ML, Korchmaros JD, Prescott TL, Birungi R. A Randomized Controlled Trial to Increase HIV Preventive Information, Motivation, and Behavioral Skills in Ugandan Adolescents. Ann Behav Med. 2015 Jun;49(3):473-85. doi: 10.1007/s12160-014-9673-0.</citation>
    <PMID>25633626</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ribeiro LH, Prota C, Gomes CM, de Bessa J Jr, Boldarine MP, Dall'Oglio MF, Bruschini H, Srougi M. Long-term effect of early postoperative pelvic floor biofeedback on continence in men undergoing radical prostatectomy: a prospective, randomized, controlled trial. J Urol. 2010 Sep;184(3):1034-9. doi: 10.1016/j.juro.2010.05.040.</citation>
    <PMID>20643454</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Thüroff JW, Abrams P, Andersson KE, Artibani W, Chapple CR, Drake MJ, Hampel C, Neisius A, Schröder A, Tubaro A. EAU guidelines on urinary incontinence. Eur Urol. 2011 Mar;59(3):387-400. doi: 10.1016/j.eururo.2010.11.021. Epub 2010 Nov 24.</citation>
    <PMID>21130559</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nambiar AK, Bosch R, Cruz F, Lemack GE, Thiruchelvam N, Tubaro A, Bedretdinova DA, Ambühl D, Farag F, Lombardo R, Schneider MP, Burkhard FC. EAU Guidelines on Assessment and Nonsurgical Management of Urinary Incontinence. Eur Urol. 2018 Apr;73(4):596-609. doi: 10.1016/j.eururo.2017.12.031. Epub 2018 Feb 3.</citation>
    <PMID>29398262</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>August 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 22, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 22, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 28, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 22, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 22, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">August 28, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>incontinence</keyword>
  <keyword>male</keyword>
  <keyword>overactive bladder</keyword>
  <keyword>quality of life</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Urinary Incontinence</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Enuresis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Urinary Bladder, Overactive</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

