<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04066894</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2016-0754</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2019-02649</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>2016-0754</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>P30CA016672</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04066894</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Sacral Nerve Stimulation in Treating Low Anterior Resection Syndrome or Fecal Incontinence in Patients With Locally Advanced Rectal Cancer or Other Pelvic Cancer, the RESTORE Study</brief_title>
  <official_title>Sacral Nerve Stimulation for Low Anterior Resection Syndrome or Fecal Incontinence in Patients Following a Low Anterior Resection or Proctectomy With Coloanal Anastomosis or in Patients After Pelvic Chemoradiation (RESTORE)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This trial studies how well sacral nerve stimulation works in treating low anterior resection
      syndrome or fecal incontinence (the body's passage of stool without control) in patients with
      rectal cancer that has spread to nearby tissues or lymph nodes, or other pelvic cancer.
      Sacral nerve stimulation is a permanent implant that may improve bowel functions by
      stimulating the nerves that control the muscles related to bowel function.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PRIMARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To investigate the efficacy of sacral nerve stimulator placement in patients with fecal
      incontinence (FI) or low anterior resection syndrome (LARS) who have previously undergone
      chemoradiation treatment and/or a restorative partial or complete proctectomy with colorectal
      or coloanal anastomosis for cancer treatment as per standard of care (restorative surgery
      cohort).

      II. To evaluate the feasibility of sacral nerve stimulator placement in patients with fecal
      incontinence (FI) or other defecatory dysfunction who have received pelvic radiation
      treatment without undergoing rectal or other pelvic surgery as per standard of cancer care
      (radiation only cohort).

      SECONDARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To evaluate the effectiveness of sacral nerve stimulation (SNS) as measured by validated
      questionnaires in patients with FI or LARS within both patient cohorts.

      II. To evaluate pelvic floor and sphincter physiology using anorectal manometry (ARM) before
      and after SNS in patients with FI or LARS within both patient cohorts.

      III. To assess potential impact of SNS on urinary incontinence measuring a post-void urinary
      bladder residual and validated urinary symptom questionnaires in both patient cohorts.

      IV. To assess efficacy of SNS on long-term bowel dysfunction at 1 and 3 years post battery
      implantation as measured by validated questionnaires for both patient cohorts.

      OUTLINE:

      Patients undergo scheduled, elective surgery for placement of the sacral nerve stimulator
      with external battery pack. After 2 weeks, patients undergo implantation of a subcutaneous
      internal battery or removal of the leads if the sacral nerve stimulator is working but does
      not improve symptoms. If the sacral nerve stimulator is not working, it is repositioned and
      patients return 2 weeks later for implantation of external battery or removal of leads.

      After completion of study, patients are followed up at 1 month, 1 year, and 3 years.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">April 12, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 31, 2025</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 31, 2025</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of patients with Sacral nerve stimulation (SNS) success</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 2 weeks (+7) days post SNS placement</time_frame>
    <description>Primary Outcome Measure should read only: &quot;SNS success will be measured as a patient having the battery implanted up to 2 weeks (+7) days post SNS placement. Patients who do not have the SNS placed, for any reason other than insurance coverage issues, will count as not having a success.&quot;</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Fecal Incontinence Severity Index</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Will be reported descriptively with graphs or tabulations for categorical survey outcomes.
ranges from 0 to 61, a number of 30 has been shown to be reflective of severe fecal incontinence.
the higher the severity of the fecal incontinence,
no subscales</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Fecal Incontinence Quality of Life Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Will be reported descriptively with graphs or tabulations for categorical survey outcomes.
Scales range from 1-5, scale scores are the averages responses to all questions divided by the number of items (29) on the scale
Score of 1 indicates a lower functional status relating to quality of life
Subscales:
Lifestyle (10 items)
Coping/Behavior (9 items)
Depression/Self Perception (7 items)
Embarrassment (3 items)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Anorectal manometry score</measure>
    <time_frame>At 1 month after completion of surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Will be reported descriptively with graphs or tabulations for anorectal manometry measures.
The interpretation of the manometry findings will be documented but are not part of the determination as to if SNS is needed or not. They are not tabulated as part of a score.
Anal Sphincter Electromyography: Surface Electrode Anal EMG is recording by placing small electrodes peri-anally.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Euroqol-5 Dimensions-5 Levels (EQ-5D-5L)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Will be reported descriptively with graphs or tabulations for categorical survey outcomes.
5 dimensions (mobility, self care, usual activities, pain/discomfort, anxiety/depression) rated on 5 levels: no problems, slight problems, moderate problems, severe problems, extreme problems
Additionally, participant is also asked to rate their health that day, from 0 to 100, 0 being the worst they could imagine, 100 being the best
This decision results in a 1-digit number expressing the level selected for that dimension. The digits for 5 dimensions can be combined in a 5-digit number describing the respondent's health state.
Scores will be assessed and compared pre and post placement to reflect general quality of life</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>International Continence Society male Short Form</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Will be reported descriptively with graphs or tabulations for categorical survey outcomes.
Higher scores indicate greater impact of individual symptoms on participant
11 items assessing Voiding (5) and Incontinence (6) - renders two scores
Scoring:
0-20 voiding symptoms subscale
0-24 incontinence symptoms subscale
Frequency, Nocturia and QoL scores indicate impact of symptoms for the patient separately
Scale:
Occasionally = less than one third of the time
Sometimes = between one and two thirds of the time
Most of the time = more than two thirds of the time</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>International Consultation on Incontinence Society - Female Lower Urinary Tract Symptoms</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Will be reported descriptively with graphs or tabulations for categorical survey outcomes.
Overall score 0-48, (addition of all subscores)
Higher scores indicate greater impact of individual symptoms on participant
12 items assessing Nocturia, Urgency, Bladder pain, Frequency, Hesitancy, Straining, Intermittency, Urge urinary incontinence, Frequency of urinary incontinence, Stress urinary incontinence, Unexplained urinary incontinence, Nocturnal enuresis
Scoring:
0-16 filling symptoms subscale
0-12 voiding symptoms subscale
0-20 incontinence symptoms subscale
Bother scales are not incorporated in the overall score but indicate impact of individual symptoms for the patient</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center Bowel Function Questionnaire (BFQ) (restorative surgery cohort)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Will be reported descriptively with graphs or tabulations for categorical survey outcomes.
five frequency options range from never to always (except for one question asking about the number of bowel movements per 24 hours)
18 questions (14 within subscales and with four single items do not belong to a subscale). A global score can be calculated as the sum of the subscale scores, and a total score can be calculated by adding all the item scores (subscale plus single item scores). A higher score represents better bowel function.
Three subscales
frequency, 6 items
diet, 4 items
urgency/soilage, 4 items</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Low anterior resection syndrome score BFQ</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Will be reported descriptively with graphs or tabulations for categorical survey outcomes.
range 0-42 points: (&quot;no LARS&quot;: 0-20), (&quot;minor LARS&quot;: 21-29), (&quot;major LARS&quot;: 30-42). Major LARS requires treatment
5 issues graded,
Incontinence for flatus (0: no, never; 4: yes, less than once/week; 7: yes, at least once/week)
Incontinence for liquid stool (0: no, never; 3: yes, less than once/week; 3: yes, at least once/week)
Frequency (4: &gt;7x/day (24 hrs); 2: 4-7x/day, 0: 1-3x/day; 5: less than 1x/day)
Clustering (0: no, never; 9: yes - less than once/week; 11: yes, at least once/week)
Urgency (0: no, never; 11: yes - less than once/week; 16: yes, at least once/week)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cleveland Clinic Incontinence Score (radiation cohort)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Will be reported descriptively with graphs or tabulations for categorical survey outcomes.
• 5 questions. The frequency with which each type of incontinence occurs is rated on a scale from 0 (never) to 4 (always or to 1/day). The sum of the frequencies is added for a total score that can range from 0 - 20, with higher scores indicating higher levels of incontinence.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Impact of SNS on bowel dysfunction</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 30 days (visit 2)</time_frame>
    <description>Will be measured using bowel diaries.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Impact of SNS on urinary incontinence of the Bladder Diaries</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 30 days (visit 2)</time_frame>
    <description>Will be measured using bladder diaries and a post-void urinary bladder residual and validated urinary symptom questionnaire.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>European Organization for Research and Treatment of Cancer Quality of Life Questionnaire-Colorectal 29</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Will be reported descriptively with graphs or tabulations for categorical survey outcomes.
has 5 functional and 18 symptom scales.
Contains 4 subscales (urinary frequency (UF), blood and mucus in stool (BMS), stool frequency (SF), and body image (BI)) and 19 single items (urinary incontinence, dysuria, abdominal pain, buttock pain, bloating, dry mouth, hair loss, taste, anxiety, weight, flatulence, fecal incontinence, sore skin, embarrassment, stoma care problems, sexual interest (men), impotence, sexual interest (women), and dyspareunia).
Scores can be linearly transformed to provide a score from 0 to 100.
Higher scores represent better functioning on the functional scales and a higher level of symptoms on the symptom scales</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Fecal Incontinence</condition>
  <condition>Low Anterior Resection Syndrome</condition>
  <condition>Malignant Anal Neoplasm</condition>
  <condition>Malignant Bladder Neoplasm</condition>
  <condition>Malignant Cervical Neoplasm</condition>
  <condition>Malignant Ovarian Neoplasm</condition>
  <condition>Malignant Pelvic Neoplasm</condition>
  <condition>Malignant Prostate Neoplasm</condition>
  <condition>Malignant Uterine Neoplasm</condition>
  <condition>Malignant Vaginal Neoplasm</condition>
  <condition>Malignant Vulvar Neoplasm</condition>
  <condition>Rectal Adenocarcinoma</condition>
  <condition>Stage III Rectal Cancer AJCC v8</condition>
  <condition>Stage IIIA Rectal Cancer AJCC v8</condition>
  <condition>Stage IIIB Rectal Cancer AJCC v8</condition>
  <condition>Stage IIIC Rectal Cancer AJCC v8</condition>
  <condition>Stage IV Rectal Cancer AJCC v8</condition>
  <condition>Stage IVA Rectal Cancer AJCC v8</condition>
  <condition>Stage IVB Rectal Cancer AJCC v8</condition>
  <condition>Stage IVC Rectal Cancer AJCC v8</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Supportive Care (sacral nerve stimulator)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients undergo scheduled, elective surgery for placement of the sacral nerve stimulator with external battery pack. After 2 weeks, patients undergo implantation of a subcutaneous internal battery or removal of the leads if the sacral nerve stimulator is working but does not improve symptoms. If the sacral nerve stimulator is not working, it is repositioned and patients return 2 weeks later for implantation of external battery or removal of leads.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Explantation</intervention_name>
    <description>Undergo lead removal</description>
    <arm_group_label>Supportive Care (sacral nerve stimulator)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Implant, removal of</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Quality-of-Life Assessment</intervention_name>
    <description>Ancillary studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Supportive Care (sacral nerve stimulator)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Quality of Life Assessment</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Questionnaire Administration</intervention_name>
    <description>Ancillary studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Supportive Care (sacral nerve stimulator)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sacral Nerve Stimulator</intervention_name>
    <description>Undergo sacral nerve stimulator implantation</description>
    <arm_group_label>Supportive Care (sacral nerve stimulator)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Sacral Neuromodulator</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sacral Nerve Stimulator Battery</intervention_name>
    <description>Undergo sacral nerve stimulator battery implantation</description>
    <arm_group_label>Supportive Care (sacral nerve stimulator)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Sacral Neuromodulator Battery</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Therapeutic Conventional Surgery</intervention_name>
    <description>Undergo sacral nerve stimulator implantation</description>
    <arm_group_label>Supportive Care (sacral nerve stimulator)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Cohort 1: Patients with pathologically proven diagnosis of primary rectal cancer

          -  Cohort 1: Patients who have previously undergone surgical resection and anastomosis
             (restorative) with curative intent treatment with or without chemoradiation

          -  Cohort 1: Patients with T1 and T2 pathologic stage patients treated with restorative
             surgical resection without radiation

          -  Cohort 1: Patients with locally advanced rectal adenocarcinoma (T3 and T4 or lymph
             node positive) treated with radiation and restorative surgery

          -  Cohort 1: Patients with self-reported FI or LARS

          -  Cohort 1: Patients must be able to speak and understand English

          -  Cohort 1: Patients must be willing to and able to sign an approved informed consent
             document

          -  Cohort 1: Patients must be &gt;= 24 months post-resection of rectal cancer

          -  Cohort 1: Patients must have failed prior conservative measures such as Metamucil and
             motility medications and already been assessed and treated in a pelvic floor
             rehabilitation program (biofeedback) designed to treat FI and LARS, and continue to
             experience significant defecatory dysfunction, allowable per principal investigator
             (PI) discretion

          -  Cohort 1: Patients must be willing and able to complete Patient Reported Outcomes
             Questionnaires for before device placement, during the testing phase following lead
             placement, and after implantation of the battery

          -  Cohort 1: Patients must be willing and able to undergo elective ARM testing to
             objectively measure pelvic floor function

          -  Cohort 1: Patients who have an average resting tone &lt; 40 mmHg (normal &gt; 40 mmHg) and
             maximal tolerance &lt; 200 milliliters (normal 200-300 milliliters) as measured by ARM

          -  Cohort 2: Patients with pathologically proven malignancy of the pelvis, other than
             rectal cancer (e.g. prostate, bladder, anus, vagina, vulva, cervix, uterus, or ovary)

          -  Cohort 2: Patients treated with standard of care radiation therapies without surgical
             resection

          -  Cohort 2: Patients with self-reported FI or other defecatory dysfunction

          -  Cohort 2: Patients must be able to speak and understand English

          -  Cohort 2: Patients must be willing to and able to sign an approved informed consent
             document

          -  Cohort 2: Patients must be &gt;= 18 months post-pelvic chemoradiation

          -  Cohort 2: Patients must have already been assessed and treated in a pelvic floor
             rehabilitation program design to treat FI or other defecatory dysfunction and continue
             to experience significant defecatory dysfunction

          -  Cohort 2: Patients must be willing and able to complete Patient Reported Outcomes
             (PROs) and bowel and bladder diaries (Medtronic) at multiple times during the study

          -  Cohort 2: Patients must be willing and able to undergo elective ARM testing to measure
             pelvic floor function

          -  Cohort 2: Patients who have an average resting tone &lt; 40 mmHg (normal &gt; 40 mmHg) and
             maximal tolerance &lt; 200 milliliters (normal 200-300 milliliters) as measured by ARM

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Cohort 1: Patients with co-morbid illnesses or concurrent disease, which in the
             judgment of the clinician obtaining informed consent, would make the patient
             inappropriate for entry into this study or interfere significantly with the proper
             assessment of safety and toxicity of the prescribed regimens

          -  Cohort 1: Any diverting bowel ostomy at the time of consent to this study

          -  Cohort 1: Patients with an absolute neutrophil count (ANC) &lt; 1.7 within 30 days of
             consent

          -  Cohort 1: Patients with an international normalized rate (INR) &gt; 1.3 within 30 days of
             consent

          -  Cohort 1: Patients with a platelet count &lt; 50 K within 30 days of consent

          -  Cohort 1: Patients currently being treated with chemotherapy or within preceding 30
             days at the time consent

          -  Cohort 1: Patients previously treated with a SNS for urinary or FI

          -  Cohort 1: Patients who were documented to have an anastomotic leak following their
             restorative surgical resection

          -  Cohort 1: Patients with an Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance
             status &gt; 2 at the time of consent

          -  Cohort 1: Patients with an active infection requiring systemic therapy at the time of
             consent

          -  Cohort 1: Patients with a significant history of uncontrolled cardiac disease
             including, but not limited to hypertension, unstable angina, myocardial infarction
             within the last 4 months, and uncontrolled congestive heart failure

          -  Cohort 2: Co-morbid illnesses or other concurrent disease, which in the judgment of
             the clinician obtaining informed consent, would make the patient inappropriate for
             entry into this study or interfere significantly with the proper assessment of safety
             and toxicity of the prescribed regimens

          -  Cohort 2: Patients with an ANC &lt; 1.7 within 30 days of consent

          -  Cohort 2: Patients with an INR &gt; 1.3 within 30 days of consent

          -  Cohort 2: Patients with a platelet count &lt; 50 K, within 30 days of consent

          -  Cohort 2: Patients currently being treated with chemotherapy or within the preceding
             30 days at the time of consent

          -  Cohort 2: Patients previously treated with a sacral nerve stimulator for urinary or
             fecal incontinence

          -  Cohort 2: Patients with an ECOG performance status &gt; 2 at the time of consent

          -  Cohort 2: Patients with an active infection requiring systemic therapy at the time of
             consent

          -  Cohort 2: Patients with a significant history of uncontrolled cardiac disease
             including, but not limited to hypertension, unstable angina, myocardial infarction
             within the last 4 months, and uncontrolled congestive heart failure

          -  Cohort 2: Patients with an active autoimmune disease requiring systemic treatment
             within the past 3 months or a documented history of clinically severe autoimmune
             disease, or a syndrome that requires systemic steroids or immunosuppressive agents.
             Subjects with vitiligo or resolved childhood asthma/atopy would be an exception to
             this rule. Subjects that require intermittent use of bronchodilators or local steroid
             injections would not be excluded from the study. Subjects with hypothyroidism stable
             on hormone replacement or Sjogren's syndrome will not be excluded from the study

          -  Cohort 2: Patients who are human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) positive (+) or have
             hepatitis B or C remain eligible, however, HIV+ patients must have a CD4 T cell count
             &gt; 200 cells per microliter
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Craig A Messick</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>M D Anderson Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Craig A. Messick</last_name>
      <phone>713-792-6940</phone>
      <email>cmessick@mdanderson.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Craig A. Messick</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>MD Anderson in Sugar Land</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sugar Land</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77478</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Craig A. Messick</last_name>
      <phone>713-792-6940</phone>
      <email>cmessick@mdanderson.org2016-0754</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Craig A. Messick</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.mdanderson.org</url>
    <description>MD Anderson Cancer Center Website</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>August 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 11, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 21, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 26, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 21, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 21, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">August 26, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Rectal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ovarian Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Uterine Cervical Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Urinary Bladder Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Prostatic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Uterine Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vulvar Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pelvic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vaginal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Anus Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fecal Incontinence</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Neurotransmitter Agents</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

