<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02383472</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IRB-P00002527</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02383472</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>LED Therapy for the Treatment of Concussive Brain Injury</brief_title>
  <official_title>Transcranial LED Therapy for the Treatment of Chronic Mild Traumatic Brain Injury</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Boston Children’s Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>United States Department of Defense</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Football League</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Boston Children’s Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      A double blind randomized trial of light-emitting diode (LED) therapy for patients suffering
      from mild traumatic brain injury (mTBI). Patients seen in the Sports Concussion Clinic with
      cognitive symptoms lasting for greater than 4 weeks will be randomized to either placebo
      therapy (controls) or treatment with LED therapy (cases). Both cases and controls would
      complete post-concussion symptom scales Delis-Kaplan Executive Function System (D-KEFS), and
      ImPACT studies on entry into the study and at weeks 3 and 6, or earlier if their symptoms
      resolve before the end of the 6 week period.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Concussion, also known as mild traumatic brain injury (mTBI), results from a rotational
      acceleration of the brain. The biomechanical forces which cause concussion lead to the
      opening of ion channels within the neuronal cell membranes, allowing for a massive influx of
      sodium and efflux of potassium. This results in a spreading depression type of phenomenon,
      leading to the depolarization of neurons diffusely throughout the brain.19 In order to
      restore the homeostatic ion gradients across the membrane, the sodium-potassium pumps require
      increasing amounts of adenosine triphosphate (ATP). Thus, there is an increased need for ATP
      after concussion. ATP is supplied by the glycolysis of glucose from the blood stream. Both
      experimental models of concussion and human studies, however, show decreased cerebral blood
      flow after the initial response to injury. Thus, there is an increased demand for ATP after
      concussion; but a diminished supply of glucose to meet the demand.

      The absorption of light in the red/near infrared wavelength spectrum by cytochrome C oxidase
      increases ATP synthesis. Thus, by increasing ATP synthesis, red/near infrared LEDs can treat
      the underlying pathophysiological cause of concussion symptoms. If successful, this would be
      the first therapy to directly treat the underlying pathophysiology of concussion.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean Difference in Change in Immediate Post-Concussion Assessment and Cognitive Testing (ImPACT) Score at Baseline and 6 Weeks.</measure>
    <time_frame>From baseline to 6 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The primary outcome is mean difference on composite scores of Immediate Post-Concussion Assessment and Cognitive Testing (ImPACT) between entry into the study and completion of treatment (visit 18, week 6) for both the LED group and the placebo group. The mean difference is calculated by taking the mean of differences of the entry scores minus the 6 week scores. There are 5 composite scores on the ImPACT test; verbal memory, visual memory, visual motor speed, reaction time, and symptom score. The ranges for these subscales are as follows: verbal memory and visual memory: 0-100, visual motor speed: 0-60, reaction time: 0-1.0, and symptom score: 0-132. A higher verbal memory, visual memory, and visual motor speed represent a better outcome, while a lower reaction time and lower symptom score represent a better outcome.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean Difference in Change in Delis-Kaplan Executive Function System (D-KEF) Color-Word Interference and Trail Making Test Performance at Weeks 3 and 6.</measure>
    <time_frame>From baseline to 3 weeks and from baseline to 6 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>This measure indicates the mean differences in Delis-Kaplan Executive Function System (D-KEF) tests between entry into the study and 3 weeks and entry into the study and 6 weeks for both the LED group and the placebo group. The mean difference is calculated by taking the mean of differences of the entry scores minus the 3 week scores and the entry scores minus the 6 week scores. D-KEFs color-word interferences, made up of color naming, word reading, and inhibition, is measured in seconds, a smaller number represents a better outcome. Participants were given 90 seconds to complete color naming and word reading and 180 seconds to complete inhibition. D-KEFs trail making test, made up of number sequencing, letter sequencing, and number-letter sequencing, is measured in seconds, a faster speed (lower number) represents a better outcome. Participants were given 150 seconds to complete number and letter sequencing and 240 seconds to complete number-letter sequencing.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean Difference in Change in Delis-Kaplan Executive Function System (D-KEF) Verbal Fluency Performance at Weeks 3 and 6.</measure>
    <time_frame>From baseline to 3 weeks and from baseline to 6 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>This measure indicates the mean differences in Delis-Kaplan Executive Function System (D-KEF) tests between entry into the study and 3 weeks and entry into the study and 6 weeks for both the LED group and the placebo group. The mean difference is calculated by taking the mean of differences of the entry scores minus the 3 week scores and the entry scores minus the 6 week scores. D-KEFs Verbal Fluency Test, made up of letter fluency and category fluency, is measured by number of responses, a larger number represents a better outcome. Participants were given 60 seconds to complete each fluency test.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean Difference in Change in Total Post Concussion Symptom Score (PCSS) at Weeks 3 and Weeks 6.</measure>
    <time_frame>From baseline to 3 weeks and from baseline to 6 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>This measure indicates the mean differences in total post concussion symptom score (PCSS) between entry into the study and 3 weeks and entry into the study and 6 weeks for both the LED group and the placebo group. The mean difference is calculated by taking the mean of differences of the entry scores minus the 3 week scores and the entry scores minus the 6 week scores. The PCSS is a sum of severity scores from 0-6 (0=none, 6=severe) for 22 individual symptoms, like headache, neck pain, or drowsiness. The range for the PCSS is 0-132, a lower score represents a better outcome.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean Difference in Change in Total Cognitive Symptom Score at Weeks 3 and Weeks 6</measure>
    <time_frame>From baseline to 3 weeks and from baseline to 6 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>This measure indicates the mean difference in total cognitive symptom scores between entry into the study and 3 weeks and entry into the study and 6 weeks for both the LED group and the placebo group. The mean difference is calculated by taking the mean of differences of the entry scores minus the 3 week scores and the entry scores minus the 6 weeks scores. The total cognitive symptom scored is a sum of 7 symptom scores from the PCSS; feeling slowed down, feeling like &quot;in a fog&quot;, &quot;don't feel right&quot;, difficulty concentrating, difficulty remembering, fatigue or low energy, and confusion. The severity of these symptoms are scored 0-6, 0=none, 6=severe. The range for the total cognitive symptom score is 0-42, a lower score represents a better outcome.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">53</enrollment>
  <condition>Brain Concussion</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>MedX Health Console model 1100</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The treatment group will receive LED treatments over 6 weeks, 3 times per week, totaling 18 visits. All treatments will take place at Boston Children's Hospital. The cluster heads are applied to frontal, parietal, and temporal areas. Each cluster head is applied to the forehead/scalp areas for up to 10 minutes. There will be two 10-minute LED/placebo treatment periods per visit, each with different cluster head placements on the head/scalp.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>MedX Health Console model 1100-placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects enrolled in the placebo group will be on the same schedule as the treatment group. The placebo group will receive LED placebo over 6 weeks, 3 times per week, totaling 18 visits. All placebo patients will take place at Boston Children's Hospital. The cluster heads are applied to frontal, parietal, and temporal areas. Each cluster head is applied to the forehead/scalp areas for up to 10 minutes. There will be two 10-minute LED/placebo treatment periods per visit, each with different cluster head placements on the head/scalp.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>MedX Health Console model 1100</intervention_name>
    <description>All treatments will be administered using the MedX Health Console model 1100. These units were cleared by the FDA as non-significant risk in 2003 and approved for home treatment use in 2005 &quot;for temporary increase in local blood flow circulation . . . for temporary relief of minor muscle and joint aches.&quot; Cluster heads are 2 inches in diameter. Each contains 9 red (633nm wavelength) diodes and 52 near infrared (870 nm wavelength) diodes. LED cluster heads would be applied to the frontal, parietal and temporal areas, as well as the mid sagittal suture line</description>
    <arm_group_label>MedX Health Console model 1100</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>MedX LCT 100 &amp; Duolight</other_name>
    <other_name>Manufacturer-MedX Health Inc.</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>MedX Health Console model 1100-placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>The placebo machine is identical in appearance as the treatment machine; It vibrates, warms, and does everything the treatment machine does except it does not have LED lights on the marker, therefore it cannot emit light. Subjects enrolled in the placebo group will be on the same schedule as the treatment group. They will have two, 10 minute treatments, three times a week totaling 18 visits. The placebo allows the researchers to isolate the effect of the study treatment. If patient's in the LED treatment group fare significantly better than those in the placebo treatment group, the study helps support the conclusion that the LED therapy is effective.</description>
    <arm_group_label>MedX Health Console model 1100-placebo</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>MedX LCT 100 &amp; Duolight</other_name>
    <other_name>Manufacturer-MedX Health Inc.</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients 11 years old or greater

          -  Diagnosed with a concussion whose symptoms have persisted for more than 4 weeks

          -  Total score on the cognitive components of the post-concussion symptom scale exceeds
             9, or if they have a composite score on any one of the 4 main outputs of the
             computerized neurocognitive assessment: Immediate Post-concussion Assessment and
             Cognitive Testing (ImPACT) that is below the 90th percentile for their age.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Clinically indicated imaging has been obtained where a hemorrhage is demonstrated

          -  Being considered for an alternate diagnosis (other than concussion)

          -  Have a pre-injury diagnosis of any of the following: depression, post-traumatic stress
             disorder, other psychiatric disorder

          -  Taking any of the following medications: amantadine, , amphetamine, atomoxetine
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>11 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>William P Meehan, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Boston Children’s Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Boston Children's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02115</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Boston Children's Hospital at Waltham</name>
      <address>
        <city>Waltham</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02453</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Naeser MA, Zafonte R, Krengel MH, Martin PI, Frazier J, Hamblin MR, Knight JA, Meehan WP 3rd, Baker EH. Significant improvements in cognitive performance post-transcranial, red/near-infrared light-emitting diode treatments in chronic, mild traumatic brain injury: open-protocol study. J Neurotrauma. 2014 Jun 1;31(11):1008-17. doi: 10.1089/neu.2013.3244. Epub 2014 May 8.</citation>
    <PMID>24568233</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hoge CW, McGurk D, Thomas JL, Cox AL, Engel CC, Castro CA. Mild traumatic brain injury in U.S. Soldiers returning from Iraq. N Engl J Med. 2008 Jan 31;358(5):453-63. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa072972. Epub 2008 Jan 30.</citation>
    <PMID>18234750</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cantu RC. Chronic traumatic encephalopathy in the National Football League. Neurosurgery. 2007 Aug;61(2):223-5. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>17762733</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Collins MW, Lovell MR, Iverson GL, Cantu RC, Maroon JC, Field M. Cumulative effects of concussion in high school athletes. Neurosurgery. 2002 Nov;51(5):1175-9; discussion 1180-1.</citation>
    <PMID>12383362</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gronwall D, Wrightson P. Cumulative effect of concussion. Lancet. 1975 Nov 22;2(7943):995-7.</citation>
    <PMID>53547</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Guskiewicz KM, Marshall SW, Bailes J, McCrea M, Cantu RC, Randolph C, Jordan BD. Association between recurrent concussion and late-life cognitive impairment in retired professional football players. Neurosurgery. 2005 Oct;57(4):719-26; discussion 719-26.</citation>
    <PMID>16239884</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Guskiewicz KM, Mihalik JP, Shankar V, Marshall SW, Crowell DH, Oliaro SM, Ciocca MF, Hooker DN. Measurement of head impacts in collegiate football players: relationship between head impact biomechanics and acute clinical outcome after concussion. Neurosurgery. 2007 Dec;61(6):1244-52; discussion 1252-3.</citation>
    <PMID>18162904</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Guskiewicz KM, McCrea M, Marshall SW, Cantu RC, Randolph C, Barr W, Onate JA, Kelly JP. Cumulative effects associated with recurrent concussion in collegiate football players: the NCAA Concussion Study. JAMA. 2003 Nov 19;290(19):2549-55.</citation>
    <PMID>14625331</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jordan BD, Relkin NR, Ravdin LD, Jacobs AR, Bennett A, Gandy S. Apolipoprotein E epsilon4 associated with chronic traumatic brain injury in boxing. JAMA. 1997 Jul 9;278(2):136-40.</citation>
    <PMID>9214529</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>McKee AC, Cantu RC, Nowinski CJ, Hedley-Whyte ET, Gavett BE, Budson AE, Santini VE, Lee HS, Kubilus CA, Stern RA. Chronic traumatic encephalopathy in athletes: progressive tauopathy after repetitive head injury. J Neuropathol Exp Neurol. 2009 Jul;68(7):709-35. doi: 10.1097/NEN.0b013e3181a9d503. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19535999</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Omalu BI, DeKosky ST, Hamilton RL, Minster RL, Kamboh MI, Shakir AM, Wecht CH. Chronic traumatic encephalopathy in a national football league player: part II. Neurosurgery. 2006 Nov;59(5):1086-92; discussion 1092-3.</citation>
    <PMID>17143242</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Beauchamp K, Mutlak H, Smith WR, Shohami E, Stahel PF. Pharmacology of traumatic brain injury: where is the &quot;golden bullet&quot;? Mol Med. 2008 Nov-Dec;14(11-12):731-40. doi: 10.2119/2008-00050.Beauchamp. Epub 2008 Aug 18. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18769636</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mittenberg W, Burton DB. A survey of treatments for post-concussion syndrome. Brain Inj. 1994 Jul;8(5):429-37.</citation>
    <PMID>7951205</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zafonte R, Friedewald WT, Lee SM, Levin B, Diaz-Arrastia R, Ansel B, Eisenberg H, Timmons SD, Temkin N, Novack T, Ricker J, Merchant R, Jallo J. The citicoline brain injury treatment (COBRIT) trial: design and methods. J Neurotrauma. 2009 Dec;26(12):2207-16. doi: 10.1089/neu.2009.1015.</citation>
    <PMID>19803786</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Meehan WP 3rd. Medical therapies for concussion. Clin Sports Med. 2011 Jan;30(1):115-24, ix. doi: 10.1016/j.csm.2010.08.003. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21074086</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Meehan WP 3rd, Bachur RG. Sport-related concussion. Pediatrics. 2009 Jan;123(1):114-23. doi: 10.1542/peds.2008-0309. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19117869</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ommaya AK, Gennarelli TA. Cerebral concussion and traumatic unconsciousness. Correlation of experimental and clinical observations of blunt head injuries. Brain. 1974 Dec;97(4):633-54.</citation>
    <PMID>4215541</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Giza CC, Hovda DA. The Neurometabolic Cascade of Concussion. J Athl Train. 2001 Sep;36(3):228-235.</citation>
    <PMID>12937489</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yamakami I, McIntosh TK. Effects of traumatic brain injury on regional cerebral blood flow in rats as measured with radiolabeled microspheres. J Cereb Blood Flow Metab. 1989 Feb;9(1):117-24.</citation>
    <PMID>2910893</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yoshino A, Hovda DA, Kawamata T, Katayama Y, Becker DP. Dynamic changes in local cerebral glucose utilization following cerebral conclusion in rats: evidence of a hyper- and subsequent hypometabolic state. Brain Res. 1991 Oct 4;561(1):106-19.</citation>
    <PMID>1797338</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yuan XQ, Prough DS, Smith TL, Dewitt DS. The effects of traumatic brain injury on regional cerebral blood flow in rats. J Neurotrauma. 1988;5(4):289-301.</citation>
    <PMID>3249308</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mochizuki-Oda N, Kataoka Y, Cui Y, Yamada H, Heya M, Awazu K. Effects of near-infra-red laser irradiation on adenosine triphosphate and adenosine diphosphate contents of rat brain tissue. Neurosci Lett. 2002 May 3;323(3):207-10.</citation>
    <PMID>11959421</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yu W, Naim JO, McGowan M, Ippolito K, Lanzafame RJ. Photomodulation of oxidative metabolism and electron chain enzymes in rat liver mitochondria. Photochem Photobiol. 1997 Dec;66(6):866-71.</citation>
    <PMID>9421973</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Oron A, Oron U, Streeter J, de Taboada L, Alexandrovich A, Trembovler V, Shohami E. low-level laser therapy applied transcranially to mice following traumatic brain injury significantly reduces long-term neurological deficits. J Neurotrauma. 2007 Apr;24(4):651-6.</citation>
    <PMID>17439348</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>McCrory P, Meeuwisse W, Johnston K, Dvorak J, Aubry M, Molloy M, Cantu R. Consensus statement on concussion in sport - The 3rd international conference on concussion in sport held in Zurich, November 2008. PM R. 2009 May;1(5):406-20. doi: 10.1016/j.pmrj.2009.03.010.</citation>
    <PMID>19627927</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Collins M, Lovell MR, Iverson GL, Ide T, Maroon J. Examining concussion rates and return to play in high school football players wearing newer helmet technology: a three-year prospective cohort study. Neurosurgery. 2006 Feb;58(2):275-86; discussion 275-86.</citation>
    <PMID>16462481</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Field M, Collins MW, Lovell MR, Maroon J. Does age play a role in recovery from sports-related concussion? A comparison of high school and collegiate athletes. J Pediatr. 2003 May;142(5):546-53.</citation>
    <PMID>12756388</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lovell MR, Collins MW, Iverson GL, Field M, Maroon JC, Cantu R, Podell K, Powell JW, Belza M, Fu FH. Recovery from mild concussion in high school athletes. J Neurosurg. 2003 Feb;98(2):296-301.</citation>
    <PMID>12593614</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lovell MR, Collins MW, Iverson GL, Johnston KM, Bradley JP. Grade 1 or &quot;ding&quot; concussions in high school athletes. Am J Sports Med. 2004 Jan-Feb;32(1):47-54.</citation>
    <PMID>14754723</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Delis DC, Kramer JH, Kaplan E, Holdnack J. Reliability and validity of the Delis-Kaplan Executive Function System: an update. J Int Neuropsychol Soc. 2004 Mar;10(2):301-3.</citation>
    <PMID>15012851</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Stuss DT, Ely P, Hugenholtz H, Richard MT, LaRochelle S, Poirier CA, Bell I. Subtle neuropsychological deficits in patients with good recovery after closed head injury. Neurosurgery. 1985 Jul;17(1):41-7.</citation>
    <PMID>4022286</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 4, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 4, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 9, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <results_first_submitted>March 21, 2018</results_first_submitted>
  <results_first_submitted_qc>May 31, 2018</results_first_submitted_qc>
  <results_first_posted type="Actual">June 29, 2018</results_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 29, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 29, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 26, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Boston Children’s Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>William Meehan III</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>MD, Director of Research - Sports Medicine</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Concussion</keyword>
  <keyword>Mild Traumatic Brain Injury</keyword>
  <keyword>MTBI</keyword>
  <keyword>LED</keyword>
  <keyword>Light Emitting Diode</keyword>
  <keyword>Headache</keyword>
  <keyword>Brain Concussion</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Brain Injuries</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Brain Concussion</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>

  <clinical_results>

    <participant_flow>
      <recruitment_details>Recruitment began in the September of 2012 from the Concussion Clinic within the Department of Sports Medicine and lasted through the spring on 2016.</recruitment_details>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="P1">
          <title>MedX Health Console Model 1100</title>
          <description>The treatment group will receive LED treatments over 6 weeks, 3 times per week, totaling 18 visits. The cluster heads are applied to frontal, parietal, and temporal areas. Each cluster head is applied to the forehead/scalp areas for up to 10 minutes. There will be two 10-minute LED/placebo treatment periods per visit, each with different cluster head placements on the head/scalp.
MedX Health Console model 1100: All treatments will be administered using the MedX Health Console model 1100. These units were cleared by the FDA as non-significant risk in 2003 and approved for home treatment use in 2005 “for temporary increase in local blood flow circulation . . . for temporary relief of minor muscle and joint aches.” Cluster heads are 2 inches in diameter. Each contains 9 red (633nm wavelength) diodes and 52 near infrared (870 nm wavelength) diodes. LED cluster heads would be applied to the frontal, parietal and temporal areas, as well as the mid sagittal suture line</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="P2">
          <title>MedX Health Console Model 1100-placebo</title>
          <description>Subjects enrolled in the placebo group will be on the same schedule as the treatment group. The placebo group will receive LED placebo over 6 weeks, 3 times per week, totaling 18 visits. The cluster heads are applied to frontal, parietal, and temporal areas. Each cluster head is applied to the forehead/scalp areas for up to 10 minutes. There will be two 10-minute placebo treatment periods per visit, each with different cluster head placements on the head/scalp.
MedX Health Console model 1100-placebo: The placebo machine is identical in appearance as the treatment machine; It vibrates, warms, and does everything the treatment machine does except it does not have LED lights on the marker, therefore it cannot emit light. The placebo allows the researchers to isolate the effect of the study treatment. If patient's in the LED treatment group fare significantly better than those in the placebo treatment group, the study helps support the conclusion that the LED therapy is effective.</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <period_list>
        <period>
          <title>Overall Study</title>
          <milestone_list>
            <milestone>
              <title>STARTED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="23"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="30"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>COMPLETED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="22"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="29"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>NOT COMPLETED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="1"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="1"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
          </milestone_list>
          <drop_withdraw_reason_list>
            <drop_withdraw_reason>
              <title>Withdrawal by Subject</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="1"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="1"/>
              </participants_list>
            </drop_withdraw_reason>
          </drop_withdraw_reason_list>
        </period>
      </period_list>
    </participant_flow>

    <baseline>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="B1">
          <title>MedX Health Console Model 1100</title>
          <description>The treatment group will receive LED treatments over 6 weeks, 3 times per week, totaling 18 visits. The cluster heads are applied to frontal, parietal, and temporal areas. Each cluster head is applied to the forehead/scalp areas for up to 10 minutes. There will be two 10-minute LED/placebo treatment periods per visit, each with different cluster head placements on the head/scalp.
MedX Health Console model 1100: All treatments will be administered using the MedX Health Console model 1100. These units were cleared by the FDA as non-significant risk in 2003 and approved for home treatment use in 2005 “for temporary increase in local blood flow circulation . . . for temporary relief of minor muscle and joint aches.” Cluster heads are 2 inches in diameter. Each contains 9 red (633nm wavelength) diodes and 52 near infrared (870 nm wavelength) diodes. LED cluster heads would be applied to the frontal, parietal and temporal areas, as well as the mid sagittal suture line</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="B2">
          <title>MedX Health Console Model 1100-placebo</title>
          <description>Subjects enrolled in the placebo group will be on the same schedule as the treatment group. The placebo group will receive LED placebo over 6 weeks, 3 times per week, totaling 18 visits. The cluster heads are applied to frontal, parietal, and temporal areas. Each cluster head is applied to the forehead/scalp areas for up to 10 minutes. There will be two 10-minute placebo treatment periods per visit, each with different cluster head placements on the head/scalp.
MedX Health Console model 1100-placebo: The placebo machine is identical in appearance as the treatment machine; It vibrates, warms, and does everything the treatment machine does except it does not have LED lights on the marker, therefore it cannot emit light. The placebo allows the researchers to isolate the effect of the study treatment. If patient's in the LED treatment group fare significantly better than those in the placebo treatment group, the study helps support the conclusion that the LED therapy is effective.</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="B3">
          <title>Total</title>
          <description>Total of all reporting groups</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <analyzed_list>
        <analyzed>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <scope>Overall</scope>
          <count_list>
            <count group_id="B1" value="22"/>
            <count group_id="B2" value="29"/>
            <count group_id="B3" value="51"/>
          </count_list>
        </analyzed>
      </analyzed_list>
      <measure_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Age</title>
          <units>years</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>Standard Deviation</dispersion>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="21.55" spread="13.12"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="21.21" spread="13.25"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="21.35" spread="13.19"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Sex: Female, Male</title>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <param>Count of Participants</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <title>Female</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="13"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="19"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="32"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Male</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="9"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="10"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="19"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Race (NIH/OMB)</title>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <param>Count of Participants</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <title>American Indian or Alaska Native</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Asian</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Native Hawaiian or Other Pacific Islander</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Black or African American</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="2"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="2"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>White</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="22"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="27"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="49"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>More than one race</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Unknown or Not Reported</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Participants taking stimulant medications</title>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <param>Count of Participants</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="10"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="14"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="24"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Migraine Headache</title>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <param>Count of Participants</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="2"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="7"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="9"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Psychiatric hx</title>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <param>Count of Participants</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>Undefined</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="14"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="22"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="36"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Anxiety</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="1"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="1"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Depression</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="3"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="3"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>PTSD</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="1"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="1"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Neurodevelopmental Diagnosis</title>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <param>Count of Participants</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>ADHD</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="5"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="2"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="7"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Learning Disability</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="1"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="2"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="3"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Prior Concussions</title>
          <units>Concussions</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>Full Range</dispersion>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="3.5" lower_limit="1" upper_limit="10"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="2" lower_limit="1" upper_limit="6"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="2.5" lower_limit="1" upper_limit="10"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Injury characteristics</title>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <param>Count of Participants</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>Sport-related concussion</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="14"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="22"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="36"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Loss of Consciousness</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="3"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="3"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="6"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Amnesia</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="8"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="10"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="18"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </measure_list>
    </baseline>

    <outcome_list>
      <outcome>
        <type>Primary</type>
        <title>Mean Difference in Change in Immediate Post-Concussion Assessment and Cognitive Testing (ImPACT) Score at Baseline and 6 Weeks.</title>
        <description>The primary outcome is mean difference on composite scores of Immediate Post-Concussion Assessment and Cognitive Testing (ImPACT) between entry into the study and completion of treatment (visit 18, week 6) for both the LED group and the placebo group. The mean difference is calculated by taking the mean of differences of the entry scores minus the 6 week scores. There are 5 composite scores on the ImPACT test; verbal memory, visual memory, visual motor speed, reaction time, and symptom score. The ranges for these subscales are as follows: verbal memory and visual memory: 0-100, visual motor speed: 0-60, reaction time: 0-1.0, and symptom score: 0-132. A higher verbal memory, visual memory, and visual motor speed represent a better outcome, while a lower reaction time and lower symptom score represent a better outcome.</description>
        <time_frame>From baseline to 6 weeks</time_frame>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>MedX Health Console Model 1100</title>
            <description>The treatment group will receive LED treatments over 6 weeks, 3 times per week, totaling 18 visits. The cluster heads are applied to frontal, parietal, and temporal areas. Each cluster head is applied to the forehead/scalp areas for up to 10 minutes. There will be two 10-minute LED/placebo treatment periods per visit, each with different cluster head placements on the head/scalp.
MedX Health Console model 1100: All treatments will be administered using the MedX Health Console model 1100. These units were cleared by the FDA as non-significant risk in 2003 and approved for home treatment use in 2005 “for temporary increase in local blood flow circulation . . . for temporary relief of minor muscle and joint aches.” Cluster heads are 2 inches in diameter. Each contains 9 red (633nm wavelength) diodes and 52 near infrared (870 nm wavelength) diodes. LED cluster heads would be applied to the frontal, parietal and temporal areas, as well as the mid sagittal suture line</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>MedX Health Console Model 1100-placebo</title>
            <description>Subjects enrolled in the placebo group will be on the same schedule as the treatment group. The placebo group will receive LED placebo over 6 weeks, 3 times per week, totaling 18 visits. The cluster heads are applied to frontal, parietal, and temporal areas. Each cluster head is applied to the forehead/scalp areas for up to 10 minutes. There will be two 10-minute LED/placebo treatment periods per visit, each with different cluster head placements on the head/scalp.
MedX Health Console model 1100-placebo: The placebo machine is identical in appearance as the treatment machine except it does not have LED lights on the marker, therefore it cannot emit light. The placebo allows the researchers to isolate the effect of the study treatment. If patient's in the LED treatment group fare significantly better than those in the placebo treatment group, the study helps support the conclusion that the LED therapy is effective.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Mean Difference in Change in Immediate Post-Concussion Assessment and Cognitive Testing (ImPACT) Score at Baseline and 6 Weeks.</title>
          <description>The primary outcome is mean difference on composite scores of Immediate Post-Concussion Assessment and Cognitive Testing (ImPACT) between entry into the study and completion of treatment (visit 18, week 6) for both the LED group and the placebo group. The mean difference is calculated by taking the mean of differences of the entry scores minus the 6 week scores. There are 5 composite scores on the ImPACT test; verbal memory, visual memory, visual motor speed, reaction time, and symptom score. The ranges for these subscales are as follows: verbal memory and visual memory: 0-100, visual motor speed: 0-60, reaction time: 0-1.0, and symptom score: 0-132. A higher verbal memory, visual memory, and visual motor speed represent a better outcome, while a lower reaction time and lower symptom score represent a better outcome.</description>
          <units>Units on a scale</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>Standard Deviation</dispersion>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="22"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="29"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>Verbal Memory</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="-0.9" spread="17.11"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="-5.78" spread="12.08"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Visual Memory</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="3.52" spread="14.82"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="-7.26" spread="12.07"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Visual Motor Speed</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="-2.04" spread="6.36"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="-5.15" spread="5.04"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Reaction Time</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="-0.001" spread="0.16"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="0.030" spread="0.18"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Symptom Score</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="10.14" spread="10.13"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="11.44" spread="19.07"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Secondary</type>
        <title>Mean Difference in Change in Delis-Kaplan Executive Function System (D-KEF) Color-Word Interference and Trail Making Test Performance at Weeks 3 and 6.</title>
        <description>This measure indicates the mean differences in Delis-Kaplan Executive Function System (D-KEF) tests between entry into the study and 3 weeks and entry into the study and 6 weeks for both the LED group and the placebo group. The mean difference is calculated by taking the mean of differences of the entry scores minus the 3 week scores and the entry scores minus the 6 week scores. D-KEFs color-word interferences, made up of color naming, word reading, and inhibition, is measured in seconds, a smaller number represents a better outcome. Participants were given 90 seconds to complete color naming and word reading and 180 seconds to complete inhibition. D-KEFs trail making test, made up of number sequencing, letter sequencing, and number-letter sequencing, is measured in seconds, a faster speed (lower number) represents a better outcome. Participants were given 150 seconds to complete number and letter sequencing and 240 seconds to complete number-letter sequencing.</description>
        <time_frame>From baseline to 3 weeks and from baseline to 6 weeks</time_frame>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>MedX Health Console Model 1100</title>
            <description>The treatment group will receive LED treatments over 6 weeks, 3 times per week, totaling 18 visits. Treatments will take place at Boston Children's Hospital. The cluster heads are applied to frontal, parietal, and temporal areas. Each cluster head is applied to the forehead/scalp areas for up to 10 minutes. There will be two 10-minute LED/placebo treatment periods per visit, each with different cluster head placements on the head/scalp.
MedX Health Console model 1100: All treatments will be administered using the MedX Health Console model 1100. These units were cleared by the FDA as non-significant risk in 2003 and approved for home treatment use in 2005 “for temporary increase in local blood flow circulation . . . for temporary relief of minor muscle and joint aches.” Cluster heads are 2 inches in diameter. Each contains 9 red (633nm wavelength) diodes and 52 near infrared (870 nm wavelength) diodes. LED cluster heads would be applied to the frontal, parietal and temporal ar</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>MedX Health Console Model 1100-placebo</title>
            <description>Subjects enrolled in the placebo group will be on the same schedule as the treatment group. The placebo group will receive LED placebo over 6 weeks, 3 times per week, totaling 18 visits. Placebo patients will take place at Boston Children's Hospital. The cluster heads are applied to frontal, parietal, and temporal areas. Each cluster head is applied to the forehead/scalp areas for up to 10 minutes. There will be two 10-minute LED/placebo treatment periods per visit, each with different cluster head placements on the head/scalp.
MedX Health Console model 1100-placebo: The placebo machine is identical in appearance as the treatment machine; It vibrates, warms, and does everything the treatment machine does except it does not have LED lights on the marker, therefore it cannot emit light. Subjects enrolled in the placebo group will be on the same schedule as the treatment group. They will have two, 10 minute treatments, three times a week totaling 18 visits. The placebo allows the r</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Mean Difference in Change in Delis-Kaplan Executive Function System (D-KEF) Color-Word Interference and Trail Making Test Performance at Weeks 3 and 6.</title>
          <description>This measure indicates the mean differences in Delis-Kaplan Executive Function System (D-KEF) tests between entry into the study and 3 weeks and entry into the study and 6 weeks for both the LED group and the placebo group. The mean difference is calculated by taking the mean of differences of the entry scores minus the 3 week scores and the entry scores minus the 6 week scores. D-KEFs color-word interferences, made up of color naming, word reading, and inhibition, is measured in seconds, a smaller number represents a better outcome. Participants were given 90 seconds to complete color naming and word reading and 180 seconds to complete inhibition. D-KEFs trail making test, made up of number sequencing, letter sequencing, and number-letter sequencing, is measured in seconds, a faster speed (lower number) represents a better outcome. Participants were given 150 seconds to complete number and letter sequencing and 240 seconds to complete number-letter sequencing.</description>
          <units>Seconds</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>Standard Deviation</dispersion>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="22"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="29"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>D-KEFs Color Naming - 3 Weeks</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="3.27" spread="4.03"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="4.76" spread="8.88"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>D-KEFs Color Naming - 6 Weeks</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="3.76" spread="5.12"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="4.07" spread="9.00"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>D-KEFs Word Reading - 3 Weeks</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="0.95" spread="2.98"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="4.07" spread="10.05"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>D-KEFs Word Reading - 6 Weeks</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="1.71" spread="3.73"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="3.44" spread="13.98"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>D-KEFs Inhibition - 3 Weeks</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="7.64" spread="5.49"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="4.48" spread="17.00"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>D-KEFs Inhibition - 6 Weeks</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="32.62" spread="9.13"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="31.59" spread="14.73"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>D-KEFs Number Sequencing - 3 weeks</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="-24.45" spread="15.04"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="-21.17" spread="17.55"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>D-KEFs Letter Sequencing- 3 weeks</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="-28.41" spread="14.06"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="-19.51" spread="20.15"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>D-KEFs Number-Letter Sequencing- 3 weeks</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="8.00" spread="12.66"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="21.93" spread="32.19"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>D-KEFs Number Sequencing - 6 weeks</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="11.33" spread="7.3"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="6.89" spread="10.78"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>D-KEFs Letter Sequencing- 6 weeks</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="6.86" spread="4.29"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="10.59" spread="9.49"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>D-KEFs Number-Letter Sequencing- 6 weeks</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="12.95" spread="13.28"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="19.81" spread="30.34"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Secondary</type>
        <title>Mean Difference in Change in Delis-Kaplan Executive Function System (D-KEF) Verbal Fluency Performance at Weeks 3 and 6.</title>
        <description>This measure indicates the mean differences in Delis-Kaplan Executive Function System (D-KEF) tests between entry into the study and 3 weeks and entry into the study and 6 weeks for both the LED group and the placebo group. The mean difference is calculated by taking the mean of differences of the entry scores minus the 3 week scores and the entry scores minus the 6 week scores. D-KEFs Verbal Fluency Test, made up of letter fluency and category fluency, is measured by number of responses, a larger number represents a better outcome. Participants were given 60 seconds to complete each fluency test.</description>
        <time_frame>From baseline to 3 weeks and from baseline to 6 weeks</time_frame>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>MedX Health Console Model 1100</title>
            <description>The treatment group will receive LED treatments over 6 weeks, 3 times per week, totaling 18 visits. Treatments will take place at Boston Children's Hospital. The cluster heads are applied to frontal, parietal, and temporal areas. Each cluster head is applied to the forehead/scalp areas for up to 10 minutes. There will be two 10-minute LED/placebo treatment periods per visit, each with different cluster head placements on the head/scalp.
MedX Health Console model 1100: All treatments will be administered using the MedX Health Console model 1100. These units were cleared by the FDA as non-significant risk in 2003 and approved for home treatment use in 2005 “for temporary increase in local blood flow circulation . . . for temporary relief of minor muscle and joint aches.” Cluster heads are 2 inches in diameter. Each contains 9 red (633nm wavelength) diodes and 52 near infrared (870 nm wavelength) diodes. LED cluster heads would be applied to the frontal, parietal and temporal ar</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>MedX Health Console Model 1100-placebo</title>
            <description>Subjects enrolled in the placebo group will be on the same schedule as the treatment group. The placebo group will receive LED placebo over 6 weeks, 3 times per week, totaling 18 visits. Placebo patients will take place at Boston Children's Hospital. The cluster heads are applied to frontal, parietal, and temporal areas. Each cluster head is applied to the forehead/scalp areas for up to 10 minutes. There will be two 10-minute LED/placebo treatment periods per visit, each with different cluster head placements on the head/scalp.
MedX Health Console model 1100-placebo: The placebo machine is identical in appearance as the treatment machine; It vibrates, warms, and does everything the treatment machine does except it does not have LED lights on the marker, therefore it cannot emit light. Subjects enrolled in the placebo group will be on the same schedule as the treatment group. They will have two, 10 minute treatments, three times a week totaling 18 visits. The placebo allows the r</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Mean Difference in Change in Delis-Kaplan Executive Function System (D-KEF) Verbal Fluency Performance at Weeks 3 and 6.</title>
          <description>This measure indicates the mean differences in Delis-Kaplan Executive Function System (D-KEF) tests between entry into the study and 3 weeks and entry into the study and 6 weeks for both the LED group and the placebo group. The mean difference is calculated by taking the mean of differences of the entry scores minus the 3 week scores and the entry scores minus the 6 week scores. D-KEFs Verbal Fluency Test, made up of letter fluency and category fluency, is measured by number of responses, a larger number represents a better outcome. Participants were given 60 seconds to complete each fluency test.</description>
          <units>Correct responses</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>Standard Deviation</dispersion>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="22"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="29"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>D-KEFs Verbal Fluency- letters 3 weeks</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="-3.45" spread="6.52"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="-6.10" spread="8.26"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>D-KEFs Verbal Fluency- letters 6 weeks</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="-6.71" spread="7.89"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="-9.89" spread="11.34"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>D-KEFs Verbal Fluency- category 3 weeks</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="-1.14" spread="4.17"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="-0.03" spread="4.12"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>D-KEFs Verbal Fluency- category 6 weeks</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="-1.62" spread="4.09"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="-2.00" spread="4.62"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Secondary</type>
        <title>Mean Difference in Change in Total Post Concussion Symptom Score (PCSS) at Weeks 3 and Weeks 6.</title>
        <description>This measure indicates the mean differences in total post concussion symptom score (PCSS) between entry into the study and 3 weeks and entry into the study and 6 weeks for both the LED group and the placebo group. The mean difference is calculated by taking the mean of differences of the entry scores minus the 3 week scores and the entry scores minus the 6 week scores. The PCSS is a sum of severity scores from 0-6 (0=none, 6=severe) for 22 individual symptoms, like headache, neck pain, or drowsiness. The range for the PCSS is 0-132, a lower score represents a better outcome.</description>
        <time_frame>From baseline to 3 weeks and from baseline to 6 weeks</time_frame>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>MedX Health Console Model 1100</title>
            <description>The treatment group will receive LED treatments over 6 weeks, 3 times per week, totaling 18 visits. Treatments will take place at Boston Children's Hospital. The cluster heads are applied to frontal, parietal, and temporal areas. Each cluster head is applied to the forehead/scalp areas for up to 10 minutes. There will be two 10-minute LED/placebo treatment periods per visit, each with different cluster head placements on the head/scalp.
MedX Health Console model 1100: All treatments will be administered using the MedX Health Console model 1100. These units were cleared by the FDA as non-significant risk in 2003 and approved for home treatment use in 2005 “for temporary increase in local blood flow circulation . . . for temporary relief of minor muscle and joint aches.” Cluster heads are 2 inches in diameter. Each contains 9 red (633nm wavelength) diodes and 52 near infrared (870 nm wavelength) diodes. LED cluster heads would be applied to the frontal, parietal and temporal ar</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>MedX Health Console Model 1100-placebo</title>
            <description>Subjects enrolled in the placebo group will be on the same schedule as the treatment group. The placebo group will receive LED placebo over 6 weeks, 3 times per week, totaling 18 visits. Placebo patients will take place at Boston Children's Hospital. The cluster heads are applied to frontal, parietal, and temporal areas. Each cluster head is applied to the forehead/scalp areas for up to 10 minutes. There will be two 10-minute LED/placebo treatment periods per visit, each with different cluster head placements on the head/scalp.
MedX Health Console model 1100-placebo: The placebo machine is identical in appearance as the treatment machine; It vibrates, warms, and does everything the treatment machine does except it does not have LED lights on the marker, therefore it cannot emit light. Subjects enrolled in the placebo group will be on the same schedule as the treatment group. They will have two, 10 minute treatments, three times a week totaling 18 visits. The placebo allows the r</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Mean Difference in Change in Total Post Concussion Symptom Score (PCSS) at Weeks 3 and Weeks 6.</title>
          <description>This measure indicates the mean differences in total post concussion symptom score (PCSS) between entry into the study and 3 weeks and entry into the study and 6 weeks for both the LED group and the placebo group. The mean difference is calculated by taking the mean of differences of the entry scores minus the 3 week scores and the entry scores minus the 6 week scores. The PCSS is a sum of severity scores from 0-6 (0=none, 6=severe) for 22 individual symptoms, like headache, neck pain, or drowsiness. The range for the PCSS is 0-132, a lower score represents a better outcome.</description>
          <units>units on a scale</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>Standard Deviation</dispersion>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="22"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="29"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>PCSS Total Score - 3 Weeks</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="9.41" spread="12.62"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="7.03" spread="16.96"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>PCSS Total score - 6 Weeks</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="7.86" spread="14.5"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="14.63" spread="23.41"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Secondary</type>
        <title>Mean Difference in Change in Total Cognitive Symptom Score at Weeks 3 and Weeks 6</title>
        <description>This measure indicates the mean difference in total cognitive symptom scores between entry into the study and 3 weeks and entry into the study and 6 weeks for both the LED group and the placebo group. The mean difference is calculated by taking the mean of differences of the entry scores minus the 3 week scores and the entry scores minus the 6 weeks scores. The total cognitive symptom scored is a sum of 7 symptom scores from the PCSS; feeling slowed down, feeling like &quot;in a fog&quot;, &quot;don't feel right&quot;, difficulty concentrating, difficulty remembering, fatigue or low energy, and confusion. The severity of these symptoms are scored 0-6, 0=none, 6=severe. The range for the total cognitive symptom score is 0-42, a lower score represents a better outcome.</description>
        <time_frame>From baseline to 3 weeks and from baseline to 6 weeks</time_frame>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>MedX Health Console Model 1100</title>
            <description>The treatment group will receive LED treatments over 6 weeks, 3 times per week, totaling 18 visits. Treatments will take place at Boston Children's Hospital. The cluster heads are applied to frontal, parietal, and temporal areas. Each cluster head is applied to the forehead/scalp areas for up to 10 minutes. There will be two 10-minute LED/placebo treatment periods per visit, each with different cluster head placements on the head/scalp.
MedX Health Console model 1100: All treatments will be administered using the MedX Health Console model 1100. These units were cleared by the FDA as non-significant risk in 2003 and approved for home treatment use in 2005 “for temporary increase in local blood flow circulation . . . for temporary relief of minor muscle and joint aches.” Cluster heads are 2 inches in diameter. Each contains 9 red (633nm wavelength) diodes and 52 near infrared (870 nm wavelength) diodes. LED cluster heads would be applied to the frontal, parietal and temporal ar</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>MedX Health Console Model 1100-placebo</title>
            <description>Subjects enrolled in the placebo group will be on the same schedule as the treatment group. The placebo group will receive LED placebo over 6 weeks, 3 times per week, totaling 18 visits. Placebo patients will take place at Boston Children's Hospital. The cluster heads are applied to frontal, parietal, and temporal areas. Each cluster head is applied to the forehead/scalp areas for up to 10 minutes. There will be two 10-minute LED/placebo treatment periods per visit, each with different cluster head placements on the head/scalp.
MedX Health Console model 1100-placebo: The placebo machine is identical in appearance as the treatment machine; It vibrates, warms, and does everything the treatment machine does except it does not have LED lights on the marker, therefore it cannot emit light. Subjects enrolled in the placebo group will be on the same schedule as the treatment group. They will have two, 10 minute treatments, three times a week totaling 18 visits. The placebo allows the r</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Mean Difference in Change in Total Cognitive Symptom Score at Weeks 3 and Weeks 6</title>
          <description>This measure indicates the mean difference in total cognitive symptom scores between entry into the study and 3 weeks and entry into the study and 6 weeks for both the LED group and the placebo group. The mean difference is calculated by taking the mean of differences of the entry scores minus the 3 week scores and the entry scores minus the 6 weeks scores. The total cognitive symptom scored is a sum of 7 symptom scores from the PCSS; feeling slowed down, feeling like &quot;in a fog&quot;, &quot;don't feel right&quot;, difficulty concentrating, difficulty remembering, fatigue or low energy, and confusion. The severity of these symptoms are scored 0-6, 0=none, 6=severe. The range for the total cognitive symptom score is 0-42, a lower score represents a better outcome.</description>
          <units>units on a scale</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>Standard Deviation</dispersion>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="22"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="29"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>Cognitive Sx Score - 3 Weeks</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="3.95" spread="6.56"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="1.31" spread="6.96"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Cognitive Sx Score - 6 Weeks</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="4.00" spread="6.59"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="5.00" spread="8.95"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
    </outcome_list>

    <reported_events>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="E1">
          <title>MedX Health Console Model 1100</title>
          <description>The treatment group will receive LED treatments over 6 weeks, 3 times per week, totaling 18 visits. All treatments will take place at Boston Children's Hospital. The cluster heads are applied to frontal, parietal, and temporal areas. Each cluster head is applied to the forehead/scalp areas for up to 10 minutes. There will be two 10-minute LED/placebo treatment periods per visit, each with different cluster head placements on the head/scalp.
MedX Health Console model 1100: All treatments will be administered using the MedX Health Console model 1100. These units were cleared by the FDA as non-significant risk in 2003 and approved for home treatment use in 2005 “for temporary increase in local blood flow circulation . . . for temporary relief of minor muscle and joint aches.” Cluster heads are 2 inches in diameter. Each contains 9 red (633nm wavelength) diodes and 52 near infrared (870 nm wavelength) diodes. LED cluster heads would be applied to the frontal, parietal and temporal ar</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="E2">
          <title>MedX Health Console Model 1100-placebo</title>
          <description>Subjects enrolled in the placebo group will be on the same schedule as the treatment group. The placebo group will receive LED placebo over 6 weeks, 3 times per week, totaling 18 visits. All placebo patients will take place at Boston Children's Hospital. The cluster heads are applied to frontal, parietal, and temporal areas. Each cluster head is applied to the forehead/scalp areas for up to 10 minutes. There will be two 10-minute LED/placebo treatment periods per visit, each with different cluster head placements on the head/scalp.
MedX Health Console model 1100-placebo: The placebo machine is identical in appearance as the treatment machine; It vibrates, warms, and does everything the treatment machine does except it does not have LED lights on the marker, therefore it cannot emit light. Subjects enrolled in the placebo group will be on the same schedule as the treatment group. They will have two, 10 minute treatments, three times a week totaling 18 visits. The placebo allows the r</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <serious_events>
        <category_list>
          <category>
            <title>Total</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, serious adverse events</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="23"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="30"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
        </category_list>
      </serious_events>
      <other_events>
        <frequency_threshold>0</frequency_threshold>
        <default_assessment>Non-systematic Assessment</default_assessment>
        <category_list>
          <category>
            <title>Total</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, other adverse events</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="23"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="30"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Discomfort</sub_title>
                <description>Patient complained cluster heads were &quot;uncomfortable and hot&quot;</description>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="23"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="30"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
        </category_list>
      </other_events>
    </reported_events>

    <certain_agreements>
      <pi_employee>Principal Investigators are NOT employed by the organization sponsoring the study.</pi_employee>
      <restrictive_agreement>There is NOT an agreement between Principal Investigators and the Sponsor (or its agents) that restricts the PI's rights to discuss or publish trial results after the trial is completed. </restrictive_agreement>
    </certain_agreements>
    <point_of_contact>
      <name_or_title>Dr. William Meehan</name_or_title>
      <organization>Boston Children's Hospital</organization>
      <phone>781-216-1328</phone>
      <email>William.Meehan@childrens.harvard.edu</email>
    </point_of_contact>
  </clinical_results>
</clinical_study>

