<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01047410</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>METc 2014/190</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01047410</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>ACtive Care After Transplantation, the ACT Study</brief_title>
  <acronym>ACT</acronym>
  <official_title>ACtive Care After Transplantation, a Lifestyle Intervention in Renal Transplant Recipients</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University Medical Center Groningen</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Dutch Kidney Foundation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Innovation Fund of the Dutch Medical Insurance Companies</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University Medical Center Groningen</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The aim of the present study is to compare the outcomes of standard care to the effects of
      exercise alone, and exercise combined with nutrition counseling, on post-transplantation
      weight gain and quality of life in renal transplant recipients (RTR). The primary outcome is
      subdomain physical functioning of quality of life, (SF-36 PFS).

      Secondary outcomes include other evaluations of quality of life (SF-36, KDQOL-SF, EQ-5D),
      objective measures of physical functioning (aerobic capacity and muscle strength), level of
      physical activity, gain in adiposity (body fat percentage by bio-electrical impedance
      assessment, BMI, waist circumference), and cardiometabolic risk factors (blood pressure,
      lipids, glucose metabolism). Additionally it is planned to study data on renal function,
      medical history, medication, psychological factors (motivation, kinesiophobia, coping style),
      nutrition knowledge, nutrition intake, nutrition status, fatigue, work participation, process
      evaluation and cost-effectiveness.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Patient and graft survival in the first year after renal transplantation have improved
      substantially over the last decade, but long-term graft loss and patient mortality have
      remained high. It is increasingly recognized that the alarmingly poor cardio-metabolic risk
      profile in renal transplant recipients (RTR) plays a main role in long-term outcome.
      Improvement of long-term outcome will require specific efforts to improve cardio-metabolic
      profile and its complications. Importantly, the substantial increase in body weight and body
      fat that occurs after transplantation is a major trigger for the poor cardiometabolic profile
      in the RTR, including post-transplant diabetes and metabolic syndrome.

      The increase in body weight is mostly fat tissue and typically around 9-10 kg. Most of this
      weight gain (~90%) occurs in the first year after transplantation. Recent data indicate that
      steroid avoidance could not prevent this early increase in adiposity. This warrants specific
      focus on lifestyle factors, i.e diet and physical activity. In the UMCG RTR cohort we found
      that a lack of physical activity was related to a worse cardiometabolic profile and was an
      independent predictor of mortality. Moreover, the substantial increase in fat massweight gain
      was strongly related to low physical activity, high intake of energy-dense drinks, low
      consumption of vegetables, to increased plasma triglycerides and the metabolic syndrome. The
      intake of salt and saturated fat was high and fibre intake was low, indicating dietary habits
      that deviate substantially from recommendations for a healthy diet. Thus, both physical
      activity and dietary habits are important targets for lifestyle intervention in RTR.

      Lasting improvements in lifestyle are notoriously difficult to obtain, but in recent years
      substantial intervention expertise has been developed in other high risk groups including
      prediabetes. It is now established that for long term purposes, prevention of excessive
      weight gain is more effective than treatment of weight excess. Since in RTR most of the
      weight is gained in the first year after transplantation, prevention is a very promising
      approach. Moreover, data in prediabetes suggest that combined intervention targeting both
      diet and physical activity may be particularly effective to this purpose.

      Therefore, our aim is to investigate the effects on quality of life by a combined
      diet-and-physical activity program in RTR in the first year after transplantation.

      This randomized controlled intervention study will use a combined diet-and-physical activity
      approach. After hospital discharge for transplantation, 219 patients will be randomized to
      three either a control groups: one group, who will receive standard care, one group will be
      exposed to a 3-month exercise program followed by individual counselling and one group will
      be exposed to the exercise program + dietary or to intervention followed by individual
      counselling. The individual counselling is to consolidate the achieved improvements in diet
      and physical activity and will be provided until 15 months after inclusion. This counselling
      is based on theories of behavioural change and motivational interviewing. Daily physical
      activity is evaluated with a pedometer and dietary habits by questionnaires and food records.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2010</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">November 1, 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">August 1, 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>3-arm randomized controlled trial</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
    <masking_description>Outcomes assessors are blinded if possible.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of life - Physical Functioning Score</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 12 weeks, 6 months and 15 months</time_frame>
    <description>The subdomain 'Physical Functioning' of Quality of Life (SF36 questionnaire)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of Life Scores</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 12 weeks, 6 months and 15 months</time_frame>
    <description>Physical and Mental scores of the Quality of Life SF36 questionnaire</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Physical functioning</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 12 weeks, 6 months and 15 months</time_frame>
    <description>Exercise capacity by VO2max test and/or submax test</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Physical functioning</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 12 weeks, 6 months and 15 months</time_frame>
    <description>skeletal muscle strength by maximal strenght test</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Body composition</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 12 weeks, 6 months and 15 months</time_frame>
    <description>waist circumference</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Body composition</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 12 weeks, 6 months and 15 months</time_frame>
    <description>body fat percentage (bioelectrical impedance)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Body composition</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 12 weeks, 6 months and 15 months</time_frame>
    <description>Height and weight to calculate BMI</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cardiometabolic risk factors</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 12 weeks, 6 months and 15 months</time_frame>
    <description>Blood pressure</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cardiometabolic risk factors</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 12 weeks, 6 months and 15 months</time_frame>
    <description>Lipid profiles (cholesterol)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cardiometabolic risk factors</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 12 weeks, 6 months and 15 months</time_frame>
    <description>Lipid profiles (triglycerides)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cardiometabolic risk factors</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 12 weeks and 15 months</time_frame>
    <description>glucose metabolism</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>nutrition</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 12 weeks, (6 months for nutrition intervention only) and 15 months</time_frame>
    <description>dietary intake (food diaries)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>nutrition</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and 15 months</time_frame>
    <description>nutritional knowledge (questionnaire)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Psychological factors</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks and 15 months</time_frame>
    <description>motivation (questionnaire)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Psychological factors</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and 15 months</time_frame>
    <description>kinesiophobia (questionnaire)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Psychological factors</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline</time_frame>
    <description>coping style (questionnaire)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Chronic fatigue</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 12 weeks, 6 months and 15 months</time_frame>
    <description>CIS-20 questionnaire</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Fatigue and work participation</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 12 weeks, 6 months and 15 months</time_frame>
    <description>Fatigue and work questionnaire (NFR)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cost-effectiveness</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 12 weeks, 6, 9, 12 and 15 months</time_frame>
    <description>care consumption and intervention costs</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">221</enrollment>
  <condition>Post-transplant Weight Gain</condition>
  <condition>Kidney Transplant</condition>
  <condition>Metabolic Syndrome</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Usual care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients assigned to the usual care group receive the standard medical care (usual care) during the 15 months lasting study period. Physical training does not form a part of the usual care of renal transplant and dialysis patients. After randomisation, patients assigned to the usual care group receive the advice to meet the 'Nederlandse Norm Gezond Bewegen (NNGB), i.e. the advice to perform 30 minutes of moderately intense physical activity at at least five but preferably all days of the week.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Exercise intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The exercise intervention in this group is identical to the exercise-only group. Patients assigned to the exercise intervention participate in a 12 weeks lasting, intensive, standardized and supervised physical training program which consists of a combination of endurance and strength training. After completion of the training program, patients receive an individual sport- and physical activity advice and lifestyle coaching.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Exercise intervention and dietary advice</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The exercise intervention in this group is identical to the exercise-only group. The nutritional intervention runs throughout the entire 15 month intervention. The nutritional intervention aims to critically discuss pre-transplantation nutritional habits, and to set goals for healthier, better quality nutrition to prevent over eating and weight gain. These goals are set together with the subject to facilitate an autonomy supportive coaching climate.During the dietary consults, special attention goes out to saturated fat intake, whole-wheat and high fibre foods, fruit and vegetable intake, dietary salt consumption, and the use of energy-rich beverages such as soda, dairy drinks and fruit juices.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Exercise intervention</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients assigned to the exercise intervention participate in a 12 weeks lasting, intensive, standardized and supervised physical training program which consists of a combination of endurance and strength training. After completion of the training program, patients receive an individual sport- and physical activity advice and lifestyle coaching.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Exercise intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Exercise intervention and dietary advice</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Exercise intervention and dietary advice</intervention_name>
    <description>The exercise intervention in this group is identical to the exercise-only group. The nutritional intervention runs throughout the entire 15 month intervention. The nutritional intervention aims to critically discuss pre-transplantation nutritional habits, and to set goals for healthier, better quality nutrition to prevent over eating and weight gain. These goals are set together with the subject to facilitate an autonomy supportive coaching climate.During the dietary consults, special attention goes out to saturated fat intake, whole-wheat and high fibre foods, fruit and vegetable intake, dietary salt consumption, and the use of energy-rich beverages such as soda, dairy drinks and fruit juices.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Exercise intervention and dietary advice</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age ≥ 18 years;

          -  Informed Consent;

          -  &gt;1 year after transplantation

          -  Medical approvement for participation in the study by the nephrologist.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Psychopathology;

          -  Severe cognitive disorders;

          -  Negative advice of the nephrologist and/or cardiologist.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Eva Corpleleijn, dr</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>UMCG</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Reade</name>
      <address>
        <city>Amsterdam</city>
        <state>Noord-Holland</state>
        <zip>1056 AB</zip>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Revalidatiecentrum Lindenhof</name>
      <address>
        <city>Goes</city>
        <state>Zeeland</state>
        <zip>4462 RA</zip>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>AMC</name>
      <address>
        <city>Amsterdam</city>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Isala Kliniek</name>
      <address>
        <city>Zwolle</city>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Vogellanden</name>
      <address>
        <city>Zwolle</city>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Netherlands</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>van den Ham EC, Kooman JP, Schols AM, Nieman FH, Does JD, Akkermans MA, Janssen PP, Gosker HR, Ward KA, MacDonald JH, Christiaans MH, Leunissen KM, van Hooff JP. The functional, metabolic, and anabolic responses to exercise training in renal transplant and hemodialysis patients. Transplantation. 2007 Apr 27;83(8):1059-68.</citation>
    <PMID>17452896</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>van den Ham EC, Kooman JP, Schols AM, Nieman FH, Does JD, Franssen FM, Akkermans MA, Janssen PP, van Hooff JP. Similarities in skeletal muscle strength and exercise capacity between renal transplant and hemodialysis patients. Am J Transplant. 2005 Aug;5(8):1957-65.</citation>
    <PMID>15996245</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>van den Ham EC. Body composition and exercise intolerance in renal transplant patients: the response to exercise training. Thesis. 2006.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>van den Ham EC, Kooman JP, Christiaans MH, Nieman FH, van Hooff JP. Weight changes after renal transplantation: a comparison between patients on 5-mg maintenance steroid therapy and those on steroid-free immunosuppressive therapy. Transpl Int. 2003 May;16(5):300-6. Epub 2003 Feb 20.</citation>
    <PMID>12759720</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>van den Ham EC, Kooman JP, Christiaans ML, van Hooff JP. The influence of early steroid withdrawal on body composition and bone mineral density in renal transplantation patients. Transpl Int. 2003 Feb;16(2):82-7. Epub 2003 Jan 18.</citation>
    <PMID>12595969</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>van den Ham EC, Kooman JP, Christiaans MH, Leunissen KM, van Hooff JP. Posttransplantation weight gain is predominantly due to an increase in body fat mass. Transplantation. 2000 Jul 15;70(1):241-2.</citation>
    <PMID>10919614</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>van den Ham EC, Kooman JP, Christiaans MH, van Hooff JP. Relation between steroid dose, body composition and physical activity in renal transplant patients. Transplantation. 2000 Apr 27;69(8):1591-8.</citation>
    <PMID>10836368</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zelle DM, Kok T, Dontje ML, Danchell EI, Navis G, van Son WJ, Bakker SJ, Corpeleijn E. The role of diet and physical activity in post-transplant weight gain after renal transplantation. Clin Transplant. 2013 Jul-Aug;27(4):E484-90. doi: 10.1111/ctr.12149. Epub 2013 Jun 13.</citation>
    <PMID>23758229</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zelle DM, Corpeleijn E, Stolk RP, de Greef MH, Gans RO, van der Heide JJ, Navis G, Bakker SJ. Low physical activity and risk of cardiovascular and all-cause mortality in renal transplant recipients. Clin J Am Soc Nephrol. 2011 Apr;6(4):898-905. doi: 10.2215/CJN.03340410. Epub 2011 Mar 3.</citation>
    <PMID>21372213</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kwakernaak AJ, Zelle DM, Bakker SJ, Navis G. Central body fat distribution associates with unfavorable renal hemodynamics independent of body mass index. J Am Soc Nephrol. 2013 May;24(6):987-94. doi: 10.1681/ASN.2012050460. Epub 2013 Apr 11.</citation>
    <PMID>23578944</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zelle DM, Corpeleijn E, Deinum J, Stolk RP, Gans RO, Navis G, Bakker SJ. Pancreatic β-cell dysfunction and risk of new-onset diabetes after kidney transplantation. Diabetes Care. 2013 Jul;36(7):1926-32. doi: 10.2337/dc12-1894. Epub 2013 Feb 1.</citation>
    <PMID>23378624</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Corpeleijn E, Bakker SJ, Stolk RP. Obesity and impaired renal function: potential for lifestyle intervention? Eur J Epidemiol. 2009;24(6):275-80. doi: 10.1007/s10654-009-9345-8. Epub 2009 May 7.</citation>
    <PMID>19455406</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mensink M, Corpeleijn E, Feskens EJ, Kruijshoop M, Saris WH, de Bruin TW, Blaak EE. Study on lifestyle-intervention and impaired glucose tolerance Maastricht (SLIM): design and screening results. Diabetes Res Clin Pract. 2003 Jul;61(1):49-58.</citation>
    <PMID>12849923</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Oterdoom LH, de Vries AP, Gansevoort RT, van Son WJ, van der Heide JJ, Ploeg RJ, de Jong PE, Gans RO, Bakker SJ. Determinants of insulin resistance in renal transplant recipients. Transplantation. 2007 Jan 15;83(1):29-35.</citation>
    <PMID>17220787</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>de Vries AP, Bakker SJ, van Son WJ, van der Heide JJ, Ploeg RJ, The HT, de Jong PE, Gans RO. Metabolic syndrome is associated with impaired long-term renal allograft function; not all component criteria contribute equally. Am J Transplant. 2004 Oct;4(10):1675-83.</citation>
    <PMID>15367224</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>August 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 11, 2010</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 11, 2010</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 12, 2010</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 28, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 28, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">August 31, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University Medical Center Groningen</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Eva Corpeleijn</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Dr.</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>physical exercise training</keyword>
  <keyword>quality of life</keyword>
  <keyword>exercise capacity</keyword>
  <keyword>skeletal muscle strength</keyword>
  <keyword>physical activity level</keyword>
  <keyword>costeffectiveness</keyword>
  <keyword>renal transplantation</keyword>
  <keyword>hemodialysis</keyword>
  <keyword>peritoneal dialysis</keyword>
  <keyword>diet</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Metabolic Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Weight Gain</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

