<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01374412</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Transregio79B8</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01374412</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Investigation of Bone Defects and Microcirculation With Computed Tomography and Magnetic Resonance Imaging</brief_title>
  <official_title>Examination of Bone Defects and Microcirculation Using Volume Computed Tomography and Dynamic Contrast-enhanced Magnetic Resonance Imaging</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>German Cancer Research Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Heidelberg University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>German Cancer Research Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Subject of the proposed study is the non-invasive in vivo imaging of bone, bone marrow and
      localized microcirculation in test animals with osteoporosis, fractures and after placement
      of bone substitute material with volume computed tomography (VCT) (animals only) and
      functional magnetic resonance imaging (MRI).

      In vivo imaging by means of functional MRI and VCT is carried out in osteoporotic rats, both
      after the induction of fracture as well as after the placement of bone substitute material.

      Furthermore, patients with asymptomatic MM are investigated with functional MR-Imaging
      (Dynamic Contrast Enhancement- MRI and Intravoxel incoherent motion (IVIM)-imaging)
      longitudinally to predict the occurrence of osteolysis and the time to progression regarding
      SLIM-CRAB-Criteria (Rajkumar et al., Lancet Oncology, 2014).

      Hypothesis:

        1. Affection of microcirculation at the junction of bone and bone substitute material can
           be displayed by VCT and functional MRI

        2. Functional MRI has prognostic value regarding occurrence of osteolysis and progression
           to MM regarding SLIM-CRAB-Criteria
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      In an experimental study, rat models were used for imaging studies employing MRI
      (morphological, DCE- and DWI) and VCT. Mice were not used for imaging purposes due to the
      small size. Rats were shown to be of optimal size for small imaging studies.

      147 patients with (suspected) asymptomatic MM were recruited for dynamic contrast-enhanced
      MRI (DCE-MRI) and diffusion weighted imaging (DWI) of the vertebral column as well as
      whole-body MRI using T1tse and STIR images every 6 months until progression and/ or
      occurrence of first osteolysis.

      While during planning and initiation of this prospective trial MM was defined by
      CRAB-criteria only, in 2014 the SLIM-CRAB-criteria were proposed by the International Myeloma
      Working Group (Rajkumar et al., Lancet Oncology, 2014) with the goal to treat patients before
      development of osteolysis or other CRAB-criteria. These criteria were consequently introduced
      in clinical practice at our institution during the observation period of this study, which
      affects both inclusion and progression criteria of this study. In order to obtain a
      conclusive cohort with homogenous inclusion and progression criteria, SLIM-CRAB-criteria
      where retrospectively applied to restage all patients regarding inclusion and progression to
      MM defined by SLIM-CRAB-criteria.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2010</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes of microcirculation at the interface between bone and implanted xenomaterial in animal models.</measure>
    <time_frame>VCT and MRI 2-6 weeks after xenomaterial implantation</time_frame>
    <description>Characteristics of the microcirculation within and in the close proximity of the bone defect in early stages and during the healing process after the placement of bone substitute materials in animal models. Correlation of functional imaging parameters derived from DCE-MRI, DWI and VCT assessed in the bone defect area with the later stage healing processes in the affected bone.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression to multiple myeloma defined by SLIM-CRAB-Criteria (Rajkumar, Lancet Oncology, 2014)</measure>
    <time_frame>At inclusion in the study and in repetitive follow up every 6 months until progression requiring therapy, until contraindications for MRI are present, until patient wishes to leave the study or until death (assessed up to 20 years)</time_frame>
    <description>In the study part applying functional imaging in asymptomatic myeloma patients, progression to Multiple Myeloma defined by SLIM-CRAB-Criteria is the primary outcome measure</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Occurrence of osteolysis</measure>
    <time_frame>At inclusion in the study and in repetitive follow up every 6 months until progression requiring therapy, until contraindications for MRI are present, until patient wishes to leave the study or until death (assessed up to 20 years)</time_frame>
    <description>In the study part applying functional imaging in asymptomatic myeloma patients, occurrence of osteolysis in x-ray / CT imaging is the secondary outcome measure.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">147</enrollment>
  <condition>Osteoporosis</condition>
  <condition>Multiple Myeloma</condition>
  <condition>Vertebral Fracture</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>osteoporosis</arm_group_label>
    <description>patients with benign osteoporosis</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        patients with benign osteoporosis
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  benign osteoporosis

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  contra-indications for MRI
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Reinhard Schnettler, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Gießen University, Heidelberg</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>German Cancer Research Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Heidelberg</city>
        <zip>69120</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Germany</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rajkumar SV, Dimopoulos MA, Palumbo A, Blade J, Merlini G, Mateos MV, Kumar S, Hillengass J, Kastritis E, Richardson P, Landgren O, Paiva B, Dispenzieri A, Weiss B, LeLeu X, Zweegman S, Lonial S, Rosinol L, Zamagni E, Jagannath S, Sezer O, Kristinsson SY, Caers J, Usmani SZ, Lahuerta JJ, Johnsen HE, Beksac M, Cavo M, Goldschmidt H, Terpos E, Kyle RA, Anderson KC, Durie BG, Miguel JF. International Myeloma Working Group updated criteria for the diagnosis of multiple myeloma. Lancet Oncol. 2014 Nov;15(12):e538-48. doi: 10.1016/S1470-2045(14)70442-5. Epub 2014 Oct 26. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25439696</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>April 14, 2010</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 15, 2011</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 16, 2011</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 24, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 24, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">July 28, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Multiple Myeloma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Osteoporosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Spinal Fractures</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

