<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02579928</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>1506016041</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02579928</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Ketamine Infusion for Adolescent Depression and Anxiety</brief_title>
  <official_title>Efficacy of Rapid-Acting NMDA Antagonist for Treatment of Adolescent Depression and Anxiety Disorders</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Yale University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>American Academy of Child Adolescent Psychiatry.</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Yale University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to determine the tolerability and short-term efficacy of a
      single ketamine infusion for the treatment of adolescents with 1) medication-refractory major
      depressive disorder (MDD) and/or 2) medication-refractory anxiety disorders (social anxiety
      disorder, panic disorder, generalized anxiety disorder and/or separation anxiety disorder).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      We will conduct a crossover trial in which as many as 36 adolescents (18 with MDD and 18 with
      anxiety disorders) will be given a single infusion of ketamine (study drug) or midazolam
      (active control). MDD symptoms and anxiety symptoms will be monitored over a two-week period.
      If applicable, comorbid school refusal symptoms will also be monitored over a two-week period
      for both cohorts. A 2-week washout period will be required between infusion doses. Our
      primary outcomes will be 1) improvement in MDD symptoms (measured by Montgomery-Asberg
      Depression Rating Scale, revised (MADRS) score) 1 day after infusion, for the cohort of
      subjects enrolled in the MDD arm of this trial and 2) improvement in the anxiety symptoms
      (measured by the Multimodal Anxiety Scale for Children (MASC) acute physical symptoms
      subscale) for the cohort of subjects enrolled in the anxiety disorders arm of the trial.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">September 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">September 28, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Participants were randomly assigned the treatment order, with participants receiving a single infusion of either ketamine hydrochloride (0.5 mg/kg) or midazolam (0.045 mg/kg) on Day 1, and the alternate compound 2 weeks later.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>Midazolam was chosen as an active placebo in keeping with its similar pharmacokinetic profile and precedent as a reasonable comparator for nonspecific behavioral effects of ketamine</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Montgomery-Asberg Depression Rating Scale Score 1 Day After Infusion</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day after the infusion</time_frame>
    <description>Depressive symptoms (measured by Montgomery-Asberg Depression Rating Scale, revised (MADRS) score) on 1 day after infusion, for the cohort of subjects enrolled in the MDD arm of this trial.
Higher MADRS score indicates more severe depression, and each item yields a score of 0 to 6. The overall score ranges from 0 to 60.
Usual cutoff points are:
0 to 6 - normal /symptom absent. 7 to 19 - mild depression. 20 to 34 - moderate depression. &gt;34 - severe depression.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">17</enrollment>
  <condition>Major Depressive Disorder</condition>
  <condition>Anxiety Disorder</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Ketamine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants were randomly be assigned to receive a dose of 0.5 mg/kg of Ketamine (administered intravenously over 40 minutes with a maximum total dose allowed in this study will be 50mg).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Midazolam</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants were randomly assigned to receive a dose of 0.045mg/kg of Midazolam (administered Intravenously over 40 minutes with a the maximum total dose allowed in this study of 4.5mg),</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ketamine</intervention_name>
    <description>A single dose of 0.5mg/kg of Ketamine will be administered Intravenously during 40 minutes in the Hospital Research Unit of YNHH. The subject will be monitored continuously during the procedure, and every hour for three hours after the infusion.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Ketamine</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Ketalar</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Midazolam</intervention_name>
    <description>A single dose of 0.045mg/kg of Midazolam will be administered intravenously during 40 minutes in the Hospital Research Unit of YNHH. The subject will be monitored continuously during the procedure, and every hour for three hours after the infusion.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Midazolam</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Versed</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion:

        MDD Cohort:

          -  Meet DSM-5 criteria for Major Depressive Disorder by structured interview (MINI-KID)

          -  CDRS-R score &gt;40.

          -  Failure to achieve remission with at least 1 adequate prior antidepressant trial (e.g.
             SSRI, SNRI, or TCA), meaning at least 8 weeks at therapeutic dosing, including at
             least 4 weeks of stable dosing.

        Anxiety Cohort:

          -  Meet DSM-5 criteria for any of the following anxiety disorders: Social Anxiety
             Disorders, Generalized Anxiety Disorder, Separation Anxiety Disorder and/or Panic
             Disorder by structured interview (MINI-KID)

          -  ADIS Clinical Severity Rating ≥4 (moderately severe) for any of the 4 included anxiety
             disorders

          -  Failure to achieve remission with at least 1 adequate prior anxiolytic medication
             trial (e.g. SSRI, SNRI, or TCA), meaning at least 8 weeks at therapeutic dosing,
             including at least 4 weeks of stable dosing.

          -  Failure to achieve remission with previous CBT or subject declines current CBT therapy

        Both cohorts:

          -  Stable psychiatric medications and doses for the month prior to enrollment. Subjects
             may continue to engage in any ongoing psychotherapy.

          -  Medically and neurologically healthy on the basis of physical examination and medical
             history.

          -  Parents able to provide written informed consent and adolescents must additionally
             provide assent.

        Exclusion:

          -  Current inpatient hospitalization or active suicidal ideation requiring referral for
             inpatient hospitalization for safety.

          -  History of psychotic disorder or manic episode diagnosed by MINI-KID

          -  History of substance dependence diagnosis by MINI-KID (excluding tobacco) or positive
             urine toxicology.

          -  Pregnancy (urine pregnancy tests on the day of scans for menstruating girls).

          -  Inability to provide written informed consent according to the Yale Human
             Investigation Committee (HIC) guidelines in English.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>13 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>17 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Michael H. Bloch, MD MS</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Yale University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Research Unit at the Yale New Haven Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>New Haven</city>
        <state>Connecticut</state>
        <zip>06510</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Yale Child Study Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>New Haven</city>
        <state>Connecticut</state>
        <zip>06520</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Krystal JH, Karper LP, Seibyl JP, Freeman GK, Delaney R, Bremner JD, Heninger GR, Bowers MB Jr, Charney DS. Subanesthetic effects of the noncompetitive NMDA antagonist, ketamine, in humans. Psychotomimetic, perceptual, cognitive, and neuroendocrine responses. Arch Gen Psychiatry. 1994 Mar;51(3):199-214.</citation>
    <PMID>8122957</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Berman RM, Cappiello A, Anand A, Oren DA, Heninger GR, Charney DS, Krystal JH. Antidepressant effects of ketamine in depressed patients. Biol Psychiatry. 2000 Feb 15;47(4):351-4.</citation>
    <PMID>10686270</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zarate CA Jr, Singh JB, Carlson PJ, Brutsche NE, Ameli R, Luckenbaugh DA, Charney DS, Manji HK. A randomized trial of an N-methyl-D-aspartate antagonist in treatment-resistant major depression. Arch Gen Psychiatry. 2006 Aug;63(8):856-64.</citation>
    <PMID>16894061</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Niciu MJ, Ionescu DF, Richards EM, Zarate CA Jr. Glutamate and its receptors in the pathophysiology and treatment of major depressive disorder. J Neural Transm (Vienna). 2014 Aug;121(8):907-24. doi: 10.1007/s00702-013-1130-x. Epub 2013 Dec 8. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24318540</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ballard ED, Ionescu DF, Vande Voort JL, Niciu MJ, Richards EM, Luckenbaugh DA, Brutsché NE, Ameli R, Furey ML, Zarate CA Jr. Improvement in suicidal ideation after ketamine infusion: relationship to reductions in depression and anxiety. J Psychiatr Res. 2014 Nov;58:161-6. doi: 10.1016/j.jpsychires.2014.07.027. Epub 2014 Aug 12.</citation>
    <PMID>25169854</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 16, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 19, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">October 20, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <results_first_submitted>December 5, 2019</results_first_submitted>
  <results_first_submitted_qc>March 2, 2020</results_first_submitted_qc>
  <results_first_posted type="Actual">March 16, 2020</results_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 29, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 29, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 14, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Ketamine</keyword>
  <keyword>Depression</keyword>
  <keyword>Major Depressive Disorder</keyword>
  <keyword>Anxiety</keyword>
  <keyword>School refusal</keyword>
  <keyword>Suicide</keyword>
  <keyword>Generalized Anxiety</keyword>
  <keyword>Suicidal Ideation</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depression</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Anxiety Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder, Major</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Midazolam</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ketamine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <provided_document_section>
    <provided_document>
      <document_type>Study Protocol and Statistical Analysis Plan</document_type>
      <document_has_protocol>Yes</document_has_protocol>
      <document_has_icf>No</document_has_icf>
      <document_has_sap>Yes</document_has_sap>
      <document_date>September 13, 2017</document_date>
      <document_url>https://ClinicalTrials.gov/ProvidedDocs/28/NCT02579928/Prot_SAP_000.pdf</document_url>
    </provided_document>
  </provided_document_section>

  <clinical_results>

    <participant_flow>
      <recruitment_details>Adolescents (aged 13 to 17 years old) were recruited via (1) physician referral or (2) via direct inquiries from families via ClinicalTrials.gov listing. Subjects were enrolled at the Yale Child Study Center (New Haven, CT) between May 2016 and September 2018.</recruitment_details>
      <pre_assignment_details>Participants were to remain on stable dosing of their current medication regimen for the four weeks prior to the first infusion, and during the four-week trial itself. All participants underwent a physical examination, laboratory screening, and electrocardiography.</pre_assignment_details>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="P1">
          <title>Ketamine First Then Midazolam</title>
          <description>Participants received a Ketamine infusion under blinded conditions, followed by a Midazolam infusion 14 days later. The subject were monitored continuously during both infusions, and every hour for three hours after the infusion and then followed clinically for two weeks.
Ketamine was infused at a dose of 0.5mg/kg over 40 minutes and midazolam was infused at a dose of 0.045mg/kg over 40 minutes on the Hospital Research Unit of YNHH.</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="P2">
          <title>Midazolam First Then Ketamine</title>
          <description>Participants received a midazolam infusion under blinded conditions, followed by a ketamine infusion 14 days later. The subject were monitored continuously during both infusions, and every hour for three hours after the infusion and then followed clinically for two weeks.
Midazolam was infused at a dose of 0.045mg/kg over 40 minutes and ketamine was infused at a dose of 0.5mg/kg over 40 minutes on the Hospital Research Unit of YNHH.</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <period_list>
        <period>
          <title>Overall Study</title>
          <milestone_list>
            <milestone>
              <title>STARTED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="6"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="11"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>COMPLETED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="5"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="11"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>NOT COMPLETED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="1"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="0"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
          </milestone_list>
          <drop_withdraw_reason_list>
            <drop_withdraw_reason>
              <title>Withdrawal by Subject</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="1"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="0"/>
              </participants_list>
            </drop_withdraw_reason>
          </drop_withdraw_reason_list>
        </period>
      </period_list>
    </participant_flow>

    <baseline>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="B1">
          <title>Received Ketamine in the First Infusion</title>
          <description>Participants that were randomly assigned to receive a dose of 0.5 mg/kg of Ketamine to be administered Intravenously during 40 minutes in the Hospital Research Unit of YNHH. Participants were monitored continuously during the procedure, and every hour for three hours after the infusion.</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="B2">
          <title>Received Midazolam in the First Infusion</title>
          <description>Participants that were assigned to receive a dose of 0.045mg/kg of Midazolam, administered Intravenously during 40 minutes in the Hospital Research Unit of YNHH. Participants were monitored continuously during the procedure, and every hour for three hours after the infusion</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="B3">
          <title>Total</title>
          <description>Total of all reporting groups</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <analyzed_list>
        <analyzed>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <scope>Overall</scope>
          <count_list>
            <count group_id="B1" value="6"/>
            <count group_id="B2" value="11"/>
            <count group_id="B3" value="17"/>
          </count_list>
        </analyzed>
      </analyzed_list>
      <measure_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Age</title>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <param>Count of Participants</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <title>&lt;=18 years</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="6"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="11"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="17"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Between 18 and 65 years</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>&gt;=65 years</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Age</title>
          <units>years</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>Full Range</dispersion>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="15.3" lower_limit="13" upper_limit="17"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="15.6" lower_limit="13" upper_limit="17"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="15.4" lower_limit="13" upper_limit="17"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Sex: Female, Male</title>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <param>Count of Participants</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <title>Female</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="5"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="8"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="13"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Male</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="1"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="3"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="4"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Race (NIH/OMB)</title>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <param>Count of Participants</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <title>American Indian or Alaska Native</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Asian</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="1"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="1"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Native Hawaiian or Other Pacific Islander</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Black or African American</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="2"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="2"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>White</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="5"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="9"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="14"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>More than one race</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Unknown or Not Reported</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Baseline Score for the Montgomery-Asberg Depression Rating Scale sc ore</title>
          <description>Higher scores in this scale indicate more severe depression; each item yields a score of 0 to 6. Clinical judgment determines the rate on the defined scale steps 0, 2, 4, 6 points or between them1, 3, 5 points, denoted as Worsening symptoms.
It questions the following symptoms:Apparent sadness, Reported sadness, Inner tension, Reduced sleep, Reduced appetite, Concentration difficulties, Lassitude, Inability to feel, Pessimistic thoughts, Suicidal thoughts.
Usual cutoff are:0 to 6 normal /symptom absent;7 to 19 mild depression; 20 to 34 moderate depression and &gt;34 severe depression.</description>
          <units>units on a scale</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>Standard Deviation</dispersion>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="35.6" spread="7.1"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="31.8" spread="10.2"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="32.9" spread="9.1"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </measure_list>
    </baseline>

    <outcome_list>
      <outcome>
        <type>Primary</type>
        <title>Montgomery-Asberg Depression Rating Scale Score 1 Day After Infusion</title>
        <description>Depressive symptoms (measured by Montgomery-Asberg Depression Rating Scale, revised (MADRS) score) on 1 day after infusion, for the cohort of subjects enrolled in the MDD arm of this trial.
Higher MADRS score indicates more severe depression, and each item yields a score of 0 to 6. The overall score ranges from 0 to 60.
Usual cutoff points are:
0 to 6 - normal /symptom absent. 7 to 19 - mild depression. 20 to 34 - moderate depression. &gt;34 - severe depression.</description>
        <time_frame>1 day after the infusion</time_frame>
        <population>A total of 17 patients were randomized to receive either Ketamine or Midazolam in the first infusion, one participant in withdrew from the trail after the first infusion because of improvement in her depressive symptoms and did not receive the second infusion.</population>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Ketamine</title>
            <description>Participants were randomly be assigned to receive a dose of 0.5 mg/kg of Ketamine (administered intravenously over 40 minutes with a maximum total dose allowed in this study will be 50mg). The participants were monitored continuously during the procedure, and every hour for three hours after the infusion.
Followed up clinically for the next 2 weeks.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>Midazolam</title>
            <description>Participants were assigned to receive a dose of 0.045mg/kg of Midazolam (administered Intravenously over 40 minutes with a the maximum total dose allowed in this study of 4.5mg), The participants were monitored continuously during the procedure, and every hour for three hours after the infusion.They were followed clinically for two weeks.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Montgomery-Asberg Depression Rating Scale Score 1 Day After Infusion</title>
          <description>Depressive symptoms (measured by Montgomery-Asberg Depression Rating Scale, revised (MADRS) score) on 1 day after infusion, for the cohort of subjects enrolled in the MDD arm of this trial.
Higher MADRS score indicates more severe depression, and each item yields a score of 0 to 6. The overall score ranges from 0 to 60.
Usual cutoff points are:
0 to 6 - normal /symptom absent. 7 to 19 - mild depression. 20 to 34 - moderate depression. &gt;34 - severe depression.</description>
          <population>A total of 17 patients were randomized to receive either Ketamine or Midazolam in the first infusion, one participant in withdrew from the trail after the first infusion because of improvement in her depressive symptoms and did not receive the second infusion.</population>
          <units>units on a scale</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>95% Confidence Interval</dispersion>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="16"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="16"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="15.44" lower_limit="10.51" upper_limit="20.37"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="24.13" lower_limit="18.21" upper_limit="30.04"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
    </outcome_list>

    <reported_events>
      <time_frame>1 hour after after infusion.</time_frame>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="E1">
          <title>Ketamine</title>
          <description>Participants were randomly be assigned to receive a dose of 0.5 mg/kg of Ketamine (administered intravenously over 40 minutes with a maximum total dose allowed in this study will be 50mg).
Ketamine: A single dose of 0.5mg/kg of Ketamine will be administered Intravenously during 40 minutes in the Hospital Research Unit of YNHH. The subject will be monitored continuously during the procedure, and every hour for three hours after the infusion.</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="E2">
          <title>Midazolam</title>
          <description>Participants were randomly assigned to receive a dose of 0.045mg/kg of Midazolam (administered Intravenously over 40 minutes with a the maximum total dose allowed in this study of 4.5mg),
Midazolam: A single dose of 0.045mg/kg of Midazolam will be administered intravenously during 40 minutes in the Hospital Research Unit of YNHH. The subject will be monitored continuously during the procedure, and every hour for three hours after the infusion.</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <serious_events>
        <category_list>
          <category>
            <title>Total</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, all-cause mortality</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="17"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="16"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, serious adverse events</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="17"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="16"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
        </category_list>
      </serious_events>
      <other_events>
        <frequency_threshold>5</frequency_threshold>
        <default_vocab>CADSS</default_vocab>
        <default_assessment>Systematic Assessment</default_assessment>
        <category_list>
          <category>
            <title>Total</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, other adverse events</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="15" subjects_at_risk="17"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="13" subjects_at_risk="16"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Nervous system disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Feeling like I am in a dream</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="15" subjects_affected="15" subjects_at_risk="17"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="16"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Spaced out</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="14" subjects_affected="14" subjects_at_risk="17"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="13" subjects_affected="13" subjects_at_risk="16"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Disconnected from body</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="12" subjects_affected="12" subjects_at_risk="17"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="2" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="16"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Feeling like thigs are in slow motion</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="11" subjects_affected="11" subjects_at_risk="17"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="16"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Body parts feel large or small</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="11" subjects_affected="11" subjects_at_risk="17"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="16"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Time is moving quickly</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="11" subjects_affected="11" subjects_at_risk="17"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="16"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Feeling like you are in a movie or are a robot</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="9" subjects_affected="9" subjects_at_risk="17"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="16"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Objects appear different</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="9" subjects_affected="9" subjects_at_risk="17"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="16"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Sounds changed</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="9" subjects_affected="9" subjects_at_risk="17"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="16"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>World appears in a fog</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="7" subjects_affected="7" subjects_at_risk="17"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="16"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Gaps in memory</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="7" subjects_affected="7" subjects_at_risk="17"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="3" subjects_affected="3" subjects_at_risk="16"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
        </category_list>
      </other_events>
    </reported_events>

    <certain_agreements>
      <pi_employee>Principal Investigators are NOT employed by the organization sponsoring the study.</pi_employee>
      <restrictive_agreement>There is NOT an agreement between Principal Investigators and the Sponsor (or its agents) that restricts the PI's rights to discuss or publish trial results after the trial is completed. </restrictive_agreement>
    </certain_agreements>
    <limitations_and_caveats>The small sample size and the smaller number of subjects who were randomized to receive ketamine prior to midazolam.</limitations_and_caveats>
    <point_of_contact>
      <name_or_title>Dr. Michael H. Bloch</name_or_title>
      <organization>Yale University</organization>
      <phone>2037374539</phone>
      <email>michael.bloch@yale.edu</email>
    </point_of_contact>
  </clinical_results>
</clinical_study>

