<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02575079</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IRB00080344</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02575079</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Parafilm to Prevent CLABSI in Pediatric Patients Undergoing HCT</brief_title>
  <official_title>Parafilm Application to Prevent Central Line Associated Bloodstream Infections in Pediatric Patients Undergoing Hematopoietic Cell Transplantation</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Emory University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Emory University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to see if applying parafilm as an external barrier on the
      central line in children having a bone marrow transplant helps to prevent central line
      associated bloodstream infection(s) and also to assess the ease of use of parafilm.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Central line associated bloodstream infections (CLABSI) result in significant morbidity and
      mortality, particularly in patients undergoing hematopoietic cell transplantation (HCT). HCT
      patients are at high risk for CLABSI due to multiple factors, including prolonged immune
      suppression and the need for long-term central venous access. The investigators want to
      assess the feasibility of the use of a parafilm central line barrier (parafilm) as standard
      of care in pediatric HCT patients. The investigators will also assess the effectiveness of
      the parafilm to reduce the incidence of CLABSI in these patients.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 29, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 29, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Arm 1 is comprised of study participants receiving parafilm applied over the CVC hub or around the CVC hub connection. Arm 2 is a retrospective historical cohort of pediatric patients receiving HCT for the purpose of comparing CLABSI rates.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of Central Line Associated Bloodstream Infections (CLABSI)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline (at the time of placement of the CVC or admission for HCT, whichever occurs later) to end of study (CVC removal or transfer back to primary service, whichever occurs sooner, average of 3 months)</time_frame>
    <description>Central line associated bloodstream infections (CLABSI) is the identification of a bacterial infection from a blood culture drawn from a central venous catheter (CVC) in the absence of a primary source of infection from another body site. The CLABSI rate (total number of CLABSI/1000 catheter-days) in parafilm study participants will be calculated and compared to the CLABSI rate in a historical cohort of pediatric patients who are serving as a control group.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Reported Inpatient Percentage of Central-line Days With Correctly Applied Parafilm</measure>
    <time_frame>At discharge (an expected average of 6 weeks from admission)</time_frame>
    <description>In the inpatient setting, compliance was measured by once daily recording of parafilm change by nursing in the electronic medical record. These data were significantly limited by electronic medical record charting on parafilm change being required only once per day. Thus, once daily data collection failed to capture daily parafilm change, given multiple nursing shifts on a single calendar day. Nonetheless, the percentage of catheter-days with intact correctly applied parafilm, as reported by nursing staff, was calculated.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Observed Inpatient Percentage of Catheter-days With Correctly Applied Parafilm</measure>
    <time_frame>Time between initial bone marrow transplant (BMT) discharge and either central venous line (CVL) removal or transfer back to primary MD (an expected average of 2-3 months)</time_frame>
    <description>Observed compliance occurred during weekly line rounds. Rounding providers indicated whether a patient's parafilm is intact and correctly applied, not applied, or incorrectly applied or not intact. The percentage of &quot;observed catheter-days&quot; where patients had correct use of intact parafilm were to be calculated. To track observed inpatient compliance with applying parafilm, data fields were added to the entered to the nursing charts of the participant's electronic medical record (EMR). The primary field added was a no/question about parafilm applied. Per study protocol, the intent was to document nursing changing of the parafilm, at the time it was changed. However, on reviewing the data, it appears that nursing just charted once per day whether they had changed parafilm or not, while the parafilm may have been changed earlier by a different nurse.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Reported Outpatient Percentage of Catheter-days With Correctly Applied Parafilm</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline (at the time of placement of the CVC or admission for HCT, whichever occurs later) to end of study (CVC removal or transfer back to primary service, whichever occurs sooner, average of 3 months)</time_frame>
    <description>For outpatient reported compliance, parents of study participants provided their logs to outpatient staff who documented the number of days parafilm was correctly in use/intact vs not in use or incorrectly in use/not intact. The cumulative percentage of catheter-days where parafilm was intact was calculated.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Observed Outpatient Percentage of Catheter-days With Correctly Applied Parafilm</measure>
    <time_frame>Time between initial BMT discharge and either CVL removal or transfer back to primary MD (an expected average of 2-3 months)</time_frame>
    <description>For observed compliance, the outpatient nurse recorded whether the patient's parafilm was correctly applied/intact (yes), not applied (no), or incorrectly applied/not intact (yes-inc) at the beginning of the visit. The percentage of outpatient &quot;observed catheter-days&quot; where parafilm was correctly in use/intact was calculated.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Antibiotic Treatment Courses Per Participant</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline (at the time of placement of the CVC or admission for HCT, whichever occurs later) to end of study (CVC removal or transfer back to primary service, whichever occurs sooner, average of 3 months)</time_frame>
    <description>The number of antibiotic treatment courses per participant in the parafilm study will be recorded.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of Antibiotic Treatment Exposure</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline (at the time of placement of the CVC or admission for HCT, whichever occurs later) to end of study (CVC removal or transfer back to primary service, whichever occurs sooner, average of 3 months)</time_frame>
    <description>Total duration of antibiotic treatment exposure (excluding prophylactic antibiotics) among participants in the parafilm study will be reported.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of ICU Admissions Secondary to Sepsis</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline (at the time of placement of the CVC or admission for HCT, whichever occurs later) to end of study (CVC removal or transfer back to primary service, whichever occurs sooner, average of 3 months)</time_frame>
    <description>The cumulative number of ICU admissions secondary to sepsis among participants in the parafilm study is reported.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Death</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline (at the time of placement of the CVC or admission for HCT, whichever occurs later) to end of study (CVC removal or transfer back to primary service, whichever occurs sooner, average of 3 months)</time_frame>
    <description>Deaths from infection and death from any cause among participants in the parafilm study are reported.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Perception of Parafilm</measure>
    <time_frame>Month 3 (average time till removal of CVC)</time_frame>
    <description>The perception of parafilm from provider and caregiver surveys regarding parafilm ease of use, perceived benefit, and other parameters will be reported</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">119</enrollment>
  <condition>Central Line Associated Bloodstream Infections (CLABSI)</condition>
  <condition>Bone Marrow Transplant</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Parafilm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Pediatric patients undergoing hematopoietic stem cell transplant (HCT) with central venous catheters (CVCs) will have pre-cut, single-use sections of parafilm applied over the CVC hub (if not connected) or around the CVC hub connection (if connected). Parafilm will be maintained on the CVC and routine CVC care will be continued, per institutional standard of practice, until the CVC is removed.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Historical Cohort</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Pediatric patients receiving hematopoietic cell transplantation in the 16 months preceding the study intervention. Data were obtained retrospectively through medical records for the purpose of comparing CLABSI rates among recipients of parafilm to a control group.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Parafilm</intervention_name>
    <description>Single-use, pre-cut sections of parafilm over the central venous catheter (CVC) hub (if not connected) or around the CVC hub connection (if connected). Parafilm will be maintained on the CVC until it is removed.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Parafilm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Must be between the age of 0 and 21 years at the time of enrollment

          -  Must be undergoing allogeneic or autologous HCT for a malignant or non-malignant
             disorder

          -  Must have or be scheduled to have a tunneled CVC

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients undergoing other interventions to prevent CLABSI (e.g. Children's Oncology
             Group (COG) study ACCL1034 with Chlorhexidine Gluconate (CHG); antimicrobial lock
             therapy, etc.)

          -  Patients who only have a port
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>21 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Lakshmanan Krishnamurti, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Emory University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Children's Healthcare of Atlanta</name>
      <address>
        <city>Atlanta</city>
        <state>Georgia</state>
        <zip>30322</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Stenger EO, Newton JG, Leong T, Kendrick L, McManus L, Rooke C, Krishnamurti L. Application of parafilm as a physical barrier on CVC connections is feasible and may reduce CLABSI among pediatric HCT patients. Biology of Blood Marrow Transplantation 25 (Suppl 3): S131, 2019.</citation>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>June 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 12, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 12, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">October 14, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <results_first_submitted>March 29, 2019</results_first_submitted>
  <results_first_submitted_qc>June 6, 2019</results_first_submitted_qc>
  <results_first_posted type="Actual">June 25, 2019</results_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 6, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 6, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 25, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Emory University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Lakshmanan Krishnamurti</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Infection</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <provided_document_section>
    <provided_document>
      <document_type>Study Protocol and Statistical Analysis Plan</document_type>
      <document_has_protocol>Yes</document_has_protocol>
      <document_has_icf>No</document_has_icf>
      <document_has_sap>Yes</document_has_sap>
      <document_date>October 24, 2018</document_date>
      <document_url>https://ClinicalTrials.gov/ProvidedDocs/79/NCT02575079/Prot_SAP_000.pdf</document_url>
    </provided_document>
  </provided_document_section>

  <clinical_results>

    <participant_flow>
      <recruitment_details>Participants were enrolled in the parafilm study between March 2015 and June 2017. All study procedures and follow up was completed on March 29, 2018.</recruitment_details>
      <pre_assignment_details>Fifty-one individuals consented to participate in the study. Prior to beginning any study interventions one was lost to follow up, one withdrew, and one did not begin the prep regimen, resulting in 48 participants who began the study intervention.</pre_assignment_details>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="P1">
          <title>Parafilm</title>
          <description>Pediatric patients undergoing hematopoietic stem cell transplant (HCT) with central venous catheters (CVCs) who had pre-cut, single-use sections of parafilm applied over the CVC hub (if not connected) or around the CVC hub connection (if connected).</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="P2">
          <title>Historical Cohort</title>
          <description>Pediatric patients receiving hematopoietic cell transplantation in the 16 months preceding the study intervention. Data were obtained retrospectively through medical records for the purpose of comparing CLABSI rates among recipients of parafilm to a control group.</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <period_list>
        <period>
          <title>Overall Study</title>
          <milestone_list>
            <milestone>
              <title>STARTED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="48"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="71"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>COMPLETED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="42"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="71"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>NOT COMPLETED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="6"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="0"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
          </milestone_list>
          <drop_withdraw_reason_list>
            <drop_withdraw_reason>
              <title>Death</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="3"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="0"/>
              </participants_list>
            </drop_withdraw_reason>
            <drop_withdraw_reason>
              <title>Withdrawal by Subject</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="3"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="0"/>
              </participants_list>
            </drop_withdraw_reason>
          </drop_withdraw_reason_list>
        </period>
      </period_list>
    </participant_flow>

    <baseline>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="B1">
          <title>Parafilm</title>
          <description>Pediatric patients undergoing hematopoietic stem cell transplant (HCT) with central venous catheters (CVCs) who had pre-cut, single-use sections of parafilm applied over the CVC hub (if not connected) or around the CVC hub connection (if connected).</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="B2">
          <title>Historical Cohort</title>
          <description>Pediatric patients receiving hematopoietic cell transplantation in the 16 months preceding the study intervention. Data were obtained retrospectively through medical records for the purpose of comparing CLABSI rates among recipients of parafilm to a control group.</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="B3">
          <title>Total</title>
          <description>Total of all reporting groups</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <analyzed_list>
        <analyzed>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <scope>Overall</scope>
          <count_list>
            <count group_id="B1" value="48"/>
            <count group_id="B2" value="71"/>
            <count group_id="B3" value="119"/>
          </count_list>
        </analyzed>
      </analyzed_list>
      <measure_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Age, Customized</title>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <param>Count of Participants</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>Age in years</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <title>Less than or equal to 2 years</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="7"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="21"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="28"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Between 3 and 9 years</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="25"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="22"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="47"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Between 10 and 21 years</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="16"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="28"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="44"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Sex: Female, Male</title>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <param>Count of Participants</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <title>Female</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="17"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="25"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="42"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Male</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="31"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="46"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="77"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Ethnicity (NIH/OMB)</title>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <param>Count of Participants</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <title>Hispanic or Latino</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="8"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="6"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="14"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Not Hispanic or Latino</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="40"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="65"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="105"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Unknown or Not Reported</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Race/Ethnicity, Customized</title>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <param>Count of Participants</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>Ethnicity</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <title>Asian</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="4"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="4"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Black or African American</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="21"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="32"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="53"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>White</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="25"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="34"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="59"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Other</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="2"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="1"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="3"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Region of Enrollment</title>
          <units>participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>United States</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="48"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="71"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="119"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Type of HCT</title>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <param>Count of Participants</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <title>Allogeneic</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="35"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="49"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="84"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Autologous</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="13"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="22"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="35"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Underlying disease</title>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <param>Count of Participants</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <title>Malignant, hematologic</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="17"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="24"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="41"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Malignant, solid tumor</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="12"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="21"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="33"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Non-malignant</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="19"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="26"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="45"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </measure_list>
    </baseline>

    <outcome_list>
      <outcome>
        <type>Primary</type>
        <title>Rate of Central Line Associated Bloodstream Infections (CLABSI)</title>
        <description>Central line associated bloodstream infections (CLABSI) is the identification of a bacterial infection from a blood culture drawn from a central venous catheter (CVC) in the absence of a primary source of infection from another body site. The CLABSI rate (total number of CLABSI/1000 catheter-days) in parafilm study participants will be calculated and compared to the CLABSI rate in a historical cohort of pediatric patients who are serving as a control group.</description>
        <time_frame>Baseline (at the time of placement of the CVC or admission for HCT, whichever occurs later) to end of study (CVC removal or transfer back to primary service, whichever occurs sooner, average of 3 months)</time_frame>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Parafilm</title>
            <description>Pediatric patients undergoing hematopoietic stem cell transplant (HCT) with central venous catheters (CVCs) who had pre-cut, single-use sections of parafilm applied over the CVC hub (if not connected) or around the CVC hub connection (if connected).</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>Historical Cohort</title>
            <description>Pediatric patients receiving hematopoietic cell transplantation in the 16 months preceding the study intervention. Data were obtained retrospectively through medical records for the purpose of comparing CLABSI rates among recipients of parafilm to a control group.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Rate of Central Line Associated Bloodstream Infections (CLABSI)</title>
          <description>Central line associated bloodstream infections (CLABSI) is the identification of a bacterial infection from a blood culture drawn from a central venous catheter (CVC) in the absence of a primary source of infection from another body site. The CLABSI rate (total number of CLABSI/1000 catheter-days) in parafilm study participants will be calculated and compared to the CLABSI rate in a historical cohort of pediatric patients who are serving as a control group.</description>
          <units>CLABSI/1000 catheter-days</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <dispersion>95% Confidence Interval</dispersion>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="48"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="71"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="3.69" lower_limit="2.19" upper_limit="5.83"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="4.37" lower_limit="2.86" upper_limit="6.40"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Primary</type>
        <title>Reported Inpatient Percentage of Central-line Days With Correctly Applied Parafilm</title>
        <description>In the inpatient setting, compliance was measured by once daily recording of parafilm change by nursing in the electronic medical record. These data were significantly limited by electronic medical record charting on parafilm change being required only once per day. Thus, once daily data collection failed to capture daily parafilm change, given multiple nursing shifts on a single calendar day. Nonetheless, the percentage of catheter-days with intact correctly applied parafilm, as reported by nursing staff, was calculated.</description>
        <time_frame>At discharge (an expected average of 6 weeks from admission)</time_frame>
        <population>Participants in the parafilm study are included in this analysis. Percentage of inpatient days where nursing charted parafilm change in the electronic medical record is reported for the entire parafilm cohort.</population>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Parafilm</title>
            <description>Pediatric patients undergoing hematopoietic stem cell transplant (HCT) with central venous catheters (CVCs) who had pre-cut, single-use sections of parafilm applied over the CVC hub (if not connected) or around the CVC hub connection (if connected).</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Reported Inpatient Percentage of Central-line Days With Correctly Applied Parafilm</title>
          <description>In the inpatient setting, compliance was measured by once daily recording of parafilm change by nursing in the electronic medical record. These data were significantly limited by electronic medical record charting on parafilm change being required only once per day. Thus, once daily data collection failed to capture daily parafilm change, given multiple nursing shifts on a single calendar day. Nonetheless, the percentage of catheter-days with intact correctly applied parafilm, as reported by nursing staff, was calculated.</description>
          <population>Participants in the parafilm study are included in this analysis. Percentage of inpatient days where nursing charted parafilm change in the electronic medical record is reported for the entire parafilm cohort.</population>
          <units>percentage of central-line days</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="48"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="65.2"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Primary</type>
        <title>Observed Inpatient Percentage of Catheter-days With Correctly Applied Parafilm</title>
        <description>Observed compliance occurred during weekly line rounds. Rounding providers indicated whether a patient's parafilm is intact and correctly applied, not applied, or incorrectly applied or not intact. The percentage of &quot;observed catheter-days&quot; where patients had correct use of intact parafilm were to be calculated. To track observed inpatient compliance with applying parafilm, data fields were added to the entered to the nursing charts of the participant's electronic medical record (EMR). The primary field added was a no/question about parafilm applied. Per study protocol, the intent was to document nursing changing of the parafilm, at the time it was changed. However, on reviewing the data, it appears that nursing just charted once per day whether they had changed parafilm or not, while the parafilm may have been changed earlier by a different nurse.</description>
        <time_frame>Time between initial bone marrow transplant (BMT) discharge and either central venous line (CVL) removal or transfer back to primary MD (an expected average of 2-3 months)</time_frame>
        <population>The data collected indicated that nursing staff did not understand how the parafilm monitoring needed to be charted for the purposes of data analysis. Although a data field was created in the EMR, in practice, the data collected was not an accurate assessment of parafilm use, thus no data are available for analysis of this outcome measure.</population>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Parafilm</title>
            <description>Pediatric patients undergoing hematopoietic stem cell transplant (HCT) with central venous catheters (CVCs) who had pre-cut, single-use sections of parafilm applied over the CVC hub (if not connected) or around the CVC hub connection (if connected).</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Observed Inpatient Percentage of Catheter-days With Correctly Applied Parafilm</title>
          <description>Observed compliance occurred during weekly line rounds. Rounding providers indicated whether a patient's parafilm is intact and correctly applied, not applied, or incorrectly applied or not intact. The percentage of &quot;observed catheter-days&quot; where patients had correct use of intact parafilm were to be calculated. To track observed inpatient compliance with applying parafilm, data fields were added to the entered to the nursing charts of the participant's electronic medical record (EMR). The primary field added was a no/question about parafilm applied. Per study protocol, the intent was to document nursing changing of the parafilm, at the time it was changed. However, on reviewing the data, it appears that nursing just charted once per day whether they had changed parafilm or not, while the parafilm may have been changed earlier by a different nurse.</description>
          <population>The data collected indicated that nursing staff did not understand how the parafilm monitoring needed to be charted for the purposes of data analysis. Although a data field was created in the EMR, in practice, the data collected was not an accurate assessment of parafilm use, thus no data are available for analysis of this outcome measure.</population>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="0"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Primary</type>
        <title>Reported Outpatient Percentage of Catheter-days With Correctly Applied Parafilm</title>
        <description>For outpatient reported compliance, parents of study participants provided their logs to outpatient staff who documented the number of days parafilm was correctly in use/intact vs not in use or incorrectly in use/not intact. The cumulative percentage of catheter-days where parafilm was intact was calculated.</description>
        <time_frame>Baseline (at the time of placement of the CVC or admission for HCT, whichever occurs later) to end of study (CVC removal or transfer back to primary service, whichever occurs sooner, average of 3 months)</time_frame>
        <population>The population used for this analysis consists of caretakers who returned outpatient logs of parafilm use at the end of the study. Forty-one participants used parafilm in the outpatient setting and of these 34 returned the outpatient logs.</population>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Parafilm</title>
            <description>Pediatric patients undergoing hematopoietic stem cell transplant (HCT) with central venous catheters (CVCs) who had pre-cut, single-use sections of parafilm applied over the CVC hub (if not connected) or around the CVC hub connection (if connected).</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Reported Outpatient Percentage of Catheter-days With Correctly Applied Parafilm</title>
          <description>For outpatient reported compliance, parents of study participants provided their logs to outpatient staff who documented the number of days parafilm was correctly in use/intact vs not in use or incorrectly in use/not intact. The cumulative percentage of catheter-days where parafilm was intact was calculated.</description>
          <population>The population used for this analysis consists of caretakers who returned outpatient logs of parafilm use at the end of the study. Forty-one participants used parafilm in the outpatient setting and of these 34 returned the outpatient logs.</population>
          <units>percent of catheter-days</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="34"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="64.7"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Primary</type>
        <title>Observed Outpatient Percentage of Catheter-days With Correctly Applied Parafilm</title>
        <description>For observed compliance, the outpatient nurse recorded whether the patient's parafilm was correctly applied/intact (yes), not applied (no), or incorrectly applied/not intact (yes-inc) at the beginning of the visit. The percentage of outpatient &quot;observed catheter-days&quot; where parafilm was correctly in use/intact was calculated.</description>
        <time_frame>Time between initial BMT discharge and either CVL removal or transfer back to primary MD (an expected average of 2-3 months)</time_frame>
        <population>Observed outpatient compliance was not performed as it was difficult to implement this in a busy clinic setting.</population>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Parafilm</title>
            <description>Pediatric patients undergoing hematopoietic stem cell transplant (HCT) with central venous catheters (CVCs) who had pre-cut, single-use sections of parafilm applied over the CVC hub (if not connected) or around the CVC hub connection (if connected).</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Observed Outpatient Percentage of Catheter-days With Correctly Applied Parafilm</title>
          <description>For observed compliance, the outpatient nurse recorded whether the patient's parafilm was correctly applied/intact (yes), not applied (no), or incorrectly applied/not intact (yes-inc) at the beginning of the visit. The percentage of outpatient &quot;observed catheter-days&quot; where parafilm was correctly in use/intact was calculated.</description>
          <population>Observed outpatient compliance was not performed as it was difficult to implement this in a busy clinic setting.</population>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="0"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Secondary</type>
        <title>Number of Antibiotic Treatment Courses Per Participant</title>
        <description>The number of antibiotic treatment courses per participant in the parafilm study will be recorded.</description>
        <time_frame>Baseline (at the time of placement of the CVC or admission for HCT, whichever occurs later) to end of study (CVC removal or transfer back to primary service, whichever occurs sooner, average of 3 months)</time_frame>
        <population>Data on antibiotic treatment courses were not collected.</population>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Parafilm</title>
            <description>Pediatric patients undergoing hematopoietic stem cell transplant (HCT) with central venous catheters (CVCs) who had pre-cut, single-use sections of parafilm applied over the CVC hub (if not connected) or around the CVC hub connection (if connected).</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Number of Antibiotic Treatment Courses Per Participant</title>
          <description>The number of antibiotic treatment courses per participant in the parafilm study will be recorded.</description>
          <population>Data on antibiotic treatment courses were not collected.</population>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="0"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Secondary</type>
        <title>Duration of Antibiotic Treatment Exposure</title>
        <description>Total duration of antibiotic treatment exposure (excluding prophylactic antibiotics) among participants in the parafilm study will be reported.</description>
        <time_frame>Baseline (at the time of placement of the CVC or admission for HCT, whichever occurs later) to end of study (CVC removal or transfer back to primary service, whichever occurs sooner, average of 3 months)</time_frame>
        <population>Data on duration of antibiotic treatments were not collected.</population>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Parafilm</title>
            <description>Pediatric patients undergoing hematopoietic stem cell transplant (HCT) with central venous catheters (CVCs) who had pre-cut, single-use sections of parafilm applied over the CVC hub (if not connected) or around the CVC hub connection (if connected).</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Duration of Antibiotic Treatment Exposure</title>
          <description>Total duration of antibiotic treatment exposure (excluding prophylactic antibiotics) among participants in the parafilm study will be reported.</description>
          <population>Data on duration of antibiotic treatments were not collected.</population>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="0"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Secondary</type>
        <title>Number of ICU Admissions Secondary to Sepsis</title>
        <description>The cumulative number of ICU admissions secondary to sepsis among participants in the parafilm study is reported.</description>
        <time_frame>Baseline (at the time of placement of the CVC or admission for HCT, whichever occurs later) to end of study (CVC removal or transfer back to primary service, whichever occurs sooner, average of 3 months)</time_frame>
        <population>Participants in the parafilm study are included in this analysis.</population>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Parafilm</title>
            <description>Pediatric patients undergoing hematopoietic stem cell transplant (HCT) with central venous catheters (CVCs) who had pre-cut, single-use sections of parafilm applied over the CVC hub (if not connected) or around the CVC hub connection (if connected).</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Number of ICU Admissions Secondary to Sepsis</title>
          <description>The cumulative number of ICU admissions secondary to sepsis among participants in the parafilm study is reported.</description>
          <population>Participants in the parafilm study are included in this analysis.</population>
          <units>ICU admissions</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="48"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="8"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Secondary</type>
        <title>Death</title>
        <description>Deaths from infection and death from any cause among participants in the parafilm study are reported.</description>
        <time_frame>Baseline (at the time of placement of the CVC or admission for HCT, whichever occurs later) to end of study (CVC removal or transfer back to primary service, whichever occurs sooner, average of 3 months)</time_frame>
        <population>Participants in the parafilm study are included in this analysis.</population>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Parafilm</title>
            <description>Pediatric patients undergoing hematopoietic stem cell transplant (HCT) with central venous catheters (CVCs) who had pre-cut, single-use sections of parafilm applied over the CVC hub (if not connected) or around the CVC hub connection (if connected).</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Death</title>
          <description>Deaths from infection and death from any cause among participants in the parafilm study are reported.</description>
          <population>Participants in the parafilm study are included in this analysis.</population>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <param>Count of Participants</param>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="48"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>Death from infection</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Death from any cause</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="3"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Secondary</type>
        <title>Perception of Parafilm</title>
        <description>The perception of parafilm from provider and caregiver surveys regarding parafilm ease of use, perceived benefit, and other parameters will be reported</description>
        <time_frame>Month 3 (average time till removal of CVC)</time_frame>
        <population>A survey was initially planned for in the protocol but was removed from the study procedures prior to any participants completing the survey.</population>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Parafilm</title>
            <description>Pediatric patients undergoing hematopoietic stem cell transplant (HCT) with central venous catheters (CVCs) who had pre-cut, single-use sections of parafilm applied over the CVC hub (if not connected) or around the CVC hub connection (if connected).</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Perception of Parafilm</title>
          <description>The perception of parafilm from provider and caregiver surveys regarding parafilm ease of use, perceived benefit, and other parameters will be reported</description>
          <population>A survey was initially planned for in the protocol but was removed from the study procedures prior to any participants completing the survey.</population>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="0"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
    </outcome_list>

    <reported_events>
      <time_frame>Adverse events were collected from the time a participant entered the study until CVC removal (3 months on average).</time_frame>
      <desc>Adverse events will be described using event terms and severity grading from the National Cancer Institute (NCI) CTCAE version 4.0. Adverse events will be characterized by severity grading, attribution (relationship to study treatment), and expectedness (based upon prior experience). Only unexpected serious adverse events and serious adverse events related to the study intervention were collected. Non-serious adverse events were not collected.</desc>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="E1">
          <title>Parafilm</title>
          <description>Pediatric patients undergoing hematopoietic stem cell transplant (HCT) with central venous catheters (CVCs) who had pre-cut, single-use sections of parafilm applied over the CVC hub (if not connected) or around the CVC hub connection (if connected).</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <serious_events>
        <default_assessment>Non-systematic Assessment</default_assessment>
        <category_list>
          <category>
            <title>Total</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, all-cause mortality</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="3" subjects_at_risk="48"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, serious adverse events</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="3" subjects_at_risk="48"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Immune system disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Graft versus host disease (GVHD)</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="2" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="48"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Respiratory, thoracic and mediastinal disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Acute hypoxemic respiratory failure</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="48"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
        </category_list>
      </serious_events>
      <other_events>
        <frequency_threshold>0</frequency_threshold>
        <category_list>
          <category>
            <title>Total</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, other adverse events</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="0"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
        </category_list>
      </other_events>
    </reported_events>

    <certain_agreements>
      <pi_employee>All Principal Investigators ARE employed by the organization sponsoring the study.</pi_employee>
      <restrictive_agreement>There is NOT an agreement between Principal Investigators and the Sponsor (or its agents) that restricts the PI's rights to discuss or publish trial results after the trial is completed. </restrictive_agreement>
    </certain_agreements>
    <limitations_and_caveats>Assessing feasibility of outpatient parafilm use was limited by difficulty collecting parafilm compliance calendars from caretakers and observed variability of compliance in the outpatient setting.</limitations_and_caveats>
    <point_of_contact>
      <name_or_title>Elizabeth Stenger</name_or_title>
      <organization>Emory University</organization>
      <phone>404-785-1272</phone>
      <email>elizabeth.o'brien.stenger@emory.edu</email>
    </point_of_contact>
  </clinical_results>
</clinical_study>

