<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04303143</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HypDax1</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04303143</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Hypnosis and Direct Autonomic Experience Influence on Chronic Symptoms</brief_title>
  <acronym>HDAX1</acronym>
  <official_title>Hypnosis and Direct Autonomic Experience Influence on Chronic Symptoms</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Inner Group Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Inner Group Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Study will look at a limited number of participants with various chronic symptoms.
      Investigating a new and novel form of hypnosis application called &quot;Direct Autonomic
      Experience (DAX)&quot; which is using combination of visualization, metaphor, post-hypnotic
      suggestion and anchoring.

      Purpose is to confirm that DAX generally appears to impact SUDS value and subjects report
      observed level of effect on short and longer term measurements.

      Most significantly, testing that DAX technique/action is reusable later if the measured SUDS
      value returns or increases.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Hypnosis and Direct Autonomic Experience Influence on Chronic Symptoms One common
      characteristic of many chronic conditions is the neurology/ biology/ symptomology may change
      slightly or signficantly over time. So an initial process/plan that worked well for affecting
      a SUDS discomfort level, may no longer work or work as well.

      DAX is designed to be adaptive such that as matters that affected the initial SUDS conditions
      may have changed, shifted, grown or otherwise be different.

      (Examples are increased lesions with MS). Where initial patterns were created with a certain
      set of neural condition and pathways. But now days/weeks later, with new pathways created,
      can a previously installed DAX pattern adjust and shift to accommodate the new neural
      patterns based on participants willingness and self-instruction, or does it require
      professional adjustment.

      Example participant given strong post-hypnotic suggestions/anchor/etc to squeeze right hand
      in certain way to bring relief to leg discomfort. Initial testing shows working. Now time has
      shifted, maybe new pathways or other chronic conditions have changed. Can the DAX processes
      the participant has been taught handle these changes or does it require a professional to
      re-apply/boost or incorporate new details to get significant changes to reported SUDS
      discomfort values.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">March 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational [Patient Registry]</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Other</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Other</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <target_duration>6 Months</target_duration>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>SUDS</measure>
    <time_frame>7 days</time_frame>
    <description>Subject Unit of Discomfort Symptom. Each patient will have different types and levels of discomfort. Could be back, legs, whatever. Once identified and a numerical value applied to level of discomfort on scale of 1 to 10. We will track that particular SUDS metric through the study, looking for various factors that enable the measured value to drop to lowest value and to re-correct back to lower value if conditions cause it to rise again.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>DAX Control of SUDS Change</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day</time_frame>
    <description>Direct Autonomic Experience (DAX) is patients ability to use pre-learned applied conscious and subconscious controls to their specified Subject Unit of Discomfort Symptom (SUDS) Discomfort related to their chronic condition. (self-adjustment). Comparing what patient can do on own, compared to when professional doing same to impact the identified SUDS discomfort item.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Professional Control of SUDS change</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day</time_frame>
    <description>Participants ability to use pre-learned applied conscious and subconscious controls to their specified Subject Unit of Discomfort Symptom (SUDS) Discomfort related to their chronic condition with professional assistance (professional-adjustment)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Restless Legs Syndrome</condition>
  <condition>Multiple Sclerosis</condition>
  <condition>Trauma, Psychological</condition>
  <condition>Chronic Disease</condition>
  <condition>Trauma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Primary</arm_group_label>
    <description>Primary</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Self-Hypnosis</intervention_name>
    <description>Self-Hypnosis</description>
    <arm_group_label>Primary</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Direct Autonomic Experience Control</intervention_name>
    <description>Direct Autonomic Experience Control. Use of learned mental tool/process to affect outcome measure of SUDS discomfort experience. (eg. Squeeze hand as pre-learned mental anchor to relieve discomfort in lower legs)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Primary</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>DAX Control</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Open to anyone over age or 12 (with proper adult/guardian supervision/authorization) with a
        proper medical chronic condition with one discomfort item (may have many, but only picking
        one) to be measured and evaluated over term of this study
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Participant must have a proper medical diagnosis of chronic condition.

          -  Existing medical treatments are having little to no effect on a discomfort metric to
             measure

          -  SUDS to be evaluated could be physical or emotional in nature (e.g. Anxiety level, or
             Leg Cramping/moving)

          -  Must be motivated and willing to participate in a study that uses hypnosis, placebo
             and/or nocebo type mental matters.

          -  Participant must continue existing medical treatments (as recommended/adjusted by such
             outside professionals) and continue to see and be monitored by new/existing medical
             professionals during the term of study.

          -  Must have technology of computers/internet/support to be able to attend regular video
             chat/conferences for needed interactions with study.

          -  Must have schedule availability and flexibility to meet in video chats/conferences as
             required.

          -  Must have the computer skills/resources and aptitude to handle video chat/conference
             and able to have resources/friends/knowledge that can help if technical issues arise
             to allow conference to occur (can handle restarting a video conference if crashes or
             network acts up)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Acute and short term discomfort matters not being measured that outside scope of
             chronic condition.

          -  Must not be active in any other studies or such studies deemed to not interact with
             this.

          -  Does not have a properly diagnosed chronic condition (exception are control subjects)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>12 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Martin Vendemia, BCH, MNLP</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Inner Group Inc.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Martin Vendemia, BCH, MNLP</last_name>
    <phone>410-709-7449</phone>
    <email>Martin@innergroupinc.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 7, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 7, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 10, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 7, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 7, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 10, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>hypnosis</keyword>
  <keyword>trauma</keyword>
  <keyword>chronic disease</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Multiple Sclerosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Restless Legs Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Chronic Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Psychological Trauma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Wounds and Injuries</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

