<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04304079</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CRE 2019.607-T</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04304079</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Novel Augmented Reality System (ARssist) for the Assistant Surgeon in Robotic Assisted Surgery</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Novel Augmented Reality System (ARssist) for the Assistant Surgeon in Robotic Assisted Surgery: A Pilot Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Chinese University of Hong Kong</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Chinese University of Hong Kong</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Robotic prostatectomy is a surgery for treating localized prostate cancer. The ARssist system
      is a novel augmented reality system designed for the assistant surgeon, allowing delivery of
      augmented reality information via Microsoft HoloLens 2 (a head mount display developed by
      Microsoft) to better delineate the 3-D operative environment and enable better visualization.
      To date, there is no prospective study on the clinical performance and utilization of the
      ARssist system. This study is to evaluate the clinical feasibility and safety of the ARssist
      system during robotic surgery with the da Vinci Xi system.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The da Vinci robotic surgery system offers advantages such as immersive three-dimensional
      visualization, intuitive control, and high degree of movement freedom to the chief surgeon.
      However, major surgery remains a team-based effort. Apart from the chief surgeon who remotely
      controls the da Vinci system at the console, the success of robotic assisted surgical
      procedures also relies on the assistant surgeon positioned at the patient side, who provides
      assistance laparoscopically. Throughout a robotic assisted operation, the patient side
      surgeon is responsible for tasks such as the exchange of instruments, retraction of tissue to
      enhance operative fields, manipulation of instruments, etc. Literature has demonstrated that
      the performance of the assistant surgeon has an effect on the outcomes of robotic surgery
      such as operative time.

      Traditionally the patient side surgeon relies on the monitor mounted on the vision cart to
      guide his/her movement. The monitor provides real-time relay of the image captured from the
      endoscope, but does not provide the full three-dimensional stereo endoscopy view unless set
      up with specialized stereo-vision equipment. The position of the monitor is also often
      awkward, creating problems such as obstructed views and non-ergonomic positioning of the
      patient side surgeon to overcome the view obstruction. The complex three-dimensional set-up
      of endoscope, robotic instruments, and hand-held instruments inside the patient body could
      prove difficult to imagine from the patient side surgeon's perspective, and guesswork could
      be involved during transfer of instruments/objects towards the operative field as the
      hand-held instruments are often out of the visualized field of the endoscope.

      Augmented reality (AR) technology delivered via optical see-through head-mounted display
      (OST-HMD) could potentially be the solution to the aforementioned issues. OST-HMD, such as
      Microsoft HoloLens, can superimpose computer graphics on top of real-world view through
      optical combiners. The clinical application of such a technology has been gaining interest in
      the surgical community, with preliminary study demonstrating feasibility of AR technology in
      ureteroscopic procedures.

      The ARssist system is a novel AR system designed for the patient side surgeon in robotic
      assisted surgeries. It integrates the da Vinci surgical system and Microsoft HoloLens, and
      provides valuable AR information to the patient side surgeon including (i) three-dimensional
      real-time rendering of the endoscope, robotic instruments, and hand-held instruments within
      the patient body, and (ii) real-time stereo endoscopy that is configurable for the assistant
      surgeon's preferred hand-eye coordination. The ARssist system would in theory grant the
      patient side surgeon improved orientation and navigation of hand-held laparoscopic
      instruments, thus improving their laparoscopic performance and the performance of the surgery
      as a whole.

      Based on the Innovation, Development, Exploration, Assessment, Long-term Study (IDEAL)
      Collaboration group methodology of promoting surgical innovation and research through planned
      prospective studies within an established staged process, we propose a stage 1 (Innovation)
      study to evaluate the feasibility and safety of the ARssist system.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">March 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>This is a prospective case series to be conducted as a pilot study to evaluate the clinical feasibility and safety of the ARssist system during robotic surgery with the da Vinci Xi system.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>30-day complications</measure>
    <time_frame>Thirty days after the allocated treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Complications which occur within 30 days after the operation</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Performance parameters</measure>
    <time_frame>Immediately post-operative</time_frame>
    <description>Performance of the patient side surgeon will be assessed using Global Operative Assessment of Laparoscopic Skills (GOALS) by different evaluators, including the patient side surgeon him/herself (self-evaluation), the console surgeon, and a third-party evaluator</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Performance parameters</measure>
    <time_frame>Immediately post-operative</time_frame>
    <description>The surgeries will be recorded audio-visually, with the captured video clips later reviewed by an independent assessor to determine objective performance outcomes of included tasks via motion analysis parameters</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>User-generated usability feedbacks</measure>
    <time_frame>Immediately post-operative</time_frame>
    <description>Specific feedback on the use of ARssist system will be collected from the patient side surgeon at the pre-operative and post-operative time points using a customized questionnaire of 10 items on a 5-point Likert scale</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Operating time</measure>
    <time_frame>Immediately post-operative</time_frame>
    <description>Duration of operation</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Blood loss</measure>
    <time_frame>Immediately post-operative</time_frame>
    <description>Volume of blood loss during operation</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Length of hospital stay</measure>
    <time_frame>Three days after the allocated treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Patients undergoing robotic radical prostatectomy have an average hospital stay of three days</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">10</enrollment>
  <condition>Prostate Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>ARssist system</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The surgery will follow the same steps of a standard robotic assisted radical prostatectomy procedure, with the addition of the ARssist system used by the patient side surgeon.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ARssist system</intervention_name>
    <description>As stated in ARssist system arm description</description>
    <arm_group_label>ARssist system</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age ≥ 18 years old with informed consent

          -  Suitable for minimally invasive surgery

          -  Clinically diagnosed with urological conditions that are indicated for robotic
             assisted radical prostatectomy with or without lymph node dissection

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Body mass index ≥ 35 kg/m2

          -  Contraindication to general anaesthesia

          -  Severe concomitant illness that drastically shortens life expectancy or increases risk
             of therapeutic intervention

          -  Untreated active infection

          -  Uncorrectable coagulopathy

          -  Presence of another malignancy or distant metastasis

          -  Emergency surgery
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jeremy Yuen Chun TEOH, MBBS, FRCSEd</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Chinese University of Hong Kong</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Jeremy Yuen Chun TEOH, MBBS, FRCSEd</last_name>
    <phone>+852 35052625</phone>
    <email>jeremyteoh@surgery.cuhk.edu.hk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Prince of Wales Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hong Kong</city>
        <country>Hong Kong</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jeremy Yuen Chun TEOH, MBBS, FRCSEd</last_name>
      <phone>35052625</phone>
      <email>jeremyteoh@surgery.cuhk.edu.hk</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Chi Ho LEUNG</last_name>
      <phone>35051663</phone>
      <email>stevenleung@surgery.cuhk.edu.hk</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Qinyang LIU</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Chi Hang YEE</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Peter Ka Fung CHIU</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Samson Yun Sang CHAN</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Chi Fai NG</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Hong Kong</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nayyar R, Yadav S, Singh P, Dogra PN. Impact of assistant surgeon on outcomes in robotic surgery. Indian J Urol. 2016 Jul-Sep;32(3):204-9. doi: 10.4103/0970-1591.185095.</citation>
    <PMID>27555678</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sgarbura O, Vasilescu C. The decisive role of the patient-side surgeon in robotic surgery. Surg Endosc. 2010 Dec;24(12):3149-55. doi: 10.1007/s00464-010-1108-9. Epub 2010 May 22.</citation>
    <PMID>20495980</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Al Janabi HF, Aydin A, Palaneer S, Macchione N, Al-Jabir A, Khan MS, Dasgupta P, Ahmed K. Effectiveness of the HoloLens mixed-reality headset in minimally invasive surgery: a simulation-based feasibility study. Surg Endosc. 2020 Mar;34(3):1143-1149. doi: 10.1007/s00464-019-06862-3. Epub 2019 Jun 18.</citation>
    <PMID>31214807</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Qian L, Deguet A, Kazanzides P. ARssist: augmented reality on a head-mounted display for the first assistant in robotic surgery. Healthc Technol Lett. 2018 Sep 17;5(5):194-200. doi: 10.1049/htl.2018.5065. eCollection 2018 Oct.</citation>
    <PMID>30800322</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>McCulloch P, Altman DG, Campbell WB, Flum DR, Glasziou P, Marshall JC, Nicholl J; Balliol Collaboration, Aronson JK, Barkun JS, Blazeby JM, Boutron IC, Campbell WB, Clavien PA, Cook JA, Ergina PL, Feldman LS, Flum DR, Maddern GJ, Nicholl J, Reeves BC, Seiler CM, Strasberg SM, Meakins JL, Ashby D, Black N, Bunker J, Burton M, Campbell M, Chalkidou K, Chalmers I, de Leval M, Deeks J, Ergina PL, Grant A, Gray M, Greenhalgh R, Jenicek M, Kehoe S, Lilford R, Littlejohns P, Loke Y, Madhock R, McPherson K, Meakins J, Rothwell P, Summerskill B, Taggart D, Tekkis P, Thompson M, Treasure T, Trohler U, Vandenbroucke J. No surgical innovation without evaluation: the IDEAL recommendations. Lancet. 2009 Sep 26;374(9695):1105-12. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(09)61116-8.</citation>
    <PMID>19782876</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Barkun JS, Aronson JK, Feldman LS, Maddern GJ, Strasberg SM; Balliol Collaboration, Altman DG, Barkun JS, Blazeby JM, Boutron IC, Campbell WB, Clavien PA, Cook JA, Ergina PL, Flum DR, Glasziou P, Marshall JC, McCulloch P, Nicholl J, Reeves BC, Seiler CM, Meakins JL, Ashby D, Black N, Bunker J, Burton M, Campbell M, Chalkidou K, Chalmers I, de Leval M, Deeks J, Grant A, Gray M, Greenhalgh R, Jenicek M, Kehoe S, Lilford R, Littlejohns P, Loke Y, Madhock R, McPherson K, Rothwell P, Summerskill B, Taggart D, Tekkis P, Thompson M, Treasure T, Trohler U, Vandenbroucke J. Evaluation and stages of surgical innovations. Lancet. 2009 Sep 26;374(9695):1089-96. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(09)61083-7.</citation>
    <PMID>19782874</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ahmed K, Miskovic D, Darzi A, Athanasiou T, Hanna GB. Observational tools for assessment of procedural skills: a systematic review. Am J Surg. 2011 Oct;202(4):469-480.e6. doi: 10.1016/j.amjsurg.2010.10.020. Epub 2011 Jul 28. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21798511</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Vassiliou MC, Feldman LS, Andrew CG, Bergman S, Leffondré K, Stanbridge D, Fried GM. A global assessment tool for evaluation of intraoperative laparoscopic skills. Am J Surg. 2005 Jul;190(1):107-13.</citation>
    <PMID>15972181</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wolf R, Medici M, Fiard G, Long JA, Moreau-Gaudry A, Cinquin P, Voros S. Comparison of the goals and MISTELS scores for the evaluation of surgeons on training benches. Int J Comput Assist Radiol Surg. 2018 Jan;13(1):95-103. doi: 10.1007/s11548-017-1645-y. Epub 2017 Aug 20.</citation>
    <PMID>28825199</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Faulkner H, Regehr G, Martin J, Reznick R. Validation of an objective structured assessment of technical skill for surgical residents. Acad Med. 1996 Dec;71(12):1363-5.</citation>
    <PMID>9114900</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mason JD, Ansell J, Warren N, Torkington J. Is motion analysis a valid tool for assessing laparoscopic skill? Surg Endosc. 2013 May;27(5):1468-77. doi: 10.1007/s00464-012-2631-7. Epub 2012 Dec 12. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23233011</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dindo D, Demartines N, Clavien PA. Classification of surgical complications: a new proposal with evaluation in a cohort of 6336 patients and results of a survey. Ann Surg. 2004 Aug;240(2):205-13.</citation>
    <PMID>15273542</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 9, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 9, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 11, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 9, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 9, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 11, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Chinese University of Hong Kong</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Jeremy Yuen Chun TEOH</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Prostate cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Augmented reality</keyword>
  <keyword>ARssist system</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Prostatic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

