<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04302701</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Dichoptic-123</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04302701</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Dichoptic Treatment vs. Patching for Moderate Anisometropic Amblyopia</brief_title>
  <official_title>Patching Versus Dichoptic Stimulation Using Virtual Reality in Anisometropic Amblyopia</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Cairo University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Cairo University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Recently, there has been an increased interest in evaluating binocular therapies (e.g
      perceptual learning and dichoptic treatment) for amblyopia. They are designed to improve
      amblyopia through binocular stimulation by unlocking binocular visual function. The objective
      of the study is to compare the visual and sensory outcome of 2-hour patching to dichoptic
      stimulation using virtual reality head mounted display in the management of patients with
      moderate anisometropic amblyopia. The investigators will include children older than 6 years
      and adults up to the age of thirty five years with anisometropic amblyopia who either had no
      prior treatment for amblyopia or had prior treatment for amblyopia using patching therapy but
      with residual amblyopia defined as &gt;= 0.3 logMAR lines between the best-corrected visual
      acuity in the sound eye and in the amblyopic eye and with moderate amblyopia in the more
      anisometropic eye defined as best-corrected visual acuity better than 6/60 but =&lt; 6/18.
      Patients will be randomized into 2 groups according to age using stratified randomization:

        -  Group P: (Patching Group): This group will have 2 hours of patching each day for 10
           weeks.

        -  Group D (Dichoptic Group): This group will have 1 hour of dichoptic stimulation using
           the virtual reality system twice a week for 10 weeks for a total of 20 hours of
           training.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The investigators are planning to conduct a study to compare the visual and sensory outcome
      of 2-hour patching to dichoptic stimulation using virtual reality head mounted display in the
      management of patients with moderate anisometropic amblyopia. This is a randomized clinical
      trial. The investigators will include children older than 6 years and adults up to the age of
      thirty five years with anisometropic amblyopia who either had no prior treatment for
      amblyopia or had prior treatment for amblyopia using patching therapy but with residual
      amblyopia defined as &gt;= 0.3 logMAR lines between the best-corrected visual acuity in the
      sound eye and in the amblyopic eye and with moderate amblyopia in the more anisometropic eye
      defined as best-corrected visual acuity better than 6/60 but =&lt; 6/18.n Recruitment will occur
      from the Ophthalmology Outpatient Clinics in Kasr El-Ainy Hospital.

      Eligible patients who agree to participate in the study will undergo a 1-hour trial session
      of dichoptic stimulation using the same head-mounted virtual reality system that will be used
      in the study to ensure that the patient can use the system. Only patients who are able to
      understand and to complete the 1-hour session will be enrolled in the study.

      Patients will be randomized into 2 groups according to age using stratified randomization:

        -  Group P: (Patching Group): This group will have 2 hours of patching each day for 10
           weeks.

        -  Group D (Dichoptic Group): This group will have 1 hour of dichoptic stimulation using
           the virtual reality system twice a week for 10 weeks for a total of 20 hours of
           training.

      Patients will be further subdivided into 2 subgroups according to whether prior patching
      therapy has been done and failed, or the patient has never received any form of patching
      therapy. The difference in the outcomes in both subgroups will be analyzed separately.

      All patients will have a baseline ophthalmological examination including visual acuity
      testing, manifest and cycloplegic refraction, slit lamp examination with funduscopy, cover
      test and worth four dot test. Best corrected visual acuity (BCVA) will be measured using a
      single crowded letter in an ETDRS chart mounted on a computer display projector. The
      stereoacuity will be measured using the TNO test. The motor alignment will be evaluated using
      prism and alternating cover test at 6 meters and at 33 cm. BCVA and stereoacuity will be
      measured before and after 10 weeks of treatment. Then, they will be re-measured 10 weeks
      after the cessation of both treatments to assess their long-term effects. All measurements
      will be taken by an investigator who will be masked to the study design.

      Dichoptic treatment group: Dichoptic visual training will be performed with the patient
      wearing his spectacles using the computer game included in Vivid Vision (Vivid Vision, San
      Francisco, USA) which will be run in the Oculus Rift OC CV1 virtual reality head mounted
      display (Oculus VR, Menlo Park, California, USA). Each subject will have 20 treatment
      sessions, divided into 1 hour-sessions performed twice a week for 10 weeks. Each session will
      be 60 minutes. Adherence to the treatment regimen will be assessed by the number of hours
      spent in training at the end of 5th week.

      Patching group: Patients in the control group will be instructed to continue wearing
      spectacles if required. Patients will be prescribed two continuous hours of daily patching
      with at least one hour of near activities during patching. Adhesive skin patches will be
      provided by the study. The parent/patient will be instructed to spend at least one of the
      hours of patching time each day performing eye-hand coordination activities at near.
      Adherence to the treatment protocol will be assessed by having the parent call / send a
      message to an investigator at the start and end of the occlusion sessions completed each day,
      thus making the most as accurate as possible assessment of the patient's adherence to the
      prescribed treatment. Written consent will be obtained by either the principal investigator
      or other investigators in the study. Adverse events will include any sense of dizziness,
      vertigo, or diplopia at any time and will be tabulated and reported at the end of each week.
      The data will be collected with privacy and confidentiality as patients will be allocated ID
      numbers and data will be analyzed accordingly.

      A sample size of 38 participants in each group will be selected to have 90% power with a
      2-sided type I error of 5% to detect a treatment group difference at 10 weeks if the true
      difference in the mean gain of new letters was 3.75, assuming a standard deviation (SD) of
      change of 5 letters, based on a prior PEDIG study. Assuming a 10% drop-out rate, a total of
      42 patients in each group will need to be recruited.

      Comparison between both groups will be done using independent t-test for continuous variables
      and Fisher Exact test for categorical variables. Analyses for secondary outcomes of visual
      acuity and stereoacuity will be adjusted for multiple testing using the Bonferroni method
      such that the overall type I error rate will be 5% within the 2sets of secondary outcomes.
      Exploratory analyses will be conducted for secondary outcomes and adherence measures for
      participants assigned to control treatment who later received 10 weeks of binocular
      treatment. Log file data at 5 weeks and 10 weeks will be used to quantify measures of
      adherence (treatment duration and change in contrast presented to the fellow eye) and to
      examine the relationship between these adherence measures and treatment response. For each
      participant, the total hours of completed and prescribed game play will be calculated, and
      the percentage of prescribed treatment completed (adherence) will be computed using the ratio
      of the completed and prescribed hours of game play for that interval. Analyses will be
      conducted using SAS version 9.4 (SAS Inc, Cary, NC).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">June 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 30, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Visual acuity at 10 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>10 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Change in amblyopic eye VA letter score from baseline to 10 weeks.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Compliance to treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>10 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Average number of hours of completed treatment in both groups defined as number of hours of completed dichoptic treatment in the dichootic group and number of hours of patching as self reported by patients in the patching group</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of patients developing misalignment</measure>
    <time_frame>10 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Number of patients developing misalignment after 10 weeks of therapy will be assessed</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Regression of amblyopic eye visual acuity</measure>
    <time_frame>20 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Amblyopic eye visual acuity letter score 10 weeks after cessation of treatments</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in visual acuity in the sound eye</measure>
    <time_frame>10 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Change in sound eye VA letter score from baseline to 10 weeks.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in near stereopsis</measure>
    <time_frame>10 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Stereopsis using TNO test will be assessed</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">84</enrollment>
  <condition>Amblyopia</condition>
  <condition>Anisometropia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Dichoptic arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Dichoptic visual training will be performed with the patient wearing his spectacles using the computer game included in Vivid Vision (Vivid Vision, San Francisco, USA) which will be run in the Oculus Rift OC CV1 virtual reality head mounted display (Oculus VR, Menlo Park, California, USA). Each subject will have 20 treatment sessions, divided into 1 hour-sessions performed twice a week for 10 weeks. Each session will be 60 minutes. Adherence to the treatment regimen will be assessed by the number of hours spent in training at the end of 5th week.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Patching</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients in the control group will be instructed to continue wearing spectacles if required. Patients will be prescribed two continuous hours of daily patching with at least one hour of near activities during patching. Adhesive skin patches will be provided by the study. The parent/patient will be instructed to spend at least one of the hours of patching time each day performing eye-hand coordination activities at near. Adherence to the treatment protocol will be assessed by having the parent call / send a message to an investigator at the start and end of the occlusion sessions completed each day, thus making the most as accurate as possible assessment of the patient's adherence to the prescribed treatment</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Dichoptic treatment using virtual reality</intervention_name>
    <description>Dichoptic visual training will be performed with the patient wearing his spectacles using the computer game included in Vivid Vision (Vivid Vision, San Francisco, USA) which will be run in the Oculus Rift OC CV1 virtual reality head mounted display (Oculus VR, Menlo Park, California, USA). Each subject will have 20 treatment sessions, divided into 1 hour-sessions performed twice a week for 10 weeks. Each session will be 60 minutes. Adherence to the treatment regimen will be assessed by the number of hours spent in training at the end of 5th week.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Dichoptic arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Patching</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients in the control group will be instructed to continue wearing spectacles if required. Patients will be prescribed two continuous hours of daily patching with at least one hour of near activities during patching. Adhesive skin patches will be provided by the study. The parent/patient will be instructed to spend at least one of the hours of patching time each day performing eye-hand coordination activities at near.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Patching</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with anisometropic amblyopia who had proper optical correction using
             spectacles or contact lenses for the past 6 weeks. Anisometropic amblyopia will be
             defined as difference &gt; 0.3 logMAR lines in best-corrected visual acuity with
             difference in the spherical equivalent of both eyes &gt; 1 D, in the absence of other
             causes for amblyopia such as organic causes, or manifest strabismus &lt; 5 PD by
             simultaneous prism and cover test. Patients will be included in the study only if they
             had no treatment for amblyopia for the past month other than spectacles and/or contact
             lenses.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with development delay

          -  Prior ocular surgery

          -  Co-existing ocular disease

          -  Patients with allergy to patch material

          -  History of problems with prior use of virtual reality systems
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>6 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>35 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <link>
    <url>https://www.seevividly.com/</url>
    <description>The link to the software of the VR games used in this study</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Holmes JM, Kraker RT, Beck RW, Birch EE, Cotter SA, Everett DF, Hertle RW, Quinn GE, Repka MX, Scheiman MM, Wallace DK; Pediatric Eye Disease Investigator Group. A randomized trial of prescribed patching regimens for treatment of severe amblyopia in children. Ophthalmology. 2003 Nov;110(11):2075-87.</citation>
    <PMID>14597512</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hess RF, Thompson B, Baker DH. Binocular vision in amblyopia: structure, suppression and plasticity. Ophthalmic Physiol Opt. 2014 Mar;34(2):146-62. doi: 10.1111/opo.12123. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24588532</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Polat U, Ma-Naim T, Spierer A. Treatment of children with amblyopia by perceptual learning. Vision Res. 2009 Oct;49(21):2599-603. doi: 10.1016/j.visres.2009.07.008. Epub 2009 Jul 19.</citation>
    <PMID>19622368</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Manh VM, Holmes JM, Lazar EL, Kraker RT, Wallace DK, Kulp MT, Galvin JA, Shah BK, Davis PL; Pediatric Eye Disease Investigator Group. A Randomized Trial of a Binocular iPad Game Versus Part-Time Patching in Children Aged 13 to 16 Years With Amblyopia. Am J Ophthalmol. 2018 Feb;186:104-115. doi: 10.1016/j.ajo.2017.11.017. Epub 2017 Nov 28.</citation>
    <PMID>29196184</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Li SL, Reynaud A, Hess RF, Wang YZ, Jost RM, Morale SE, De La Cruz A, Dao L, Stager D Jr, Birch EE. Dichoptic movie viewing treats childhood amblyopia. J AAPOS. 2015 Oct;19(5):401-5. doi: 10.1016/j.jaapos.2015.08.003.</citation>
    <PMID>26486019</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Žiak P, Holm A, Halička J, Mojžiš P, Piñero DP. Amblyopia treatment of adults with dichoptic training using the virtual reality oculus rift head mounted display: preliminary results. BMC Ophthalmol. 2017 Jun 28;17(1):105. doi: 10.1186/s12886-017-0501-8.</citation>
    <PMID>28659140</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 2, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 6, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 10, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 6, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 6, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 10, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Cairo University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Ahmed Awadein</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor of Ophthalmology</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Amblyopia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Anisometropia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>All collected IPD data will be shared</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Statistical Analysis Plan (SAP)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Informed Consent Form (ICF)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Clinical Study Report (CSR)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Analytic Code</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>after 3 years</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>The principal investigator will review requests for information.</ipd_access_criteria>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

