<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04307927</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>LA-PMCF-02</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04307927</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Lifetech LAmbre™ Left Atrial Appendage Closure System Post-Market Registry</brief_title>
  <official_title>Lifetech LAmbre™ Left Atrial Appendage Closure System Post-Market Registry Single-center, Single-arm, Prospective, Post-market Registry</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Lifetech Scientific (Shenzhen) Co., Ltd.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Lifetech Scientific (Shenzhen) Co., Ltd.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Single-center, single-arm, prospective, post-market study of LAmbre™ LAA Closure System. To
      evaluate immediate and long term procedural success of Lifetech LAmbre™ occluders in
      patients.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Detailed Description:

      Atrial fibrillation (AF) is the most common cardiac arrhythmia causing ischemic stroke. The
      CHA2DS2-VASc score was developed to estimate the stroke rate in patients with non-valvular
      AF, and high scores predict a raised annual stroke risk. The yearly stroke risks without
      treatment in patients with CHA2DS2-VASc score 2 and 9 are 2.2% and 15.2% respectively. For
      patients with increased stroke risk (CHA2DS2-VASc score ≧2), warfarin or other novel oral
      anticoagulants (NOAC) recommended for stroke prevention. Despite the effectiveness of current
      pharmacological therapies for stroke prevention in atrial fibrillation, around 20% of
      patients discontinue therapy - whether new oral anticoagulants (NOAC) or warfarin because of
      side effects and/or bleeding. In addition, warfarin needs to be dosed individually to target
      an international normalized ratio (INR) of 2-3 for striking an optimal balance between
      bleeding and ischemic stroke events. This, combined with drug-drug interaction that occurs
      with both NOACs and warfarin, results in inadequate stroke protection in a substantial
      portion of AF patients. The LAA is the source of 90% of cardiac emboli attributed to stroke
      events. This is a windsock-like structure on the lateral border of the left atrium with
      internal trabeculations, and being a confined space, is prone to blood stasis and thrombus
      formation. Currently, there are surgical, epicardial and percutaneous techniques for
      occluding this structure in order to reduce stroke in AF patients cannot take long term oral
      anticoagulants, and the percutaneous route is intuitively the most attractive given its
      relative non-invasiveness. The two devices in most widespread use for percutaneous LAA
      closure worldwide are the Watchman (Boston Scientific, Natick, MA, USA) and the Amplatzer
      Cardiac Plug (ACP) (Abbott, IL, CA USA). However, both devices have limitations including the
      need for relatively large delivery sheaths (9-14 French) and limited recapture and
      repositioning capabilities.

      LAmbreTM LAA Closure System (Lifetech Scientific, Shenzhen, China) is a novel self-expanding
      LAA occluder constructed from a nitinol mesh and polyester membranes and consists of an
      umbrella and a cover connected by a short central waist. The device is delivered by an 8-10
      French sheath and has full recapture and repositioning capabilities. LAmbreTM LAA Closure
      System received the CE mark in June 2016.

      This PMCF study will be carried out following the CE mark of LAmbreTM LAA Closure System and
      is intended to confirm the effectiveness and safety of LAmbreTM LAA Closure System.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">July 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 31, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>1.Absence of peri-procedural stroke/TIA, device embolization, cardiac or vascular perforation, any other device or procedure related serious adverse event or death (procedure or device related or of unknown cause);</measure>
    <time_frame>7 days</time_frame>
    <description>Peri-procedure defined as within 7 days of the procedure.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Implant success</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day</time_frame>
    <description>Implant success defined as correct positioning and release of the occluder device into the proper anatomical location. Correct positioning is assessed as absence of major residual jet flow (&gt;5mm) into the LAA closure with the device evaluated by transesophageal echocardiogram (TEE).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of stroke or systemic embolism or death through 24 months post implantation</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Incidence of stroke or systemic embolism or death through 24 months post</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Successful sealing around the device at the LAA orifice with residual jet ≤5 mm flow measured by TEE at 1-3 months, 6 months post-implantation</measure>
    <time_frame>1-3 months, 6 months post-implantation</time_frame>
    <description>Successful sealing around the device at the LAA orifice with residual jet ≤5 mm flow measured by TEE at 1-3 months, 6 months post-implantation</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Device or procedure related Serious Adverse Events (SAEs) from attempted procedure through 24 months post implantation</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Device or procedure related Serious Adverse Events (SAEs) from attempted procedure through 24 months post implantation</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>All SAEs (death included) from attempted procedure through 24 months post implantation</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>All SAEs (death included) from attempted procedure through 24 months post implantation</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of bleeding event through 24 months post implantation.</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Incidence of bleeding event through 24 months post implantation.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Atrial Fibrillation</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients with non-valvular paroxymal, persistent or permanent atrial fibrillation with
        long-term sustainability scheduled for interventional LAA closure.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  1. Patients must be at least 18 years of age; 2. Patients with non-valvular
             paroxysmal, persistent or permanent atrial fibrillation with long-term sustainability
             scheduled for interventional LAA closure; 3. Patient characteristics consistent with
             the corresponding IFU and sizing guidelines*; 4. The patient or legally authorized
             representative has been informed of the nature of the study, agrees to its provisions
             and has provided written informed consent, approved by the appropriate Ethics
             Committee (EC); 5. The patient agrees to comply with requirements of the study
             including the 24 months follow- up.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  1. Any contra-indication mentioned in the corresponding IFU*; 2. Currently
             participating in other investigational drug- or device studies; 3. Patient who is
             pregnant, planning to become pregnant, or breast feeding; 4. Patients cannot tolerate
             transoesophageal echocardiogram (TEE).

               -  Note: In IFU, the Left Atrial Appendage Closure System is contraindicated for the
                  following: • Patients' LAA anatomy not suitable for the REF of the device.

                    -  Patients' with intracardiac thrombus.

                    -  Patients with active endocarditis or other infections causing bacteremia.

                    -  Patients where placement of the device would interfere with any intracardiac
                       or intravascular structures.

                    -  Patients with contraindications to X-Ray and/or trans-esophageal
                       echocardiographic examinations.

                    -  Patients with known hypersensitivity to nickel.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jiangtao Yu, Professor</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Katholisches Klinikum Koblenz ·Montabaur</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Yun Li</last_name>
    <phone>+86 13534247025</phone>
    <email>liyun@lifetechmed.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Katholisches Klinikum Koblenz ·Montabaur</name>
      <address>
        <city>Koblenz</city>
        <zip>56073</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jiangtao Yu, Professor</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Germany</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 12, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 12, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 13, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 2, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 2, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 4, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Left atrial appendage occluder</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Atrial Fibrillation</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

