<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04302675</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>19-1312</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>1R21AI141822-01A1</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04302675</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Adapting Motivational Interviewing for Maternal Immunizations (MI4MI)</brief_title>
  <acronym>MI4MI</acronym>
  <official_title>Adapting Motivational Interviewing for Maternal Immunizations (MI4MI)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Colorado, Denver</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Colorado, Denver</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Vaccinating pregnant women affords a unique opportunity to protect both mother and child
      against influenza and pertussis, yet uptake of maternal immunizations remain far below
      national target goals. A significant barrier to vaccine uptake is the lack of evidence to
      guide provider communication with patients who have concerns about vaccines. This novel study
      will adapt motivational interviewing to the ob-gyn setting to provide information about how
      to improve provider communication and increase vaccine uptake among pregnant women.

      The investigators propose a pragmatic practice-based study in 5 ob-gyn practices in Colorado
      to develop the MI for maternal immunizations (MI4MI) intervention and assess fidelity,
      acceptability, and feasibility among patients and providers. Aim 1 will use an iterative
      process building upon existing knowledge of patient concerns about maternal immunizations and
      our prior experience training providers in MI for childhood immunizations to develop the
      MI4MI training. During development, the study team will conduct focus groups to elicit
      provider input during. The MI4MI intervention will include a video-module, in-person
      training, provider reference sheets, and practice study champions. Aim 2 will include
      intervention implementation and assessment of intervention fidelity, acceptability, and
      feasibility. In Aim 2a, will conduct pre- and post-intervention chart reviews among
      participating practices to evaluate the impact of MI4MI on influenza and Tdap vaccine uptake
      among pregnant patients.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Pertussis and influenza are the most poorly controlled vaccine preventable diseases in the
      United States. Pregnant women have increased risk of severe disease from influenza and
      newborns have increased risk of severe disease from influenza and pertussis. The Advisory
      Committee on Immunization Practices and American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists
      recommend women receive influenza and pertussis (Tdap) vaccine during each pregnancy, yet
      only about half of pregnant women receive these vaccines. Among identified barriers to
      maternal immunization are patient concerns about vaccine safety and effectiveness and lack of
      evidence for how ob-gyn providers can best communicate vaccine recommendations. Interventions
      to address these barriers and increase uptake of maternal immunizations are urgently needed.
      Motivational interviewing (MI) is a communication technique that has proven effective for
      changing health behaviors including increasing adolescent vaccination rates. MI is both
      time-effective and acceptable to providers. The long-term goal of this project is to adapt MI
      to the ob-gyn setting to improve influenza and Tdap vaccine uptake in pregnancy. There is
      evidence to support use of MI for childhood immunizations; however it is unknown if MI is
      feasible and acceptable among ob-gyn providers and pregnant women. The investigators propose
      a pragmatic practice-based study in 5 Colorado ob-gyn practices to develop the MI for
      maternal immunizations (MI4MI) intervention and assess acceptability, adoption and
      implementation among patients and providers. Aim 1 will use an iterative process building
      upon existing knowledge of patient concerns about maternal immunizations and our prior
      experience training providers in MI for childhood immunizations to develop the MI4MI
      training. During development, the investigators will conduct focus groups for provider input
      and [organizational context. The MI4MI intervention will include a video-module, in-person
      training, provider reference sheets, and practice study champions. Aim 2 will include
      intervention implementation and assessment of MI4MI acceptability, adoption, and
      implementation. The study team will audio-record a sample of provider visits with patients
      with vaccine concerns to assess fidelity of the intervention. Audio-elicitation interviews
      will be conducted to assess acceptability of MI4MI among patients. This qualitative method
      uses a recorded interaction to guide a semi-structured interview. The investigators will
      conduct post-intervention provider focus groups to assess acceptability and adoption of the
      MI training intervention. The study team will also conduct pre- and post-intervention surveys
      among providers to assess time spent and self-efficacy in vaccine communication. Providers
      will receive Maintenance of Certification or Continuing Medical/Nursing Education credit for
      participation. In Aim 2a, investigators will conduct pre- and post-intervention chart reviews
      in study practices to evaluate the impact of MI4MI on influenza and Tdap vaccine uptake in
      pregnant patients. This study will provide data for a larger implementation study with
      rigorous assessment of the effectiveness of MI4MI in increasing maternal immunization uptake
      in the future.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 27, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Pre-post feasibility study</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Receipt of influenza vaccination</measure>
    <time_frame>12-18 months</time_frame>
    <description>Pre-post percent change of pregnant patients that receive influenza vaccination during influenza seasons from 2019/2020 influenza season versus 2020/2021 season.
Patients may have increased knowledge about immunization issues, and decreased anxiety about getting vaccinated. Patients in the study could benefit by having improved compliance with recommended vaccines. Increased use of recommended vaccines would lead to a decreased risk of contracting vaccine-preventable diseases for themselves and their newborns.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Receipt of Tdap vaccination</measure>
    <time_frame>12-18 months</time_frame>
    <description>Pre-post percent change of pregnant patients that receive Tdap vaccination.
Patients may have increased knowledge about immunization issues, and decreased anxiety about getting vaccinated. Patients in the study could benefit by having improved compliance with recommended vaccines. Increased use of recommended vaccines would lead to a decreased risk of contracting vaccine-preventable diseases for themselves and their newborns.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in provider self-efficacy</measure>
    <time_frame>12-18 months</time_frame>
    <description>The potential of increased understanding of vaccine communication, barriers to implementing Tdap and influenza and other vaccines targeted at pregnant women, and therefore improved immunization delivery strategies; based on self-report survey.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">1500</enrollment>
  <condition>Maternal Immunization</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Prevention, Maternal Immunization</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Prevention, Maternal Immunization</intervention_name>
    <description>This intervention will be focused on behavior change, both through providers gaining context, knowledge, confidence, and skills in talking to pregnant mothers about vaccination during pregnancy, but also with patients having increased knowledge about immunization issues, and decreased anxiety about getting vaccinated.
There is only one intervention arm in this study, and this study is looking at prevention in a pre-post feasibility study.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Prevention, Maternal Immunization</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients attending ob-gyn practice in Colorado that is participating in the MI4MI
             project (5 total practices)

          -  Patients attending a pre-natal clinic visit at a participating practice during the
             intervention period who are eligible for maternal immunizations

          -  Pregnant patients who are less than 18 years of age will also be eligible to
             participate in audio-recorded encounters and audio-elicitation interviews.]

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with hypersensitivity to any component of one of the recommended vaccines

          -  No subjects will be excluded because of ethnicity or insurance status.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <gender_based>Yes</gender_based>
    <gender_description>Participants must be currently pregnant, therefore anatomically female.</gender_description>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Sean O'Leary, MD, MPH</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Colorado, Denver</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Mary Fisher, MPH</last_name>
    <phone>303-724-9953</phone>
    <email>mary.fisher@cuanschutz.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Colorado at Denver and Health Sciences Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Aurora</city>
        <state>Colorado</state>
        <zip>80045</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Mary Fisher, MPH</last_name>
      <phone>303-724-9953</phone>
      <email>mary.fisher@cuanschutz.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Sean O'Leary, MD, MPH</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 25, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 6, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 10, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 11, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 11, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 16, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Maternal Immunization</keyword>
  <keyword>Immunization - Influenza</keyword>
  <keyword>Immunization - Tdap</keyword>
  <keyword>Tetanus</keyword>
  <keyword>Diphtheria</keyword>
  <keyword>Pertussis</keyword>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Vaccines</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>No - We do not plan to make individual participant data (IPD) available to other researchers.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

