<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04308109</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>979984</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04308109</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Simulation Training in the Pediatric Tracheostomy and Home Ventilator Population</brief_title>
  <official_title>Simulation Training in the Pediatric Tracheostomy and Home Ventilator Population</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Medical College of Wisconsin</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Children's Hospital and Health System Foundation, Wisconsin</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Medical College of Wisconsin</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The investigators will develop, refine and pilot a highly-realistic simulation program that
      will allow caregivers opportunities to manage critical situations as it pertains to a
      medically complex child dependent on tracheostomy with or without home ventilation. The
      investigators hope to demonstrate that the use of highly realistic simulation training will
      improve hospital utilization as caregivers will have a more realistic understanding of
      clinical and equipment-related emergencies that may occur outpatient.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The investigators propose a prospective randomized control trial evaluating the use of
      simulation to prepare caregivers for the discharge of children dependent on respiratory
      technology. All caregivers of children who are (1) inpatient with a newly placed tracheostomy
      tube and (2) anticipated to start discharge teaching after the first date of Institutional
      Review Board (IRB) approval will be enrolled, regardless of home ventilator need. Caregivers
      with prior experience caring for tracheostomies within the last 10 years will be excluded.
      Estimated sample size is 60 caregivers (trainees) (2 trained caregivers anticipated per
      child). Trainees must be able to speak and read English.

      All trainees will be randomized by child (up to 4 per child) into one of three arms (Figure
      1), stratified by the need for invasive home ventilation and randomized in blocks of four.
      All trainees will complete our current state of education including bedside education
      provided by Pediatric Intensive Care Unit (PICU) or Neonatal Intensive Care Unit (NICU)
      nursing staff and a formal classroom-based skills class (either a 'tracheostomy-only' or a
      'tracheostomy/home ventilator' class) taught by a Children's Hospital of Wisconsin (CHW)
      Tracheostomy and Home Ventilator respiratory therapist or durable medical equipment company
      (DME) respiratory therapist, and an individual scenario-based review of equipment and skills
      workshop with a CHW Tracheostomy and Home Ventilator Respiratory Therapist.

      In addition to the current state of education, the active study group will also undergo
      highly realistic simulation. This involves the use of a highly realistic tracheostomy
      mannequin and audiovisual devices which will be used to replicate emergent clinical
      situations. If home invasive ventilation is anticipated, a home ventilator will be used. The
      active control will undergo low-fidelity simulation that approximates the highly realistic
      clinical scenarios except with the use of a low-fidelity doll equipped with a tracheostomy
      and without the audiovisual inputs. Both active arms will occur in the simulation center or
      sleep lab and replicate the same clinical situations by the simulation instructor. After the
      simulation, participants will be debriefed by the instructor, who will use a tape of their
      session as a teaching tool.

      Commonly encountered emergent outpatient problems to be simulated include 1) obstructed
      tracheostomy tube leading to the need for cardiopulmonary resuscitation; 2) bleeding from the
      tracheostomy tube; 3) acute desaturation and/or bradycardia; and 4) accidental decannulation.
      If invasive home ventilation is anticipated, ventilator alarm troubleshooting for high
      pressure alarms, low minute ventilation alarms, auto-cycling of the ventilator and water in
      the tubing will be included in the simulation.

      All trainees will undergo a teach-back session with a CHW Tracheostomy and Home Ventilator
      Program respiratory therapist during which essential skills and responses to clinical
      situations are assessed. If a trainee passes this session, the respiratory therapist has
      determined that they have met criteria to move onto independent care sessions and the
      trainees have acquired the trach and home ventilator knowledge to provide care in the home.
      If a trainee fails this teach-back session, the information failed will be reviewed and the
      family will repeat the teach-back session until they pass and then move into independent care
      sessions. Independent care sessions are practical demonstrations of all skills needed to take
      care of the child at home. Independent care sessions are repeated until all skills have been
      passed. Teach-back and independent care sessions are part of the current state of education.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 22, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 22, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 22, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Randomized control trial</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Health Services Research</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Teach-back session performance</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 4 weeks of hospital discharge</time_frame>
    <description>Difference in Teach-back performance between active study and control groups. Measured from 0-24, with higher scores being better.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Independent Care session performance</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 4 weeks of hospital discharge</time_frame>
    <description>Independent Care performance between active study and control groups.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Hospital length of stay</measure>
    <time_frame>First teaching session to discharge, an average of 4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Difference in hospital length of stay between active study and active control groups. Measured from 0-7, with higher scores being better.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Phone Calls</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year after initial discharge</time_frame>
    <description>Difference in number of Phone Calls (from participants to medical providers/home care company) between active and control groups.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Hospital Re-admissions/Emergency Room (ER) visits</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year after initial discharge</time_frame>
    <description>Difference in the number of Hospital Re-admissions/ER visit counts between active and control groups.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of discharge teaching scores</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 48 hours of initial hospital discharge</time_frame>
    <description>Quality of Discharge Teaching Scale measured on day of discharge; scale of 0 to 10; very high/very low scores indicate stronger opinions</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Caregiver post-discharge coping scores</measure>
    <time_frame>Scale administered 24 hours after discharge and about 1 month after discharge</time_frame>
    <description>Post Discharge Coping Difficulty Scale administered 24 hours after discharge and at first Tracheostomy/Home Ventilator clinic visit; scale of 0 to 10; very high/very low scores indicate stronger opinions</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">90</enrollment>
  <condition>Tracheostomy Complication</condition>
  <condition>Simulation of Physical Illness</condition>
  <condition>Teach-Back Communication</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>No intervention, the same as the current state of education. Caregivers will still complete the teaching and post-discharge surveys (QDTS and PDCDS) and be followed for a year after discharge.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Active study</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>In addition to the current state of education, the active study group will undergo highly realistic simulation. This involves the use of a highly realistic tracheostomy mannequin and audiovisual devices which will be used to replicate emergent clinical situations. If home invasive ventilation is anticipated, a home ventilator will be used. Caregivers will complete the teaching and post-discharge surveys (QDTS and PDCDS) and be followed for a year after discharge.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Active control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>In addition to the current state of education, the active control will undergo low-fidelity simulation that approximates the highly realistic clinical scenarios except with the use of a low-fidelity doll equipped with a tracheostomy and without the audiovisual inputs. If home invasive ventilation is anticipated, a home ventilator will be used. Caregivers still complete the teaching and post-discharge surveys (QDTS and PDCDS) and be followed for a year after discharge.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Simulation</intervention_name>
    <description>Simulation involves the use of a highly realistic tracheostomy mannequin and audiovisual devices which will be used to replicate emergent clinical situations. If home invasive ventilation is anticipated, a home ventilator will be used. The simulation will last approximately 2 hours and will end with reviewing the taped session as part of debriefing. Both active arms will occur in the simulation center or sleep lab and replicate the same clinical situations by the same simulation instructor.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Active control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Active study</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Anticipated count of 90 participants includes 30 patients and 60 caregivers (2 per
        patient). Caregivers are the primary subjects, and patients are enrolled so the
        investigators can use their medical records.

        Caregivers:

        Inclusion Criteria

          -  Must be able to read and speak English

          -  Caring for a patient with a tracheostomy being discharged from the NICU/PICU for the
             first time

        Exclusion Criteria

        - Can not have cared for a child with a tracheostomy in the last 10 years
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jennifer Henningfeld, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Medical College of Wisconsin</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Jennifer Henningfeld, MD</last_name>
    <phone>4142666730</phone>
    <email>jhenningfeld@mcw.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Thomas M Wade, BS</last_name>
    <phone>4142665435</phone>
    <email>tmwade@mcw.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Children's Hospital of Wisconsin</name>
      <address>
        <city>Wauwatosa</city>
        <state>Wisconsin</state>
        <zip>53226</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jennifer Henningfeld, MD</last_name>
      <phone>414-266-6730</phone>
      <email>jhenningfeld@mcw.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>December 16, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 11, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 13, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 11, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 11, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 13, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Medical College of Wisconsin</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Jennifer Henningfeld</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Simulation</keyword>
  <keyword>Teach-back</keyword>
  <keyword>Caregiver</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

