<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04302727</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>19-1712</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>1R61HL142680-01A1</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04302727</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Delicious Eating for Life in Southern Homes</brief_title>
  <acronym>DELISH</acronym>
  <official_title>Randomized Explanatory Trial of a Mediterranean Dietary Pattern Weight Loss Intervention for Primary Care Practices</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will compare a new weight loss program that focuses on a healthy eating pattern,
      with WW™ (formally Weight Watchers), an effective and widely available weight loss program.
      Study researchers have developed an adapted version of the Mediterranean eating pattern to be
      more acceptable and realistic for southerners; this adapted version is known as &quot;Med-South.&quot;
      Those who take part in the study will be randomly assigned to either the Med-South weight
      loss program or WW™. Both programs will last for 2 years with measurement visits at the start
      of the study and at 4-, 12- and 24-month follow-up. While the primary outcome measured by the
      trial will be weight loss at 24 months, researchers will collect other data which may show
      additional health benefits of the Med-South diet. The study team will measure blood markers
      of inflammation, which are known to improve with better diet quality. Researchers will also
      measure participants' skin carotenoid levels, which increase with greater fruit and vegetable
      consumption. The study will be conducted within 2 regional catchment areas (n=360
      participants) representing a diverse spectrum of patients and settings. Patients with a BMI ≥
      30 kg/m^2 will be enrolled and randomized to intervention or augmented usual care. To assure
      adequate subgroup representation, ≥ 40% of the sample will have diabetes, ≥ 40% will be male,
      and ≥ 40% will be African American. The intervention will be delivered in 3 phases over 24
      months by research staff: Phase I (4 months) focuses on adopting a Med-style dietary pattern;
      Phase II (8 months) on weight loss; and Phase III (12 months) on weight loss maintenance.
      Outcomes will be assessed at 4, 12, and 24 months. The primary outcome is weight loss at 24
      months. Secondary outcomes include change in physiologic, behavioral, and psychosocial
      measures. Researchers will also assess implementation cost and the incremental
      cost-effectiveness of the intervention relative to the augmented usual care group.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Below, each of the treatment arms is described in detail.

      Med-South Weight Loss Program

      Most weight loss programs offer weekly one-on-one or group counseling sessions for 16-20
      weeks. The Med-South Weight Loss Program is different and is given in 3 phases. The program
      begins with Phase I, a 4-month lifestyle phase that focuses on the &quot;basics&quot; of healthy eating
      rather than weight loss. Over the next 8 months in Phase II, we focus on weight loss,
      followed by a year-long (Phase III) phase to help maintain weight loss. In Phase I, the main
      counseling sessions happen at monthly visits, to which check-in phone calls are added. In
      Phase II, the main counseling sessions will occur weekly for 6-8 weeks, depending on
      participants' progress. There are also check in phone calls—the number will vary based on
      progress. During Phase III, there are 2 main visits and follow-up phone calls. More details
      about these visits are in the table below.

      Some of the counseling visits will be face-to-face with the counselor and some by phone. Only
      one member of a family may join this study, but other family members are invited to take part
      in face-to-face and phone counseling sessions. Of the 14 core counseling sessions), the
      face-to-face format will be required for only 4 (the 1st session of each Phase and after 2
      months of the weight loss program). Of these, the first session of each Phase will happen
      right after study measurement visits at enrollment, and 4 and 12 months. The other sessions
      may be done by phone or in person. During face-to-face sessions, the participant and the
      counselor will sit side-by-side and use a web-based program or the paper format to review
      educational materials, select dietary goals, and list first steps to reach these goals. If
      the phone format is used for major counseling sessions, the participant may view the
      educational content online or use the paper version. The program also includes brief
      telephone calls to check on progress towards goals selected at previous sessions and provide
      support for lifestyle change. The number of phone calls will depend on the participant
      meeting his/her personal weight loss goals in Phase II or keeping the weight off in Phase
      III. Detail for each Phase is given below.

      Phase I

        -  8 total contacts

             -  4 core sessions: the first must be in-person; choice of in-person or phone for all
                others

             -  4 follow-up phone calls

        -  Core session = 45-60 min.

        -  Follow-up call = 15 min.

        -  total time: 4 - 5 hours

      Phase II

        -  14 core sessions: the first and third must be in-person; choice of in-person or phone
           for all others.

        -  6-12 follow-up phone calls

        -  Core session (In-person) = 45-60 min.

        -  Core session (phone) = 30-45 min.

        -  Follow-up call = 20-30 min. Total time 8.7 - 14 hours (core) 4.7 - 9.5 hours (Follow-up)

      Phase III

        -  2 core sessions (both in-person)

        -  12-24 follow-up phone calls (1-2 per month)

        -  Core session (In-person) = 45-60 min.

        -  Follow-up call = 15-20 min. Total time 1.25 - 2 hours (Core) 3 - 8 hours (Follow-up)

           2-Year Program TOTAL 44 - 60 Contacts -- 21.7 - 38.5 hours

      WW™ Weight Loss Program

      Those randomized to WW™ will have access to both the Workshop and Digital components of the
      WW™ program for 2 years. WW offers in-person coaching and community-based learning through
      weekly Workshops at WW Studios.The Workshop component allows for attending weekly group
      meeting at a WW™ studio (local WW™ office).

      The Digital component can be accessed using the WW™ website or the smart phone App. The
      digital tools available thought the WW Digital program include food tracking (either manually
      or with bar code scanning), progress charts, lifestyle coaching with 24/7 chat with a WW
      Coach, ability to track activity (manually or by syncing a fitness tracking device),
      incentives for behavior change (WellnessWins), recipes, and even local restaurant
      recommendations using GPS. Those in the WW group will also have access to Connect, WW's
      members-only digital community.

      The WW™ program uses &quot;SmartPoints&quot; assigned to foods based on energy content and nutritional
      value, allocating a certain number of points to users daily based on their starting weight,
      weight loss goals, age and sex. Participants will receive a personalized SmartPoints budget
      made up of Daily SmartPoints, plus some extra Weekly SmartPoints for those days when a
      cushion is needed.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Enrolling by invitation</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 6, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Study participants will be randomized to either the intervention group (Med-Diet Weight Loss Program) or an enhanced usual care control group (WW); both groups will participate in the respective programs for two years.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
    <masking_description>The investigators (excluding bio-statistician) will be masked to weight change and other major outcomes (will not have access to the data) until all data are collected. The bio-statistician will have access to study group assignment as liaison to the Data Safety Monitoring Committee</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean Weight Change from Baseline to Month 24</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Month 24</time_frame>
    <description>Weight will be collected by study staff who are masked to treatment using scales tested monthly for accuracy up to 350 pounds.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean Weight Change from Baseline to Months 4 and 12</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Months 4 and 12</time_frame>
    <description>Weight will be collected by study staff who are masked to treatment using scales tested monthly for accuracy up to 350 pounds.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean Weight Change from Baseline through Follow-Up by Sub-Groups</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Months 4, 12, and 24</time_frame>
    <description>Weight will be collected by study staff who are masked to treatment using scales tested monthly for accuracy up to 350 pounds. Change in weight will be assessed across 3 pre-specified subgroups: 1) with vs. without diabetes; 2) females vs. males; and 3) whites vs. African Americans.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage Weight from Baseline through Follow-Up</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Months 4, 12, and 24</time_frame>
    <description>Weight will be collected by study staff who are masked to treatment using scales tested monthly for accuracy up to 350 pounds. Assess difference between study groups in percentage losing ≥ 5% body weight for all participants and across 3 pre-specified subgroups: 1) participants with vs. without diabetes; 2) females vs. males; and 3) Whites vs. African Americans.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean Change in Systolic Blood Pressure from Baseline through Follow-Up</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Months 4, 12, and 24</time_frame>
    <description>Blood pressure assessed by Omron-907xl, average of 3 readings.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean Change in Diastolic Blood Pressure from Baseline through Follow-Up</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Months 4, 12, and 24</time_frame>
    <description>Blood pressure assessed by Omron-907xl, average of 3 readings.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean Change in Total Cholesterol from Baseline through Follow-Up</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Month 4, 12, and 24</time_frame>
    <description>Total cholesterol assessed by commercial lab (LabCorp).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean Change in HDL-Cholesterol from Baseline through Follow-Up</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Month 4, 12, and 24</time_frame>
    <description>HDL-Cholesterol assessed by commercial lab (LabCorp).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean Change in Triglycerides from Baseline through Follow-Up</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Month 4, 12, and 24</time_frame>
    <description>Triglycerides as assessed by commercial lab (LabCorp).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean Change LDL-cholesterol from Baseline through Follow-up</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Month 4, 12, and 24</time_frame>
    <description>Calculated from above lipid assessments by commercial lab (LabCorp).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean Change in A1c from Baseline through Follow-Up</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Month 4, 12, and 24</time_frame>
    <description>A1c assessed by commercial lab (LabCorp).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean Change in CRP from Baseline through Follow-Up</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Month 4, 12, and 24</time_frame>
    <description>CRP assessed by commercial lab (LabCorp).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean Change in IL-6 from Baseline through Follow-Up</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Month 4, 12, and 24</time_frame>
    <description>Assessed by independent lab blinded to participant arm.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean Change in TNF-alpha from Baseline through Follow-Up</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Month 4, 12, and 24</time_frame>
    <description>Assessed by independent lab blinded to participant arm.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean Change in Skin Carotenoids from Baseline through Follow-Up</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Month 4, 12, and 24</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluated as the sum of 3 measures assessed by veggie-meter by Longevity Link Corporation.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean Change in Quality of Life Scale from Baseline through Follow-Up</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Month 4, 12, and 24</time_frame>
    <description>The Euro Quality of Life five Dimensions Questionnaire EQ-5D-5L scale measures patients' quality of healthy living. It has 5 items (Mobility, Self-care, Usual activities, Pain/discomfort, Depression/anxiety). Each item contains 5 levels: 1= no difficulty, 2= slight difficulty, 3= moderate difficulty, 4= serious difficulty, 5= extremely serious difficulty. The higher the score has the worse the health. Then, the score calculation of the European Five-Dimensional Health Scale is based on the calculation formula published by the EuroQol Group. Based on 5 combinations of different severity levels, a score of 0 to 1 is obtained. 0 is the least healthy and 1 is the most healthy.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean Change in Alternate Healthy Eating Index (AHEI)-2010 from Baseline through Follow-Up</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Month 4, 12, and 24</time_frame>
    <description>The AHEI-2010 is calculated from items on the Willett Food Frequency Questionnaire. It addresses intake of foods and nutrients consistently associated with lower risk for chronic diseases in the literature. The AHEI-2010 score is comprised of 11 sub-scales, each scored from 0 to 10, yielding a total score with a range of 0-110. A higher score indicates a more healthful dietary pattern.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean Change in Global Physical Activity Questionnaire (GPAQ) from Baseline through Follow-Up</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Month 4, 12, and 24</time_frame>
    <description>The GPAQ was developed by the WHO for physical activity surveillance. It collects information on physical activity participation in three settings (or domains) as well as sedentary behavior. The domains are: activity at work, travel to and from places, and recreational activities. The summary measure will be the sum of all activity per day with a higher score indication more physical activity.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean Change in Weight Loss Self-Efficacy from Baseline through Follow-Up</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Month 4, 12, and 24</time_frame>
    <description>The Weight Efficacy Lifestyle Questionnaire Short-Form (WEL-SF1) is a short version of the original Weight-Efficacy Lifestyle Questionnaire and includes 8 questions and 1 situational component representing &quot;confidence in ability to resist eating.&quot; Three of the questions are related to emotional eating situations, two to availability, one to social pressure, one to positive activities, and one to physical discomfort.
Scoring: The instrument range scores on a Likert-scale from 0 (not at all confident) to 10 (very confident), with sum scores between 0 and 80. High scores are associated with high eating self-efficacy.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean Change in Dietary Self-Regulation from Baseline through Follow-Up</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Month 4, 12, and 24</time_frame>
    <description>Treatment Self-regulation Questionnaire (TSRQ) measures the quality of motivation for a particular health goal. Motivation is psychological energy directed at a particular goal such as weight loss. This measure assesses three types of motivation: autonomous self-regulation, controlled self-regulation, and a-motivation or lack of motivation. This 15-item scale will focus on the reasons why people would either start eating a healthier diet or continue to do so.
Scoring: Participants rate each statement on a 7-point Likert scale ranging from 1 (not at all true) to 7 (very true). It assesses the degree to which a person's motivation for eating a healthy diet is autonomous or self-determined. The three sub-scale scores can be used separately or a Relative Autonomous Motivation score can be calculated. A higher score indicates greater motivation.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean Change in Eating Attitudes from Baseline through Follow-Up</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Month 4, 12, and 24</time_frame>
    <description>The Three Factor Eating Questionnaire (18 item revised version) measures eating attitudes with scales representing three dimensions of eating behavior: cognitive restraint (control over food intake in order to influence body weight / body shape), uncontrolled eating (loss of control over eating), and emotional eating (eating in response to positive and negative emotions).
Scoring: Each scale (dimension) is scored separately. Six of the eighteen items measure cognitive restraint, nine measure uncontrolled eating, and three measure emotional eating. Higher scores indicate greater cognitive restraint.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean Change in Diet Self-Efficacy from Baseline through Follow-Up</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Month 4, 12, and 24</time_frame>
    <description>Perceived self-efficacy is regarded as a suitable predictor of behavioral intentions and reported health behaviors. This 5-item scale of perceived self-efficacy measuring action self-efficacy and coping self-efficacy related to healthful eating behaviors. Responses are on a 4-point scale of 'very uncertain' to 'very certain.'
Scoring: Higher scores indicate higher perceived self-efficacy.
Validation: Evidence for the validity of the scales has been published in several articles. Cronbach's alpha for the nutrition self-efficacy measure ranges from 0.79 to 0.85.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean Change in Self-Weighing Behaviors from Baseline through Follow-Up</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Month 4, 12, and 24</time_frame>
    <description>EARLY Self-Weighing Questionnaire: This is a 2-item screener measures frequency of self-weighing and access to a bathroom scale. It was adapted from the Pound of Prevention Health Habits Questionnaire, Year 2. Validity of construct confirmed in Linde et al, 2005, as reports of higher weighing frequency was associated with greater 24-month weight loss or less weight gain.
Scoring: Higher scores indicate higher frequency of self-weighing and access to a bathroom scale.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Economic Outcome--Incremental Cost-Effectiveness</measure>
    <time_frame>Month 24</time_frame>
    <description>Computed as the incremental cost per kilogram of weight loss relative to control.
The budgetary assessment will quantify the total and per participant costs of intervention delivery from the health system perspective using an Activity Based Costing (ABC) approach and cost tracking forms that the health economist (Finkelstein) has developed and refined in past behavioral trials. Using this approach, all relevant labor, materials and supplies, contracted services, and other relevant costs required to deliver the interventions will be captured by key activities</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Economic Outcome--Incremental Cost per Quality Adjusted Life Year (QALY) gained</measure>
    <time_frame>Month 24</time_frame>
    <description>The numerator for this analysis will be the incremental program delivery costs of the intervention relative to control, minus any cost offsets based on differences in health services and medication use across arms. The denominator will be the incremental QALYs based on average differences in Euro Quality of Life five Dimensions Questionnaire (EQ-5D-5L) scores across arms collected at each assessment point. These scores can be used to quantify net QALY differences during the intervention period.
EQ-5D-5L scale measures patients' quality of healthy living. It has 5 items (Mobility, Self-care, Usual activities, Pain/discomfort, Depression/anxiety). The score calculation of the European Five-Dimensional Health Scale is based on the calculation formula published by the EuroQol Group. Based on 5 combinations of different severity levels, a score of 0 to 1 is obtained. 0 is the least healthy and 1 is the most healthy.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">360</enrollment>
  <condition>Weight Loss</condition>
  <condition>Diet, Healthy</condition>
  <condition>Cardiovascular Risk Factor</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Med-South Weight Loss Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The intervention will be delivered in 3 phases over 24 months: Phase I (4 months) provides a foundation for adopting and maintaining a healthful dietary pattern (Med-style, tailored for the southeastern United States); Phase II (8 months) focuses on weight loss; and Phase III (12 months) on maintenance of or continued weight loss, as appropriate.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Augmented Usual Care (WW)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The intervention that will be offered to control group participants is WW™ (formerly known as Weight Watchers). The study will provide access to the 'Workshop + Digital' option of WW™ during the 2 year intervention.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Med-South Weight Loss Intervention</intervention_name>
    <description>Phase I is a 4-month lifestyle program focused on the basics of healthy eating. Phase II (8 months) focuses on weight loss, followed by a year-long (Phase III) focused on weight loss maintenance. In Phase I, the main counseling sessions happen at monthly visits, with added check-in phone calls. In Phase II, the main counseling sessions will occur weekly for 6-8 weeks. There are also check-in phone calls - number based on weight loss progress. During Phase III, there are 2 main visits and follow-up phone calls. Counseling visits will be in-person with a health counselor and by phone. Of the 14 core counseling sessions, the in-person format will be required for only 4 (the 1st session of each Phase and after 2 months of the weight loss program). The program also includes brief phone calls to check on progress towards goals for lifestyle change. The number of phone calls will depend on success in meeting personal weight loss goals in Phase II or keeping the weight off in Phase III.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Med-South Weight Loss Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Delicious Eating for Life in Southern Homes (DELISH) Weight Loss Program</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>WW</intervention_name>
    <description>If participants are randomized to WW™, they will have access to both the workshop and digital components of the WW™ program for 2 years. The workshop component includes the option of attending weekly group meeting at a WW™ studio (local WW™ office). The digital component can be accessed using the WW™ website or the smart phone App. The study research staff will provide basic instructions on how to use the WW™ digital resources.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Augmented Usual Care (WW)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Weight Watchers</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Male or female

          -  English speaking

          -  Ages 18-75 (inclusive)

          -  BMI &gt; or = 30 kg/m^2

          -  Approval for participation by primary care clinician

          -  Established patient at participating practice defined as at least one prior visit at
             the practice within the prior 2 years

          -  Access to telephone

          -  No plans to move from the area for at least 1 year

          -  Free living to the extent that participant has control over dietary intake

          -  Those with known cardiovascular disease will be allowed to participant

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Participant in intensive weight loss program (more than 6 visits) in the prior year

          -  Another family member or household member is a study participant. Only one member of
             each household may take part in this study.

          -  Considering bariatric surgery in the next year or prior bariatric surgery

          -  Type 1 diabetes. Rationale is patients with type 1 diabetes already received intensive
             dietary counseling with a focus on total and distribution of daily carbohydrates.

          -  Pregnancy/breastfeeding or intended pregnancy in the next year

          -  History of malignancy, other than non-melanoma skin cancer, unless surgically or
             medically cured &gt; 5 years ago or in remission. Patients with localized prostate and
             breast cancer diagnosed during the course of routine screening will not be excluded.

          -  Advanced kidney disease (estimated creatinine clearance &lt; 30 mL/min)

          -  Known drug or alcohol misuse in the past 2 years

          -  Known psychosis or major psychiatric illness. Those with major depression who have
             responded to treatment may participate.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Carmen D Samuel-Hodge, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Thomas C Keyserling, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UNC Center for Health Promotion and Disease Prevention</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chapel Hill</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27514</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Keyserling TC, Samuel-Hodge CD, Pitts SJ, Garcia BA, Johnston LF, Gizlice Z, Miller CL, Braxton DF, Evenson KR, Smith JC, Davis GB, Quenum EL, Elliott NT, Gross MD, Donahue KE, Halladay JR, Ammerman AS. A community-based lifestyle and weight loss intervention promoting a Mediterranean-style diet pattern evaluated in the stroke belt of North Carolina: the Heart Healthy Lenoir Project. BMC Public Health. 2016 Aug 5;16:732. doi: 10.1186/s12889-016-3370-9.</citation>
    <PMID>27495295</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Keyserling TC, Samuel Hodge CD, Jilcott SB, Johnston LF, Garcia BA, Gizlice Z, Gross MD, Saviñon CE, Bangdiwala SI, Will JC, Farris RP, Trost S, Ammerman AS. Randomized trial of a clinic-based, community-supported, lifestyle intervention to improve physical activity and diet: the North Carolina enhanced WISEWOMAN project. Prev Med. 2008 Jun;46(6):499-510. doi: 10.1016/j.ypmed.2008.02.011. Epub 2008 Feb 15.</citation>
    <PMID>18394692</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Keyserling TC, Sheridan SL, Draeger LB, Finkelstein EA, Gizlice Z, Kruger E, Johnston LF, Sloane PD, Samuel-Hodge C, Evenson KR, Gross MD, Donahue KE, Pignone MP, Vu MB, Steinbacher EA, Weiner BJ, Bangdiwala SI, Ammerman AS. A comparison of live counseling with a web-based lifestyle and medication intervention to reduce coronary heart disease risk: a randomized clinical trial. JAMA Intern Med. 2014 Jul;174(7):1144-57. doi: 10.1001/jamainternmed.2014.1984.</citation>
    <PMID>24861959</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Embree GG, Samuel-Hodge CD, Johnston LF, Garcia BA, Gizlice Z, Evenson KR, DeWalt DA, Ammerman AS, Keyserling TC. Successful long-term weight loss among participants with diabetes receiving an intervention promoting an adapted Mediterranean-style dietary pattern: the Heart Healthy Lenoir Project. BMJ Open Diabetes Res Care. 2017 Mar 29;5(1):e000339. doi: 10.1136/bmjdrc-2016-000339. eCollection 2017.</citation>
    <PMID>28405344</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Samuel-Hodge CD, Holder-Cooper JC, Gizlice Z, Davis G, Steele SP, Keyserling TC, Kumanyika SK, Brantley PJ, Svetkey LP. Family PArtners in Lifestyle Support (PALS): Family-based weight loss for African American adults with type 2 diabetes. Obesity (Silver Spring). 2017 Jan;25(1):45-55. doi: 10.1002/oby.21700. Epub 2016 Dec 2.</citation>
    <PMID>27911049</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Samuel-Hodge CD, Garcia BA, Johnston LF, Gizlice Z, Ni A, Cai J, Kraschnewski JL, Gustafson AA, Norwood AF, Glasgow RE, Gold AD, Graham JW, Evenson KR, Trost S, Keyserling TC. Translation of a behavioral weight loss intervention for mid-life, low-income women in local health departments. Obesity (Silver Spring). 2013 Sep;21(9):1764-73. doi: 10.1002/oby.20317. Epub 2013 May 24.</citation>
    <PMID>23408464</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Samuel-Hodge CD, Johnston LF, Gizlice Z, Garcia BA, Lindsley SC, Bramble KP, Hardy TE, Ammerman AS, Poindexter PA, Will JC, Keyserling TC. Randomized trial of a behavioral weight loss intervention for low-income women: the Weight Wise Program. Obesity (Silver Spring). 2009 Oct;17(10):1891-9. doi: 10.1038/oby.2009.128. Epub 2009 Apr 30.</citation>
    <PMID>19407810</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 6, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 6, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 10, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 9, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 9, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 10, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Behavioral weight loss</keyword>
  <keyword>Mediterranean dietary pattern</keyword>
  <keyword>Lifestyle program</keyword>
  <keyword>Inflammatory markers</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Weight Loss</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Deidentified individual data that supports the results will be shared beginning 9 to 36 months following publication provided the investigator who proposes to use the data has approval from an Institutional Review Board (IRB), Independent Ethics Committee (IEC), or Research Ethics Board (REB), as applicable, and executes a data use/sharing agreement with UNC.</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Informed Consent Form (ICF)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>9 to 36 months following publication</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>Approval from an IRB, IEC, or REB, as applicable, and an executed data use/sharing agreement with UNC.</ipd_access_criteria>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

