<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04308733</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Restivo Domenico</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04308733</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>tDCS for Dysphagia Associated to Brainstem Stroke</brief_title>
  <official_title>Transcranial Direct Current Stimulation (tDCS) for Patients With Oro-pharyngeal Dysphagia Associated to Brainstem Stroke</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Presidio Ospedaliero Garibaldi-Centro</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Presidio Ospedaliero Garibaldi-Centro</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The aim of the study is to investigate the effect of anodal transcranial direct current
      stimulation applied over the pharyngeal motor area in 60 dysphagic patients with acute
      isolated brainstem stroke. Thirty patients will undergo stimulation on the pharyngeal area
      contralateral to the side of brainstem lesion, and 30 patients will receive sham stimulation
      over the contralateral area, for 4 consecutive days. Patients will be re-evaluated after 4
      consecutive days of stimulation. Primary outcome: The Penetration/Aspiration Scale after 4
      consecutive days of stimulation. Secondary outcomes: changes in electromyographic parameters
      and pharyngeal cortical motor evoked potentials, changes in the Dysphagia Severity Rating
      Scale (DSRS), in the Functional Oral Intake Scale (FOIS), and in the &quot;Dysphagia Limit Test&quot;,
      after 4 consecutive days of stimulation.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Sixty consecutive patients with dysphagia associated to isolated acute (within the previous
      24 hours) brainstem ischemic stroke satisfying the inclusion/exclusion criteria will be
      enrolled.

      Swallowing evaluation Clinical evaluation comprises fiberoptic endoscopy that will be used
      for scoring the Penetration/Aspiration Scale. The Penetration/Aspiration Scale will be scored
      by two otolaryngologists and one neurologist blinded to the patient's study group allocation.
      Moreover, feeding status will be evaluated by the clinical &quot;Dysphagia Severity Rating Scale&quot;,
      ranging from 0 (normal fluids, normal diet, and eating independently) to 12 (no oral fluids,
      no oral feeding). Moreover the &quot;Functional Oral Intake Scale&quot;, ranging from 1 (nothing by
      mouth) to 7 (total oral diet with no restriction), and the &quot;Dysphagia Limit Test&quot;, evaluating
      the amount of water that can be swallowed without piece-meal deglutition or clinical signs of
      aspiration, will be used in patient evaluation. Piecemeal deglutition will be evaluated both
      clinically and by means of electromyographic recordings from the mouth floor muscles.
      Moreover, simultaneous electromyographic/mechanographic recordings from the above mentioned
      muscles, as well as from cricopharyngeal muscle and from the thyroid cartilage will be also
      performed. The changes in cortico-pharyngeal excitability will be evaluated by recording
      motor evoked potentials from the pharyngeal muscles after transcranial magnetic stimulation.

      Randomization: patients will be randomly assigned to either the active treatment (real) or
      sham groups according to a computer-generated list. Randomization will be stratified in order
      to match age, and severity of dysphagia.

      Transcranial direct current stimulation: anodal transcranial direct current stimulation will
      be delivered through two 25-cm2 rectangular surface electrodes, with the active one placed
      over the &quot;pharyngeal&quot; area of the motor cortex contralateral to the side of brainstem lesion
      and the reference one on the contralateral supraorbital ridge. Furthermore, the electrodes
      will be fixed in their position using a set of adjustable rubber straps placed around the
      head. For the active intervention (the &quot;real&quot; stimulation group), current intensity will be
      slowly increased up to 2mA. This intensity will be maintained for 20 min before the
      stimulation will be slowly turned off over a 10-sec period. For the &quot;sham&quot; intervention, the
      current will be left on only for 30 sec, while the electrodes will be left in place for a
      further 20-min period. All patients will be evaluated at baseline, and after 4 consecutive
      days of stimulation.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">March 30, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 30, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 30, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
    <masking_description>double-blind</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Penetration Aspiration Scale (PAS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline PAS at 4 days</time_frame>
    <description>PAS is an 8-point severity scale from 1 = no material enters the airways to 8 = material enters the airways, passes below the vocal folds in the absence of any effort to eject it.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Functional Oral Intake Scale (FOIS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline FOIS at 4 days</time_frame>
    <description>FOIS is a scale ranging from 1 (nothing by mouth) to 7 (total oral diet with no restriction)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Dysphagia Limit Test</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline &quot;Dysphagia Limit Test&quot; at 4 days</time_frame>
    <description>The &quot;Dysphagia Limit Test&quot;, evaluates the amount of water that can be swallowed without piece-meal deglutition or clinical signs of aspiration.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharyngeal (motor evoked potentials (MEPs) after Transcranial Magnetic Stimulation (TMS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline pharyngeal MEPs at 4 days</time_frame>
    <description>the changes in amplitude of MEPs recorded from pharyngeal muscle after TMS over the pharyngeal contralateral motor cortex will be evaluated</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>electromyographic/cinematic evaluation of swallowing</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline electromyographic/cinematic parameters at 4 days</time_frame>
    <description>Simultaneous electromyographic/cinematic recordings from mouth floor muscles, cricopharyngeal muscle and thyroid cartilage will be performed</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Dysphagia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>real tDCS</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>30 patients will be treated with real anodal tDCS over the contralateral pharyngeal motor cortex</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>sham tDCS</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Sham Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>30 patients will be treated with sham tDCS over the contralateral pharyngeal motor cortex</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Anodal tDCS</intervention_name>
    <description>patients will be stimulated over the contralateral pharyngeal motor cortex with anodal tDCS (2mA, 20 minutes) for 4 consecutive days</description>
    <arm_group_label>real tDCS</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>sham tDCS</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  accepting to participating to the study

          -  age not &lt; 18 years

          -  bulbar stroke occurring within the previous 24 hours

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  age &lt; 18 years

          -  inability to give informed consent because of cognitive impairment

          -  stroke occurring over the previous 24 hours
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Domenico A Restivo, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+39 095 7593909</phone>
    <email>darestivo@libero.it</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Domenico A. Restivo</name>
      <address>
        <city>Catania</city>
        <zip>95100</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Domenico A Restivo, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>+39 095 7593909</phone>
      <email>darestivo@libero.it</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Italy</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 8, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 13, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 16, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 13, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 13, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 16, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Presidio Ospedaliero Garibaldi-Centro</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Domenico Antonio Restivo</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Consutant Neurologist</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Deglutition Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Brain Stem Infarctions</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

