<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04303065</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>eudraCT: 2019-004038-41</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04303065</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Dexamethasone for the Treatment of Vasogenic Pericontusional Edema.</brief_title>
  <acronym>DEXCON-TBI</acronym>
  <official_title>Dexamethasone for the Treatment of Traumatic Brain Injured Patients With Brain Contusions and Pericontusional Edema: Study Protocol for a Prospective, Randomized and Double Blind Trial.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Hospital Son Espases</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Hospital Son Espases</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The DEXCON-TBI trial is a multicenter, pragmatic, randomized, triple-blind, placebo
      controlled trial to quantify the effects of the administration of dexamethasone on the
      prognosis of TBI patients with brain contusions and pericontusional edema. Adult patients who
      fulfil the elegibility criteria will be randomized to receive dexamethasone or placebo.
      Patients who have suffered a head injury and have one or more cerebral contusions with
      visible pericontusional edema in the CT scan can be included in the study. The doses of
      dexamethasone will be a short and descending course: 4mg/6 hours (2 days); 4 mg/8 hours (2
      days); 2 mg/6 hours (2 days); 2 mg/8 hours (2 days); 1 mg/8 hours (2 days); 1 mg/12 hours (2
      days). The primary outcome is the Glasgow Scale Outcome Extended (GOSE) performed one month
      and 6 months after trauma. Other secondary outcomes are: compare the number of episodes of
      neurological deterioration; compare the symptoms associated with TBI; compare the presence of
      adverse events during treatment; compare the volume of pericontusional edema before and after
      12 days of treatment in both groups of patients; and compare the results of the
      neuropsychological tests between the two groups of patients one month and 6 months after the
      TBI. The main analysis will be on an ``intention-to-treat´´ basis. A descriptive analysis of
      the baseline variables will be made for each treatment group. Logistic regression will be
      used to estimate the effect of dexamethasone and placebo on GOSE at one month and at 6
      months, dichotomized in unfavorable outcome (GOSE 1-6) and favorable outcome (GOSE 7-8).
      Since the severity of the initial injury will determine significantly the final outcome of
      the patient, to assess the effect of dexamethasone, efficacy will also be analyzed using the
      'sliding dichotomy'. A subgroup analysis will be carried out by stratifying the patients as
      they present more or less than 10mL of pericontusional edema in the preinclusion CT. We will
      perform an interim analysis with the patients included during the first year to calculate the
      conditional power. An independent statistician will blindly perform this analysis. At the
      same time a safety analysis will be also perfomed. A study with 600 patients would have about
      80% power (two sided alpha=5%) to detect a 12% absolute increased (from 50% to 62%) in good
      outcome.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">May 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 1, 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 1, 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>Only the pharmacist, who masks the capsules and labels the containers, will know the assignement of the codes, and will keep them blind until the last phase of the study, after the main statistical analysis, or when unmasking is required.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Glasgow Scale Outcome Extended (GOSE).</measure>
    <time_frame>one month</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of episodes of neurological deterioration in both groups of patients during the 12 days of treatment.</measure>
    <time_frame>14 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Symptoms associated with TBI in both groups of patients during the 12 days of treatment.</measure>
    <time_frame>14 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Volume of pericontusional edema before and after 12 days of treatment in both groups of patients.</measure>
    <time_frame>14 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Presence of adverse events between the two groups during the 12 days of treatment.</measure>
    <time_frame>14 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Neuropsychological tests between the two groups of patients one month and 6 months after the TBI.</measure>
    <time_frame>one month</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">600</enrollment>
  <condition>Traumatic Brain Injury</condition>
  <condition>Cerebral Edema</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Dexamethasone</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Dexamethasone will be a short and descending course: 4mg/6 hours (2 days); 4 mg/8 hours (2 days); 2 mg/6 hours (2 days); 2 mg/8 hours (2 days); 1 mg/8 hours (2 days); 1 mg/12 hours (2 days).
Dexamethasone (Fortecortin®) will be acquired from ERN, SA. Laboratories (Barcelona, Spain). The Son Espases Pharmacy Department will be in charge of developing and conditioning the 4mg, 2mg and 1mg dexamethasone / placebo capsules needed for 12 days of treatment, keeping the researchers blind</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The preparation and conditioning of the capsules will be carried out following the standardized work procedures of the pharmaceutical laboratory and its quality controls, previously authorized by the Agencia Española del Medicamento (AEMPS).
The Son Espases Pharmacy Department will be responsible for identifying the containers and sending them by courier to the participating hospitals. A record of the dispensing of test samples will be kept and will be sent in acknowledgment of receipt for control</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Dexamethasone Oral</intervention_name>
    <description>It will be a short and descending course of oral dexamethasone: 4mg/6 hours (2 days); 4 mg/8 hours (2 days); 2 mg/6 hours (2 days); 2 mg/8 hours (2 days); 1 mg/8 hours (2 days); 1 mg/12 hours (2 days).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Dexamethasone</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo oral tablet</intervention_name>
    <description>The preparation and conditioning of the placebo capsules will be carried out following the standardized work procedures of the pharmaceutical laboratory and its quality controls, previously authorized by the Agencia Española del Medicamento (AEMPS).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  -Patients who have suffered a head injury and have one or more cerebral contusions
             with visible pericontusional edema in the CT scan.

          -  Patients with brain contusions in whom non-sugical treatment has been selected
             initially.

          -  Age 18 or over and under 85

          -  Signing of informed consent by the patient or by his legal representative. The
             fundamental eligibility criterion is the responsible clinician's 'uncertainty' as to
             whether or not to use dexamethasone in a particular patient with TBI. This pragmatic
             approach will allow us to see whether the intervention improves patient outcomes under
             real-life conditions.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with TBI and brain contusions who have required surgery to evacuate the
             cerebral contusion before randomization.

          -  Patients with TBI who have required a craniotomy before randomization for any other
             reason: evacuation of subdural, epidural hematoma or depressed skull fracture.

          -  Patients with an extracranial Injury Severity Score greater than 18 points.

          -  Patients in whom the use of corticosteroids is contraindicated.

          -  Patients who take oral corticosteroids chronically.

          -  Patients included in another clinical trial.

          -  Known intolerance or hypersensitivity to dexamethasone.

          -  Patients with allergy or intolerance to the following excipients contained in
             dexamethasone / placebo capsules: lactose, corn starch or microcrystalline cellulose.

          -  Patients with a history of psychotic disorders.

          -  Patients with inability to take medication orally due to swallowing problems in which
             it is not indicated to place a nasogastric tube.

          -  Pregnant or breastfeeding patients.

          -  Patients in a GCS 3 points situation with bilateral dilated pupils.

          -  Patients with associated spinal cord injuries.

          -  Patient with any systemic condition that contraindicates the use of corticosteroids.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>85 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 5, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 9, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 10, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 9, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 9, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 10, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Hospital Son Espases</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Jon Pérez Bárcena</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>MD</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>traumatic</keyword>
  <keyword>brain</keyword>
  <keyword>injury</keyword>
  <keyword>contusion</keyword>
  <keyword>edema</keyword>
  <keyword>steroids</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Brain Injuries</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Brain Injuries, Traumatic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Brain Edema</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Edema</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Dexamethasone</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

