<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04307563</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IRB-54792</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04307563</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effects of Mindfulness Training on Burnout and Mood in Hospital Employees</brief_title>
  <official_title>Mindfulness Effects on Burnout and Mood in Hospital Employees</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Stanford University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Stanford University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The primary aims of the study are to 1) provide a hospital employee population with a
      mindfulness based stress reduction workshop and 2) evaluate the impact of this clinically
      validated group mindfulness intervention on burnout in health care employees. Secondary
      outcomes will be anxiety, depression, quality of life and self compassion.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">September 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 31, 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 31, 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Burnout</measure>
    <time_frame>Four time points (week 1 and 6 of intervention, and 3 &amp; 6 month post intervention)</time_frame>
    <description>1. Differences in Burnout scale between time points
The Burnout Scale has been validated by Trockel et al. (2018).It is composed of two subscales (emotional exhaustion containing 4 questions and interpersonal disengagement containing 6 questions.) Both scales are scored on a Likert scale of 0 to 4 (&quot;not at all&quot; to &quot;extremely&quot;). For total Burnout score, the scores of the combined scale (10 total) are averaged. The higher scores indicate higher levels of overall burnout. Individual subscale means will also be computed (with higher scores indicating higher amounts of emotional exhaustion and interpersonal disengagement. Difference in overall burnout measured at four time points (week 1 and 6 of the intervention and 3 &amp; 6 months post intervention) will be reported and compared. The composite scales take approximately 2 minutes to complete.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Anxiety</measure>
    <time_frame>Four time points (week 1 and 6 of intervention, and 3 &amp; 6 month post intervention)</time_frame>
    <description>1. Differences in GAD-7 between time points.
The Generalized Anxiety Disorder-7 is a well validated seven-item self-administered questionnaire used to measure anxiety. It has 7 questions with Likert scores ranging from &quot;not at all&quot; (score 0), &quot;several days&quot; (score 1), &quot;more than half the days&quot; (score 2), and &quot;nearly every day (score 3). Scores range from 0 to 21 with higher scores indicating higher levels of anxiety, and a cutoff of or above 10 representing high likelihood of generalized anxiety disorder. Differences in GAD-7 measured at four time points (week 1 and 6 of the intervention and 3 &amp; 6 months post intervention) will be reported and compared. The scale takes approximately 2 minutes.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Depression</measure>
    <time_frame>Four time points (week 1 and 6 of intervention, and 3 &amp; 6 month post intervention)</time_frame>
    <description>1. Differences in CES-D between time points.
The Center for Epidemiological Studies - Depression scale is a well validated self-administered questionnaire used to measure depression. The 20 item scale has Likert scores ranging from &quot;rarely or none of the time&quot; (score 0), &quot;some or little of the time&quot; (score 1), &quot;moderate or much of the time&quot; (score 2), and &quot;most or almost all the time&quot; (score 3). Scores range from 0 to 60 with higher scores indicated greater depressive symptoms. A cut off at or above 20 has sensitivity 79% and specificity of 80% for major depression. Difference in CES-D in 2019 measured at four time points (week 1 and 6 of the intervention and 3 &amp; 6 month post intervention) will be reported and compared. The scale takes approximately 5 minutes to complete.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Perceived Health</measure>
    <time_frame>Four time points (week 1 and 6 of intervention, and 3 &amp; 6 month post intervention)</time_frame>
    <description>1. Differences in GSRH between time points.
A single item of the Health Related Quality of Life - 4 questionnaire &quot;In general, would you say your health is Excellent (score 1), Very Good (score 2), Good (score 3), Fair (score 4), or Poor (score 5), the general self-rated health (GSRH), is a strong predictor of future health care utilization and mortality. It also has excellent validity. Higher scores of the GSRH are related to higher health care expenditures. Difference in GSRH measured at four time points (week 1 and 6 of the intervention and 3 &amp; 6 month post intervention) will be reported and compared. The scale takes less than 1 minute to complete.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in compassion</measure>
    <time_frame>Four time points (week 1 and 6 of intervention, and 3 &amp; 6 months post intervention)</time_frame>
    <description>1. Differences in compassion scores between time points.
The 12 item Self-Compassion Scale - Short Form is strongly validated scale to measure self-compassion or &quot;the ability to hold one's feelings of suffering with a sense of warmth, connection and concern&quot;. Higher levels of self-compassion are associated with less depression and anxiety. Five-point Likert score are from 1 (&quot;Almost Never&quot;) to 5 (&quot;Almost Always&quot;). Total score is computed by reverse scoring negative items of self-judgement, isolation and over-identification (ie 1=5, 2=4, 3=3, 4=2, 5=1) and computing total mean. Difference in Compassion measured at four time points (week 1 and 6 of the intervention, and 3 &amp; 6 month post intervention) will be reported and compared. The scale takes approximately 5-10 minutes to complete.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Anxiety Depression</condition>
  <condition>Burnout</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Mindfulness group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will attend 6 weekly educational and mindfulness sessions.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Mindfulness session</intervention_name>
    <description>1.5 hour weekly session with health educator</description>
    <arm_group_label>Mindfulness group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  English speaking

          -  Employees of Stanford Health Care

          -  Ability to attend a minimum of 4 out of 6 sessions

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Non-English speaking

          -  Employees with severe medical or psychiatric conditions that prevent them from
             participating in the group format
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Maria G Juarez-Reyes</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Stanford University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Alexandria Blacker</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Stanford University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jordana Harshman</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Stanford University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Maria G Juarez-Reyes, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>6504989000</phone>
    <email>mjuarezreyes@stanford.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Alexandria Blacker</last_name>
    <phone>650-724-4141</phone>
    <email>blacker@stanford.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Stanford Health Care</name>
      <address>
        <city>Palo Alto</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94305</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Alexandra Blacker, MPH</last_name>
      <phone>650-724-4141</phone>
      <email>blacker@stanford.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Maria Juarez-Reyes, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bazarko D, Cate RA, Azocar F, Kreitzer MJ. The Impact of an Innovative Mindfulness-Based Stress Reduction Program on the Health and Well-Being of Nurses Employed in a Corporate Setting. J Workplace Behav Health. 2013 Apr;28(2):107-133.</citation>
    <PMID>23667348</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Aiken LH, Clarke SP, Sloane DM, Sochalski J, Silber JH. Hospital nurse staffing and patient mortality, nurse burnout, and job dissatisfaction. JAMA. 2002 Oct 23-30;288(16):1987-93.</citation>
    <PMID>12387650</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Vøllestad J, Nielsen MB, Nielsen GH. Mindfulness- and acceptance-based interventions for anxiety disorders: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Br J Clin Psychol. 2012 Sep;51(3):239-60. doi: 10.1111/j.2044-8260.2011.02024.x. Epub 2011 Sep 9. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22803933</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hoge EA, Bui E, Marques L, Metcalf CA, Morris LK, Robinaugh DJ, Worthington JJ, Pollack MH, Simon NM. Randomized controlled trial of mindfulness meditation for generalized anxiety disorder: effects on anxiety and stress reactivity. J Clin Psychiatry. 2013 Aug;74(8):786-92. doi: 10.4088/JCP.12m08083.</citation>
    <PMID>23541163</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>DeSalvo KB, Jones TM, Peabody J, McDonald J, Fihn S, Fan V, He J, Muntner P. Health care expenditure prediction with a single item, self-rated health measure. Med Care. 2009 Apr;47(4):440-7. doi: 10.1097/MLR.0b013e318190b716.</citation>
    <PMID>19238099</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zich JM, Attkisson CC, Greenfield TK. Screening for depression in primary care clinics: the CES-D and the BDI. Int J Psychiatry Med. 1990;20(3):259-77.</citation>
    <PMID>2265888</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Spitzer RL, Kroenke K, Williams JB, Löwe B. A brief measure for assessing generalized anxiety disorder: the GAD-7. Arch Intern Med. 2006 May 22;166(10):1092-7.</citation>
    <PMID>16717171</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Raes F, Pommier E, Neff KD, Van Gucht D. Construction and factorial validation of a short form of the Self-Compassion Scale. Clin Psychol Psychother. 2011 May-Jun;18(3):250-5. doi: 10.1002/cpp.702. Epub 2010 Jun 8.</citation>
    <PMID>21584907</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Trockel M, Bohman B, Lesure E, Hamidi MS, Welle D, Roberts L, Shanafelt T. A Brief Instrument to Assess Both Burnout and Professional Fulfillment in Physicians: Reliability and Validity, Including Correlation with Self-Reported Medical Errors, in a Sample of Resident and Practicing Physicians. Acad Psychiatry. 2018 Feb;42(1):11-24. doi: 10.1007/s40596-017-0849-3. Epub 2017 Dec 1.</citation>
    <PMID>29196982</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 11, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 11, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 13, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 19, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 19, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 23, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Stanford University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Maria Juarez-Reyes</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Clinical Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>self-compassion</keyword>
  <keyword>meditation</keyword>
  <keyword>health personnel</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Burnout, Psychological</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

