<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04306328</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>APHP190280</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04306328</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Neural Stimulation for Hand Grasp</brief_title>
  <acronym>AGILIS</acronym>
  <official_title>Functional Evaluation of the Recovery of Prehension in Quadriplegics by Implanted Neural Stimulation</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Assistance Publique - Hôpitaux de Paris</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Institut National de Recherche en Informatique et en Automatique</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>CRRF La Châtaigneraie</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>NEURINNOV</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Assistance Publique - Hôpitaux de Paris</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      A selective neural stimulation as the investigators propose allows to stimulate several
      muscles via a single electrode. Neural stimulation requires less energy for muscle
      activation. In our approach, 2 electrodes will be implanted above the elbow on the median and
      radial nerves. This considerably reduces the number of implanted elements and therefore i)
      the risk of infection, ii) the risk of failure, iii) the surgical risk through minimally
      invasive surgery.

      Our main hypothesis is that multipolar neural electrical stimulation of the median nerve
      (flexion) and the radial nerve (extension) allows:

        -  on the one hand, a selective, individualized motor activation (muscle by muscle)

        -  on the other hand, a synergistic motor activation (association of several muscles) for
           the purpose of production of functional movements.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Electrical stimulation of the muscles has been used for decades in rehabilitation units
      specializing in the treatment of spinal cord injuries. It has been shown to be effective in
      building muscle and preventing muscle atrophy following spinal cord injury (SCI) or stroke.
      It can also be used to reduce spasticity and above all to promote functionally useful motor
      control. It is then a Functional Electric Stimulation (FES). In the quadriplegic person
      marked by a severe motor deficiency of the upper limbs, FES is today the only technique
      allowing to restore a functional gripping movements in the case where the active muscular
      resources below the elbows are missing or too weak to allow tendon transfer surgery.

      Like &quot;Freehand&quot;, all the devices using FES directly stimulate the muscles (surface,
      intramuscular or epimysial electrodes) and therefore require a high number of internal
      components with a theoretical risk of infection and greater rejection. since each muscle must
      be activated via an electrode (up to 12 in the case of &quot;FreeHand&quot;). The investigators propose
      instead selective neural stimulation as it allows stimulating several muscles via a single
      electrode. Neural stimulation requires less energy for muscle activation. In our approach, 2
      electrodes will be implanted above the elbow on the median and radial nerves. This
      considerably reduces the number of implanted elements and therefore i) the risk of infection,
      ii) the risk of failure, iii) the surgical risk thanks to minimally invasive surgery. The
      procedure consisted of placing a multi-contact cuff electrode around the radial or median
      nerves and observing the effects of electrical neural stimulation in terms of muscle
      selectivity, force produced and movement induced. In a previous study, the investigators
      already proved through acute intra operative testing (under Ethics Committee approval,
      #NCT03721861) that:

        -  No failure of the electrodes or of the stimulator was noted.

        -  For all of the 8 subjects, it was possible to selectively stimulate muscle groups to
           obtain the opening of the thumb and fingers, or the flexion of the thumb, fingers and
           obtaining possibly functional grip like the forceps with opposition of the thumb or
           palmar grip.

      A second feasibility study (Ethics committee registration #2016-A00711-50) with 17
      quadriplegic patients assessed the subject's ability to use voluntary contractions of sus
      lesional muscles (EMG recordings in 8 subjects) or voluntary movements of shoulders (inertial
      recordings in 9 subjects) to control the movements of a robotic hand or the triggering of an
      electrical surface stimulation of the muscles of the forearm. All of the patients managed to
      master the proposed interface after a short familiarization period.

      On the basis of the results of these two studies, the investigator wish to take an additional
      step in the development of a gripping assistance device for patients with spinal cord injury:

      - by proposing the implantation of two cuff electrodes with percutaneous connection on the
      arm of quadriplegic people. The electrodes will be kept in place for a period of 1 month
      before being definitively explanted. An implanted cable will connect the electrodes to an
      external connector.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">March 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Selectivity index of the configurations which allow an individualized recruitment of the different muscles at D+29</measure>
    <time_frame>End of the protocole (day 29)</time_frame>
    <description>Selectivity index of the configurations (active contacts of the electrode and stimulation parameters) which allow an individualized recruitment of the different muscles at D+29 based on the combination of the increase of the Root Mean Square (RMS) value of the Electromyography (EMG) and variation of 10% of the maximum distance covered by the considered segment compared with the rest position.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Motor Capacities Scale (MCS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 29</time_frame>
    <description>The Motor Capacity Scale (MCS) which studies the Key Grip and Grasp sockets in their 3 facets (catching, holding and letting go). MCS should be above 27.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Test n°1 of the 400 Points assessment</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 29</time_frame>
    <description>functional relevance of neural implantation via the production of 4 movements considered useful: an opening of the 5 fingers, a digito-palmar grip with thumb, a digito-palmar grip without thumb and an end-to-side thumb grip Test No. 1 of the 400 POINTS balance sheet, which brings together the study of 12 hand functions. POINTS score should be above 60.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The rate in % of total tests of grasping objects.</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 29</time_frame>
    <description>Testing of two methods of autonomous control of the device by the patient. The successful rate in % of total tests of grasping objects. The success rate should be above 80%.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Optimal stimulation strategies obtained for a synergistic functional control</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 29</time_frame>
    <description>For each movement, the minimum stimulation intensity to produce the movement will be noted. In mA this intensity should be as low as possible. A value above 1.5 mA of failure to obtain the desired movement will be considered as a failed outcome.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The impedance of the electrode contacts.</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 29</time_frame>
    <description>Assessment of the evolution of the quality of the stimulation over time (stability of the settings and of the tissue / electrode interface). A Impedance of the electrode contacts to assess the state of the contact between the electrode poles and the nerve tissue.
The state of contact between the electrode poles and the nervous tissue will be evaluated by measuring the impedance of the electrode contacts. This impedance expressed in k ohms, should not be higher than 5. Above this threshold the contact will be considered to be non-functional.
For each movement, the minimum stimulation intensity (in mA) to initiate the movement should stay below 1.5 mA.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Local skin tolerance</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 29</time_frame>
    <description>Local skin tolerance assessed by the number of patients with dermatological lesions at the implantation site, of allergic and/or infectious type during the month following implantation. The answer provided daily will be binary yes / no.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Local algological tolerance (1)</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 29</time_frame>
    <description>Local algological tolerance assessed by number of patients with at least one pain at the implant site, qualified as neuropathic or nociceptive and quantified as &gt; or = 3/10 using a digital analog scale from 0 to 10, during the month following implantation.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Local algological tolerance (2)</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 29</time_frame>
    <description>Local algological tolerance assessed by average intensity of daily pain</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">6</enrollment>
  <condition>Quadriplegia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Neurostimulation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Neurostimulation</intervention_name>
    <description>Implantation of 2 multicontact cuff electrodes in the upper limb of patients with tetraplegia and control of the stimulation by contralateral shoulder movements</description>
    <arm_group_label>Neurostimulation</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Informed consent signed

          -  Patient affiliated to a social security (state medical aid excepted).

          -  Neurological level ≥ C7

          -  18 years old ≤ age ≤ 65 years old,

          -  complete traumatic injury: defined by an A or B score on the AIS scale. (AIS A or -
             complete motor deficit under injury. This is an internationally agreed standard for
             describing spinal cord injury)

          -  neurological stability (no change in muscle testing) &gt; 6 months,

          -  post-injury duration &gt; 6 months

          -  patients without active muscle resources for conventional tendon transfer surgery on
             the forearm and hand

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  patient deprived of liberty (by judicial or administrative decision).

          -  adult patient who is subject to a legal protection measure or unable to express
             consent

          -  participation in another ongoing clinical trial

          -  pregnant or breastfeeding women or women of childbearing age without effective
             contraception

          -  spasticity and contractures in flexion or extension of the upper limbs of a
             destabilizing nature.

          -  unstable epilepsy with a notion of a epileptic seizure that occurred within the
             previous 12 months.

          -  unstable cardiovascular pathology (coronary heart disease, major hypertension, heart
             failure, etc.).

          -  infectious pathology under treatment at the inclusion visit

          -  wearing a pacemaker.

          -  dermatological problems contraindicating the application of surface electrodes.

          -  body weight &gt;100 kg

          -  psychiatric condition and/or history contraindicating participation in research

          -  any contraindications to anesthesia and/or surgery

          -  hypersensitivity to low molecular weight heparin (LMWH) or to any of the excipients of
             the specialty used

          -  history of immune-mediated heparin-induced thrombocytopenia (HIT) within the last 100
             days or presence of circulating antibodies

          -  clinically significant active bleeding or a condition associated with a high risk of
             bleeding

          -  electrical mapping identified as negative during the inclusion visit, i.e. with
             muscles revealing a rating &lt; 4 MRC for at least one of the extensors (ECRL, ECRB, EDC,
             EPL) or one of the flexors (FPL, FDS, FDP).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Charles FATTAL, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Assistance Publique - Hôpitaux de Paris</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Charles FATTAL, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>01 36 45 64 22</phone>
    <email>cfattal@lachataigneraie.fr</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Christine AZEVEDO, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>04 67 41 86 92</phone>
    <email>Christine.Azevedo@inria.fr</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Service MPR Hôpital : CRRF La Chataigneraie</name>
      <address>
        <city>Menucourt</city>
        <zip>95180</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Charles FATTAL, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>01 36 45 64 22</phone>
      <email>cfattal@lachataigneraie.fr</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 31, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 11, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 12, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 11, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 11, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 12, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Percutaneous Electrical Nerve Stimulation</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Quadriplegia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

