<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04306822</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>01201178178</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04306822</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Epidemiology of Cardiovascular Diseases and Their Risk Factors in Regions of Russian Federation</brief_title>
  <acronym>ECVD-RF</acronym>
  <official_title>Epidemiology of Cardiovascular Diseases and Their Risk Factors in Regions of Russian Federation</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Research Center for Preventive Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Medical Research Center for Cardiology, Ministry of Health of Russian Federation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Federal State Budgetary Institution, V. A. Almazov Federal North-West Medical Research Centre, of the Ministry of Health</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Research Center for Preventive Medicine</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The study carried out in 2012-2014 years. The aim was to evaluate the prevalence of CVD and
      their RF in different regions of the Russian Federation and to develop epidemiological models
      of the CVD risk profile for the population based on traditional factors, as well as to assess
      the contribution of traditional and &quot;new&quot; cardiovascular risk factors to the mortality rate
      of the country's population based on domestic data. Thirteen regions were included. We
      examined 22,906 males and females, aged 25-64 years. The examination consist of
      anthropometry; the measurement of BP, resting heart rate, and a 12-lead standard
      electrocardiography (ECG) in a supine position. The personal interview information was
      collected using a structured questionnaire, and included socio-demographic and socio-economic
      measures; health parameters; medical history; stress, and depression. Continued monitoring of
      mortality, the latest mortality update includes deaths through 2019.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The representative (systematic stratified multistage) random sample was generated according
      to the territorial principle (Kish method) in 13 regions of the Russian Federation. The study
      sample included 22,906 participants (8353 males and 13553 females) 25-64 years old, with a
      response rate - 80%, examined in 2012-2014. The following regions were included: Volgograd,
      Voronezh, Vologda, Ivanovo, Kemerovo, Orenburg, Samara, Tomsk, Tyumen regions, St.
      Petersburg, Krasnoyarsk, Primorsky Territory and the Republic of North Ossetia-Alania. All of
      the subjects were examined using a standard questionnaire consisting of 12 modules and
      containing information on age and gender composition, educational status, professional
      affiliation, level of well-being of survey participants, the presence of behavioral risk
      factors: smoking, excessive alcohol consumption, low physical activity, poor nutrition, as
      well as anxiety and depressive disorders. In addition, the questionnaire included anamnestic
      data on chronic diseases and drug therapy. Quality of life was assessed using the EUROQOL
      international questionnaire - EQ-5D All subjects were measured blood pressure (BP) and heart
      rate twice according to the standard procedure. Anthropometric procedures included measuring
      weight (kg), height (m), waist circumference (cm), calculating body mass index (BMI; kg /
      m2). The lipid profile was determined for all patients, including levels of HDL and HDL
      cholesterol, triglycerides, as well as glucose, creatinine and uric acid. The levels of these
      parameters in blood serum were determined by Abbot Architect c8000 biochemical analyzer
      (USA). The Additional Screening program, included sphygmomanometry, duplex scanning of
      carotid arteries, and evaluation of the parameters characterizing the functioning of
      metabolic systems (apo B and apo AI, as well as LP (a), C-reactive protein (hsCRP), NT-proBNP
      - the N-terminal propeptide of cerebral natriuretic hormone B-type, dash Nootropic hormone
      (TSH), insulin, D-dimer) in addition to the main survey was conducted in the 5
      regions.Continued monitoring of mortality. Deaths were verified in residential registers and
      from telephone calls. The latest mortality update includes deaths through 2019.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">January 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">January 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The number of fatal and non-fatal events</measure>
    <time_frame>6 years</time_frame>
    <description>cardiovascular death, noncardiovascular death, all-cause death, the triple composite of cardiovascular death, non-fatal MI or non-fatal stroke, fatal MI, fatal stroke, non-fatal MI, non-fatal stroke, hospitalization for HF, coronary angiography, PCI, and CABG</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">22906</enrollment>
  <condition>Risk Factor, Cardiovascular</condition>
  <condition>Non-communicable Diseases</condition>
  <condition>Cardiovascular Diseases</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        The study participants were randomly selected from 13 regions of Russian Federation between
        2012-2014. The final sample included 22,906 individuals (8353 males, 13553 females) who
        completed an interview and medical tests (response rate 80%).
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  randomly selected males and females aged 25-64 years from 13 regions of Russian
             Federation

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  males and females younger than 24 years and older than 64 years
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>25 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>64 Years</maximum_age>
  </eligibility>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 10, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 10, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 13, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 13, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 13, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 17, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>epidemiology</keyword>
  <keyword>risk factor</keyword>
  <keyword>adult</keyword>
  <keyword>non-communicable diseases</keyword>
  <keyword>cardio-vascular diseases</keyword>
  <keyword>dietary habits</keyword>
  <keyword>arterial hypertension</keyword>
  <keyword>smoking</keyword>
  <keyword>physical activity</keyword>
  <keyword>hypercholesterinemia</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Noncommunicable Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cardiovascular Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

