<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04306250</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>145-19</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04306250</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Comparison of Posterior and Anterior Approach to Sacrospinous Ligament Apical Fixation - Randomized Controlled Trial</brief_title>
  <official_title>Comparison of Posterior and Anterior Approach to Sacrospinous Ligament Apical Fixation - Randomized Controlled Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>HaEmek Medical Center, Israel</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>HaEmek Medical Center, Israel</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>Yes</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Pelvic organ prolapse (POP) is a common problem among women. Apical prolapse (AP) is a
      prolapse of the uterus, or vaginal cuff, in women post hysterectomy.

      Apical fixation to the sacrospinous ligament (SSLF) was first introduced in 1968 by
      K.RICHTER. .In a large review study, the subjective cure rate after SSLF ranged from 70 to
      98%, while objective cure rate was 67-97%.

      The success rates of SSLF in a randomized study comparing SSLF to uterosacral ligament
      fixation after two years were 63.1%. In women with combined apical and anterior wall
      prolapse, SSLF can be performed in two ways: anterior access through the anterior vaginal
      wall or posterior approach through the posterior vaginal wall.

      A retrospective comparison of the two methods was performed, demonstrating some efficacy to
      the anterior approach over the posterior approach mainly in respect to the vaginal length.

      From the literature review to date, no comparisons were made between the methods in a
      randomized controlled trial.

      Objective: To compare the success rates between two approaches (anterior and posterior) for
      SSLF
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Pelvic organ prolapse (POP) is a common problem among women and its incidence is rising due
      to population aging. Approximately 11-19% of women will undergo surgery for pelvic organ
      prolapse (POP) or urinary incontinence during their lifetime and approximately 30% will need
      repeat surgery during their lifetime .Apical prolapse (AP) is a prolapse of the uterus, or
      vaginal cuff, in women post hysterectomy. The severity of the prolapsed organ can be graded
      according to the POP-Q classification .There are several approaches to apical fixation, some
      of which are done vaginally and include fixation by sutures to the uterosacral ligament
      (USLF) or the sacrospinous ligament (SSLF). A mesh can be used for ligament fixation as well.
      The abdominal approach is also an option, the sacro-colpo-pexy fixation using a Y mesh.
      Apical fixation to the SSL was first introduced in 1968 by K.RICHTER. medical devices such as
      the Capio that assist in performing SSLF were also developed with ease.

      In a review article that included 2,390 women undergoing SSLF subjective cure rate ranged
      from 70 to 98%, while objective cure rate was 67-97% .Such fixation in combination with
      posterior or anterior wall repair, especially after hysterectomy, showed a 94% objective cure
      rate at 7-year postoperative follow-up. A randomized study (The &quot;OPTIMAL randomised trial&quot;)
      comparing SSLF with USLF found no preference for either method. Success rates were measured
      according to three criteria - 1) no significant vaginal dome or one of the vaginal walls 2)
      no vaginal bulge symptoms 3) no need for repeated surgery within two years of the original
      surgery. According to this study, the success rates of SSLF after two years were 63.1%.

      Among women with anterior vaginal wall prolapse and AP, SSLF can be performed in two ways:
      anterior access, ie dissection through the anterior wall of the vagina or fixation through
      the posterior wall of the vagina. A retrospective comparison of the two methods was
      performed, demonstrating some efficacy in anterior approach in terms of vaginal length and
      postoperative apical fixation with less reference to healing rates or impact on the anterior
      compartment, compared with a posterior approach.

      From the literature review to date, no comparisons were made between the methods in a
      randomized controlled trial.

      Objective: To compare the success rates of two approaches (anterior and posterior) for SSLF
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">April 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 1, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Compound cure rate</measure>
    <time_frame>6-month (and will be further followed yearly until 2 years of total follow up)</time_frame>
    <description>A compound cure rate is composite outcome used to measure the success rate of a surgery designed to repair pelvic organ prolapse. Surgery will be considered successful based on each of the following criteria at the 6-month follow-up (and will be further followed yearly until 2 years of total follow up):
A. Lack of apical and anterior wall prolapse beyond stage 1 (POP-Q stage&lt;=1) b. Subjective success- a negative response (&quot;no&quot; or not at all to the question, &quot;Do you usually have a bulge or something falling out that you can see or feel in your vaginal area?&quot; (Question 3 on the PFDI-20 questionnaire), (score &lt;2).
c. No re-treatment (surgical/ non-surgical) for index compartment</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of surgery</measure>
    <time_frame>From the time of the first cut of the surgery to the time the surgery ends (as documented in the surgery report), up to 240 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>Duration of surgery in minutes</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in hemoglobin level from pre-operation level to post-operative level in g/dl units</measure>
    <time_frame>Hb level will be measured up to 1 month before the surgery and at the 24 hours after surgery. Further examinations will be taken if there is clinical suspicious for bleeding, up to the day of discharge)</time_frame>
    <description>to assess the difference in Hb level before and after the surgery</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Intraoperative complications</measure>
    <time_frame>Any complication the occured during the duration of the surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Any documented event of perforation of adjacent organs such as bladder, ureter, intestine or blood vessel injury that occured during the surgery</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Peri-operative complications</measure>
    <time_frame>Any complications that occured from the end of the surgery until the first check-up visit (6 weeks after rthe surgery)</time_frame>
    <description>Any event of fever / abnormal discharge / abscess / contaminated hematoma/ need for blood transfusion</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximal pain score</measure>
    <time_frame>Maximal pain level during the 6 weeks after the surgery</time_frame>
    <description>To assess a patient's pain level, the investigators will use visual analog scale (VAS)- scale for patient self-reporting of pain. 0 represents no pain, 1-3 represents mild pain, 4-6 represents moderate pain, 7-10 represents severe pain).
the investigators will assess the maximum pain level during the 6 weeks after the surgery</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in PFDI-20 score</measure>
    <time_frame>6, 12 and 24 months post the operation</time_frame>
    <description>Mean scores and change from baseline of PFDI-20 score at 6 and 12, 24 months. To evaluate prolapse, urinary and bowel function(PFDI-20).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient global impression of improvement from surgery</measure>
    <time_frame>6, 12 and 24 months post the operation</time_frame>
    <description>Mean scores of PGI-I at 6 and 12, 24 months. To evaluate patient satisfaction from the surgery.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cure rate at 12 months post-operation</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months post the operation</time_frame>
    <description>A compound cure rate is composite outcome used to measure the success rate of a surgery designed to repair pelvic organ prolapse. Surgery will be considered successful based on each of the following criteria at the 12-month follow-up :
A. Lack of apical and anterior wall prolapse beyond stage 1 (POP-Q stage&lt;=1) b. Subjective success- a negative response (&quot;no&quot; or not at all to the question, &quot;Do you usually have a bulge or something falling out that you can see or feel in your vaginal area?&quot; (Question 3 on the PFDI-20 questionnaire), (score &lt;2).
c. No re-treatment (surgical/ non-surgical) for index compartment</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cure rate at 24 months post-operation</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months post the operation</time_frame>
    <description>A compound cure rate is composite outcome used to measure the success rate of a surgery designed to repair pelvic organ prolapse. Surgery will be considered successful based on each of the following criteria at the 24-month follow-up :
A. Lack of apical and anterior wall prolapse beyond stage 1 (POP-Q stage&lt;=1) b. Subjective success- a negative response (&quot;no&quot; or not at all to the question, &quot;Do you usually have a bulge or something falling out that you can see or feel in your vaginal area?&quot; (Question 3 on the PFDI-20 questionnaire), (score &lt;2).
c. No re-treatment (surgical/ non-surgical) for index compartment</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>long term complications</measure>
    <time_frame>6, 12 and 24 months post the operation</time_frame>
    <description>Incidence of new-onset dyspareunia; de-novo urinary or bowel problems; re-operation for prolapse in the index compartment; de-novo pelvic pain.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">278</enrollment>
  <condition>Pelvic Organ Prolapse</condition>
  <condition>Surgical Procedure, Unspecified</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>anterior approach for apical fixation to the SSL</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>In this group the apical fixation will be done using the anterior access, ie dissection through the anterior vaginal wall.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>posterior approach for apical fixation to the SSL</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>In this group the apical fixation will be done using the posterior access, ie fixation through the vaginal posterior wall.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Apical prolapse fixation - anterior access</intervention_name>
    <description>The surgery is done in anterior access</description>
    <arm_group_label>anterior approach for apical fixation to the SSL</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Apical prolapse fixation - posterior access</intervention_name>
    <description>The surgery is done in posterior access</description>
    <arm_group_label>posterior approach for apical fixation to the SSL</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Women with grade 2 or above apical prolapse, according to POP Q, combined with Grade
             II or above of anterior wall prolapse.

          -  Women who suffer from symptomatic POP and care for a surgical treatment

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Women with a contra-indication for surgical treatment
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <gender_based>Yes</gender_based>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>meirav breverman, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>haemek medical center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>meirav breverman, MD</last_name>
    <phone>97246495507</phone>
    <email>meirav_al@clalit.org.il</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>eyal rom, MD</last_name>
    <phone>97246495507</phone>
    <email>eyalro@clalit.org.il</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 24, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 10, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 12, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 24, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 24, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 25, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>HaEmek Medical Center, Israel</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Meirav Braverman</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>medical doctor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Prolapse</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pelvic Organ Prolapse</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

