<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04302194</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Phenylketonuria</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04302194</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Early Dietary Treated Patients With Phenylketonuria Can Achieve Normal Growth and Mental Development.</brief_title>
  <official_title>Early Dietary Treated Patients With Phenylketonuria Can Achieve Normal Growth and Mental Development.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Assiut University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Assiut University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The study aim is to follow up body growth(body weight by kg, length by cm, head
      circumference, abdominal circumference, and body mass index ) and mental development of
      infants on phenylalanine restricted diet in comparison with normal matchable infants.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Phenylketonuria is rare genetic disease caused by mutation in gene of phenylalanine (Phe)
      hydroxylase that converts Phenylalanine into tyrosine. The absence of this enzyme leads to
      elevation and accumulation of Phenylalanine and, increased phenylketones in urine (hence
      PKU), and also leads to decrease myelin formation, dopamine, norepinephrine, and serotonin
      production.

      Phenylketonuria worldwide affects about 1 in 12,000 babies.

      In Egypt the incidence rate reported 1 : 3000 (0.03%), The actual prevalence of PKU in this
      study were 1/3000. This is higher than that reported by Temtamy25, who found in a pilot study
      on 15,000 newborns in 3 governorates in Egypt that the incidence of PKU was 1/ 7500 . The
      latest consensus in Egypt showed that at least one million babies are born every year.

      Phenylalanine hydroxylase deficiency (PAH deficiency) causes a spectrum of disorders,
      including classic phenylketonuria (PKU).

      A rarer form of hyperphenylalaninemia is tetrahydrobiopterin deficiency, which occurs when
      the PAH enzyme is normal, and a defect is found in the biosynthesis or recycling of the
      cofactor tetrahydrobiopterin (BH4).

      Elevations of phenylalanine in the plasma depend on the degree of enzyme deficiency. In
      patients with severe PAH deficiency (previously referred to classic phenylketonuria ), plasma
      phenylalanine levels on unrestricted diet usually exceed 20 mg/dL (&gt;1,200 μmol/L). In
      affected infants with plasma concentrations &gt;20 mg/dL, excess phenylalanine is metabolized to
      phenylketones (phenylpyruvate and phenylacetate) that are excreted in the urine, giving rise
      to the term phenylketonuria (PKU).

      If left untreated and not detected early , irreversible damage may occur due to the
      accumulation of Phenylalanine and its metabolites in the body and will affect the growth and
      development of patients .

      Without treatment most children develop profound and irreversible intellectual disability,
      seizures, hyperactive behavior with autistic features, psychiatric symptoms, eczema, musty
      body odor, and light pigmentation.

      Newborn screening is performed to detect the disease and initiate treatment before any damage
      is done. The blood sample is usually taken by heel prick, typically performed 2-7 days after
      birth. This test can reveal elevated phenylalanine levels after one or two days of normal
      infant feeding. PKU is commonly included in the newborn screening panel of many countries and
      Egypt , with varied detection techniques. Most babies are screened for PKU soon after birth.

      If left untreated and not detected early , irreversible damage may occur due to the
      accumulation of Phenylalanine and its metabolites in the body and will affect the growth and
      development of patients .

      Without treatment most children develop profound and irreversible intellectual disability,
      seizures, hyperactive behavior with autistic features, psychiatric symptoms, eczema, musty
      body odor and light pigmentation.

      Newborn screening is performed to detect the disease and initiate treatment before any damage
      is done. The blood sample is usually taken by heel prick, typically performed 2-7 days after
      birth. This test can reveal elevated phenylalanine levels after one or two days of normal
      infant feeding. PKU is commonly included in the newborn screening panel of many countries and
      Egypt , with varied detection techniques. Most babies are screened for PKU soon after birth.

      Treatment is with a diet low in foods that contain phenylalanine and special supplements.
      Babies should use a special formula with a small amount of breast milk. The diet should begin
      as soon as possible after birth and be continued for life. People who are diagnosed early and
      maintain a strict diet can have normal health and a normal life .

      The target of the treatment is to reach optimal health ranges of phenylalanine (or &quot;target
      ranges&quot;) are between 120 and 360 µmol/L or equivalently 2 to 6 mg/dL, and aimed to be
      achieved during at least the first 10 years, to allow the brain to develop normally.

      The dietary restriction in phenylketonuria should be only in protein diet
      (phenylalanine),while fat and carbohydrate diet don't need to be restricted.

      Lifelong treatment will provide the best effect on growth and development, prevents
      neurocognitive impairment and abnormal executive functioning and helps maintaining mental
      health.

      Anthropometric measures are important for evaluating the growth development and nutritional
      status of infants with phenylketonuria.

      The dietary restriction in phenylketonuria should be only in protein diet
      (phenylalanine),while fat and carbohydrate diet don't need to be restricted.

      Lifelong treatment will provide the best effect on growth and development, prevents
      neurocognitive impairment and abnormal executive functioning and helps maintaining mental
      health.

      Anthropometric measures are important for evaluating the growth development and nutritional
      status of infants with phenylketonuria.

      Intelligence and mental development in PKU PKU results, in untreated patients, a profound
      intellectual disability and more subtle cognitive deficits in individuals who were treated
      early and continuously. The assessment of intellectual functioning in PKU has been an
      important target outcome variable since the implementation of neonatal PKU screening programs
      in the 1960s . Research on intellectual functioning in individuals with PKU has played a
      significant role in guiding treatment recommendations and improving outcomes.

      Brumm and Grant conducted a literature review examining the relationship between intellectual
      outcome and treatment parameters including initiation of treatment, duration of treatment,
      and blood phenylalanine (Phe) levels from infancy through adulthood. While current PKU
      treatment practices have eliminated severe neurological and cognitive impairment, evidence
      suggests that intellectual functioning, although typically within the average range when PKU
      is treated early and continuously, may not be maximized under the current definition of
      well-controlled PKU, which is based on blood Phe levels.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">May 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Control</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Cross-Sectional</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Normal growth in early dietary treated patients with Phenylketonuria to assessed by body mass index in kg/m^2</measure>
    <time_frame>one year</time_frame>
    <description>Normal growth in early dietary treated patients with Phenylketonuria to assessed by body mass index in kg/m^2</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Normal growth in Early dietary treated patients with Phenylketonuria to assessed by head circumference in centimeters</measure>
    <time_frame>one year</time_frame>
    <description>Normal growth in Early dietary treated patients with Phenylketonuria to assessed by head circumference in centimeters</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Normal growth in Early dietary treated patients with Phenylketonuria to assessed by abdominal circumference in centimeters</measure>
    <time_frame>one year</time_frame>
    <description>Normal growth in Early dietary treated patients with Phenylketonuria to assessed by abdominal circumference in centimeters</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Mental development in early dietary treated patients with Phenylketonuria to assessed by using Emerging Pattern Of Behavior of infants</measure>
    <time_frame>one year</time_frame>
    <description>Mental development in early dietary treated patients with Phenylketonuria to assessed by using Emerging Pattern Of Behavior of infants</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Comparison between early dietary treated patients with Phenylketonuria with normal matchable infants regarding normal growth and mental development</measure>
    <time_frame>one year</time_frame>
    <description>Comparison between early dietary treated patients with Phenylketonuria with normal matchable infants regarding normal growth and mental development</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Phenylketonurias</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Patients with Phenylketonuria</arm_group_label>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>normal healthy children</arm_group_label>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>phenylalanine restricted diet</intervention_name>
    <description>Infants with hyperphenylalaninemia on special formula and diet</description>
    <arm_group_label>Patients with Phenylketonuria</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>normal healthy children</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Cases:Infants with hyperphenylalaninemia on special formula and diet Controls: normal
        healthy children match with cases in the same social class, age and sex
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Infants with hyperphenylalaninemia on special formula and diet

          2. Infants of both sexes

          3. Age since birth till three years

          4. Type of feeding : diet restriction of phenylalanine

          5. Controls: normal healthy children match with cases in the same social class, age and
             sex

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Age greater than three years

          2. Patients diagnosed with PKU and not regular in feeding for special diet and formula.

          3. PKU patients not diagnosed since birth
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>1 Month</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>3 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Farouk Hassanein</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Assiut University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Monica Dobs</last_name>
    <phone>01220777433</phone>
    <email>monicaibrahim9111@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Shaimaa Khalaf</last_name>
    <phone>01001400503</phone>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <reference>
    <citation>Belanger-Quintana A, Martínez-Pardo M. Physical development in patients with phenylketonuria on dietary treatment: a retrospective study. Mol Genet Metab. 2011 Dec;104(4):480-4. doi: 10.1016/j.ymgme.2011.08.002. Epub 2011 Aug 10.</citation>
    <PMID>21878401</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Blau N. Genetics of Phenylketonuria: Then and Now. Hum Mutat. 2016 Jun;37(6):508-15. doi: 10.1002/humu.22980. Epub 2016 Mar 18. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26919687</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Brumm VL, Grant ML. The role of intelligence in phenylketonuria: a review of research and management. Mol Genet Metab. 2010;99 Suppl 1:S18-21. doi: 10.1016/j.ymgme.2009.10.015. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20123465</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Burgard P. Development of intelligence in early treated phenylketonuria. Eur J Pediatr. 2000 Oct;159 Suppl 2:S74-9. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>11043149</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cleary M, Trefz F, Muntau AC, Feillet F, van Spronsen FJ, Burlina A, Bélanger-Quintana A, Giżewska M, Gasteyger C, Bettiol E, Blau N, MacDonald A. Fluctuations in phenylalanine concentrations in phenylketonuria: a review of possible relationships with outcomes. Mol Genet Metab. 2013 Dec;110(4):418-23. doi: 10.1016/j.ymgme.2013.09.001. Epub 2013 Sep 9. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24090706</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Evans S, Daly A, MacDonald J, Pinto A, MacDonald A. Fifteen years of using a second stage protein substitute for weaning in phenylketonuria: a retrospective study. J Hum Nutr Diet. 2018 Jun;31(3):349-356. doi: 10.1111/jhn.12510. Epub 2017 Sep 21.</citation>
    <PMID>28940742</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Evans S, Daly A, MacDonald J, Preece MA, Santra S, Vijay S, Chakrapani A, MacDonald A. The micronutrient status of patients with phenylketonuria on dietary treatment: an ongoing challenge. Ann Nutr Metab. 2014;65(1):42-8. doi: 10.1159/000363391. Epub 2014 Sep 4.</citation>
    <PMID>25196394</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jani R, Coakley K, Douglas T, Singh R. Protein intake and physical activity are associated with body composition in individuals with phenylalanine hydroxylase deficiency. Mol Genet Metab. 2017 Jun;121(2):104-110. doi: 10.1016/j.ymgme.2017.04.012. Epub 2017 Apr 28.</citation>
    <PMID>28465125</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dokoupil K, Gokmen-Ozel H, Lammardo AM, Motzfeldt K, Robert M, Rocha JC, van Rijn M, Ahring K, Bélanger-Quintana A, MacDonald A. Optimising growth in phenylketonuria: current state of the clinical evidence base. Clin Nutr. 2012 Feb;31(1):16-21. doi: 10.1016/j.clnu.2011.09.001. Epub 2011 Sep 29. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21959353</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>MacDonald A, Gokmen-Ozel H, van Rijn M, Burgard P. The reality of dietary compliance in the management of phenylketonuria. J Inherit Metab Dis. 2010 Dec;33(6):665-70. doi: 10.1007/s10545-010-9073-y. Epub 2010 Apr 7. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20373144</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Meli C, Bianca S. Dietary control of phenylketonuria. Lancet. 2002 Dec 21-28;360(9350):2075-6.</citation>
    <PMID>12504428</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mitchell JJ, Trakadis YJ, Scriver CR. Phenylalanine hydroxylase deficiency. Genet Med. 2011 Aug;13(8):697-707. doi: 10.1097/GIM.0b013e3182141b48. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21555948</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rocha JC, van Rijn M, van Dam E, Ahring K, Bélanger-Quintana A, Dokoupil K, Gokmen Ozel H, Lammardo AM, Robert M, Heidenborg C, MacDonald A. Weight Management in Phenylketonuria: What Should Be Monitored. Ann Nutr Metab. 2016;68(1):60-5. doi: 10.1159/000442304. Epub 2015 Nov 25. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26598928</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 7, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 7, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 10, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 19, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 19, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 23, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Assiut University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Monica Ibrahim</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Phenylketonurias</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

