<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04301466</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>B20020126</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04301466</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Efficacy and Safety of Qi Zhi Tong Luo Capsule in Vascular Cognitive Impairment</brief_title>
  <official_title>Efficacy and Safety of Qi Zhi Tong Luo Capsule in Vascular Cognitive Impairment: a Randomized, Double-blind, Placebo- Controlled, Multicentre Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Dongzhimen Hospital, Beijing</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Shanxi Zhendong Pharmacy Co., Ltd</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Dongzhimen Hospital, Beijing</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Qi Zhi Tong Luo (QZTL) capsule, a traditional Chinese herbal medicine, which was used to
      treat stoke-related symptoms, include trouble speaking, paralysis and trouble walking. This
      study aimed to evaluate the efficacy and safety of QZTL capsule in the treatment of vascular
      cognitive impairment. This study was designed as randomized, double-blind, parallel,
      placebo-controlled, multicentre trial. It consisted of a single-blind run-in period using
      placebo only (2 weeks) and a double-blind treatment phase after randomization (24 weeks), and
      follow-up 12 weeks after withdrawal.The primary efficacy variables included changes from
      baseline in the Clinical Dementia Rating scale-Sum Box (CDR-SB) and the Mini-mental State
      Examination (MMSE) after 24 weeks of treatment. The secondary efficacy measurements include
      the Clock Drawing Test (CDT), Hopkins Verbal Learning Test (HVLT) and Ability of Daily Living
      (ADL).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 16, 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 30, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 30, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2/Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes of Clinical Dementia Rating-Sum of the Boxes scale (CDR-SB) from baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>week 0, 12, 24,36</time_frame>
    <description>CDR-SB is a standard for disease grading in clinical studies of dementia and is used for overall endpoint assessment in clinical trials. The CDR-SB scores from 0-18 points, and a higher score indicates higher impairment.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes of Mini-mental State Examination(MMSE from baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>week 0, 12, 24,36</time_frame>
    <description>MMSE, 0-30 points, a lower score means severe global cognition impairment, which is used for overall endpoint assessment in clinical trials.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes of Hopkins Verbal Learning Test from baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>week 0, 12, 24,36</time_frame>
    <description>0-48 points, higher score indicates better memory function</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes of Clock drawing test from baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>week 0, 12, 24,36</time_frame>
    <description>0-10 points, with higher scores indicating better visuo-spatial function</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes of Ability of daily living scale from baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>week 0, 12, 24,36</time_frame>
    <description>0-56 points, higher score means severe ability daily living function</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">362</enrollment>
  <condition>Vascular Cognitive Impairment</condition>
  <condition>Qi Zhi Tong Luo Capsule</condition>
  <condition>Randomized Controlled Trial</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Qi Zhi Tong Luo group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients were receiveed Qi Zhi Tong Luo Capsule 4 capsules, 2 times per day for 24 weeks. Each capsule was weighted 0.5g. Qi Zhi Tong Luo capsule (batch number: 20140805) were produced by Shanxi Zhendong Pharmaceutical Co., Ltd.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients were allocated to placebo, 4 capsules, 2 times per day for 24 weeks. Placebo (batch number: 20140805) were produced by Shanxi Zhendong Pharmaceutical Co., Ltd.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Qi Zhi Tong Luo capsule</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients were receiveed Qi Zhi Tong Luo Capsule 4 capsules, 2 times per day for 24 weeks. QZTL capsule, a traditional Chinese medicine. Each capsule was weighted 0.5g.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Qi Zhi Tong Luo group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebos</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients were allocated to placebo, 4 capsules, 2 times per day for 24 weeks.To preserve blinding, the placebo had an identical taste and appearance to the experimental drugs. Placebo (batch number: 20140805) were produced by Shanxi Zhendong Pharmaceutical Co., Ltd.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Decline in cognitive function from a prior baseline and impairment in at least 1
             cognitive domain, the domain of cognition including executive function(Trail Making
             Test-part A(Chinese version,150s)&gt;98s)), memory function decline (Hopkins verbal
             learning test free recall(36 points) &lt;18.5 points), language function decline (Boston
             naming test (Chinese version 30 items)&lt;22 points), and visuo-spatial functions (Clock
             drawing test(10 points)&lt;8.5 points) ;

          2. Evidence of cerebrovascular disease relies on structural magnetic resonance imaging
             (MRI) , history and clinical feature. The neuroimaging should include at least one of
             following: a) a single large vessel infarction which was sufficient to cause cognition
             decline; b) infarction at a single strategic place was sufficient to cause severe
             cognition decline( the thalamus, angular gyrus, and basal ganglia, including the
             caudate nucleus and globus pallidus); c) multiple lacunar infarctions (≥3) outside the
             brainstem, or 2 lacunar infarcts at key locations, a single lacunar focus with
             extensive white matter lesions(WMLs) ; d) extensive and integrated WMLs(Fazekas
             scale≥3 points) ; e) intracranial hemorrhage in key parts, or ≥2 intracranial
             hemorrhages; f) combination of above.

          3. There was a clear temporal relationship between a vascular event and onset of
             cognitive deficit, cognitive impairment should appear within 3 months after a stroke,
             or abrupt deterioration, or stepwise progression of deficits; or cognitive impairment
             may be related to vascular factors, the Hachinski Ischemia scale (HIS) score ≥7;

          4. And the patients must have adequate vision and hearing to participate in study
             assessments;

          5. Have a stable caregiver;

          6. Can read simple articles and write simple sentences;

          7. Informed consent, signed informed consent by legal guardian.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Evidence of other reasons caused cognitive impairment, like Alzheimer disease,
             frontotemporal dementia, Parkinson disease dementia, dementia with Lewy bodies,
             Huntington disease, etc;

          2. Subdural hematoma, traffic hydrocephalus, brain tumor, thyroid disease, vitamin
             deficiency, or other diseases which can lead to cognitive impairment;

          3. Major depression (Hamilton depression rating scale [HAMD] ≥17) or other mental
             disorders ;

          4. History of drug or alcohol abuse in the past 6 month;

          5. History of epilepsy;

          6. Patients with myasthenia gravis;

          7. Subject cannot complete related test due to severe neurologic deficits;

          8. Other uncontrolled chronic illnesses, like severe cardiovascular disease (severe
             arrhythmia, myocardial infarction within 3 months, severe heart failure(New York Heart
             Association Functional Classification III and IV,); uncontrolled hypertension,
             diabetes);

          9. Severe liver or kidney dysfunction (alanine aminotransferase or aspartate transaminase
             was more than 1.5 times the upper limit of normal, or serum creatinine was more than
             the upper limit of normal);

         10. Concomitant use of the anticonvulsants, antipsychotics, cholinomimetic drugs,
             anticholinergic agents, anti-Parkinson drugs, cholinesterase inhibitors, memantine,
             nootropic drug, nimodipine, anticholinergic or anticholinergic antidepressant or
             anxiolytic and other cognition enhancers within 1 month;

         11. Severe asthma and chronic obstructive pulmonary disease;

         12. Patients with severe indigestion, gastrointestinal obstruction, gastric or duodenal
             ulcers;

         13. Patients with glaucoma;

         14. History of hypersensitivity to the treatment drugs;

         15. Participate in other clinical study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>45 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Dongzhimen Hospital ,Beijing University of Chinese Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Beijing</city>
        <state>Beijing</state>
        <zip>100700</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 6, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 6, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 10, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 9, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 9, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 11, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Dongzhimen Hospital, Beijing</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Jinzhou Tian</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Vice president</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cognitive Dysfunction</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

