<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04300426</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2019-004400-35</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04300426</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluate Safety and Efficacy of Anaerobic Cultivated Human Intestinal Microbiome Transplantation in Systemic Sclerosis (ReSScue) Transplantation in Systemic Sclerosis</brief_title>
  <acronym>ReSScue</acronym>
  <official_title>Aiming to Reduce Disease-related Gastro-intestinal Symptoms in Patients With Systemic Sclerosis by Repeat Intestinal Infusions of Anaerobic Cultivated Human Intestinal Microbiome (ACHIM); a Phase II, Randomized, Double-blinded Placebo-controlled 12 Week Study Followed by a 14 Week Blinded Extension With Open Label Oral ACHIM Capsules</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Oslo University Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>South-Eastern Norway Regional Health Authority</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Oslo University Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study evaluates the effect of intestinal microbiota therapy on gastro-intestinal
      symptoms in patients with systemic sclerosis (SSc). This is a mulicenter randomized
      controlled trial conducted at university hospitals in Oslo, Tromsø, Bergen and Trondheim in
      Norway. Half of the patients will receive active substance (intestinal microbiota cultured in
      the lab - &quot;ACHIM&quot;) in the small intestine twice by gastroduodenoscopy, the other half will
      receive placebo. The primary outcome will be measured on week 12 by patient reported outcome
      measures. There will be a 14-week extension where all participants will receive capsules with
      the active substance. The blind from the first intervention will not be opened before the
      open-label intervention with capsules is completed.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">April 20, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 1, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 17, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>1:1 randomization and doble-blind administration of active substance / placebo by endoscopy with primary outcome at week 12. A second 14-wekk period without placebo (ie all receiving active substance) where blinding from the first intervention is maintained.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>Masking will apply for the whole duration of study (12 + 14 weeks), although second period (14-week period) is open-label.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>• ACHIM compared to placebo on lower GIT symptoms</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline to week 12</time_frame>
    <description>mean of UCLA Scleroderma Clinical Trial Consortium Gastrointestinal Tract (UCLA SCTC GIT) score items diarrhea and bloating</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>• Assess safety and tolerability of intestinal ACHIM infusions in participants with SSc</measure>
    <time_frame>• during the entire 26 week study period</time_frame>
    <description>• Registration of number of adverse events as defined and specified in the protocol</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>• ACHIM compared to placebo on overall GIT symptoms</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, week 6 and week 12.</time_frame>
    <description>total UCLA GIT score</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>• ACHIM compared to placebo on fecal soilage episodes</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline to week 12</time_frame>
    <description>• Fecal incontinence quality of life scale (FIQLS) Norwegian version</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>• ACHIM compared to placebo on overall fecal, microbiome composition</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline to weeks 2, 6 and 12</time_frame>
    <description>fecal microbiome composition measured by 16sRNA based methods</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>• ACHIM compared to placebo on the saliva microbiome</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline to week 12</time_frame>
    <description>saliva, skin and urine microbiome measured by 16sRNA based methods</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>• ACHIM compared to placebo on the skin microbiome</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline to week 12</time_frame>
    <description>saliva, skin and urine microbiome measured by 16sRNA based methods</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>• ACHIM compared to placebo on the urine microbiome</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline to week 12</time_frame>
    <description>saliva, skin and urine microbiome measured by 16sRNA based methods</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>• ACHIM compared to placebo on immunglobulin bound fraction of the overall fecal microbiome</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline to weeks 2, 6 and 12</time_frame>
    <description>immunglobulin bound fraction of the overall fecal microbiome sorted by flow-cytometry subjected to 16sRNA based methods</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>• ACHIM compared to placebo on changes in gastrointestinal transit time in a subset of patients</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline to weeks 12</time_frame>
    <description>gastrointestinal transit time evaluated by SmartPill technology along with registration of stool frequency and consistency by Bristol Stool Scale.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>• ACHIM compared to placebo on changes in peripheral blood B cell receptor repertoire</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline to weeks 6 and 12</time_frame>
    <description>peripheral blood B cell receptor repertoire as evaluated by single cell B cell receptor sequencing.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>• ACHIM compared to placebo on changes in mucosal immune parameters</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, weeks 2 and 12</time_frame>
    <description>adaptive immune cell receptor repertoire as evaluated by single cell receptor sequencing in samples prepared from duodenal biopsies</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>• ACHIM compared to placebo on changes in skin stiffness in a subset of participants</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline to week 12</time_frame>
    <description>elastography</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>• ACHIM compared to placebo on changes in skin thickness in a subset of participants</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline to week 12</time_frame>
    <description>ultrasonographic skin thickness</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>• Health-related Quality of Life Assessment</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline to week 12</time_frame>
    <description>EQ-5d</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>• Estimate effects of oral ACHIM capsules on lower GIT symptoms in patients who received intestinal infusions of ACHIM at baseline and week 2</measure>
    <time_frame>• Baseline to week 26</time_frame>
    <description>mean of UCLA GIT score items diarrhea and bloating</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>• Estimate effects of oral ACHIM capsules on lower GIT symptoms in patients who received intestinal infusions of placebo at baseline and week 2</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to week 26</time_frame>
    <description>mean of UCLA GIT score items diarrhea and bloating</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>• Assess safety of oral ACHIM capsules in participants with SSc</measure>
    <time_frame>• during the entire 26 week study period</time_frame>
    <description>• Registration of number of adverse events as defined and specified in the protocol physical examination, vital signs, clinical laboratory testing and electrocardiogram</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>• Estimate effects of oral ACHIM capsules on overall fecal microbiome composition in patients who received intestinal infusions of ACHIM at baseline and week 2</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline to week 26</time_frame>
    <description>overall fecal microbiome composition measured by 16sRNA based methods</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>• Estimate effects of oral ACHIM capsules on overall fecal microbiome composition in patients who received intestinal infusions of placebo at baseline and week 2</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to week 26</time_frame>
    <description>overall fecal microbiome composition measured by 16sRNA based methods</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>• Estimate effects of oral ACHIM capsules on the saliva, skin and urine microbiome from week 12 to week 26</measure>
    <time_frame>week 12 to week 26</time_frame>
    <description>saliva, skin and urine microbiome measured by 16sRNA based methods</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>• Estimate effects of oral ACHIM capsules on peripheral blood B cell receptor repertoire in patients who received intestinal infusions of placebo at baseline and week 2</measure>
    <time_frame>week 12 to week 26</time_frame>
    <description>peripheral blood B cell receptor repertoire as evaluated by single cell B cell receptor sequencing</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>• Characterize upper GI symptoms and look for mucosal inflammation</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 12 to week 26</time_frame>
    <description>• Plot association of subitem reflux in UCLA GIT score in period 2 with number of inflammatory cells per high power microscope field in biopsy taken from oesophagus at week 26.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>• Characterize upper GI symptoms and look for mucosal antibody deposits</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 12 to week 26</time_frame>
    <description>• Plot association of subitem reflux in UCLA GIT score in period 2 with intensity of immundeposits of antinuclear antibodies in biopsy taken from oesophagus at week 26.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>• Estimate effects of ACHIM compared to placebo on changes from in mucosal immune parameters</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline to week 12 to week 26</time_frame>
    <description>adaptive immune cell receptor repertoire as evaluated by single cell receptor sequencing in samples prepared from duodenal biopsies</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>• Health-related Quality of Life Assessment</measure>
    <time_frame>week 12 to week 26</time_frame>
    <description>EQ-5d</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">70</enrollment>
  <condition>Systemic Sclerosis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>ACHIM by gastroduodenoscopy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Intestinal microbiota (acronym ACHIM - anaerobically cultured human intestinal microbiota) will be administered by gastroduodenoscope twice (given at baseline and study-week 2). Each with volume 30 ml, containing approximately 10^9 bacteria / ml.
Primary outcome measured at week 12. Hereafter a 14 week period 2 starts. Administration of ACHIM capsules from week 14 to week 26. Each capsule contain 0,5 ml ACHIM. First dose will be 5 capsules taken once daily, the following dose will be 2 capsules once daily.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo by gastroduodenoscopy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>ACHIM culture media (no bacteria) will be administered by gastroduodenoscope twice (given at baseline and study-week 2). Each with volume 30 ml.
Primary outcome measured at week 12. Hereafter a 14 week period 2 starts. Administration of ACHIM capsules from week 14 to week 26. Each capsule contain 0,5 ml ACHIM. First dose will be 5 capsules taken once daily, the following dose will be 2 capsules once daily.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>&quot;ACHIM&quot; as solute (10^9 intestinal microbes/ml) or as capsules</intervention_name>
    <description>Intesinal microbiota originally derived from one healthy subject are translocated to another human being. It has not been clarified if this intervention should be cathegorized as a drug or as a transplant. This intervention is applied for and pending decision by the Norwegion medicinal regulatory authorities. The trial will only be initiated if approved by the Norwegian medicinal regulatory authorities.</description>
    <arm_group_label>ACHIM by gastroduodenoscopy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo by gastroduodenoscopy</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Fecal microbiota transplantation</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Age

          1. Participant must be 18 to 85 years of age inclusive, at the time of signing the
             informed consent.

             Type of Participant and Disease Characteristics

          2. Participants must have been clinically diagnosed with SSc by a rheumatologist having
             experience with the disease.

          3. Participants must have disease characteristics that fulfill the 2013 ACR/EULAR
             classification criteria for SSc.

          4. Participants must be able to understand and follow trial procedures including
             completion of questionnaires regarding Patient Reported Outcome measures, such as the
             Norwegian version of the UCLA GIT V2.0 score.

          5. Participants must have moderate to severe SSc-related lower GI symptoms at time of
             inclusion, as defined by UCLA GIT score values of ≥1.01 for bloating and/or ≥0.50 for
             diarrhea at the screening visit.

             Sex

          6. Male and female Informed Consent

          7. Capable of giving signed informed consent as described in Appendix 1 which includes
             compliance with the requirements and restrictions listed in the informed consent form
             (ICF) and in this protocol.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Medical Conditions

               1. Cardiovascular diseases, any of the following

                    1. Severe hypertension, uncontrolled under treatment (≥160/100 mmHg), within 6
                       month of Visit 1

                    2. Myocardial infarction within 6 months of Visit 1

                    3. Unstable cardiac angina within 6 months of Visit 1

               2. Lung disease with impaired respiratory function, any of the following

                    1. Forced Vital Capacity (FVC) &lt; 50% of expected reference value within 12
                       month of Visit 1

                    2. Diffusing lung capacity for carbon monoxide (DLCO) &lt; 40% of expected
                       reference value within 12 month of Visit 1

                    3. LTOT or lung-tx

               3. Significant pulmonary hypertension, any of the following

                    1. Previous clinical or echocardiographic evidence of significant right heart
                       failure

                    2. History of right heart catheterisation showing a cardiac index ≤ 2 l/min/m²

               4. History of thrombotic event (including stroke and transient ischemic attack)
                  within 12 months of Visit 1

               5. Severe anemia with Hb &lt; 8.0 g/l within 4 weeks prior to Visit 1. Repeat testing
                  of Hb is allowed.

               6. Bleeding risk, any of the following

                    1. History of hemorrhagic central nervous system (CNS) event within 12 months
                       of Visit 1.

                    2. Known genetic predisposition to bleeding

                    3. Platelet counts &lt; 50 x 109/l

               7. Chronic liver disease or gastro-intestinal condition, any of the following

                    1. Primary biliary cholangitis

                    2. Primary sclerosing cholangitis

                    3. Decompensated chronic liver disease

                    4. Inflammatory bowel disease

                    5. Celiac disease treated for less than 12 months.

               8. Gastro-intestinal surgery performed within the within 12 months of Visit 1

               9. Hepatic dysfunction, as defined as AST, ALT or bilirubin levels &gt;3 times the
                  Upper limit of normal range (x ULN) within 4 weeks prior to Visit 1. Repeat
                  testing of AST, ALT and bilirubin are allowed in participants with no prior
                  history of hepatic dysfunction.

              10. Chronic renal insufficiency, with estimated Glomerular Filtration Rate (eGFR) &lt;
                  30.

              11. Active digital ulcers within 4 weeks of Visit 1.

              12. Anaphylactic food allergy.

              13. Eating disorder diagnosed by a physician

              14. Other diseases or conditions that may interfere with testing procedures (for
                  example inability to conduct gastroduodenoscopy) or in the judgment of the
                  Investigator may interfere with trial participation or may put the patient at
                  risk when participating in this trial (for example severe GI symptoms due to
                  other diseases than SSc).

                  Prior/Concomitant Therapy

              15. Any antibiotic therapy within 3 months of Visit 1

              16. Prednisone &gt;10 mg/day or equivalent within 4 weeks prior to Visit 1

              17. Cyclophosphamide or rituximab treatment within 6 months prior to Visit 1

              18. Unstable background monotherapy with any of the following therapeutics;
                  mycophenolate mofetil/sodium, methotrexate, azathioprine, tocilizumab, abatacept,
                  leflunomide, tacrolimus, tofacitinib and cyclosporine A. Participants have to be
                  on stable monotherapy with any of these medications for at least 6 months prior
                  to visit 1

              19. Combined therapy of two or more of the following therapeutics: mycophenolate
                  mofetil/sodium, methotrexate, azathioprine, tocilizumab, abatacept, leflunomide,
                  tacrolimus, tofacitinib and ciclosporine A within at least 8 weeks prior to visit
                  1.

              20. Need for full-dose therapeutic anticoagulation (e.g. vitamin K antagonists,
                  direct thrombin inhibitors or heparin)

              21. Previous hematopoietic stem cell transplantation (HSCT) within 12 months of Visit
                  1, or HSCT planned within 12 months after Visit 1.

              22. Other investigational therapy received within 1 month or 6 half-lives (whichever
                  was greater) prior to screening visit.

                  Prior/Concurrent Clinical Study Experience

              23. Prior participation in FMT study in the last 12 months. Diagnostic assessments

              24. Abnormal coagulation parameters as defined as International normalised ratio
                  (INR) &gt;2, prolongation of prothrombin time (PT) and partial thromboplastin time
                  (PTT) by &gt;1.5 x ULN at Visit 1 Other Exclusions

              25. Women who are pregnant, nursing, or who plan to become pregnant while in the
                  trial. (Women of child bearing potential should be tested with Hcg (urine or
                  serum). Woman of child bearing potential if not using highly efficient
                  contraception.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>85 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Vikas Kumar Sarna, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Oslo University Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Anna-Maria Hoffmann-Vold, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Oslo University Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Maylen Carstens, Study nurse</last_name>
    <phone>91502770</phone>
    <phone_ext>47</phone_ext>
    <email>maylno@ous-hf.no</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Vikas Kumar Sarna, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>91502770</phone>
    <phone_ext>47</phone_ext>
    <email>vikas.sarna@ous-hf.no</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kowal-Bielecka O, Fransen J, Avouac J, Becker M, Kulak A, Allanore Y, Distler O, Clements P, Cutolo M, Czirjak L, Damjanov N, Del Galdo F, Denton CP, Distler JHW, Foeldvari I, Figelstone K, Frerix M, Furst DE, Guiducci S, Hunzelmann N, Khanna D, Matucci-Cerinic M, Herrick AL, van den Hoogen F, van Laar JM, Riemekasten G, Silver R, Smith V, Sulli A, Tarner I, Tyndall A, Welling J, Wigley F, Valentini G, Walker UA, Zulian F, Müller-Ladner U; EUSTAR Coauthors. Update of EULAR recommendations for the treatment of systemic sclerosis. Ann Rheum Dis. 2017 Aug;76(8):1327-1339. doi: 10.1136/annrheumdis-2016-209909. Epub 2016 Nov 9.</citation>
    <PMID>27941129</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hansi N, Thoua N, Carulli M, Chakravarty K, Lal S, Smyth A, Herrick A, Ogunbiyi O, Shaffer J, Mclaughlin J, Denton C, Ong V, Emmanuel AV, Murray CD. Consensus best practice pathway of the UK scleroderma study group: gastrointestinal manifestations of systemic sclerosis. Clin Exp Rheumatol. 2014 Nov-Dec;32(6 Suppl 86):S-214-21. Epub 2014 Nov 5. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25372804</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Volkmann ER, Hoffmann-Vold AM, Chang YL, Jacobs JP, Tillisch K, Mayer EA, Clements PJ, Hov JR, Kummen M, Midtvedt Ø, Lagishetty V, Chang L, Labus JS, Molberg Ø, Braun J. Systemic sclerosis is associated with specific alterations in gastrointestinal microbiota in two independent cohorts. BMJ Open Gastroenterol. 2017 Apr 1;4(1):e000134. doi: 10.1136/bmjgast-2017-000134. eCollection 2017.</citation>
    <PMID>28761687</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>van Nood E, Vrieze A, Nieuwdorp M, Fuentes S, Zoetendal EG, de Vos WM, Visser CE, Kuijper EJ, Bartelsman JF, Tijssen JG, Speelman P, Dijkgraaf MG, Keller JJ. Duodenal infusion of donor feces for recurrent Clostridium difficile. N Engl J Med. 2013 Jan 31;368(5):407-15. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa1205037. Epub 2013 Jan 16.</citation>
    <PMID>23323867</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Staley C, Kaiser T, Vaughn BP, Graiziger C, Hamilton MJ, Kabage AJ, Khoruts A, Sadowsky MJ. Durable Long-Term Bacterial Engraftment following Encapsulated Fecal Microbiota Transplantation To Treat Clostridium difficile Infection. mBio. 2019 Jul 23;10(4). pii: e01586-19. doi: 10.1128/mBio.01586-19.</citation>
    <PMID>31337728</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Juul FE, Garborg K, Bretthauer M, Skudal H, Øines MN, Wiig H, Rose Ø, Seip B, Lamont JT, Midtvedt T, Valeur J, Kalager M, Holme Ø, Helsingen L, Løberg M, Adami HO. Fecal Microbiota Transplantation for Primary Clostridium difficile Infection. N Engl J Med. 2018 Jun 28;378(26):2535-2536. doi: 10.1056/NEJMc1803103. Epub 2018 Jun 2.</citation>
    <PMID>29860912</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Khanna D, Hays RD, Maranian P, Seibold JR, Impens A, Mayes MD, Clements PJ, Getzug T, Fathi N, Bechtel A, Furst DE. Reliability and validity of the University of California, Los Angeles Scleroderma Clinical Trial Consortium Gastrointestinal Tract Instrument. Arthritis Rheum. 2009 Sep 15;61(9):1257-63. doi: 10.1002/art.24730.</citation>
    <PMID>19714600</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Khanna D, Furst DE, Maranian P, Seibold JR, Impens A, Mayes MD, Clements PJ, Getzug T, Hays RD. Minimally important differences of the UCLA Scleroderma Clinical Trial Consortium Gastrointestinal Tract Instrument. J Rheumatol. 2011 Sep;38(9):1920-4. doi: 10.3899/jrheum.110225. Epub 2011 Jul 1.</citation>
    <PMID>21724699</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dehli T, Martinussen M, Mevik K, Stordahl A, Sahlin Y, Lindsetmo RO, Vonen B. Translation and validation of the Norwegian version of the fecal incontinence quality-of-life scale. Scand J Surg. 2011;100(3):190-5.</citation>
    <PMID>22108748</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yang Y, Qiu L, Wang L, Xiang X, Tang Y, Li H, Yan F. Quantitative Assessment of Skin Stiffness Using Ultrasound Shear Wave Elastography in Systemic Sclerosis. Ultrasound Med Biol. 2019 Apr;45(4):902-912. doi: 10.1016/j.ultrasmedbio.2018.11.015. Epub 2019 Jan 18.</citation>
    <PMID>30665723</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Benno P, Norin E, Midtvedt T, Hellström PM. Therapeutic potential of an anaerobic cultured human intestinal microbiota, ACHIM, for treatment of IBS. Best Pract Res Clin Gastroenterol. 2019 Jun - Aug;40-41:101607. doi: 10.1016/j.bpg.2019.03.003. Epub 2019 Apr 29. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>31594647</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jorup-Rönström C, Håkanson A, Sandell S, Edvinsson O, Midtvedt T, Persson AK, Norin E. Fecal transplant against relapsing Clostridium difficile-associated diarrhea in 32 patients. Scand J Gastroenterol. 2012 May;47(5):548-52. doi: 10.3109/00365521.2012.672587. Epub 2012 Apr 2.</citation>
    <PMID>22468996</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 25, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 6, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 9, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 6, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 6, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 9, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Oslo University Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Vikas Kumar Sarna</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>PI at main study site - coordinating center</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Scleroderma, Systemic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Scleroderma, Diffuse</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sclerosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>The investigators plan to publish the protocol and statistical analysis plan separately. The IPD will be published according to relevant legislation and as required by publishing authority.</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Statistical Analysis Plan (SAP)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>Not known yet.</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>Not known yet.</ipd_access_criteria>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

