<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04304573</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>KBCSM13</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04304573</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Is Correcting Total Serum Calcium Levels Important After Thyroidectomy</brief_title>
  <official_title>Is Correcting Total Serum Calcium Levels for Serum Albumin Necessary in Assessing Symptomatic Hypocalcemia After Total Thyroidectomy: a Prospective Cohort Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University Hospital &quot;Sestre Milosrdnice&quot;</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University Hospital &quot;Sestre Milosrdnice&quot;</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study is designed as a prospective non-randomized longitudinal single- center cohort
      study to evaluate the importance of correcting total serum calcium levels. It will enroll
      around 100 patients undergoing total thyroidectomy with data being collected from March 2020
      up to August 2020. The aim of this study is to determine whether total serum calcium level
      should be corrected for serum albumin in assessing symptomatic hypocalcemia after total
      thyroidectomy and which variable (total serum calcium, ionized calcium, corrected serum
      calcium for albumin with Payne's formula or early PTH) is the most valuable predictor of
      symptomatic hypocalcemia after total thyroidectomy.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study is designed as a prospective non-randomized longitudinal single- center cohort
      study to evaluate the importance of correcting total serum calcium levels. It will enroll
      around 100 patients undergoing total thyroidectomy with data being collected from March 2020
      up to August 2020.The patients will be eligible if they undergo total thyroidectomy
      regardless of the surgical indication, if complete serum PTH and calcium data are available
      through the first five postoperative days and if they sign an informed consent form. Patients
      with incomplete data, preoperative pathological calcium or PTH levels, or suffering from
      conditions affecting calcium metabolism and parathyroid function will be excluded from the
      study.

      Demographic and clinical data including age, sex, preoperative and postoperative laboratory
      values (total serum calcium, ionized calcium, corrected total serum calcium for serum albumin
      and PTH), neck dissection procedures, and postoperative calcium supplement therapy will be
      noted.

      Primary outcome measures are presence of hypocalcemia on the first and fifth postoperative
      day. Secondary outcome measures are the need for calcium supplement therapy during the first
      five postoperative days, amount of medication given and correlation between presence of
      symptoms and low values of corrected total serum calcium levels. Preoperative blood samples
      for serum PTH and calcium measurements will be obtained after hospital admission.
      Postoperative serum PTH will be sampled 1 hour after surgery and at 7 am on the firstand
      fifth postoperative day. Serum calcium sampling will be performed daily if a patient has
      hypocalcemia detected on the first postoperative day. Hypocalcemia is defined as serum
      calcium levels &lt; 2.00 mmol/L regardless of clinical symptoms present. Normal PTH range is
      defined by the Department of Laboratory Diagnostics reference range - from 1.6 to 6.9 pmol/L.
      The recovery of parathyroid function is defined as the return of serum PTH and serum calcium
      to normal values, requiring no further calcium or vitamin D supplementation. If the patient
      does not have laboratory or clinical signs of hypocalcemia, calcium supplement therapy will
      not be administered. Supplement therapy will be administered in patients with laboratory
      findings confirming hypocalcemia. Supplement therapy consists of either peroral elemental
      calcium (calcium carbonate, 1-gram unit) or calcitriol (0.5 microgram unit) or both. If
      postoperative calcium and PTH are normal and there are no symptoms of discomfort, the patient
      will be discharged on the first or second postoperative day and serum PTH and calcium
      sampling will be performed on an outpatient basis. If the patient did not receive treatment
      during hospitalization, no supplements will be prescribed after hospital discharge.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">June 9, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 9, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 9, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Corrected total serum calcium value</measure>
    <time_frame>5 days</time_frame>
    <description>Statistically significant correlation between low value of corrected total serum calcium level for albumin and hypocalcemia symptoms</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Administration of postoperative calcium supplement therapy</measure>
    <time_frame>5 days</time_frame>
    <description>Whether or not, and the amount of postoperative calcium supplement therapy needed in case of hypocalcemia.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Hypocalcemia</condition>
  <condition>Thyroid</condition>
  <condition>Parathyroid Dysfunction</condition>
  <condition>Calcium Disorder</condition>
  <condition>Hormone Disturbance</condition>
  <condition>Postoperative Complications</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Patients with hypocalcemia symptoms and low serum calcium</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients with postoperative hypocalcemia defined as serum calcium levels &lt; 2.00 mmol/L. Patients may have low or normal PTH range (defined by the Department of Laboratory Diagnostics reference range from 1.6 to 6.9 pmol/L)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Patients with hypocalcemia symptoms and normal serum calcium</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients with hypocalcemia symptoms but without postoperative hypocalcemia defined as serum calcium levels &gt; 2.00 mmol/L. Patients may have low or normal PTH range (defined by the Department of Laboratory Diagnostics reference range from 1.6 to 6.9 pmol/L)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Total serum calcium blood test</intervention_name>
    <description>Total serum calcium measurements will be done on the first postoperative day. Also ionized calcium, corrected total serum calcium for serum albumin with Payne's formula and PTH will be monitored.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Patients with hypocalcemia symptoms and low serum calcium</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Patients with hypocalcemia symptoms and normal serum calcium</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients undergoing total thyroidectomy regardless of the surgical indication.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  The patients were eligible if they underwent total thyroidectomy regardless of the
             surgical indication, if complete serum PTH and calcium data were available through the
             first five postoperative days and if they signed an informed consent form.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with incomplete data, preoperative pathological calcium or PTH levels, or
             suffering from conditions affecting calcium metabolism and parathyroid function were
             excluded from the study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ivan Rašić, MD,PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Department of Otorhinolaryngology and Head and Neck Surgery</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Andro Košec, MD,PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+385989817156</phone>
    <email>andro.kosec@yahoo.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Ana Gašić, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+385996879905</phone>
    <email>anagasic4@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Hospital Center Sestre milosrdnice</name>
      <address>
        <city>Zagreb</city>
        <zip>10000</zip>
        <country>Croatia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Andro Košec, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>+385989817156</phone>
      <email>andro.kosec@yahoo.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Ana Gašić, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+385996879905</phone>
      <email>anagasic4@gmail.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Croatia</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 9, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 9, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 11, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 26, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 26, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 30, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Andro Košec, MD, PhD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Consultant Otorhinolaryngologist and Head and Neck Surgeon</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>hypocalcemia</keyword>
  <keyword>total thyroidectomy</keyword>
  <keyword>Payne's formula</keyword>
  <keyword>ionized calcium</keyword>
  <keyword>parathyroid hormone</keyword>
  <keyword>predictive factor</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hypocalcemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Parathyroid Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Postoperative Complications</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Endocrine System Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Calcium</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

