<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04309461</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>47917</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04309461</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Make Better Choices 2 for Rural Appalachians</brief_title>
  <acronym>MBC2</acronym>
  <official_title>Implementing the Make Better Choices 2 mHealth Energy Balance Intervention for Rural Appalachians</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Nancy Schoenberg</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Kentucky</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The program consists of four interconnected components: (1) app, (2) accelerometer, (3)
      health coaching, and (4) behavioral incentives to increase food and vegetable intake, reduce
      saturated fat intake, increase physical activity, and decrease sedentary screen time among
      adults Appalachia Kentuckians.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Rural Appalachians suffer among the worst health profiles in the US including elevated rates
      of cardiovascular disease. Although a healthy diet and active lifestyle can reduce mortality
      and morbidity, only 12% of rural Appalachian Kentuckians consume the recommended daily intake
      for fruits and vegetables and nearly 35% indicate no physical activity. Personal technology
      is increasingly common in rural Appalachia, presenting a new opportunity to prevent and
      manage chronic disease. Most (68%) Appalachian Kentuckians have smart phones and reliable
      internet access (78%). We propose the first (to our knowledge) adapted evidence-based,
      multicomponent mHealth (mobile health) intervention program among rural Appalachians. The
      Make Better Choices 2 (MBC2) intervention has produced significant and sustained improvements
      in diet and physical activity, using personalized health coaching, an app, accelerometer, and
      financial incentives. Because of sparse local resources, rural Appalachian residents could
      greatly benefit from access to appropriate virtual resources through health coaching and
      mHealth.

      In this study, 350 participants will be randomized to receive either the adapted MBC2 or a
      stress management program. The primary outcome, diet and activity improvement, is a composite
      change score relative to baseline scores for fruit and vegetable (F/V) intake, fat, physical
      activity, and sedentary leisure screen time.

      Adapted MBC2 intervention content:

      The program consists of four interconnected components: (1) app, (2) accelerometer, (3)
      health coaching, and (4) behavioral incentives. These components encompass behavioral and
      implementation principles—effectiveness, scalability, and synergy and correspond to the Goal
      Systems Theory, enhanced by sociocultural and environmental considerations.

        1. App: As demonstrated in recent research, increasing personal technology use among rural
           populations provides a new opportunity for health equity. Apps and accelerometers enable
           connectivity, accountability, and personalization between participants and their
           coaches. This app includes a decision support system and display that helps participants
           monitor fruit &amp; vegetable (F/V) intake, moderate-vigorous physical activity, and
           sedentary screen time relative to their daily target. This daily diet and activity data
           entry is a core component of the MBC2 intervention rather than an outcome or assessment.
           The app also transmits this information to a web-based dashboard accessed by coaches,
           who use it to tailor telephone counseling.

           During the in-person training, participants will be given materials to help in portion
           size estimation, plus reminders that entries are time and date-stamped to encourage
           prompt entry. The app involves automatic wireless data uploading, which enables
           detection of entry error or non-adherence to protocols. Additional procedures to support
           adherence to personal goals include: a) visual thermometers to provide feedback about
           intake and expenditure relative to targets; b) ability to access smart phone diet and
           activity databases to support decision-making about diet and activity choices; c) visual
           feedback about goal progress throughout the day to guide self-regulation; and d) use of
           stepped goals to facilitate incremental attainment of targets. Diet and activity data to
           assess intervention effectiveness will additionally be collected at the assessment
           periods via REDCap (baseline and months 3 and 9).

        2. Accelerometer: Activity monitors also enhance accountability. Our prior work shows that
           Appalachian residents have high levels of adherence and satisfaction with
           accelerometers. For the proposed study, participants will be given a gold standard
           accelerometer, the triaxial Actigraph GT9X. They will wear it on the non-dominant wrist
           daily during the intervention. The accelerometer collects data on three axes at a 100 Hz
           sampling rate, which will be sent via API (application program interface) to display
           minutes of MVPA (moderate-to-vigorous physical activity) on the study smart phone
           application as feedback to the participant.

        3. Telephone coaching has demonstrated scalability (particularly in more isolated rural
           locations), effectiveness, and greater reach than in-person counseling. In addition to
           these benefits, during preparatory focus groups, Appalachians indicated that they prefer
           telephone coaching over group meetings (due to lack of privacy, time-consuming trips) or
           home visits (too intrusive). Despite these benefits, telephone coaching is associated
           with more modest behavioral changes that can undermine longer-term behavior change.

        4. Behavioral incentives: An incentive is provided weekly to participants in both
           conditions if their behavioral average meets goal criterion for the correct use of the
           app (for data collection) and adherence to behavioral targets (F/V consumption, physical
           activity and sedentary activity or stress management).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">August 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 31, 2025</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in diet and activity</measure>
    <time_frame>9 months (at baseline, 3 months and 9 months)</time_frame>
    <description>A single composite MBC (Make Better Choices) score of four behaviors (fruit and vegetable intake, fat intake, physical activity, and sedentary screen time) will be used to assess change across multiple diet and activity behaviors. Fruit and vegetable intake, saturated fat intake, and screen time will be measured from smart phone data. Time spent in moderate/vigorous physical activity will be transmitted from the accelerometer to the app. The MBC score, expressing each participant's overall change across the multiple diet and activity behaviors relative to baseline is calculated as the mean of four behavioral individual Z scores at each time point. Scores have an unlimited range; higher values represent greater healthy lifestyle improvement relative to the overall baseline distribution.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Health-Related Quality of Life</measure>
    <time_frame>9 months (at baseline, 3 months and 9 months)</time_frame>
    <description>The SF-36 (Short Form-36) Health Outcomes Survey will be used to assess patient-reported health. The SF-36 consists of 8 scaled scores, which are weighted sums of the questions in their section. Scores range from 0-100; lower scores indicate more disability.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Blood Pressure</measure>
    <time_frame>9 months (at baseline, 3 months and 9 months)</time_frame>
    <description>Sitting total (diastolic and systolic) pressure will be measured according to the CARDIA protocol.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Weight</measure>
    <time_frame>9 months (at baseline, 3 months and 9 months)</time_frame>
    <description>Weight will be measured without shoes, wearing a standard hospital gown on a calibrated beam balance scale.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Height</measure>
    <time_frame>9 months (at baseline, 3 months and 9 months)</time_frame>
    <description>Height will be measured using a stadiometer.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Body Mass Index (BMI)</measure>
    <time_frame>9 months (at baseline, 3 months and 9 months)</time_frame>
    <description>Body Mass Index (BMI) will be calculated as weight in pounds/ (height in inches)^2) x 704.5 and the difference will be calculated.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Waist Circumference</measure>
    <time_frame>9 months (at baseline, 3 months and 9 months)</time_frame>
    <description>Waist circumference will be assessed twice during expiration, taking the average for analyses, by positioning an anthropometric tape midway between the palpated iliac crest and the palpated lowest rib margin in the mid-axillary lines.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Change in total cholesterol</measure>
    <time_frame>9 months (at baseline, 3 months and 9 months)</time_frame>
    <description>A12 hour fasting blood sample will be collected for a lipid panel and the change in total cholesterol will be calculated.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Change in triglycerides</measure>
    <time_frame>9 months (at baseline, 3 months and 9 months)</time_frame>
    <description>A12 hour fasting blood sample will be collected for a lipid panel and the change in triglycerides will be calculated.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Change in HDL-C</measure>
    <time_frame>9 months (at baseline, 3 months and 9 months)</time_frame>
    <description>A12 hour fasting blood sample will be collected for a lipid panel and the change in HDL-C will be calculated.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Change in LDL-C</measure>
    <time_frame>9 months (at baseline, 3 months and 9 months)</time_frame>
    <description>A12 hour fasting blood sample will be collected for a lipid panel and the change in LDL-C will be calculated.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Change in plasma glucose</measure>
    <time_frame>9 months (at baseline, 3 months and 9 months)</time_frame>
    <description>A12 hour fasting blood sample will be collected and the change in glucose will be calculated.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">350</enrollment>
  <condition>Health Behavior</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Stress Management Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The Stress Management Program will utilize a smart phone app, accelerometers, telephone coaching, and behavioral incentives to target stress, relaxation, and sleep. Participants will wear accelerometers, log hours slept, enter real-time information about their relaxation exercises and stress, and monitor 3 goal thermometers (sleep, relaxation, stress) to meet behavioral targets. The Stress Management Program, including the use of the app and assessments, is identical to the Adapted MBC2 program, with the exception of the content.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Adapted MBC2 Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The Adapted MBC2 Program will utilize a smart phone app, accelerometers, telephone coaching, and behavioral incentives to target fruit and vegetable intake, dietary fat intake, physical activity, and high sedentary leisure screen time. Participants will wear accelerometers, log hours slept, enter real-time information about their relaxation exercises and stress, and monitor goal thermometers to meet targets.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Stress Management Control</intervention_name>
    <description>The Stress Management Program will utilize a smart phone app, accelerometers, telephone coaching, and behavioral incentives to target stress, relaxation, and sleep. Participants will wear accelerometers, log hours slept, enter real-time information about their relaxation exercises and stress, and monitor 3 goal thermometers (sleep, relaxation, stress) to meet behavioral targets. The Stress Management Program, including the use of the app and assessments, is identical to the Adapted MBC2 program, with the exception of the content.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Stress Management Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Adapted MBC2 Program</intervention_name>
    <description>The Adapted MBC2 Program will utilize a smart phone app, accelerometers, telephone coaching, and behavioral incentives to target fruit and vegetable intake, dietary fat intake, physical activity, and high sedentary leisure screen time. Participants will wear accelerometers, log hours slept, enter real-time information about their relaxation exercises and stress, and monitor goal thermometers to meet targets.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Adapted MBC2 Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  adults residing in Appalachian Kentucky

          -  willingness to use smart phone to record and modify diet and activity

          -  willingness to wear an accelerometer

          -  consume &lt;4.5 cups fruit/vegetables daily

          -  consume &gt;8% daily calories from fat

          -  engage in &lt;150 minutes of moderate-intensity physical activity weekly

          -  spend &gt;90 minutes daily on non-work, non-education-related sedentary recreational use
             of screen time.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  unstable medical conditions

          -  cognitive impairment

          -  hospitalization for psychiatric disorder within the last 5 years

          -  active suicidal ideation

          -  substance use disorder other than nicotine dependence

          -  at risk for adverse cardiovascular events with moderate-intensity activity

          -  taking weight loss medication

          -  trying to get pregnant, pregnant or lactating

          -  active eating disorders

          -  using mobility assistive devices

          -  inability to read study materials
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>100 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Susan C Westneat, MA</last_name>
    <phone>859 323 8282</phone>
    <email>swest1@email.uky.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <verification_date>May 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 12, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 12, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 16, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 14, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 14, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 15, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Kentucky</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Nancy Schoenberg</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>app</keyword>
  <keyword>coaching</keyword>
  <keyword>Appalachian</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

