<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02276443</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2014-0185</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2015-00191</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>2014-0185</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02276443</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Molecular Testing and Imaging in Improving Response in Patients With Stage I-III Triple-Negative Breast Cancer Receiving Chemotherapy MDACC Breast Moonshot Initiative</brief_title>
  <official_title>ARTEMIS: A Robust TNBC Evaluation Framework to Improve Survival</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This clinical trial assesses whether a newly designed algorithm which looks at the genomic
      signature of each patient's tumor to predict their sensitivity to standard of care treatment
      verses being placed on a personally designed treatment trial can improve the responses in
      patients with newly diagnosed triple-negative breast cancer (TNBC). Testing the primary tumor
      biopsy for certain proteins and monitoring the lymphocyte infiltration into the tumors may
      help doctors determine the sub-type of TNBC, and direct treatments that may work well. It is
      not yet known whether assigning treatment based on the patient's tumor classification will
      improve how well the tumor responds.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PRIMARY OBJECTIVE:

      I. To conduct a prospective single arm, non-randomized trial to determine the impact of
      implementation of a research platform that includes diagnostic imaging to assess response to
      the initial phase of neoadjuvant chemotherapy combined with subtyping of TNBC in order to
      select the appropriate targeted therapy trial to complete neoadjuvant chemotherapy in
      patients found to have chemo-insensitive disease by imaging.

      SECONDARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. Measured as defined by Standardized Definitions for Efficacy End Points (STEEP) criteria
      using the following prioritization: distant recurrence free interval (DRFI), recurrence free
      survival (RFS), distant relapse-free survival (DRFS), overall survival (OS), invasive disease
      free survival (IDFS), disease free survival including ductal carcinoma in situ (DFS-DCIS).

      II. Evaluate the rates of enrollment into clinical trials for patients identified as having
      chemotherapy insensitive disease.

      III. Compare the rates of enrollment into therapeutic clinical trials between the two arms of
      the trial, i.e. those who do, versus do not, receive the results of molecular genomic
      prediction of chemotherapy response.

      IV. Evaluate the frequency of pathologic response rates (pCR, RCB I-III residual disease) in
      patients identified as chemotherapy sensitive versus insensitive.

      V. Compare the pathologic response rates of tumors between the two arms of the trial for the
      patients whose tumor was molecularly classified as chemotherapy- sensitive or
      chemotherapy-insensitive, and in whose neoadjuvant chemotherapy (NACT) followed the
      recommendation of the trial schema.

      VI. Determine the estimates of DRFI, RFS, DRFS, IDFS and DFS-DCIS at 3 years, and OS at 5
      years in all patients.

      VII. Compare the estimates between the two arms of the trial for the patients whose tumor was
      molecularly classified as chemotherapy-sensitive or chemotherapy-insensitive, and for whose
      NACT followed the recommendation of the trial schema.

      VIII. Determine the pathologic response based on molecular characterization. IX. Determine
      the estimates of DRFI, RFS, DRFS, IDFS and DFS-DCIS at 3 years, and OS at 5 years.

      X. Subset analyses of pathologic response and 3-year DRFI, RFS, DRFS, IDFS and DFS-DCIS.

      XI. Estimate for the subsets where gene expression levels of receptor status (estrogen
      receptor [ER], progesterone receptor [PR] and HER2) were, or were not concordant with TNBC
      status as defined by routine diagnostic tests (immunohistochemistry and/or fluorescent in
      situ hybridization.

      XII. Compare the results of pathologic node-negative status (sentinel and/or non-sentinel
      nodes) after neoadjuvant chemotherapy according to a genomic predictor of nodal response to
      NACT, in subsets defined by pre-treatment clinical nodal status.

      EXPLORATORY OBJECTIVES:

      I. Future re-analysis of residual samples using a customized genomic diagnostic platform
      (integrated &quot;prospective-retrospective&quot; biomarker analysis) to predict chemotherapy
      sensitivity.

      II. Generation and subsequent molecular characterization of patient derived xenograph (PDX)
      models.

      III. Clinical diagnostic development studies using residual samples (fresh and/or
      formalin-fixed) within the Clinical Laboratory Improvement Amendments (CLIA)-compliant
      Molecular Diagnostics Laboratory and patient derived xenographs (PDX), to formally evaluate
      the clinical validity and utility of future clinical genomic diagnostic tests that would
      predict both response and survival from the treatments used in this clinical trial
      (correlative &quot;retrospective-prospective&quot; biomarker analyses).

      IV. Correlative science studies to identify molecular therapeutic targets for
      treatment-insensitive TNBC using residual samples and PDX models.

      V. Correlation of changes in diagnostic imaging to determine potential predictions of
      treatment responses.

      VI. Determine polymerase chain reaction (pCR) rates in a cohort of patients who undergo
      surgical resection after achieving complete radiological response after 4 cycles of adjuvant
      chemotherapy (AC).

      OUTLINE:

      Patients undergo baseline molecular and immunohistochemistry (IHC) evaluation of their tumor
      biopsy, and receive the results. Patients then receive standard anthracycline-based
      chemotherapy and undergo standard ultrasound at baseline, after 2 courses, and after 4
      courses of treatment. Patients and physicians are notified of the results of the molecular
      evaluation. Patients may then choose to continue with standard taxane +/- platinum-based
      chemotherapy or participate in an experimental clinical trial designed to match the molecular
      profile and triple-negative subtype. Patients with tumors predicted to be insensitive to
      chemotherapy are advised to participate in a clinical trial treating their tumor subtype.

      After completion of study treatment, patients are followed up for up to 5 years.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 9, 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 30, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 30, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Response rate</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <description>A one-sided z-test will be used to compare the response rates of the treatment and control arms. The study will have 80% power to detect an increase in the response rate of 14.2 percentage points assuming a control arm response rate of 50% at the 0.05 significance level allowing for two interim tests for both futility and superiority.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">1000</enrollment>
  <condition>Invasive Breast Carcinoma</condition>
  <condition>Stage I Breast Cancer AJCC v7</condition>
  <condition>Stage IA Breast Cancer AJCC v7</condition>
  <condition>Stage IB Breast Cancer AJCC v7</condition>
  <condition>Stage II Breast Cancer AJCC v6 and v7</condition>
  <condition>Stage IIA Breast Cancer AJCC v6 and v7</condition>
  <condition>Stage IIB Breast Cancer AJCC v6 and v7</condition>
  <condition>Stage III Breast Cancer AJCC v7</condition>
  <condition>Stage IIIA Breast Cancer AJCC v7</condition>
  <condition>Stage IIIB Breast Cancer AJCC v7</condition>
  <condition>Stage IIIC Breast Cancer AJCC v7</condition>
  <condition>Triple-Negative Breast Carcinoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (predictive results given)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients undergo baseline molecular and IHC evaluation of their tumor biopsy, and receive the results. Patients then receive standard anthracycline-based chemotherapy and undergo standard ultrasound at baseline, after 2 courses, and after 4 courses of treatment. Patients and physicians are notified of the results of the molecular evaluation. Patients may then choose to continue with standard taxane +/- platinum-based chemotherapy or participate in an experimental clinical trial designed to match the molecular profile and triple-negative subtype. Patients with tumors predicted to be insensitive to chemotherapy are advised to participate in a clinical trial treating their tumor subtype.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Chemotherapy</intervention_name>
    <description>Undergo standard chemotherapy</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (predictive results given)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Chemo</other_name>
    <other_name>Chemotherapy (NOS)</other_name>
    <other_name>Chemotherapy, Cancer, General</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Laboratory Biomarker Analysis</intervention_name>
    <description>Correlative studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (predictive results given)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Lymph Node Biopsy</intervention_name>
    <description>Undergo baseline lymph node evaluation</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (predictive results given)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Biopsy of Lymph Node</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ultrasonography</intervention_name>
    <description>Undergo standard ultrasound</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (predictive results given)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>2-Dimensional Grayscale Ultrasound Imaging</other_name>
    <other_name>2-Dimensional Ultrasound Imaging</other_name>
    <other_name>2D-US</other_name>
    <other_name>Ultrasound</other_name>
    <other_name>Ultrasound Imaging</other_name>
    <other_name>Ultrasound Test</other_name>
    <other_name>Ultrasound, Medical</other_name>
    <other_name>US</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  The patient can undergo biopsy or surgery of a primary tumor site for suspected or
             proven invasive breast cancer of clinical stage I to III and are planned to receive
             neoadjuvant chemotherapy with anthracycline/taxane based regimes

          -  The patient was proven to have TNBC, defined from standard pathologic assays as
             negative for ER and PR (&lt; 10% tumor staining) and negative for HER2
             (immunohistochemistry [IHC] score &lt; 3, gene copy number not amplified)

          -  Primary tumor sample was collected before NACT begins

          -  Patients must have left ventricular ejection fraction (LVEF) &gt; 50% by multi gated
             acquisition scan (MUGA) or echocardiogram (ECHO) within 12 weeks prior to starting
             adriamycin

          -  Leukocytes &gt; 3,000/mcL

          -  Absolute neutrophil count &gt; 1,500/mcL

          -  Platelets &gt; 100,000/mcL

          -  Total bilirubin within normal institutional limits

          -  Aspartate aminotransferase (AST) (serum glutamic oxaloacetic transaminase
             [SGOT])/alanine aminotransferase (ALT) (serum glutamate pyruvate transaminase [SGPT])
             &lt; 2.5 x institutional upper limit of normal

          -  Creatinine 1.5X the upper limits of normal OR creatinine clearance &gt; 60 mL/min/1.73
             m^2 for patients with creatinine levels above institutional normal

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  The patient has diagnosis of stage IV disease or is found to have stage IV disease
             prior to start of NACT

          -  Prior history of invasive cancer within 5 years of study entry or history of
             metastatic cancer; exceptions include non-metastatic, curatively treated basal and
             squamous cell carcinoma of the skin

          -  Prior excisional biopsy of the primary invasive breast cancer

          -  Patients with hematomas or biopsy site changes that limit response assessment of the
             primary tumor by diagnostic imaging

          -  Patients not eligible for chemotherapy with taxane and/or anthracycline based
             chemotherapy regimens

          -  Prior therapy with anthracyclines

          -  Grade II or higher neuropathy

          -  Patients with Zubrod performance status of &gt; 2

          -  Patients with history of serious cardiac events defined as:

               -  Patients with a history of New York Heart Association class 3 or 4 heart failure,
                  or history of myocardial infarction, unstable angina or cerebrovascular accident
                  (CVA) within 6 months of protocol registration

               -  Patients who have history of PR prolongation (grade 2 or higher) or
                  atrioventricular (AV) block
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Stacy L Moulder</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Stacy Moulder</last_name>
    <phone>713-792-2817</phone>
    <email>smoulder@mdanderson.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>MD Anderson in The Woodlands</name>
      <address>
        <city>Conroe</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77384</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Stacy L. Moulder</last_name>
      <phone>713-792-2817</phone>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Stacy L. Moulder</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>M D Anderson Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Stacy L. Moulder</last_name>
      <phone>713-792-2817</phone>
      <email>smoulder@mdanderson.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Stacy L. Moulder</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>MD Anderson West Houston</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77079</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Rachel L. Theriault</last_name>
      <email>rltheriault1@mdanderson.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Rachel L. Theriault</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>MD Anderson League City</name>
      <address>
        <city>League City</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77573</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sausan Z. Abouharb</last_name>
      <phone>713-563-0670</phone>
      <email>sabouharb@mdanderson.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Sausan Z. Abouharb</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>MD Anderson in Sugar Land</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sugar Land</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77478</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sadia Saleem</last_name>
      <email>ssaleem@mdanderson.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Sadia Saleem</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.mdanderson.org</url>
    <description>MD Anderson Cancer Center Website</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>December 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 21, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 24, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">October 28, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 21, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 21, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 23, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

