<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03675386</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>18-5207</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03675386</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Reducing Opioid Use for Chronic Pain Patients Following Surgery</brief_title>
  <acronym>RECOUP</acronym>
  <official_title>Ontario Transitional Pain and Opioid Safety Program: Improving Pain and Opioid Practices for Complex Chronic Pain Patients Following Surgery</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University Health Network, Toronto</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University Health Network, Toronto</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Patients with chronic pain are often prescribed long-term opioid therapy, despite the serious
      risks and growing concerns related to opioid use. The Toronto General Hospital has created
      the world's first multidisciplinary perioperative Transitional Pain Service Program (TPSP)
      aimed at reducing the incidence and severity of chronic post-surgical pain. The TPSP
      incorporates a variety of mechanisms and interventions to help patients manage pain and to
      wean off opioids. The approach consists of: pain education, Acceptance and Commitment Therapy
      (ACT), and an e-mobile self- management tool to help patients manage chronic pain more
      effectively. With the TPSP team, the investigators hope to continually assist patients to
      achieve a balance between the benefits and potential harms of opioid use to promote long-term
      health and well-being.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The proposed research program encompasses several study designs to evaluate the effectiveness
      and potential implementation of the TPSP across Ontario. The investigators will use three
      approaches to create a comprehensive evidence-base that can be used to guide future policy
      and programs related to the management of surgical patients with complex pain and chronic
      opioid use. In the first phase, a multicenter randomized controlled trial will be conducted
      in 5 hospital sites to evaluate the effectiveness and potential implementation of TPSP across
      Ontario. The aim is to recruit a total of 210 patients who are currently taking opioids and
      also undergoing a surgical intervention (e.g., spinal fusion, hip or knee arthroplasty, major
      cardiac surgery, hysterectomy, colectomy, cholecystectomy, major vascular surgery, hernia
      repairs, bariatric surgery, and thyroidectomies). The randomized controlled trial will
      determine the effectiveness of the TPSP at weaning patients completely off opioids while
      still managing pain after one year. Secondly, an economic and healthcare utilization analysis
      of the program via linkage to provincial administrative databases will be carried out to
      understand the impact the TPSP program has on the healthcare system as a whole. Lastly, a
      qualitative study will be conducted on both the treatment and control groups. The
      investigators hope to capture further insight to understand patients and providers
      experiences of the TPSP intervention.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 24, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Health Services Research</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Portion of patients weaned off opioids</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Opioid weaning measured by number of patients successfully weaned off opioids comparing the intervention arm versus control arm</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pain interference</measure>
    <time_frame>One year</time_frame>
    <description>Brief Pain Inventory Scale is a measure that assess the severity of pain and the impact of pain on daily functions. Measurement of this scale is rated on a 0-10 numerical-rating-scale ( 0= No Pain to 10= Pain as bad as you can imagine or 0= Does not interfere to 10= Completely interferes). The BPI assess pain at its worst, least, average, and now. Pain Severity Score is calculated by adding the scores for questions 2, 3, 4 and 5 and then dividing by 4. This gives a severity score out of 10. Pain Interference Score is calculated by adding the scores for questions 8a, b, c, d, e, f and g and then dividing by 7. This gives an interference score out of 10.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">210</enrollment>
  <condition>Chronic Pain</condition>
  <condition>Opioid Use</condition>
  <condition>Postoperative Pain</condition>
  <condition>Opioid Dependence</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients in the control group will receive standard care, which involves standard postoperative follow-up with their surgeon/primary care provider. Patients will also be sent with a link for an online multimedia tool during each follow-up time point that will provide information and education regarding non-pharmacologic techniques for managing pain. At the end, all patients in the control arm will be invited to join the TPSP after one year of follow-up if they are still taking opioids.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Interventional Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients in the interventional group will be given a Transitional Pain Service follow-up appointment at the following postoperative time points (2 to 6 visits for the first two months, and then 1 to 2 visits on a monthly basis until one year). At each visit, patients will meet with the clinical psychologist and chronic pain specialist. Patients in the intervention group will have access to the Manage My Pain (MMP) App. which allows people living with pain to quickly and easily track their pain and function on a daily basis on their smartphones or a browser on their desktop or mobile device. One-page clinical reports will capture the changes in patients' outcome data between clinical visits over the course in time.Clinic visits can be offered in person at the hospital or over telehealth (video conference) based on the patient's preference and clinician's judgment for telehealth suitability.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Interventional Group</intervention_name>
    <description>The Transitional Pain Service Program enables targeted, mechanism-based, treatment innovations aimed at reducing the incidence and severity of chronic post-surgical pain, disability and enabling safe opioid prescribing/ weaning after major surgery. The investigator's TPSP intervention uses a variety of methods to support patients to manage pain and wean off opioids. This includes physician-guided opioid and non-opioid pharmacotherapy and tapering, and clinical psychology services specializing in pain education, Acceptance &amp; Commitment Therapy (ACT) and e-mobile self-management tools.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Interventional Group</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Transitional Pain Service Program</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Control Intervention</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients in the control group will receive standard care, which involves standard postoperative follow-up with their surgeon/primary care provider. Patients will also be sent with a link for an online multimedia tool during each follow-up time point that will provide information and education regarding non-pharmacologic techniques for managing pain. At the end, all patients in the control arm will be invited to join the TPSP after one year of follow-up if they are still taking opioids.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  ≥ 18 years of age

          -  Taking 20 -- 200 mg of preoperative oral morphine equivalents daily

          -  Any type of surgical procedure, with the exception of those with palliative intent or
             organ transplantation

          -  Able to read and understand English as posed on the questionnaire surveys prior to
             informed consent

          -  Must be taking opioids for at least one month prior to their operation

          -  Must have a personal email address for the set-up of the Manage My Pain (MMP) App or
             online multimedia tool

        Exclusion Criteria:

        • Subjects who are undergoing palliative care or procedures, organ transplantation, or
        prescribed with Methadone/Buprenorphine will be excluded from the trial
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Karim Ladha, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Toronto General Hospital, University Health Network</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Hance Clarke, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Toronto General Hospital, University Health Network</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Elaheh Adly, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Hamilton Health Sciences Centre</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Paul Tumber, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University Health Network, Toronto</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Anton Marinov, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Rouge Valley Medical Centre</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Melanie Toman, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Thunder Bay Reginal Health Sciences Centre</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Karim Ladha, MD</last_name>
    <phone>416-719-0030</phone>
    <email>Karim.Ladha@uhn.ca</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Hance Clarke, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>416-340-4800</phone>
    <phone_ext>6649</phone_ext>
    <email>Hance.Clarke@uhn.ca</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Toronto General Hospital- University Health Network</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toronto</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>M5G 2N2</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Karim Ladha, MD</last_name>
      <phone>(416) 719-0030</phone>
      <email>karim.ladha@uhn.ca</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Hance Clarke, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>(416) 340-4800</phone>
      <email>hance.clarke@uhn.ca</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Elaheh Adly, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ramesh Zacharias, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Anton Marinov, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Pawan Basati, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Paul Tumber, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Melanie Toman, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Angst MS, Clark JD. Opioid-induced hyperalgesia: a qualitative systematic review. Anesthesiology. 2006 Mar;104(3):570-87. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>16508405</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fletcher D, Martinez V. Opioid-induced hyperalgesia in patients after surgery: a systematic review and a meta-analysis. Br J Anaesth. 2014 Jun;112(6):991-1004. doi: 10.1093/bja/aeu137. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24829420</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Savage SR. Long-term opioid therapy: assessment of consequences and risks. J Pain Symptom Manage. 1996 May;11(5):274-86. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>8636626</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chou R, Turner JA, Devine EB, Hansen RN, Sullivan SD, Blazina I, Dana T, Bougatsos C, Deyo RA. The effectiveness and risks of long-term opioid therapy for chronic pain: a systematic review for a National Institutes of Health Pathways to Prevention Workshop. Ann Intern Med. 2015 Feb 17;162(4):276-86. doi: 10.7326/M14-2559. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25581257</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Katz J, Seltzer Z. Transition from acute to chronic postsurgical pain: risk factors and protective factors. Expert Rev Neurother. 2009 May;9(5):723-44. doi: 10.1586/ern.09.20. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19402781</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Clarke H, Soneji N, Ko DT, Yun L, Wijeysundera DN. Rates and risk factors for prolonged opioid use after major surgery: population based cohort study. BMJ. 2014 Feb 11;348:g1251. doi: 10.1136/bmj.g1251.</citation>
    <PMID>24519537</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sun EC, Dixit A, Humphreys K, Darnall BD, Baker LC, Mackey S. Association between concurrent use of prescription opioids and benzodiazepines and overdose: retrospective analysis. BMJ. 2017 Mar 14;356:j760. doi: 10.1136/bmj.j760.</citation>
    <PMID>28292769</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Katz J, Weinrib A, Fashler SR, Katznelzon R, Shah BR, Ladak SS, Jiang J, Li Q, McMillan K, Santa Mina D, Wentlandt K, McRae K, Tamir D, Lyn S, de Perrot M, Rao V, Grant D, Roche-Nagle G, Cleary SP, Hofer SO, Gilbert R, Wijeysundera D, Ritvo P, Janmohamed T, O'Leary G, Clarke H. The Toronto General Hospital Transitional Pain Service: development and implementation of a multidisciplinary program to prevent chronic postsurgical pain. J Pain Res. 2015 Oct 12;8:695-702. doi: 10.2147/JPR.S91924. eCollection 2015.</citation>
    <PMID>26508886</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Weinrib AZ, Burns LC, Mu A, Azam MA, Ladak SS, McRae K, Katznelson R, Azargive S, Tran C, Katz J, Clarke H. A case report on the treatment of complex chronic pain and opioid dependence by a multidisciplinary transitional pain service using the ACT Matrix and buprenorphine/naloxone. J Pain Res. 2017 Mar 27;10:747-755. doi: 10.2147/JPR.S124566. eCollection 2017.</citation>
    <PMID>28392713</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tan G, Jensen MP, Thornby JI, Shanti BF. Validation of the Brief Pain Inventory for chronic nonmalignant pain. J Pain. 2004 Mar;5(2):133-7.</citation>
    <PMID>15042521</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rampakakis E, Ste-Marie PA, Sampalis JS, Karellis A, Shir Y, Fitzcharles MA. Real-life assessment of the validity of patient global impression of change in fibromyalgia. RMD Open. 2015 Sep 14;1(1):e000146. doi: 10.1136/rmdopen-2015-000146. eCollection 2015. Erratum in: RMD Open. 2015;1(1):e000146corr1.</citation>
    <PMID>26535150</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Portenoy R. Development and testing of a neuropathic pain screening questionnaire: ID Pain. Curr Med Res Opin. 2006 Aug;22(8):1555-65.</citation>
    <PMID>16870080</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dworkin RH, Turk DC, Wyrwich KW, Beaton D, Cleeland CS, Farrar JT, Haythornthwaite JA, Jensen MP, Kerns RD, Ader DN, Brandenburg N, Burke LB, Cella D, Chandler J, Cowan P, Dimitrova R, Dionne R, Hertz S, Jadad AR, Katz NP, Kehlet H, Kramer LD, Manning DC, McCormick C, McDermott MP, McQuay HJ, Patel S, Porter L, Quessy S, Rappaport BA, Rauschkolb C, Revicki DA, Rothman M, Schmader KE, Stacey BR, Stauffer JW, von Stein T, White RE, Witter J, Zavisic S. Interpreting the clinical importance of treatment outcomes in chronic pain clinical trials: IMMPACT recommendations. J Pain. 2008 Feb;9(2):105-21. Epub 2007 Dec 11.</citation>
    <PMID>18055266</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Löwe B, Wahl I, Rose M, Spitzer C, Glaesmer H, Wingenfeld K, Schneider A, Brähler E. A 4-item measure of depression and anxiety: validation and standardization of the Patient Health Questionnaire-4 (PHQ-4) in the general population. J Affect Disord. 2010 Apr;122(1-2):86-95. doi: 10.1016/j.jad.2009.06.019. Epub 2009 Jul 17.</citation>
    <PMID>19616305</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Darnall BD, Sturgeon JA, Cook KF, Taub CJ, Roy A, Burns JW, Sullivan M, Mackey SC. Development and Validation of a Daily Pain Catastrophizing Scale. J Pain. 2017 Sep;18(9):1139-1149. doi: 10.1016/j.jpain.2017.05.003. Epub 2017 May 19.</citation>
    <PMID>28528981</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wicksell RK, Renöfält J, Olsson GL, Bond FW, Melin L. Avoidance and cognitive fusion--central components in pain related disability? Development and preliminary validation of the Psychological Inflexibility in Pain Scale (PIPS). Eur J Pain. 2008 May;12(4):491-500. Epub 2007 Sep 20.</citation>
    <PMID>17884643</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chapman SL, Jamison RN, Sanders SH. Treatment Helpfulness Questionnaire: a measure of patient satisfaction with treatment modalities provided in chronic pain management programs. Pain. 1996 Dec;68(2-3):349-61.</citation>
    <PMID>9121824</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 11, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 17, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 18, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 15, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 15, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 17, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Chronic Pain</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Opioid-Related Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

