<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03670264</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>17-014620</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>UL1TR001878</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03670264</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>BE Smokefree: Behavioral Economics Incentives to Engage Adolescents in Smoking Cessation</brief_title>
  <official_title>BE Smokefree: Behavioral Economics Incentives to Engage Adolescents in Smoking Cessation</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Children's Hospital of Philadelphia</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Pennsylvania</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Center for Advancing Translational Science (NCATS)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Children's Hospital of Philadelphia</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      More than 90% of adult smokers initiate tobacco use before age 18, making prevention and
      treatment of adolescent smoking a critical health priority. Behavioral economic interventions
      utilizing financial incentives can promote smoking cessation in adult populations. No studies
      have evaluated financial incentives among adolescents to promote engagement in effective
      tobacco cessation programs through primary care settings. The goal of this study is to to
      compare, through a pilot, randomized controlled trial, an intervention incentivizing contact
      with a tobacco cessation program (the Quitline), an intervention incentivizing quitting, or
      no financial incentive intervention on adolescent smoker enrollment and depth of engagement
      in the tobacco cessation program.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Context:

      Cigarette smoking remains a leading preventable cause of death in the United States (U.S.)
      with substantial morbidity, mortality, and financial costs each year. More than 90% of adult
      smokers initiate tobacco use before age 18, making prevention and treatment of adolescent
      tobacco use a critical health priority. Further, e-cigarettes are now the most common tobacco
      product used by teenagers, and adolescent use of e-cigarettes is strongly associated with
      transition to cigarette use. Behavioral economic interventions utilizing financial incentives
      can promote smoking cessation in adult populations. No studies have evaluated financial
      incentives among adolescents to promote engagement in effective tobacco cessation programs
      through primary care settings.

      Objectives:

      Primary Objective: To compare, through a pilot, randomized controlled trial, an intervention
      incentivizing contact with the Quitline, an intervention incentivizing quitting, or no
      financial incentive intervention on adolescent enrollment and depth of engagement in a
      tobacco cessation program (Free Smoker Quitline).

      Secondary Objective: To compare cotinine-confirmed 2-month quit rates across the 3 groups,
      among users who report abstinence.

      Study Design:

      This is a randomized controlled trial of a Quitline incentive versus tobacco cessation
      incentive versus no financial incentive on adolescent engagement with a tobacco cessation
      program.

      Setting/Participants:

      Setting: Primary care sites within the Children's Hospital of Philadelphia (CHOP's) Pediatric
      Research Consortium along with other non-clinical community settings.

      60 adolescent tobacco users will be recruited. Eligibility criteria include adolescents (aged
      14-17 years), who speak English, screen positive for tobacco use during their routine well
      child or acute visit, are interested in quitting, and have a smart phone.

      Study Interventions and Measures:

      Adolescents will be randomized to 1 of 3 financial incentive groups: (1) Quitline Incentive:
      the payment structure emphasizes engaging with the Quitline, with an additional smaller
      payment for tobacco cessation; (2) Tobacco Cessation Incentive: the payment structure
      emphasizes quitting regardless of engagement with the quitline (though the quitline will be
      presented as a helpful tool); and (3) no financial incentive. The Quitline is funded by the
      Pennsylvania Department of Health and staffed by trained cessation counselors available 24
      hours a day, 7 days a week.

      Outcomes Measures: Objective 1: The main outcome of interest is adolescent completion of the
      tobacco cessation program, defined as the proportion of tobacco users identified in the
      clinic that enroll, use, and complete the Quitline program compared across the 3 groups.
      Objective 2: The secondary outcome is to confirm abstinence, via salivary cotinine
      concentration of &lt;30 ng per milliliter at 10 weeks after the start of the study.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 21, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Randomized controlled trial</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Program Completion</measure>
    <time_frame>10 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Adolescent completion of the tobacco cessation program, defined as the proportion of tobacco users identified in the clinic that enroll, use, and complete the Quitline program compared across the 3 groups</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Confirmation of tobacco abstinence</measure>
    <time_frame>10 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Confirmation of abstinence will be measured by assessing if participants salivary cotinine concentration are &lt;30 ng per milliliter</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Smoking Cessation</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Quitline Incentive</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The incentive structure emphasizes engaging with the Quitline Delivered Treatment, with an additional smaller payment for tobacco cessation. Each adolescent can receive compensation for enrolling in the Quitline, for maintaining involvement in the Quitline program (per call for up to 5 calls), and, for those reporting abstinence, for submitting the cotinine swab and for confirmed quitting (negative salivary cotinine). Study procedures, payments and reminders are managed through the Way to Health (WTH) platform.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Tobacco Cessation Incentive</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The incentive structure emphasizes quitting regardless of engagement with the Quitline Delivered Treatment (though the Quitline will be presented as a helpful tool). Each adolescent will receive compensation for enrolling in the Quitline and, for those reporting abstinence, compensation for submitting the cotinine swab and for confirmed quitting (negative salivary cotinine). Study procedures, payments and reminders are managed through the WTH platform.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>No Financial Incentive</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>No financial incentive to engage in Quitline Delivered Treatment or report abstinence. Study procedures and reminders are managed through the WTH platform.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Quitline Incentive</intervention_name>
    <description>The incentive structure emphasizes engaging with the quitline, with an additional smaller payment for tobacco cessation. Each adolescent can receive compensation for enrolling in the quitline, for maintaining involvement in the quitline program (compensation per call for up to 5 calls), and, for those reporting abstinence, for submitting the cotinine swab and for confirmed quitting (negative cotinine swab).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Quitline Incentive</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Tobacco Cessation Incentive</intervention_name>
    <description>The incentive payment structure emphasizes quitting regardless of engagement with the quitline (though the quitline will be presented as a helpful tool). Each adolescent will receive compensation for enrolling in the Quitline and, for those reporting abstinence, for submitting the cotinine swab and for confirmed quitting (negative cotinine swab).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Tobacco Cessation Incentive</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Way to Health (WTH) Platform</intervention_name>
    <description>The WTH platform is a web-based platform that sends reminder text messages to participants regarding study procedures and has has secure financial tracking and processing systems to manage participant payments, including the ability to track earnings and pay participants via a non-integrated payment system.</description>
    <arm_group_label>No Financial Incentive</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Quitline Incentive</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Tobacco Cessation Incentive</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Quitline Delivered Treatment</intervention_name>
    <description>The quitline provides tobacco cessation treatment to individuals who enroll in treatment. This treatment includes 5 proactive counseling calls, each designed to help develop problem-solving and coping skills, secure social support, and plan for long-term abstinence. Participants can also call an 800 telephone number as needed for additional support between proactive calls.</description>
    <arm_group_label>No Financial Incentive</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Quitline Incentive</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Tobacco Cessation Incentive</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Adolescents (aged 14-17 years), male or female, who speak English, screen positive for
             tobacco use (defined as having smoked cigarette(s) and/or used an e-cigarette product
             on at least 1 day during the 30 days before the clinical encounter) during their
             routine well child or acute visit, are interested in quitting, have a smart phone, and
             provide assent to participate.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects that do not meet all of the inclusion criteria will not be enrolled.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>14 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>17 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Brian Jenssen, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Children's Hospital of Philadelphia</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Brian Jenssen, MD</last_name>
    <phone>2155544390</phone>
    <email>jenssenb@email.chop.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Children's Hospital of Philadelphia, Care Network</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19146</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Brian Jenssen, MD</last_name>
      <phone>215-554-4390</phone>
      <email>jenssenb@email.chop.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 12, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 12, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 13, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 8, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 8, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 9, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

