<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03674749</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>18-5271</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03674749</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Effects of Meditation and Hyperbaric Oxygen Therapy on Chronic Wounds</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effect of Meditation and Hyperbaric Oxygen Therapy on Cognition, Healing Process and Overall Well-being in Elderly Patients With Chronic Wounds</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University Health Network, Toronto</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University Health Network, Toronto</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      In Ontario, wound care support has steadily increased over the years. With the growth of the
      aging population, the financial and psychological burden related to wound care will continue
      to rise. Studies have shown that structured meditation programs can improve on the recovery
      process for both physical and psychological disease. Therapeutic treatments like Hyperbaric
      Oxygen Therapy (HBOT) for chronic wounds have shown to promote angiogenesis, cerebral blood
      and neuroplasticity in patients with stroke, traumatic brain injury and chronic pain. By
      combining meditation and HBOT, this have been independently shown to improve healing and
      reducing costs associated with chronic wounds.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Each year, Community Care Access Centers (CCAC) provide long-term wound care for over 22,000
      patients in Ontario, with numbers steadily increasing with the aging population. In Ontario,
      the cost of community care for lower leg ulcers has been estimated at over $500 million per
      year. This does not include the additional cost of adjunctive HBOT, which averages over $120
      thousand for a standard 40 treatment course. These costs are further compounded by the
      psychological comorbidities that often accompany chronic disease, although these numbers are
      difficult to capture. Across Canada, the health burden cost of anxiety and depression alone
      totals over $14 billion annually, with disability costs comparable to those associated with
      heart disease. Furthermore, recent evidence suggests that psychological interventions are
      more cost-effective than drug treatment, with comparable results.

      The elderly patients with chronic non-healing wounds experience a sense of powerlessness and
      loss of autonomy that profoundly impacts subjective wellbeing. These psychological effects in
      turn compromise healing, as growing evidence suggests that psychological stress impacts wound
      repair [1, 2]. Recent studies have shown that structured meditation programs can improve
      recovery from both physical and psychological disease. For example, meditation enhances
      immune response [3, 4] while reducing blood pressure [5], insulin resistance [6], oxidative
      stress [7], inflammation [8], and other risk indices. Furthermore, meditation therapy can be
      broadly applied with few limitations, having successfully been used in elderly [9], ill [10]
      and disabled [11] populations.

      Hyperbaric oxygen therapy (HBOT) is an adjuvant therapy for chronic wounds. HBOT increases
      oxygen delivery to tissues via inhalation of 100% oxygen at high barometric pressures. HBOT
      has been shown to promote angiogenesis, cerebral blood and neuroplasticity in patients with
      stroke, traumatic brain injury and chronic pain. Furthermore, HBOT also alleviates
      inflammation, reduces oxidative stress, inhibits apoptosis and stimulates signaling pathways
      essential for wound healing.

      Patients referred for HBOT assessment often have &quot;problem wounds&quot; that have failed prolonged
      courses of standard wound care. These refractory wounds may benefit from a multimodal
      approach that targets both the physical and psychological manifestations of chronic disease.
      Meditation is a simple and economical addition to HBOT that may further enhance the rate of
      healing by alleviating psychological stressors. Meditation encompasses a spectrum of
      mindfulness-based interventions that have been shown to improve mental and physical health in
      randomized trials. Meditation reduces stress, pain, anxiety, depression and blood pressure
      while improving cognition and memory performance. A variety of specialties have begun to use
      meditation as a cost-effective, low-stigma adjunct to standard medical and psychiatric care.

      Meditation and HBOT have been independently shown to improve healing, and may have
      synergistic effects when applied together. This combined intervention has the potential to
      improve mood while enhancing the healing process, offering improved health while reducing the
      costs associated with chronic wounds.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 10, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 30, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 31, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Care Provider)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of patients finishing the study protocol.</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Wound</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Hyperbaric Oxygen</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Hyperbaric oxygen treatment with 100% oxygen at 2.0 ATA for 90 min, once daily, five times a week for 8 consecutive weeks</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Meditation with Hyperbaric Oxygen</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Meditation session combined with each hyperbaric oxygen treatment with 100% oxygen at 2.0 ATA for 90 min, once daily, five times a week for 8 consecutive weeks,</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Meditation and Hyperbaric Oxygen Treament</intervention_name>
    <description>Meditation sessions will be combined with hyperbaric oxygen treatment</description>
    <arm_group_label>Hyperbaric Oxygen</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Meditation with Hyperbaric Oxygen</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion criteria:

          1. at least 3 month history of non-healing wounds, affecting lower extremities

          2. 55 years

        Exclusion criteria:

          1. claustrophobia

          2. seizure disorder

          3. active asthma

          4. severe chronic obstructive pulmonary disease

          5. history of pneumothorax

          6. history of severe congestive heart failure with left ventricular ejection fraction &lt;
             25%

          7. unstable angina

          8. chronic or acute otitis media or major ear drum trauma

          9. current treatment with bleomycin, cisplatin, doxorubicin and disulfiram

         10. recent relapse of depression, psychosis, schizophrenia, hallucinations, suicidal
             thoughts
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>55 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Rita Katznelson, MD, FRCPC</last_name>
    <phone>416-340-4800</phone>
    <phone_ext>6273</phone_ext>
    <email>rita.katznelson@uhn.ca</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Ray Janisse</last_name>
    <email>ray.janisse@uhn.ca</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Rouge Valley Medical Centre</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toronto</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>M1E 4B9</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Anton Marinov, MD</last_name>
      <email>a.marinov@utoronto.ca</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Toronto General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toronto</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>M5G 2C4</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Rita Katznelson, MD</last_name>
      <phone>416-340-4800</phone>
      <phone_ext>6273</phone_ext>
      <email>rita.katznelson@uhn.ca</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Broadbent E, Petrie KJ, Alley PG, Booth RJ. Psychological stress impairs early wound repair following surgery. Psychosom Med. 2003 Sep-Oct;65(5):865-9.</citation>
    <PMID>14508033</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gouin JP, Kiecolt-Glaser JK. The impact of psychological stress on wound healing: methods and mechanisms. Immunol Allergy Clin North Am. 2011 Feb;31(1):81-93. doi: 10.1016/j.iac.2010.09.010. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21094925</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Davidson RJ, Kabat-Zinn J, Schumacher J, Rosenkranz M, Muller D, Santorelli SF, Urbanowski F, Harrington A, Bonus K, Sheridan JF. Alterations in brain and immune function produced by mindfulness meditation. Psychosom Med. 2003 Jul-Aug;65(4):564-70.</citation>
    <PMID>12883106</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pace TW, Negi LT, Adame DD, Cole SP, Sivilli TI, Brown TD, Issa MJ, Raison CL. Effect of compassion meditation on neuroendocrine, innate immune and behavioral responses to psychosocial stress. Psychoneuroendocrinology. 2009 Jan;34(1):87-98. doi: 10.1016/j.psyneuen.2008.08.011. Epub 2008 Oct 4.</citation>
    <PMID>18835662</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Goldstein CM, Josephson R, Xie S, Hughes JW. Current perspectives on the use of meditation to reduce blood pressure. Int J Hypertens. 2012;2012:578397. doi: 10.1155/2012/578397. Epub 2012 Mar 5.</citation>
    <PMID>22518287</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Paul-Labrador M, Polk D, Dwyer JH, Velasquez I, Nidich S, Rainforth M, Schneider R, Merz CN. Effects of a randomized controlled trial of transcendental meditation on components of the metabolic syndrome in subjects with coronary heart disease. Arch Intern Med. 2006 Jun 12;166(11):1218-24.</citation>
    <PMID>16772250</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mahagita C. Roles of meditation on alleviation of oxidative stress and improvement of antioxidant system. J Med Assoc Thai. 2010 Nov;93 Suppl 6:S242-54.</citation>
    <PMID>21280542</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Buric I, Farias M, Jong J, Mee C, Brazil IA. What Is the Molecular Signature of Mind-Body Interventions? A Systematic Review of Gene Expression Changes Induced by Meditation and Related Practices. Front Immunol. 2017 Jun 16;8:670. doi: 10.3389/fimmu.2017.00670. eCollection 2017. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>28670311</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gard T, Hölzel BK, Lazar SW. The potential effects of meditation on age-related cognitive decline: a systematic review. Ann N Y Acad Sci. 2014 Jan;1307:89-103. doi: 10.1111/nyas.12348. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24571182</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bonadonna R. Meditation's impact on chronic illness. Holist Nurs Pract. 2003 Nov-Dec;17(6):309-19. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>14650573</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Squier S. Meditation, disability, and identity. Lit Med. 2004 Spring;23(1):23-45; discussion 61-5. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>15264508</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Harris C, Bates-Jensen B. et al. ,The Bates-Jensen Wound Assessment Tool (BWAT): Development of a Pictorial Guide for Training Nurses. Wound Care Canada, 2009, 7 (2): p 33-38</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cohen S, Kamarck T, Mermelstein R. A global measure of perceived stress. J Health Soc Behav. 1983 Dec;24(4):385-96.</citation>
    <PMID>6668417</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Scarpina F, Tagini S. The Stroop Color and Word Test. Front Psychol. 2017 Apr 12;8:557. doi: 10.3389/fpsyg.2017.00557. eCollection 2017. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>28446889</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Geisser ME, Clauw DJ, Strand V, Gendreau RM, Palmer R, Williams DA. Contributions of change in clinical status parameters to Patient Global Impression of Change (PGIC) scores among persons with fibromyalgia treated with milnacipran. Pain. 2010 May;149(2):373-8. doi: 10.1016/j.pain.2010.02.043. Epub 2010 Mar 23.</citation>
    <PMID>20332060</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zigmond AS, Snaith RP. The hospital anxiety and depression scale. Acta Psychiatr Scand. 1983 Jun;67(6):361-70.</citation>
    <PMID>6880820</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>December 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 14, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 14, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 18, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 13, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 13, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">December 16, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Wounds and Injuries</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

