<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03670121</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CSP-2346</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03670121</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Pilot Study to Assess Treatment of Patients With Homogeneous Emphysema Using Sequential Segmental Bronchoscopic Thermal Vapor Ablation (NEXT STEP)</brief_title>
  <acronym>NEXT STEP</acronym>
  <official_title>A Pilot Study to Assess Treatment of Patients With Homogeneous Emphysema Using Sequential Segmental Bronchoscopic Thermal Vapor Ablation</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Uptake Medical Technology, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>MedPass International</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Uptake Medical Technology, Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study is a Prospective, single arm, single center pilot study following outcomes for 12
      months after initial BTVA treatment. The primary objectives of the study are to prospectively
      document the safety and efficacy of sequential segmental treatment with BTVA in patients with
      a homogeneous distribution of emphysema that are not candidates for endobronchial valve
      therapy.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The study will include patients with severe emphysema as defined by pulmonary function tests,
      a homogeneous distribution of emphysema as determined by CT, who are not eligible for
      endobronchial valve therapy based on fissure integrity as determined by CT. Enrollment will
      continue until 10 patients have been treated per protocol or until a maximum of 15 patients
      total have been treated.

      Patients will be enrolled at Thoraxklinik University of Heidelberg, Germany and followed for
      twelve (12) months.

      The follow up data collected will include pulmonary function testing (spirometry, body
      plethysmography, DLCO), exercise capacity (six minute walk test) and imaging findings (chest
      x-ray and CT). Dyspnea score (mMRC) and quality of life questionnaire (SGRQ-C) information
      will be obtained. Information regarding adverse events, serious adverse events, and major
      medical complications will be collected at each visit. Serious adverse events will be
      adjudicated by an independent medical monitor in order to establish relatedness to the
      InterVapor device and procedure.

      Descriptive statistics will be used to summarize all safety and efficacy data. There is no
      predefined hypothesis regarding safety, or efficacy.

      Monitoring of the study will be undertaken as a continuous process to ensure that
      high-quality data are obtained and to ensure compliance with study procedures.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 5, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 31, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 30, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Single arm Pilot Study</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of SAEs, Major Medical complications, and unanticipated serious adverse device effects (USADEs) (safety endpoint)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Occurrence of SAEs, Major Medical complications, and unanticipated serious adverse device effects (USADEs) (safety endpoint)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in FEV1 (efficacy endpoint)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Change in FEV1 (efficacy endpoint)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in St Georges Respiratory Questionnaire for COPD Patients (SGRQ-C) score (efficacy endpoint)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>This trial will utilize the SGRQ-C which is a shortened version of the SGRQ questionnaire. The SGRQ is a validated, disease specific questionnaire that measures health-related quality of life in patients with COPD.
The instrument has 3 domains (activity, symptoms and impacts) and a total score.A Total and three component scores are calculated: Symptoms; Activity; Impacts. Each questionnaire response has a unique empirically derived 'weight'. The lowest possible weight is zero and the highest is 100. Each component of the questionnaire is scored separately. Sum of maximum possible weights for each component and Total: Symptoms 566.2, Activity 982.9, Impacts 1652.8. Total (sum of maximum for all three components) 3201.9 Higher weights indicate worse outcomes. The difference in the domain scores and total score at follow-up visits relative to baseline will be calculated and reported.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in FVC</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Change in Forced Vital Capacity</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in FRC</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Change in Forced Residual Capacity</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in RV</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Change in Residual Volume</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in TLC</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Change in Total Lung Capacity</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in RV/TLC</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Change in Residual Volume/Total Lung Capacity</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in DLCO</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Change in Diffusing capacity of the lung for carbon monoxide</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Modified Medical Research Council (mMRC) Dyspnea scale</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Change in dyspnea score.
Grade Degree of Breathlessness Related to Activities Grade 0 No breathlessness except with strenuous exercise Grade 1 Breathlessness when hurrying on the level or walking up a slight hill Grade 2 Walks slower than people of the same age on the level because of breathlessness or has to stop for breath when walking at own pace on the level Grade 3 Stops for breath after walking about 100 yards or a few minutes on the level Grade 4 Too breathless to leave the house or breathless when dressing or undressing Max score=4, Min score=0 One score is reported based on grade. Higher values represent worse outcomes. For patients with a higher mMRC grade (e.g. ≥2) and clinical circumstances consistent with respiratory disease, measuring spirometry (e.g., FEV₁ and FVC), determining the patient's GOLD stage, helps guide therapeutic interventions.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in 6MWD</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Change in six minute walk distance</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in volume of the treated lobe(s)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Change in lung volume assessed by CT</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">11</enrollment>
  <condition>Emphysema or COPD</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>BTVA Treatment</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>All patients that will receive Bronchoscopic Thermal Vapor Ablation (BTVA) Treatment</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Bronchoscopic Thermal vapor ablation (BTVA)</intervention_name>
    <description>Bronchoscopic vapor delivery to airway segment(s) targeted for treatment</description>
    <arm_group_label>BTVA Treatment</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>BTVA</other_name>
    <other_name>InterVapor</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Age &gt; or equal to 40 and ≤ 75 years old

          2. At least one lung with a homogeneous distribution of emphysema (defined as a
             heterogeneity index &lt; 1.2 when calculated as the ratio of upper lobe to lower lobe
             %-950 and when calculated as the ratio of lower lobe to upper lobe %-950) and a
             fissure integrity score &lt; 95% as measured by CT

          3. Contralateral lung (to lung targeted for the initial BTVA treatment) with tissue to
             air ratio &gt; 8%

          4. FEV1 between 20% and 45% predicted

          5. TLC &gt; or equal to 100% predicted

          6. RV &gt; or equal to 200% predicted

          7. Post-rehabilitation 6MWD &gt; 140 meters

          8. Marked dyspnea scoring &gt; or equal to 2 on the mMRC

          9. Arterial blood gas levels of: PaCO2 ≤ 50 mm Hg; PaO2 &gt; 45 mm Hg on room air

         10. Non-smoking for 2 months prior to study enrollment, as confirmed by negative urine
             point of contact strips or serum cotinine level of ≤ 10 ng/mL, or negative CO Hb test

         11. Optimized medical management (treatment consistent with GOLD guidelines)

         12. Evidence of completed pulmonary rehabilitation:

               -  ≥ 6 weeks out-patient or ≥ 3 weeks in-patient within 6 months of enrollment; or,

               -  Patient has or continues to participate in regular physical activity beyond
                  activities of daily living (i.e. a walking program) for ≥ 6 weeks with 6 months
                  of enrollment under the supervision of a health care professional

         13. Current influenza vaccination

         14. Mentally and physically able to cooperate with the study procedures, follow-up
             requirements, and are able and willing to provide informed consent to participate in
             the study.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Any condition that would interfere with the completion of the study, follow-up
             assessments, bronchoscopy, or that would adversely affect study outcomes. Concomitant
             illnesses or medications that would pose a significant increased risk for
             complications following treatment with BTVA. Relevant examples of relevance include
             immune system disorders, immunosuppressant medications of clinical relevance, bleeding
             disorders and unstable cardiovascular conditions, history of asthma or alpha-1
             antitrypsin deficiency

          2. DLCO &lt; 20% predicted or immeasurable DLCO

          3. BMI &lt; 18kg/m2 or &gt; 35 kg/m2

          4. Clinically significant bronchiectasis with more than 30 ml productive cough

          5. Heart and/or lung transplant, lung volume reduction surgery (LVRS), bullectomy, or
             thoracic surgery with removal of lung tissue

          6. Prior lung volume reduction via endobronchial valves(s), stent(s), coil(s), and/or
             polymer. Patients whose endobronchial valves have been removed can be treated if: all
             valves removed ≥ 6 months prior to BTVA and baseline bronchoscopy reveals no airway
             obstruction or obvious tissue granulation

          7. Recent respiratory infections or COPD exacerbation in preceding 6 weeks

          8. Unstable COPD (any of the following):

               -  &gt;3 COPD related hospitalizations requiring antibiotics in past 12 months

               -  COPD related hospitalization in past 3 months

               -  daily use of systemic steroids, i.e. &gt; 5 mg prednisolone

          9. Single large bulla (defined as &gt; 1/3 volume of the lobe) or a paraseptal distribution
             of emphysema in lobe to be treated

         10. Bacterial infection or symptoms indicative of active infection (i.e., fever, elevated
             white blood cell count)

         11. History of any of the following:

               -  Left ventricular ejection fraction (EF) ≤ 40%

               -  Stroke

               -  Myocardial infarction or acute coronary syndrome in previous year

               -  Current use of anticoagulants (including warfarin, and NOACs such as dabigatran,
                  rivaroxaban, apixaban, and similar).

               -  Patient is unable to stop antiplatelet therapy (including dipyridamole,
                  clopidogrel, prasugrel, and ticlopidine) 7 days before and not restart until 7
                  days after study procedure.

               -  Known sensitivity to medications required to perform bronchoscopy

         12. Pulmonary hypertension:

               -  Peak systolic PAP &gt; 45 mm Hg or

               -  Mean PAP &gt; 35 mm Hg

               -  Right heart catheter measurements (if available) will be considered definitive
                  over echocardiography or cardiac scintigraphy measurements

         13. Newly prescribed morphine derivatives within the last 4 weeks

         14. Pregnant or breastfeeding

         15. Pneumothorax or pleural effusion within previous 6 months

         16. Indwelling pacemaker or implantable cardiac defibrillator (ICD)

         17. Patients dependent on the sponsor or investigator

         18. Current enrollment in any other investigational study which has not completed
             requisite follow-up
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>40 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Felix Herth</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Univ.-Prof. Felix JF Herth, Thoraxklinik University of Heidelberg Heidelberg, Germany</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Thoraxklinik University of Heidelberg</name>
      <address>
        <city>Heidelberg</city>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Germany</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 5, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 11, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 13, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 8, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 8, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 9, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>COPD, Emphysema, Homogenous, Collateral Ventilation</keyword>
  <keyword>vapor</keyword>
  <keyword>ablation</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pulmonary Emphysema</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Emphysema</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

