<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03678259</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>AMY1001</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03678259</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>124I-p5+14 Injection Safety in Subjects With Systemic Amyloidosis</brief_title>
  <official_title>Evaluation of 124I-p5+14 Injection as an Imaging Agent for the Detection of Systemic Amyloidosis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Tennessee Graduate School of Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Tennessee Graduate School of Medicine</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a single-center, exploratory, Phase 1 Positron Emission Tomography/x-ray Computed
      Tomography (PET/CT) imaging study to detect amyloidosis that will enroll patients with a
      confirmed diagnosis of systemic amyloidosis. The purpose of this exploratory trial is to
      assess the safety and efficacy of 124I-p5+14 Injection at a single-injection dose adequate
      for imaging amyloid deposits by using PET/CT imaging in subjects with confirmed systemic
      Immunoglobulin Light Chain-associated Amyloidosis (AL), Transthyretin-associated Amyloidosis
      (ATTR), Leukocyte Chemotactic Factor 2-associated Amyloidosis (ALect2) as well as other
      types.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The rationale for this study is the discovery of a synthetic polypeptide, designated p5+14, a
      synthetic 45 amino acid peptide that binds many forms of amyloid, including human AL-, ATTR-
      and ALect2-associated amyloid, as well as human and murine serum amyloid protein A-associated
      (AA) amyloid. In preclinical studies, using SPECT and PET imaging, as well as
      microautoradiography, it has been shown that radioiodinated p5+14 binds rapidly and
      specifically to all amyloid deposits in abdominothoracic organs and tissues.

      This is a single site, exploratory, open-label Phase I PET/CT imaging and dosimetry study.
      The investigational drug product (designated 124I-p5+14 Injection) is an amyloid-reactive
      synthetic peptide, p5+14 (also known as APi1832), radiolabeled with iodine-124 (I-124 or
      124I). All patients enrolled in this exploratory trial will be outpatients with a confirmed
      diagnosis of systemic amyloidosis.

      The first three patients enrolled in the trial (Part 1) will take part in a dose-escalation
      dosimetry study and will receive a single intravenous (IV) dose of 11.1 Megabecquerel (MBq)
      (0.3 millicuries (mCi); n = 1), 37 MBq (1 mCi; n = 1) or 74 MBq (2 mCi; n = 1) of 124I-p5+14
      Injection for the purpose of determining estimates of organ-associated and whole body
      radioactive dosimetry. Thereafter, the trial will be opened to include another 40 patients
      who will be administered a single IV bolus injection of 124I-p5+14 Injection at a dose, to be
      determined in Part 1 of the study, based on the dosimetry data. Likely, 2 mCi will be used.
      Every patient participating will receive &lt; 2 mg of peptide p5+14
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 1, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 1, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 1, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>The first three patients enrolled in the trial (Part 1) will take part in a dose-escalation dosimetry study and will receive a single IV dose 11.1 MBq (0.3 mCi; n = 1), 37 MBq (1 mCi; n = 1) or 74 MBq (2 mCi; n = 1) of 124I-p5+14 Injection for the purpose of determining estimates of organ-related and whole body radioactive dosimetry. Thereafter, the trial will be opened to include another 40 patients who will be administered a single IV bolus injection of 124I-p5+14 Injection at a dose, to be determined in Part 1 of the study, based on the dosimetry data. Likely, 2 mCi will be used. Every patient participating will receive &lt; 2 mg of peptide p5+14</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
    <masking_description>open-label</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Organ-specific radioactivity dosimetry (Part 1).</measure>
    <time_frame>Through 48 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Localization of 124I-p5+14 will be taken from PET/CT images performed at intervals during the 48 hours after injection. Organ-specific dosimetry and whole body dose measurements will be made using Olinda software (Olinda/Exp; Organ Level Internal Dose Assessment/Exponential Modeling)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Absolute values and changes from baseline in clinical laboratory values.</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 24 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Laboratory assessments will include hematology and clinical chemistry.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinically defined amyloidosis organ involvement.</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline</time_frame>
    <description>For each subject, the clinician/investigator will designate each organ as involved or not involved with amyloidosis, based on available medical history including prior imaging, prior biopsy results, and clinical laboratory values.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Measure of background radioactivity uptake.</measure>
    <time_frame>6 hours and 24 hours</time_frame>
    <description>For each subject, a background radioactivity uptake measure will be derived from the PET images at an uninvolved anatomic site (the lumen of a large blood vessel).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Measure of radioactivity uptake by each organ</measure>
    <time_frame>6 hours and 24 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Uptake of 124I-p5+14 will be derived from PET/CT scans performed at 6 hours and 24 hours after injection. Any organ with &gt;=2-fold higher accumulation of radiotracer, relative to the background uptake, will be considered positive.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Concentration of radiotracer in specific anatomic sites, for each subject and anatomic site</measure>
    <time_frame>6 hours and 24 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Concentration of 124I-p5+14 will be derived from PET/CT scans performed at 6 hours and 24 hours after injection.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Organ and tissue-specific sensitivity of the 124I-p5+14 Injection radiotracer</measure>
    <time_frame>6 hours and 24 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Sensitivity for each organ will be derived from the list of clinically involved organs (Secondary Measure 1) and the list of organ radioactivity uptake (Secondary Measure 4), using the formula, true positive rate = [True positive/(True positive + False negative)].</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Correlation between concentration of the radiotracer (Bq/cc) in the kidney with organ-associated clinical biomarkers.</measure>
    <time_frame>6 hours and 24 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Statistical correlation of kidney radiotracer uptake with proteinuria, albuminuria, creatinine, and blood urea nitrogen (BUN).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Correlation between concentration of the radiotracer (Bq/cc) in the heart with organ-associated clinical biomarkers.</measure>
    <time_frame>6 hours and 24 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Statistical correlation of heart radiotracer uptake with N-terminal-pro-brain natriuretic peptide (NT-BNP) or Brain Natriuretic Peptide (BNP) serum levels, intraventricular septal thickness, and ejection fraction (measures as available from medical history)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Peptide uptake in the heart.</measure>
    <time_frame>6 hours and 24 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Peptide uptake will be recorded as the Standard Uptake Value (SUV) or as Bq/cc of organ volume; obtained from the Region of Interest (ROI) analysis</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Peptide uptake in the kidney</measure>
    <time_frame>6 hours and 24 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Peptide uptake will be recorded as the Standard Uptake Value (SUV) or as Bq/cc of organ volume; obtained from the Region of Interest (ROI) analysis.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Peptide uptake in organ(s) other than kidney or heart if clinically relevant</measure>
    <time_frame>6 hours and 24 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Peptide uptake will be recorded as the Standard Uptake Value (SUV) or as Bq/cc of organ volume; obtained from the Region of Interest (ROI) analysis</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Correlation between uptake of peptide and clinical status of kidney, heart and other organs</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 24 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Correlation between uptake of peptide (from ROI measurements) and the clinical status of kidney, heart, and other organs if indicated (clinical status defined as in Secondary Endpoint 1).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">43</enrollment>
  <condition>Systemic Amyloidosis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>124I-p5+14 Injection</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>A single-injection dose of 124I-p5+14 adequate for imaging amyloid deposits by using PET/CT imaging in subjects with confirmed systemic amyloidosis of several sub-types.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>124I-p5+14 Injection</intervention_name>
    <description>124I-p5+14 Injection which is a formulation of a synthetic, all natural, 45 amino acid peptide (MW = 4766.4) with a net +12 positive charge</description>
    <arm_group_label>124I-p5+14 Injection</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>APi1832</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  1. Patients must have a confirmed diagnosis of systemic amyloidosis, based on
             histologic confirmation that a biopsy contains deposits of apple-green birefringent,
             Congophilic material. Additionally, the type of amyloidosis (AL, ATTR, ALect2, or
             other) should be characterized.

          -  2. Patients enrolled in Part 1 must have widespread AL amyloidosis, defined as biopsy
             proven or clinically detectable involvement, of at least two organs (excluding the
             peripheral nervous system).

          -  3. All patients will be 18 years of age or older, and there are no gender or racial
             restrictions.

          -  4. Women of child bearing potential (those who have not been surgically sterilized,
             are not postmenopausal [typically understood to mean last menstrual period &gt;2 y ago
             without pharmaceutical intervention], and women who are fertile) must test negative
             for pregnancy in a laboratory test administered by the site physician.

          -  5. Patients who have had or are currently receiving therapy or other drug-based
             anti-amyloid regimens can be included on study.

          -  6. Patients must provide signed, written, informed consent and be willing to comply
             with eligibility requirements, scheduled visits, and follow-up studies.

          -  7. Due to annual dosimetry limitations, patients who have participated in another
             nuclear medicine amyloid imaging clinical trial protocol can be included in this study
             no earlier than 12 months after the previous radiotracer injection.

          -  8. Inclusion of patients with amyloid subsets: AL, ATTR, and ALect2 will continue
             until the trial has achieved recruitment goals for each subset: 20 AL; 10 ATTR; 5
             ALect2; and 5 &quot;Other&quot;.

        Exclusion Criteria:

        -1. Individuals with significant cardiac dysfunction (New York Heart Association class IV -
        &quot;Unable to carry on any physical activity without shortness of breath or angina.

        Shortness of breath at rest. If any physical activity is undertaken, discomfort increases&quot;)
        or renal insufficiency that requires dialysis.

          -  2. Those with significant co-morbidity (e.g., Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group
             (ECOG) score of 3 or greater), uncontrolled infection, or other serious illness.

          -  3. Patients with an Saturation of Peripheral Oxygen (SpO2) of ≤ 92% as noted in the
             medical record.

          -  4. Women who are of child bearing potential (those who have not been surgically
             sterilized, are not postmenopausal [typically understood to mean last menstrual period
             &gt;2 y ago without pharmaceutical intervention], and women who are fertile), are
             pregnant, or are nursing. Women who test positive for pregnancy in a laboratory test
             administered by the site physician.

          -  5. Patients who have received any amyloidophilic radiotracer within the past 12
             months.

          -  6. Patients with exposure to heparin, or heparin-based medications, within 7 days
             prior to the imaging study.

          -  7. Patients who have a known allergy to acetaminophen, Benadryl, or iOSAT iodine
             treatment.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jonathan Wall, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>UTHSC Graduate School of Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Jonathan Wall, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <phone>865-305-5447</phone>
    <email>jwall@utmck.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Tennessee Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Knoxville</city>
        <state>Tennessee</state>
        <zip>37920</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jonathan Wall, Ph.D.</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 30, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 17, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 19, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 2, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 2, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 3, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Amyloidosis, AL, ATTR, ALect2</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Amyloidosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

