<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03673371</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>OP160063</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03673371</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Women's-Specific Footwear With Prosthetic Feet</brief_title>
  <acronym>WSF</acronym>
  <official_title>Women's-Specific Footwear With Prosthetic Feet</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Minneapolis Veterans Affairs Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>United States Department of Defense</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Minneapolis Veterans Affairs Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to address footwear challenges unique to women prosthesis users.
      Comparing the effectiveness of different footwear and prosthesis combinations will help guide
      clinical decision making regarding the prescription of prosthetic devices, while keeping what
      the patient wants in mind.

      It is expected that these results will be used to generate new knowledge for the development
      of versatile prosthetic devices that accommodate a user's unique lifestyle while helping the
      patient to make good progress in rehabilitation.

      Investigators will characterize perceived limitations in footwear among women prosthesis
      users. Investigators think that women prosthesis users will be restricted in footwear choices
      and clothing choices due to the use of a prosthetic device.

      Specifically, investigators expect perceived limitations in footwear will be greater for
      shoes with higher heels than shoes without heels.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The project involves development, distribution, and analysis of a questionnaire designed to
      address footwear use among women lower limb prosthesis users. Responses from sixty women with
      a lower extremity amputation will be targeted. VA participants will be identified by the
      MVAHCS. These potential participants will receive the IRB-approved survey via mail. Eligible
      participants include women with unilateral or bilateral lower extremity amputations.

      The questionnaire will target the types of footwear worn by prosthesis users and the types of
      footwear desired to be worn. It will also capture the various types of prosthetic feet worn
      in each footwear category, amputation type, time spent walking in a prosthetic device, and
      general satisfaction with the prosthesis function during daily living when worn with shoes.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 4, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Women's-Specific Footwear and Prosthetic Feet Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>through data collection, an average of one year</time_frame>
    <description>Questionnaire regarding Women Veterans and their use of different types of footwear with prosthetic feet. The subscales are derived from the following scales:Patient Reported Outcome System (PROMIS) Anxiety - 4 Patient Reported Outcome System (PROMIS) Depression - 4 Patient Reported Outcome System - Ability to Participate in Social Roles and Activities Patient Reported Outcome System - Satisfaction with Social Roles and Activities - 4a Amputee Body Image Scale - Revised Prosthetic Limb Users Survey of Mobility Community Participation Index - Importance subscale Community Participation Index - Control subscale Community Participation Index - Frequency index Activities-Specific Balance Confidence Scale Prosthesis Evaluation Questionnaire - Appearance Prosthesis Evaluation Questionnaire - Utility</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Lower Limb Amputation Below Knee (Injury)</condition>
  <condition>Lower Limb Amputation Above Knee (Injury)</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Women Veterans with Lower Limb Amputations</arm_group_label>
    <description>Questionnaire</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Questionnaire</intervention_name>
    <description>This is a questionnaire developed by DoD and VA researchers specifically for this study.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Women Veterans with Lower Limb Amputations</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>&quot;WSF Questionnaire&quot;</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Women Veterans with Lower Limb Amputation (excluding Syme's and Hip Disarticulation)
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Woman Veteran

          -  Age 18-80

          -  Lower Limb Amputation (transtibial, through the knee, transfemoral)

          -  Eligible to receive care through the VA Health Care System

          -  Ambulatory and currently using a prosthesis

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Syme's Amputation

          -  Hip Disarticulation
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <gender_based>Yes</gender_based>
    <gender_description>Women</gender_description>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Elizabeth Russell Esposito, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Extremity Trauma and Amputation Center of Excellence</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Andrew H. Hansen, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>612-467-2910</phone>
    <email>andrew.hansen2@va.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Billie Slater, MAEd</last_name>
    <phone>612-629-7830</phone>
    <email>billie.slater@va.gov</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Minneapolis VA Health Care System</name>
      <address>
        <city>Minneapolis</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55417</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Andrew H Hansen, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>612-467-2910</phone>
      <email>andrew.hansen2@va.gov</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Billie Slater, MAEd</last_name>
      <phone>612-629-7830</phone>
      <email>billie.slater@va.gov</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ziegler-Graham K, MacKenzie EJ, Ephraim PL, Travison TG, Brookmeyer R. Estimating the prevalence of limb loss in the United States: 2005 to 2050. Arch Phys Med Rehabil. 2008 Mar;89(3):422-9. doi: 10.1016/j.apmr.2007.11.005.</citation>
    <PMID>18295618</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Elnitsky CA, Latlief GA, Andrews EE, Adams-Koss LB, Phillips SL. Preferences for rehabilitation services among women with major limb amputations. Rehabil Nurs. 2013 Jan-Feb;38(1):32-6. doi: 10.1002/rnj.62.</citation>
    <PMID>23365003</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Klodd E, Hansen A, Fatone S, Edwards M. Effects of prosthetic foot forefoot flexibility on gait of unilateral transtibial prosthesis users. J Rehabil Res Dev. 2010;47(9):899-910.</citation>
    <PMID>21174254</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Meier MR, Tucker KA, Hansen AH. Development of inexpensive prosthetic feet for high-heeled shoes using simple shoe insole model. J Rehabil Res Dev. 2014;51(3):439-50. doi: 10.1682/JRRD.2013.01.0010.</citation>
    <PMID>25019666</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 23, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 13, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 17, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 8, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 8, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 11, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Minneapolis Veterans Affairs Medical Center</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Andrew H. Hansen</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Site Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Limb Prosthesis</keyword>
  <keyword>Shoe</keyword>
  <keyword>Self Concepts</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Wounds and Injuries</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>A de-identified, anonymized data set will be created and shared under a written agreement that prohibits the recipient from identifying or attempting to re-identify any individual whose data are included in the data set.</ipd_description>
    <ipd_time_frame>Starting 6 months after publication for up to 10 years.</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>The Principal Investigator and Site Principal Investigator will review requests for the de-identified final data set. It is possible that the de-identified final data set will be available through PubMed Central.</ipd_access_criteria>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

