<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03670719</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>N13/2018</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03670719</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effectiveness of Manual Therapy and Exercise vs Exercise in Subjects With Chronic Cervical Pain and Upper Cervical Spine Dysfunction</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effectiveness of Manual Therapy and Exercise vs Exercise in Subjects With Chronic Cervical Pain and Upper Cervical Spine Dysfunction: A Randomized Controlled Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Universidad de Zaragoza</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Universidad de Zaragoza</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      There is a lot of scientific evidence about the effectiveness of manual therapy and exercise
      / training in subjects with cervical pain. Most of the high quality systematic reviews agree
      on the need to combine manual therapy and exercise for the treatment of chronic cervical
      pain. However, articles that focus on manual therapy in the treatment of the upper cervical
      spine are not as common, being that the most commonly prescribed exercises are those of
      craniocervical flexion, (flexion of the upper cervical spine).

      The investigators believe that participants who are going to benefit more from the
      integration of manual therapy and exercise will be those who have a real restriction of the
      upper cervical spine, and for these, is indispensable, the application of manual therapy
      techniques before the integration of the active exercise to obtain optimal results.

      This project is going to try to define participants with chronic cervical pain and upper
      cervical spine restriction that may benefit more from the combination of manual therapy and
      exercise than the rest. The investigators are going to study changes in different variables
      about function, pain, ultrasound, muscle tone, joints... Strengthen the importance of
      specificity in physiotherapy interventions and increase the evidence on the importance of
      manual therapy in a subgroup of participants with chronic cervical pain, improve knowledge
      about the involvement of the upper cervical spine in cervical pathology and check the
      effectiveness of a self-treatment program for participants with chronic cervical pain.

      The objective of this trial is to compare the effectiveness of an integrative approach of
      manual therapy associated with exercise versus exercise in participants with chronic cervical
      pain and upper cervical spine dysfunction.

      For this purpose, the investigators conduct a randomized controlled trial, simple-blind (Only
      is possible to blind the evaluator).

      The Sample size is 52 participants (2 groups of 26 participants). One of the groups will
      receive 4 training sessions with exercises for the cervical spine between 30 and 45 minutes
      duration per session and the other group will receive 4 sessions of a combination of manual
      therapy and training exercises also between 30 and 45 minutes each session. In addition, all
      participants will receive self-treatment techniques for self-management of their dysfunction.

      Cervical exercises will consist of a set of training techniques to improve the function and
      symptomatology that the participant has. These exercises have been widely evidenced and do
      not suppose any health risk.

      The techniques of manual therapy can be the manipulation technique in resting position,
      vertebral mobilization and / or musculature (massage and / or stretching). All the treatments
      applied follow the safety recommendations of the International Federation of Orthopedic
      Manual Therapists (IFOMPT). If participants need clarification, they can talk to the
      principal investigator (Jacobo Rodríguez Sanz) at any time.

      One physiotherapist will perform the physical examination, and a different one will apply the
      treatment. Physical therapists doing the screening will not know which group has been
      assigned to them, so the participant will be asked not to provide the evaluators any
      information about the assignment of his group to improve the quality of the study.

      The examination will consist of tests to assess whether the participant is a candidate to
      participate in the study, the measurement of pain, the exhaustive assessment of all cervical
      musculature with different measuring instruments and the measurement of joint mobility.

      The first day theparticipant be given information about his pain, his daily habits and
      activities that he usually does.

      The assessment of his problem will consist in the measurement of the amount of movement he
      can makes in the cervical area without pain, the ability to orient himself in certain
      movements with his eyes closed, the intensity of his pain, the evaluation of the state of his
      muscles. stabilizing as a mobilizer through ultrasound, muscle test and palpation. The
      functionality of his cervical vertebrae will also be evaluated and he will be asked different
      questionnaires about the functionality, pain and condition of his cervical pain, headache (in
      case of suffering) and kinesiophobia.

      Both the evaluation and the treatment will be without pain. In addition, he will be given a
      series of personalized exercises to improve his problem, which must be done every day during
      the study.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 10, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">January 1, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">November 1, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>Only the evaluator is blinded</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Neck Disability Index (NDI) Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>Change between baseline (immediately before intervention) and post intervention (1 month), after 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>The NDI is a modification of the Oswestry Low Back Pain Disability Index . It is a patient-completed, condition-specific functional status questionnaire with 10 items including pain, personal care, lifting, reading, headaches, concentration, work, driving, sleeping and recreation. The NDI has sufficient support and usefulness to retain its current status as the most commonly used self-report measure for neck pain</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Flexion Rotation Test (FRT)</measure>
    <time_frame>Change between baseline(immediately before intervention) and post intervention (immediately after intervention), and post intervention (1 month) after 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>This test is used to see the amount of movement of the upper cervical spine and is the test most used in the literature. It is positive when there is a decrease of 10 degrees or more in the cervical rotation with maximum flexion, in a sense with respect to the contralateral or presents hypomobility of segment C1 with a mobility less than 32º</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Pressure Pain Threshold</measure>
    <time_frame>Change between baseline(immediately before intervention) and post intervention (immediately after intervention), and post intervention (1 month) after 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Pressure pain threshold (PPT) is defined as the minimum force applied which induces pain. This measure has proven to be commonly useful in evaluating tenderness symptom. This force is applied by a portable and digital machine. This machine has a push button so the patient can press at the moment in which the applied force begins to be slightly painful. When the patient presses the button, the evaluator registers the number that appears on the screen.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Cervical Range of Movement</measure>
    <time_frame>Change between baseline(immediately before intervention) and post intervention (immediately after intervention), and post intervention (1 month), after 3 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Numeric Pain Rating Scale (NPRS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Change between baseline(immediately before intervention) and post intervention (immediately after intervention), and post intervention (1 month), after 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>The Numeric Pain Rating Scale (NPRS) is a one-dimensional measure of pain intensity in adults. The NPRS is a segmented numeric version of the visual analog scale (VAS) in which a respondent selects a whole number (0-10 integers) that best reflects the intensity of his/her pain. The common format is a horizontal bar or line. Similar to the VAS, the NPRS is anchored by terms describing pain severity extremes.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Ultrasound</measure>
    <time_frame>Change between baseline(immediately before intervention) and post intervention (1 month), after 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>To measure the thickness of the longus colli muscle</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">52</enrollment>
  <condition>Neck Pain</condition>
  <condition>Cervical Pain</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Manual Therapy and Exercise Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Combination of manual therapy and exercises for chronic cervical pain</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Exercise Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Only exercises for chronic cervical pain</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Manual Therapy and Exercise</intervention_name>
    <description>Combination of physiotherapy (manual therapy) techniques and exercises for the cervical spine</description>
    <arm_group_label>Manual Therapy and Exercise Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Exercise</intervention_name>
    <description>Exercises for the cervical spine</description>
    <arm_group_label>Exercise Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  18 years old and over

          -  Medical diagnosis of chronic cervical pain (more than 3 months of cervical pain
             evolution)

          -  Positive flexion rotation test

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Recent spine, head or mouth surgery.

          -  Diabetes mellitus

          -  Recent infection and/or inflammatory arthritis, and cervical and/or brain traumatism
             records.

          -  Contraindication for manual therapy or cervical training
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>90 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jacobo Rodríguez-Sanz, Pt</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Physiotherapy Research Unit, University of Zaragoza</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Faculty of Health Sciences of University of Zaragoza</name>
      <address>
        <city>Zaragoza</city>
        <zip>50009</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Spain</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 6, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 12, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 13, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 13, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 13, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 17, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Universidad de Zaragoza</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Jacobo Rodríguez-Sanz</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>manual therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>exercise</keyword>
  <keyword>physiotherapy</keyword>
  <keyword>chronic cervical pain</keyword>
  <keyword>upper cervical spain</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Neck Pain</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

