<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03672045</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>18-07</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03672045</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Carbetocin at Elective Cesarean Deliveries: A Dose-finding Study in Women With BMI ≥ 40kg/m2</brief_title>
  <official_title>Carbetocin at Elective Cesarean Deliveries: A Dose-finding Study in Women With BMI ≥ 40kg/m2</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Samuel Lunenfeld Research Institute, Mount Sinai Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Samuel Lunenfeld Research Institute, Mount Sinai Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Postpartum hemorrhage (PPH) due to uterine atony is a major cause of maternal morbidity and
      mortality. Carbetocin is a uterotonic with a superior pharmacokinetic profile to oxytocin. In
      a study performed at Mount Sinai Hospital, the investigators have shown that smaller doses of
      carbetocin (14.8 mcg) are as effective in achieving adequate uterine tone at elective
      cesarean section compared to the current recommended dose of 100mcg. However, this study was
      limited to those women with a body mass index (BMI) of &lt;40 kg/m2. Maternal obesity has been
      shown to increase the risks of hemorrhage secondary to uterine atony, therefore the
      investigators wish to perform a dose finding study to determine the ED90 of carbetocin at
      caesarean section in those women with a BMI&gt;40.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Postpartum hemorrhage (PPH) is one of the leading causes of death during childbirth and
      accounts for an estimated 140,000 deaths per year worldwide. The World Health Organization
      (WHO) recommends active management of the third stage of labor to prevent PPH, even in low
      risk patients. Prophylactic uterotonic drugs administered after delivery are the main element
      of active management of the third stage and have been demonstrated to reduce the incidence of
      PPH by up to 40%.

      Oxytocin is the most commonly used uterotonic in North America, however it has a very short
      duration of action and requires a continuous infusion to achieve sustained effect, with large
      doses associated with adverse effects like low blood pressure, nausea, vomiting, abnormal
      heart rhythms and changes on ECG. Carbetocin is a synthetic oxytocin analogue. It causes
      uterine contraction via the same mechanism as oxytocin. Its duration of action is 4 to 7
      times that of oxytocin due to an increased biological half-life in plasma and at the oxytocin
      receptors in the uterus. The Society of Obstetricians and Gynecologists of Canada (SOGC) has
      recommended a single dose of 100 mcg of carbetocin at elective cesarean delivery to promote
      uterine contraction. In a study performed at Mount Sinai Hospital, the investigators have
      shown that smaller doses of carbetocin (14.8 mcg) are effective in achieving adequate uterine
      tone at elective cesarean section. However this study was limited to those women with a BMI
      of &lt;40 kg/m2

      The prevalence of obesity is increasing in young women and some studies have shown that obese
      women have higher rates of caesarean delivery compared to non-obese women. Other studies have
      demonstrated an increased risk of hemorrhage due to poor uterine tone in obese women.
      Laboratory studies show that BMI alone appears to contribute to blunted uterine muscle
      responses and therefore contraction responses to oxytocin in obese women. Previous dose
      finding studies have excluded those women with a BMI of ≥40kgm2. Therefore, the investigators
      wish to perform a double-blind dose finding study using the biased coin up-and-down
      sequential allocation technique to determine the ED90 of carbetocin at caesarean section in
      those women with a BMI&gt;40.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 19, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 17, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 16, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Biased coin up-and-down design.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Intraoperative requirement for additional uterotonic medication</measure>
    <time_frame>1 hour</time_frame>
    <description>A request made by the obstetrician performing the cesarean delivery for additional uterotonic medication, due to bleeding or poor uterine tone.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Uterine tone 2 minutes</measure>
    <time_frame>2 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>Uterine tone, defined as satisfactory or unsatisfactory by the obstetrician at 2 minutes after completion of the carbetocin injection.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Uterine tone 5 minutes</measure>
    <time_frame>5 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>Uterine tone, defined as satisfactory or unsatisfactory by the obstetrician at 5 minutes after completion of the carbetocin injection.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Additional uterotonics administered</measure>
    <time_frame>45 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>The drug, dosage and timing of any additional uterotonic medication given during surgery.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Estimated blood loss</measure>
    <time_frame>24 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Blood loss will be calculated through the difference in hematocrit values assessed prior to surgery and 24 hours after the cesarean delivery.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Intravenous fluid administered during surgery</measure>
    <time_frame>2 hours</time_frame>
    <description>The total volume (ml) of fluid administered from entering the operating room to skin closure.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hypotension: systolic blood pressure less than 80% of baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>2 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Systolic blood pressure &lt; 80% of baseline, from drug administration until end of surgery</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Tachycardia: heart rate greater than 130% of baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>2 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Heart rate &gt; 130% of baseline, from drug administration until end of surgery</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Bradycardia: heart rate less than 70% of baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>2 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Heart rate &lt; 70% of baseline or a heart rate &lt; 50bpm, from drug administration until end of surgery</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Presence of ventricular tachycardia: ECG</measure>
    <time_frame>2 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Presence of ventricular tachycardia as recorded by ECG, from drug administration until end of surgery</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Presence of atrial fibrillation: ECG</measure>
    <time_frame>2 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Presence of atrial fibrillation as recorded by ECG, from drug administration until end of surgery</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Presence of atrial flutter: ECG</measure>
    <time_frame>2 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Presence of atrial flutter as recorded by ECG, from drug administration until end of surgery</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Presence of nausea: questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>2 hours</time_frame>
    <description>The presence of nausea and number of episodes, from drug administration until end of surgery, as reported by the patient</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Presence of vomiting: questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>2 hours</time_frame>
    <description>The presence of vomiting and number of episodes, from drug administration until end of surgery</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Presence of chest pain: questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>2 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Any presence of chest pain, from drug administration until end of surgery, as reported by the patient</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Presence of shortness of breath: questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>2 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Any presence of shortness of breath, from drug administration until end of surgery, as reported by the patient</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Presence of headache: questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>2 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Any presence of headache, from drug administration until end of surgery, as reported by the patient</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Presence of flushing: questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>2 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Any presence of flushing, from drug administration until end of surgery</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>6</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Postpartum Hemorrhage</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Carbetocin 10mcg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patient is given 10 mcg of carbetocin intravenously over 1 minute, immediately upon delivery of the fetal head.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Carbetocin 20mcg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patient is given 20 mcg of carbetocin intravenously over 1 minute, immediately upon delivery of the fetal head.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Carbetocin 40mcg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patient is given 40 mcg of carbetocin intravenously over 1 minute, immediately upon delivery of the fetal head.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Carbetocin 60mcg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patient is given 60 mcg of carbetocin intravenously over 1 minute, immediately upon delivery of the fetal head.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Carbetocin 80mcg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patient is given 80 mcg of carbetocin intravenously over 1 minute, immediately upon delivery of the fetal head.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Carbetocin 100mcg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patient is given 100 mcg of carbetocin intravenously over 1 minute, immediately upon delivery of the fetal head.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Carbetocin</intervention_name>
    <description>carbetocin administered IV, over 1 minute following delivery of the fetal head</description>
    <arm_group_label>Carbetocin 100mcg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Carbetocin 10mcg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Carbetocin 20mcg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Carbetocin 40mcg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Carbetocin 60mcg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Carbetocin 80mcg</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Duratocin</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  BMI ≥40kg/m2

          -  Elective cesarean delivery under regional anesthesia

          -  Gestational age ≥ 37 weeks

          -  No known additional risk factors for postpartum hemorrhage

          -  Written informed consent to participate in this study

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Refusal to give written informed consent

          -  Allergy or hypersensitivity to carbetocin or oxytocin

          -  Conditions (other than high BMI) that may predispose to uterine atony and postpartum
             hemorrhage such as placenta previa, multiple gestation, polyhydramnios, uterine
             fibroids, previous history of uterine atony and postpartum bleeding, or bleeding
             diathesis.

          -  Hepatic, renal, and vascular disease

          -  Use of general anesthesia prior to the administration of the study drug
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>50 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jose Carvalho, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>MOUNT SINAI HOSPITAL</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mount Sinai Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toronto</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>M5G1X5</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 13, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 13, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 14, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 6, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 6, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 7, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>pregnancy</keyword>
  <keyword>postpartum hemorrhage</keyword>
  <keyword>Cesarean delivery</keyword>
  <keyword>carbetocin</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Postpartum Hemorrhage</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hemorrhage</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Carbetocin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

