<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03670290</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MEUANEST001</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03670290</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Clinical Outcomes of Analgesia Methods in Patients With Hip Fracture</brief_title>
  <official_title>Clinical Outcomes of Analgesia Methods in Patients With Hip Fracture</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Mersin University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Mersin University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The goal of this study is to determine of clinical outcomes of analgesia methods. The primary
      outcomes are opioid consumption, static and dynamic visual analog scale (VAS) scores.
      Secondary outcomes are occurrence of side effects.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Hip fracture is one of the most serious consequences of falls in the elderly, with a
      mortality of 10% at one month and 30% at one year. Factors of associated with increased
      morbidity and mortality have been researched to prevent complications.

      Pain has been associated with delirium and depression in hip fracture patients. Besides,
      narcotic drugs are also associated with some side effects such as delirium, postoperative
      nausea and vomiting (PONV ), cardiovascular and respiratory depression. These clinical
      problems are especially important in the elderly population.

      Fascia iliaca compartment block (FICB) is one of the methods applied for postoperative
      analgesia, which is applied under the inguinal ligament and distributes between the femoral
      nerve and lateral femoral cutaneous nerve block by volumetric effect. Recently, studies have
      been published on hip fracture patients using pop up technique in emergency services.
      Although many studies have shown that FICB is effective in perioperative analgesia, the
      effects of this method on complications and mortality rate have not yet been investigated.

      The primary objective is to compare morphine consumption and VAS scores in patients with hip
      fracture who treated with epidural catheter, fascia iliaca compartment catheter or patient
      controlled analgesia.

      The secondary objective is to determine complications. The investigators hypothesize that
      FICB catheter will provide good pain control same as epidural catheter, and will decrease
      complications such as delirium and pain with less mortality rate.

      Patients with pain in the hip fracture, will be evaluated after admission to the hospital and
      analgesic treatment will be applied to patients with Visual Analog Pain Scale (VAS) score 3
      and above.

      Patients will be divided into three groups; Group I will include patients with treated FICB
      catheter, Group II will include patients with treated patient controlled analgesia, Group III
      will include patients with treated epidural catheter,

      Catheters will be placed with US visualization in Group I. A hyperechoic needle will be used
      (18 G 80 mm) for inserting catheter in Group I and III.

      Group I will receive 30 ml of Bupivacaine 0.25% solution through the fascia iliaca
      compartment catheter.

      Group II will receive, morphine 0.1 mg/ml via patient controlled analgesia pump. every pump
      will be set 1 mg dose morphine per use and 15 min lockout time.

      Group III will receive 10 ml of Bupivacaine 0.25% solution through the epidural catheter.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">December 15, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">October 15, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">August 31, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Morphine consumption</measure>
    <time_frame>From the beginning of treatment to discharge (Totally 5 days)</time_frame>
    <description>All perioperative morphine consumption will be recoreded every 6 hours.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Visual analogue score</measure>
    <time_frame>From admission to second postoperative day. (Totally 5 days)</time_frame>
    <description>Mean visual analogue scores will be compared for 3 groups. VAS score will measured from 0 to 10. Higher values represent worse outcome.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>incidence of postoperative complications in 30 day post-surgery.</measure>
    <time_frame>From end of surgery to Day 30 after surgery (totally 30 days)</time_frame>
    <description>Patients will be monitored and every serious complication related with surgery including respiratory failure, hypotension, delirium, thromboembolism, nausea and vomiting will be recorded. These events will be measured as percentage (%)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Anticoagulant medication status in the S-FICB group</measure>
    <time_frame>First day (15 min)</time_frame>
    <description>The use of anticoagulant drugs will be questioned and recorded in the S-FICB group</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>3</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">120</enrollment>
  <condition>Hip Fractures</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group 1</arm_group_label>
    <description>Group I will receive 30 ml of Bupivacaine 0.25% solution through the fascia iliaca compartment catheter. Catheter will be inserted with US.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group 2</arm_group_label>
    <description>Group II will receive, morphine 0.1 mg/ml via patient controlled analgesia pump. every pump will be set 1 mg dose morphine per use and 15 min lockout time.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group 3</arm_group_label>
    <description>Group III will receive 10 ml of Bupivacaine 0.25% solution through the epidural catheter.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Fascia iliaca compartment catheter</intervention_name>
    <description>Patient will evaluate and if VAS score &gt;3, catheter will be inserted and 30 ml bupivacaine 0.25% will be applied after admission. Dose will be repeated VAS&gt;3 or patient enounce pain.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group 1</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>epidural catheter</intervention_name>
    <description>Patient will evaluate and if VAS score &gt;3, catheter will be inserted and 10 ml bupivacaine 0.25% will be applied after admission. Dose will be repeated VAS&gt;3 or patient enounce pain.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group 3</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>patient controlled analgesia</intervention_name>
    <description>Patient will evaluate and if VAS score &gt;3, patient controlled analgesia pump will be set 1mg morphine/15 min lockout.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group 2</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Study will be performed from 01/12/2018 to 01/06/2019. It is estimated to each group
        includes 40 patient.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients without communication problems (delirium, hearing loss, language problems
             etc.)

          -  Patients who do not use regular analgesic medication for any chronic disease

          -  Patients without any neurological deficit at the lower extremity

          -  Patients without renal or hepatic dysfunction

          -  Patients without bleeding diathesis

          -  Patients with isolated femur fractures

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with communication problems

          -  Patients who use regular analgesic medication for any chronic disease

          -  Patients with neurological deficits in the lower extremity

          -  Patients with renal or hepatic dysfunction

          -  Patients with bleeding diathesis

          -  Patients with multiple trauma
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>90 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mustafa Azizoglu</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Mersin University, Anesthesia and Reanimation Department</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mustafa AZİZOĞLU</name>
      <address>
        <city>Mersin</city>
        <zip>33343</zip>
        <country>Turkey</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Turkey</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 6, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 11, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 13, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 21, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 21, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 25, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Mersin University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Mustafa Azizoğlu</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Proffessor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>hip fracture</keyword>
  <keyword>fascia iliaca compartment catheter</keyword>
  <keyword>epidural catheter</keyword>
  <keyword>delirium</keyword>
  <keyword>postoperative complications</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Fractures, Bone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hip Fractures</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Every entered data could share to other researchers</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>After 01/03/2019</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>Sharing access will be depends on requests.</ipd_access_criteria>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

