<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03674333</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>U1111-1220-5275</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03674333</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effect of Adding Folic Acid on Lipid Parameters in Population With Dyslipidemias</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effect of Adding Folic Acid on Lipid Parameters in Population With Dyslipidemias</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Shaheed Zulfiqar Ali Bhutto Medical University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Shaheed Zulfiqar Ali Bhutto Medical University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background: Homocysteinemia is associated with increased risk of stroke, dyslipidemias,
      dementia, peripheral vascular disease and coronary artery disease. folic acid is involved in
      the metabolism of homocysteine. Folic acid supplementation helps to reduce homocysteine
      levels and lowering of homocysteine may cause improvement in serum lipid profile. In this
      study we will assess the effect of folic acid supplementation for 6 weeks, on lipid parameter
      in patients who have dyslipidemia.

      Methods: It is a placebo controlled randomized trial, consisting of two groups, Group A
      (n=34) and Group B (n=34). Group A (intervention group) will be given Folic acid supplements
      and the second group will be given a placebo. After 6 weeks changes in lipid parameters, will
      be measured in both groups.

      Discussion: Folic acid is water soluble vitamin also known as vitamin B-9. Folic acid works
      as co-factor in many biochemical enzymatic reactions. Homocysteine metabolism also requires
      folic acid, homocysteinemia may worsen renal function, lipid parameter, accelerate
      atherosclerosis, angiopathies, and progression of dementia, also increase the risk of stroke
      and coronary artery disease. In this study, Group A (treatment Group) will be given folic
      acid supplementation while the Group B (Placebo Group) will be given placebo and at the end
      of 6 weeks, HDL, LDL, Triglycerides and serum cholesterol levels will be measured and
      compared with the pre-treatment levels. If Post-treatment group shows significant decrease in
      serum LDL, total cholesterol, triglycerides and increase in HDL then Folic acid
      supplementation may be routinely recommended for patient with dyslipidemias.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Hyperlipidemia, increases the risk of stroke, hypertension, coronary artery disease and other
      associated disorders. World-wide about one-third of coronary artery disease is attributed
      high cholesterol. Overall it has been estimated that elevated blood cholesterol causes 26
      million deaths (4.5% of the total deaths) world-wide. Hyperlipidemias is a major cause of
      morbidity in both developed and developing countries as a risk factor for stroke and coronary
      artery disease. The prevalence of raised total cholesterol increased noticeably according to
      the income level of the country. In low income countries around a quarter of adults had
      raised total cholesterol, in lower middle income countries this rose to around a third of the
      population for both sexes. In high-income countries, over 50% of adults had raised total
      cholesterol; more than double the level of the low-income countries.

      Homocysteine, on the other hand, is a sulfur amino acid, which is metabolized by two
      pathways, either it is re-methylated to methionine or it undergoes trans-sulfuration to
      cystathionine which is eventually converted into cysteine, an amino acid. Folic acid is
      involved in remethylation of homocysteine to methionine. Thus, folic acid supplementation may
      enhance the metabolism of homocysteine level and thereby may decrease its level in blood.
      Homocysteine in blood is termed as homocysteinemia. Homocysteinemia is associated with
      dyslipidemias, increased risk of atherosclerosis, micro-angiopathies, coronary artery
      disease, stroke, dementia and also found to be associated with suppressed immunity.
      Supplementation with folic acid may lower homocysteine level by accelerating its metabolism
      to methionine. In this study investigators will be assessing the effect of folate
      supplementation on the lipid profile, particularly on the blood levels of HDL, LDL,
      Triglycerides and total cholesterol. The HDL has cardio-protective effect, while on the other
      hand, the higher level of LDL, total cholesterol and triglycerides may accelerate
      atherosclerosis, angiopathies and increases the risk of stroke and heart diseases.

      Research question: Does addition of folic acid supplementation decrease LDL, total
      cholesterol, triglycerides and increase HDL in patients with dyslipidemias.

      OBJECTIVE:

      To assess the effect of folic acid supplementation on HDL, LDL, total cholesterol and
      triglycerides in patients with dyslipidemias.

      HYPOTHESIS Addition of folic acid supplementation will improve lipid parameters (HDL, total
      cholesterol, triglycerides &amp; LDL) in patients with dyslipidemias.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">September 24, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 15, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 28, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Group A receives Folic Acid and Group B receives Placebo.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
    <masking_description>Participants of both the groups will be unaware of whether they received placebo or folic acid.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>LDL</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>mg/dL</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>HDL</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>mg/dL</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Triglycerides</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>mg/dL</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Total Cholesterol</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>mg/dL</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">68</enrollment>
  <condition>Dyslipidemias</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Folic acid 1mg daily will be given to the participants of Group A.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group B</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>A Placebo (a sugar pill) will be given to the participants of the Group B.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Folic Acid</intervention_name>
    <description>Folic acid is a water soluble vitamin, required for various biological functions in human body, including metabolism of homocysteine.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group A</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Placebo - a sugar pill</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group B</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  1. Otherwise, healthy individuals of either sex with any of the following
             characteristics will be including in the study.

               1. Serum cholesterol &gt;200mg/dl

               2. Serum triglyceride &gt; 150mg/dl

               3. Serum LDL &gt;100mg/dl

               4. Serum HDL &lt; 40mg/dl

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients who have any clinically significant or unstable medical or psychiatric
             illnesses.

          2. Patients with CKD, diabetes mellitus, coronary artery disease, with history of stroke,
             myocardial infarction or any chronic illnesses.

          3. Substance abuse such as alcoholism excluded by taking history.

          4. Patients who are pregnant are excluded by taking history and urine dipstick test where
             applicable.

          5. Patient who are treated with any investigational drug within last 60 days.

          6. Patients who are taking a statin or any other lipid lowering drug.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Adil Ramzan, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Shaheed Zulfiqar Ali Bhutto Medical University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Adil Ramzan, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+923336671671</phone>
    <email>adilramzan@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>M Ali Arif, FRCP</last_name>
    <email>mohammad_ali_arif@hotmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Shaheed Zulfiqar Ali Bhutto Medical University, Pakistan Institute of Medical Sciences Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Islamabad</city>
        <zip>44000</zip>
        <country>Pakistan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Fibhaa Syed, FCPS, MRCP</last_name>
      <phone>923335300002</phone>
      <email>Fibhaasyed@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Pakistan</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Blom HJ, Smulders Y. Overview of homocysteine and folate metabolism. With special references to cardiovascular disease and neural tube defects. J Inherit Metab Dis. 2011 Feb;34(1):75-81. doi: 10.1007/s10545-010-9177-4. Epub 2010 Sep 4. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20814827</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mierzecki A, Kłoda K, Bukowska H, Chełstowski K, Makarewicz-Wujec M, Kozłowska-Wojciechowska M. Association between low-dose folic acid supplementation and blood lipids concentrations in male and female subjects with atherosclerosis risk factors. Med Sci Monit. 2013 Sep 4;19:733-9. doi: 10.12659/MSM.889087.</citation>
    <PMID>24002360</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Baszczuk A, Thielemann A, Musialik K, Kopczynski J, Bielawska L, Dzumak A, Kopczynski Z, Wysocka E. The Impact of Supplementation with Folic Acid on Homocysteine Concentration and Selected Lipoprotein Parameters in Patients with Primary Hypertension. J Nutr Sci Vitaminol (Tokyo). 2017;63(2):96-103. doi: 10.3177/jnsv.63.96.</citation>
    <PMID>28552882</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>September 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 14, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 14, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 17, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 14, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 14, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">September 18, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Shaheed Zulfiqar Ali Bhutto Medical University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Adil Ramzan</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Folic Acid</keyword>
  <keyword>Dyslipidemias</keyword>
  <keyword>Hyperlipidemia</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Dyslipidemias</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Folic Acid</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Individual participants data will be available. Individual participant data that underlie the results reported in this article, after deidentification (text, tables, figures and appendices) will be shared to the researchers who provide a methodologically sound proposal to the primary investigator (Dr. Adil Ramzan).</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Statistical Analysis Plan (SAP)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Clinical Study Report (CSR)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>Beginning 3 months and ending 5 years following publication of the article.</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>Proposal should be directed to &quot;adilramzan@gmail.com&quot;. To access data, data requestors will need to sign a data access agreement. Data are available for 5 years at 3rd party website.</ipd_access_criteria>
    <ipd_url>http://www.dradilramzan.com</ipd_url>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

