<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03671928</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>18-AOI-12</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03671928</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study of Circulating Levels of Glicentin</brief_title>
  <acronym>GLICENTINEDIGE</acronym>
  <official_title>Study of Circulating Glicentin Levels in Patients With Intestinal Ischemia</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Centre Hospitalier Universitaire de Nice</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Centre Hospitalier Universitaire de Nice</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Hormones derived from proglucagon represent a family of peptides produced by the alpha cells
      of the pancreas and by the intestinal L cells. In the pancreas, the maturation of proglucagon
      mainly leads to the synthesis of glucagon, while in the intestine, the cleavage of
      proglucagon allows the synthesis of different peptides including glicentine, oxyntomodulin,
      Glucagon Like Peptide-1 (GLP-1) and Glucagon Like Peptide-2 (GLP-2).

      Glicentin is produced by L cells throughout the digestive tract, from the small intestine to
      the rectum, with a majority secretion in the colon. Studies in humans and animals have shown
      its role in the intestinal mucosa. It has a stimulating effect on the proliferation of the
      intestinal mucosa as well as an effect on smooth muscle cells and regulates trophicity and
      intestinal motility. Its circulating rate could be modified in case of intestinal ischemia.
      Mesenteric ischemia is a major diagnostic problem with high morbidity and mortality,
      particularly in the event of delayed treatment.

      The sensitivity and specificity of current markers are low. The identification of new
      biomarkers of the disease would improve the diagnosis and management of patients with the
      disease.

      The objective of the project is to determine a difference in circulating glicentin levels in
      patients with intestinal ischemia versus a control group.

      On this prospective monocentric study, 40 patients with digestive ischemia will be included
      in the Emergency Department of the University Hospital of Nice. A control group of 40
      patients with abdominal pain will be formed. The circulating glicentin levels will be
      measured on serum by Elisa technique at the Biochemistry Laboratory of the University
      Hospital of Nice, work that has been published in 3 scientific journals allowing us to
      develop and validate the technique.The staff will determine whether patients with digestive
      ischemia have impaired serum glicentin levels.

      The evaluation of the interest of new biological markers of mesenteric ischemia such as
      glicentine would constitute a definite diagnostic advance. This project could eventually
      offer new diagnostic and/or therapeutic perspectives in the management of these patients.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">January 15, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 15, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 15, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>difference of at least 20% of the serum glicentin dosage in the &quot;intestinal ischemia&quot; group versus the &quot;control&quot; volunteers.</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>glicentine dosage</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">80</enrollment>
  <condition>Ischemia Bowel</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>bowel ischemia</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>non-digestive abdominal pain</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>additional blood tube</intervention_name>
    <description>sampling of an additional tube at the usual blood test to determine the glicentin level</description>
    <arm_group_label>bowel ischemia</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>non-digestive abdominal pain</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>additional blood sample</intervention_name>
    <description>for le group control, another blood sample is taken outside the usual care.</description>
    <arm_group_label>non-digestive abdominal pain</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  For patients with intestinal ischemia

          -  The combination of abdominal pain, altered general condition with abdominal defence
             and venous or arterial hyperlactatemia will be signs suggestive of a diagnosis of
             digestive ischemia.

          -  Patients suspected of digestive ischemia with the following comorbidities may be
             included as clinical suspicion and excluded post-operatively: emboligenic heart
             disease, arteriopathy, aortic and/or digestive atheromatosis.

          -  Patients with suspected digestive ischemia and functional scanning ileus.

          -  Patients with intestinal ischemia proven by CT scan with contrast injection: arterial
             abnormality such as dissection of an artery for digestive use, thrombosis or embolism
             of an artery for digestive use; intestinal or colonic thickening suggestive of
             reversible ischemic suffering of the digestive tract; parietal pneumatosis;
             gastrointestinal parietal enhancement abnormality (hypo-density ranges or total
             absence of enhancement).

        The following pathologies will be taken into account: mesenteric ischemia by embolism or
        thrombosis.

          -  Age over 18 years old

          -  Able to understand the study

          -  Affiliation to a social security system

          -  Signing of an informed consent

          -  Accept participation in the study (collection of a Non-Opposition)

        For the control group

          -  Age over 18 years old

          -  Able to understand the study

          -  Affiliation to a social security system

          -  Signing of an informed consent

          -  No personal history of colorectal cancer and obesity

          -  Admission to the Emergency Department of the University Hospital of Nice for abdominal
             pain with EVA &gt; 3/10 of non-intestinal origin: nephritic colic, hepatobiliary
             pathology, gynaecological disease, etc.

          -  Abdominal CT excluding digestive tract pathology

          -  Accept participation in the study

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  History of bariatric or digestive surgery (stomach, small intestine, colon or rectum)

          -  History of chronic inflammatory bowel disease

          -  Obese patients (BMI&gt; 30kg/m2)

          -  History of type 1 diabetes or insulin treatment
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Damien MASSALOU</last_name>
    <phone>33492038614</phone>
    <email>massalou.d@chu-nice.fr</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Nice Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nice</city>
        <zip>06000</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Damien MASSALOU</last_name>
      <phone>33492038614</phone>
      <email>massalou.d@chu-nice.fr</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Damien MASSALOU</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 13, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 13, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 14, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 14, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 14, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">September 17, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Ischemia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

