<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03671434</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>00010061</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03671434</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluation of the Research to Policy Collaboration Model</brief_title>
  <acronym>RPC</acronym>
  <official_title>Testing an Approach to Improve the Use of Evidence</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Penn State University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>William T. Grant Foundation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Penn State Social Science Research Insititute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>London School of Hygiene and Tropical Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Child Trends</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Penn State University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This work aims to evaluate an approach for improving federal legislators' use of
      evidence—known as the Research-to-Policy Collaboration (RPC) - which seeks to address known
      barriers to policymakers' use of research, including a lack of personal contact between
      researchers and policymakers and limited relevance of research translation efforts to current
      policy priorities. The RPC involves structured processes for identifying policymakers'
      priorities, building researchers' capacity for nonpartisan responses to current policy
      priorities, and facilitating ongoing and productive researcher-policymaker interactions. This
      implementation of the RPC will focus on child and family policies relevant to child
      maltreatment.

      This study assesses both processes for collaboration and policymakers' use of research within
      a randomized controlled trial (RCT) employing a mixed methods approach—including quantitative
      and qualitative evaluation of impact. The proposed project will be guided by three
      overarching questions:

        1. How does the RPC impact researchers and legislative staff?

        2. How does the RPC impact legislative activity?

        3. How might perceptions and experiences of collaboration through the RPC relate to
           different forms of evidence use among researchers and policymakers?

      The RPC's effectiveness will be tested through experimental design (randomization) using
      qualitative and quantitative assessments of researcher-policymaker interactions and impact.
      This includes surveying congressional staff and researchers, reviewing records of
      policymaker's public statements and introduced legislation, and conducting qualitative
      interviews around researchers' and legislative staffs' experiences with
      researcher-policymaker collaboration prior to and during the RPC.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Objective: The aim of this study is to examine the effectiveness of a model for supporting
      policymakers' use of research evidence within a randomized controlled trial (RCT) employing
      both qualitative and quantitative analyses of survey, interview, and observational data to
      understand the use of research in policy and collaboration. Legislators' research use will be
      assessed with multiple methods, including (1) self-report via a survey protocol, (2)
      legislative activity (i.e., introduced bills and official statements), and (3) qualitative
      interviews. Additionally, interviews and surveys will assess researchers' reported efficacy,
      skill and engagement in public policy, and the extent to which their work is informed by the
      policy process.

      Intervention: The Research-to-Policy Collaboration (RPC) builds upon theoretical and
      empirical literature that suggests the need to (a) translate research relevant to current
      policy priorities, and (b) facilitate productive interactions between policymakers and
      researchers. The RPC is a nonpartisan, manualized model implemented by an intermediary
      organization that cultivates relationships between researchers and legislative offices.
      Implementation occurs in two phases involving a series of seven interrelated activities.
      During the capacity-building phase, the RPC simultaneously aims to support researcher's
      development of honest knowledge broker skills with training and coaching, while also
      conducting iterative needs assessments with congressional offices regarding their current
      priorities and desire for research evidence. In the collaboration phase, researchers with
      relevant expertise are coalesced into rapid response teams that are matched with legislative
      offices. Through a scaffolded series of interactions, the RPC model is used to cultivate
      productive researcher-policymaker relationships and support responses to legislative
      requests. Evaluating the effectiveness of the RPC is the focus of the current study.

      Study Design:

      This study employs both qualitative and quantitative analyses of survey, interview, and
      observational data within the context of an RCT. Three overarching research questions guide
      this work and align with the study's three different components - self-report via a
      quantitative survey, observation of research use via coded legislative activity, and
      ethnography via in-depth interviews and participant observations.

        1. How does the RPC impact researchers and legislative staff? (Self-Report)

             1. Do researchers report improved policy competencies and motivation for conducting
                policy-relevant research?

             2. Will legislative staff report increases in positive attitudes toward, knowledge of,
                intended application, and actual use of research evidence?

             3. Might the impact on legislative and research participants will vary as a function
                of aspects of their collaborative relationship (e.g., enhanced by mutual trust)?

        2. How does the RPC impact legislative activity? (Observation)

           a) Will congressional offices increase their use of research evidence in legislative
           activities (i.e., bills, official statements)?

        3. How might perceptions and experiences of collaboration through the RPC relate to
           different forms of evidence use among researchers and policymakers? (Ethnography)

             1. What are the barriers and facilitators of participation in the RPC?

             2. What types of interactions between researchers and policymakers does the RPC
                influence?

             3. How does the RPC affect participants' assumptions about each other, interactions
                with each other, and their intentions?

             4. What types of evidence use are supported by RPC participation?

      Sampling Framework All study components draw from an initial sampling framework through which
      researchers and congressional staff who opt into participating in the RPC will be asked to
      participate in the study; those who agree to participate in the study will be randomized for
      either the full RPC intervention or a light-touch control group that receives little direct
      engagement. This study will oversample to combat anticipated attrition. The final sample is
      expected to include 60 congressional offices (30 in RPC, 30 in control group) and 60
      researchers (30 in RPC, 30 in control group). These samples will be derived from an
      identified population of eligible intervention participants.

        -  A population of relevant legislative offices (Senate and House) will be identified based
           on the number of child/family bills legislator have (co)sponsored. The random selection
           process will be stratified to ensure proportional partisan representation and
           representation of legislators who range in activity related to child welfare. Prior to
           randomization, the population of relevant legislators will be assigned an Activity
           Ranking based on the number of times a legislator has sponsored a child/family policy
           bill. Activity Rankings will range from 1-10 such that 10% of legislators who
           (co)sponsored the fewest bills will be ranked 1, and 10% of legislators who co-sponsored
           the most bills will be ranked 10. Recruitment and stratified sampling across a continuum
           of activity on child/family policy will improve bipartisan representation of the sample.
           Also aiding with bipartisan representation are targeted outreach efforts that intensify
           along party lines if participation becomes skewed.

        -  Researchers who work on relevant child/family research will be identified via research
           institutions, professional networks and listservs, literature searches, and referrals
           from other researchers. Researchers include research-oriented practitioners and program
           evaluators from both academic and non-academic settings who are interested in
           translating their expertise with policymakers. Subsequent to opting-in to participate in
           a policy engagement intervention, researchers are asked to participate in the study.
           Study participants will be randomized to receive the RPC or the control condition.

      Study Component 1: Quantitative Evaluation of Self-Reported RPC Impact A structured survey
      will be used to assess researchers' capacity for engaging in public policy processes. A
      corresponding survey protocol will assess legislative staff's attitudes, knowledge, intent,
      and reported behavior regarding the use of research evidence. Both researchers and
      legislative staff will be asked about the nature of their collaborative interactions with one
      another. Surveys will be conducted approximately every three months. Survey constructs are
      described in outcome measures. Missing data will be handled with multiple imputation because
      this is best practice when data are not missing at random. Multilevel modelling will be used
      to examine individual trajectories in outcome variables. Multiple regression will examine
      changes between select time points; for instance, whether researchers' reported policy skills
      improve between baseline and subsequent to trainings. These analyses will allow us to examine
      whether RPC participation is associated with increases in (1) researchers' reported efficacy
      to engage with policymakers, (2) legislative staff's interest and willingness to use research
      evidence, and (3) both researchers' and policymakers' positive sentiment toward working
      together. Longitudinal analyses will further allow us to explore the trajectory of outcome
      variables over time (e.g., improved researcher competencies, legislators' use of
      research)—specifically modelling change in evidence use and other outcomes of interest.
      Analyses of researcher and legislative staff outcomes are all powered at least at a 90% level
      to detect effect sizes of 0.2 or greater (power analysis conducted with Optimal Design plus
      Empirical Evidence).

      Study Component 2: Quantitative Evaluation of Observed RPC Impact on Legislative Activity To
      complement the self-reported quantitative assessment of change, use of research evidence in
      legislative activities will be observed before and following RPC participation. Data will be
      selected, extracted, and coded prior to quantitative analyses with indicators derived from
      deductive codes. Legislative data will be selected based upon the use of keywords indicating
      relevance to child/family. Since each bill will comprise more text than is feasible to code
      with traditional qualitative methods, relevant provisions will be extracted prior to coding
      (those containing keywords). Further, all subsection titles for each sampled bill will be
      reviewed for potential relevance and extracted if research evidence is used but not captured
      otherwise by keywords. Data on legislative activity will be coded based on a detailed
      codebook informed by prior findings of how research has been used by policymakers and in
      legislation. This coding scheme will be applied by two coders and the codebook will be
      revised and further specified until the intercoder reliability reaches at least .70 and 30%
      of the data for the first time period has been coded. Subsequently, trained coders will code
      individually and a lead investigator will randomly sample 10% of these to ensure consistency
      in coding quality. These codes will be converted into quantitative indicators of research
      use, which are described in outcome measures. Legislative activity will be assessed annually.
      Multivariate Poisson regression analyses will assess change in research use in thematic codes
      of (1) bills and (2) official statements between the RPC intervention and control conditions.
      Moderation analyses will further explore the extent to which changes in legislative activity
      depend on the nature of collaboration experiences, other survey data (e.g., policymakers'
      perceptions of the value of research), and legislator characteristics (e.g., party
      affiliation, years of age).

      Study Component 3: Ethnographic Evaluation of the RPC model The qualitative component of this
      study is closely linked with the quantitative work and seeks to better understand the
      experiences of RPC participants and processes underlying the use of research evidence in the
      RPC context. Using participatory and ethnographic methods, data will be collected from two
      sources: (1) semi-structured interviews of trial participants and RPC staff, and (2)
      observations of researcher trainings and researcher-staff meetings. Interview participants
      will be sampled from the pool of study participants randomly assigned to receive the RPC,
      including 11 RPC researchers and 11 RPC congressional office staff that will be interviewed
      prior to their involvement in the RPC, and 11 RPC researchers and 11 congressional office
      staff that will be interviewed following collaboration activities via the RPC. Additionally,
      3 RPC staff will be interviewed prior to and following the RPC. To gain additional insight
      into the RPC operations and impact, observations will be conducted of trainings for
      researchers, formal meetings and informal interactions between researchers and congressional
      staff, and meetings that occur as part of any RPC collaboration. Following ethnographic best
      practices, &quot;open-observations&quot; of key meetings and training events will be conducted to
      enrich the interviews with more information about how attendees interact and how they respond
      to the RPC. Field notes and transcripts will be analysed with thematic analysis and an
      interpretive policy analysis that explores different rationalities and rhetoric when
      discussing evidence used in the collaboration.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 8, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 31, 2025</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 31, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Participants will be randomly assigned to either a comprehensive intervention or a control group that receives minimal intervention.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>Participants: Participants will not be informed of their status as part of an intervention or control group.
Provider: No masking
Investigator: No masking
Outcome Assessor: Survey data will indicate intervention assignment; observational data will be masked such that document coders will not be aware of the condition associated with coded documents.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Reported Use of Evidence</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed multiple times through study completion, an average of one year.</time_frame>
    <description>Congressional study participants will be asked how often they have accessed research and used research in decision-making processes in the past 3 months.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Evidence Sources</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed multiple times through study completion, an average of one year.</time_frame>
    <description>Congressional study participants will be asked what sources (e.g., personal contacts, academic journals) use to obtain evidence on policy issues.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Interactions with Researchers</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed multiple times through study completion, an average of one year.</time_frame>
    <description>Congressional study participants will be asked how often they have interacted with researchers in different settings in the past 3 months.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Attitudes and Readiness Regarding Evidence Use</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed multiple times through study completion, an average of one year.</time_frame>
    <description>Congressional study participants will be asked how valuable research is perceived by the staff and within the congressional office as a whole, as well as perceived benefit of social science specifically.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Policy Engagement</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed multiple times through study completion, an average of one year.</time_frame>
    <description>Researcher study participants will be asked how frequently they have engaged with policymakers in different activities and at different stages of the policy process.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Policy-Informed Research</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed multiple times through study completion, an average of one year.</time_frame>
    <description>Researcher study participants will be asked their perceived value in engaging policymakers in the research process, the extent to which their research activities are informed or guided by policymakers' needs, and the extent to which researchers have actively engaged policymakers in the research process in the last 3 months.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Policy-Related Self-Efficacy</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed multiple times through study completion, an average of one year.</time_frame>
    <description>Researcher study participants will be asked how confident and prepared they feel about engaging with policymakers.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Reported Policy Knowledge</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed multiple times through study completion, an average of one year.</time_frame>
    <description>Researcher study participants will be asked the extent to which they understand policy processes and norms, and the degree to which they perceive a need for additional policy training.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Official Statement Research Use</measure>
    <time_frame>Bills that were introduced one year prior to the RPC implementation, during the implementation period and one year following the RPC completion.</time_frame>
    <description>Legislators' public statements will be dichotomously coded to indicate any type of research use. These statement-level indicators will be aggregated by legislator.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Research Use in Legislation</measure>
    <time_frame>Bills that were introduced one year prior to the RPC implementation, during the implementation period and one year during or following the RPC completion.</time_frame>
    <description>Child/Family bills will be dichotomously coded to indicate any type of research use. These statement-level indicators are then aggregated by legislator.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Intensive Research Use in Legislation</measure>
    <time_frame>Bills that were introduced one year prior to the RPC implementation, during the implementation period and one year during or following the RPC completion.</time_frame>
    <description>Each section in child/family bills will be dichotomously coded to indicate any type of research use. Each bill will be scored to indicate a proportion of sections in which evidence is used out of the sum of sections in the bill. These statement-level indicators are then aggregated by legislator.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Type of Use in Legislation</measure>
    <time_frame>Bills that were introduced one year prior to the RPC implementation, during the implementation period and one year during or following the RPC completion.</time_frame>
    <description>Child/family bills will be dichotomously coded to indicate the observation of different types of research use (e.g., conceptual, instrumental). These statement-level indicators are then aggregated by legislator.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Satisfaction with Collaboration</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed during the collaboration component of the intervention or up to one year after study initiation.</time_frame>
    <description>Both researcher and congressional study participants will be asked about the quality of the collaborative interactions, such as the adequacy of communication and working styles of fellow collaborators.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Perceived Value of the Partnership</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed during the collaboration component of the intervention or up to one year after study initiation.</time_frame>
    <description>Both researcher and congressional study participants will be asked the extent to which the partnership was valuable in relation to time investment and would be worth recommending or doing again.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Perceived Impact of the Collaboration</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed during the collaboration component of the intervention or up to one year after study initiation.</time_frame>
    <description>Both researcher and congressional study participants will be asked the extent to which the collaboration improved aspects of participants' work, mutual understanding, or addressed needs and common goals.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Trust and Respect</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed during the collaboration component of the intervention or up to one year after study initiation.</time_frame>
    <description>Both researcher and congressional study participants will be asked about their perceptions of the quality of their interactions with collaborative partners, including comfort, trust, shared commitment, and conflict management.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">120</enrollment>
  <condition>Legislation</condition>
  <condition>Policy</condition>
  <condition>Child Abuse</condition>
  <condition>Family and Household</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>RPC Researchers</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Researchers who are assigned to the experimental group that is eligible to receive the full RPC intervention</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>RPC Congressional Offices</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Congressional offices that are assigned to the experimental group that is eligible to receive the full RPC intervention</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control Researchers</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Researchers who are assigned to an Active Comparator control group that is enrolled in a light-touch intervention</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control Congressional Offices</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Congressional offices that are assigned to the control group that receives no intervention</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Research-to-Policy Collaboration</intervention_name>
    <description>The RPC is a behavioral intervention through which RPC Researchers and RPC Congressional Offices are prepared and matched for collaboration. Specifically, congressional offices are asked to identify opportunities for researcher engagement in policy efforts, researchers with expertise related to policy opportunities are identified and prepared to collaborate with congressional offices, researchers and congressional staff are matched for ongoing collaborative partnerships, and both researchers and congressional staff receive ongoing support to facilitate research translation.</description>
    <arm_group_label>RPC Congressional Offices</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>RPC Researchers</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Light Touch Policy Training</intervention_name>
    <description>Control Researchers are provided information on policy engagement via email.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control Researchers</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Participants who voluntarily enlist in the RPC will be asked to participate in the
             trial.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Participants who choose to stop participating in the study or the RPC itself. All
             study participants can choose to opt-out of the study at any time.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>D. Max Crowley, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Penn State University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>J. Taylor Scott, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Penn State University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>D. Max Crowley, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <phone>1-866-905-1872</phone>
    <email>dmc397@psu.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>J. Taylor Scott, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <phone>864-431-2411</phone>
    <email>jxs1622@psu.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Child Trends</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20814</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Lauren Supplee, Ph.D.</last_name>
      <phone>240-223-9200</phone>
      <email>lsupplee@childtrends.org</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Elizabeth Jordan, J.D.</last_name>
      <phone>240-223-9200</phone>
      <email>ejordan@childtrends.org</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Penn State University</name>
      <address>
        <city>University Park</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>16802</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>D. Max Crowley, Ph.D.</last_name>
      <phone>866-905-1872</phone>
      <email>dmc397@psu.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>J. Taylor Scott, Ph.D.</last_name>
      <phone>864-431-2411</phone>
      <email>jxs1622@psu.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>London School of Hygiene &amp; Tropical Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>London</city>
        <zip>WC1E 7HT</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Kathryn Oliver, Ph.D.</last_name>
      <phone>x2232</phone>
      <email>Kathryn.Oliver@lshtm.ac.uk</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://research2policy.org</url>
    <description>Describes the intervention</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Crowley M, Scott JTB, Fishbein D. Translating Prevention Research for Evidence-Based Policymaking: Results from the Research-to-Policy Collaboration Pilot. Prev Sci. 2018 Feb;19(2):260-270. doi: 10.1007/s11121-017-0833-x.</citation>
    <PMID>28849362</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Scott JT, Larson JC, Buckingham SL, Maton KI, Crowley DM. Bridging the research-policy divide: Pathways to engagement and skill development. Am J Orthopsychiatry. 2019;89(4):434-441. doi: 10.1037/ort0000389.</citation>
    <PMID>31305112</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 7, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 12, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 14, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 8, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 8, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 9, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Penn State University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Daniel Max Crowley</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor of Human Development and Family Studies</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Research</keyword>
  <keyword>Knowledge Translation</keyword>
  <keyword>Knowledge Management</keyword>
  <keyword>Health Policy</keyword>
  <keyword>Social Policy</keyword>
  <keyword>Public Policy</keyword>
  <keyword>Policy Makers</keyword>
  <keyword>Legislation as Topic</keyword>
  <keyword>Evidence-based Policy</keyword>
  <keyword>Use of Research Evidence</keyword>
  <keyword>Dissemination</keyword>
  <keyword>Policy Training</keyword>
  <keyword>Collaboration</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Data dictionaries and all collected IPD will be stripped of identifiers and may be made available upon request.</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Statistical Analysis Plan (SAP)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Informed Consent Form (ICF)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Analytic Code</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>Anonymous IPD may be shared following or during the publication of summary data. Archival data may be accessed for up to 10 years following the end of the study.</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>Those who request the anonymous IPD must provide a plan of study explaining how the data will be used. Requests may be sent to the Central Contact Person or Central Contact Backup. Requests will be reviewed based on the potential for the planned use of the IPD for advancing scientific knowledge and theory.</ipd_access_criteria>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

