<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03673592</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IGX14-MOS-AC-18-03</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03673592</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Clinical Value of Mosaicism Diagnosis on the Trophectoderm Biopsies</brief_title>
  <acronym>NS-MOSAICISM</acronym>
  <official_title>Prospective Non-selection Study to Investigate the Clinical Predictive Value of Chromosome Copy Number Values Consistent With the Presence of Mosaicism Within the Trophectoderm Biopsy (NON-SELECTION MOSAICISM)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Igenomix</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Igenomix</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Mosaicism within an embryo is defined as the presence of two or more cell populations with
      different genotypes. Blastocysts classified as mosaic by Preimplamtation Genetic Testing for
      Aneuploidy (PGT-A) have been reported to implant less and miscarry more frequently than
      embryos classified as euploid. Because of the unknown impact of mosaicism on embryo
      development, these embryos are given low priority and are discarded for transfer. However,
      recent papers on the transfer of human embryos classified by PGT-A as mosaic suggest that
      embryos with a low fraction of abnormal cells resulting in viable, chromosomally normal
      ongoing pregnancies, and high-level mosaics resulting in fewer viable pregnancies, but so far
      none producing mosaic babies.

      The apparent presence of mosaicism in an embryo is used as a selection criteria for embryo
      transfer (ET), introducing a strong bias in terms of patient prognosis and embryo quality.
      Additionally, it is also possible that some embryos are incorrectly classified as &quot;mosaic&quot;
      due to technical variability derived from the processing of a uniform aneuploid embryo.

      The aims of this study is to provide evidences about the clinical significance of chromosomal
      mosaicism in PGT-A cycles by a prospective non-selection based methodology.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      One of the most common reasons why in vitro fertilization (IVF) is unsuccessful, or why
      miscarriages occur, is because of chromosomal abnormalities in the embryo. Embryos with less
      than 20% aneuploidy are considered as euploid, while those between 20-80% are reported as
      mosaic, and those over 80% as aneuploid. Embryos with the correct number of chromosomes
      (euploid) have a higher chance of leading to a successful pregnancy than those with the
      incorrect number of chromosomes (aneuploid) or mosaics.

      Mosaicism within an embryo is defined as the presence of two or more cell populations with
      different genotypes. Preliminary data suggested that embryos identified as mosaic by
      Preimplamtation Genetic Testing for Aneuploidy (PGT-A) may have a reduced chance of
      implantation compared with euploid and may play a significant role in pregnancy loss.

      Because of the unknown impact of mosaicism on embryo development, these embryos are given low
      priority and are discarded for transfer. They are transferred mostly in poor prognosis
      patients, explaining the reported lower clinical performances. However, other recent data
      regarding the transfer of embryos diagnosed as mosaic has shown that embryos with a low
      fraction of abnormal cells may result in viable, chromosomally normal ongoing pregnancies.

      The apparent presence of mosaicism in an embryo is used as a selection criteria for embryo
      transfer (ET), introducing a strong bias in terms of patient prognosis and embryo quality.
      Additionally, it is also possible that some embryos are incorrectly classified as mosaic due
      to technical variability derived from the processing of a uniform aneuploid embryo. Thus,
      there is an urgent need to understand how to appropriately select and counsel patients
      regarding such embryos.

      This study aims to provide evidences about the clinical significance of chromosomal mosaicism
      in PGT-A cycles by a prospective non-selection based methodology.

      The objectives are to investigate the clinical predictive value for intermediate copy number
      results consistent with the presence of low mosaicism in TE biopsies, and to validate the
      thresholds for the classification of embryos in relation with their reproductive potential,
      providing comprehensive data for clinicians and patients.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 3, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Sustained implantation rate</measure>
    <time_frame>20 weeks after the embryo transfer</time_frame>
    <description>Presence of a viable pregnancy after 20 weeks of gestation measured by ultrasound scan</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Miscarriage rate</measure>
    <time_frame>20 weeks after the embryo transfer</time_frame>
    <description>The spontaneous loss of an intra-uterine pregnancy prior to 20 completed weeks of gestational age.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>4</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">878</enrollment>
  <condition>Aneuploidy</condition>
  <condition>Chromosome Abnormality</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Euploid embryos analyzed by PGT-A</arm_group_label>
    <description>Embryos with a normal chromosome copy number. This embryos will be transferred to the uterus.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Low-grade mosaic embryos (PGT-A)</arm_group_label>
    <description>Embryos with a lower aneuploidy percentage (&lt;50%). This embryos will be considered for transfer to the uterus.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>High-grade mosaic embryos (PGT-A)</arm_group_label>
    <description>Embryos with a high aneuploidy percentage (50-70%). This embryos will be discarded for transfer.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Aneuploid embryos analyzed by PGT-A</arm_group_label>
    <description>Embryos with an abnormal number of chromosomes. This embryos will be discarded for transfer.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>PGT-A</intervention_name>
    <description>PGT-A will be carried out following the usual clinical practice: Trophectoderm biopsy samples from blastocysts are analyzed by NGS to screen for numerical chromosomal abnormalities.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Aneuploid embryos analyzed by PGT-A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Euploid embryos analyzed by PGT-A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>High-grade mosaic embryos (PGT-A)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Low-grade mosaic embryos (PGT-A)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      DNA analysis of each patient's embryos
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Embryos from In Vitro Fertilization (IVF) patients up to 44 years old (also included) with
        medical indication of PGT-A and own oocytes.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  PGT-A cases for any medical indication and sign the written informed consent form
             approved by the Ethics Committee (EC) after having been duly informed of the nature of
             the research and voluntarily accepted to participate in the study.

          -  Only PGT-A cycles with own oocytes.

          -  Female age up to 44 years old (also included).

          -  ICSI treatment must be done in all oocytes.

          -  Have at least one euploid blastocyst or one low-grade mosaicism diagnosis for a single
             chromosome after PGT-A analysis (excluding aneuploidies compatible with life, e.g.
             chromosomes 13, 18, 21 and X/Y).

          -  Single or Double Embryo Transfer (SET or DET). The patient remains included in the
             study until the 4th ET (fresh or frozen) from the initial stimulation cycle or until
             patient's enrolment period ends (whichever comes first). The data collected until one
             of these points will be included in the study, whilst clinical outcomes from
             additional ET will be disregarded.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  No embryo reaching blastocyst stage with a proper morphology for trophectoderm biopsy.

          -  Embryo transfer coming from the worst grade blastocyst morphology according to
             Gardner's criteria (Annex 1) will be excluded.

          -  DET resulting in singletons. (Note: DET resulting in dizygotic twins or implantation
             failure to the both embryos transferred will be allowed).

          -  Any illness or medical condition that is unstable or can put patient safety at risk
             and compliance in the study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <gender_based>Yes</gender_based>
    <gender_description>Embryos from IVF patients up to 44 years of age (also included) undergoing PGT-A.</gender_description>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>44 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Antonio Capalbo, BSc PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Igenomix S.L.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Antonio Capalbo, BSc PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+39 0424472449</phone>
    <email>antonio.capalbo@igenomix.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Demetra</name>
      <address>
        <city>Florence</city>
        <zip>50141</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Claudia Livi, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+39 055 488709</phone>
      <email>livi@centrodemetra.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Genera</name>
      <address>
        <city>Roma</city>
        <zip>00197</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Laura Rienzi, MD PhD</last_name>
      <phone>+39 063269791</phone>
      <email>rienzi@generaroma.it</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Humanitas Fertility Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Roma</city>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Paolo Levi Setti, MD PhD</last_name>
      <phone>+39 282244500</phone>
      <email>paolo.levi_setti@humanitas.it</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Italy</country>
  </location_countries>
  <removed_countries>
    <country>Mexico</country>
  </removed_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 13, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 14, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 17, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 6, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 6, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 7, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Mosaicism</keyword>
  <keyword>PGT-A</keyword>
  <keyword>Blastocyst biopsy</keyword>
  <keyword>Aneuploidy testing</keyword>
  <keyword>Preimplantation genetics</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Chromosome Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Aneuploidy</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Chromosome Aberrations</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

