<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03677128</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Pro00094010</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>1R21CA217268-01A1</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03677128</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Mobile Health Case Management System for Reducing Pediatric Treatment Abandonment</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Mobile Health (mHealth) Case Management System for Reducing Pediatric Cancer Treatment Abandonment</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Duke University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Duke University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Digital case management systems have the potential to increase compliance with
      protocol-driven treatment, reduce treatment abandonment and ultimately help to close the
      discrepancy in pediatric cancer outcomes between Low and Middle Income Countries (LMICs) and
      high-income countries (HICs). The investigators aim to adapt an open-source digital case
      management platform to incorporate standardized pediatric oncology protocols. Effectiveness
      will be evaluated by provider protocol compliance (primary outcome) and patient treatment
      abandonment rates using the digital case management system as compared to historic controls.
      The study population will include patients diagnosed with Burkitt lymphoma or retinoblastoma
      at Bugando Medical Centre in Tanzania.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Each year, approximately 220,000 children globally are newly diagnosed with cancer. Over 85%
      of these new diagnoses are made in low- and middle-income countries (LMICs). Survival rates
      in LMICs are 5-25% compared to 80% in high-income countries (HICs). One of the primary
      contributors to the discrepancy in survival outcomes between LMICs and HICs is a high rate of
      treatment abandonment, defined as refusal to initiate or failure to complete curative
      treatment. Treatment abandonment rate in Tanzania is higher than in other LMICs (40% compared
      to 10-25%), directly impacting patient survival. In HICs, protocol-driven treatment for
      children with cancer has led to increased treatment compliance and large improvements in
      survival. However, it is often not feasible or appropriate to use protocol-driven treatment
      in LMICs without necessary supportive care, human resources and infrastructure. Not
      surprisingly, protocol-related compliance is lower in LMICs compared to HICs. Digital
      technologies for health (i.e., digital health) can facilitate implementation of and
      compliance with standardized pediatric oncology protocols through step-by-step decision
      support algorithms, reminders and alerts related to patient visits, and timely data for
      health service coordination with allied health providers (e.g., nurses, pharmacists etc.).
      This multidisciplinary team from Duke University and Dimagi Inc. in USA, and Bugando Medical
      Center (BMC) in Tanzania, proposes to adapt, implement, and evaluate a digital case
      management system, called mNavigator, at BMC to improve health provider compliance with
      standardized pediatric oncology protocols.

      For Aim 1, mNavigator development will initially focus on the two nationally-approved
      protocols for Burkitt lymphoma and retinoblastoma. Using principles of persuasive system
      design and the Consolidated Framework for Implementation Research (CFIR), prompts that guide
      users through protocol implementation will be used as behavioral triggers to assist with
      perceived ease of use.

      For Aim 2, allied health providers at BMC will receive training on using mNavigator as part
      of an in-country workshop led by the M-PIs. This training will be followed by supported
      implementation. Following this training period, mNavigator will be used to enroll pediatric
      patients at BMC with pre-clinical diagnosis of BL or Rb, over a period of 1 year and manage
      their care for the duration of treatment (up to 3 months for BL and 4 months for Rb). BMC
      receives and treats approximately 150 patients every year, with an estimated 50 patients with
      Burkitt lymphoma (BL) and Rb. To review historic compliance, files of patients diagnosed
      after 2015 with BL and Rb (when protocols were introduced) will be abstracted by trained
      research assistants. Compliance with protocol-driven treatment will be monitored using
      mNavigator. System functionality will be assessed. Semi-structured assessments of provider
      system acceptance and usability will be conducted along with elucidating caregiver reported
      barriers to treatment completion.

      Secondary objective is to describe factors that facilitate or inhibit implementation of
      mNavigator.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 23, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Effects on outcomes when using mNaviagtor will be compared to historical controls (preceding mNavigator use). Number of participants below references those who will be consented prospectively to participate in the study.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Health Services Research</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Protocol compliance</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage difference in protocol compliance with mNavigator and historical compliance.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to diagnosis (in days)</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>The number of days to diagnosis using mNavigator compared to historical controls. Time to diagnosis is computed as the duration (in days) from registration to diagnosis.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Treatment abandonment</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Calculated as the difference in proportion of patients registered in mNavigator who abandon treatment compared to historical controls who abandon treatment. Treatment abandonment is defined as missing 4 or more consecutive weeks of treatment or follow-up while on therapy.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Treatment completion</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Calculated as the proportion of patients registered in mNavigator who completed treatment (excludes patient deaths).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>System usability scale score</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>System usability scale (SUS) score ranging from 0-100 measured using a 10-point validated system usability scale. A SUS score above 68 is considered above average usability.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Monthly utilization of mNavigator</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Number of forms submitted using mNavigator, stratified, by users, per month of implementation.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of patients registered in mNavigator during study period</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Number of patients registered in mNavigator during study period</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of instances of mNavigator failure per month (all-causes)</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Number of instances of mNavigator failure per month (all-causes)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of instances of CommCare failure per month (all-causes)</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Number of instances of CommCare failure per month (all-causes)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of instances of device failure per month (all-causes)</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Number of instances of device failure per month (all-causes)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of hours of initial training as well as hours of ongoing support provided during the first month of implementation</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Number of hours of initial training as well as hours of ongoing support provided during the first month of implementation</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of users who are proficient in use of mNavigator within first month of implementation</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Number of users who are proficient in use of mNavigator within first month of implementation</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Average time in minutes spent completing each form, stratified by form</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Average time in minutes spent completing each form, stratified by form</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time per patient</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Total time in minutes spent entering patient data in mNavigator, from time of registration until an outcome is recorded. Calculated by summing time for completing each form, by patient.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">65</enrollment>
  <condition>Burkitt Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Retinoblastoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>mNavigator</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Allied health providers will use mNavigator to guide diagnosis and treatment for pediatric cancer patients at Bugando Medical Centre (BMC).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Historical controls</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>BL/Rb retrospective patients (treated between 2015-2019) when standardized treatment protocols for BL and Rb were introduced at BMC.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>mNavigator</intervention_name>
    <description>Allied health providers at BMC will use mNavigator to facilitate compliance with protocol-driven treatment and reduce patient abandonment for patients diagnosed with Burkitt lymphoma or retinoblastoma.</description>
    <arm_group_label>mNavigator</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        There are two categories of participants: Patients with Burkitt Lymphoma or retinoblastoma;
        and health providers at BMC who participate in testing and/or use of mNavigator.
        Eligibility criteria are as follows:

        A) For patients:

        *All patients will be registered in the pre-diagnosis cohort but, for the purposes of this
        study, primary and secondary outcomes will only be tracked for patients with BL or RB once
        the diagnosis is made.

        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Inclusion criteria are pediatric oncology patients diagnosed with Burkitt Lymphoma or
             Retinoblastoma under the age of 18

        Exclusion criteria:

          -  Patients older than 18 years at registration

          -  Patients with diagnoses other than Burkitt lymphoma or retinoblastoma.

        B) For providers:

        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Must be health provider or staff working at BMC who provides care for cancer patients.

          -  Must be 18 years of age or older.

        Exclusion:

        - Persons younger than 18 years of age.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Kristin Schroeder, MD MPH</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Duke University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Lavanya Vasudevan, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Duke University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Christina Makarushka, MPH</last_name>
    <phone>919-613-0154</phone>
    <email>christina.makarushka@duke.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Kristin Schroeder, MD MPH</last_name>
    <email>kristin.schroeder@duke.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Bugando Medical Centre</name>
      <address>
        <city>Mwanza</city>
        <state>Lake Zone</state>
        <country>Tanzania</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Nestory Masalu, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Tanzania</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 21, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 17, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 19, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 15, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 15, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 17, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Digital Health</keyword>
  <keyword>Pediatric Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Low and middle-income country</keyword>
  <keyword>Tanzania</keyword>
  <keyword>Healthcare provider decision support</keyword>
  <keyword>Protocol-driven treatment</keyword>
  <keyword>Burkitt lymphoma</keyword>
  <keyword>Retinoblastoma</keyword>
  <keyword>Treatment abandonment</keyword>
  <keyword>Client health records</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Burkitt Lymphoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Retinoblastoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

