<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03675451</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>1311014489</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03675451</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>PSMA Imaging of Localized Prostate Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>PSMA Imaging of Localized Prostate Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Weill Medical College of Cornell University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Weill Medical College of Cornell University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The present study is a phase II, open label, single-center, non-randomized, single-dose
      study.

      Twenty subjects in total will be enrolled at Weill Cornell Medical College (WCMC)/ NYPH.

      The primary objective is to evaluate the ability of 89Zr-Df-IAB2M to detect localized,
      clinically significant (defined as: ≥ 0.5 cm3 with Gleason pattern ≥ 4) prostate cancer
      (PCa).

      After the screening period (up to 28 days), each subject will be scheduled to receive 10 mg
      infusion of IAB2M conjugated with 2.5 mCi 89Zr-Df.

      2 - 4 days post-infusion, subjects will undergo a 89Zr-Df-IAB2M PET/CT scan. Images read by a
      Nuc Med MD reporting: location, SUV and, if possible, size of all areas with abnormal uptake.

      (they will also undergo a pelvic MRI if they have not obtained an MR image during the
      screening period or on day of infusion)

      Optional but recommended 68Ga-PSMA-HBED-CC (5±2mCi) injection and PET/CT scan (1 to 3 hours
      after the injection) will also be performed prior to radical prostatectomy depending on
      subject's availability and compliance.

      Patient will undergo radical prostatectomy after completion of above imaging procedures.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The primary endpoint of this study is the proportion of subjects with PSMA-positive
      (identified by H&amp;E staining and immunohistochemistry) &quot;dominant&quot; PC lesion(s) greater than
      5mm in diameter, whose lesion(s) have been successfully identified by 89Zr-Df-IAB2M imaging.
      Because this is an exploratory pilot study, no formal sample size/power calculation is
      required. However, with a sample size of 20 patients in the study, a two-sided 95% confidence
      interval for the proportion of patients successfully imaged by 89Zr-Df-IAB2M can be
      constructed to be within ± 19.0% of the observed proportion of patients with successful
      imaging by 89Zr-Df-IAB2M. This calculation assumes an 89Zr-Df-IAB2M imaging-success
      proportion of 75%. All estimates from the study will serve as preliminary data (i.e.,
      hypothesis-generating) for future studies.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 8, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 1, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of subjects with PSMA-positive (prostate-specific membrane antigen) &quot;dominant&quot; PC lesion(s) greater than 5mm in diameter, whose lesion(s) have been successfully identified by 89Zr-df-IAB2M imaging</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 10 Weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The proportion of subjects whose lesions have been successfully identified will be ascertained using a combination of the descriptive statistics and lesion-based analysis, which both utilize multiple measurements
Descriptive statistics: Median and inter-quartile range, or mean and standard deviation for age, biopsy Gleason score (1o, 2o, Total), number of cores and positive cores on biopsy, prostate-specific antigen, and Gleason score (1o, 2o, total) and number of lesions and lesion size on prostatectomy pathology
Lesion-based analysis: SUVmax (maximum standardized uptake value) measurements of 89Zr-df-IAB2M PET/CT (Positron emission tomography-computed tomography) images obtained in tumor and non-tumor regions will be compared. To account for intrapatient correlation of multiple lesions, a linear mixed-effects model with a random intercept will be used to estimate and compare the mean SUVmax values in different regions. P&lt;0.05 will be indicative of a significant difference</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>ability of in vivo 89Zr-df-IAb2M PET/CT (Positron emission tomography-computed tomography) to correlate with pathological features</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 10 Weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The Wilcoxon rank sum test will be used to compare lesions that were and were not identified on in vivo PET (Positron emission tomography) with respect to lesion size, immunohistochemical PSMA (prostate-specific membrane antigen) staining, and Gleason score (demonstrated by histopathology). This lesion based analysis will be performed in a similar fashion as described above.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>89Zr-df-IAb2M PET/CT (Positron emission tomography-computed tomography) and 68Ga-PSMA-HBED-CC PET/CT (Positron emission tomography-computed tomography) compared to in vivo mpMRI (multiparametric magnetic resonance imaging)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 10 Weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The diagnostic accuracy of 89Zr-df-IAB2M PET/CT Positron emission tomography-computed tomography) and 68Ga-PSMA-HBED-CC PET/CT (Positron emission tomography-computed tomography) imaging in patients with prostate cancer will be compared with that of mpMRI (multiparametric magnetic resonance imaging) imaging by using sector-based analysis. The estimates of patient-specific sensitivity and specificity will be defined as the proportion of true-positive sectors and the proportion of true-negative sectors in each patient. Overall sensitivity and specificity will then be estimated by calculating the mean (and standard error) of these individual-specific estimates across patients. Differences in sensitivity and specificity between modalities will then be evaluated by the Wilcoxon signed-rank test.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Correlation of IAB2M positivity (SUV (standardized uptake value)) and lesion size</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 10 Weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The Spearman-rank correlation coefficient will be used to evaluate the association between SUV (standardized uptake value) and size of the lesion</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Correlation of IAB2M positivity (SUV (standardized uptake value)) and Gleason pattern (3, 4 and 5)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 10 Weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The Spearman-rank correlation coefficient will be used to evaluate the association between correlate SUV (standardized uptake value) and the histopathologically defined Gleason pattern. The Wilcoxon rank-sum test will also be used to compare SUVmax (standardized uptake value) measurements between lesions with low Gleason score (3+4 or lower) and high Gleason score (4+3 or higher).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Correlation of IAB2M positivity (SUV (standardized uptake value)) and PSA (Prostate-Specific Antigen)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 10 Weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The Spearman-rank correlation coefficient will be used to evaluate the association between SUV (standardized uptake value) and serum PSA levels obtained during screening.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>the ability of in vivo 89Zr-df-IAB2M PET/CT (Positron emission tomography-computed tomography) to identify extra-prostatic extension</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 10 Weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The Wilcoxon rank-sum test will be used to compare SUVmax (standardized uptake value)measurements of IAB2M-positive extra-prostatic sites between lesions with and without histopathologically confirmed extra-prostatic extension.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>the ability of in vivo 89Zr-df-IAB2M PET/CT (Positron emission tomography-computed tomography) to identify occult lymph node involvement</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 10 Weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The Wilcoxon rank-sum test will be used to compare SUVmax (standardized uptake value) measurements of IAb2M-positive lymph nodes between patients with and without histopathologically confirmed lymph node involvement.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of Treatment-Emergent Adverse Events following 89ZR-DF-IAB2M PET/CT (Positron emission tomography-computed tomography)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 10 Weeks</time_frame>
    <description>There are no known contraindications for 89Zr-df-IAB2M. No drug related adverse events were reported in the Phase I study. Subjects will be monitored for safety for one hour following the infusion.
The 14-day sterility testing will not be completed at the time of 89Zr-df-IAB2M infusion. The 89Zr-df-IAB2M dose will be released based on the controlled process along with a history of sterile lots. Sterility tests will be evaluated during the 14-day period.
All adverse events will be recorded on a patient specific adverse event log. The AE log will be maintained by the research staff and kept in the patient's research chart.
Changes in the the following labs RFT (Renal Function Test), LFT (Liver Function Test), CBC (Complete Blood Count), CMP (comprehensive metabolic panel) will be examined, including following the parameters for toxicity throughout study participation</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of Treatment-Emergent Adverse Events following 68Ga-PSMA-HBED-CC imaging</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 10 Weeks</time_frame>
    <description>There are no known contraindications for 68Ga-PSMA-HBED-CC. Because of the potential for infusion or allergic reaction, the subject will be monitored for safety for one hour following the infusion.
All adverse events will be recorded on a patient specific adverse event log. The AE log will be maintained by the research staff and kept in the patient's research chart.
Changes in the the following labs RFT (Renal Function Test), LFT (Liver Function Test), CBC (Complete Blood Count), CMP (comprehensive metabolic panel) will be examined, including following the parameters for toxicity throughout study participation.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Prostate Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Interventional</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Injection of study drug followed by PET/CT imaging.
Optional but recommended 68Ga-PSMA-HBED-CC (5±2mCi) injection and PET/CT scan (1 to 3 hours after the injection) will also be performed prior to radical prostatectomy depending on subject's availability and compliance.
Followed by prostatectomy</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>89ZR-DF-IAB2M</intervention_name>
    <description>injection of 10 milligrams of radioactive 89Zr-Df-IAB2M followed by PET/CT scan</description>
    <arm_group_label>Interventional</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>68Ga-PSMA-HBED-CC</intervention_name>
    <description>Optional but recommended 68Ga-PSMA-HBED-CC (5±2mCi) injection and PET/CT scan (1 to 3 hours after the injection) will also be performed prior to radical prostatectomy depending on subject's availability and compliance.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Interventional</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients must have histologically or cytologically confirmed localized prostate cancer
             that are scheduled to undergo radical prostatectomy.

          -  Age &gt;18 years.

          -  Patients must have laboratory values consistent with eligibility to undergo a radical
             prostatectomy:

               -  creatinine less than or equal to 1.5 X upper limit of normal

               -  creatinine clearance &gt; 60 mL/min

          -  The effects of 89Zr-Df-IAB2M on the developing human fetus at the recommended
             therapeutic dose are unknown. For this reason, men must agree to use adequate
             contraception (hormonal or barrier method of birth control; abstinence) prior to study
             entry and for the duration of study participation. Should a woman become pregnant or
             suspect she is pregnant while her male partner is participating in this study, she
             should inform her treating physician immediately.

          -  Ability to understand and the willingness to sign a written informed consent document.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Treatment or plans for treatment with radiation therapy, surgery, chemotherapy, or
             investigational therapy between the time of conventional imaging, 89Zr-Df-IAB2M PET/CT
             and the surgical resection used for the study evaluation.

          -  Transrectal prostate biopsy performed less than four weeks prior to 89Zr-Df-IAB2M
             administration.

          -  Uncontrolled illness including, but not limited to, ongoing or active infection,
             symptomatic congestive heart failure, unstable angina pectoris, cardiac arrhythmia, or
             psychiatric illness/social situations that would limit compliance with study
             requirements.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Douglas S Scherr, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Weill Cornell Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Weill Cornell Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10065</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>December 6, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 4, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 18, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 29, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 29, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 31, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>PET/CT</keyword>
  <keyword>Imaging</keyword>
  <keyword>Nuclear Medicine</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Prostatic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

