<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03674450</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>UPCC 05518</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03674450</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Lung Heart Rate Variability</brief_title>
  <acronym>HRV</acronym>
  <official_title>A Pilot Study at a Single Institution of Heart Rate Variability Biofeedback on Lung Cancer Patients Receiving Radiation Thearpy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Abramson Cancer Center of the University of Pennsylvania</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Abramson Cancer Center of the University of Pennsylvania</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to examine the effects of heart-rate variability biofeedback
      training on lung cancer patients receiving definitive radiation therapy. The target
      population consists of non-small cell lung cancer (NSCLC) patients receiving 6 weeks of
      radiation therapy. The study will utilize the Physiolab GP8 heart rate variability and
      respiration system to collect data as well as several survey instruments to analyze quality
      of life measures. The goal is to show the HRV training can improve certain QOL measures like
      anxiety and sleep quality.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Withdrawn</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    This study never enrolled any subjects. It was terminated due to staffing and technology
    changes.
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 2, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">April 11, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">April 11, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>EORTC QLQ-C30 Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Questionnaire developed to assess the quality of life of cancer patients. The QLQ-C30 is composed of both multi-item scales and single-item measures. These include five functional scales, three symptom scales, a global health status / QoL scale, and six single items.
Each of the multi-item scales includes a different set of items - no item occurs in more than one scale. All of the scales and single-item measures range in score from 0 to 100. A high scale score represents a higher response level.Thus a high score for a functional scale represents a high / healthy level of functioning, a high score for the global health status / QoL represents a high QoL, but a high score for a symptom scale / item represents a high level of symptomatology / problems.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index (PSQI)</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Measure the quality and patterns of sleep in adults. It differentiates from &quot;poor&quot; and &quot;good&quot; sleep quality by measuring seven areas. The order of the PSQI items has been modified from the original order in order to fit the first 9 items (which are the only items that contribute to the total score). Item 10 does not contribute to the PSQI score. In scoring the PSQI, seven component scores are derived, each scored 0 (no difficulty) to 3 (severe difficulty). The component scores are summed to produce a global score (range 0 to 21). Higher scores indicate worse sleep quality.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">0</enrollment>
  <condition>Non Small Cell Lung Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Interventional</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Heart Rate Variability Biofeedback Training</intervention_name>
    <description>The study will utilize the Physiolab GP8 heart rate variability and respiration system on a laptop computer used solely for the study with the proper security passwords to protect participant information. The equipment consists of two electrocardiogram sensors (one per wrist) attached by sports wrist bands, a respiration monitoring belt placed around the upper abdomen, two galvanic skin conductance sensors attached to the fingertips, and a thermistor sensor attached to one of the finger tips. Participants will perform a series of monitored breathing exercises.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Interventional</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Participants must be older than 18 years of age

          -  Both women and men of all ethnic background are eligible to participate in the study.

          -  Must be diagnosed with non-small cell lung cancer and receiving 6 weeks of radiation
             therapy.

          -  Must be available and willing to participate in 4, approximately 1 hour HRV
             biofeedback treatment sessions.

          -  Signed informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Participant is younger than 18 or older than 70

          -  Diagnosed with early stage NSCLC

          -  Patients who are pregnant

          -  Patients with cardiac arrhythmias

          -  Patients with Pacemakers

          -  Patients taking beta-blockers

          -  Patients with any major mental illness, cognitive impairment

          -  Incapable of giving informed consent
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>William Levin</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Abramson Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Abramson Cancer Center of the University of Pennsylvania</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19104</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ancoli-Israel S, Moore PJ, Jones V. The relationship between fatigue and sleep in cancer patients: a review. Eur J Cancer Care (Engl). 2001 Dec;10(4):245-55. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>11806675</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Badger TA, Braden CJ, Mishel MH, Longman A. Depression burden, psychological adjustment, and quality of life in women with breast cancer: patterns over time. Res Nurs Health. 2004 Feb;27(1):19-28.</citation>
    <PMID>14745853</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Guo Y, Koshy S, Hui D, Palmer JL, Shin K, Bozkurt M, Yusuf SW. Prognostic Value of Heart Rate Variability in Patients With Cancer. J Clin Neurophysiol. 2015 Dec;32(6):516-20. doi: 10.1097/WNP.0000000000000210.</citation>
    <PMID>26629761</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hassett AL, Radvanski DC, Vaschillo EG, Vaschillo B, Sigal LH, Karavidas MK, Buyske S, Lehrer PM. A pilot study of the efficacy of heart rate variability (HRV) biofeedback in patients with fibromyalgia. Appl Psychophysiol Biofeedback. 2007 Mar;32(1):1-10. Epub 2007 Jan 12.</citation>
    <PMID>17219062</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hertzog MA. Considerations in determining sample size for pilot studies. Res Nurs Health. 2008 Apr;31(2):180-91. doi: 10.1002/nur.20247. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18183564</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Karavidas MK, Lehrer PM, Vaschillo E, Vaschillo B, Marin H, Buyske S, Malinovsky I, Radvanski D, Hassett A. Preliminary results of an open label study of heart rate variability biofeedback for the treatment of major depression. Appl Psychophysiol Biofeedback. 2007 Mar;32(1):19-30. Epub 2007 Mar 1.</citation>
    <PMID>17333315</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Liu L, Ancoli-Israel S. Sleep Disturbances in Cancer. Psychiatr Ann. 2008 Sep 1;38(9):627-634.</citation>
    <PMID>21243092</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Reiner R. Integrating a portable biofeedback device into clinical practice for patients with anxiety disorders: results of a pilot study. Appl Psychophysiol Biofeedback. 2008 Mar;33(1):55-61. doi: 10.1007/s10484-007-9046-6. Epub 2008 Feb 20.</citation>
    <PMID>18286369</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 10, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 14, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 17, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 3, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 3, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 7, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lung Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

