<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03671499</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>0000518843</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03671499</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study for Testing Text Messaging and Newsletter as a Strategy for Interrupting Sedentary Behavior</brief_title>
  <acronym>SLMM</acronym>
  <official_title>A Pilot Study for Testing the Feasibility and Efficacy of Text Messaging and Newsletter as a Strategy for Interrupting Sedentary Behavior (Sit Less, Move More)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Alabama at Birmingham</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Consortium of Multiple Sclerosis Centers</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Alabama at Birmingham</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The study will examine the possibility of reducing sedentary behavior (SB) in African
      Americans with MS. SB consists of any waking activities that are done lying or sitting and do
      not demand significant physical effort (e.g., watching television, using the computer). SB is
      a major public health issue because it is associated with mortality and higher probabilities
      of presenting with health conditions and morbidity. There is indication that SB is related to
      physical disability, which is the inability of performing daily activities independently.
      This outcome is of high concern for persons with MS, especially those from underserved
      groups, such as African Americans. Thus, reducing the amount of time that people with MS
      spend in SB is important, but it is hard to find ways of doing so in large groups of people
      with MS. One possibility is to use text-messages to inform people about the necessity and
      benefits of interrupting SB by standing up, walking, or doing another activity. Text-messages
      are an ideal way to prompt behavior change because almost everyone owns a
      cellphone/smartphone in today's world. Considering this potential, the investigators will be
      studying whether or not it is possible to have a small group of African Americans with MS
      spend less time in SB by sending informative text-messages prompting individuals to stand-up
      and move around. This study will be used to inform the development of a much larger study
      that will aim to reduce SB in a very large sample of persons with MS.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The investigators are conducting a pilot study to examine the feasibility and efficacy of a
      technology-based behavior change intervention for reducing SB in African Americans with MS
      located in the United States. The intervention combines text message- and print-based
      approaches for behavior change based on Social Cognitive Theory (SCT). SCT-based content will
      be the active component for changing SB, while cellphone text messages and print newsletter
      will be the delivery mechanism. The use of cellphone to deliver the intervention content is
      based, in part, on the fact that cellphone is an ordinary form of communication in today's
      world, providing an optimal medium for reaching large groups of people remotely. The study
      will yield major advancement in identifying the feasibility and efficacy of interrupting and
      reducing SB via a technology-based intervention in African Americans with MS, a segment of
      the MS population that has been underrepresented in MS therapeutic management studies. If
      successful, this research will lay the foundation for applying the current strategy in
      large-scale interventions including African Americans and possibly other minority groups with
      MS.

      The intervention will be 12 weeks and divided into two parts. Part 1: Weeks 1-6 will focus on
      interrupting long periods of SB. At the beginning of the first week, participants will
      receive a packet containing print material providing lay information on what constitutes SB
      and examples of such behavior, highlighting the importance of interrupting prolonged periods
      of SB and the associated health benefits. The aim of the packet is to provide the basis to
      introduce the key element (i.e., SCT-based instructional cellphone text-messages) of the
      intervention. This will occur during the following six weeks, wherein participants will
      receive two text-messages/day (i.e., morning and afternoon) on the importance and health
      benefits of interrupting SB hourly. The text-messages will prompt individuals to interrupt SB
      by standing still, standing while performing tasks, or walking around. The text-messages will
      include further tips and strategies for interrupting SB. The investigators have previously
      developed a computerized messaging system that will be used to send the text-messages twice a
      day in the proposed intervention. The investigators will supplement the text messaging by
      sending bi-weekly SCT-based newsletters to participants that highlight ways of overcoming
      difficulties in effectively interrupting SB. The SCT content for the messages and newsletter
      has been created in previous research and will be revised for the proposed intervention. Part
      2: Weeks 7-12 will focus on replacing SB with light PA. On the first day of week 7,
      participants will receive a second packet of print material explaining the concept of light
      PA and emphasizing the importance of moving more daily. The print material will highlight the
      benefits of replacing SB with light PA and will contain instructions for goal setting (i.e.,
      target number of steps/day) and self-monitoring of daily PA, including receive a pedometer
      and a log for recording total steps/day. Similar to part 1, the key element for intervention
      delivery will be the SCT-based instructional cellphone text-messages, which participants will
      receive during the second six-week intervention period. More specifically, they will receive
      two text-messages/day on the importance and health benefits of replacing SB with light PA.
      The text-messages will recommend participants to watch for prolonged periods of SB and try
      and substitute these for light PA, such as light intensity walking and light-intensity focal
      exercise (e.g., stationary walk, marching). The text-messages will also remind participants
      to use the pedometer to set incremental personal goals for steps/day and to gauge the
      replacement of SB with light PA by watching the pedometer readings. The investigators further
      will include tips and strategies for replacing SB with light PA based on common daily
      activities. Bi-weekly SCT-based newsletters will be used to supplement the stimulus from the
      text-messages, by reinforcing the importance of sitting less and moving more.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 27, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">October 25, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 5, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in sedentary behavior evaluated with activity monitors</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessments will be conducted at baseline and at the midpoint of the experiment (intervention week 6)</time_frame>
    <description>Activity monitors are Actigraph accelerometers that participants will wear on an elastic belt around their waist for 7 days. These activity monitors measure how frequently and how much an individual moves.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in sedentary behavior evaluated with activity monitors</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessments will be conducted at the midpoint of the intervention (intervention week 6) and at at the end of the intervention (immediately after intervention week 12).</time_frame>
    <description>Activity monitors are Actigraph accelerometers that participants will wear on an elastic belt around their waist for 7 days. These activity monitors measure how frequently and how much an individual moves.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in sedentary behavior evaluated with activity monitors</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessments will be conducted at baseline and at at the end of the intervention (immediately after intervention week 12).</time_frame>
    <description>Activity monitors are Actigraph accelerometers that participants will wear on an elastic belt around their waist for 7 days. These activity monitors measure how frequently and how much an individual moves.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in physical activity evaluated with activity monitors</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessments will be conducted at baseline and at the midpoint of the experiment (intervention week 6)</time_frame>
    <description>Activity monitors are Actigraph accelerometers that participants will wear on an elastic belt around their waist for 7 days. These activity monitors measure how frequently and how much an individual moves.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in physical activity evaluated with activity monitors</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessments will be conducted at the midpoint of the intervention (intervention week 6) and at at the end of the intervention (immediately after intervention week 12).</time_frame>
    <description>Activity monitors are Actigraph accelerometers that participants will wear on an elastic belt around their waist for 7 days. These activity monitors measure how frequently and how much an individual moves.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in physical activity evaluated with activity monitors</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessments will be conducted at baseline and at at the end of the intervention (immediately after intervention week 12).</time_frame>
    <description>Activity monitors are Actigraph accelerometers that participants will wear on an elastic belt around their waist for 7 days. These activity monitors measure how frequently and how much an individual moves.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of Life will be evaluated with the 36-Item Short Form Health Survey (SF-36 questionnaire).</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessments will be conducted at baseline and at the midpoint of the experiment (intervention week 6)</time_frame>
    <description>The SF-36 questionnaire is a 36 item self-report questionnaire designed to assess patient health status. The questionnaire is scored on 8 sections: vitality, physical functioning, bodily pain, general health perceptions, physical role functioning, emotional role functioning, social role functioning, and mental health. Scores are transformed into a 0-100 scale with 0 equivalent to maximum disability and 100 equivalent to no disability.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of Life will be evaluated with the 36-Item Short Form Health Survey (SF-36 questionnaire).</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessments will be conducted at the midpoint of the intervention (intervention week 6) and at at the end of the intervention (immediately after intervention week 12).</time_frame>
    <description>The SF-36 questionnaire is a 36 item self-report questionnaire designed to assess patient health status. The questionnaire is scored on 8 sections: vitality, physical functioning, bodily pain, general health perceptions, physical role functioning, emotional role functioning, social role functioning, and mental health. Scores are transformed into a 0-100 scale with 0 equivalent to maximum disability and 100 equivalent to no disability.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of Life will be evaluated with the 36-Item Short Form Health Survey (SF-36 questionnaire).</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessments will be conducted at baseline and at at the end of the intervention (immediately after intervention week 12).</time_frame>
    <description>The SF-36 questionnaire is a 36 item self-report questionnaire designed to assess patient health status. The questionnaire is scored on 8 sections: vitality, physical functioning, bodily pain, general health perceptions, physical role functioning, emotional role functioning, social role functioning, and mental health. Scores are transformed into a 0-100 scale with 0 equivalent to maximum disability and 100 equivalent to no disability.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Multiple Sclerosis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Social Cognitive Theory based text messages</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The study only contains 1 arm. All participants will receive the same experimental protocol. Participants will receive daily text messages and bi-weekly newsletters for reducing sedentary behavior based on Social Cognitive Theory.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Social Cognitive Theory based text messages</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants receive daily text messages and bi-weekly newsletters with information about reducing sitting behavior and increasing physical activity.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Social Cognitive Theory based text messages</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  African American

          -  Definite diagnosis of MS

          -  Relapse free in the last 30 days

          -  Ambulatory with or without assistance

          -  Having a Patient-Determined Disease Steps score of 0-5

          -  Daily engagement in sedentary behavior ≥ 480 min/day

          -  Health contribution score of &lt;14 calculated from the Godin Leisure-Time Exercise
             Questionnaire

          -  Absence of major musculoskeletal problems, and/or cardiovascular, cardiopulmonary,
             and/or metabolic diseases that can influence physical activity and sedentary behavior
             levels

        Exclusion Criteria:

        -
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>64 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Robert W Motl, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Alabama at Birmingham</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Alabama Birmingham</name>
      <address>
        <city>Birmingham</city>
        <state>Alabama</state>
        <zip>35209</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 10, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 13, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 14, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 26, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 26, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 29, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Alabama at Birmingham</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Robert W Motl</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Primary Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>sedentary behavior</keyword>
  <keyword>physical activity</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Multiple Sclerosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

