<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03677414</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>FWF Project KLI 710-B26</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>21-228 ex 09/10</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03677414</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Analysis of Androgene Receptors Axis and DNA Damage Repair Genes in Patients With Prostate Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>Analysis of Androgene Receptors Axis and DNA Damage Repair Genes From Plasma DNA (ctDNA) in Patients With Prostate Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Medical University of Graz</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Medical University of Graz</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      In this project, we would like to focus on castration-sensitive prostate cancer (CRPC). This
      is a highly variable clinical picture with differentiated and burdening symptoms. The
      clinical parameters used to estimate the prognosis have so far only shown a very limited
      valence; genetic markers have so far only rarely been investigated.

      In the course of our preliminary investigations, we were already able to isolate 189 plasma
      samples from 59 patients with metastatic prostate cancer. These samples are prepared by
      highly innovative techniques, e.g. &quot;whole genome sequencing&quot;, in order to gain comprehensive
      insights into the spectrum of genetic changes under therapy and the associated tumor
      evolution. These results should be compared with the genetic material of the respective
      prostate tumors, which originate from previous operations. This highly comprehensive data,
      which will yield results on copy number changes, mutations, and gene expression, will allow
      analysis of signaling pathways of unprecedented resolution to increase the efficacy of
      targeted therapies in patients and minimize the burden of non-effective therapy side effects.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The investigators collected 189 plasma samples from 59 patients with metastasized CRPC
      treated with abiraterone/enzalutamide. In order to stratify plasma DNA samples based on the
      presence of low (i.e. z-score ≤5; corresponds to &lt;10% ctDNA) versus high (z-score &gt;5;
      corresponds to ≥10% ctDNA) genomic complexity in ctDNA the investigators employed the
      modified Fast Aneuploidy Screening Test-Sequencing System (mFAST-SeqS), which provides a
      plasma based marker of aneuploidy (z-score). Altogether 106 plasma samples with a low z-score
      will be evaluated only with the AVENIO ctDNA Expanded Kit, which is capable of detecting
      mutations with VAFs as low as 0.1% . From the 83 plasma samples with increased z-score will
      be sequenced with high coverage (70x) so that both mutations and nucleosome positions can be
      extracted from the obtained sequences. With the other 32 high z-score samples plasma-Seq will
      be conducted to establish genome-wide copy number profiles and 31 prostate cancer genes will
      be enriched to screen for mutations in these genes.

      At present, there is no evidence what parameters should be used to decide which treatment
      options are best for metastatic prostate cancer patients. The suggested innovative
      technologies, i.e. nucleosome position mapping and gene expression analyses will provide
      systematic maps of nucleosome positions. The sequencing of plasma samples with 70x will
      provide in addition a comprehensive view on the mutation spectrum in metastatic prostate
      cancer. By inclusion of primary tumor analyses, an unprecedented view on prostate cancer
      genome Evolution will be obtained. Overall, the comprehensive data set (copy number changes,
      mutations, gene expression) will allow pathway analyses with unprecedented resolution.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 10, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 31, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 31, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Cross-Sectional</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Nucleosome positioning patterns</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Here, samples with increased z-score (z-score &gt;5; corresponds to ≥10% ctDNA; modified Fast Aneuploidy Screening Test-Sequencing System (mFAST-SeqS)) will be sequenced with high coverage (70x) so that nucleosome positions can be extracted from the obtained sequences. As at TSSs (transcriptional start site), the nucleosome occupancy results in different read-depth coverage patterns in expressed and silent genes (Ulz et al., Nat Genet 2016), systematic maps of nucleosome positions in defined patients will be generated.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Focal amplifications in ctDNA</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Mapping (absolute number and size) of recurrent focal amplifications/gained regions and identification of the driver genes within these amplicons by systematic cataloging of genes expressed in focal amplifications/gained regions. In order to facilitate the identification of focal amplifications we apply very stringent/conservative criteria regarding amplicon size and gene density, which we applied in previous publications (Ulz et al., Nat Commun 2016; Ulz, Heitzer, Speicher, Nat Genet 2016).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Prostate Cancer Panel</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Characterization of mutation frequency of enriched prostate cancer genes using plasma-Seq (i.e. AKAP9, APC, AR, ATM, BRAF, BRCA1, BRCA2, CTNNB1, EGFR, ERG, FOXA1, GNAS, GRIN2A, HRAS, KRAS, MED12, MLL, MLL2, MLL3, MLLT3, NOTCH1, NRG1, PIK3CA, PIK3CB, PIK3R1, PTEN, RB1, SPOP, TMPRSS2, TP53, ZFHX3).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinico-pathological characteristics</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Documentation of clinico-pathological characteristics (PSA, NSE; blood count; localization, number and size of metastases by imaging) including prior and subsequent therapies.To identify predictive/prognostic biomarkers, newly occurring genomic changes in the plasma DNA (see primary outcome and further secondary outcome measures) will be correlated with outcomes of given therapies.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Analyses of primary tumors</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Measurement of copy number changes in primary tumors by next-generation sequencing, i.e. SCNA-seq, and RNA-Seq for comparison with the nucleosome positions, see above.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Buccal swap</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Distinction germ line vs. somatic mutations</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">59</enrollment>
  <condition>Prostatic Neoplasms</condition>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Plasma DNA Primary tumor Buccal swap
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        The study includes men with proven histological diagnosis of prostate cancer and treatment
        with abiraterone and/or enzalutamide.

        Participants were recruited at the Medical University Hospital of Graz.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  subject has proven histological diagnosis of prostate cancer

          -  subject was treated with abiraterone and/or enzalutamide.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  patient rejects the participation
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <gender_based>Yes</gender_based>
    <gender_description>The study includes men with metastasized prostate cancer.</gender_description>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jochen B Geigl, Prof, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Institute of Human Genetics</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Institute of Human Genetics, Medical University of Graz</name>
      <address>
        <city>Graz</city>
        <zip>8010</zip>
        <country>Austria</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Austria</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ulz P, Belic J, Graf R, Auer M, Lafer I, Fischereder K, Webersinke G, Pummer K, Augustin H, Pichler M, Hoefler G, Bauernhofer T, Geigl JB, Heitzer E, Speicher MR. Whole-genome plasma sequencing reveals focal amplifications as a driving force in metastatic prostate cancer. Nat Commun. 2016 Jun 22;7:12008. doi: 10.1038/ncomms12008.</citation>
    <PMID>27328849</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ulz P, Heitzer E, Speicher MR. Co-occurrence of MYC amplification and TP53 mutations in human cancer. Nat Genet. 2016 Feb;48(2):104-6. doi: 10.1038/ng.3468.</citation>
    <PMID>26813759</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ulz P, Thallinger GG, Auer M, Graf R, Kashofer K, Jahn SW, Abete L, Pristauz G, Petru E, Geigl JB, Heitzer E, Speicher MR. Inferring expressed genes by whole-genome sequencing of plasma DNA. Nat Genet. 2016 Oct;48(10):1273-8. doi: 10.1038/ng.3648. Epub 2016 Aug 29.</citation>
    <PMID>27571261</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>September 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 17, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 17, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 19, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 17, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 17, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">September 19, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>circulating-tumor DNA ctDNA</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Prostatic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

