<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03671876</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>TASMC-08-ID-052717-CTIL</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>MOH_2018-04-11_002309</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03671876</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluation of Improvement in Mobility Skills for Sub-acute Stroke Patients, Using the Selfit System.</brief_title>
  <acronym>Selfit</acronym>
  <official_title>Improving the Mobility of Patients After a Stroke (at a Sub-acute Stage) With the Help of the Selfit System - Testing the System's Feasibility, From the Point of View of the Therapist and the Patient.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Selfit Medical</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Tel-Aviv Sourasky Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Selfit Medical</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Stroke is a leading cause of mobility disability for adults. Selfit is an advanced practice
      system that enables a wide range of exercises to improve patient mobility in the sub-acute
      stage after a stroke. The system collects, measures and analyzes the patient's activity in
      practice.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Objectives of the study: An evaluation of the improvement of mobility after a stroke using
      the Selfit system.

      Type of study: Case Control Study. Study population: 30 patients, after stroke (men and women
      aged 18-85). Criteria for Inclusion: Stroke patients who are capable to walk with a little
      help or no help at all, with or without any assitive device, for a distance of 10 meters.

      Intervention: Random distribution of the study participants into two groups - Case: stroke
      patients (15 patients) - evaluation of patients using Selfit for 2 sessions per week, for a
      period of at least 30 minutes per session, during 3 weeks.

      Control: Stroke patients (15 patients) - continuing with current therapy with no use of the
      Selfit system.

      Measurement tools and outcome measures:

      Duration of each treatment session, the duration of the actual treatment, the number of
      technical failures in the system during the exercise and the duration of each session will be
      recorded. At the end of the intervention, questionnaires describing the experience of using
      the system will be completed with a rating of the degree of satisfaction, convenience and
      simplicity of using the Selfit system. The following tests will be carried out : 10 meter
      walk test, Timed up and go test, Dynamic Gait Index (DGI).

      Analysis of the data: For each patient's treatment, a personal activity profile will be
      established that includes the timing and speed of walking, the number of steps, the length
      and width of each step, the elevation of the leg at each step and the accuracy of the
      patient's performance. Statistical analysis will examine the various levels of activity
      throughout the intervention period for each patient and for the entire study population
      before and after the intervention. At the same time, the correlation between the level of
      activity in the treatment and the scores on the neurological tests will be examined. The data
      will be presented descriptively for the therapist and patient. For statistical analysis, the
      SPPS version 21 (IBM) will be used.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 11, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">January 31, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 31, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in patient's average speed</measure>
    <time_frame>3 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Change from baseline in mobility skills - speed (m/sec)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in patient's average distance</measure>
    <time_frame>3 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Change from baseline in mobility skills - distance (m)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in patient's number of steps</measure>
    <time_frame>3 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Change from baseline in mobility skills - number of steps</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in patient's steps height</measure>
    <time_frame>3 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Change from baseline in mobility skills - steps height (avg. in cm)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Stroke</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention plus therapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Case group:
A population that suffered a stroke and treated to improve mobility with the Selfit system (25 patients) for twice a week, at least 30 minutes per session, for a period of 3 weeks.
Intervention with the Selfit system include a set of mobility task exercises.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Therapy and no intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Control group:
A population that suffered a stroke and is being treated in the hospital without any interventions with the Selfit system.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Intervention plus therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>Task oriented exercise plan to improve mobility for stroke patients</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention plus therapy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Clinical diagnosis of Stroke .Must walk with little or no help at all, with or without
             an assistive device, for a distance of at least 10 meters.

        Exclusion Criteria:

        - .Patients suffering from significant lower back pain and / or previous orthopedic
        impairment and / or cognitive impairment (grade 18 and below according to the MOCA test).

        .Patients who are unable to move with little or no help at all, with or without an
        assistive device, for a distance of 10 meters.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>85 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Israel Dudkiewicz, Prof.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Tel-Aviv Sourasky Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Tel Aviv Sourasky Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tel-Aviv</city>
        <zip>6291789</zip>
        <country>Israel</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Israel</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 6, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 13, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 14, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 1, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 1, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">September 4, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Stroke</keyword>
  <keyword>Sub-acute</keyword>
  <keyword>Mobility</keyword>
  <keyword>Movement therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Exercise</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Stroke</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

