<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03671759</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>18-25195</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03671759</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Coffee and Real-time Atrial and Ventricular Ectopy</brief_title>
  <acronym>CRAVE</acronym>
  <official_title>Coffee and Real-time Atrial and Ventricular Ectopy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of California, San Francisco</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of California, San Francisco</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Atrial fibrillation (AF) and heart failure (HF) are morbid, costly, and incompletely
      understood diseases that have reached epidemic proportions worldwide. A dose-dependent
      relationship exists between premature atrial and ventricular contractions (PACs and PVCs) and
      development of AF and HF, respectively. Identifying and understanding the mechanisms of
      additional modifiable risk factors for ectopy has the potential to markedly reduce the
      healthcare burden of these diseases. In considering how to modify the prevalence of these
      ectopic beats, the investigators believe common exposures in daily life are prime candidates.
      Current guidelines suggest that caffeine may be an important trigger for frequent ectopy,
      although large population-based studies have not demonstrated an association between caffeine
      consumption and development of clinically significant arrhythmias. No study has employed an
      actual randomization intervention to assess the effects of caffeine on cardiac ectopy.
      Utilizing the Eureka platform, the investigators plan to utilize the N-of-1 strategy to
      rigorously investigate the real-time effect of caffeine intake on ectopy.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      For two weeks, participants will be asked to wear a continuously recording heart monitor and
      utilize the Eureka mobile application. On the Eureka app, participants will be able to track
      caffeine consumption and answer questions about mood and sleep. Participants will also
      receive their randomization assignment through Eureka. Participants will be asked to modify
      caffeine intake habits in two-day blocks; these assignments are either a) to consume caffeine
      for one day, then avoid caffeine the next day, or b) to avoid caffeine for one day, then
      consume caffeine the next day. Participants will also be given a wrist-worn fitness device
      (Fitbit), to track sleep, step counts, and heart rate data.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in cardiac ectopy burden</measure>
    <time_frame>2 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Participants will be wearing a continuously recording ECG monitor for two weeks. The primary outcome will be change in ectopy burden due to caffeine consumption or avoidance during the enrollment period.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">108</enrollment>
  <condition>Premature Atrial Contractions</condition>
  <condition>Premature Ventricular Contractions</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Experimental: N-of-1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will be randomized in two-day blocks to consume then avoid caffeine (&quot;Start: On Caffeine&quot;) or avoid then consume caffeine (&quot;Start: Off Caffeine&quot;). Using an N-of-1 strategy delivered by the NIH-funded, UCSF-run Eureka platform utilizing a mobile smartphone-based application, participants will receive instructions and answer questions to help us understand the relationship between caffeine and heart rhythm.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Start: On Caffeine</intervention_name>
    <description>In this two-day block, participants will be instructed to consume caffeine for one day and avoid caffeine the next day.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Experimental: N-of-1</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Start: Off Caffeine</intervention_name>
    <description>In this two-day block, participants will be instructed to avoid caffeine for one day and consume caffeine the next day.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Experimental: N-of-1</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Able to read and write in English

          -  Has a smartphone

          -  Is willing to receive message reminders from study

          -  Drinks caffeinated coffee or espresso drinks

          -  Is willing to abstain from caffeinated products when instructed

          -  Is willing to provide saliva sample for analysis of genetic variants related to
             caffeine metabolism

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Is taking an anti-arrhythmic, beta-blocker, or calcium channel blocker

          -  Has a pacemaker or ICD
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Gregory M Marcus, MD, MAS</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of California, San Francisco</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>David Rosenthal, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of California, San Francisco</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of California, San Francisco</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Francisco</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94143</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://emedicine.medscape.com/article/158939-treatment-a1130</url>
    <description>Ventricular Premature Complexes Treatment &amp; Management</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.uptodate.com/contents/ventricularpremature-beats</url>
    <description>Ventricular Premature Beats</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chugh SS, Blackshear JL, Shen WK, Hammill SC, Gersh BJ. Epidemiology and natural history of atrial fibrillation: clinical implications. J Am Coll Cardiol. 2001 Feb;37(2):371-8. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>11216949</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Coyne KS, Paramore C, Grandy S, Mercader M, Reynolds M, Zimetbaum P. Assessing the direct costs of treating nonvalvular atrial fibrillation in the United States. Value Health. 2006 Sep-Oct;9(5):348-56.</citation>
    <PMID>16961553</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Roger VL, Go AS, Lloyd-Jones DM, Benjamin EJ, Berry JD, Borden WB, Bravata DM, Dai S, Ford ES, Fox CS, Fullerton HJ, Gillespie C, Hailpern SM, Heit JA, Howard VJ, Kissela BM, Kittner SJ, Lackland DT, Lichtman JH, Lisabeth LD, Makuc DM, Marcus GM, Marelli A, Matchar DB, Moy CS, Mozaffarian D, Mussolino ME, Nichol G, Paynter NP, Soliman EZ, Sorlie PD, Sotoodehnia N, Turan TN, Virani SS, Wong ND, Woo D, Turner MB; American Heart Association Statistics Committee and Stroke Statistics Subcommittee. Heart disease and stroke statistics--2012 update: a report from the American Heart Association. Circulation. 2012 Jan 3;125(1):e2-e220. doi: 10.1161/CIR.0b013e31823ac046. Epub 2011 Dec 15. Erratum in: Circulation. 2012 Jun 5;125(22):e1002.</citation>
    <PMID>22179539</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dewland TA, Vittinghoff E, Mandyam MC, Heckbert SR, Siscovick DS, Stein PK, Psaty BM, Sotoodehnia N, Gottdiener JS, Marcus GM. Atrial ectopy as a predictor of incident atrial fibrillation: a cohort study. Ann Intern Med. 2013 Dec 3;159(11):721-8. doi: 10.7326/0003-4819-159-11-201312030-00004.</citation>
    <PMID>24297188</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dukes JW, Dewland TA, Vittinghoff E, Mandyam MC, Heckbert SR, Siscovick DS, Stein PK, Psaty BM, Sotoodehnia N, Gottdiener JS, Marcus GM. Ventricular Ectopy as a Predictor of Heart Failure and Death. J Am Coll Cardiol. 2015 Jul 14;66(2):101-9. doi: 10.1016/j.jacc.2015.04.062.</citation>
    <PMID>26160626</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Blomström-Lundqvist C, Scheinman MM, Aliot EM, Alpert JS, Calkins H, Camm AJ, Campbell WB, Haines DE, Kuck KH, Lerman BB, Miller DD, Shaeffer CW, Stevenson WG, Tomaselli GF, Antman EM, Smith SC Jr, Alpert JS, Faxon DP, Fuster V, Gibbons RJ, Gregoratos G, Hiratzka LF, Hunt SA, Jacobs AK, Russell RO Jr, Priori SG, Blanc JJ, Budaj A, Burgos EF, Cowie M, Deckers JW, Garcia MA, Klein WW, Lekakis J, Lindahl B, Mazzotta G, Morais JC, Oto A, Smiseth O, Trappe HJ; European Society of Cardiology Committee, NASPE-Heart Rhythm Society. ACC/AHA/ESC guidelines for the management of patients with supraventricular arrhythmias--executive summary. a report of the American college of cardiology/American heart association task force on practice guidelines and the European society of cardiology committee for practice guidelines (writing committee to develop guidelines for the management of patients with supraventricular arrhythmias) developed in collaboration with NASPE-Heart Rhythm Society. J Am Coll Cardiol. 2003 Oct 15;42(8):1493-531. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>14563598</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dixit S, Stein PK, Dewland TA, Dukes JW, Vittinghoff E, Heckbert SR, Marcus GM. Consumption of Caffeinated Products and Cardiac Ectopy. J Am Heart Assoc. 2016 Jan 26;5(1). pii: e002503. doi: 10.1161/JAHA.115.002503.</citation>
    <PMID>26813889</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 12, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 12, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 14, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 24, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 24, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 26, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of California, San Francisco</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Gregory Marcus</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Director of Clinical Research for the UCSF Division of Cardiology</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Caffeine</keyword>
  <keyword>Coffee</keyword>
  <keyword>Arrhythmias</keyword>
  <keyword>Palpitations</keyword>
  <keyword>Cardiac ectopy</keyword>
  <keyword>PACs</keyword>
  <keyword>PVCs</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Premature Birth</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ventricular Premature Complexes</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Atrial Premature Complexes</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Caffeine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

