<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04000724</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ATN160</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04000724</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>TechStep: Technology-based Stepped Care to Stem Transgender Adolescent Risk Transmission</brief_title>
  <official_title>TechStep: Technology-based Stepped Care to Stem Transgender Adolescent Risk Transmission</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Friends Research Institute, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>San Diego State University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of North Carolina</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Emory University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Baylor College of Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Children's Hospital of Philadelphia</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>The Fenway Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Hunter College of City University of New York</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Children's Hospital Los Angeles</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Friends Research Institute, Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      TechStep is a three-arm, technology-based randomized controlled trial (RCT), with a stepped
      care approach, among high-risk HIV-negative transgender feminine, transgender masculine, and
      gender non-conforming youth and young adults for reducing sexual risk behaviors and
      increasing pre-exposure prophylaxis (PrEP) uptake. Participants are randomized into one of
      three conditions for a 6-month intervention: Group 1: culturally relevant theory-based text
      messages (Text+Step); or, Group 2: culturally relevant mobile-enhanced website (WebApp+Step);
      or, Group 3: informational website control condition with no theoretically based text
      messages or WebApp.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      TechStep is a three-arm, technology-based randomized controlled trial (RCT), with a stepped
      care approach, among high-risk HIV-negative transgender feminine, transgender masculine, and
      gender non-conforming youth and young adults for reducing sexual risk behaviors and
      increasing PrEP uptake. Transgender youth and young adults are enrolled for 9 months in the
      RCT. During the RCT, 250 participants will be enrolled and randomized to either: (1) text
      messaging (n=83), (2) WebApp (n=83), or (3) an informational website control (n=83)
      condition. Participants will include HIV-negative youth and young adults (ages 15-24) who are
      self-identified transgender feminine, transgender masculine or gender non-conforming.
      Participants will be recruited from venues in Boston, Houston, Los Angeles, New York, and
      Philadelphia. There will be four data collection time points: baseline, 3-, 6-, and 9-month.
      Visits will be conducted in-person at the venues. An ACASI will be completed using online
      survey tools. An HIV test, sexually transmitted infection (STI) panel, urine screen for
      recent illicit drug use, and blood microsampling, for those who report PrEP uptake, to verify
      PrEP adherence will be collected in-person at the participants local venue. Process data of
      each participant activity at each step of the intervention, as well as the control
      intervention, will be collected. The study aims to measure the effects of the
      information-only (Info) arm compared to a text messaging intervention (Text+Step) to a WebApp
      intervention (WebApp+Step) for reducing sexual risk behaviors and increasing PrEP uptake.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 18, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 31, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 31, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Condomless Intercourse Events</measure>
    <time_frame>9 Months</time_frame>
    <description>Participants will report the frequency of condomless sexual intercourse events they have engaged in for the past 3 months at baseline and at each follow-up. The value of interest is the cumulative number of events over follow-up.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Condomless Intercourse Events while High on Drugs/Alcohol</measure>
    <time_frame>9 Months</time_frame>
    <description>Participants will report the number of condomless sexual intercourse events they have engaged in while high on drugs or alcohol during their three most recent sexual encounters in the past 3 months at baseline and at each follow-up. The value of interest is the cumulative number of events over follow-up.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Condomless Intercourse Events during Sex Work</measure>
    <time_frame>9 Months</time_frame>
    <description>Participants will report the number of exchange partners in the past 3 months at baseline and at each follow-up. The value of interest is the cumulative number of events over follow-up.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>PrEP Adherence</measure>
    <time_frame>9 Months</time_frame>
    <description>Mitra blood microsamples (10-30 µL) will be collected at each time point to verify PrEP uptake and adherence.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>HIV Seroconversion</measure>
    <time_frame>9 Months</time_frame>
    <description>Rapid HIV tests will be collected at each time point. Incident infections will be recorded.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incident STIs</measure>
    <time_frame>9 Months</time_frame>
    <description>Participants will be tested for gonorrhea and chlamydia via throat, rectal, and urogenital swab specimen collection, as well as via urine samples at each time point. Incident STIs will be recorded.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incident Syphilis</measure>
    <time_frame>9 Months</time_frame>
    <description>Participants will be tested for syphilis via a blood draw by a trained phlebotomist at each time point. Incident syphilis cases will be recorded.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Transgender Syndemic Health Index</measure>
    <time_frame>9 Months</time_frame>
    <description>Participants will endorse items on a pre-populated list of structural-level (e.g., transphobia, housing insecurity, educational attainment, access to healthcare) and individual-level (e.g., identity formation, gender transition, gender expression, stigma, discrimination) factors known to be detrimental to transgender health. Endorsements will be factor analyzed at each time point to construct an index representing the syndemic burden on each participant.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">250</enrollment>
  <condition>HIV</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Text+Step</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The TechStep Text+Step messaging intervention is a six-month technology-based culturally competent theory-based text messaging intervention that sends three automated text messages to participants daily to reduce HIV risk and increase PrEP uptake and adherence.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>WebApp+Step</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The TechStep WebApp+Step website intervention is a six-month technology-based intervention that uses peer-to-peer interaction, daily self-monitoring, and tailored content to address barriers to HIV sexual risk reduction and PrEP uptake and adherence.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Information</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The Information/No Step intervention includes nothing more than access to a website with information about trans health, HIV/STI information and local resources tailored for transgender persons.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Text Messaging (Text+Step)</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants receive three culturally competent, theory-based pre-written messages per day sent on a predetermined schedule. Participants who still exhibit sexual risk and do not uptake and/or adhere to PrEP at the 3-month assessment may also receive eCoaching for up to 12 weeks.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Text+Step</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>WebApp (App+Step)</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants receive access to a culturally competent password-protected web-based application with transgender-specific resources, support, and health information. Participants who still exhibit sexual risk and do not uptake and/or adhere to PrEP at the 3-month assessment may also receive eCoaching for up to 12 weeks.</description>
    <arm_group_label>WebApp+Step</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Information/No Step</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants in the Information/No Step intervention will receive access to a static website with information about trans health, HIV/STI information and local resources tailored for transgender persons.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Information</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Report vaginal or anal sex (either insertive or receptive; excluding sex toys) with
             another person in the previous 12 months;

          -  Confirmed negative HIV rapid test;

          -  Availability to meet with research staff at either the Baylor College of Medicine
             (BCM) Adolescent Medicine Trials Unit in Houston, Children's Hospital of Philadelphia,
             Children's Hospital Los Angeles, the PRIDE Health Research Consortium in New York
             City, or the Fenway Institute in Boston

          -  Have a mobile device with short messaging service (SMS; i.e. &quot;texting&quot;) and Internet
             access capabilities; and

          -  Read and speak English (since the intervention is built in English)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Does not report vaginal or anal sex (either insertive or receptive; excluding sex
             toys) with another person in the previous 12 months;

          -  Unable to meet with research staff at either the Baylor College of Medicine (BCM)
             Adolescent Medicine Trials Unit in Houston, Children's Hospital of Philadelphia,
             Children's Hospital Los Angeles, the PRIDE Health Research Consortium in New York
             City, or the Fenway Institute in Boston

          -  Does not have a mobile device with SMS and Internet access capabilities;

          -  Unable to read and speak English (since the intervention is built and delivered in
             English)

          -  Unwilling or unable to comply with protocol requirements;

          -  Unable to understand the Informed Consent/Assent Form.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <gender_based>Yes</gender_based>
    <gender_description>Participants will include youth and young adults who are self-identified trans feminine, trans masculine or gender non-conforming OR whose birth sex and current gender differ</gender_description>
    <minimum_age>15 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>24 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Lisa Hightow-Wideman, MD, MPH</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>University of North Carolina</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Travis Sanchez, DVM, MPH</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Emory University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Cathy J Reback, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Friends Research Institute, Inc.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Keith J Horvath, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>San Diego State University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Children's Hospital Los Angeles</name>
      <address>
        <city>Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90027</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The Fenway Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02215</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>PRIDE Health Research Consortium at Hunter CUNY</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10018</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Children's Hospital of Philadelphia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19104</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Baylor College of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 16, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 26, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 27, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 2, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 2, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 3, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Text Messaging</keyword>
  <keyword>mHealth</keyword>
  <keyword>HIV</keyword>
  <keyword>AIDS</keyword>
  <keyword>PrEP</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>The investigators will assure the timely release and sharing of data two years after the publication of the main trial findings from the final dataset. Study variables will be available; however, the investigators will protect the rights and privacy of human subjects by redacting all identifiers from the data set. The de-identified data from this project will be available through individual requests directed to the Principal Investigator.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

