<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04008563</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>19-5487</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04008563</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Bariatric Surgery for Fertility-Sparing Treatment of Atypical Hyperplasia and Grade 1 Cancer of the Endometrium</brief_title>
  <acronym>B-FiERCE</acronym>
  <official_title>Bariatric Surgery for Fertility-Sparing Treatment of Atypical Hyperplasia and Grade 1 Cancer of the Endometrium</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University Health Network, Toronto</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University Health Network, Toronto</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      A growing population of young women with obesity are developing atypical hyperplasia
      (pre-cancer) and endometrial cancer. Progestin is the standard treatment for women who wish
      to preserve fertility, but this approach does not address the underlying cause of endometrial
      cancer/atypical hyperplasia (obesity); thus response rates are low and recurrence rates are
      high. Significant weight loss by bariatric surgery, in combination with progestin therapy may
      result in greater and more durable response rates.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The incidence of endometrial cancer is increasing at an alarming rate (2.6% per year). This
      trend parallels the rising rate of obesity, the most significant increasing risk factor for
      endometrial cancer. Young women with obesity and endometrial cancer or atypical hyperplasia
      who want to maintain their fertility and thus avoid hysterectomy are treated with progestin
      therapy, such as progestin intra-uterine device (pIUD). However, the pIUD achieves cancer
      regression in only 50-70% of women, and over 50% of initial responders will develop
      recurrence within two years. The effectiveness of the pIUD may be improved if the driver of
      endometrial cancer (obesity) was simultaneously addressed. Multiple epidemiologic studies
      have demonstrated that bariatric surgery reduces the risk of developing endometrial cancer.
      Our research aims to answer the question: &quot;Is bariatric surgery in addition to the pIUD a
      feasible and acceptable option for young women with endometrial cancer/atypical hyperplasia
      who wish to maintain their childbearing potential compared to standard treatment of pIUD
      alone?

      This is a pilot randomized controlled trial to assess the feasibility of a full-scale
      randomized controlled trial. Eligible women will be identified and consented over a 21-month
      period, and participants will be randomized to bariatric surgery plus standard pIUD
      (intervention group) or to standard pIUD alone (non-intervention group) in a 1:1 fashion.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">August 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 1, 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 1, 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Intervention Group: Bariatric Surgery and Progestin Intrauterine Device (pIUD) Non-Intervention Group: Progestin Intrauterine Device (pIUD) alone
Participants who consent will be randomized in a 1:1 allocation.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Recruitment Rate</measure>
    <time_frame>Year 3</time_frame>
    <description>To determine the proportion of eligible women who agree to participate in the study (recruitment rate). The primary outcome will be met and a full scale randomized controlled trial to assess efficacy will be conducted if ≥ 40% recruitment rate is achieved. Patients' reasons for participation or non-participation will be recorded.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Completion of Bariatric Surgery</measure>
    <time_frame>Year 3</time_frame>
    <description>Proportion of patients who complete bariatric surgery within 3 months of randomization. A rate of &gt;85% will be considered feasible.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Loss to Follow-Up Rate</measure>
    <time_frame>Year 3</time_frame>
    <description>Loss to follow-up rate, defined as proportion of patients who do not complete 15-month assessment. A loss to follow-up rate of &lt;20% will be considered feasible.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Completion of Patient Reported Outcome Questionnaires</measure>
    <time_frame>Year 3</time_frame>
    <description>Completion rate of patient reported outcomes that will be used in the full-scale randomized controlled trial. Completion of &gt;80% of patient reported outcomes at baseline will indicate that use of these questionnaires is feasible.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Complete Response Rate</measure>
    <time_frame>Year 3</time_frame>
    <description>Overall complete response rate (CRR) after treatment with progestin intrauterine device (pIUD). This study is not powered to detect an improvement in CRR in the intervention vs. non-intervention group. However, the proportion of women who obtain a complete response in the pIUD alone group at 15 months will be used as the baseline CRR for this population and will be used to derive a sample size for a full-scale randomized controlled trial. We believe that this will be more accurate than using published data retrospective studies that are not specific to women with obesity. We will also collect the following data: (a) time to complete response, (b) overall recurrence rate, and (c) time to recurrence.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">36</enrollment>
  <condition>Endometrial Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Atypical Hyperplasia</condition>
  <condition>Bariatric Surgery Candidate</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Bariatric Surgery and Progestin Intrauterine Device</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>This group will receive a progestin intrauterine device and be offered to undergo bariatric surgery.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Progestin Intrauterine Device Alone</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>This group will receive a progestin intrauterine device alone.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Bariatric Surgery</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients who are randomized to the intervention group will receive a progestin intrauterine device and be referred for bariatric service to undergo bariatric surgery within 3 months of their study consent.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Bariatric Surgery and Progestin Intrauterine Device</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  BMI ≥ 35

          -  Diagnosis of grade 1 endometrioid endometrial cancer or complex atypical hyperplasia

          -  Clinical stage 1 disease - no evidence of metastatic disease beyond the uterus by
             physical exam or imaging performed (MRI, CT)

          -  ECOG status &lt;2

          -  Desire for fertility preservation

          -  No contraindications to progestin intrauterine device (IUD)

          -  Have signed an approved informed consent form

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Evidence of myometrial invasion or extra-uterine disease on imaging

          -  High grade or p53 endometrial cancer

          -  History of other malignancies, except if curatively treated with no evidence of
             disease for &gt; 5 years

          -  Evidence of adenomyosis seen on MRI

          -  Previous major upper abdominal surgery (ex. splenectomy, partial gastrectomy, liver
             resection, bowel resection). *Appendectomy, cholecystectomy, hernia repair, and
             caesarean section are acceptable procedures for inclusion

          -  Current use of weight loss medication

          -  Contraindications to sleeve gastrectomy

          -  Medical co-morbidity with end-organ dysfunction

          -  Unable to understand and participate in the informed consent process

          -  Currently pregnant
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>41 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Sarah E Ferguson, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University Health Network, Toronto</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Gabrielle Ene</last_name>
    <phone>416-946-4501</phone>
    <phone_ext>3969</phone_ext>
    <email>Gabrielle.Ene@uhnresearch.ca</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 3, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 3, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 5, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 23, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 23, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 25, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Endometrial Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hyperplasia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

