<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04008407</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>AU RED HREC/17/WMEAD/497</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04008407</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>ESD for Colorectal LSL Using a Selective Strategy - a Prospective Cohort Study</brief_title>
  <acronym>COVERT</acronym>
  <official_title>Endoscopic Submucosal Dissection for Sessile Polyps and Laterally Spreading Lesions of the Colorectum Using a Selective Strategy - a Prospective Cohort Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Western Sydney Local Health District</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Western Sydney Local Health District</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Colonic Laterally spreading lesions (LSL) =&gt; 20mm are at high risk to progress to cancer.
      Overt stigmata of submucosal invasive cancer (SMIC) has been well characterized and includes
      ulceration and surface pit pattern changes as per the Kudo classification of type V.

      In a recent report, risk factors for LSL with SMIC and no overt stigmata (i.e. covert SMIC)
      were described. Resection of these lesions 'en-bloc' can allow for better histological
      staging and potentially reduce the need for surgical resection.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      With over 14,000 patients diagnosed annually, colorectal carcinoma (CRC) is the second most
      frequently invasive malignancy in Australia. By not only diagnosing CRC at an early stage,
      but also removing precursor adenomas, colonoscopy with polypectomy reduces the risk of
      developing and dying from CRC.

      Laterally spreading lesions &gt;= 20mm (LSL) are more likely to progress to cancer. The
      prevalence of LSL ranges from 1-5% in screening population. The risk of malignant progression
      of colorectal adenomas found during colonoscopy increases with lesion size, i.e. the cancer
      preventive effect is likely to be maximal in large lesions. Patients with LSL have a higher
      risk of malignancy and a higher recurrence rate of adenoma after lesion removal compared with
      diminutive polyps.

      Endoscopic imaging can now accurately predict LSL with submucosal invasive cancer (SMIC)
      through assessment of LSLs morphology (Paris classification, granularity) and surface
      pit-pattern (Kudo classification). Such cases can be considered to have LSL with overt risk
      of SMIC.

      Recent publication has highlighted that some LSLs might hrbor SMIC without overt
      morphological features (i.e. high risk for covert SMIC). These LSL with high risk of covert
      SMIC stratified LSLs based on lesion location and lesion morphology.

      Generally LSLs can be safely and effectively removed by wide field endoscopic mucosal
      resection (WF-EMR) in over 90% of cases in competent hands.

      One of the draw backs with WF-EMR is it requires piecemeal resection and thus is limited in
      providing assessment of complete excision and depth of submucosal invasion in cases where
      SMIC is present.

      Thus, endoscopic en-bloc resection is preferable from an oncologic standpoint to obtain a
      single specimen for proper histopathologic assessment. Endoscopic submucosal dissection (ESD)
      is a technique that is now becoming the preferred method for achieving a complete endoscopic
      and histologic resection, referred to as R0. Evidence from retrospective cohort and
      meta-analyses suggests ESD provides a more consistent oncologic resection with a reduced rate
      of recurrence. However, the major limitations with the technique relate to increased
      procedure time and the skill-set required for performing the procedure.

      One of the other major limitations of ESD is significant cost associated with the procedure,
      which includes procedure time and additional equipment in addition to the treatment of any
      subsequent complications. As such the implementation of ESD as the standard of care for all
      colorectal lesions has not been undertaken in Western countries, however it may have an
      important role for selective cases especially where there is concern for sub-mucosal invasive
      cancer (SMIC).

      The investigators propose a selective ESD strategy to be performed for patients focusing on
      overt evidence of SMIC and those at high risk of covert SMIC (defined as risk &gt;10%). The
      investigators will follow a prospective cohort study assessing the use of selective ESD
      strategy in the colorectum in the Western population.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">August 14, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 31, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 31, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Selective treatment algorithm of ESD or EMR according to risk stratification.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of surgical referral</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months post procedure</time_frame>
    <description>Incidence of surgical referral due to non-curative endoscopic resection.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>R0 resection rate</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months post procedure</time_frame>
    <description>Rate of en-bloc resection with clear resection margins.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>En Bloc resection rate</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months post procedure</time_frame>
    <description>Rate of en-bloc resection</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Technical success rate</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months post procedure</time_frame>
    <description>Rate of procedures completed as per protocol</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of procedure</measure>
    <time_frame>procedure</time_frame>
    <description>Procedure duration in minutes.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adenoma recurrence rate</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years post procedure</time_frame>
    <description>Rate of recurrent adenoma at resection site on follow-up.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">391</enrollment>
  <condition>Colorectal Neoplasm</condition>
  <condition>Endoscopic Mucosal Resection</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>ESD</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Lesion with overt stigmata of SMIC or those with high risk (=&gt; 10%) for covert SMIC.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>EMR</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Lesion with no overt or a low risk for (&lt;10%) for covert SMIC</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Endoscopic Submucosal Dissection</intervention_name>
    <description>Endoscopic Submucosal Dissection (ESD) results in en-bloc resection of LSL, regardless of lesion size. This allows for accurate histopathological assessment of SMIC, R0/R1 resection and depth of invasion. ESD is considered a potentially curative for superficial cancers (T1a).</description>
    <arm_group_label>ESD</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>ESD</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Endoscopic Mucosal Resection</intervention_name>
    <description>EMR is the current standard for treating colonic LSL and has been validated to be safe and efficacious. LSLs =&gt; 20mm are frequently resected piecemeal. Recent research show that resection margin soft coagulation reduces recurrence rates to those similar to en-bloc resections.</description>
    <arm_group_label>EMR</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>EMR</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  All patients referred for colorectal resection of large laterally spreading lesions in
             colon.

          -  Can give informed consent to trial participation

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Previous resection or attempted resection of target adenoma lesion

          -  Endoscopic appearance of invasive malignancy

          -  Age less than 18 years

          -  Pregnancy

          -  Active Inflammatory colonic conditions (e.g. inflammatory bowel disease)

          -  Use of anticoagulant or antiplatelet agents other than aspirin outside of
             internationally recognised guidelines

          -  American Society of Anesthesiology (ASA) Grade IV-V
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Michael J Bourke, Prof.</last_name>
    <phone>+61288905555</phone>
    <email>endoscopyresearch.westmead@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Iddo Bar-Yishay, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+61288905555</phone>
    <email>iddo.baryishay@health.nsw.gov.au</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Westmead Endoscopy Unit</name>
      <address>
        <city>Westmead</city>
        <state>New South Wales</state>
        <zip>2145</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Iddo Bar-Yishay, MD</last_name>
      <phone>88905555</phone>
      <email>iddo.baryishay@health.nsw.gov.au</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Australia</country>
  </location_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Winawer SJ, Zauber AG, Ho MN, O'Brien MJ, Gottlieb LS, Sternberg SS, Waye JD, Schapiro M, Bond JH, Panish JF, et al. Prevention of colorectal cancer by colonoscopic polypectomy. The National Polyp Study Workgroup. N Engl J Med. 1993 Dec 30;329(27):1977-81.</citation>
    <PMID>8247072</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Zauber AG, Winawer SJ, O'Brien MJ, Lansdorp-Vogelaar I, van Ballegooijen M, Hankey BF, Shi W, Bond JH, Schapiro M, Panish JF, Stewart ET, Waye JD. Colonoscopic polypectomy and long-term prevention of colorectal-cancer deaths. N Engl J Med. 2012 Feb 23;366(8):687-96. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa1100370.</citation>
    <PMID>22356322</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Iishi H, Tatsuta M, Iseki K, Narahara H, Uedo N, Sakai N, Ishikawa H, Otani T, Ishiguro S. Endoscopic piecemeal resection with submucosal saline injection of large sessile colorectal polyps. Gastrointest Endosc. 2000 Jun;51(6):697-700.</citation>
    <PMID>10840302</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Risio M. The natural history of colorectal adenomas and early cancer. Pathologe. 2012 Nov;33 Suppl 2:206-10. doi: 10.1007/s00292-012-1640-6. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22945585</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Moss A, Bourke MJ, Williams SJ, Hourigan LF, Brown G, Tam W, Singh R, Zanati S, Chen RY, Byth K. Endoscopic mucosal resection outcomes and prediction of submucosal cancer from advanced colonic mucosal neoplasia. Gastroenterology. 2011 Jun;140(7):1909-18. doi: 10.1053/j.gastro.2011.02.062. Epub 2011 Mar 8.</citation>
    <PMID>21392504</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Nanda KS, Tutticci N, Burgess NG, Sonson R, Williams SJ, Bourke MJ. Endoscopic mucosal resection of laterally spreading lesions involving the ileocecal valve: technique, risk factors for failure, and outcomes. Endoscopy. 2015 Aug;47(8):710-8. doi: 10.1055/s-0034-1391732. Epub 2015 Mar 12.</citation>
    <PMID>25763831</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Oka S, Tanaka S, Saito Y, Iishi H, Kudo SE, Ikematsu H, Igarashi M, Saitoh Y, Inoue Y, Kobayashi K, Hisabe T, Tsuruta O, Sano Y, Yamano H, Shimizu S, Yahagi N, Watanabe T, Nakamura H, Fujii T, Ishikawa H, Sugihara K; Colorectal Endoscopic Resection Standardization Implementation Working Group of the Japanese Society for Cancer of the Colon and Rectum, Tokyo, Japan. Local recurrence after endoscopic resection for large colorectal neoplasia: a multicenter prospective study in Japan. Am J Gastroenterol. 2015 May;110(5):697-707. doi: 10.1038/ajg.2015.96. Epub 2015 Apr 7.</citation>
    <PMID>25848926</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Lee EJ, Lee JB, Lee SH, Youk EG. Endoscopic treatment of large colorectal tumors: comparison of endoscopic mucosal resection, endoscopic mucosal resection-precutting, and endoscopic submucosal dissection. Surg Endosc. 2012 Aug;26(8):2220-30. doi: 10.1007/s00464-012-2164-0. Epub 2012 Jan 26.</citation>
    <PMID>22278105</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Terasaki M, Tanaka S, Oka S, Nakadoi K, Takata S, Kanao H, Yoshida S, Chayama K. Clinical outcomes of endoscopic submucosal dissection and endoscopic mucosal resection for laterally spreading tumors larger than 20 mm. J Gastroenterol Hepatol. 2012 Apr;27(4):734-40. doi: 10.1111/j.1440-1746.2011.06977.x.</citation>
    <PMID>22098630</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Burgess NG, Hourigan LF, Zanati SA, Brown GJ, Singh R, Williams SJ, Raftopoulos SC, Ormonde D, Moss A, Byth K, Mahajan H, McLeod D, Bourke MJ. Risk Stratification for Covert Invasive Cancer Among Patients Referred for Colonic Endoscopic Mucosal Resection: A Large Multicenter Cohort. Gastroenterology. 2017 Sep;153(3):732-742.e1. doi: 10.1053/j.gastro.2017.05.047. Epub 2017 Jun 2.</citation>
    <PMID>28583826</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>July 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 2, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 3, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 5, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 8, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 8, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 10, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Western Sydney Local Health District</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Professor Michael Bourke</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Director of Endoscopy</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Colorectal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

