<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04004676</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>113713</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04004676</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Ketone Supplementation, Glycogen Replenishment and Time Trial Performance Following Glycogen Lowering Exercise</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effect of Ketone Supplementation on Glycogen Replenishment and Time Trial Performance Following Glycogen Lowering Exercise</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Western University, Canada</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Western University, Canada</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      20 healthy trained males will volunteer to participate in this study. there will be 2
      treatments: Carbohydrate- ketone supplementation and carbohydrate alone. The purpose of this
      study is to evaluate the effect of glucose-ketone supplementation on a 20 km cycling time
      trial with a 2-hour feeding during a 4-hour recovery period following glycogen depleting
      exercise.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Carbohydrates (starches &amp; sugars) are important muscle fuel for exercise at moderate to high
      intensities. Low glycogen content (stored form of carbohydrates in the body) is associated
      with fatigue. Thus, greater initial glycogen content has been associated with better
      performance not only in high intensity intermittent sports, but also in prolonged endurance
      sports. Dose-response studies have determined that ingestion of 1.2 g·kg-1·h-1 of CHO is the
      appropriate acute recovery dose to optimize glycogen repletion, with no apparent benefit at
      higher doses. Protein in combination with CHO has also been proposed to enhance glycogen
      resynthesis when 1 part protein is provided with ~4 parts CHO. Both strategies, optimal CHO
      intake and CHO in combination with protein for glycogen resynthesis, have resulted in better
      exercise performance a few hours after a depleting exercise bout. A recent study provided
      athletes with ketone esters in a drink after glycogen depleting exercise and found that in
      the presence of high glucose availability, ketone esters increased glycogen stores by 50%
      compared to a no ketone, high carbohydrate treatment. However, the authors of this study
      provided a large quantity of carbohydrates intravenously to maintain blood glucose at 10Mm/L.
      Consequently, it is unknown whether or not ingesting glucose at the optimal dosage would have
      the same effect. Furthermore, it is unclear whether or not this difference would translate
      into improved performance in efforts of more moderate duration. Therefore, the purpose of
      this study is to assess the effect of glucose-ketone supplementation on a 20 km cycling time
      trial with a 2-hour feeding during a 4-hour recovery period following glycogen depleting
      exercise.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 1, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 1, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>This will be a double blind repeated measures cross over study. There will be two treatments involved: cabohydrate-ketone supplements and carbohydrates alone (placebo). Participants will complete the protocol twice and the treatment order will be systematically rotated to avoid any order effect. Design of the study is composed of a glycogen depleting exercise session, followed by 4 hours of recovery/supplementation, and a 20 km cycling time trial. All participants will arrive in a fasted state to the laboratory. a glycogen depleting exercise bout will be done followed by a 4 hour recovery period. during this 4 hours, participants will ingest the corresponding treatment for the first 2 hours. after recovery, they will perform a 20 km cycling time trial.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
    <masking_description>Participants and investigators will be blinded as an individual not involved in the project will assemble and distribute the treatment (drinks) according to a coding system that is kept confidential until the study is completed. Participants will complete the protocol three times and the treatment order will be systematically rotated to avoid any order effect. taste and texture of treatments will be matched and will be distribute in opaque bottles to keep participant blinded</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>20 km cycling time trial</measure>
    <time_frame>40 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>participants will ride for 20 km on a stationary bike and time to finish will be measured</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Blood insulin</measure>
    <time_frame>2 hours</time_frame>
    <description>insulin in blood will be measured using ELISA kits</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Blood Lactate</measure>
    <time_frame>45 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>blood lactate will be measured using lactate meter</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Blood Ketones</measure>
    <time_frame>2 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Ketones in blood will be measured using ketone meter</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Ketonemia</condition>
  <condition>Exercise Performance</condition>
  <condition>Ketosis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>isocaloric carbohydrate - only containing drink will be ingested post glycogen lowering exercise, followed by a 20 km time trial intervention</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Ketone_CHO</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Ketone - Carbohydrate supplementation will be ingested post glycogen lowering exercise, followed by a 20 km time trial intervention</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>20 km time trial performance</intervention_name>
    <description>20 km time trial cycling test will be conducted to measure the effect of different drinks on performance time</description>
    <arm_group_label>Ketone_CHO</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Glycogen lowering exercise</intervention_name>
    <description>Glycogen will be lowered using a 10-min warm-up period at a workload of 50% max wattage power output (Wmax). Thereafter, participants will be instructed to cycle 2-min block periods at alternating workloads of 90% and 50% of Wmax, respectively. This will be continued until the participants are no longer able to complete the 2 min at 90% Wmax. That moment will be defined as the time at which the individual is unable to maintain cycling speed at 60 revolutions/min. At that moment the high-intensity block will be reduced to 80% Wmax. Again, athletes will cycle until they are unable to complete a 2-min block at 80% Wmax, after which the high-intensity block will be reduced to 70% Wmax. Finally, participants will be allowed to stop when pedalling speed could not be maintained at 70% Wmax.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Ketone_CHO</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  In order to be eligible to participate in this study you must be a healthy male or
             female exercise trained individual (at least 1y training experience - at least 3x
             week), aged 18-40 years.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  have not involved been involved in regular exercise (at least 3x week for at least the
             past year)

          -  Have symptoms or take medication for respiratory, cardiovascular, metabolic,
             neuromuscular disease

          -  Use any medications with side effects of dizziness, lack of motor control, or slowed
             reaction time

          -  Are taking part in another research study

          -  For women, if you are pregnant or become pregnant during the study.

          -  Have a history of concussion/head injuries.

          -  Have an excessive alcohol intake (&gt;2 drinks/day)

          -  Are a smoker
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>40 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Peter Lemon, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Western Universiy</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Peter Lemon, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>519 6612111</phone>
    <phone_ext>88139</phone_ext>
    <email>plemon@uwo.ca</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Manuel Quinones, MSc</last_name>
    <phone>519 6612111</phone>
    <phone_ext>88139</phone_ext>
    <email>mquinon2@uwo.ca</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Exercise Nutrition Laboratory (Western University)</name>
      <address>
        <city>London</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>N6A 3K7</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Peter Lemon, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>519 6612111</phone>
      <phone_ext>88139</phone_ext>
      <email>plemon@uwo.ca</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 27, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 27, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 2, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 30, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 30, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 2, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Western University, Canada</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Peter Lemon</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Ketones</keyword>
  <keyword>Glycogen replenishment</keyword>
  <keyword>Exercise Performance</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Ketosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

