<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04006132</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>C71</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04006132</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluation of the Benefits of Bilateral Fitting in BAHS Users</brief_title>
  <official_title>Evaluation of the Benefits of Bilateral Fitting in Bone-anchored Hearing System Users</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Oticon Medical</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Oticon Medical</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to evaluate the benefit of bilateral implantation with
      bone-anchored hearing systems (BAHS), in terms of sound localization abilities, as well as
      auditory working memory. The hypothesis is that the use of two BAHS (bilateral condition)
      will not only improve localization abilities, but it will also increase the ability to retain
      words in working memory, compared to performance with only one BAHS (unilateral condition).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The patients included in this study are adult patients with a bilateral conductive or mixed
      hearing loss, that are already bilaterally implanted with two percutaneous bone-anchored
      devices (BAHS). The study consists of two visits. At visit 1, the patients are fitted
      unilaterally and bilaterally with the investigational device (Ponto 3 SuperPower). After
      fitting, the patients perform a test of spatial resolution (minimum audible angle, visit 1)
      and an auditory working memory test (visit 2). These two outcome measures are conducted in
      the laboratory using the Ponto 3 SuperPower unilaterally and bilaterally. Additionally, the
      patients fill in a questionnaire (SSQ12) to report perceived performance in their everyday
      life with their own devices. This is a post market study and all products used are CE marked
      and used in clinical practice worldwide.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 4, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">January 10, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">January 7, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
    <masking_description>The participants are blinded to the tested condition (unilateral vs bilateral)</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Minimum Audible Angle test</measure>
    <time_frame>4 months</time_frame>
    <description>Minimum angle at which noise bursts are accurately localized (Right/Left) in the unilateral and bilateral conditions</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>SWIR test</measure>
    <time_frame>4 months</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of recalled words in the unilateral and bilateral conditions</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>SSQ12</measure>
    <time_frame>4 months</time_frame>
    <description>Subjective performance as measured by Speech, Spatial and Qualities of Hearing questionnaire (SSQ); 12 items with a scale from 0-10 where 0 represents &quot;Not at all&quot; and 10 represents &quot;Perfect&quot;</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">26</enrollment>
  <condition>Bilateral Hearing Loss</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Ponto 3 SuperPower sound processor</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>All patients will be fitted with two bone-anchored sound processors (Ponto 3 SuperPower), unilaterally and bilaterally.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Fitting of Ponto 3 SuperPower</intervention_name>
    <description>Bone-anchored hearing systems (BAHS) use the body's natural ability to transfer sound through bone conduction. The sound processor picks up sound and converts it into vibrations that are transferred through the skull bone to the inner ear (cochlea). Thus, for patients with conductive or mixed hearing losses, patients with lasting hearing loss following a middle ear disease or malformations (such as microtia), the vibrations are bypassing the conductive problem in the ear canal or middle ear. The intervention in this study is audiologically fitting two bone-anchored sound processors (Ponto 3 SuperPower) to patients that are already bilaterally implanted with abutments.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Ponto 3 SuperPower sound processor</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Adult BAHS users, minimum 18 years and maximum 75 years.

          -  Native English speakers.

          -  Patients that are already bilaterally implanted.

          -  Patients with a bilateral conductive or mixed conductive-sensorineural hearing loss.

          -  Experience with bilateral Ponto of at least 6 months.

          -  Patients that are using both their sound processors daily.

          -  PTA BC (at 0.5, 1, 2, 3 kHz) on both sides lower or equal to 65 dB HL.

          -  If the masked BC is available on the patient's journal, the average difference in
             masked BC (at 0.5, 1, 2, 4 kHz) between L and R ear should be lower than 15 dB.

          -  If the masked BC is not available on the patient's journal, the average difference in
             unmasked BC (at 0.5, 1, 2, 4 kHz) between L and R ear should be lower than 15 dB.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Not deemed suited by the principal investigator.

          -  If the physician assesses that the patient is not fit for trial participation at any
             stage.

          -  Audiogram at 1st visit shows too large masked BC thresholds (PTA BC - at 0.5, 1, 2, 3
             kHz - on either side larger than 65 dB HL).

          -  Audiogram at 1st visit shows asymmetric masked BC thresholds (average difference in
             masked BC - at 0.5, 1, 2, 4 kHz - between L and R ear larger or equal to 15 dB).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>William Brassington</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University Hospitals Birmingham, United Kingdom</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Audiology Department, Nuffield House, University Hospitals Birmingham</name>
      <address>
        <city>Birmingham</city>
        <state>West Midlands</state>
        <zip>B15 2TH</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 27, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 1, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 5, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 22, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 22, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 23, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Bone anchored hearing systems</keyword>
  <keyword>BAHS</keyword>
  <keyword>Bilateral benefit</keyword>
  <keyword>Ponto 3 SuperPower</keyword>
  <keyword>Minimum Audible Angle</keyword>
  <keyword>Auditory working memory</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hearing Loss</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hearing Loss, Bilateral</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

