<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04009096</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>VAC071</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04009096</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>VAC071: A Study to Assess Efficacy of the ChAd63/MVA PvDBP Vaccines</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase IIa Challenge Study to Assess Efficacy of the Plasmodium Vivax Malaria Vaccine Candidates ChAd63 PvDBP and MVA PvDBP in Healthy Adults Living in the UK</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Oxford</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Oxford</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is an open label, Phase IIa, controlled human malaria infection (CHMI) study aimed to
      assess whether the new vivax malaria vaccines ChAd63 PvDBP and MVA PvDBP can protect against
      malaria infection.

      The participants will receive two vaccinations, one dose of each vaccine, administered 8
      weeks apart.

      Approximately 4 weeks after the second vacccination, the volunteers will be challenged
      (deliberately infected) with malaria by intravenous injection blood-stage
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Volunteers will be recruited and vaccinated at the CCVTM, Oxford.

      There will be two vaccinated groups across two phases of the trial, with a total of 15
      volunteers. These will be compared to 15 infectivity controls who will be recruited as part
      of a separate study (VAC069 - NCT03797989).

      Study participants will be involved in this trial for approximately 1 year.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 18, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Efficacy of the ChAd63 and MVA PvDBP vaccines, administered in a heterologous prime-boost regimen, assessed by a reduced parasite multiplication rate in vaccinated subjects</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Quantitative PCR-derived parasite multiplication rate (PMR) will be the primary efficacy endpoint and a comparison of the endpoint between Groups 1 and 2 (pooled data) and malaria-naïve controls partaking in simultaneous CHMI, under identical conditions, will constitute the primary analysis for efficacy.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety of the ChAd63 and MVA PvDBP vaccines andidates, administered in a heterologous prime-boost regimen in a CHMI study in healthy volunteers</measure>
    <time_frame>for approximately 1 year following priming with ChAd63 PvDBP</time_frame>
    <description>The specific endpoints for safety and reactogenicity will be actively and passively collected data on adverse events.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The humoral immunogenicity ChAd63 and MVA PvDBP vaccine candidates, administered in a heterologous prime-boost regimen</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Antibody responses to the P. vivax Duffy-binding protein (PvDBP) - total IgG, isotypes and avidity</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The cellular immunogenicity ChAd63 and MVA PvDBP vaccine candidates, administered in a heterologous prime-boost regimen</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>T cell responses to PvDBP by ex-vivo ELISpot and flow cytometry assays and in vitro functional PvDBP_RII inhibitory binding assays.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Immunological readouts for association with a reduced parasite multiplication rate</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Statistical correlation between anti-PvDBP antibody responses induced by the ChAd63 and MVA PvDBP vaccines and PMR.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">15</enrollment>
  <condition>Malaria, Vivax</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>3 volunteers receiving one dose of 5 x 10^10 vp ChAd63 PvDBP and one dose of 2 x 10^8 pfu MVA PvDBP 8 weeks later, in a heterologous prime-boost regimen, followed by blood-stage CHMI 2 weeks later.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>12 volunteers receiving one dose of 5 x 10^10 vp ChAd63 PvDBP and one dose of 2 x 10^8 pfu MVA PvDBP 8 weeks later, in a heterologous prime-boost regimen, followed by blood-stage CHMI 2 weeks later.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ChAd63 PvDBP and MVA PvDBP</intervention_name>
    <description>one dose of 5 x 10^10 vp ChAd63 PvDBP and one dose of 2 x 10^8 pfu MVA PvDBP 8 weeks later, in a heterologous prime-boost regimen.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Group 2</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Healthy adult aged 18 to 45 years.

          -  Red blood cells positive for the Duffy antigen/chemokine receptor (DARC).

          -  Normal serum levels of Glucose-6-phosphate dehydrogenase (G6PD).

          -  Able and willing (in the Investigator's opinion) to comply with all study
             requirements.

          -  Willing to allow the Investigators to discuss the volunteer's medical history with
             their General Practitioner.

          -  Women only: Must practice continuous effective contraception* for the duration of the
             study

          -  Agreement to permanently refrain from blood donation

          -  Written informed consent to participate in the trial.

          -  Reachable (24/7) by mobile phone during the period between CHMI and completion of all
             antimalarial treatment.

          -  Willing to take a curative anti-malarial regimen following CHMI.

          -  Willing to reside in Oxford for the duration of the study, until antimalarials have
             been completed.

          -  Answer all questions on the informed consent quiz correctly.

               -  Female volunteers are required to use an effective form of contraception during
                  the course of the study as malaria challenge could pose a serious risk to both
                  maternal health and the unborn foetus.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  History of clinical malaria (any species).

          -  Travel to a clearly malaria endemic locality during the study period or within the
             preceding six months.

          -  Current or planned treatment with long-acting immune-modifying drugs at any time
             during the study period (e.g. infliximab).

          -  Chronic use of antibiotics with antimalarial effects (e.g. tetracyclines for
             dermatologic patients, trimethoprim-sulfamethoxazole for recurrent urinary tract
             infections, etc.).

          -  Haemoglobin &lt;125 g/L for a female volunteer or &lt;135 g/L for a male volunteer), as
             measured at screening

          -  Weight less than 50kg, as measured at the screening visit

          -  Use of immunoglobulins or blood products (e.g., blood transfusion) at any time in the
             past

          -  Peripheral venous access unlikely to allow twice daily blood testing (as determined by
             the Investigator)

          -  Receipt of an investigational product in the 30 days preceding enrolment, or planned
             receipt during the study period

          -  Receipt of any vaccine in the 30 days preceding enrolment, or planned receipt of any
             other vaccine within 30 days following each vaccination

          -  Concurrent involvement in another clinical trial or planned involvement during the
             study period

          -  Prior receipt of an investigational vaccine likely to impact on interpretation of the
             trial data or the P. vivax parasite as assessed by the Investigator

          -  History of sickle cell anaemia, sickle cell trait, thalassaemia or thalassaemia trait
             or any haematological condition that could affect susceptibility to malaria infection.

          -  Any confirmed or suspected immunosuppressive or immunodeficient state, including HIV
             infection; asplenia; recurrent, severe infections and chronic (more than 14 days)
             immunosuppressant medication within the past 6 months (inhaled and topical steroids
             are allowed).

          -  History of allergic disease or reactions likely to be exacerbated by any component of
             the vaccine e.g. egg products, Kathon

          -  History of allergic disease or reactions likely to be exacerbated by malaria
             infection.

        History of clinically significant contact dermatitis

          -  Any history of anaphylaxis in reaction to vaccinations

          -  Pregnancy, lactation or intention to become pregnant during the study.

          -  Use of medications known to cause prolongation of the QT interval and existing
             contraindication to the use of Malarone.

        Use of medications known to have a potentially clinically significant interaction with
        Riamet and Malarone.

          -  Any clinical condition known to prolong the QT interval.

          -  History of cardiac arrhythmia, including clinically relevant bradycardia.

          -  Disturbances of electrolyte balance, e.g. hypokalaemia or hypomagnesaemia.

          -  Family history of congenital QT prolongation or sudden death.

          -  Contraindications to the use of both of the proposed anti-malarial medications; Riamet
             Malarone.

          -  History of cancer (except basal cell carcinoma of the skin and cervical carcinoma in
             situ).

          -  History of serious psychiatric condition that may affect participation in the study.

          -  Any other serious chronic illness requiring hospital specialist supervision.

          -  Suspected or known current alcohol abuse as defined by an alcohol intake of greater
             than 25 standard UK units every week.

          -  Suspected or known injecting drug abuse in the 5 years preceding enrolment.

          -  Hepatitis B surface antigen (HBsAg) detected in serum.

          -  Seropositive for hepatitis C virus (antibodies to HCV) at screening or (unless has
             taken part in a prior hepatitis C vaccine study with confirmed negative HCV antibodies
             prior to participation in that study, and negative HCV RNA PCR at screening for this
             study).

          -  Positive family history in both 1st AND 2nd degree relatives &lt; 50 years old for
             cardiac disease.

          -  Volunteers unable to be closely followed for social, geographic or psychological
             reasons.

          -  Any clinically significant abnormal finding on biochemistry or haematology blood
             tests, urinalysis or clinical examination. In the event of abnormal test results,
             confirmatory repeat tests will be requested. Procedures for identifying laboratory
             values meeting exclusion criteria are shown in SOP VC027.

          -  Any other significant disease, disorder, or finding which may significantly increase
             the risk to the volunteer because of participation in the study, affect the ability of
             the volunteer to participate in the study or impair interpretation of the study data.

          -  Inability of the study team to contact the volunteer's GP to confirm medical history
             and safety to participate
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>45 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Angela M Minassian, MBBS MA DPhil MRCP FRCPath</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Oxford</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Volunteer Recruitment Co-ordinator</last_name>
    <phone>01865 611424</phone>
    <email>vaccinetrials@ndm.ox.ac.uk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Volunteer Recruitment Co-ordinator</last_name>
    <email>vaccinetrials@ndm.ox.ac.uk</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Centre for Clinical Vaccinology &amp; Tropical Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Oxford</city>
        <state>Oxfordshire</state>
        <zip>OX3 7LE</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Angela M Minassian</last_name>
      <phone>01865 611425</phone>
      <email>angela.minassian@ndm.ox.ac.uk</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Fay L Nugent</last_name>
      <phone>01865 611412</phone>
      <email>fay.nugent@ndm.ox.ac.uk</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 3, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 3, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 5, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 13, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 13, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">September 16, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>PvDBP</keyword>
  <keyword>efficacy</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Malaria</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Malaria, Vivax</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

