<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04005170</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>TORIDEFEC</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04005170</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Combination of Toripalimab and Chemoradiotherapy in Esophageal Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase II Trial of Combination of Toripalimab and Definitive Chemoradiotherapy in Esophageal Squamous Cell Carcinoma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Mian XI</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Sun Yat-sen University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Definitive chemoradiotherapy (CRT) is the standard treatment option for unresectable
      esophageal cancer (EC). However, as high as more than 40% of EC patients experienced
      locoregional recurrence after concurrent CRT. Immunotherapy targeting the PD-1/PD-L1
      checkpoints has demonstrated promising activity in advanced EC. The aim of this study was to
      evaluate the efficacy and safety of the combination of toripalimab (an anti-PD-1 antibody)
      combined with definitive CRT in locally advanced esophageal squamous cell carcinoma (ESCC).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 25, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>clinical complete response rate</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months after chemoradiotherapy (plus or minus 14 days)</time_frame>
    <description>Tumor response was evaluated 3 months after the completion of chemoradiotherapy based on CT or PET-CT scans, endoscopy with biopsies.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>2-year overall survival</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of randomization until the date of death from any cause or the date of last follow-up, whichever came first, assessed up to 24 months</time_frame>
    <description>The 2-year overall survival of the whole group</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>2-year progression-free survival</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of randomization until the date of death from any cause or the date of first documented disease progression whichever came first, assessed up to 24 months</time_frame>
    <description>The 2-year progression-free survival of the whole group</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of response</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of first CR/PR to the date of first PD according to RECIST criteria, assessed up to 24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Tumor response was evaluated every two months after chemoradiotherapy according to RECIST criteria</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of treatment-related adverse events as assessed by CTCAE v4.0</measure>
    <time_frame>From the start of treatment to 2 year after the completion of treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Toxicity of treatment was evaluated according to CTCAE 4.0</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>The impact of PD-L1 expression on clinical response</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline biopsies of primary tumor in esophagus</time_frame>
    <description>To investigate the impact of programmed cell death-ligand 1 (PD-L1) expression on clinical response</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>The impact of IDO1 expression on clinical response</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline biopsies of primary tumor in esophagus</time_frame>
    <description>To investigate the impact of indoleamine 2,3-dioxygenase 1 (IDO1) expression on clinical response</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">42</enrollment>
  <condition>Unresectable Esophageal Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>PD-1 group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>All patients will receive standard fractionation radiation therapy (RT) scheme: 50.4 Gy in 28 fractions over 5-6 weeks, concurrently with 5 cycles of paclitaxel/cisplatin (paclitaxel 50mg/m2 and cisplatin 25 mg/m2) on days 1, 8, 15, 22, 29 and 2 cycles of toripalimab 240 mg on days 1, 22 followed by a maintenance phase of toripalimab IV 240 mg every 3 weeks for up to 1 year.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Toripalimab</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients received toripalimab 240 mg on days 1 and 22 during radiotherapy followed by a maintenance phase of toripalimab IV 240 mg every 3 weeks for up to 1 year.</description>
    <arm_group_label>PD-1 group</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>JS-001</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Paclitaxel/Cisplatin</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients received 5 cycles of paclitaxel/cisplatin (paclitaxel 50mg/m2 and cisplatin 25 mg/m2) on days 1, 8, 15, 22, 29 during radiotherapy.</description>
    <arm_group_label>PD-1 group</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>TP</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Radiation</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Intensity-modulated radiotherapy</intervention_name>
    <description>All patients received external-beam radiation using intensity-modulated radiotherapy. The prescribed dose is 50.4 Gy in 28 fractions over 5-6 weeks.</description>
    <arm_group_label>PD-1 group</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>IMRT</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Histologically confirmed squamous cell carcinoma of the esophagus;

          2. Absence of hematogenous metastasis disease, confirmed by endoscopic ultrasound (EUS)
             and PET-CT scan (according to UICC TNM version 8);

          3. Not suitable for surgery (either for medical reasons or patient's choice);

          4. Age at diagnosis 18 to 70 years;

          5. No prior cancer therapy;

          6. Estimated life expectancy &gt;6 months;

          7. Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group performance status ≤ 2

          8. No history of concomitant or previous malignancy;

          9. The function of important organs meets the following requirements: a. white blood cell
             count (WBC) ≥ 4.0×109/L, absolute neutrophil count (ANC) ≥ 1.5×109/L; b. platelets ≥
             100×109/L; c. hemoglobin ≥ 9g/dL; d. serum albumin ≥ 2.8g/dL; e. total bilirubin ≤
             1.5×ULN, ALT, AST and/or AKP ≤ 2.5×ULN; f. serum creatinine ≤ 1.5×ULN or creatinine
             clearance rate &gt;60 mL/min;

         10. Ability to understand the study and sign informed consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients who have been treated previously with anti-tumor therapy (including
             chemotherapy, radiotherapy, surgery, immunotherapy, etc.);

          2. Patients with hematogenous metastasis disease at diagnosis;

          3. Known or suspected allergy or hypersensitivity to monoclonal antibodies, any
             ingredients of Toripalimab, and the chemotherapeutic drugs paclitaxel or cisplatin;

          4. Patients who have a preexisting or coexisting bleeding disorder;

          5. Female patients who are pregnant or lactating;

          6. Inability to provide informed consent due to psychological, familial, social and other
             factors;

          7. Presence of CTC grade ≥ 3 peripheral neuropathy;

          8. A history of malignancies other than esophageal cancer before enrollment, excluding
             non-melanoma skin cancer, in situ cervical cancer, or cured early prostate cancer

          9. A history of diabetes for more than 10 years and poorly controlled blood glucose
             levels;

         10. Patients who cannot tolerate chemoradiotherapy due to severe cardiac, lung, liver or
             kidney dysfunction, or hematopoietic disease or cachexia.

         11. Active autoimmune diseases, a history of autoimmune diseases (including but not
             limited to these diseases or syndromes, such as colitis, hepatitis, hyperthyroidism),
             a history of immunodeficiency (including a positive HIV test result), or other
             acquired or congenital immunodeficiency diseases, a history of organ transplantation
             or allogeneic bone marrow transplantation;

         12. A history of interstitial lung disease or non-infectious pneumonia;

         13. A history of active pulmonary tuberculosis infection within 1 year or a history of
             active pulmonary tuberculosis infection more than 1 year ago but without formal
             anti-tuberculosis treatment;

         14. Presence of active hepatitis B (HBV DNA ≥ 2000 IU/mL or 104 copies/mL), hepatitis C
             hepatitis C antibody, and HCV-RNA levels higher than the lower limit of the assay).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Mian XI, MD</last_name>
    <phone>86-20-87343385</phone>
    <email>ximian@sysucc.org.cn</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sun Yat-sen University Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Guanzhou</city>
        <state>Guangdong</state>
        <zip>510060</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Mian Xi, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+86-20-87343385</phone>
      <email>ximian@sysucc.org.cn</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fu J, Wang F, Dong LH, Zhang J, Deng CL, Wang XL, Xie XY, Zhang J, Deng RX, Zhang LB, Wu H, Feng H, Chen B, Song HF. Preclinical evaluation of the efficacy, pharmacokinetics and immunogenicity of JS-001, a programmed cell death protein-1 (PD-1) monoclonal antibody. Acta Pharmacol Sin. 2017 May;38(5):710-718. doi: 10.1038/aps.2016.161. Epub 2017 Mar 20.</citation>
    <PMID>28317872</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tang B, Yan X, Sheng X, Si L, Cui C, Kong Y, Mao L, Lian B, Bai X, Wang X, Li S, Zhou L, Yu J, Dai J, Wang K, Hu J, Dong L, Song H, Wu H, Feng H, Yao S, Chi Z, Guo J. Safety and clinical activity with an anti-PD-1 antibody JS001 in advanced melanoma or urologic cancer patients. J Hematol Oncol. 2019 Jan 14;12(1):7. doi: 10.1186/s13045-018-0693-2.</citation>
    <PMID>30642373</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zhou S, Zhao L, Liang Z, Liu S, Li Y, Liu S, Yang H, Liu M, Xi M. Indoleamine 2,3-dioxygenase 1 and Programmed Cell Death-ligand 1 Co-expression Predicts Poor Pathologic Response and Recurrence in Esophageal Squamous Cell Carcinoma after Neoadjuvant Chemoradiotherapy. Cancers (Basel). 2019 Feb 1;11(2). pii: E169. doi: 10.3390/cancers11020169.</citation>
    <PMID>30717285</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>July 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 26, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 30, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 2, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 1, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 1, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 5, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Sun Yat-sen University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Mian XI</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Esophageal squamous cell carcinoma</keyword>
  <keyword>Definitive chemoradiotherapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Toripalimab</keyword>
  <keyword>Clinical complete response</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Esophageal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Esophageal Squamous Cell Carcinoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Paclitaxel</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cisplatin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

