<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04006769</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>gist-ent</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04006769</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Entacapone Combination With Imatinib for Treatment of GIST</brief_title>
  <official_title>Entacapone in Combination With Imatinib Mesylate for Treatment of Patients With Gastrointestinal Stromal Tumors(GIST) Following Failure of at Least Imatinib and Sunitinib</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Xiangya Hospital of Central South University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Xiangya Hospital of Central South University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study evaluates the combination of entacapone and imatinib in the treatment of
      gastrointestinal stromal Tumors who have progressed on the setting of at least Imatinib and
      Sunitinib. 5 participants will be included in this open-label observatory study.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Most patients with Metastatic/unresectable Gastrointestinal stromal tumors will progress on
      the treatment of tyrosine kinase inhibitor(TKI) including Imatinib and Sunitinib.

      Entacapone and imatinib can each inhibit the role of v-kit Hardy-Zuckerman 4 feline sarcoma
      viral oncogene homolog(KIT) which is a kind of transmembrane receptor tyrosine kinase
      promoting the clonal proliferation and growth of GIST cells, but they do so by different
      mechanisms.

      Entacapone has been approved from China Food and Drug Administration(cFDA) for controlling
      the symptom of Parkinson' s disease in the combination with levodopa. Recently, entacapone
      was identified to be an inhibitor of Fat mass and obesity-associated protein(FTO) enzyme,
      which was reported as the first N6-methyladenosine (m6A) demethylase of eukaryotic messenger
      RNA(mRNA). Entacapone can inhibit the transcriptional level of KIT mRNA leading to the
      decreased expression of KIT protein.

      Imatinib mesylate, an oral multiple TKI targeting the KIT-oncoprotein, was the standard
      first-line therapy of c-KIT-mutated GISTs. Imatinib can prohibit the activation of mutated
      c-KIT tyrosine kinase and then impede the kinase cascade of c-KIT signal pathway.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">July 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Early Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Objective response rate(ORR)</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days, 90days, 180days</time_frame>
    <description>the total proportion of patients with reduction in tumor burden of a predefined amount. The ORR is the sum of complete response(CR)+partial responses(PR) per Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors(RECIST) v1.1</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Disease control rate(DCR)</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days, 90days, 180days</time_frame>
    <description>the total proportion of patients who demonstrate a response to treatment. The DCR is the sum of complete response(CR)+partial responses(PR)+ stable disease(SD) per Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors(RECIST) v1.1</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">5</enrollment>
  <condition>Gastrointestinal Stromal Tumor, Malignant</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Entacapone &amp; Imatinib mesylate</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Entacapone 200mg tablet by mouth, three times a day and then increasing to 400mg tablet by mouth, three times a day until disease progression, intolerable toxicity, or withdrawal of informed consent, whichever occurs first.
And Imatinib mesylate 400mg tablet by mouth, once a day until disease progression, intolerable toxicity, or withdrawal of informed consent, whichever occurs first.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Entacapone</intervention_name>
    <description>Entacapone tablet</description>
    <arm_group_label>Entacapone &amp; Imatinib mesylate</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Comtan</other_name>
    <other_name>Comtess</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Imatinib Mesylate</intervention_name>
    <description>Imatinib Mesylate tablet</description>
    <arm_group_label>Entacapone &amp; Imatinib mesylate</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Gleevec</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Able to provide written informed consent and can understand and comply with the
             requirements of the study and the schedule of assessments.

          2. Age ≥ 18 years on the day of signing the informed consent form (or the legal age of
             consent in the jurisdiction in which the study is taking place).

          3. Expected life span &gt; 12 weeks.

          4. Histologically confirmed disease which is currently metastatic/unresectable
             gastrointestinal stroma tumor(GIST) of c-KIT E11 mutation genotype.

          5. Patients received imatinib as the first-line treatment and no progression within the
             first 6 months(no primary resistance to imatinib ). With disease progression following
             treatment with at least imatinib and sunitinib.

          6. Patients must be able to provide archival tumor tissues (approximately 4 [at least 2]
             unstained Formalin Fixed and Paraffin Embedded Tissues （FFPET）slides) for biomarker
             analysis to assess the expression of FTO and c-KIT protein.

          7. At least 1 measurable lesion (the longest diameter≥ 10mm). Note: Computed
             Tomography（CT） abdomen and pelvis with contrast including peritoneum, or positron
             emission tomography/computed tomography(PET/CT) performed skull base to knees or whole
             body before the first day of entacapone.

          8. Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group-performance status(ECOG PS) ≤ 2,or 3(the symptoms
             were definitely caused by GIST itself).

          9. Adequate hematologic and end-organ function, as defined by the following laboratory
             results (obtained ≤ 28 days prior to the first day of entacapone):

               -  Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) ≥ 1.5 × 10 9 /L, hemoglobin ≥ 80 g/L and
                  platelets ≥80 × 10 9 /L.

               -  Total serum bilirubin ≤ 2.5 × upper limit of normal (ULN); Aspartate and alanine
                  aminotransferase (AST and ALT) ≤ 2.5× ULN.

               -  Estimated creatinine clearance rate≥ 60 mL/min（According to the formula of
                  Cockcroft-Gault）.

         10. Females of childbearing potential must be willing to practice highly effective method
             of birth control for the duration of the study, and at least 120 days after the last
             dose of entacapone or imatinib. Non-sterile males must be willing to use a highly
             effective method of birth control for the duration of the study and at least 120 days
             after the last dose of entacapone or imatinib.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Age &lt; 18 years on the day of signing the informed consent form (or the legal age of
             consent in the jurisdiction in which the study is taking place).

          2. Progression within the first 6 months of first-line imatinib treatment (primary
             imatinib resistance).

          3. Patients with active/symptomatic carrier or chronic hepatitis B virus (HBV) whose HBV
             DNA ≥ 1×104 copies/mL should be excluded. Note: Patients with detectable hepatitis B
             surface antigen(HBsAg) or HBV DNA should be managed per treatment guidelines. Patients
             receiving antivirals at screening should have been treated for ≥2 weeks prior to
             written informed consent and should continue treatment for 6 months after study drug
             treatment discontinues.

             Note: Patients with active hepatitis C may enroll and those with detectable hepatitis
             C virus(HCV) RNA who are receiving antiviral therapy at time of screening should
             remain on continuous, effective antiviral therapy during the study.

          4. A known history of human immunodeficiency virus(HIV) infection.

          5. Malignancy other than GIST and still under the active treatment.

          6. Was administered a live vaccine ≤ 4 weeks before written informed consent.

          7. Any of the following medical conditions may threaten the safety of patients or affect
             the trial obedience including symptomatic heart failure requiring systematic
             treatment, unstable angina , acute myocardial infarction and severe chronic or active
             infections (including tuberculosis infection) requiring systemic antibacterial,
             antifungal, or antiviral therapy.

          8. History of severe hypersensitivity reactions to any ingredient of entacapone and
             imatinib.

          9. Pheochromocytoma or history of neuroleptic malignant syndrome(NMS) and/or
             non-traumatic rhabdomyolysis (NRML).

         10. Female in pregnancy or lactation(Urine or serum pregnancy test and documented as
             negative within 7 days prior to the first dose of entacapone for the female with
             fertility expectation or sexual intercourse.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Bin Li, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Xiangya Hospital, Central South University, Changsha, Hunan,China,410008</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Zhi Li, PHD</last_name>
    <phone>+86-1580265-4231</phone>
    <email>peries@csu.edu.cn</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Lun-Quan Sun, PHD</last_name>
    <phone>+86-13908454347</phone>
    <email>lunquansun@csu.edu.cn</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Bin Li, MD</name>
      <address>
        <city>Changsha</city>
        <state>Hunan</state>
        <zip>410008</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Bin Li, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+8613467713587</phone>
      <email>bincsuxy@csu.edu.cn</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Demetri GD, von Mehren M, Blanke CD, Van den Abbeele AD, Eisenberg B, Roberts PJ, Heinrich MC, Tuveson DA, Singer S, Janicek M, Fletcher JA, Silverman SG, Silberman SL, Capdeville R, Kiese B, Peng B, Dimitrijevic S, Druker BJ, Corless C, Fletcher CD, Joensuu H. Efficacy and safety of imatinib mesylate in advanced gastrointestinal stromal tumors. N Engl J Med. 2002 Aug 15;347(7):472-80.</citation>
    <PMID>12181401</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Demetri GD, van Oosterom AT, Garrett CR, Blackstein ME, Shah MH, Verweij J, McArthur G, Judson IR, Heinrich MC, Morgan JA, Desai J, Fletcher CD, George S, Bello CL, Huang X, Baum CM, Casali PG. Efficacy and safety of sunitinib in patients with advanced gastrointestinal stromal tumour after failure of imatinib: a randomised controlled trial. Lancet. 2006 Oct 14;368(9544):1329-38.</citation>
    <PMID>17046465</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tabone S, Théou N, Wozniak A, Saffroy R, Deville L, Julié C, Callard P, Lavergne-Slove A, Debiec-Rychter M, Lemoine A, Emile JF. KIT overexpression and amplification in gastrointestinal stromal tumors (GISTs). Biochim Biophys Acta. 2005 Jun 30;1741(1-2):165-72. Epub 2005 Apr 13.</citation>
    <PMID>15869870</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Peng S, Xiao W, Ju D, Sun B, Hou N, Liu Q, Wang Y, Zhao H, Gao C, Zhang S, Cao R, Li P, Huang H, Ma Y, Wang Y, Lai W, Ma Z, Zhang W, Huang S, Wang H, Zhang Z, Zhao L, Cai T, Zhao YL, Wang F, Nie Y, Zhi G, Yang YG, Zhang EE, Huang N. Identification of entacapone as a chemical inhibitor of FTO mediating metabolic regulation through FOXO1. Sci Transl Med. 2019 Apr 17;11(488). pii: eaau7116. doi: 10.1126/scitranslmed.aau7116.</citation>
    <PMID>30996080</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Eisenhauer EA, Therasse P, Bogaerts J, Schwartz LH, Sargent D, Ford R, Dancey J, Arbuck S, Gwyther S, Mooney M, Rubinstein L, Shankar L, Dodd L, Kaplan R, Lacombe D, Verweij J. New response evaluation criteria in solid tumours: revised RECIST guideline (version 1.1). Eur J Cancer. 2009 Jan;45(2):228-47. doi: 10.1016/j.ejca.2008.10.026.</citation>
    <PMID>19097774</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 27, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 30, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 5, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 30, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 30, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 5, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Xiangya Hospital of Central South University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Lun-Quan Sun</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Director of Center for molecular medicine, Xiangya hospital, Central South University</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>entacapone</keyword>
  <keyword>Imatinib mesylate</keyword>
  <keyword>GIST</keyword>
  <keyword>treatment</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Gastrointestinal Stromal Tumors</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Imatinib Mesylate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Entacapone</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>De-identified individual participant data for all primary and secondary outcome measures will be made available.</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Statistical Analysis Plan (SAP)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Informed Consent Form (ICF)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Clinical Study Report (CSR)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Analytic Code</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>Data will be available within 6 months of study completion.</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>Data access requests will be reviewed by an external independent Review Panel. Requestors will be required to sign a Data Access Agreement.</ipd_access_criteria>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

