<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04007679</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>KutahyaMSUnpq</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04007679</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Pain Neuroscience Education In Students</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Effects Of Pain Neuroscience Education In Undergraduate Physiotherapy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Kutahya Medical Sciences University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Kutahya Medical Sciences University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study was designed to evaluate the effect of a 70-minute Pain neuroscience education
      (PNE) session on physiotherapy students' knowledge of pain and their beliefs and attitudes
      about the treatment of patients with chronic pain.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      To investigate the effect of a 70 minute pain neuroscience education session on physiotherapy
      students' knowledge of pain and their beliefs and attitudes about the treatment of patients
      with chronic pain. This study was a single-center, cross-sectional study on the pain
      knowledge of students in a four-year physiotherapy program and their beliefs and attitudes
      about patients with back pain.Students were eligible to participate if they were enrolled at
      physiotherapy undergraduate program at Kütahya Health Sciences University Faculty of Health
      Sciences. Individuals were excluded if they had previously received in depth-teaching on pain
      neuroscience. The study was completed with 156 students from different classes (first,
      second, and third year of the program) who agreed to participate in the study. All
      participants were informed about the study and signed informed consent forms. Pain
      neurophysiology questionnaire and Pain Attitudes and Beliefs Scale for Physiotherapists were
      used to assess pain knowladge and attitudes and beliefs. After recording their demographic
      information, the participants completed the Neuroscience of Pain Questionnaire (NPQ) and Pain
      Attitudes and Beliefs Scale for Physiotherapists (PABS-PT) at three time points: pre-PNE,
      immediately post-PNE, and 6 months after PNE.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 20, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 30, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 30, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Neurophysiology of Pain Questionnaire (NPQ)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and six months</time_frame>
    <description>The NPQ was designed to assess pain knowledge and consists of 19 questions with choices of &quot;true&quot;, &quot;false&quot;, or &quot;I don't know.&quot; The questionnaire was developed in 2003 by Moseley , the validity study was conducted by Catley et al. , and it was determined as effective in the evaluation of pain knowledge. The total score is 0-19, with higher score indicating more correct answers. It was reported that the NPQ can be used both with healthcare professionals and with patients after some modifications to make it more comprehensible for patients.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pain Attitudes and Beliefs Scale for Physiotherapists (PABS-PT)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and six months</time_frame>
    <description>This tool was developed to distinguish between biomedical and biopsychosocial orientations toward the treatment of low back pain in physiotherapists. In the biomedical treatment orientation, the predominant belief is that the source of pain and disability is a specific pathology and tissue damage, and therefore the main goal is to treat the signs and symptoms of the pathology [19]. In the biopsychosocial treatment orientation, pain and disability can occur in the absence of tissue injury and are affected by psychological and social factors. The scale uses a 6-point Likert-type scale (1=definitely disagree, 6=definitely agree). Treatment orientation is measured on the biomedical (factor 1) and biopsychosocial (factor 2) subscales. Subscale scores are calculated by simply adding the scores corresponding to the selected response for each item.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">156</enrollment>
  <condition>Chronic Pain</condition>
  <condition>Educational Problems</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Pain education group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Pain education was conducted in physical conditions similar to the university classrooms where the study was performed for all participants.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pain neuroscience education</intervention_name>
    <description>Pain neuroscience education (PNE) was conducted in physical conditions similar to the university classrooms where the study was performed. The sessions were conducted as 70-minute didactic group lessons with the same content held in separate sessions for students in each class. PowerPoint (Microsoft Corp., Redmond, WA, USA) presentations prepared by the instructor were used in all sessions. Metaphors, anecdotes, graphics, and pictures were used in an attempt to convey the information and messages about pain physiology and theory more permanently and effectively. In the PNE sessions, it was explained that the nervous system can be overprotective and that in addition to the sensitivity of the central nervous system, nociceptive transmission can be affected by an individual's thoughts, beliefs, and surroundings. At the end of the session, the students were given time to ask questions, but group discussion was limited to 15 minutes due to time restrictions.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Pain education group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  participants who study in physiotherapy.

          -  willing to participate

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Individuals in years 4 were excluded.

          -  participants who received an in-depth session about pain previously.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>30 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Cihan AKSOY, Phd</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Kutahya Medical Sciences University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>KutahyaMSU</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kutahya</city>
        <state>Kutahya Health Sciences University</state>
        <zip>43000</zip>
        <country>Turkey</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Turkey</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 1, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 2, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 5, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 2, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 2, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 5, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Kutahya Medical Sciences University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Ismail Saracoglu</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>pain neuroscience education</keyword>
  <keyword>chronic pain</keyword>
  <keyword>physiotherapy students</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Chronic Pain</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

