<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04000165</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>190097</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>19-H-0097</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04000165</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Safety, Tolerability, Pharmacokinetics, and Pharmacodynamics of Escalating Multiple Oral Doses of AG-348 in Subjects With Stable Sickle Cell Disease</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Pilot Study to Evaluate the Safety, Tolerability, Pharmacokinetics, and Pharmacodynamics of Escalating Multiple Oral Doses of AG-348 in Subjects With Stable Sickle Cell Disease</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      Sickle Cell Disease (SCD) is an inherited blood disorder. People with SCD have abnormal
      hemoglobin in their red blood cells. Researchers are investigating the safety and efficacy of
      an investigational medicine called AG-348 (mitapivat sulfate) to determine if it will help
      people with SCD.

      Objective:

      To test the tolerability and safety of AG-348 in people with SCD.

      Eligibility:

      People ages 18 and older with SCD.

      Design:

      Participants will have 8 visits over approximately 14 weeks. At the first visit participants
      will be screened with a medical history; a physical exam; and blood, urine, and heart tests.
      At the following 5 visits participants will stay at the clinic for 1 night each. Participants
      will take study drug in increasing doses upto visit 6, after which the drug will be tapered
      off. All visits will include physical exam, blood, and urine tests. The last visit will occur
      4 weeks after stopping the drug and also includes a heart test. Participants will provide DNA
      from the blood samples they provide. The DNA will be tested for an inherited gene that can
      cause differences in response to the study drug. Researchers may also test other genes to see
      if they can find any genes that interact with SCD.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Sickle cell disease (SCD) is a multisystem disorder associated with episodes of acute
      clinical events and progressive organ damage. Episodic pain, triggered by micro-vasoocclusion
      induced by sickled red blood cells, is the most common acute complication and the leading
      cause of hospitalization. Management strategies for SCD have evolved very slowly, and
      treatment of acute pain is still limited to supportive therapy with opioid medication. Until
      recently in 2017, the only approved therapy for SCD was hydroxyurea (HU), indicated to reduce
      frequency of acute painful crises but not universally effective. In addition to HU,
      transfusions with normal red blood cells are widely used to treat severe sickle crises, but
      this strategy has limitations (not uniformly accessible, accompanied by risks of
      alloimmunization, hemolytic transfusion reactions and transfusional iron overload). The only
      curative treatment is bone marrow transplantation, but this option carries significant risks
      and is limited by the availability of histocompatible donors.

      As the root cause of SCD is polymerization of deoxy-HbS, there is a strong rationale for
      exploring agents that could inhibit/reduce the polymerization process itself. HbS polymerizes
      only when deoxygenated, its oxygenation is influenced by a few factors, one key factor being
      the 2,3- diphosphoglycerate (2,3-DPG) concentration in the red blood cell. Increased
      intracellular 2,3-DPG decreases oxygen binding and stabilizes the deoxygenated form (T form)
      of hemoglobin. In addition, increased 2,3-DPG concentration decreases intracellular red cell
      pH further promoting HbS polymerization. 2,3-DPG is an intermediate substrate in the
      glycolytic pathway, the only source of ATP production in red blood cells. Pyruvate kinase
      (PK) is a key enzyme in the final step of glycolysis; PK converts phosphoenolpyruvate to
      pyruvate, creating 50% of the total red cell ATP that is essential for maintaining integrity
      of the red cell membrane. Reduced PK activity leads to accumulation of the upstream enzyme
      substrates, including 2,3- DPG, that favours polymerization of deoxy-HbS. In humans with SCD,
      and even in sickle carriers who are generally asymptomatic, reduced oxygen affinity will
      favour deoxygenation of HbS and its polymerisation, and thus sickling. Indeed, the
      combination of PK deficiency and sickle cell trait causing an acute sickling syndrome has
      been previously reported in two cases.

      Current approaches to reduce HbS polymerization include fetal haemoglobin induction via
      multiple strategies and drugs that targets HbS polymerization through increasing affinity of
      hemoglobin for oxygen (eg. Oxbryta (TM) / Voxelotor / GBT440). Increasing red cell PK (PK-R)
      activity, leading to a decrease in intracellular 2,3-DPG concentration, presents a
      potentially attractive therapeutic target for thwarting HbS polymerization and acute sickle
      pain. AG-348 is a novel, orally bioavailable, small molecule allosteric activator of PK-R,
      that is currently in Phase II/III clinical trials in humans with PK deficiency (NCT02476916,
      NCT03548220 / AG348-C-006; NCT03559699 / AG348-C-007). Overview of the preclinical AG-348
      data and other data support dose-dependent changes in blood glycolytic intermediates
      consistent with glycolytic pathway activation at all multiple ascending doses tested,
      supporting the potential role of AG-348 in the treatment of sickle cell disease. The overall
      objective of the present study is to determine the clinical safety and tolerability of AG-348
      in subjects with SCD.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 11, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety and tolerability</measure>
    <time_frame>day 51</time_frame>
    <description>Frequency and severity of AEs, and changes in laboratory parameters, including levels in hemoglobin, reticulocyte counts, bilirubin and lactate dehydrogenase</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PK &amp;amp; PD</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 51</time_frame>
    <description>RBC 2,3-DPG activities from baseline, 2,3-DPG, ATP level sat different doses of AG-348 and change from baseline etc.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">25</enrollment>
  <condition>Sickle Cell Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>AG-348</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Single arm, intrapatient dose escalation Q 2 weeks</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>AG-348</intervention_name>
    <description>All subjects will receive an initial dose of 5 mg BID of AG-348 for 2 weeks followed by 2 dose increases, from 5 to 20 mg BID and from 20 to 50 mg BID, depending on safety and tolerability. Specifically, the treating clinician will assess the safety and tolerability of the current dose level before a decision is taken to escalate the dose to the next level.</description>
    <arm_group_label>AG-348</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITIERIA:

        For enrollment, subjects must meet all of the following criteria during the screening
        period:

          1. Have provided signed written informed consent prior to performing any study procedure,
             including screening procedures.

          2. Age between 18-70 years

        5.1.3 Unequivocal diagnosis of HbSS confirmed by hemoglobin electrophoresis performed on
        patients at least 90 days after a blood transfusion if previously transfused, or DNA
        genotyping within 30 days prior to study enrollment

        4 No transfusion in the 90 days prior to the first dose of study drug

        5 Have adequate organ function, as defined by:

          1. Serum aspartate aminotransferase (AST) less than or equal to 2.5 (SqrRoot) Upper Limit
             of Normal (ULN) (unless the increased AST is assessed by the Investigator as due to
             hemolysis and/or hepatic iron deposition) and alanine aminotransferase (ALT)

             less than or equal to 2.5 (SqrRoot) ULN (unless the increased ALT is assessed by the
             Investigator as due to hepatic iron deposition).

          2. Serum creatinine less than or equal to 1.25 (SqrRoot) ULN. If serum creatinine is
             &gt;1.25 (SqrRoot) ULN, then glomerular filtration rate (based on creatinine) must be
             greater than or equal to 60 mL/min.

          3. Absolute neutrophil count greater than or equal to 1.0 (SqrRoot) 109/L.

          4. Hemoglobin greater than or equal to 7 g/dL

          5. Platelet count greater than or equal to 100 (SqrRoot) 109/L.

          6. Activated partial thromboplastin time and international normalized ratio less than or
             equal to 1.5 (SqrRoot) ULN, unless the subject is receiving therapeutic
             anticoagulants.

             6 For women of reproductive potential, have a negative serum or urine pregnancy test
             during the screening period. Women of reproductive potential are defined as sexually
             mature women who have not undergone a hysterectomy, bilateral oophorectomy, or tubal
             occlusion; or who have not been naturally postmenopausal (i.e., who have not
             menstruated at all for at least the preceding 12 months prior to signing informed
             consent and have an elevated folliclestimulating hormone level indicative of menopause
             during the screening period).

             7 For women of reproductive potential as well as men and their partners who are women
             of reproductive potential, be abstinent as part of their usual lifestyle, or agree to
             use 2 effective forms of contraception from the time of giving informed consent,
             during the study, and for 28 days (both men and women) following the last dose of
             study treatment. An effective form of contraception is defined as

        hormonal oral contraceptives, injectables, patches, and barrier methods.

        8 Be willing to comply with all study procedures for the duration of the study.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

        Subjects who meet any of the following criteria during screening will not receive AG348 and
        will not be counted toward the final enrollment count for statistical purposes:

          1. Documented pyruvate kinase deficiency

          2. Have a significant medical condition that confers an unacceptable risk to
             participating in the study, and/or that could confound the interpretation of the study
             data. Such significant medical conditions include, but are not limited to the
             following:

               1. Poorly controlled hypertension (defined as systolic blood pressure [BP] &gt;150 mmHg
                  or diastolic BP &gt;90 mmHg) refractory to medical

                  management.

               2. History of recent (within 6 months prior to signing informed consent) congestive
                  heart failure; myocardial infarction or unstable angina pectoris; hemorrhagic,
                  embolic, or thrombotic stroke; deep venous thrombosis; or pulmonary or arterial
                  embolism.

               3. Cardiac dysrhythmias judged as clinically significant by the Investigator.

               4. Heart-rate corrected QT interval-Fredericia's method (QTcF) &gt;480 msec with the
                  exception of subjects with right or left bundle branch block.

               5. Clinically symptomatic cholelithiasis or cholecystitis. Prior cholecystectomy is
                  not exclusionary. Subjects with symptomatic

                  cholelithiasis or cholecystitis may be rescreened once the disorder has been
                  treated and clinical symptoms have resolved.

               6. History of drug-induced cholestatic hepatitis.

               7. Iron overload sufficiently severe to result in a clinical diagnosis by the
                  Investigator of cardiac (e.g., clinically significant impaired left ventricular
                  ejection fraction), hepatic (e.g., fibrosis, cirrhosis), or pancreatic (e.g.,
                  diabetes) dysfunction.

               8. Have a diagnosis of any other congenital or acquired blood disorder, or any other
                  hemolytic process as defined by a positive direct antiglobulin test (DAT), except
                  mild allo-immunization as a consequence of transfusion therapy.

               9. Positive test for hepatitis B surface antigen or hepatitis C virus (HCV) antibody
                  (Ab) with signs of active hepatitis B or C virus infection. If the subject is
                  positive for HCV Ab, a reverse transcriptase-polymerase chain reaction test will
                  be conducted. Subjects with hepatitis C may be rescreened after receiving
                  appropriate hepatitis C treatment.

              10. Positive test for human immunodeficiency virus 1 or 2 Ab.

              11. Active infection requiring any use of systemic antimicrobial agents (parenteral
                  or oral) or Grade greater than or equal to 3 in severity (per National Cancer
                  Institute Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events) within 2 months prior
                  to signing informed consent.

              12. Diabetes mellitus judged to be under poor control by the Investigator or
                  requiring &gt;3 antidiabetic agents, including insulin (all insulins are considered
                  1 agent); use of insulin per se is not exclusionary.

              13. History of any primary malignancy, with the exception of: curatively treated
                  nonmelanomatous skin cancer; curatively treated cervical or breast carcinoma in
                  situ; or other primary tumor treated with curative intent, no known active
                  disease present, and no treatment administered during the last 3 years.

              14. Unstable extramedullary hematopoiesis that could pose a risk of imminent
                  neurologic compromise.

              15. Current or recent history of psychiatric disorder that, in the opinion of the
                  Investigator or Medical Monitor, could compromise the ability of the subject to
                  cooperate with study visits and procedures.

              16. Are currently enrolled in another therapeutic clinical trial involving ongoing
                  therapy with any investigational or marketed product or placebo. Sickle cell
                  anemia subjects on hydroxyurea or L-glutamine will also be considered, provided
                  that they have been on an unchanged dose of hydroxyurea or L-Glutamine for three
                  months prior to enrollment.

              17. Have exposure to any investigational drug, device, or invasive procedure within 3
                  months prior to the first dose of study treatment. All noninvestigational
                  invasive procedures within 3 months of starting study treatment may be considered
                  as a potential exclusion criteria per the PI s discretion.

              18. Have had any prior treatment with a pyruvate kinase activator.

              19. Have a prior bone marrow or stem cell transplant.

              20. Are currently pregnant or breastfeeding.

              21. Are currently receiving medications that are strong inhibitors of cytochrome P450
                  (CYP)3A4, strong inducers of CYP3A4, strong inhibitors of P-glycoprotein (P-gp),
                  or digoxin (a P-gp sensitive substrate medication) that have not been stopped for
                  a duration of at least 5 days or a timeframe equivalent to 5 half-lives
                  (whichever is longer) prior to the first dose of AG-348.

              22. Are currently receiving hematopoietic stimulating agents (e.g., erythropoietins,
                  granulocyte colony stimulating factors, thrombopoietins) that have not been
                  stopped for a duration of at least 28 days prior to the first dose of study
                  treatment.

              23. Have a history of allergy to sulfonamides if characterized by acute hemolytic
                  anemia, drug-induced liver injury, anaphylaxis, rash of erythema multiforme type
                  or Stevens-Johnson syndrome, cholestatic hepatitis, or other serious clinical
                  manifestations.

              24. Have a history of allergy to AG-348 or its excipients (microcrystalline
                  cellulose, croscarmellose sodium, sodium stearyl fumarate, and mannitol).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Swee Lay Thein, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Ingrid C Frey</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 402-6674</phone>
    <email>freyic@nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>For more information at the NIH Clinical Center contact Office of Patient Recruitment (OPR)</last_name>
      <phone>800-411-1222</phone>
      <phone_ext>TTY8664111010</phone_ext>
      <email>prpl@cc.nih.gov</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?A_2019-H-0097.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>April 29, 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 22, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 26, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 27, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 30, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 30, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 1, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>HbS polymerization</keyword>
  <keyword>pyruvate kinase</keyword>
  <keyword>2,3- diphosphoglycerate</keyword>
  <keyword>ATP in red blood cells</keyword>
  <keyword>acute sickle pain</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Anemia, Sickle Cell</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

