<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04000256</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>19G.279</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04000256</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Understanding Experiences of People With Spinal Cord Injury Undergoing Activity-based Rehabilitation</brief_title>
  <official_title>Understanding Experiences of People With Spinal Cord Injury Undergoing Activity-based Rehabilitation</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Thomas Jefferson University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute on Disability, Independent Living, and Rehabilitation Research</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Thomas Jefferson University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Incomplete cervical spinal cord injury (SCI) makes up half of all the newly admitted
      patients. For these individuals, the use of their upper limbs is critical for managing daily
      activities and self-care and impacts their quality of life. For home-based monitored
      rehabilitation, also called telerehabilitation, there are various rehabilitation equipment
      that are used. No studies have systematically gathered information regarding the perceptions
      of individuals with SCI regarding these equipment, training, and feasibility within the home.
      Further, their perceptions of the usability of high vs low end equipment is also not
      explored. In this study, investigators plan to gather survey and interview data from
      individuals with SCI regarding their experience with using rehabilitation equipment that uses
      games, muscle stimulation, and object manipulation. This study will inform the development of
      a tele-rehabilitation intervention in the future.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Incomplete cervical spinal cord injury (SCI) makes up half of all the newly admitted
      patients. The overall prognosis for walking is better than the upper limb recovery in
      incomplete tetraplegia. Upper limb deficits result in difficulty in managing daily activities
      and self-care and impacts quality of life. Rehabilitation of the upper limb involves high
      intensity repetitive activities that are directed to a specific task. The demands of these
      programs can be up to 5 hours of therapy, 5 days a week for 12 weeks. Home-based therapies
      augmented by tele-rehabilitation presents a more realistic alternative to clinic-based
      application of these programs due to transportation and time commitment. However, engaging
      and motivating therapy options are needed for home to enhance client outcomes and improve
      compliance. Some of the latest equipment provides this capability and engages the patient
      using games for training. However, high equipment cost limits its widespread use.

      In this study, we will engage individuals with cervical SCI in a 4-week (8 visit) evaluation
      of a variety of training protocols to gather information on their perceptions regarding
      motivation, engagement, and challenge it offers; its ability to address limitations they
      experience; and its feasibility within the home.

      The long-term goal of this National Institute of Disability Independent Living and
      Rehabilitation (NIDILRR) funded Spinal Cord Injury Model System (SCIMS) project is to develop
      an engaging and evidence-informed intervention for home-based upper limb activity-based
      rehabilitation in individuals with spinal cord injury (SCI). A review of literature was
      recently conducted by the research team to get a scope of the evidence related to current
      activity-based therapies and the equipment used to deliver these programs. There is
      insufficient information about the value of high-end equipment involving games relative to
      lower cost alternatives, or the perceptions of clients regarding the use of various
      technologies related to motivation, engagement, appropriate level of difficulty and
      feasibility within the home. This lab-based study aims to understand the experiences related
      to rehabilitation training and high and low end equipment for upper limb activity-based
      rehabilitation in individuals with spinal cord injury.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 15, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 15, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>10-item questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 4</time_frame>
    <description>Quantitative feedback using a 10-question survey regarding experiences with the rehabilitation training and equipment for feasibility, motivation, engagement and difficulty.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Qualitative interview</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 4</time_frame>
    <description>Interview to explore further the experiences with rehabilitation training and equipment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Qualitative interview</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 2</time_frame>
    <description>Interview to explore further the experiences with rehabilitation training and equipment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>10-item questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 2</time_frame>
    <description>Quantitative feedback using a 10-question survey regarding experiences with the rehabilitation training and equipment for feasibility, motivation, engagement and difficulty.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Spinal Cord Injuries</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Spinal Cord Injury</arm_group_label>
    <description>The data during the first visit involves questionnaires, performance and observational measures for baseline evaluation. The 2nd to 8th visit involves feedback survey and interview data collection based on experiences of participants undergoing activity-based training using upper extremity rehabilitation equipment.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Activity based rehabilitation</intervention_name>
    <description>Activity based rehabilitation for the upper extremity involves various gross and fine movements, reach and object transportation, and object manipulation. The rehabilitation equipment used during training will include gaming and instrumented training equipment, conventional table-top tasks, and exercise aids.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Spinal Cord Injury</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Adults 18 years or older with chronic stable cervical spinal cord injury affecting one or
        both arms
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Motor incomplete cervical SCI, neurologic levels C1-C7

          2. Atleast one arm with active shoulder flexion (reach with gravity eliminated) and
             atleast one grasp pattern/able to move fingers

          3. At least 6 months post injury

          4. At least one arm with greater than 50% normal passive range of motion in all upper
             limb joints, excluding the interphalangeal joints of the fingers

          5. Medically stable with no contraindications to the activities or to sitting

          6. 18 years of age or older

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Uncontrolled pain in the upper limbs

          2. Upper extremity amputations

          3. Unable to commit to at least 3 visits

          4. Surgical procedures (e.g., tendon transfers) or orthopedic trauma (e.g., fracture)
             within the past 3 months

          5. Other neurological conditions

          6. Mechanical Ventilation
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ralph Marino, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Thomas Jefferson University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Namrata Grampurohit, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>2063536054</phone>
    <email>namrata.grampurohit@jefferson.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Ralph Marino, MD</last_name>
    <phone>215 955-5756</phone>
    <email>ralph.marino@jefferson.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Chapman University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Orange</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>92866</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Susan Duff, EdD</last_name>
      <phone>714-997-6794</phone>
      <email>duff@chapman.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Thomas Jefferson University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19107</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Namrata Grampurohit, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>206-353-6054</phone>
      <email>namrata.grampurohit@jefferson.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ralph Marino, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Szturm T, Peters JF, Otto C, Kapadia N, Desai A. Task-specific rehabilitation of finger-hand function using interactive computer gaming. Arch Phys Med Rehabil. 2008 Nov;89(11):2213-7. doi: 10.1016/j.apmr.2008.04.021.</citation>
    <PMID>18996252</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gauthier LV, Kane C, Borstad A, Strahl N, Uswatte G, Taub E, Morris D, Hall A, Arakelian M, Mark V. Video Game Rehabilitation for Outpatient Stroke (VIGoROUS): protocol for a multi-center comparative effectiveness trial of in-home gamified constraint-induced movement therapy for rehabilitation of chronic upper extremity hemiparesis. BMC Neurol. 2017 Jun 8;17(1):109. doi: 10.1186/s12883-017-0888-0.</citation>
    <PMID>28595611</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Thielen CC, Marino RJ, Duff S, Kaplan G, Mulcahey MJ. Activity-based Rehabilitation Interventions of the Neurologically Impaired Upper Extremity: Description of a Scoping Review Protocol. Top Spinal Cord Inj Rehabil. 2018 Summer;24(3):288-294. doi: 10.1310/sci2403-288. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>29997431</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 17, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 25, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 27, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 25, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 25, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 27, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Spinal cord injuries</keyword>
  <keyword>Telerehabilitation</keyword>
  <keyword>Qualitative</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Spinal Cord Injuries</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Wounds and Injuries</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Participant data from both sites will be pooled for analysis and reporting of results</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Statistical Analysis Plan (SAP)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Clinical Study Report (CSR)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>1 year</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>De-identified data only</ipd_access_criteria>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

