<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03902028</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>RECHMPL18_0040</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03902028</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Optimized Medico-pharmaceutical Collaboration in the Drug Management of Patients With Heart Failure</brief_title>
  <acronym>COMPIC</acronym>
  <official_title>Interest of an Optimized Medico-pharmaceutical Collaboration in the Drug Management of Patients With Heart Failure: Controlled, Randomized, Multicentric Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University Hospital, Montpellier</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University Hospital, Montpellier</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a controlled, randomized, open-label, multicentric study evaluating the value of
      coordinated medico-pharmaceutical management compared to standard management in patients with
      heart failure. The aim of this study is to evaluate the impact of these optimized activities
      on the re-hospitalization of the patient with cardiac insufficiency for a disease-related
      event within three months of the initial hospitalization.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Heart failure (FH) is a public health problem with an estimated prevalence of about 1.5% in
      developed countries. In 2013, the number of patients hospitalized in France for heart failure
      amounted to 165 231 and 20% of them were re-hospitalized at least once for the same reason
      during this year. Several factors contribute to the occurrence of cardiac decompensation (DC)
      : some modifiable (age, severity of IC, etiology ...) and others modifiable, such as
      therapeutics. Various elements could reduce the frequency of re-hospitalizations and the
      mortality due to this disease :

        -  a better knowledge of treatments by patients and consequently a better therapeutic
           compliance

        -  a better knowledge of the factors and signs of DC (low-sodium diet, weighing...)

        -  a better implementation of prescribing recommendations : less than 50% of patients have
           optimal treatment compared to ESC recommendations

        -  a better communication at the transition points of the patient pathway. The creation of
           a binomial cardiologist-clinical pharmacist during hospitalization and the maintenance
           of this optimized multidisciplinary follow-up within 3 months post-hospitalization is a
           proposal to intervene on these factors. Indeed, the clinical pharmacist (present in the
           care unit) works in collaboration with the medical and paramedical teams and can improve
           the care of patients. In the experimental group, a specific multidisciplinary
           consultation is planned for one month after the end of the hospitalization. A 3-month
           follow-up visit will be carried out by phone call to meet the criteria for readmission,
           mortality, quality of life, adherence and persistence of treatments.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">August 2, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Rehospitalisation for heart failure</measure>
    <time_frame>Call at 3 months after hospitalisation discharge</time_frame>
    <description>At least one rehospitalisation with heart failure related cause</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Prescriptions conformity rates compared to heart failure recommendations edited by the European Society of Cardiology in 2016</measure>
    <time_frame>At hospitalisation discharge (Day 0)</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluated by a pharmacist</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Prescriptions conformity rates compared to heart failure recommendations edited by the European Society of Cardiology in 2016</measure>
    <time_frame>Call at 3 months after hospitalisation discharge</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluated by a pharmacist</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Compliance level</measure>
    <time_frame>At hospitalisation discharge (Day 0)</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluated by the &quot; Girerd medication adherence questionnaire &quot;
The &quot; Girerd medication adherence questionnaire &quot; contains 6 questions which answers are &quot; yes &quot; or &quot; no &quot;. The number of &quot; yes &quot; responses permits to evaluate the level of the patient medication adherence as following :
0 yes : good compliance
1 or 2 yes : minor non compliance 3 or more yes : non compliance</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Compliance level</measure>
    <time_frame>At 1 month after hospitalisation discharge for the experimental group only</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluated by the &quot;Girerd medication adherence questionnaire&quot; Evaluated by the &quot; Girerd medication adherence questionnaire &quot;
The &quot; Girerd medication adherence questionnaire &quot; contains 6 questions which answers are &quot; yes &quot; or &quot; no &quot;. The number of &quot; yes &quot; responses permits to evaluate the level of the patient medication adherence as following :
0 yes : good compliance
1 or 2 yes : minor non compliance 3 or more yes : non compliance</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Compliance level</measure>
    <time_frame>Call at 3 months after hospitalisation discharge</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluated by the &quot;Girerd medication adherence questionnaire&quot; Evaluated by the &quot; Girerd medication adherence questionnaire &quot;
The &quot; Girerd medication adherence questionnaire &quot; contains 6 questions which answers are &quot; yes &quot; or &quot; no &quot;. The number of &quot; yes &quot; responses permits to evaluate the level of the patient medication adherence as following :
0 yes : good compliance
1 or 2 yes : minor non compliance 3 or more yes : non compliance</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Treatment persistence rates</measure>
    <time_frame>Call at 3 months after hospitalisation discharge</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluated by a pharmacist</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Death rate</measure>
    <time_frame>Call at 3 months after hospitalisation discharge</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluated by a pharmacist</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time before death</measure>
    <time_frame>Call at 3 months after hospitalisation discharge</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluated by a pharmacist</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time of occurrence of a potential rehospitalisation related to the disease</measure>
    <time_frame>Call at 3 months after hospitalisation discharge</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluated by a pharmacist</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of life score</measure>
    <time_frame>Call at 3 months after hospitalisation discharge</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluated by the Minnesota Living with Heart Failure Questionnaire the Minnesota Living with Heart Failure Questionnaire contains 21 questions. Each of the 21 questions ask the patients to indicate how much a possible effect of heart failure have affected their ability to live as wanted during the past month using a scale from 0 (not present or no effect), 1 (very little), 2, 3, 4, or 5 (very much).The measurement of heart failure severity is assessed by summing the responses that ranges from 0 to 105.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Satisfaction of the patient</measure>
    <time_frame>Call at 3 months after hospitalisation discharge</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluated by Likert scale This questionnaire indicates the degree of patient satisfaction using 9 questions which explore the improvement of patient behavior concerning disease and treatment. The measurement of satisfaction is assessed by summing the responses that range from 9 (unsatisfied) to 36 (very satisfied)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Satisfaction of health professionals</measure>
    <time_frame>online questionnaire at 3 months after hospitalisation discharge</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluated by Likert scale (only for interventional arm) This questionnaire indicates the degree of health professional satisfaction using 6 questions which explore the improvement of transition between hospital to community and comprehension of therapeutic optimization. The measurement of satisfaction is assessed by summing the responses that range from 6 (unsatisfied) to 24 (very satisfied)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incremental cost-effectiveness ratio</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months after hospitalisation discharge</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">248</enrollment>
  <condition>Heart Failure</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Reinforced multidisciplinary follow-up</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Entrance medication reconciliation performed by a pharmacist
Patient compliance evaluation
Patient quality of life evaluation
Pharmaceutical analysis with focus on medication optimization with a specific check-list (according to ESC 2016 recommendations)
Hospitalisation discharge medication reconciliation
Patient pharmaceutic interview at the hospitalisation discharge
Transmission of informations to the general practitioner and the pharmacist's patient
Multidisciplinary consult at 1 month after hospitalisation discharge</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Standard care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Drug review by a paramedic or a pharmacist
Pharmaceutical analysis
Therapeutic optimisation based on the usual practices care of the cardiologic department
Writing of the prescription given on leaving hospital based on the usual care of the department
Treatments explanations and support to the patient on the usual care
Transmission of the hospitalisation report to the patient general practitioner as the usual practice
Medical consult in usual time frames (an average of 1 month after hospitalisation discharge) at the patient location of choice</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Reinforced multidisciplinary follow-up</intervention_name>
    <description>Reinforced multidisciplinary follow-up</description>
    <arm_group_label>Reinforced multidisciplinary follow-up</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patient aged more than 18 years

          -  Adult patient admitted in cardiology department (full hospitalisation or intensive
             care) for heart failure no matter the type and the stage of the disease

          -  Person affiliated or beneficiary of a social security system

          -  Collection of a free, informed, express and written consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Non autonomous drug management patients and not disposing

          -  a present caregiver during hospitalisation

          -  Patients living in an institution

          -  Person participating in another clinical trial with an exclusion period still ongoing

          -  Person whose physical and/or psychological health is severely altered, and which, in
             the opinion of the investigator, may affect the participation's to the study

          -  Person deprived of his rights, person under tutorship or guardianship

          -  Refusal to sign the consent
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Audrey CASTET-NICOLAS, MCU-PH, Pharm D, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>(0)467338564</phone>
    <phone_ext>+33</phone_ext>
    <email>audrey-castet@chu-montpellier.fr</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Nicolas CHAPET, Pharm D, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>(0)467338562</phone>
    <email>n-chapet@chu-montpellier.fr</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Hospital of Montpellier Cardiology departments oh the Montpellier, Nîmes and Toulouse University Hospitals</name>
      <address>
        <city>Montpellier</city>
        <state>Occitanie</state>
        <zip>34295</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Audrey CASTET-NICOLAS, MCU-PH, Pharm D, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>(0)467338564</phone>
      <email>audrey-castet@chu-montpellier.fr</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Nicolas CHAPET, Pharm D</last_name>
      <phone>(0)467338562</phone>
      <email>n-chapet@chu-montpellier.fr</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Jackevicius CA, de Leon NK, Lu L, Chang DS, Warner AL, Mody FV. Impact of a Multidisciplinary Heart Failure Post-hospitalization Program on Heart Failure Readmission Rates. Ann Pharmacother. 2015 Nov;49(11):1189-96. doi: 10.1177/1060028015599637. Epub 2015 Aug 10.</citation>
    <PMID>26259774</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Ponikowski P, Voors AA, Anker SD, Bueno H, Cleland JGF, Coats AJS, Falk V, González-Juanatey JR, Harjola VP, Jankowska EA, Jessup M, Linde C, Nihoyannopoulos P, Parissis JT, Pieske B, Riley JP, Rosano GMC, Ruilope LM, Ruschitzka F, Rutten FH, van der Meer P; ESC Scientific Document Group. 2016 ESC Guidelines for the diagnosis and treatment of acute and chronic heart failure: The Task Force for the diagnosis and treatment of acute and chronic heart failure of the European Society of Cardiology (ESC)Developed with the special contribution of the Heart Failure Association (HFA) of the ESC. Eur Heart J. 2016 Jul 14;37(27):2129-2200. doi: 10.1093/eurheartj/ehw128. Epub 2016 May 20. Erratum in: Eur Heart J. 2016 Dec 30;:.</citation>
    <PMID>27206819</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Available at: https://academic.oup.com/eurheartj/article/37/27/2129/1748921/2016-ESC-Guidelines-for-the-diagnosis-and. (Accessed: 12th September 2017).</citation>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Masters J, Morton G, Anton I, Szymanski J, Greenwood E, Grogono J, Flett AS, Cleland JG, Cowburn PJ. Specialist intervention is associated with improved patient outcomes in patients with decompensated heart failure: evaluation of the impact of a multidisciplinary inpatient heart failure team. Open Heart. 2017 Mar 8;4(1):e000547. doi: 10.1136/openhrt-2016-000547. eCollection 2017.</citation>
    <PMID>28409010</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Van Spall HGC, Rahman T, Mytton O, Ramasundarahettige C, Ibrahim Q, Kabali C, Coppens M, Brian Haynes R, Connolly S. Comparative effectiveness of transitional care services in patients discharged from the hospital with heart failure: a systematic review and network meta-analysis. Eur J Heart Fail. 2017 Nov;19(11):1427-1443. doi: 10.1002/ejhf.765. Epub 2017 Feb 24. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>28233442</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>López Cabezas C, Falces Salvador C, Cubí Quadrada D, Arnau Bartés A, Ylla Boré M, Muro Perea N, Homs Peipoch E. Randomized clinical trial of a postdischarge pharmaceutical care program vs regular follow-up in patients with heart failure. Farm Hosp. 2006 Nov-Dec;30(6):328-42. English, Spanish.</citation>
    <PMID>17298190</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Parajuli DR, Franzon J, McKinnon RA, Shakib S, Clark RA. Role of the Pharmacist for Improving Self-care and Outcomes in Heart Failure. Curr Heart Fail Rep. 2017 Apr;14(2):78-86. doi: 10.1007/s11897-017-0323-2. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>28233258</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Wan TTH, Terry A, Cobb E, McKee B, Tregerman R, Barbaro SDS. Strategies to Modify the Risk of Heart Failure Readmission: A Systematic Review and Meta-Analysis. Health Serv Res Manag Epidemiol. 2017 Apr 18;4:2333392817701050. doi: 10.1177/2333392817701050. eCollection 2017 Jan-Dec. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>28462286</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Buckley MS, Harinstein LM, Clark KB, Smithburger PL, Eckhardt DJ, Alexander E, Devabhakthuni S, Westley CA, David B, Kane-Gill SL. Impact of a clinical pharmacy admission medication reconciliation program on medication errors in &quot;high-risk&quot; patients. Ann Pharmacother. 2013 Dec;47(12):1599-610. doi: 10.1177/1060028013507428. Epub 2013 Oct 15.</citation>
    <PMID>24259613</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Warden BA, Freels JP, Furuno JP, Mackay J. Pharmacy-managed program for providing education and discharge instructions for patients with heart failure. Am J Health Syst Pharm. 2014 Jan 15;71(2):134-9. doi: 10.2146/ajhp130103.</citation>
    <PMID>24375606</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 27, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 1, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 3, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 30, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 30, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 31, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Heart failure</keyword>
  <keyword>pharmacist</keyword>
  <keyword>multidisciplinary team</keyword>
  <keyword>readmission</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Heart Failure</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

