<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03903796</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HS-10234-301</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03903796</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study of the Efficacy and Safety of HS-10234 in Patients With Chronic Hepatitis B Virus Infection</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase 3, Randomized, Multicenter, Double-blind, Double-dummy, Parallel-controlled Study to Evaluate the Safety and Efficacy of HS-10234 25 mg QD Versus TDF 300 mg QD for the Treatment of Patients With HBeAg+/- Chronic HBV Infection.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Jiangsu Hansoh Pharmaceutical Co., Ltd.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Jiangsu Hansoh Pharmaceutical Co., Ltd.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The primary objective of this study is to compare the safety and efficacy of HS-10234 versus
      tenofovir disoproxil fumarate (TDF) in treatment-naive and treatment-experienced adults with
      chronic hepatitis B virus (HBV) infection.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a phase 3, randomized, multicenter, double-blind, double-dummy, parallel-controlled,
      non-inferiority trial to evaluate the safety and efficacy of HS-10234 25 mg qd versus TDF 300
      mg qd. Patients with chronic HBV infection who are positive or negative for the hepatitis B e
      antigen (HBeAg) will be randomly assigned (2:1) to receive either 25 mg HS-10234 or 300 mg
      TDF with matching placebo. Randomization will be done by a computer-generated allocation
      sequence stratified by plasma HBV DNA concentration (HBV DNA&lt; 8 log10IU/mL；HBV DNA ≥8
      log10IU/mL) and previous treatment experience (treatment-naive and treatment-experienced).
      All patients will receive 144 weeks of antiviral therapy. After 96 weeks of double-blind
      treatment, all subjects will be eligible to receive open-label HS-10234 until 144 weeks.

      The primary efficacy endpoint is the proportion of patients with HBV DNA less than 20 IU/mL
      at week 48 in all patients who are randomly assigned and received at least one dose of study
      drug using a missing-equals-failed approach. Key pre-specified safety endpoints are bone and
      renal parameters at week 48. Other pre-specified endpoints include viral suppression,
      serologic response, normalization of alanine aminotransferase (ALT) levels and the emergence
      of resistance mutations at week 48, 96 and 144.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">August 16, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 31, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 31, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluation the percentage of Participants with Hepatitis B Virus (HBV) DNA &lt; 20 IU/mL</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 48</time_frame>
    <description>The primary efficacy endpoint was the proportion of patients with HBV DNA &lt; 20 IU/mL at week 48 in all patients who are randomly assigned and received HS-10234 25 mg or TDF 300 mg. The safety and tolerance were also observed in two treatment groups.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluation the percent Change from Baseline in Hip BMD</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 48</time_frame>
    <description>Percent Change from Baseline in Hip Bone Mineral Density (BMD) at Week 48</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluation the percent Change from Baseline in Spine BMD</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 48</time_frame>
    <description>Percent Change from Baseline in Spine BMD at Week 48</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluation the change from Baseline in Serum Creatinine</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 48</time_frame>
    <description>Change from Baseline in Serum Creatinine at Week 48</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluation the proportion of Patients Achieving Hepatitis B Surface Antigen (HBsAg) Loss</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 48, 96 and 144</time_frame>
    <description>Proportion of Patients Achieving Hepatitis B Surface Antigen (HBsAg) Loss at Weeks 48, 96, 144</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluation the proportion of Patients Achieving HBsAg Seroconversion</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 48, 96 and 144</time_frame>
    <description>Proportion of Patients Achieving HBsAg Seroconversion at Weeks 48, 96, 144</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluation the proportion of patients achieving HBeAg loss</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 48, 96 and 144</time_frame>
    <description>Proportion of patients achieving HBeAg loss at weeks 48, 96, 144</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluation the proportion of patients achieving HBeAg seroconversion</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 48, 96 and 144</time_frame>
    <description>Proportion of patients achieving HBeAg seroconversion at weeks 48, 96, 144</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">963</enrollment>
  <condition>Chronic HBV Infection</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>HS-10234 25mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>HS-10234 + TDF placebo for up to 96 weeks</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>TDF 300mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>TDF + HS-10234 placebo for up to 96 weeks</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Open-label HS-10234</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>All participants who complete the double-blind period (96 weeks) will be eligible to receive open-label HS-10234 until week 144 of the study.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>HS-10234</intervention_name>
    <description>Drug: HS-10234 HS-10234 25mg will administer orally once daily Drug: TDF placebo TDF placebo 300mg will administer orally once daily</description>
    <arm_group_label>HS-10234 25mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Open-label HS-10234</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>TDF 300mg</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>TDF</intervention_name>
    <description>Drug: TDF TDF 300mg will administer orally once daily Drug: HS-10234 placebo HS-10234 placebo 25mg will administer orally once daily</description>
    <arm_group_label>HS-10234 25mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>TDF 300mg</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects must meet all of the following inclusion criteria to be eligible for
             participation in this study:

               1. Must have the ability to understand and sign a written informed consent form,
                  which must be obtained prior to initiation of study screening.

               2. Male and non-pregnant, non-lactating females, from 18 up to 65 years of age
                  (based on the date of the screening visit). A negative serum pregnancy test at
                  screening is required for female subjects of childbearing potential.

               3. Documented evidence of chronic HBV infection (e.g. HBsAg positive for more than 6
                  months).

               4. HBeAg-positive or HBeAg-negative chronic hepatitis B with all of the following:
                  HBV DNA ≥ 2 x 104 IU/mL; Screening serum 1 ULN &lt; ALT level ≤ 10 ULN.

               5. Treatment-naive subjects (defined as &lt; 12 weeks of oral antiviral treatment with
                  any nucleoside or nucleotide analogue) OR treatment-experienced subjects (defined
                  as subjects meeting all entry criteria [including HBV DNA and serum ALT criteria]
                  and with ≥ 12 weeks of previous treatment with any nucleoside or nucleotide
                  analogue) will be eligible for enrollment. Treatment-experienced subjects
                  receiving oral antiviral treatment at Screening must continue their treatment
                  regimen until the time of randomization, when it will be discontinued.

               6. Any previous treatment with interferon (pegylated or non-pegylated) must have
                  ended at least 6 months prior to the baseline visit.

               7. Estimated creatinine clearance (CLcr) ≥ 50 mL/min（using the Cockcroft-Gault
                  method）based on serum creatinine and actual body weight as measured at the
                  screening evaluation, as follows:

             （140－age in years）(body weight [kg]) (72)(serum creatinine [mg/dL]） 8) Normal ECG (or
             if abnormal, determined by the Investigator not to be clinically significant).

             9) Must be willing and able to comply with all study requirements.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects who meet any of the following exclusion criteria are not to be enrolled in
             this study:

               1. Pregnant women, women who are breastfeeding or who believe they may wish to
                  become pregnant during the course of the study.

               2. Males and females of reproductive potential who are unwilling to use an
                  &quot;effective&quot;, protocol specified method(s) of contraception during the study.

               3. Co-infection with HCV virus, HIV, or HDV.

               4. Evidence of hepatocellular carcinoma (e.g. as evidenced by recent imaging).

               5. Any history of, or current evidence of, clinical hepatic decompensation (e.g.
                  ascites encephalopathy or variceal hemorrhage).

               6. Abnormal hematological and biochemical parameters, including:

                    -  Hemoglobin &lt; 10 g/dl

                    -  Absolute neutrophil count &lt; 0.75 × 109/L

                    -  Platelets ≤ 50 × 109/L

                    -  AST or ALT &gt; 10 × ULN

                    -  Total Bilirubin &gt; 2.5 × ULN

                    -  Albumin &lt; 3.0 g/dL

                    -  INR &gt; 1.5 × ULN (unless stable on anticoagulant regimen)

               7. Received solid organ or bone marrow transplant.

               8. Significant renal, cardiovascular, pulmonary, or neurological disease in the
                  opinion of the investigator.

               9. Significant bone disease (e.g. osteomalacia, chronic osteomyelitis, osteogenesis
                  imperfecta, osteochrondroses), or multiple bone fractures.

              10. Malignancy within the 5 years prior to screening, with the exception of specific
                  cancers that are cured by surgical resection (basal cell skin cancer, etc).

              11. Currently receiving therapy with immunomodulators (e.g. corticosteroids),
                  investigational agents, nephrotoxic agents, or agents capable of modifying renal
                  excretion.

              12. Known hypersensitivity to study drugs, metabolites, or formulation excipients.

              13. Current alcohol or substance abuse judged by the investigator to potentially
                  interfere with participant compliance.

              14. Any other clinical condition or prior therapy that, in the opinion of the
                  Investigator, would make the subject unsuitable for the study or unable to comply
                  with dosing requirements.

              15. Subjects on prohibited concomitant medications. Subjects on prohibited
                  medications, otherwise eligible, will need a wash out period of at least 30 days.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Guo Xiaolin, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>The First Hospital of Jilin University, Jilin Province</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Hou Jinlin, MD</last_name>
    <phone>0086-20-61641941</phone>
    <email>jlhousmu@163.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The First Hospital of Jilin University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Changchun</city>
        <state>Jilin</state>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Guo Xiaolin</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>August 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 3, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 3, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 4, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 3, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 3, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 4, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>HBeAg-positive or negative</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Infection</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Communicable Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

