<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03908346</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>19-0795</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>K23HL138164</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03908346</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Novel Patient Decision Aid for Surrogate Decision Makers of Comatose Survivors of Cardiac Arrest</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Novel Patient Decision Aid for Surrogate Decision Makers of Comatose Survivors of Cardiac Arrest: A Pilot Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Colorado, Denver</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Colorado, Denver</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will test the feasibility and acceptability of deploying a decision aid for
      surrogate decision makers of comatose survivors of cardiac arrest early during
      hospitalization. This decision aid is to inform, educate and support decision makers charged
      with determining goals of care during post-cardiac arrest treatment.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Survival and neurological recovery after out-of-hospital cardiac arrest are highly variable,
      driven in part by inconsistent hospital care following successful resuscitation.
      International guidelines for post-cardiac arrest care recommend delaying neurologic
      prognostication until 72-hours after resuscitation because early prognostication is imprecise
      and may precipitate inappropriate withdrawal of life sustaining therapy (WLST). Early WLST
      has been observed in-post cardiac arrest care. In order to encourage better guideline
      concordant care, the study proposes the implementation of an educational tool to support and
      inform surrogate decision makers in post-cardiac arrest care and neuro-prognostication. This
      pilot study will test the feasibility of implementing an educational tool for surrogate
      decision makers, the acceptability of such an intervention and early measures of knowledge
      translation. This study will inform the creation of a randomized controlled trial to test the
      ability of the tool to encourage guideline concordant timing of post-cardiac arrest
      neuro-prognostication.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 21, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 1, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 1, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Reach</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion, on average 1.5 years</time_frame>
    <description>To establish Reach, the investigators will determine the following: (1) number of out-of hospital cardiac arrests that present to the UCH ED; (2) number of OHCA patients with family/surrogate decision makers in the ED; (3) number of surrogate decision makers who agree to participate. Establishing reach is integral as it will allow us to determine the feasibility of intervening in the ED and will characterize the difficulties enrolling decision makers. The research assistant will keep a running tabulation of these data.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Effectiveness - Knowledge</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion, on average 1.5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Determine the number of individuals who reviewed the educational tool and completed the follow up knowledge evaluation. The pre-knowledge and post-knowledge/acceptability surveys will establish how effective the tool was at relaying information to the surrogate decision maker.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Adoption</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion, on average 1.5 years</time_frame>
    <description>To maximize adoption, 8-10 qualitative interviews will be conducted with emergency medicine providers, nurses and ancillary staff to explore barriers to use and potential adaptations to the implementation that might improve real world use. Providers who did not deploy the device will be included in order to understand their reasons for not adopting the intervention. Surrogate decision makers who did not agree to participate in the pilot intervention will be queried to understand their reasons for non-participation.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Implementation</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion, on average 1.5 years</time_frame>
    <description>In order to assess implementation (and prepare for larger implementation) a work-flow analysis will be conducted of the post-cardiac educational tools within the UCH ED. Nurses, ancillary staff (chaplain, social worker) who participate in family meetings within the emergency department will be queried. Via work-flow analysis, an understanding will be gained about when the tool was deployed, potential barriers/facilitators to deployment and how to best implement in a busy ED.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Effectiveness - Patient Outcomes</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion, on average 1.5 years</time_frame>
    <description>As a secondary outcome, outcomes data for the cardiac arrest patients will be measured. These data will include the disposition, including withdrawal of life sustaining therapy, survival, or re-arrest.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Cardiac Arrest With Successful Resuscitation</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Decision Aid for Surrogate Decision Makers</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>In this pilot trial all participants will be presented with the decision aid and queried as to the feasibility, acceptability and knowledge translation that is gained by exposure to the decision aid</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Decision Aid for Surrogate Decision Makers of Comatose Survivors of Cardiac Arrest</intervention_name>
    <description>a decision aid has been created that is a four page document meant to support surrogate decision makers for comatose survivors of cardiac arrest</description>
    <arm_group_label>Decision Aid for Surrogate Decision Makers</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Adult 18 years of age and older

          -  Identified as a surrogate decision maker for patient who is a comatose survivor of out
             of hospital cardiac arrest

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Illiterate or poor proficiency (unable to read decision aid)

          -  Non-english speaking
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>89 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Sarah M Perman, MD MSCE</last_name>
    <phone>720-848-6777</phone>
    <email>sarah.perman@ucdenver.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Bonnie J Siry, M</last_name>
    <phone>303-724-7872</phone>
    <email>bonnie.siry@ucdenver.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Colorado Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Aurora</city>
        <state>Colorado</state>
        <zip>80045</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sarah M Perman, MD MSCE</last_name>
      <phone>303-724-1721</phone>
      <email>sarah.perman@ucdenver.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>April 4, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 5, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 9, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 21, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 21, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 23, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Neurologic Prognosis</keyword>
  <keyword>Guideline Concordance</keyword>
  <keyword>Surrogate Decision Makers</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Heart Arrest</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

