<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03909854</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IRB00055128</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03909854</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Pragmatic Investigation of Volume Targeted Ventilation-1</brief_title>
  <acronym>PIVOT-1</acronym>
  <official_title>Pragmatic Investigation of Volume Targeted Ventilation-1 (PIVOT-1)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Wake Forest University Health Sciences</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Wake Forest University Health Sciences</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This proposal will test the feasibility of implementing an assist volume control ventilation
      protocol in patients receiving mechanical ventilation in the medical intensive care unit. The
      trial will consist of a before-and-after trial design of block assignment to either adaptive
      pressure control (baseline) or assist volume control .
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Over the course of 6 weeks, a before-and-after trial design of adaptive pressure control and
      assist volume control will be conducted.

      Pre-trial planning phase: study protocols will be reviewed with key stakeholders (respiratory
      therapy providers and medical teams)

      Weeks 1-2: data will be collected on our current adaptive pressure control ventilator
      protocol.

      Week 3: The investigators will implement an assist volume control protocol. . Patients
      already on mechanical ventilation will be converted to assist volume control; however, these
      patients will not be included in the primary analysis.In accordance with the Consolidated
      Framework For Implementation Research (CFIR) approach, after 1 week of assist volume control
      the investigators will engage in quantitative and qualitative feedback with care providers to
      identify facilitators and barriers of assist volume control implementation.

      Week 4-6: If the investigators identify substantial barriers, the investigators will pause
      and alter the protocol. If not, the investigators will continue assist volume control for an
      additional 2 weeks.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 9, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">November 12, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Sequential Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Before-and-after trial design of adaptive pressure control and assist volume control</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of patients receiving Assist Volume Control</measure>
    <time_frame>1 hour</time_frame>
    <description>The primary outcome for the PIVOT-1 pilot is feasibility of Assist Volume Control implementation. We define feasibility in this study as 80% of patients receiving Assist Volume Control within 1 hour of initiation of intensive care unit mechanical ventilation</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>assist volume control duration</measure>
    <time_frame>24 hours</time_frame>
    <description>A secondary feasibility outcome will be &gt;70% of ventilated time on Assist Volume Control during the first 24 hours of mechanical ventilation.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of mode crossover</measure>
    <time_frame>2 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>A secondary feasibility outcome will include &lt;10% crossover to the alternative mode</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>exhaled tidal volume</measure>
    <time_frame>2 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>exhaled tidal volume will be compared between modes using data extracted from the critical care data capsule.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of ventilator free days</measure>
    <time_frame>28 days</time_frame>
    <description>vent free days will be compared between the modes using data from the critical care data analytics platform</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>intensive care length of stay</measure>
    <time_frame>28 days</time_frame>
    <description>intensive care unit length of stay will be compared between the modes using data from the critical care data analytics platform</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">139</enrollment>
  <condition>Respiratory Failure</condition>
  <condition>Acute Respiratory Distress Syndrome (ARDS)</condition>
  <condition>Ventilator Lung</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Adaptive Pressure Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The Adaptive Pressure Control arm is the baseline mode/protocol for medical intensive care unit mechanical ventilation</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Assist Volume Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The assist volume control arm is the new protocol that will be implemented and tested for feasibility</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>mode of mechanical ventilation</intervention_name>
    <description>Adaptive Pressure Control mechanical ventilation is a dual controlled mode that is designed to auto-control flow and minimize inspiratory pressure while delivering a provider-determined tidal volume. Assist Volume Control mechanical ventilation is a mode in which the respiratory care provider determines patient tidal volume and flow.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Adaptive Pressure Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Assist Volume Control</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Acute Respiratory Failure requiring mechanical ventilation medical intensive care unit
        admission

        Exclusion Criteria:

        chronic mechanical ventilation clinician use of non-volume-targeted ventilation as initial
        mode
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Kevin Gibbs, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Wake Forest University Health Sciences</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Wake Forest Baptist Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Winston-Salem</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27157</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Esteban A, Frutos-Vivar F, Muriel A, Ferguson ND, Peñuelas O, Abraira V, Raymondos K, Rios F, Nin N, Apezteguía C, Violi DA, Thille AW, Brochard L, González M, Villagomez AJ, Hurtado J, Davies AR, Du B, Maggiore SM, Pelosi P, Soto L, Tomicic V, D'Empaire G, Matamis D, Abroug F, Moreno RP, Soares MA, Arabi Y, Sandi F, Jibaja M, Amin P, Koh Y, Kuiper MA, Bülow HH, Zeggwagh AA, Anzueto A. Evolution of mortality over time in patients receiving mechanical ventilation. Am J Respir Crit Care Med. 2013 Jul 15;188(2):220-30. doi: 10.1164/rccm.201212-2169OC.</citation>
    <PMID>23631814</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mireles-Cabodevila E, Chatburn RL. Work of breathing in adaptive pressure control continuous mandatory ventilation. Respir Care. 2009 Nov;54(11):1467-72.</citation>
    <PMID>19863830</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wunsch H, Wagner J, Herlim M, Chong DH, Kramer AA, Halpern SD. ICU occupancy and mechanical ventilator use in the United States. Crit Care Med. 2013 Dec;41(12):2712-9. doi: 10.1097/CCM.0b013e318298a139.</citation>
    <PMID>23963122</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Acute Respiratory Distress Syndrome Network, Brower RG, Matthay MA, Morris A, Schoenfeld D, Thompson BT, Wheeler A. Ventilation with lower tidal volumes as compared with traditional tidal volumes for acute lung injury and the acute respiratory distress syndrome. N Engl J Med. 2000 May 4;342(18):1301-8.</citation>
    <PMID>10793162</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shah FA, Girard TD, Yende S. Limiting sedation for patients with acute respiratory distress syndrome - time to wake up. Curr Opin Crit Care. 2017 Feb;23(1):45-51. doi: 10.1097/MCC.0000000000000382. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>27898439</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Branson RD, Chatburn RL. Controversies in the critical care setting. Should adaptive pressure control modes be utilized for virtually all patients receiving mechanical ventilation? Respir Care. 2007 Apr;52(4):478-85; discussion 485-8.</citation>
    <PMID>17417981</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Figueroa-Casas JB, Montoya R. Effect of Tidal Volume Size and Its Delivery Mode on Patient-Ventilator Dyssynchrony. Ann Am Thorac Soc. 2016 Dec;13(12):2207-2214.</citation>
    <PMID>27598383</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kallet RH, Campbell AR, Dicker RA, Katz JA, Mackersie RC. Work of breathing during lung-protective ventilation in patients with acute lung injury and acute respiratory distress syndrome: a comparison between volume and pressure-regulated breathing modes. Respir Care. 2005 Dec;50(12):1623-31.</citation>
    <PMID>16318643</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yoshida T, Fujino Y, Amato MB, Kavanagh BP. Fifty Years of Research in ARDS. Spontaneous Breathing during Mechanical Ventilation. Risks, Mechanisms, and Management. Am J Respir Crit Care Med. 2017 Apr 15;195(8):985-992. doi: 10.1164/rccm.201604-0748CP. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>27786562</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Writing Group for the PReVENT Investigators, Simonis FD, Serpa Neto A, Binnekade JM, Braber A, Bruin KCM, Determann RM, Goekoop GJ, Heidt J, Horn J, Innemee G, de Jonge E, Juffermans NP, Spronk PE, Steuten LM, Tuinman PR, de Wilde RBP, Vriends M, Gama de Abreu M, Pelosi P, Schultz MJ. Effect of a Low vs Intermediate Tidal Volume Strategy on Ventilator-Free Days in Intensive Care Unit Patients Without ARDS: A Randomized Clinical Trial. JAMA. 2018 Nov 13;320(18):1872-1880. doi: 10.1001/jama.2018.14280.</citation>
    <PMID>30357256</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Serpa Neto A, Simonis FD, Barbas CS, Biehl M, Determann RM, Elmer J, Friedman G, Gajic O, Goldstein JN, Horn J, Juffermans NP, Linko R, de Oliveira RP, Sundar S, Talmor D, Wolthuis EK, de Abreu MG, Pelosi P, Schultz MJ. Association between tidal volume size, duration of ventilation, and sedation needs in patients without acute respiratory distress syndrome: an individual patient data meta-analysis. Intensive Care Med. 2014 Jul;40(7):950-7. doi: 10.1007/s00134-014-3318-4. Epub 2014 May 9. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24811940</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Semler MW, Self WH, Wanderer JP, Ehrenfeld JM, Wang L, Byrne DW, Stollings JL, Kumar AB, Hughes CG, Hernandez A, Guillamondegui OD, May AK, Weavind L, Casey JD, Siew ED, Shaw AD, Bernard GR, Rice TW; SMART Investigators and the Pragmatic Critical Care Research Group. Balanced Crystalloids versus Saline in Critically Ill Adults. N Engl J Med. 2018 Mar 1;378(9):829-839. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa1711584. Epub 2018 Feb 27.</citation>
    <PMID>29485925</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Casey JD, Janz DR, Russell DW, Vonderhaar DJ, Joffe AM, Dischert KM, Brown RM, Zouk AN, Gulati S, Heideman BE, Lester MG, Toporek AH, Bentov I, Self WH, Rice TW, Semler MW; PreVent Investigators and the Pragmatic Critical Care Research Group. Bag-Mask Ventilation during Tracheal Intubation of Critically Ill Adults. N Engl J Med. 2019 Feb 28;380(9):811-821. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa1812405. Epub 2019 Feb 18.</citation>
    <PMID>30779528</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Damschroder LJ, Aron DC, Keith RE, Kirsh SR, Alexander JA, Lowery JC. Fostering implementation of health services research findings into practice: a consolidated framework for advancing implementation science. Implement Sci. 2009 Aug 7;4:50. doi: 10.1186/1748-5908-4-50.</citation>
    <PMID>19664226</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zuidgeest MGP, Goetz I, Groenwold RHH, Irving E, van Thiel GJMW, Grobbee DE; GetReal Work Package 3. Series: Pragmatic trials and real world evidence: Paper 1. Introduction. J Clin Epidemiol. 2017 Aug;88:7-13. doi: 10.1016/j.jclinepi.2016.12.023. Epub 2017 May 24.</citation>
    <PMID>28549929</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Meinecke AK, Welsing P, Kafatos G, Burke D, Trelle S, Kubin M, Nachbaur G, Egger M, Zuidgeest M; work package 3 of the GetReal consortium. Series: Pragmatic trials and real world evidence: Paper 8. Data collection and management. J Clin Epidemiol. 2017 Nov;91:13-22. doi: 10.1016/j.jclinepi.2017.07.003. Epub 2017 Jul 14.</citation>
    <PMID>28716504</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sjoding MW, Gong MN, Haas CF, Iwashyna TJ. Evaluating Delivery of Low Tidal Volume Ventilation in Six ICUs Using Electronic Health Record Data. Crit Care Med. 2019 Jan;47(1):56-61. doi: 10.1097/CCM.0000000000003469.</citation>
    <PMID>30308549</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>April 8, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 9, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 10, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 24, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 24, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 25, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Respiratory Distress Syndrome, Newborn</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Respiratory Distress Syndrome, Adult</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Respiratory Insufficiency</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Acute Lung Injury</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

