<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03906435</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>STU 072018-095</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03906435</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Preventing Vulnerable Child Syndrome in the NICU With Cognitive Behavioral Therapy (PreVNT Trial)</brief_title>
  <acronym>PreVNT</acronym>
  <official_title>Parental Perception of Child Vulnerability in the NICU and Development Outcomes: A Randomized Control Trial Preventative Intervention With Cognitive Behavioral Therapy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Texas Southwestern Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Stanford University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Texas Southwestern Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study is being done to see if outcomes for both a premature infant's parents and the
      infant born prematurely who have spent time in the neonatal intensive care unit (NICU) can be
      improved through parent cognitive behavioral therapy (CBT) sessions.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The NICU is a stressful experience for parents. This stress naturally affects parents in
      different ways, ranging from feelings of depression, anxiety, or post traumatic stress
      disorder (PTSD). While these feelings are very common in parents of NICU children, they can
      also impact the ways parents perceive their infants, which leads to alterations of parenting
      styles and exposure to developmental activities for growing infants. This phenomenon is well
      described in the literature as Vulnerable Child Syndrome (VCS), or Parent Perceived Child
      Vulnerability (PPCV) to illness. Traumatic events from earlier experiences in the NICU
      usually cause PPCV to occur. Examples of traumatic events include feared death of the child,
      which lead to parent anxiety, depression, or emotional trauma. This altered perception of the
      child has been linked to worsened development outcomes for NICU children further out into
      childhood and also continued feelings of depression, anxiety, or fear in the parents and lack
      of confidence in their parenting abilities.

      CBT sessions have been proven beneficial for NICU parents by decreasing feelings of
      depression, anxiety, and PTSD. However, there has not been research to see if CBT sessions
      are impactful for PPCV and the impacts it has on parent and child outcomes. Since literature
      suggests that depression, anxiety, and PTSD play an integral role in the development of PPCV
      and VCS, it could be assumed that CBT sessions should also be beneficial for PPCV and VCS.
      Therefore, this study will research if CBT sessions can improve parent-child interactions
      before and after discharge by helping parents to better understand their child's health and
      empower them with confidence in parenting skills. It will also evaluate if the effects of the
      CBT sessions will remain present and beneficial for parents' perceptions over time. With the
      results of this study, it will be evaluated if it is possible to improve the care for parents
      and children in the NICU as well as the long-term outcomes of parents and NICU children
      through CBT.

      This will be a randomized control trial and will be conducted to assess the outcomes of
      infants and parents receiving either CBT sessions versus standard of care.

      English and/or Spanish speaking parents of infants born at 30.6 weeks gestational age (GA) or
      less who survive to 33 weeks GA will be eligible to participate in the study. Families will
      be approached at 33 weeks GA to participate in the study. Once enrolled, the mother (and
      father, if willing to participate) will be randomized into a control group (standard NICU and
      follow up care information) versus the intervention group (standard NICU and follow up care
      information plus a total of 5 CBT sessions split between the NICU and outpatient clinic
      visits post discharge from NICU). The CBT sessions will address PPCV and VCS in parents and
      parenting skills to address preventing this. The CBT sessions will be standardized with a
      manual for study investigators to follow during sessions, and made with Dr. Richard Shaw from
      Stanford University, who wrote the prior CBT manual for anxiety, depression, and PTSD for
      NICU parents. Study staff will be trained to give the standardized CBT sessions using the
      manual via pilot sessions. There will be 3 CBT sessions given in the Parkland NICU before
      discharge and then 2 in the THRIVE follow up clinic at Children's Medical Center after
      discharge from the NICU.

      Scales used for assessment will be distributed at enrollment to the study and upon completion
      of the CBT sessions.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">April 15, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 30, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 30, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>This will be a non-blinded randomized control to assess the outcomes of infants and parents receiving either Cognitive Behavioral Therapy (CBT) sessions focusing on NICU trauma, emotional responses, and parent perceptions of child vulnerability (PPCV) versus standard of care without CBT sessions.
English and/or Spanish speaking parents of infants born at 30.6 weeks gestational age (GA) or less who survive to 33 weeks GA will be eligible to participate in the study. Once enrolled, the mother (and father, if willing) will be randomized into a control group (standard NICU and follow up care information) versus the intervention group (standard NICU and follow up care information plus a total of 5 CBT sessions split between the NICU and outpatient clinic visits post discharge from NICU). The CBT sessions will be standardized with a manual. Scales used for assessment will be distributed at enrollment to the study and upon completion of the CBT sessions.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>mean value score Vulnerable Baby Scale (VBSc) Score</measure>
    <time_frame>difference in the mean value score of the VBSc scores of parents at baseline of the study (33 weeks post-menstrual age) versus at six to nine months of post-birth age</time_frame>
    <description>Measures parental perceptions of child vulnerability. It has been used for parents with infants as young as 10-12 weeks of age up through 6 months to a year old. It is a 10 question scale, with each question scored on a five point likert scale (1-5). Score range is 10-50. Maximum score of 50 possible. A score of 27 or more was the median score for a sample of medically fragile neonates, and signifies relatively high perceptions of vulnerability. While a score of 23 was the median for a sample of healthy controls and thus reflect a more normal perception of vulnerability (Kerruish et al 2005). The higher the score, the higher the perception of child vulnerability.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>differences over time in subsets of Vulnerable Baby Scale (VBSc) scores</measure>
    <time_frame>measurement differences over time between the total number of questions endorsed for each of the three different question subsets of VBSc of the parents at baseline of the study (33 weeks post-menstrual age) versus at six to nine months of post-birth age</time_frame>
    <description>The VBSc can be broken down into subsets of questions addressing parent 1) thoughts: 2 questions of 10 scale questions, scored 0-2; 2) feelings: 3 questions of 10 scale questions, scored 0-3; and 3) actions/behaviors: 5 questions out of 10 scale questions, scored 0-5. This quantifies the amounts of subsets of the scale that the parent endorses. Higher numbers are markers of more and worse perceptions of child vulnerability in each category of thought, feeling, and action/behavior.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Correlation between changes over time in Vulnerable Baby Scale (VBSc) vs. Vulnerable Child Scale (VCSc) scores</measure>
    <time_frame>measurement differences of scores from baseline of the study (33 weeks post-menstrual age) versus at six to nine months of post-birth age</time_frame>
    <description>The VCSc is the most frequently and widely used scale to measure parent perceptions of vulnerability and Vulnerable Child Syndrome (VCS). It was modified by the author from the original 12 question scale to an 8 question scale. The modified scale has higher internal validity and consistency (Forsyth et al 1996). This scale was intended for and has been used for children aged mostly from 6 months to 8 years of age or older. Each question is scored on a four point likert scale (0-3). A total score of 0 to 24 is possible, the higher the score the more perceptions of vulnerability. A score of greater than 10 signifies high perceptions of vulnerability. See above for VBSc description.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>differences over time in parent depression scores measured with Beck Depression Inventory Scale- 2nd edition.</measure>
    <time_frame>measure differences of the scale's total score between timepoints at baseline of the study (33 weeks post-menstrual age) versus at six to nine months of post-birth age</time_frame>
    <description>Beck Depression Inventory - 2nd Edition: This will be used to measure parent depression scores, which can be associated with development of VCS. This will be used as a secondary outcome in change over time throughout the study. This is a 21 item questionnaire, measured on a four point likert scale (0-3). A score of greater than 14 signifies depression, with higher scores representing more severe levels of depression. Scores of 0-13= No depression; 14-19= mild; 20-28= moderate; 29-63= severe.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>child length of stay in the Parkland NICU (number of days) from birth to discharge from NICU, not including readmissions once first discharge has been accomplished.</measure>
    <time_frame>Days will be counted that are spent in the NICU starting from the day of birth of the child which is the admission day to the NICU until discharge day that is documented from Parkland NICU, through study completion, an average of 1 year.</time_frame>
    <description>child length of stay in the Parkland NICU (number of days) from birth to discharge from NICU, not including readmissions once first discharge has been accomplished. Scored in number of total days in the NICU (0 to infinite number). The higher the number, the more lengthy the NICU stay.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Child medical system usage score: number of non-well child or follow up visits/encounters until the last follow-up visit at 6-9 months averaged over the amount of months</measure>
    <time_frame>from discharge from Parkland NICU until completion of the study at 6-9 months age</time_frame>
    <description>The electronic medical record will be evaluated for how many total sick visits or hospital admissions are documented each month post discharge at Children's Medical Center and any associated hospitals that share medical records on the electronic medical record. The total number of encounters will be averaged over the amount of months from NICU discharge until the end of the study. Routine health checks will not be included in this number. A higher number will signify higher health care system usage.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>differences over time in parent anxiety scores measured with Beck Anxiety Inventory Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>measure differences of the scale's total score between timepoints at baseline of the study (33 weeks post-menstrual age) versus at six to nine months of post-birth age</time_frame>
    <description>Beck Anxiety Inventory: This will be used to measure parent anxiety scores, which can be associated with development of VCS. This will be used as a secondary outcome for change over time throughout the study. This is a 21 item questionnaire, measured on a four point likert scale (0-3). Possible scores range from 0-36. A score of greater than 7 suggests anxiety. Scores of 8-15= mild; 16-25= moderate; 26-36= severe.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Premature Infant</condition>
  <condition>Mental Health Issue (E.G., Depression, Psychosis, Personality Disorder, Substance Abuse)</condition>
  <condition>Development, Child</condition>
  <condition>Parent-Child Relations</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control Arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Standard of care information given by NICU staff and Follow up Clinic staff, including information about health care, diagnosis, medications, daily cares, anticipatory guidance, and discharge prep information.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention CBT Arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>In addition to Standard of care information that the control arm receives, this arm will also receive 5 CBT sessions focusing on past NICU trauma, emotional coping, parental perceptions of child vulnerability, and helpful parenting and emotional coping skills.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cognitive Behavioral Therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>The intervention group will receive standard NICU and follow up care information plus a total of 5 CBT sessions split between the NICU and outpatient clinic visits post discharge from NICU. The CBT sessions will address PPCV in parents and parenting skills to address this. The CBT sessions will be standardized with a manual for study investigators to follow during sessions, and made with Dr. Richard Shaw from Stanford University, who wrote the prior CBT manual for anxiety, depression, and PTSD for NICU parents. Study staff will be trained to give the standardized CBT sessions using the manual via pilot sessions. There will be 3 CBT sessions given in the Parkland NICU before discharge and then 2 in the THRIVE follow up clinic at Children's Medical Center after discharge from the NICU.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention CBT Arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Born at Parkland Hospital

          -  English or Spanish speaking mother +/- father

          -  ≤ 30.6 weeks gestation at birth

          -  Survival to 33 weeks gestation

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Significant congenital anomalies

          -  Child Protective Services (CPS) involvement or foster care placement
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Margaret K Hoge, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>UT Southwestern Medical Center Dallas</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Roy Heyne, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>UT Southwestern Medical Center Dallas</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Richard J Shaw, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Stanford University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Margaret K Hoge, MD</last_name>
    <phone>214-617-8439</phone>
    <email>margaret.hoge@utsouthwestern.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Roy Heyne, MD</last_name>
    <email>roy.heyne@utsouthwestern.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Parkland Health &amp; Hospital System</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dallas</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>75235</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Margaret K Hoge, MD</last_name>
      <phone>405-596-2075</phone>
      <email>margaret.hoge@utsouthwestern.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Roy Heyne, MD</last_name>
      <email>roy.heyne@utsouthwestern.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Kerruish NJ, Settle K, Campbell-Stokes P, Taylor BJ. Vulnerable Baby Scale: development and piloting of a questionnaire to measure maternal perceptions of their baby's vulnerability. J Paediatr Child Health. 2005 Aug;41(8):419-23.</citation>
    <PMID>16101975</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Forsyth BW, Horwitz SM, Leventhal JM, Burger J, Leaf PJ. The child vulnerability scale: an instrument to measure parental perceptions of child vulnerability. J Pediatr Psychol. 1996 Feb;21(1):89-101.</citation>
    <PMID>8820075</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>May 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 19, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 4, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 8, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 11, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 11, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 13, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Vulnerable Child Syndrome</keyword>
  <keyword>Neonatal Intensive Care Unit</keyword>
  <keyword>Cognitive Behavioral Therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Parental Perception of Child Vulnerability</keyword>
  <keyword>Child Developmental Outcomes</keyword>
  <keyword>Parent Mental Health</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Substance-Related Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Personality Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>There will be a data sharing agreement signed between all parties and institutions to agree to share data safely and confidentially. The data shared will be de-identified for the purposes of data analysis and result interpretation.</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Statistical Analysis Plan (SAP)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Informed Consent Form (ICF)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>upon start of study to completion of study and manuscript submission.</ipd_time_frame>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

