<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03908385</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>03-18-23</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03908385</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Hemoglobin Desaturation in Sickle Cell Disease</brief_title>
  <official_title>Hemoglobin Desaturation and RBC Adhesion: Potential Therapeutic Targets in Sickle Cell Disease</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University Hospitals Cleveland Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University Hospitals Cleveland Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      As part of routine care for SCD, some people are found to have low oxygen levels (≤ 88%)
      while sleeping, at rest, or with exercise. Testing is done with a small portable device
      positioned on the finger that measures oxygen levels during sleep, at rest, or following
      exercise. The investigators start oxygen treatment for people with low levels of oxygen. As a
      part of this study, the investigators will find out if any changes in cell &quot;stickiness&quot; occur
      with low oxygen levels (at rest, at night, or with exertion) and if cells become &quot;less
      sticky&quot; with oxygen treatment. Study subjects will be seen before testing and 2 months after
      testing. In some cases (people with low oxygen levels during testing), study subjects will
      have been prescribed oxygen, and the investigators will test the effects of that treatment on
      the stickiness of red cells.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      In SCD, exertional hypoxia and nocturnal hemoglobin desaturation (NHD, or hemoglobin
      deoxygenation during sleep) are common, treatable, and associated with bad outcomes in
      children and young adults15,16. The median life-expectancy of SCD has risen dramatically in
      the last 40 years. One consequence of this is an expanding young adult population in whom the
      comorbidities are not yet fully characterized. The prevalence, clinical consequences, and
      treatment outcomes of exertional hypoxia and NHD are poorly described in adults with SCD.
      Therefore, it is important to identify and better understand any clinically significant
      hypoxia (during exercise or sleep or at rest) in this expanding adult population. The
      investigators will study whether RBC adhesion at baseline and when exposed to hypoxia in
      vitro is significantly increased in adult HbSS patients with baseline hypoxia, exertional
      hypoxia or nocturnal NHD due to RBC membrane changes arising from prolonged in vivo exposure
      to hypoxia, which may be mitigated by oxygen therapy.

      Hypotheses: The investigators hypothesize that disease activity and RBC adhesion (under
      normoxia) will be greater in subjects with HbSS plus baseline in vivo hypoxia, exertional
      hypoxia, or NHD, due to RBC membrane damage from prolonged hypoxia in vivo. Successful
      treatment with therapeutic oxygen, at baseline, with exertion, or during sleep, may decrease
      RBC adhesion in vitro.

      Specific Aim 1: To evaluate for resting hypoxia, exertional hypoxia or NHD, and its clinical
      associations, in adults with HbSS.

      Specific Aim 2: To examine baseline RBC adhesion under normoxia or hypoxia in vitro in adults
      with HbSS, with and without in vivo resting or exertional hypoxia or NHD.

      Specific Aim 3: To examine serial changes in S-RBC adhesion at baseline and with hypoxia in
      vitro, in adults with HbSS and resting or exertional hypoxia or NHD, before and after
      therapeutic intervention with oxygen.

      The investigators are testing whether:

        1. Subjects with Hb desaturation at baseline, with exertion, or during sleep (NHD),
           compared to those without, will have increased disease activity (exertional or nocturnal
           symptoms, priapism, WBC activation, reticulocytosis, and/or hemolysis).

        2. S-RBCs from subjects with clinical Hb desaturation at rest, with exertion, or during
           sleep, compared to those without, will have increased adhesion at baseline and when
           exposed to hypoxia in vitro.

      2.A. Treatment of baseline hypoxia, exertional hypoxia, and/or NHD with supplemental oxygen
      will decrease S-RBC adhesion and HEA, and may decrease symptoms, especially night- time
      symptoms.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 23, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluation for resting hypoxia</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion, up to approximately 4 years</time_frame>
    <description>We will test resting SpO2 and night-time oxymetry to obtain Hb saturation results.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluation for exertional hypoxia</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion, up to approximately 4 years</time_frame>
    <description>We will evaluate 6MWT results and obtain Hb saturation results.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluation of hypoxia and its effect on CBC</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion, up to approximately 4 years</time_frame>
    <description>CBC results will be evaluated</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluation of hypoxia and its effect on reticulocyte count</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion, up to approximately 4 years</time_frame>
    <description>Reticulocyte count will be evaluated</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluation of hypoxia and its effect on LDH</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion, up to approximately 4 years</time_frame>
    <description>LDH level will be evaluated</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluation of hypoxia and its effect on serum chemistry</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion, up to approximately 4 years</time_frame>
    <description>Serum chemistry through a comprehensive panel will be evaluated</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluation of patient's incidence of hypoxia-related symptoms</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion, up to approximately 4 years</time_frame>
    <description>Incidence of hypoxia-related symptoms will be obtained from review of the patient's chart and approved symptom questionnaire.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluation of hypoxia and its effect on echocardiogram results</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion, up to approximately 4 years</time_frame>
    <description>Screening echocardiogram</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluation of patient's incidence of hypoxia-related nocturnal symptoms</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion, up to approximately 4 years</time_frame>
    <description>Incidence of nocturnal hypoxia-related symptoms will be obtained from review of the patient's chart and approved symptom questionnaire.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Examination of amount of baseline RBC adhesion and HEA in vitro in adults with HbSS</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion, up to approximately 4 years</time_frame>
    <description>Amount of S-RBC adhesion to LN on the SCD and Hypoxia Biochips will be quantitated, using &lt;400 μL surplus whole blood in EDTA, obtained during routine clinical care (as published previously1,6-8), at the clinic visit immediately prior to night-time oximetry and 6MWT</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Examination of baseline FACS results in adults with HbSS</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion, up to approximately 4 years</time_frame>
    <description>Fluorescent Activated Cell Sorting (FACS) following incubation with antibodies to CD14, CD16, and CX3CR1 will be performed on 3-400 μL of surplus whole blood.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Examination of amount of baseline RBC adhesion and HEA in vitro in adults with HbSS</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion, up to approximately 4 years</time_frame>
    <description>Simple t-tests will be used to compare RBC adhesion, HEA to LN and monocyte activation in patients with clinically significant hypoxia and those without any hypoxia</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Examination of serial changes in incidence of nocturnal symptoms at baseline and with hypoxia, in adults with HbSS and resting or exertional hypoxia or NHD, before and after therapeutic intervention with oxygen.</measure>
    <time_frame>2 months</time_frame>
    <description>At ~2 months after initial testing (and &gt;6 weeks on treatment, if needed), all subjects will be re-evaluated for incidence of hypoxia-related nocturnal symptoms through review of the patient's chart and approved symptom questionnaire</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Examination of serial changes in amount of S-RBC adhesion at baseline and with hypoxia in vitro, in adults with HbSS and resting or exertional hypoxia or NHD, before and after therapeutic intervention with oxygen</measure>
    <time_frame>2 months</time_frame>
    <description>At ~2 months after initial testing (and &gt;6 weeks on treatment, if needed), all subjects will be re-evaluated for amount of RBC adhesion</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Examination of serial changes in incidence of hypoxia-related symptoms at baseline and with hypoxia, in adults with HbSS and resting or exertional hypoxia or NHD, before and after therapeutic intervention with oxygen.</measure>
    <time_frame>2 months</time_frame>
    <description>At ~2 months after initial testing (and &gt;6 weeks on treatment, if needed), all subjects will have incidence of hypoxia-related symptoms re-evaluated through review of the patient's chart and approved symptom questionnaire</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Examination of serial changes in Hb saturation at baseline and with hypoxia in vitro, in adults with HbSS and resting or exertional hypoxia or NHD, before and after therapeutic intervention with oxygen</measure>
    <time_frame>2 months</time_frame>
    <description>We will repeat Hb saturation testing</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Examination of serial changes in amount of S-RBC adhesion at baseline and with hypoxia in vitro, in adults with HbSS and resting or exertional hypoxia or NHD, before and after therapeutic intervention with oxygen.</measure>
    <time_frame>2 months</time_frame>
    <description>Paired t-test on S-RBC adhesion to LN and HEA before and after oxygen therapy, in subjects with and without clinically significant hypoxia will be performed</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Examination of serial changes in amount of WBC activation at baseline and with hypoxia in vitro, in adults with HbSS and resting or exertional hypoxia or NHD, before and after therapeutic intervention with oxygen</measure>
    <time_frame>2 months</time_frame>
    <description>Amount of WBC activation will be determined</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Examination of serial changes in CBC at baseline and with hypoxia in vitro, in adults with HbSS and resting or exertional hypoxia or NHD, before and after therapeutic intervention with oxygen.</measure>
    <time_frame>2 months</time_frame>
    <description>CBC results will be examined for any suggestive changes</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Examination of serial changes in reticulocyte count at baseline and with hypoxia in vitro, in adults with HbSS and resting or exertional hypoxia or NHD, before and after therapeutic intervention with oxygen.</measure>
    <time_frame>2 months</time_frame>
    <description>Reticulocyte count will be examined for any suggestive changes</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Examination of serial changes in LDH at baseline and with hypoxia in vitro, in adults with HbSS and resting or exertional hypoxia or NHD, before and after therapeutic intervention with oxygen.</measure>
    <time_frame>2 months</time_frame>
    <description>LDH level will be examined for any suggestive changes</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Examination of serial changes in serum chemistry at baseline and with hypoxia in vitro, in adults with HbSS and resting or exertional hypoxia or NHD, before and after therapeutic intervention with oxygen.</measure>
    <time_frame>2 months</time_frame>
    <description>Serum chemistry through a comprehensive panel will be examined for any suggestive changes</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Sickle Cell Disease</condition>
  <biospec_retention>None Retained</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Blood samples
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Individuals with HbSS Sickle Cell Disease
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Male or Female &gt; 18 year of age at the time of consent.

          2. Documentation of Sickle Cell Disease, phenotypically HbSS (including S-Beta 0
             thalassemia)

          3. Written informed consent (and assent when applicable) obtained from subject or
             subject's legal representative and ability for subject to comply with the requirements
             of the study.

          4. English speaking patient

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Ongoing Oxygen therapy.

          2. active pregnancy, due to complex pathophysiology during that interval.

          3. Presence of a condition or abnormality that in the opinion of the Investigator would
             compromise the safety of the patient or the quality of the data. -
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jane Little, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University Hospitals Cleveland Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Jane Little, MD</last_name>
    <phone>216-844-1652</phone>
    <email>Jane.Little@UHhospitals.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Hospitals Cleveland Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cleveland</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>44106</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jane Little, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 21, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 5, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 9, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 5, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 5, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 9, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University Hospitals Cleveland Medical Center</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Jane Little</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Director, Adult Sickle Cell provider</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Anemia, Sickle Cell</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <provided_document_section>
    <provided_document>
      <document_type>Study Protocol</document_type>
      <document_has_protocol>Yes</document_has_protocol>
      <document_has_icf>No</document_has_icf>
      <document_has_sap>No</document_has_sap>
      <document_date>March 23, 2018</document_date>
      <document_url>https://ClinicalTrials.gov/ProvidedDocs/85/NCT03908385/Prot_000.pdf</document_url>
    </provided_document>
  </provided_document_section>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

