<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03900494</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ETL-R19030</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03900494</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Comparing the Efficacy of Two Valved Holding Chambers in Acute Wheezing</brief_title>
  <acronym>CHAMBER</acronym>
  <official_title>Comparing the Efficacy of Two Valved Holding Chambers for Bronchodilator Administration in 0.5-4 Years Old Children With Acute Wheezing - a Randomized Clinical Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Tampere University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Kuopio University Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Oulu University Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Tampere University Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Terveystalo Healthcare Services</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Tampere University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The incidence of physician confirmed asthma is approximately 4-7% in children. An additional
      5% of children suffer from infection-related bronchiolitis and obstructive bronchitis. Of all
      patient visits at pediatric emergency rooms, 1 out of 10 is due to breathing difficulties
      with a great proportion leading to hospitalization.

      Salbutamol is the most commonly used drug in the treatment in acute bronchial obstruction. A
      vast majority of children require a spacer device (valved holding chamber, VHC) for the
      delivery of the drug aerosol. There are several different types of VHC on the market, but no
      recommendations on the device selection have been published. Both in in vivo and in vitro
      studies significant differences between different spacer devices have been reported.

      The study compares two different VHCs in the treatment of acute breathing difficulties in
      children. The end-points in this randomized physician-blinded study are symptom relief, rate
      of hospitalization, symptom recurrence, treatment compliance, and adverse events.

      The study will be conducted in pediatric emergency rooms (ER) in three university hospitals
      in Finland and one private clinic that routinely treat this type of patients. The treatment
      is given according to national treatment guidelines and no blood samples are drawn for study
      purposes. Both of the VHCs used in this study have been approved for use in clinical
      practice.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study compares two valved holding chamber (VHC) devices in the treatment of acute airway
      obstruction in children. Eighty children (6 months to 4 years of age) will be recruited with
      moderate to severe dyspnea according to the Respiratory Distress Assessment Instrument (RDAI
      score ≥6). After receiving an informed consent from the parents/caregivers, the child is
      randomized to receive treatment with either Babyhaler® or Optichamber Diamond® VHC. Patients
      with underlying medical conditions listed in the study protocol, patients requiring immediate
      hospitalization or not willing to participate will be excluded from the study. Information on
      the medical history together with treatment response will be recorded using a manual case
      report form. According to calculations of the statistical power using the RDAI-score as an
      end-point, a total of 80 patients (40 patients in both study groups) are needed for the
      study.

      The study hypothesis is that the two VHCs are not equally efficient in treating acute
      shortage of breath in children aged 0.5-4 years.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">April 17, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of subjects whose RDAI symptom score increase by 2 or more</measure>
    <time_frame>20 minutes after the second salbutamol-dose and if necessary 20 minutes after the third or fourth salbutamol-dose. Maximum 5 hours.</time_frame>
    <description>Respiratory Distress Assessment Instrument (RDAI) score. Change from baseline at each evaluation point. Discharge time is dependent on the score at each evaluation point. Minimum score 0 (best), maximum score 17 (worst). Inclusion criteria is at least 6.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference in the mean capillary oxygen saturation change between groups</measure>
    <time_frame>20 minutes after the second salbutamol-dose and if necessary 20 minutes after the third or fourth salbutamol-dose. Maximum 5 hours.</time_frame>
    <description>Peripheral capillary oxygen saturation (%). Change from baseline at each evaluation point. Minimum 85 % (if below, not suitable for the study), maximum 100 %.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference in the mean respiratory rate change between group</measure>
    <time_frame>20 minutes after the second salbutamol-dose and if necessary 20 minutes after the third or fourth salbutamol-dose. Maximum 5 hours.</time_frame>
    <description>Respiratory rate per minute. Change from baseline at each evaluation point. Minimum N/A, maximum N/A.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Compliance to treatment, compared between groups</measure>
    <time_frame>Throughout the ER visit. Maximum 5 hours.</time_frame>
    <description>Compliance to the treatment using a structured questionnaire conducted both by the parents and by the nurses treating the child in the emergency room.
Cooperation score from 0 to 5: 0 = no measurement possible; 1 = continuously crying, screaming, or struggling against the procedure; 2 = crying, screaming, or struggling, but not continuously; 3 = not very good cooperation, but no crying or screaming; 4 = good cooperation, but clearly not comfortable; 5 = good cooperation and quiet breathing during the whole measurement.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of subjects hospitalized in both group</measure>
    <time_frame>After the last dose of salbutamol. Maximum 5 hours.</time_frame>
    <description>The information on whether the patient is discharged from the emergency room or admitted to hospital for further treatment will be recorded in the case report form.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Readmission rate in both group</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 48 hours of initial treatment.</time_frame>
    <description>Re-hospitalization within 48 hours of initial treatment based on patient records.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of drug doses given in both groups</measure>
    <time_frame>Throughout the ER visit. Maximum 5 hours.</time_frame>
    <description>Number of salbutamol-doses given to the patient. Minimum two, maximum four doses. Less dose is better.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference in the mean heart rate change between groups</measure>
    <time_frame>After each salbutamol dose. Maximum 5 hours.</time_frame>
    <description>Change in heart rate per minute. Minimum N/A, maximum N/A.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">80</enrollment>
  <condition>Bronchitis Obstructive</condition>
  <condition>Bronchiolitis; Obstruction</condition>
  <condition>Bronchospasm; Bronchitis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Children treated with VHC 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>In this group children are receiving salbutamol with valved holding chamber number 1. Otherwise the children in both groups are treated exactly the same way. The only difference is the device used to deliver the bronchodilator. Children in both arms have the same condition and the same inclusion and exclusion criteria. We only compare the efficacy of the two VHC devices.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Children treated with VHC 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>In this group children are receiving salbutamol with valved holding chamber number 2. Otherwise the children in both groups are treated exactly the same way. The only difference is the device used to deliver the bronchodilator. Children in both arms have the same condition and the same inclusion and exclusion criteria. In this group children are receiving salbutamol with valved holding chamber number 1. Otherwise the children in both groups are treated exactly the same way. The only difference is the device used to deliver the bronchodilator. Children in both arms have the same condition and the same inclusion and exclusion criteria.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>VHC 1</intervention_name>
    <description>Salbutamol 0.6-0.8 mg given 20-40 min. maximum four times depending on the bronchodilator response delivered via valved holding chamber 1. Same salbutamol dosing protocol for both arms. Only difference is the VHC used.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Children treated with VHC 1</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>VHC 2</intervention_name>
    <description>Salbutamol 0.6-0.8 mg given 20-40 min. maximum four times depending on the bronchodilator response delivered via valved holding chamber 2. Same salbutamol dosing protocol for both arms. Only difference is the VHC used.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Children treated with VHC 2</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        - Children (age 0.5-4 years) seeking medical aid due to respiratory distress caused by
        bronchial obstruction

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  requiring immediate admission to inpatient treatment in hospital

          -  peripheral capillary oxygen saturation below 85% on admission

          -  physician-confirmed pneumonia

          -  inspiratory crackles on lung auscultation

          -  croup

          -  airway foreign body

          -  impaired renal or liver function

          -  immune compromised patient

          -  general condition affecting the study per investigation judgement

          -  bronchopulmonary dysplasia

          -  long-acting beta-adrenoceptor agonist treatment

          -  recruited to the ongoing study earlier

          -  have been enrolled in a clinical trial within 30 days prior to admission

          -  not willing to participate
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>6 Months</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>4 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Peter Csonka, MD. PhD.</last_name>
    <phone>+358503661103</phone>
    <email>peter.csonka@tuni.fi</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Palmu Sauli, MD. PhD.</last_name>
    <email>sauli.palmu@pshp.fi</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Kuopio University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kuopio</city>
        <zip>70210</zip>
        <country>Finland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Marjo Renko, Professor</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Oulu University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Oulu</city>
        <zip>90220</zip>
        <country>Finland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Terhi Tapiainen, MD, PhD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Terveystalo Tampere</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tampere</city>
        <zip>33100</zip>
        <country>Finland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Peter Csonka, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>+358503661103</phone>
      <email>peter.csonka@terveystalo.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Tampere University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tampere</city>
        <zip>33521</zip>
        <country>Finland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sauli Palmu, MD. PhD.</last_name>
      <email>sauli.palmu@pshp.fi</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Finland</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 29, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 30, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 3, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 17, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 17, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 19, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Tampere University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Peter Csonka</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Specialist in pediatrics and pediatric allergology</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>salbutamol</keyword>
  <keyword>valved holding chamber</keyword>
  <keyword>pMDI</keyword>
  <keyword>inhalation therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>children</keyword>
  <keyword>toddlers</keyword>
  <keyword>emergency room</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Bronchiolitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Bronchitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Bronchial Spasm</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Acute Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Respiratory Sounds</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

