<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03902223</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CSN504-002</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03902223</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Routine Cardiac Screening in Sarcoidosis Patients</brief_title>
  <acronym>PAPLAND</acronym>
  <official_title>A Randomized Screening Trial for Cardiac Sarcoidosis (CS) in Patients Seen During Routine Clinical Care Who Have Not Been Clinically Suspected to Have (CS), Comparing the Addition of Echocardiogram and Ambulatory ECG to Standard of Care.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Foundation for Sarcoidosis Research</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Foundation for Sarcoidosis Research</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This protocol is an unblended randomized screening trial will have consecutive patients with
      no suggestion of cardiac sarcoidosis according to usual screening enroll in an enhanced
      screening protocol. The routine clinical care is to gather patient's history of symptoms and
      under go an ECG. If a patient has an abnormal results in standard screening, they typically
      have further evaluations as part of their routine medical care. These tests might include an
      echocardiogram, ambulatory ECG, and advanced cardiac imaging (MRI, PET scan as per local
      practice). A patient that has normal results on standard screening will be randomly assigned
      to enhanced screening at each center. Half the patients will be randomized to usual follow-up
      (annual symptom assessment and ECG) and the other half will be assigned to the enhanced
      screening (echocardiogram and ambulatory ECG at enrollment and at 24 months).

      The investigators hypothesize that screening using conventional history, physical and ECG in
      the general sarcoidosis population, followed by appropriate advanced imaging testing, will
      result in the identification of a higher percentage of ascertained cardiac sarcoidosis than
      has been reported historically (2-5%). The investigators hypothesize that routine use of
      echocardiogram with strain and ambulatory ECG will identify additional patients who will have
      advanced imaging abnormalities or who meet criteria for cardiac sarcoidosis. The
      investigators further hypothesize that re-screening patients after 24 months with repeat
      echocardiogram and ambulatory ECG will identify additional patients with suspicion for
      cardiac sarcoidosis who had no abnormalities on the standard screening tests.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Cardiac involvement is among the most feared complications of sarcoidosis, and it is the
      second leading cause of death from sarcoidosis. Autopsy studies and serial imaging studies in
      patients without cardiac symptoms suggest that approximately 25% of U.S. sarcoidosis patients
      have evidence of cardiac involvement. 3 Major manifestations of cardiac sarcoidosis include
      conduction delays, dysrhythmias, and cardiomyopathy. Given the increased recognition of
      cardiac involvement, prompt screening and diagnosis of cardiac sarcoidosis has been
      emphasized as a key priority for sarcoidosis research. Screening for cardiac sarcoidosis
      conventionally has relied on symptoms and electrocardiogram. However, there are no validated
      screening instruments for symptom assessment, and the usefulness of individual components of
      the medical history (e.g. palpitations, chest pain, presyncope) has not been assessed. In one
      study, symptom assessment was found to be less than 50% sensitive for identification of
      individuals with abnormal cardiac imaging studies. ECG performed poorly, with less than 10%
      sensitivity. Holter monitoring and echocardiogram were more sensitive than ECG in that study,
      identifying 50% and 25%, respectively, of those with imaging findings suggesting cardiac
      sarcoidosis (CS). The intensity of screening for CS in unselected sarcoidosis patients is
      controversial. The Heart Rhythm Society working group could not agree that echocardiogram or
      ambulatory ECG added significantly to conventional testing of eliciting cardiac symptoms and
      ECG; therefore, the working group was unable to recommend adding these procedures as a
      routine for all sarcoidosis patients. In a large series of Greek non-cardiac sarcoidosis
      patients, echocardiogram and ambulatory ECG added little prognostic information to usual
      care. On the other hand, more sophisticated echocardiographic techniques such as speckle
      tracking seem to provide independent prognostic information. In a second study, Holter
      monitoring and echocardiography abnormalities were both more common in those with MRI
      findings consistent with CS, although the usefulness of the tests disappeared in
      multivariable analysis. While history and ECG are considered the standard of care at present,
      there is a continuing need to identify markers of poor outcomes. Cardiac MRI and/or cardiac
      FDG-PET scan can identify large proportions of individuals with asymptomatic imaging
      abnormalities, but they are expensive, require specialized expertise to interpret, require
      radiation (PET scan) and are likely impractical for widespread use in all sarcoidosis
      patients. A second unresolved issue concerning screening for cardiac sarcoidosis is the
      frequency of re-screening sarcoidosis patients who demonstrate no evidence for cardiac
      sarcoidosis on an initial screen. The investigators hypothesize that screening using
      conventional history, physical and ECG in the general sarcoidosis population, followed by
      appropriate advanced imaging testing, will result in the identification of a higher
      percentage of ascertained cardiac sarcoidosis than has been reported historically (2-5%). The
      investigators hypothesize that routine use of echocardiogram with strain and ambulatory ECG
      will identify additional patients who will have advanced imaging abnormalities or who meet
      criteria for cardiac sarcoidosis. The investigators further hypothesize that re-screening
      patients after 24 months with repeat echocardiogram and ambulatory ECG will identify
      additional patients with suspicion for cardiac sarcoidosis who had no abnormalities on the
      initial screening tests.

      Aims

        1. To evaluate the rate of diagnosis of cardiac sarcoidosis during standard of care
           clinical practice that relies on patient symptoms and ECG.

        2. To evaluate whether second-tier screening tests (echocardiogram and ambulatory ECG)
           improve the rate of diagnosis of cardiac sarcoidosis beyond conventional screening
           methods.

        3. To evaluate the rate of diagnosis of cardiac sarcoidosis in sarcoidosis patients who had
           initial negative conventional and second-tier screening tests after undergoing these
           screening tests again at two years.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">April 5, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2029</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Screening</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Positive result found from enhanced cardiac sarcoidosis screening at initial visit (sensitivity)</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1</time_frame>
    <description>To evaluate whether second-tier screening tests (echocardiogram and ambulatory ECG) improve the rate of diagnosis of cardiac sarcoidosis beyond conventional screening methods.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Positive result found on enhanced cardiac screening at month 12 (sensitivity)</measure>
    <time_frame>Month 12</time_frame>
    <description>To evaluate whether second-tier screening tests (echocardiogram and ambulatory ECG) improve the rate of diagnosis of cardiac sarcoidosis beyond conventional screening methods during chart review.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Positive result found from enhanced cardiac screening at month 24 (sensitivity)</measure>
    <time_frame>Month 24</time_frame>
    <description>To evaluate the rate of diagnosis of cardiac sarcoidosis in sarcoidosis patients who had initial negative conventional and second-tier screening tests after undergoing these screening tests again at two years</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Positive result from study cohort</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 120 months after study completion</time_frame>
    <description>To evaluate the rate of diagnosis of cardiac sarcoidosis in study cohort after 10 years.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of diagnosis of cardiac sarcoidosis during standard of care of patient symptoms and ECG.</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 24 months from day 1</time_frame>
    <description>To evaluate the rate of diagnosis of cardiac sarcoidosis during standard of care clinical practice that relies on patient symptoms and ECG.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">600</enrollment>
  <condition>Sarcoidosis</condition>
  <condition>Cardiac Sarcoidosis</condition>
  <condition>Boeck's Disease</condition>
  <condition>Besnier-Boeck Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Enhanced Screening Protocol For Cardiac Sarcoidosis</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Arm will be randomly assigned to undergo enhanced screening methods (ambulatory ECG and echocardiogram) at month 0 and month 24, as well as a phone call/chart review at month 12.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Routine Screening for Suspected Cardiac Sarcoidosis</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Arm will be randomly assigned for the routine standard of care/no intervention with enhanced screening methods. They will be offered the EKG and symptom check at months 0 and 24, as well as a phone call/chart review at month 12.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Enhanced Screening Protocol for Cardiac Sarcoidosis.</intervention_name>
    <description>To utilize enhanced screening tests for cardiac sarcoidosis in an undiagnosed and potentially under-diagnosed patient population to determine the rate of missed cardiac sarcoidosis diagnosis. Following testing by the standard screening tests, this intervention includes a subsequent echocardiogram and a wearable ECG, also known as a Holter Monitor or ambulatory ECG.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Enhanced Screening Protocol For Cardiac Sarcoidosis</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Echocardiogram and ambulatory ECG</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Routine Screening for Suspected Cardiac Sarcoidosis</intervention_name>
    <description>To utilize standard of care screening tests for cardiac sarcoidosis. This includes symptom check and a standard ECG.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Routine Screening for Suspected Cardiac Sarcoidosis</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Symptom check and standard ECG.</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Diagnosis of sarcoidosis as per The American Thoracic Society guidelines

          2. First visit to the enrolling center

          3. Intent to continue care at the enrolling center at least annually

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Referred to the enrolling center to evaluate for suspected cardiac sarcoidosis.

          2. Pre-existing high suspicion for cardiac sarcoidosis, defined as having had cardiac MRI
             or cardiac PET scan, even if it was ordered by other institutions.

          3. Severe sarcoidosis or other disease conferring a high likelihood of death or
             transplant within the next year

          4. Unwilling or unable to undergo echocardiography and ambulatory ECG
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Dan Culver, DO</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>The Cleveland Clinic</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Muhunthan Thillai, MBBS</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Royal Papworth Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Noopur Singh</last_name>
    <phone>312-341-0500</phone>
    <phone_ext>107</phone_ext>
    <email>noopur@stopsarcoidosis.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Ginger Spitzer</last_name>
    <phone>773-328-8156</phone>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Jewish Health</name>
      <address>
        <city>Denver</city>
        <state>Colorado</state>
        <zip>80206</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Briana Barkes</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Lisa Maier, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Northwestern University Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chicago</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60611</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Isaac Goldberg</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Peter Sporn, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Illinois Medical Center At Chicago</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chicago</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60612</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Hasib Zabih</last_name>
      <phone>312-355-0601</phone>
      <email>hzabih2@uic.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Nadera Sweiss, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Iowa Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Iowa City</city>
        <state>Iowa</state>
        <zip>52242</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Brenda Werner</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Nabeel Y Hamzeh, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Albany Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Albany</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>12208</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Rachel Vancavage</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Marc Judson, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Cincinnati Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cincinnati</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>45219</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Rebecca Reeves</last_name>
      <phone>513-584-5226</phone>
      <email>reevesrc@ucmail.uc.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Robert Baughman, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cleveland Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cleveland</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>44195</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Allison Wimer</last_name>
      <phone>216-444-9975</phone>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Daniel Culver, DO</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Penn Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19104</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sally Thomas</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Colin Ligon, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Medical University of South Carolina</name>
      <address>
        <city>Charleston</city>
        <state>South Carolina</state>
        <zip>29425</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ashley Warden</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>W. Ennis James, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Washington Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seattle</city>
        <state>Washington</state>
        <zip>98195</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Chessa Goss</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ganesh Raghu</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>St. Antonius</name>
      <address>
        <city>Koekoekslaan</city>
        <state>Nieuwegein</state>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Marcel Veltkamp, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Marcel Veltkamp, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Royal Papworth Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cambridge</city>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Helen Holcombe</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 1223 639822</phone>
      <email>Helen.holcombe@nhs.net</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Muhunthan Thillai</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Netherlands</country>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>August 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 25, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 2, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 3, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 12, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 12, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">August 14, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>sarcoidosis</keyword>
  <keyword>cardiac sarcoidosis</keyword>
  <keyword>cardiac sarcoidosis screening</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Sarcoidosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>All data will be housed in a secured RedCap database. Protected health information (PHI) will be available only to the individual institutions, and the RedCap database will not house such data.
Each subject will be entered into the database using a unique subject identifying number.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

