<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03903250</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>AGPC-1</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03903250</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effects of A-GPC on Reaction Time and Cognitive Function</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effects of A-GPC on Reaction Time and Cognitive Function Under Acute Sleep-Deprived Conditions</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Mary Hardin-Baylor</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Chemi Nutra, LLC.</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Mary Hardin-Baylor</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>Yes</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a randomized, double blind, crossover design study which measures the effect of
      alpha-glycerylphosphorylcholine (A-GPC) on reaction time and cognitive function in
      non-resistance trained males and females. Participants will complete baseline testing and
      then be randomized into one of two crossover treatments. Participants will report to the lab
      for five consecutive days whilst only getting a maximum of five hours of sleep per night from
      Monday through Thursday night. Once testing is complete on Friday, participants will receive
      a one week washout period then return to complete the opposite treatment.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Subjects expressing interest in doing the study will be interviewed in the UMHB Human
      Performance Lab (HPL) to determine whether they qualify to participate in the study. Upon
      qualification, participants will be scheduled a familiarization session in which participants
      will be taught how to use the Makoto Arena, a reaction time machine. Participants will then
      schedule their first testing session which will include: questionnaires, hemodynamic
      measures, reaction time testing, cognitive function testing via ImPACT, an acute exercise
      bout, reaction time testing, and cognitive function testing via ImPACT. Participants will
      then be randomized into one of two treatments.

      Supplementation protocol: Participants will be randomly assigned into one of two treatments
      and will be given 4oz of either a placebo or active treatment mixed in orange flavored
      Gatorade everyday for 5 days. On Monday, participants will consume the beverage after testing
      is complete. Tuesday through Friday the beverage will be consumed as the participants arrive
      in the HPL.

      On Mondays and Fridays, testing will be as follows: questionnaires, hemodynamic measures,
      reaction time testing, cognitive function testing via ImPACT, an acute exercise bout,
      reaction time testing, and cognitive function testing via ImPACT. On Tuesdays and Thursdays,
      participants will come check into the HPL for 30 minutes. On Wednesday, participants will
      come into the HPL to complete the acute exercise bout. To control their sleep to the best of
      our ability, participants are required to send emails every 30 minutes beginning at 10pm
      until their designated sleep time so the investigators know the participants are not asleep
      and gaining more than 5 hours of sleep.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 25, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Two groups: placebo and active</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Effects of A-GPC on Reaction Time</measure>
    <time_frame>within 5 days</time_frame>
    <description>The primary purpose of this investigation is to determine the effectiveness of alpha-glycerylphosphorylcholine (A-GPC) on changes in reaction time in young, non-resistance trained males and females. This will be accomplished by observing changes in reaction time via the Makoto Arena. The Makoto Arena is an instrument that utilizes lights and noises to assess reaction time. Participants are required to hit the lights when they appear on the tower as fast as possible. Participants are instructed to hit as many lights as fast as possible to acquire a score that consists of the following: number of targets hit, number of targets that appeared, average reaction time, and percentage of targets hit.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Effects of A-GPC on Mental Alertness</measure>
    <time_frame>within 5 days</time_frame>
    <description>The primary purpose of this investigation is to determine the effectiveness of alpha-glycerylphosphorylcholine (A-GPC) on changes in mental alertness in young, non-resistance trained males and females. This will be accomplished by observing changes in ImPACT test scores before and after acute exercise, and after 4 days of sleep deprivation defined as only 5 hours of sleep per night. The ImPACT test measures cognitive function via the following tests: verbal memory, visual memory, symbol matching, color matching, and a three letter sequence memory test. For the verbal and visual memory tests, a composite score is taken between 0-100 with 100 indicating best cognitive performance and 0 indicating the worst cognitive performance. For the symbol matching and color matching, a visual motor composite score is taken from 0-60 with 60 indicating the best cognitive performance and 0 indicating the worst cognitive performance.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Effects of A-GPC on Mental Fatigue</measure>
    <time_frame>within 5 days</time_frame>
    <description>The primary purpose of this investigation is to determine the effectiveness of alpha-glycerylphosphorylcholine (A-GPC) on changes in mental fatigue in young, non-resistance trained males and females. This will be accomplished by observing changes in ImPACT test scores before and after acute exercise, and after 4 days of sleep deprivation defined as only 5 hours of sleep per night. The ImPACT test measures cognitive function via the following tests: verbal memory, visual memory, symbol matching, color matching, and a three letter sequence memory test. For the verbal and visual memory tests, a composite score is taken between 0-100 with 100 indicating best cognitive performance and 0 indicating the worst cognitive performance. For the symbol matching and color matching, a visual motor composite score is taken from 0-60 with 60 indicating the best cognitive performance and 0 indicating the worst cognitive performance.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">18</enrollment>
  <condition>Cognitive Change</condition>
  <condition>Reaction Time</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sugar</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>100% soluble in liquid. 4 oz. taken in the morning of testing sessions.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>A-GPC</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>100% soluble in liquid. 4 oz. taken in the morning of testing sessions.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>A-GPC</intervention_name>
    <description>Taken orally in liquid form</description>
    <arm_group_label>A-GPC</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sugar</intervention_name>
    <description>Taken orally in liquid form</description>
    <arm_group_label>Sugar</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria

          -  Participants will be male or female between the ages of 18-35 years;

          -  Participants regularly sleep &gt;7.5 hours per night;

          -  Participants have not been consistently resistance training for the past 6 months;

          -  Participant has provided written and dated informed consent to participate in the
             study;

          -  Participant is willing and able to comply with the protocol;

          -  Participant is apparently healthy and free from disease, as determined by a health
             history questionnaire;

          -  Participants agrees to not drive or operate heavy machinery while under sleep
             deprivation as a result of the study (Tuesday-Saturday);

        Exclusion Criteria

          -  Participant currently smokes or have quit within the last 6 months;

          -  Participant is medically prescribed by a physician to take over the counter
             medications including medications related to insomnia or sleep aids (such as
             melatonin);

          -  Participant is medically diagnosed with a mental health/psychological disorder or
             suspected of having a mental health/diagnostic disorder that would be influenced or
             made worse by sleep deprivation;

          -  Participant is allergic to any ingredient in the nutritional supplement or placebo;

          -  Participant may be pregnant, is pregnant, is trying to become pregnant, or is
             breastfeeding;

          -  Participant has a major exam or academic requirement that will fall during the sleep
             deprived portion of the study (Tuesday-Friday)

          -  Participant reports any unusual adverse events associated with this study that in
             consultation with the study investigators or their doctor recommends removal from the
             study;

          -  Participants fail to abstain from operating motor vehicles or heavy machinery;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>35 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Lemuel W Taylor IV, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>UMHB Human Performance Lab</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UMHB Human Performance Lab</name>
      <address>
        <city>Belton</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>76513</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>April 2, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 2, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 4, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 28, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 28, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 31, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>A-GPC</keyword>
  <keyword>focus</keyword>
  <keyword>non-resistance trained</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

