<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03905395</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>H-18038456</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03905395</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Meditation and Mindfulness for Recurrent Pregnancy Loss</brief_title>
  <official_title>Meditation and Mindfulness for Recurrent Pregnancy Loss</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Henriette Svarre Nielsen, MD, DMSc</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Rigshospitalet, Denmark</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      In the Danish Recurrent Pregnancy Loss Unit in Rigshospitalet in Copenhagen recurrent
      pregnancy loss (RPL) is defined as three og more consecutive pregnancy losses in accordance
      with current European guidelines.

      RPL affects approximately 3% of couples trying to achieve parenthood. Most cases of RPL are
      unexplained and have no effective treatment to improve the chance of a live birth.

      42% of the women referred to RPL Unit in Rigshospitalet has a high stress level where as it's
      22% in the background population trying to achieve parenthood. It's also known that 8,8 % of
      RPL patients have a depression at referral where as it's 2,2 % in the background population
      trying to achieve parenthood.

      The study is a RCT including 62 patients - 31 in each arm. One arm will be taught in
      meditation and mindfulness three courses over a 7 week period. This group will also do
      meditation every day for 7 weeks. The other arm will have no intervention.

      This study will investigate if a 7 weeks course in meditation and mindfulness is a useful
      tool to reduce stress and the psychological consequences for women and their partner treated
      in RPL Unit in Rigshospitalet, Copenhagen. Furthermore this study will investigate if there's
      a marital benefit such as reinforcement in their relationsship from practicing meditation and
      mindfulness.

      There is no previous study that has investigated meditation and mindfulness for RPL.

      This study has the potential to establish mental health support as a supplement to the
      medical and clinical treatment for RPL patients.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The loss of a desired pregnancy is a significant negative life event associated with grief
      comparable to the grief after a peri- or neonatal death. Recurrent pregnancy loss (RPL)
      defined as 3 or more pregnancy losses affects approximately 3% of couples trying to have
      children. Most cases of RPL are unexplained and have no effective treatment to improve the
      chance of a live birth.

      42% of the women referred to RPL Unit in Rigshospitalet has a high stress level where as it's
      22% in the background population trying to achieve parenthood. It's also known that 8,8% of
      RPL patients have a depression at referral where as it's 2,2 % in the background population
      trying to achieve parenthood.

      This study will investigate if a 7 weeks course in meditation and mindfulness is a useful
      tool to reduce stress and the psychological consequences for women and their partner treated
      in RPL Unit in Rigshospitalet, Copenhagen.

      Furthermore this study will investigate if there's a marital benefit from practicing
      meditation and mindfulness. The investigators will use four different scales to measure the
      participants stress, depression, marital benefit and fertility stress. Also the investigators
      will measure the participants before and after the intervention and 12 months after.

      All participants will have to complete:

        1. Major Depression Index, a validated self-rating depression scale, which is used both
           clinically and in epidemiological studie. The 6-point Likert scale ranges from 0 (no
           depression) to 50 (extreme depression).

        2. Perceived Stress Scale, which is a validated 10-item-self-reporting scale for stress
           symptoms. The 5 point Likert scale ranges from 0 (no stress) to 40 (extreme stress).

        3. The COMPI Fertility Problem Stress Scale, a validated scale measuring the impact of RPL
           on the woman and her interpersonal relationships.

        4. The COMPI Marital Benefit Scale measuring if RPL has reinforced the couples
           mariage/relationship.

      The investigators assume that meditation and mindfulness can improve the quality of life for
      the RPL patients and their coping strategies. It's the investigators purpose to contribute
      with new knowledge in this area for current and future patients.

      The RPL Unit in Rigshospitalet doesn't have any psychological support apart from ordinary
      attention from the nurses. This study has the potential to establish mental health support as
      a supplement to the medical and clinical treatment for RPL patients, which is in high demand.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 2, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>A randomized trial where women in an experimental arm will receive 3 times a three hour work shop with introduction to meditation and mindfulness during a 7 week period. Women in the other arm will have no intervention.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Perceived Stress Scale (PSS)</measure>
    <time_frame>7 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Change from baseline to 7 weeks after date of first course day measured by Perceived Stress Scale. PSS is a validated 10-item-self-reporting scale for stress symptoms. The 5 point Likert scale ranges from 0 (no stress) to 40 (extreme stress). The higher score the more stress.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Perceived Stress Scale (PSS)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Change from baseline to 12 months after date of first course day measured by the Perceived Stress Scale. PSS is a validated 10-item-self-reporting scale for stress symptoms. The 5 point Likert scale ranges from 0 (no stress) to 40 (extreme stress). The higher score the more stress.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>COMPI Fertility Problem Stress Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>7 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Change from baseline to 7 weeks after date of first course day using the COMPI Fertility Problem Stress Scale.
The COMPI Fertility Problem Stress Scale is a validated scale measuring the impact of RPL on the woman and her interpersonal relationships. Two questions asking if the experience of RPL has been stressful for the woman with five answering options. Followed by seven sub questions asking how big a load RPL has been for the patients interpersonal life with four answering options. The lower the score the higher stress.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Marital Benefit Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>7 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Change in marital benefit from baseline to 7 weeks after date of first course day using the COMPI Marital Benefit Scale.
The COMPI Marital Benefit Scale has two questions asking what the RPL have mattered for their relationship/mariage:
Five options to answer: totally disagree, partly disagree, neither agree or disagree, partly agree, totally agree. Answering &quot;Totally agree&quot; on both questions is defined as a high marital benefit.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>COMPI Fertility Problem Stress Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Change in fertility problem stress from baseline to 12 months after date of first course day using the COMPI Fertility Problem Stress Scale.
The COMPI Fertility Problem Stress Scale is a validated scale measuring the impact of RPL on the woman and her interpersonal relationships. Two questions used to assess how big a impact RPL has for the patient with five answering options. Followed by seven sub questions asking how big a load RPL has been for the patients interpersonal life with four answering options. The lower the score the higher stress.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Marital Benefit</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Change in marital benefit from baseline to 12 months after date of first course day using the COMPI Marital Benefit Scale.
The COMPI Marital Benefit Scale has two questions asking what the RPL have mattered for their relationship/mariage:
Five options to answer: totally disagree, partly disagree, neither agree or disagree, partly agree, totally agree. Answering &quot;Totally agree&quot; on both questions is defined as a high marital benefit.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Major Depression Index (MDI)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Change in depression score from baseline to 12 months after date of first course day. Major Depression Index is a validated self-rating depression scale, which is used both clinically and in epidemiological studie. The 6-point Likert scale ranges from 0 (no depression) to 50 (extreme depression).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">64</enrollment>
  <condition>Recurrent Pregnancy Loss</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Meditation and mindfulness intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Women in the intervention arm will 3 times receive a three hours work shop with introduction to meditation and mindfulness over a 7 week period from a certified meditation instructor. Questionnaires before and after the intervention.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Women in the no intervention arm will receive no introduction to meditation and mindfulness - only questionnaires at the same time as the intervention group receives questionnaires.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Meditation and mindfulness</intervention_name>
    <description>Women in the intervention arm will 3 times receive a three hours work shop with introduction to meditation and mindfulness over a 7 week period from a certified meditation instructor. Questionnaires before and after the intervention.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Meditation and mindfulness intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Women with RPL

          -  Speaking, reading and understanding Danish

          -  Have given a written consent

          -  Have a male partner

          -  Have a stress score &gt; 16 points on Perceived Stress Scale

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  If the patient is pregnant on inclusion day

          -  If the patient already is practing meditation and mindfulness

          -  If the patient has a depression

          -  If the patient develops a depression after inclusion in either arm
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <gender_based>Yes</gender_based>
    <gender_description>Based on biological sex</gender_description>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>46 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Karen Kirchheiner Jensen, Nurse</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Rigshospitalet, Denmark</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Henriette Svarre Nielsen, MD, DMSc</last_name>
    <phone>+4535458486</phone>
    <email>Henriette.Svarre.Nielsen@regionh.dk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Karen Henriette Kirchheiner Jensen, Nurse</last_name>
    <phone>+4535458486</phone>
    <email>Karen.Henriette.jensen@regionh.dk</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Rigshospitalet</name>
      <address>
        <city>Copenhagen</city>
        <state>Østerbro</state>
        <zip>2100</zip>
        <country>Denmark</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Henriette Svarre Nielsen, MD. MDSc</last_name>
      <phone>+4535458486</phone>
      <email>Henriette.Svarre.Nielsen@regionh.dk</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Karen Kirchheiner Jensen, Nurse</last_name>
      <phone>+4535458486</phone>
      <email>Karen.Henriette.Jensen@regionh.dk</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Denmark</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>April 2, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 4, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 5, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 4, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 4, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 5, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Rigshospitalet, Denmark</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Henriette Svarre Nielsen, MD, DMSc</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Henriette Svarre Nielsen, MD, DMSc, Consultant, Head of Recurrent Pregnancy Loss Unit, Associate Professor, Rigshospitalet, Denmark</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Meditation</keyword>
  <keyword>mindfulness</keyword>
  <keyword>pregnancy loss</keyword>
  <keyword>stress</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Abortion, Spontaneous</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fetal Death</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Abortion, Habitual</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

