<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03907033</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>15-008413</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03907033</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Liposomal Bupivacaine in Vaginal Hysterectomy</brief_title>
  <official_title>Preemptive Local Analgesia With Liposomal Bupivacaine in Vaginal Hysterectomy: A Randomized Controlled Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Mayo Clinic</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Pacira Pharmaceuticals, Inc</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Mayo Clinic</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The aim of this study is to compare the effects of preemptive analgesia using liposomal
      bupivacaine mixed with bupivacaine HCl, versus bupivacaine HCl alone for uterosacral ligament
      injection in patients undergoing vaginal hysterectomy. We hypothesize that the group
      receiving a combination of liposomal bupivacaine and bupivacaine HCl will report superior
      postoperative pain management. Enhancement in pain control should confer a decrease in opioid
      and other analgesic medication requirements, which may contribute to decreased nausea,
      vomiting, and higher overall patient satisfaction with pain control.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Prior to surgery, patients are assigned by chance (like a coin toss) to receive either the
      bupivacaine HCl injection at the time of surgery or bupivacaine HCl plus liposomal
      bupivacaine. Patients and the Principal Investigator cannot choose the study group. Patients
      will have a 50% chance of being assigned to either group; however, regardless of which group
      they are assigned to, the medical record will show that they received liposomal bupivacaine.
      The injections will be given in the vaginal area when the patient is under anesthesia.

      After surgery, patients will be asked to record their pain, medication use, pain scores and
      symptoms in a diary for each 12 hour interval up to 72 hours. Someone will also call twice a
      day during the 72 hours after surgery to ask about pain level and pain medication use.

      Patients will also receive a phone call 7-10 days after the surgery to ask about their
      recovery and pain level.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 3, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Patients will be randomized to receive either the bupivacaine HCl injection at the time of surgery or bupivacaine HCl plus liposomal bupivacaine.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator)</masking>
    <masking_description>This will be a blinded study where investigators, patients, and care providers will be blinded to treatment assignment.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Comparison of total post-surgical analgesic medication use</measure>
    <time_frame>First 72 hours following surgery completion</time_frame>
    <description>All opioids in IV morphine equivalents and total mg use of ibuprofen and/or acetaminophen combined</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean PACU Visual Analog Scale (VAS) (0-10) pain score</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed while patient in PACU for recovery post-surgery per standard procedure</time_frame>
    <description>Scale Ranges from 0 (no pain) to 10 (extreme pain)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>VAS pain score at 24, 48, and 72 hours post-surgery completion</measure>
    <time_frame>24, 48, and 72 hours post-surgery completion</time_frame>
    <description>Scale Ranges from 0 (no pain) to 10 (extreme pain)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Nausea and emesis at 24, 48, and 72 hours post-surgery completion</measure>
    <time_frame>24, 28, and 72 hours post-surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Assessed via patient diary by number of times patient reported feeling nauseous, number of times vomited, and number of times anti-nausea medications were used</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Urinary retention</measure>
    <time_frame>At voiding trial prior to discharge from hospital</time_frame>
    <description>Number of patients who had post-void residual (PVR) &gt;150cc's at voiding trial prior to discharge</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient satisfaction with pain management at 72 hours and 7-10 days post surgery</measure>
    <time_frame>72 hours and 7-10 days post surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Assessed on 0-10 scale (0 being worst level of satisfaction, 10 being best level)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">116</enrollment>
  <condition>Vaginal Hysterectomy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Standard Bupivacaine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients in the control group will receive 0.25% bupivacaine hydrochloride (bupivacaine HCl). 10cc will be injected bilaterally into each uterosacral ligament prior to the colpotomy incision. After entry into the posterior cul-de-sac, an additional 10cc of will be injected bilaterally into the deeper uterosacral ligaments.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Liposomal Bupivacaine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients in the study group will receive a mixture of 0.5% bupivacaine HCl and liposomal bupivacaine in 1:1 ratio. 10cc of the mixture will be injected bilaterally into each uterosacral ligament prior to the colpotomy incision. After entry into the posterior cul-de-sac, an additional 10cc will be injected bilaterally into the deeper uterosacral ligaments</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Liposomal bupivacaine</intervention_name>
    <description>Liposomal bupivacaine is a novel formulation of local bupivacaine and allows prolonged release of the medication, thereby providing longer lasting effects. It is approved by the FDA and has been shown to provide excellent pain control after surgery.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Liposomal Bupivacaine</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Exparel</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Bupivacaine Hydrochloride</intervention_name>
    <description>We currently administer local plain bupivacaine during vaginal hysterectomy to decrease pain in the postoperative period. Bupivacaine is an anesthetic that works by blocking nerve conduction and producing a numbing effect.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Liposomal Bupivacaine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Standard Bupivacaine</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        INCLUSION CRITERIA

        1. Women 18-85 who will be having an outpatient vaginal hysterectomy with or without
        concurrent prolapse repair surgery at Mayo Clinic Hospital in Arizona

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA

          1. Known history of hepatic (liver) disease as evidenced by an AST or ALT that is greater
             than normal values

          2. Known history of renal (kidney) disease as evidenced by a serum creatinine that is
             greater than normal values

          3. Known history of prolonged QT (QTc greater than 500 m/s)

          4. Opiate tolerance as noted by daily use of greater than 20 mg morphine daily oral
             equivalents per day for a minimum of 1 month prior to surgery

          5. Allergy or contraindication to amide local anesthetics, celecoxib, ketorolac, NSAIDs,
             acetaminophen, gabapentin, sulfa drugs, or ondansetron

          6. Allergy to both oxycodone and hydromorphone

          7. Patients with acute gastrointestinal bleed that has occurred less than 6 months prior
             to study enrollment

          8. Adults lacking the ability to consent
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>85 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jeffrey L Cornella</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Mayo Clinic</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mayo Clinic in Arizona</name>
      <address>
        <city>Phoenix</city>
        <state>Arizona</state>
        <zip>85054</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Debra L Ryan, CCRP</last_name>
      <phone>480-342-1208</phone>
      <email>ryan.debra29@mayo.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Vy L Nguyen, CCRP</last_name>
      <phone>480-342-1328</phone>
      <email>nguyen.vy@mayo.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://www.mayo.edu/research/clinical-trials</url>
    <description>Mayo Clinic Clinical Trials</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Long JB, Eiland RJ, Hentz JG, Mergens PA, Magtibay PM, Kho RM, Magrina JF, Cornella JL. Randomized trial of preemptive local analgesia in vaginal surgery. Int Urogynecol J Pelvic Floor Dysfunct. 2009 Jan;20(1):5-10. doi: 10.1007/s00192-008-0716-6. Epub 2008 Oct 2.</citation>
    <PMID>18830553</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ilfeld BM, Viscusi ER, Hadzic A, Minkowitz HS, Morren MD, Lookabaugh J, Joshi GP. Safety and Side Effect Profile of Liposome Bupivacaine (Exparel) in Peripheral Nerve Blocks. Reg Anesth Pain Med. 2015 Sep-Oct;40(5):572-82. doi: 10.1097/AAP.0000000000000283.</citation>
    <PMID>26204387</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bergese SD, Ramamoorthy S, Patou G, Bramlett K, Gorfine SR, Candiotti KA. Efficacy profile of liposome bupivacaine, a novel formulation of bupivacaine for postsurgical analgesia. J Pain Res. 2012;5:107-16. doi: 10.2147/JPR.S30861. Epub 2012 May 1.</citation>
    <PMID>22570563</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hutchins J, Delaney D, Vogel RI, Ghebre RG, Downs LS Jr, Carson L, Mullany S, Teoh D, Geller MA. Ultrasound guided subcostal transversus abdominis plane (TAP) infiltration with liposomal bupivacaine for patients undergoing robotic assisted hysterectomy: A prospective randomized controlled study. Gynecol Oncol. 2015 Sep;138(3):609-13. doi: 10.1016/j.ygyno.2015.06.008. Epub 2015 Jun 6.</citation>
    <PMID>26056753</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mont MA, Beaver WB, Dysart SH, Barrington JW, Del Gaizo DJ. Local Infiltration Analgesia With Liposomal Bupivacaine Improves Pain Scores and Reduces Opioid Use After Total Knee Arthroplasty: Results of a Randomized Controlled Trial. J Arthroplasty. 2018 Jan;33(1):90-96. doi: 10.1016/j.arth.2017.07.024. Epub 2017 Jul 25. Erratum in: J Arthroplasty. 2019 Feb;34(2):399-400.</citation>
    <PMID>28802777</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kalogera E, Bakkum-Gamez JN, Jankowski CJ, Trabuco E, Lovely JK, Dhanorker S, Grubbs PL, Weaver AL, Haas LR, Borah BJ, Bursiek AA, Walsh MT, Cliby WA, Dowdy SC. Enhanced recovery in gynecologic surgery. Obstet Gynecol. 2013 Aug;122(2 Pt 1):319-28. doi: 10.1097/AOG.0b013e31829aa780.</citation>
    <PMID>23969801</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>April 5, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 5, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 8, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 15, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 15, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 17, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Mayo Clinic</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Jeffrey L. Cornella</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor of Obstetrics and Gynecology</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Bupivacaine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

