<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03902717</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>18.47/ANESTH18.04</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03902717</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Patient-centered and Clinical Outcomes After Minimally Invasive Cardiothoracic Surgery</brief_title>
  <official_title>An Observational Cohort Study to Investigate Patient-centered and Clinical Outcomes After Minimally Invasive Cardiothoracic Surgery</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Jessa Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Jessa Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Nowadays, minimally invasive cardiothoracic surgery techniques are being performed to treat
      patients with coronary heart diseases. These newly developed procedures include laparoscopic
      techniques that do not require median sternotomy, which has several beneficial effects for
      both patient and the hospital. Although retrospective data show promising results with
      respect to clinical outcomes (e.g. 30-day mortality rate, intensive care unit length of
      stay), no prospective data with respect to patient centered outcomes (e.g. quality of
      recovery, quality of life) are available yet. Therefore, the aim of this observational
      prospective study is to explore several patient centered and clinical outcomes of patients
      that are treated with these newly developed minimally invasive cardiac procedures. The
      comparative group consists of patients undergoing open CABG (invasive) and patients
      undergoing a Transcatheter Aortic Valve Implantation (TAVI).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Introduction:

      Coronary artery disease is a leading cause of adult mortality worldwide. One of the most
      commonly performed surgical interventions to treat this vascular disease is a myocardial
      revascularization, mostly performed via a Coronary Artery Bypass Graft (CABG) (1). Over time,
      new developments in cardiac surgery have led to the introduction of less invasive and
      minimally invasive cardiac procedures (2). These minimally invasive cardiac procedures are
      proven to be safe and feasible (3) and have excellent outcomes (4) (5) (6). More
      specifically, the short term outcomes include a reduced patient recovery time (5), lower
      transfusion rates, wound infections, hospitalization time and hospital mortality rate (4),
      while the long term outcomes comprise a better vessel graft patency (7) (8). Over the past
      few years, new minimally invasive cardiothoracic surgery techniques have been developed and
      are currently being implemented at the department of cardiothoracic surgery from the Jessa
      Hospital (e.g. endo-CABG, VATS Mitral, hybrid revascularization, Yil AVR). These newly
      developed procedures include laparoscopic techniques that do not require median sternotomy,
      which has several beneficial effects for both patient and the hospital. Also, these
      techniques allow a coronary revascularization or mitral valve repair or replacement without
      the use of expensive robotic equipment and exclusion of specific patients based on
      comorbidities (e.g. elderly patients, diabetic and/or obese patients). Currently, patients
      undergo cardiothoracic surgery via these techniques and although retrospective data from our
      hospital show promising results with respect to clinical outcomes (e.g. 30-day mortality
      rate, intensive care unit length of stay), no prospective data with respect to patient
      centered outcomes (e.g. quality of recovery, quality of life) are available yet. Therefore,
      the aim of this study is to explore several patient centered and clinical outcomes of
      patients that are treated with these newly developed minimally invasive cardiac
      procedures.The comparative group consists of patients undergoing open CABG (invasive) and
      patients undergoing a Transcatheter Aortic Valve Implantation (TAVI).

      Outcome measures:

      The goal of this study is to assess several patient central outcomes (e.g. quality of
      recovery measured with quality of life) and clinical outcomes (e.g. mortality rate, serious
      complications, major cardiac events, time registration in icu and hospital, duration of
      surgery, occlusion and perfusion time, surgical parameters, revalidation of the patients)
      after minimally invasive cardiothoracic surgery.

      Design:

      This study is a single-center prospective observational cohort study in which eligible
      patients that are treated via minimally invasive cardiac surgery will be included. Inclusion
      will last for 1 year and patients will be followed-up for 12 months.

      Study Procedures:

      After signing the informed consent form, the baseline tests will be performed the day before
      the surgery. On the day of the surgery, several surgical parameters will be measured as well
      as several parameters that are included in the standard clinical practice. 2 weeks, 1 month,
      3 months and 1 year after the surgery, the QoL will be measured. Patient satisfaction will be
      assessed 3 months after surgery.

      Statistical analysis:

      Descriptive statistics will be presented as frequencies and percentages of the total amount
      of patients for categorical variables, while numerical variables will be presented as mean
      with variances. Results of the different questionnaires will be calculated according to their
      specific guidelines. The clinical significance of the questionnaires will be calculated via
      an effect size. A p-value &lt;0.05 is considered statistical significant, while p&lt;0.10 is
      considered a tendency.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 25, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of Recovery</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Quality of Recovery will be assessed via 2 questionnaires: the SF-36 and EQ-5D questionnaire concerning mobility, selfcare, daily activities and pain</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of Recovery</measure>
    <time_frame>2 weeks after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Quality of Recovery will be assessed via 2 questionnaires: the SF-36 and EQ-5D questionnaire concerning mobility, selfcare, daily activities and pain</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of Recovery</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Quality of Recovery will be assessed via 2 questionnaires: the SF-36 and EQ-5D questionnaire concerning mobility, selfcare, daily activities and pain</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of Recovery</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Quality of Recovery will be assessed via 2 questionnaires: the SF-36 and EQ-5D questionnaire concerning mobility, selfcare, daily activities and pain</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Routine measurements of standard medical practice</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Routine measurements during and after surgery (e.g. amount of blood loss, time of ventilation, time of perfusion, hematology/blood chemistry, registration of mortality rates and complications after surgery, length of stay at the ICU department after surgery, length of stay in the hospital)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient satisfaction with respect to surgery</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Patient satisfaction after surgery (assessed via the 7-point likert scale, with 1 being completely dissatisfied and 7 completely satisfied)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Physical recovery of patients after surgery</measure>
    <time_frame>2 weeks after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>A maximal exercise test will be performed after surgery to asses revalidation of the patients</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Physical recovery of patients after surgery</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>A maximal exercise test will be performed after surgery to asses revalidation of the patients</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Physical recovery of patients after surgery</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>A maximal exercise test will be performed after surgery to asses revalidation of the patients</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Physical recovery of patients after surgery</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>A maximal exercise test will be performed after surgery to asses revalidation of the patients</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">250</enrollment>
  <condition>Cardiac Disease</condition>
  <condition>Surgery</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>minimally invasive cardiac surgery</arm_group_label>
    <description>Group of patients that will undergo minimally invasive cardiac surgery</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Minimally invasive cardiac surgery</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients will undergo minimally invasive cardiac surgery</description>
    <arm_group_label>minimally invasive cardiac surgery</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        All patients that are scheduled to undergo minimally invasive cardiac surgery, open CABG or
        TAVI
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Males and females ≥ 18 years of age

          -  Patients planned to undergo minimally invasive cardiac surgery by the following
             techniques:

               -  Endo-CABG

               -  Hybrid approach

               -  VATS Mitral

               -  Mini AVR

               -  Yil AVR or open CABG or TAVI

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients &lt; 18 years old

          -  Patients that are not eligible to undergo minimally invasive cardiac surgery

          -  Patients that participate in other clinical, pharmaceutical or medical devices trials

          -  Patients that previously had a minimally invasive cardiac surgery and are now
             scheduled for a revision

          -  Patients that need a conversion to sternotomy or other non-minimally invasive
             technique

          -  Inability to understand and adhere to the study design
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Björn Stessel, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Jessa hospital, Hasselt</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Björn Stessel, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+32 11 339 856</phone>
    <email>bjorn.stessel@jessazh.be</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Jessa Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hasselt</city>
        <state>Limburg</state>
        <zip>3500</zip>
        <country>Belgium</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Björn Stessel, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>+32 11 339 856</phone>
      <email>Bjorn.stessel@jessazh.be</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of Anesthesiology and Intensive Care</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hasselt</city>
        <zip>3500</zip>
        <country>Belgium</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Bjorn Stessel, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <email>bjorn.stessel@jessazh.be</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Ina Callebaut, PhD</last_name>
      <email>ina.callebaut@jessazh.be</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Belgium</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ezelsoy M, Caynak B, Bayram M, Oral K, Bayramoglu Z, Sagbas E, Aytekın V, Akpınar B. The Comparison between Minimally Invasive Coronary Bypass Grafting Surgery and Conventional Bypass Grafting Surgery in Proximal LAD Lesion. Heart Surg Forum. 2015 Apr 28;18(2):E042-6. doi: 10.1532/hsf.1239.</citation>
    <PMID>25924029</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Diodato M, Chedrawy EG. Coronary artery bypass graft surgery: the past, present, and future of myocardial revascularisation. Surg Res Pract. 2014;2014:726158. doi: 10.1155/2014/726158. Epub 2014 Jan 2. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25374960</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ruel M, Shariff MA, Lapierre H, Goyal N, Dennie C, Sadel SM, Sohmer B, McGinn JT Jr. Results of the Minimally Invasive Coronary Artery Bypass Grafting Angiographic Patency Study. J Thorac Cardiovasc Surg. 2014 Jan;147(1):203-8. doi: 10.1016/j.jtcvs.2013.09.016. Epub 2013 Oct 30.</citation>
    <PMID>24183338</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lapierre H, Chan V, Sohmer B, Mesana TG, Ruel M. Minimally invasive coronary artery bypass grafting via a small thoracotomy versus off-pump: a case-matched study. Eur J Cardiothorac Surg. 2011 Oct;40(4):804-10. doi: 10.1016/j.ejcts.2011.01.066. Epub 2011 Mar 9.</citation>
    <PMID>21393011</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Poston RS, Tran R, Collins M, Reynolds M, Connerney I, Reicher B, Zimrin D, Griffith BP, Bartlett ST. Comparison of economic and patient outcomes with minimally invasive versus traditional off-pump coronary artery bypass grafting techniques. Ann Surg. 2008 Oct;248(4):638-46. doi: 10.1097/SLA.0b013e31818a15b5.</citation>
    <PMID>18936577</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>McGinn JT Jr, Usman S, Lapierre H, Pothula VR, Mesana TG, Ruel M. Minimally invasive coronary artery bypass grafting: dual-center experience in 450 consecutive patients. Circulation. 2009 Sep 15;120(11 Suppl):S78-84. doi: 10.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.108.840041.</citation>
    <PMID>19752390</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Biglioli P, Antona C, Alamanni F, Parolari A, Toscano T, Pompilio G, Polvani G. Minimally invasive direct coronary artery bypass grafting: midterm results and quality of life. Ann Thorac Surg. 2000 Aug;70(2):456-60.</citation>
    <PMID>10969662</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 28, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 3, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 4, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 2, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 2, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 3, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Jessa Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Stessel Björn</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator, Anesthesiologist, MD, PhD</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Minimally invasive cardiac surgery</keyword>
  <keyword>Endoscopic coronary artery bypass grafting</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Heart Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

