<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03902678</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MD /17.06.69</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03902678</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Role of EUS Guided FNA of Portal Vein Thrombus in the Diagnosis and Staging of Hepatocellular Carcinoma</brief_title>
  <official_title>Role of Endoscopic Ultrasound Guided Fine Needle Aspiration of Portal Vein Thrombus in the Diagnosis and Staging of Hepatocellular Carcinoma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Mansoura University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Mansoura University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Since not every portal vein thrombus (PVT) in a patient with hepatocellular carcinoma (HCC)
      is a tumor thrombus, since the nature of the thrombus will ultimately determine the course of
      treatment, and since PVT may be even the initial sign of an undetected HCC, every effort
      should be made to distinguish between a tumor and a non-tumor PVT. In addition, malignant PVT
      does not always demonstrate neovascularity and/or enhancement, which makes fine needle
      aspiration (FNA) necessary in order to characterize the nature of the PVT.

      Sampling of portal vein thrombus with trans-abdominal ultrasound guidance may lead to
      erroneous results because of inadvertent inclusion of normal hepatocytes or associated liver
      masses. Further, potential adverse events of trans-abdominal portal vein sampling include
      serious biliary and/or vascular injury.

      In contrast to the percutaneous approach, Endoscopic ultrasound (EUS) provides a unique view
      and access to the main portal vein. From the duodenal bulb and second part of the duodenum,
      the portal vein can be visualized from the confluence of the splenic and superior mesenteric
      veins into the porta hepatis. Periportal collateral vessels or cavernous transformation of
      the portal vein, which commonly are associated with portal vein thrombosis, are also easily
      and reliably detected by EUS instruments with color Doppler US capability.

      With a linear-array echo-endoscope, the portal vein can be punctured easily with a fine
      needle under direct visualization, while avoiding the adjacent hepatic artery, bile duct, and
      collateral vessels (if present). Because the approach is not trans-hepatic, it eliminates any
      need to avoid the primary tumor and any possibility of contaminating the specimen with
      hepatocytes, as can occur if the needle tracks through the liver parenchyma. Thus, the rate
      of false-positive diagnoses is likely to be lower with the EUS compared with the percutaneous
      approach
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a pilot study that include 30 patients with liver cirrhosis and portal vein thrombus
      which don't fulfill the criteria of malignancy by imaging technique. The patients involved in
      the study were and will be admitted to Specialized Medical Hospital, Mansoura University
      Hospitals.

      Study end-points:

      • 24 months from the start of the research (cases will be collected over 18 months).

      Methods:

      Patients will be included in this study will be subjected to the following:

      І. The study will be explained to all participants in the study, and an informed written
      consent will be obtained from them before starting the study.

      ІІ. Medical history:

      Detailed history was taken with stress on:

        -  Signs of cachexia (unintentional weight loss, progressive muscle wasting, and a loss of
           appetite)

        -  Low grade fever

        -  Recent onset fatigue

        -  Abdominal pain

        -  Dyspepsia

        -  Hematemesis and melena

        -  Back ache

      ІІІ. Full clinical examination with special stress on:

        -  Vital signs including: pulse, arterial blood pressure, temperature, respiratory rate.

        -  Abdominal Lumps and/or tenderness

      IV. Laboratory investigations:

      Complete blood count, International Normalized Ratio, Liver enzymes, Serum albumin, Serum
      bilirubin and Serum creatinine.

      V. Radiology: Abdominal ultrasound for initial assessment, Abdominal CT (Contrast Enhanced)
      (Number of HCC nodules if present, diameter of largest HCC nodule in centimeters, nature of
      PVT, presence of abdominal metastases if present ), Non contrast CT chest to exclude
      pulmonary metastasis, Bone survey for indicated or complaining cases.

      VI. EUS-FNA:

      EUS-FNA will be performed in standard fashion. Under EUS guidance, the main, left and right
      portal veins will be identified. After verifying flow signal by Doppler, a 25-gauge EUS-FNA
      needle will be advanced from the duodenal bulb or second part of the duodenum into the portal
      vein, 1-2 passes through portal vein thrombus will be taken to ensure adequate cellularity
      for histopathology. The puncture site will be monitored under EUS for complications.

      Study outcomes:

      Histopathology of biopsies taken from bland portal vein thrombus which diagnosed by triphasic
      CT abdomen to evaluate the possibility of malignant PVT that was not discovered by imaging
      technique (Abdominal ultrasound and triphasic abdominal CT ).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 11, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 11, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 11, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Use of histopathology obtained from endoscopic ultrasound -fine needle aspiration of portal vein thrombus for identification of malignant thrombus which did not fulfill criteria of malignancy by abdominal ultrasound and triphasic abdominal CT</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of patients with bland portal vein thrombosis diagnosed by triphasic abdominal CT who are proven to have malignant cells by histopathology obtained via EUS-guided FNA</measure>
    <time_frame>3 days up to 2 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Histopathology of biopsies taken from bland portal vein thrombus which diagnosed by triphasic CT abdomen to evaluate the possibility of malignant PVT that was not discovered by imaging technique (Abdominal ultrasound and triphasic abdominal CT )</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of patients with portal vein thrombosis who underwent EUS guided FNA and had complications as a result of the invasive maneuver</measure>
    <time_frame>2 days</time_frame>
    <description>assessment of safety of the procedure ( The patients admitted and the new ones will be admitted to specialized medical hospital for 24 h after the procedure to exclude the possibility of bleeding at puncture site, risk of biliary peritonitis, and extravasation from the site of the thrombus.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Portal Vein Thrombosis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>EUS - FNA for benign PVT by imaging</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Intervention: Procedure/Surgery: EUS guided fine needle aspiration of portal vein thrombus</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>EUS guided fine needle aspiration of portal vein thrombus</intervention_name>
    <description>endoscopic ultrasound guided fine needle aspiration of portal vein thrombus which did not fulfill criteria of malignancy by imaging technique</description>
    <arm_group_label>EUS - FNA for benign PVT by imaging</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with liver cirrhosis and PVT which don't fulfill criteria of malignancy by
             triphasic CT abdomen defined as, (neovascularity of thrombus, arterial enhancement
             with rapid washout, direct invasion by adjacent hepatic mass and diameter of thrombus
             more than 23 mm), either :

          -  With or without hepatic mass

          -  Undergone local treatment or surgical treatment following a diagnosis of HCC and
             develop PVT during their follow up.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Uncooperative or excessively apprehensive patient

          -  Anticoagulation treatment or non-substituted coagulopathy (International Normalized
             Ratio ≥ 1.5, Platelet count ≤ 50.000 cells/mm3, heparin administration at therapeutic
             doses).

          -  Inhibition of platelet aggregation by clopidogrel and other thienopyridines.

          -  Contraindications of sedation (Uncontrolled Diabetes Mellitus, Uncontrolled Thyroid
             Disorders, Pregnancy, Respiratory Embarrassment, Reactional Drugs like Antidepressants
             and Anti-anxiety Agents).

          -  Patients fulfilling criteria of malignancy by triphasic CT on abdomen.

          -  Extra hepatic metastasis of HCC.

          -  Child-Pugh classification stage C.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Magdy H. Atwa, Professor</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Faculty of Medicine, Mansoura University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Dina S. Eskandere</last_name>
    <phone>01148979995</phone>
    <email>dinaeskandere@mans.edu.eg</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Ahmad Y. Altonbary, MD</last_name>
    <phone>01005100091</phone>
    <email>Altonbary@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>specialized medical hospital, Mansourah University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Mansourah</city>
        <state>Dakahlia</state>
        <zip>35516</zip>
        <country>Egypt</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>dina S. eskandere, Master</last_name>
      <phone>01148979995</phone>
      <email>dinaeskandere@mans.edu.eg</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Dina S. Eskandere, Master</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ahmad Y. Altonbary, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Hazem H. ElBeltagy, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Magdy H. Atwa, Professor</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Egypt</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.pulmonarychronicles.com/index.php/pulmonarychronicles/article/view/496</url>
    <description>paper proved that benign portal vein thrombus by triphasic CT may be truly malignant by the histopathology but the researchers here used different inclusion and exclusion criteria. They obtained samples from cirrhotic patients only</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>https://www.ajol.info/index.php/pamj/article/view/134058</url>
    <description>case study proved that benign portal vein thrombus by radiology is truly malignant by histopathology</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Catalano OA, Choy G, Zhu A, Hahn PF, Sahani DV. Differentiation of malignant thrombus from bland thrombus of the portal vein in patients with hepatocellular carcinoma: application of diffusion-weighted MR imaging. Radiology. 2010 Jan;254(1):154-62. doi: 10.1148/radiol.09090304.</citation>
    <PMID>20032150</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Handa P, Crowther M, Douketis JD. Portal vein thrombosis: a clinician-oriented and practical review. Clin Appl Thromb Hemost. 2014 Jul;20(5):498-506. doi: 10.1177/1076029612473515. Epub 2013 Jan 29. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23364162</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lai R, Stephens V, Bardales R. Diagnosis and staging of hepatocellular carcinoma by EUS-FNA of a portal vein thrombus. Gastrointest Endosc. 2004 Apr;59(4):574-7.</citation>
    <PMID>15044903</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tarantino L, Ambrosino P, Di Minno MN. Contrast-enhanced ultrasound in differentiating malignant from benign portal vein thrombosis in hepatocellular carcinoma. World J Gastroenterol. 2015 Aug 28;21(32):9457-60. doi: 10.3748/wjg.v21.i32.9457. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26327753</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>ASGE Technology Committee, Trikudanathan G, Pannala R, Bhutani MS, Melson J, Navaneethan U, Parsi MA, Thosani N, Trindade AJ, Watson RR, Maple JT. EUS-guided portal vein interventions. Gastrointest Endosc. 2017 May;85(5):883-888. doi: 10.1016/j.gie.2017.02.019. Epub 2017 Mar 18. Review. Erratum in: Gastrointest Endosc. 2017 Jun;85(6):1312.</citation>
    <PMID>28320514</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Viechtbauer W, Smits L, Kotz D, Budé L, Spigt M, Serroyen J, Crutzen R. A simple formula for the calculation of sample size in pilot studies. J Clin Epidemiol. 2015 Nov;68(11):1375-9. doi: 10.1016/j.jclinepi.2015.04.014. Epub 2015 Jun 6.</citation>
    <PMID>26146089</PMID>
  </reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Kayar Y, Turkdogan KA, Baysal B, Unver N, Danalioglu A, Senturk H. EUS-guided FNA of a portal vein thrombus in hepatocellular carcinoma. Pan Afr Med J. 2015 Jun 3;21:86. doi: 10.11604/pamj.2015.21.86.6991. eCollection 2015.</citation>
    <PMID>26491529</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Michael H, Lenza C, Gupta M, Katz DS. Endoscopic Ultrasound -guided Fine-Needle Aspiration of a Portal Vein Thrombus to Aid in the Diagnosis and Staging of Hepatocellular Carcinoma. Gastroenterol Hepatol (N Y). 2011 Feb;7(2):124-9.</citation>
    <PMID>21475421</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Rustagi T, Gleeson FC, Chari ST, Abu Dayyeh BK, Farnell MB, Iyer PG, Kendrick ML, Pearson RK, Petersen BT, Rajan E, Topazian MD, Truty MJ, Vege SS, Wang KK, Levy MJ. Remote malignant intravascular thrombi: EUS-guided FNA diagnosis and impact on cancer staging. Gastrointest Endosc. 2017 Jul;86(1):150-155. doi: 10.1016/j.gie.2016.10.025. Epub 2016 Oct 20.</citation>
    <PMID>27773725</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>April 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 26, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 2, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 4, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 2, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 2, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 4, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>EUS</keyword>
  <keyword>FNA</keyword>
  <keyword>PVT</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Hepatocellular</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Thrombosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <provided_document_section>
    <provided_document>
      <document_type>Study Protocol</document_type>
      <document_has_protocol>Yes</document_has_protocol>
      <document_has_icf>No</document_has_icf>
      <document_has_sap>No</document_has_sap>
      <document_date>March 7, 2019</document_date>
      <document_url>https://ClinicalTrials.gov/ProvidedDocs/78/NCT03902678/Prot_000.pdf</document_url>
    </provided_document>
  </provided_document_section>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

