<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03905356</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>STUDY00010618</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03905356</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Exercise Therapy in Radiation Therapy</brief_title>
  <acronym>EXERT</acronym>
  <official_title>Exercise Therapy in Radiation Therapy (EXERT)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Milton S. Hershey Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Milton S. Hershey Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to evaluate exercise therapy as a method for potentially
      improving radiation therapy treatment toxicities for metastatic cancer patients receiving
      radiation therapy.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Study Objectives and Endpoints:

      Aim 1. To determine the acceptability, feasibility, and safety of an exercise intervention
      among cancer patients receiving radiation therapy. The investigators anticipate that &gt;25% of
      approached patients will consent to the protocol; &gt;33% of eligible radiation therapy patients
      who consent will perform the exercise prescribed (based on the response rate from EnACT); and
      &lt;25% of participants will experience a musculoskeletal impairment (without treatment
      alterations) and &lt;5% will experience a musculoskeletal injury with symptoms lasting ≥ week or
      requiring medical attention. The investigators' approach will be to include patients
      receiving definitive RT; excluding patients at high risk for side effects from combination
      therapy, including fracture or cardiovascular events.

      Aim 2. To discern the clinical outcomes of patients receiving RT+ET. The hypothesis is that
      adding ET to RT will improve patient reported outcomes and physical functioning. The
      investigators' approach will be to use standardized questionnaires and assessment tools:
      patient reported outcomes will be assessed using Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse
      Events - Patient Reported Outcomes (CTCAE-PROs), loaded onto tablets that patients use in the
      clinic. Questions will assess global PROs relevant to the ability to tolerate RT, including
      fatigue, pain, nausea, vomiting; and disease-site-specific PROs, including
      genitourinary/sexual symptoms for patients receiving pelvic RT. RT dose alterations will be
      documented. Scores will be compared pre- vs post- RT. The investigators will also use
      standardized measures already used in EnACT, including grip strength, 30-second chair stand,
      timed up-and-go, and 4-stage balance. Scores will be compared pre- vs post- RT.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 12, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Acceptability of exercise intervention: (number of patients agreeing to perform RT+ET)/(number approached)</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>(number of patients agreeing to perform RT+ET)/(number approached)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Feasibility of exercise intervention: (number of patients who completed RT+ET)/(number agreeing to perform RT+ET)</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>(number of patients who completed RT+ET)/(number agreeing to perform RT+ET)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of Treatment- Emergent Adverse Events</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Safety of exercise intervention: freedom from any Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE) grade 3 or higher event</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in timed up and go</measure>
    <time_frame>3 Months</time_frame>
    <description>Timed up and go</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>change in grip strength</measure>
    <time_frame>3 Months</time_frame>
    <description>Grip strength</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>change in quality of life measured via the Godin Physical Activity Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>3 Months</time_frame>
    <description>The Godin Physical Activity Questionnaire asks how much physical activity the participant engages in during a typical 7-day period.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>change in quality of life measured via the Barriers to Exercise RM 5-FM survey</measure>
    <time_frame>3 Months</time_frame>
    <description>The Barriers to Exercise RM 5-FM survey asks participants about barriers to being active. Response options include: very likely; somewhat likely; somewhat unlikely; very unlikely.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>change in quality of life measured via the Work Productivity and Activity Impairment Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>3 Months</time_frame>
    <description>The Work Productivity and Activity Impairment Questionnaire ask about the effect of the participant's health problems on the ability to work and perform regular activities. A variety of question/response styles are included in the survey.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>change in quality of life measured via the Scored Patient-Generated Subjective Global Assessment</measure>
    <time_frame>3 Months</time_frame>
    <description>The Score Patient-Generated Subjective Global Assessment asks about participant nutrition. A variety of question/response styles are included in the survey.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>change in quality of life measured via the EORTC questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>3 Months</time_frame>
    <description>The EORTC Quality of life questionnaire asks a variety of questions about their health regarding physical abilities. Response options include: not at all; a little; quite a bit; very much.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>change in quality of life measured via the ECHO EXERT survey</measure>
    <time_frame>3 Months</time_frame>
    <description>The Experience of Care and Health Outcomes (ECHO) Survey asks three questions about participant experience with the exercise intervention. Response options include: not at all; not much; mixed; somewhat; very much so.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>change in quality of life measured via the Health Belief Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>3 Months</time_frame>
    <description>The Health Belief Scale asks questions regarding exercise therapy. Response options include: strongly disagree - strongly agree, where 1 equals strongly disagree and 4 equals strongly agree.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Metastatic Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Exercise</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The exercise intervention will utilize the &quot;Moving Through Cancer: A Guide to Exercise for Cancer Survivors&quot; framework. A certified cancer exercise physiologist will work through this guide at radiation therapy visits, with at least 1 visit per week, per the study schema. The cancer exercise physiologist will teach participants proper: warm ups, use of equipment, exercise form, modes of activity, intensity of exercise, flexibility exercises, and cool down. The cancer exercise physiologist will tailor the instruction to convey special considerations for exercise based on treatment and cancer type. The patient will perform supervised exercise in the Exercise Medicine Unit under the guidance of the cancer exercise specialist. The exercise done will be educational in nature (i.e. learning about proper walking form, proper intensity for a warmup/cool down, proper techniques for resistance exercises).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Exercise Therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>Certified exercise oncology specialists will personalize, prescribe, and guide ET, including twice weekly resistance training and walking, performed at home, with supervision in the Exercise Medicine Unit. The cancer exercise physiologist will teach participants proper warm ups, use of equipment, exercise form, modes of activity, intensity of exercise, flexibility exercises, and cool down. In addition, patients will be instructed to exercise on their own, at home, according to the instructions from the cancer exercise specialist.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Exercise</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Males and females ≥18 years of age

          -  Fluent in written and spoken English

          -  Must be able to provide and understand informed consent

          -  Must have an ECOG PS of ≤ 2

          -  Diagnosed with a malignancy

          -  Cancer patients (stage 1-4)

          -  Treatment to primary site or metastatic disease

          -  Scheduled to receive radiation therapy at Penn State Cancer Institute

          -  Absence of absolute contraindications for exercise according to the American Heart
             Association (see below)

          -  Primary attending oncologist approval

          -  Receiving treatment as an outpatient

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Receiving radiation therapy at a location other than Penn State Cancer Institute

          -  Not fluent in written and spoken English

          -  Evidence in the medical record of an absolute contraindication for exercise

          -  Cardiac exclusion criteria:

               -  Class II, III or IV heart failure as defined by the New York Heart Association
                  (NYHA) functional classification system

               -  History of acute coronary syndromes (including myocardial infarction and unstable
                  angina), coronary angioplasty or stenting within the past 6 months prior to the
                  start of radiation therapy

               -  Uncontrolled arrhythmias; patients with rate controlled atrial fibrillation for
                  &gt;1 month prior to start of radiation therapy may be eligible

               -  syncope

               -  acute myocarditis, pericarditis, or endocarditis

               -  acute pulmonary embolus or pulmonary infarction

               -  thrombosis of lower extremities

               -  suspected dissecting aneurysm

               -  pulmonary edema

               -  respiratory failure

               -  acute non-cardiopulmonary disorder that may affect exercise performance or be
                  aggravated by exercise

               -  mental impairment leading to inability to cooperate

          -  Pregnant women

          -  In-patient receiving radiation therapy for a radiation emergency (e.g. cord
             compression, SVC syndrome, brain metastases)

          -  High risk of fracture or spine instability (Mirels score ≥7, SINS ≥7)

          -  Children (the protocol will only include individuals 18 and older)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Nicholas G Zaorsky, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Penn State Cancer Institute</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Kathryn Schmitz, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Penn State Cancer Institute</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Nicholas G Zaorsky, MD</last_name>
    <phone>1-717-531-8024</phone>
    <email>nzaorsky@pennstatehealth.psu.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Kelsey C Stoltzfus, MPH</last_name>
    <phone>717-531-0003</phone>
    <phone_ext>289496</phone_ext>
    <email>kstoltzfus4@pennstatehealth.psu.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Penn State Cancer Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hershey</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>17033</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Nicholas G Zaorsky, MD</last_name>
      <phone>717-531-8024</phone>
      <email>nzaorsky@pennstatehealth.psu.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Erica Schleicher, MS</last_name>
      <phone>717-531-0003</phone>
      <phone_ext>323324</phone_ext>
      <email>eschleicher1@phs.psu.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Nicholas G Zaorsky, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 28, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 4, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 5, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 13, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 13, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 17, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Milton S. Hershey Medical Center</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Nicholas Zaorsky</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor, Department of Radiation Oncology</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Neoplasm Metastasis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <provided_document_section>
    <provided_document>
      <document_type>Study Protocol and Statistical Analysis Plan</document_type>
      <document_has_protocol>Yes</document_has_protocol>
      <document_has_icf>No</document_has_icf>
      <document_has_sap>Yes</document_has_sap>
      <document_date>January 3, 2018</document_date>
      <document_url>https://ClinicalTrials.gov/ProvidedDocs/56/NCT03905356/Prot_SAP_000.pdf</document_url>
    </provided_document>
    <provided_document>
      <document_type>Informed Consent Form</document_type>
      <document_has_protocol>No</document_has_protocol>
      <document_has_icf>Yes</document_has_icf>
      <document_has_sap>No</document_has_sap>
      <document_date>January 15, 2018</document_date>
      <document_url>https://ClinicalTrials.gov/ProvidedDocs/56/NCT03905356/ICF_001.pdf</document_url>
    </provided_document>
  </provided_document_section>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

