<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03900156</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>201701926B0</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03900156</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Goal-setting With Mentoring Lifestyle Modification Intervention to Reduce Risk of Dementia in Later Life</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Goal-setting With Mentoring Lifestyle Modification Intervention to Reduce Risk of Dementia in Later Life</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Tzu-Ting Huang</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Chang Gung Memorial Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a 5-year project. In the 1st year of this study, a pilot randomized controlled trial
      evaluating the feasibility and acceptability of a goal-setting behavior change intervention
      aim at reducing modifiable risk factors for preventing cognitive decline. The aim of 2nd to
      5th year of this study to investigate whether this multidomain intervention to optimize
      self-management of cognitive decline risk factors in older individuals, delivered through a
      mentor- supported interactive internet platform, can reduce the risk of cognitive decline.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Lifestyle factors playing a role in the development of late-life cognitive decline may be
      modifiable. There is a need for robust evidence about the potential for prevention of
      cognitive decline through behavior change interventions.

      This study involves the development, implementation and initial testing of a behavior change
      intervention. At the 1st year, a small-scale randomized controlled trial (RCT) will
      investigate the implementation of a goal-setting intervention aim at promoting behavior
      change of personal modifiable risks for cognitive decline in the community for &gt;55 years with
      at least one of the 7 modifiable risk factors for dementia. These older participants in the
      community (n = 100) will be randomized to either control (had a discussion regarding health
      and daily activity) or goal-setting with mentoring (the goal-setting interview involving
      identification of up to five personal goals of personal modifiable risks). All participants
      will be reassessed after 12 months. The 2nd to the 5th year, is a multisite, prospective, RCT
      with 36 months intervention. Recruitment of 300 older people (≥55 years) with at least one of
      the 7 modifiable risk factors for dementia will take place in Northern Taiwan. Participants
      randomised to the intervention condition will have access to an interactive internet
      platform, stimulating self-management of dementia risk factors, with remote mentoring by a
      mentor.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">April 14, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">June 30, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 30, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>cognition</measure>
    <time_frame>5 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>Mini-Mental State Examination</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>cognition</measure>
    <time_frame>10 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>Montreal Cognitive Assessment</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>objective parameters</measure>
    <time_frame>2 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>systolic blood pressure</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>low-density-lipoprotein</measure>
    <time_frame>1 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>low-density-lipoprotein</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>fasting blood sugar</measure>
    <time_frame>1 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>fasting blood sugar</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>body mass index</measure>
    <time_frame>1 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>body mass index</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>waist-hip ratio</measure>
    <time_frame>1 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>waist-hip ratio</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>physical activity scale for the elderly</measure>
    <time_frame>5 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>The first page of the questionnaire provides general instructions and shows an example of a completed item. Respondents should be encouraged to answer each item by circling the correct response. All items refer to activities performed in the previous seven days. &quot;Never&quot; and &quot;No&quot; responses should always be marked to indicate any activities the respondent did not perform during that period.
The leisure activity items require respondents to first report the number of days per week the activity was performed and then the number of hours per day. Space is also provided for respondents to record the types of activities in which they engaged. These reports should be reviewed before computing PASE scores to ensure that specific sports and recreational activities have been recorded in the appropriate categories.
In this sample scores ranged from 0 to 361. The mean score was 102.9 (standard deviation = 64.1); the median was 90. Mean scores (and standard deviations).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Senior fitness test</measure>
    <time_frame>15 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>The Senior Fitness Test was developed as part of the LifeSpan Wellness Program at Fullerton University, by Dr. Roberta Rikli and Dr. Jessie Jones. As such, the test is sometimes known as the Fullerton Functional Test. It is a simple, easy-to-use battery of test items that assess the functional fitness of older adults. The test describes easy to understand and effective tests to measure aerobic fitness, strength and flexibility using minimal and inexpensive equipment.
The individual fitness test items involve common activities such as getting up from a chair, walking, lifting, bending, and stretching. The tests were developed to be safe and enjoyable for older adults, while still meeting scientific standards for reliability and validity.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mediterranean Diet Adherence Screener</measure>
    <time_frame>5 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>MEDAS. Schröder et al., 2011</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Geriatric Depression Scale-15</measure>
    <time_frame>5 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>A short-form GDS that consisted of 15 questions was the primary outcome measure (Sheikh and Yesavage, 1986). Scores of 0-4 are considered normal; 5-8 indicates mild depression; 9-11 indicates moderate depression; and 12-15 indicates severe depression.
The Chinese version of the GDS-15 demonstrates high reliability (Liao et al., 1995); in this study, the Cronbach's a is .91.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>University of California, Los Angeles, Loneliness Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>5 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>A 20-item scale designed to measure one's subjective feelings of loneliness as well as feelings of social isolation. Participants rate each item as either O (&quot;I often feel this way&quot;), S (&quot;I sometimes feel this way&quot;), R (&quot;I rarely feel this way&quot;), N (&quot;I never feel this way&quot;).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>control, autonomy, self-realization, pleasure-19</measure>
    <time_frame>5 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>Description: The Quality of Life Scale (CASP-19) uses four domains (i.e., control, autonomy, pleasure and self-realization) to assess the quality of life in individuals in early old age.
Number of items: 19, including 6 items for control, 5 items for autonomy, 4 items for pleasure and 4 items for self-realization.
Example of statement/item: &quot;I look forward to each day&quot; Response options: 4-point Likert scale ranging from 0, &quot;never&quot; to 3, &quot;often&quot;. Total score: Items are summed, yielding a range from 0 to 57 for the total score (domains are usually not used separately). Higher scores indicate higher levels of satisfaction of quality of life.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">94</enrollment>
  <condition>Risk Reduction Behavior</condition>
  <condition>Reduce Risk of Dementia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>comparison group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>The CG received no extra care.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Intervention Group, goal-setting with follow-up, will have a structured goalsetting interview using the Bangor Goal-Setting Interview ; once goals are identified and clearly expressed in accordance with SMART principles (specific, measureable, achievable, realistic, and timed)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>goal-setting</intervention_name>
    <description>The interviewer will have access to key information from the initial assessment such as details of identified risks. Areas where the participant would like to make changes or improvements will be identified and prioritized, and up to five specific, realistic and achievable goals will be identified.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  in Northern Taiwan

          -  at least one of the 8 modifiable risk factors for dementia (Hearing loss,
             Hypertension, Obesity, Smoking, Depression, Physical inactivity, Social isolation, and
             Diabetes)

          -  living independently

          -  in the local community

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  can't speak chinese
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>55 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Chang Gung University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Taoyuan</city>
        <zip>333</zip>
        <country>Taiwan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Taiwan</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 14, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 1, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 2, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 14, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 14, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 15, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Chang Gung Memorial Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Tzu-Ting Huang</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor, School of Nursing</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Dementia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

