<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03905681</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>C.2019.027d</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03905681</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>TENS Efficacy on Acute Back Pain in an Emergency Department Triage</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Use of Transcutaneous Electrical Nerve Stimulation on the Efficacy of Acute Back Pain Within an Emergency Department Triage: A Randomized Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>William Beaumont Army Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>William Beaumont Army Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Transcutaneous Electrical Nerve Stimulation (TENS) devices produce a gentle electrical
      stimulation that when applied through pads applied directly to the skin, has a noticeable
      effect in reducing pain associated with various types of injuries and ailments. Several
      recent studies have shown efficacy when used for acute pain specific to primary dysmenorrhea,
      renal colic, lower-extremity pain, and pain associated with spinal cord injury, and was
      achieved without adverse effects. This study is intended to compare the effects of TENS units
      on acute back pain on ambulatory patients who are awaiting emergency medical treatment, to
      uncover if a statistically-significant analgesic effect is noted compared to a placebo
      device.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      With the emerging amount of new data on the treatment specific to acute pain, it is theorized
      that early TENS application can be an adjunct for acute pain reduction, specifically for
      patients awaiting treatment in an emergency department triage waiting room. TENS stimulators
      are advantageous to patients in that they are non-pharmacologic and non-invasive therapy.
      TENS devices have an excellent safety profile, are associated with very few
      contraindications, and have negligible side-effects or adverse events: the most common being
      minor skin irritation. (Sluka and Walsh 2003) Of financial benefit to a hospital considering
      their implementation, these devices are also inexpensive. In the realm of emergency medicine,
      which is being scrutinized to reduce opioid prescriptions, measures must be taken to maximize
      the efficacy of alternative pain-relief adjuncts.

      There are significant gaps in the literature which have depicted no significant benefits
      compared to physical therapy and other modalities. These studies had used variable treatments
      times and frequencies, which were not solidified in scientific research at the time of their
      results. The use of these stimulators has been extensively studied, and the evidence to
      support their use on various conditions has been inconclusive. Early meta-analyses and
      systematic reviews have noted the data are inconsistent to suggest a mean reduction of pain
      when assessed on chronic pain. (Brosseau et al. 2002) However, when applied extensively and
      at regular settings, TENS has shown the presence of tolerance to TENS when used chronically
      in as few as four days. (Chandran and Sluka, 2003) This study is intended to harness the
      newest research comparing the most-effective settings and durations of TENS units, and
      compare the effects of TENS units on acute back pain on ambulatory patients who are awaiting
      emergency medical treatment.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">April 2, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 16, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 16, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Using a sample population in a military treatment facility emergency department, this prospective, randomized controlled trial utilized forty-six total participants evenly divided to both a active and placebo group, were used to determine the efficacy of Transcutaneous Electrical Nerve Stimulation (TENS) on acute back pain of ambulatory patients presenting for emergent care.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Care Provider)</masking>
    <masking_description>After computer-generated randomization, participants will either receive the active TENS treatment for 30 minutes, or receive the application of TENS pads and wear the device with no electrical stimulation. Both groups will have pre and post visual analogue scores assessed.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Decrease in pain using Visual Analogue Scores (VAS)</measure>
    <time_frame>After 30-minute duration of treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Enrolled participants will have baseline Visual Analogue Scores (VAS) pain scale scores assessed, consisting of a 0 to 100 unit scale, with instruction to locate their level of pain on the scale of 0 being &quot;No pain at all,&quot; 50 being &quot;Moderate Pain,&quot; and 100 being &quot;Worst pain imaginable,&quot; and will be compared to score on the same scale after treatment.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Increase in patient satisfaction while awaiting treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>After 30-minute duration of treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Using an assessment questionnaire of patient satisfaction, with nominal and ordinal results measured for statistical significance:
Do you feel that early intervention with this device increases your satisfaction as a patient?
If given the opportunity, would you like to continue to use this device while waiting?
If you were to guess, do you think you were part of the treatment group or the no-treatment group?
On a scale of 1 through 10, with 1 being &quot;completely dissatisfied&quot; and 10 being &quot;completely satisfied,&quot; how satisfied are you with being provided this treatment?</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">44</enrollment>
  <condition>Acute Back Injury</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Active TENS Group &quot;Group A&quot;</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>After all necessary data collection forms are obtained, a pre-VAS score will be obtained. The participant will point to the area of maximum subjective pain, and then four TENS pads will be applied directly around the point of maximal pain that was determined by the patient, located at least 3 centimeters but no more than 6 centimeters from the area in a square or frame-like placement. While the device is off, it will be set at the following settings: The selector switch will be set to 'Milli' or milliamperes, and the frequency dial will be rotated to 100 Hertz. The participant will be instructed to rotate both dials in a clockwise direction if more intensity is desired, or counter-clockwise if less intensity is desired. The participant will wear the device and pads for a 30-minute duration; upon completion, post-VAS scores and a patient satisfaction survey will be obtained.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo TENS Group &quot;Group B&quot;</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>After all necessary data collection forms are obtained, a pre-VAS score will be obtained. The participant will point to the area of maximum subjective pain, and then four TENS pads will be applied directly around the point of maximal pain that was determined by the patient, located at least 3 centimeters but no more than 6 centimeters from the area in a square or frame-like placement. However, no electrical stimulation will be provided. The participant will also wear the device and pads for a 30-minute duration; upon completion, post-VAS scores and a patient satisfaction survey will be obtained.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Transcutaneous Electrical Nerve Stimulation</intervention_name>
    <description>Application of TENS pads and wearing of the TENS device.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Active TENS Group &quot;Group A&quot;</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo TENS Group &quot;Group B&quot;</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>TENS</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Presents to the Emergency Department in an ambulatory status

          -  Has a complaint of traumatic back pain, acute or acute-on-chronic, which is 3 weeks or
             less in duration.

          -  Is designated to an Emergency Severity Index Category of 4 or 5.

          -  Patient must be unfamiliar with TENS use

          -  Projected wait time of greater than 30 minutes before a visit with an Emergency
             Department provider is anticipated based on triage category

          -  Not actively pregnant for female patients

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patient has a history of using TENS in the past

          -  Patient is actively pregnant

          -  History of narcotic use or abuse in the last 24 hours

          -  Patient has a cardiac pacemaker or a neurostimulation-implant device

          -  Patient is designated to an Emergency Severity Index Category of 1, 2, or 3

          -  Patient has an open wound, abrasion, skin rash, or tattoo &lt; 6 weeks old where pads
             will be placed

          -  Patient has a current history of Low Back Pain 'red flags' (Bilateral radicular
             symptoms, saddle anesthesia or paresthesia, bladder incontinence, or bowel
             incontinence) which require immediate attention.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>59 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>William Beaumont Army Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Fort Bliss</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>79920</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bi X, Lv H, Chen BL, Li X, Wang XQ. Effects of transcutaneous electrical nerve stimulation on pain in patients with spinal cord injury: a randomized controlled trial. J Phys Ther Sci. 2015 Jan;27(1):23-5. doi: 10.1589/jpts.27.23. Epub 2015 Jan 9.</citation>
    <PMID>25642029</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sluka KA, Walsh D. Transcutaneous electrical nerve stimulation: basic science mechanisms and clinical effectiveness. J Pain. 2003 Apr;4(3):109-21. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>14622708</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Brosseau L, Milne S, Robinson V, Marchand S, Shea B, Wells G, Tugwell P. Efficacy of the transcutaneous electrical nerve stimulation for the treatment of chronic low back pain: a meta-analysis. Spine (Phila Pa 1976). 2002 Mar 15;27(6):596-603.</citation>
    <PMID>11884907</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chandran P, Sluka KA. Development of opioid tolerance with repeated transcutaneous electrical nerve stimulation administration. Pain. 2003 Mar;102(1-2):195-201.</citation>
    <PMID>12620611</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lauretti GR, Oliveira R, Parada F, Mattos AL. The New Portable Transcutaneous Electrical Nerve Stimulation Device Was Efficacious in the Control of Primary Dysmenorrhea Cramp Pain. Neuromodulation. 2015 Aug;18(6):522-6; discussion 522-7. doi: 10.1111/ner.12269. Epub 2015 Feb 5.</citation>
    <PMID>25655828</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ayyildiz A, Akgül T, Nuhoğlu B. Re: Transcutaneous electrical nerve stimulation: an effective treatment for pain caused by renal colic in emergency care. B. Mora, E. Giorni, M. Dobrovits, R. Barker, T. Lang, C. Gore and A. Kober, J Urol 2006; 175: 1737. J Urol. 2007 Jan;177(1):405.</citation>
    <PMID>17162100</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gozani SN. Fixed-site high-frequency transcutaneous electrical nerve stimulation for treatment of chronic low back and lower extremity pain. J Pain Res. 2016 Jun 28;9:469-79. doi: 10.2147/JPR.S111035. eCollection 2016.</citation>
    <PMID>27418854</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 30, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 4, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 5, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 31, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 31, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 4, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>William Beaumont Army Medical Center</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>David Manley</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Captain David Manley, PA-C, Emergency Medicine Physician Assistant Resident</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Transcutaneous Electrical Nerve Stimulation, Acute back pain</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Back Pain</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Emergencies</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Back Injuries</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Once the study is completed, the data used for statistical analysis will be void of personally identifiable information. This data will be in electronic form for use in government-approved software, such as Microsoft Office. These documents will be distributed only to the Primary Investigator and the William Beaumont Army Medical Center (WBAMC) Department of Clinical Investigations assistance with statistical analysis or future publishing consideration. All paper documents are to be maintained in accordance with Department of Clinical Investigations policies; study-specific electronic documents will be kept for a minimum of 3 years before deletion. Upon study closure, all personally identifiable information (including the Master Key) will be destroyed or deleted, and a de-identified data set maintained by the WBAMC Emergency Medicine Physician Assistant Residency Program Director for further study as needed. No human biological specimens will be maintained.</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Statistical Analysis Plan (SAP)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Informed Consent Form (ICF)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>3 years, or as determined by the WBAMC Department of Clinical Investigations.</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>Principal Investigator, WBAMC Department of Clinical Investigations, WBAMC Emergency Medicine Physician Assistant Residency Program Director.</ipd_access_criteria>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

