<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03901703</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>465426</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03901703</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Effects of Functional Strengthening in Spastic Cerebral Palsy</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Effects of Progressive Functional Ankle Strengthening in Children With Unilateral and Bilateral Spastic Cerebral Palsy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Melek Volkan Yazici</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Gazi University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Functional strengthening exercises have been proven to be effective in patients with spastic
      cerebral palsy. However, which exercise is the most effective is unknown. The aim of this
      study is to examine the effectiveness of three different progressive functional exercise
      programs in children with unilateral and bilateral spastic cerebral palsy.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Children with Cerebral Palsy have weakness in thier muscles due to cortical lesions leading
      to deficiencies in motor control, balance and functional abilities. All children with
      Cerebral Palsy have shown to present with foot and ankle disorders; the ankle dorsi and
      plantar flexor muscles are both problematic; the plantarflexors are usually spastic and the
      dorsiflexors are usually not active enough and usually these muscle problems lead to problems
      in the childrens' gait abilities. When rehabilitation programs are examined, the results of
      exercises addressing these problems do not have precise answers. Functional strengthening
      exercises have been proven to be effective in patients with spastic cerebral palsy. However,
      which exercise is the most effective is unknown. Which muscle goup has the most effect on
      gait, balance and functional activities is still unclear. Therefore, the investigator's aim
      in planning this study is to examine the effectiveness of three progressive functional
      exercise programs in children with unilateral and bilateral spastic cerebral palsy.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 12, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 30, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 15, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pediatric Balance scale</measure>
    <time_frame>Change of The Pediatric balance scale at 6 weeks.</time_frame>
    <description>The Pediatric Balance Scale is a modified version of the Berg Balance Scale that is used to assess functional balance skills in children. The scale consists of 14 items that are scored from 0 points (lowest function) to 4 points (highest function) with a maximum score of 56 points.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Surface Electromyography (sEMG)</measure>
    <time_frame>Change of sEMG data at 6 weeks.</time_frame>
    <description>Surface electromyography is a non-invasive procedure involving the detection, recording and interpretation of the electric activity of groups of muscles during activity. The procedure is performed using electrodes placed on the skin surface over the muscles to be tested. sEMG is also used to assess the effects of rehabilitation programs and evaluate muscular function in children with cerebral palsy. Due to its non-invasive properties it is safely and widely used in the pediatric population.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The Six minute walk test</measure>
    <time_frame>Change of 6 MWT at 6 weeks.</time_frame>
    <description>The 6-min walk test (6 MWT) is a submaximal exercise test that entails measurement of distance walked over a span of 6 minutes. The 6-minute walk distance (6 MWD) provides a measure for integrated global response of multiple cardiopulmonary and musculoskeletal systems involved in exercise. The test has been shown to be valid and reliable in children with Cerebral Palsy.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">27</enrollment>
  <condition>Spastic Cerebral Palsy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Dorsiflexor Muscle Strengthening Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The children in this group will receive functional exercises aiming to strengthen their dorsiflexor muscles alongside standard functional progressive strengthening exercises.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Plantarflexor Muscle Strengthening Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The children in this group will receive functional exercises aiming to strengthen their plantarflexor muscles alongside standard functional progressive strengthening exercises.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Dorsiflexor and Plantarflexor Muscle strengthening Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The children in this group will receive functional exercises aiming to strengthen both their dorsiflexor and plantarflexor muscles alongside standard functional progressive strengthening exercises.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Physiotherapy and Rehabilitation</intervention_name>
    <description>The children in each group will receive 6 weeks of functional strengthening exercises targeting each muscle group according to the arm they are included in.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Dorsiflexor Muscle Strengthening Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Dorsiflexor and Plantarflexor Muscle strengthening Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Plantarflexor Muscle Strengthening Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Accepting to participate in the study,

          -  Being between 5-15 years old,

          -  Having a diagnosis of Spastic Cerebral Palsy,

          -  Being level I-II according to GMFCS,

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Having limited cooperation which prevents participation in the study,

          -  Refusing to participate in the study,

          -  Having an orthopedic disorder or systemic illness which prevents movement in the lower
             extremities,

          -  Having a Botulinum toxin application in the last 3 months
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>5 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>15 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Bulent Elbasan, Assoc. Prof.</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Gazi University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Gazi University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ankara</city>
        <zip>06500</zip>
        <country>Turkey</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Turkey</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>April 1, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 2, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 3, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 29, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 29, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 30, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Gazi University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Melek Volkan Yazici</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principle Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Muscle Spasticity</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cerebral Palsy</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>The exercise protocols and results will be shared with other investigators.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

