<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03909568</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>249253</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03909568</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Bone Height and Extractions Study</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomised Controlled Trial to Assess the Alveolar Bone Height Distal to Lower Second Molar Following Either Coronectomy or Extraction of the Adjacent Impacted Lower Third Molar</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>King's College London</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>King's College London</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      A coronectomy is often chosen over complete extraction of a lower third molar when the tooth
      appears to be in close proximity to the inferior dental (ID) canal, as assessed on a plain
      radiograph or a cone beam computer tomograph (CBCT). Following a coronectomy, the roots of
      the third molar may migrate in a coronal direction. This effect, along with the
      bone-preserving technique of a coronectomy over extraction, may provide increased bone height
      distal to the lower second molars, when compared to extraction. Partially erupted lower third
      molars, specifically those with mesio-angular impactions, are commonly associated with
      reduced bone height distal to lower second molars, and cause damage to the periodontal
      support of these neighboring teeth. It is assumed that maintenance of the impacted third
      molars or extraction of these teeth may compromise the periodontal status of the lower second
      molars. This study will investigate if coronectomy improves the bone levels, and therefore
      the periodontal status, of lower second molars, and may propose an indication for a
      coronectomy regardless of the proximity of the tooth to the ID canal.

      Coronectomies were first proposed as a treatment option just over thirty years ago, but there
      are very few long-term studies on the procedure reported in the literature. To the best of
      the investigator's knowledge, this will be the first randomised controlled trial comparing
      the bone height distal to the lower second molar following a coronectomy or extraction of the
      lower third molar.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">November 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Split-mouth</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
    <masking_description>Patients will be initially masked to which treatment is performed on each side, but will be notified at the follow-up appointment. In addition, the outcomes assessor carrying out the periodontal measurements (clinical attachment level and probing depths), will be unaware which treatment will be performed. The same surgical flap designs will be used for the treatment of both the right and left third molars, regardless of whether a coronectomy or extraction is carried out, and therefore the patient and clinician should be unable to differentiate between the procedures performed. Intervention will only be revealed to care provider once surgical flaps have been raised.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Linear bone height distal to lower second molar tooth</measure>
    <time_frame>Six months surgical intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Assessed by comparison of periapical radiographs pre- and post-intervention</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Alveolar Bone Loss</condition>
  <condition>Periodontal Attachment Loss</condition>
  <condition>Periodontal Pocket</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Third molar surgery</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Split mouth comparison of effect of complete third molar removal vs coronectomy of contralateral third molar</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Third molar surgery</intervention_name>
    <description>Comparing complete removal of third molar with removal of crown only on contralateral side</description>
    <arm_group_label>Third molar surgery</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients requiring extraction of both lower third molars

          -  Both lower third molars to have mesio-angular impa

          -  ctions, as assessed by location of the contact point between the crown of the third
             molar and the cemento-enamel junction (CEJ) of the second molar and the angulation of
             the third molar

          -  Both lower third molars must lie above or clear of the ID canal as assessed on a plain
             radiograph or CBCT

          -  Presence of lower second molars

          -  Patients must be ≥18yrs old

          -  Patients willing to attend follow up appointments

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Lower third molars with caries, periapical pathology or associated lesions such as
             cysts

          -  Patients who are immunocompromised, have a history of or due to have head and neck
             radiotherapy, chemotherapy, have previously been given or due to start intravenous
             bisphosphonates

          -  Smokers (&gt;5 cigarettes/day)

          -  Patients involved in current research or have recently been involved with research
             prior to recruitment
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <verification_date>April 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>April 8, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 9, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 10, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 28, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 28, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 29, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Alveolar Bone Loss</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Periodontal Pocket</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Periodontal Attachment Loss</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

