<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04099849</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PR-13008</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04099849</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Zinc Absorption From Zinc Biofortified Rice in Bangladeshi Children</brief_title>
  <official_title>Absorption of Zinc From Mixed Diets Containing Conventional Bangladeshi Rice, Zinc-biofortified Bangladeshi Rice, or Conventional Bangladeshi Rice With Added Zinc Among Young Children From a Peri-urban Community</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>International Centre for Diarrhoeal Disease Research, Bangladesh</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>International Centre for Diarrhoeal Disease Research, Bangladesh</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      It is well documented that zinc supplementation to low-income population results in the
      reduced incidence of childhood diarrhoea and pneumonia, and improves growth of stunted
      children. In Bangladesh, the risk of zinc deficiency is considered to be high and children
      could benefit greatly by improving their zinc intakes on a daily basis. Zinc supplementation
      at a national scale would be a formidable task. There is a need to find an alternative. It
      might be sustainable to improve intake of zinc through fortified staples, e.g. rice with
      increased amounts of zinc; in fact such biofortified rice has been developed through
      conventional breeding, which is designed to contain an amount of zinc that could meet at
      least 40% of the daily requirement.

      In the first round of the previously approved and completed studies, total absorbed zinc
      (TAZ) did not differ when diets containing zinc biofortified rice (ZnBfR) or conventional
      rice (CR) were compared. Thus, the current study is planned to repeat using a new variety of
      (ZnBfR) that is expected to have higher zinc content than the variety previously studied.
      Initially, a pilot study will be conducted in 4 participants using a modified isotope
      administration protocol such that the oral tracers will be given on two days each at half the
      original dose each day so as to provide a lower proportion of the total daily zinc intake as
      tracer solution.

      Hypotheses:

        1. Young children will have greater total absorbed zinc (TAZ) when they consume mixed diets
           containing ZnBfR than when they consume the same diets containing CR.

        2. TAZ will not differ in children who receive the ZnBfR-containing diet or the same diet
           containing CR plus sufficient additional zinc to match the zinc content of the ZnBfR
           diet.

      Objectives:

        1. To measure the amount of zinc absorbed from ZnBfR compared with the amount absorbed from
           CR and from CR fortified with added zinc, using the triple stable isotope tracer ratio
           technique in young children.

        2. To assess the intestinal function of the children, using a sugar permeability test
           (lactulose:mannitol test).

        3. (Pilot study) To verify that the modified tracer dose will provide adequate signal for
           assessing zinc absorption.

      Methods:

      To assess the potentials for biofortified rice in providing a good, bioavailable source of
      additional zinc, it is proposed here to measure zinc absorption from rice-based meals among
      Bangladeshi preschool children. The amount of zinc absorbed from ZnBfR compared to that
      absorbed from a conventional Bangladeshi rice (Diet-CR) (control) will be measured. Zinc
      absorbed from ZnBfR with that from zinc-fortified conventional rice (Diet-CR+Z) will also be
      compared. The study will be a cross-over, randomized, controlled clinical study. Initially, a
      pilot study will be conducted with a modified dose of zinc stable isotope among 4 children
      aged 36-59 months of either sex from a peri-urban community in Dhaka. Later on, 44 children
      aged 36-59 months of either sex will be recruited from the same community as mentioned
      before, and they will be individually randomized, in equal numbers, to one of the two
      comparison groups, A and B. During an initial one-day acclimatization period, the study
      children will receive the conventional rice based diet three times a day, to confirm that
      they will accept the study diets and adhere to the study procedures. On study days 2 and 4,
      in comparison group A, the study subjects will receive either the Diet-ZnBfR or Diet-CR based
      on the random assignments, and they will receive Diet-CR or Diet ZnBfR, respectively, on days
      3 and 5 (i.e., the diet not received on days 2 and 4), Likewise, in comparison group B, the
      study subjects will receive either Diet-ZnBfR or Diet-CR+Z on days 2 and 4 based on the
      random assignments, and they will receive Diet-CR+Z or the Diet-ZnBfR, respectively, on days
      3 and 5 (i.e., the diet not received on days 2 and 4). Zinc stable isotope tracer techniques
      will be used to measure the fractional absorption of zinc, in which tracer : tracee ratios
      will be measured in spot urine samples following administration of an intravenously
      administered tracer (68Zn) and one of two oral tracers (70Zn, 67Zn) provided with test meals
      over a four-day period.

      Outcome measures/variables: Intake of total dietary zinc (TDZ) and phytate for each subject
      will be calculated during the clinical study. Fractional absorption of zinc (FAZ) will be
      determined from the isotopic ratios obtained in urine samples using the following equation,
      which shows, as an example, the calculation that will be used for zinc absorption from the
      diet traced with 67Zn:

      FAZ = 67Zn tracer:tracee ratio / 68Zn tracer:tracee ratio * (68Zn dose given IV / 67Zn dose
      given orally)

      Total absorbed zinc (TAZ) for each child will be calculated as follows:

      TAZ (mg/d) = TDZ (mg/d) * FAZ
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">August 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 30, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 30, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Total absorbed zinc</measure>
    <time_frame>13 days</time_frame>
    <description>Total absorbed zinc (TAZ) for each child will be calculated as follows:
TAZ (mg/d) = Total Dietray Zinc (TDZ) (mg/d) * Frcational Absorbed Zinc (FAZ)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">48</enrollment>
  <condition>Malnourished Children</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Diet-ZnBfR zinc biofortified rice-based diet
Diet- CR conventional rice-based diet</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group B</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Diet-ZnBfR zinc biofortified rice-based diet
CR + Zn conventional rice-based diet plus zinc fortificant (Diet-CR+Z).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Diet-ZnBfR: Zinc biofortified rice-based diet</intervention_name>
    <description>Diet-ZnBfR: Zinc biofortified rice-based diet</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Group B</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Diet- CR: Conventional rice-based diet</intervention_name>
    <description>Diet- CR: Conventional rice-based diet</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group A</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>CR + Zn: Conventional rice-based diet plus zinc fortificant (Diet-CR+Z).</intervention_name>
    <description>CR + Zn: Conventional rice-based diet plus zinc fortificant (Diet-CR+Z).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group B</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Weight for Height Z-Score (WHZ) and Height for Age (HAZ): &gt;-2 Z-Score

        No longer breastfed

        No H/O diarrhoea in last 14 days

        Given anti-helminthics in last three months

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Not meeting the inclusion criteria.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>36 Months</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>59 Months</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Md Munirul Islam, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+880-2-9827001-10</phone>
    <phone_ext>2352</phone_ext>
    <email>mislam@icddrb.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Tahmeed Ahmed, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+880-2-9827001-10</phone>
    <phone_ext>2300</phone_ext>
    <email>tahmeed@icddrb.org</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>International Centre for Diarrhoeal Disease Research , Bangladesh (icddr,b)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dhaka</city>
        <zip>1212</zip>
        <country>Bangladesh</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Md Munirul Islam, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>+88029827001-10</phone>
      <phone_ext>2352</phone_ext>
      <email>mislam@icddrb.org</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Bangladesh</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 20, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 20, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 23, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 21, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 21, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">September 24, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>International Centre for Diarrhoeal Disease Research, Bangladesh</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>M Munirul Islam</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Senior Scientist</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Rice</keyword>
  <keyword>biofortification,</keyword>
  <keyword>Bangladeshi children</keyword>
  <keyword>zinc</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Malnutrition</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Zinc</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

