<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04090346</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>010.GID.2018.A</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04090346</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Fecal Microbiota Transplant</brief_title>
  <official_title>Fecal Microbiota Transplant</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Methodist Health System</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Methodist Health System</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The study will provide data to show the effectiveness of Fecal Microbiota Transplant in
      patients with recurrent Clostridium difficile infection.

      Fecal Microbiota Transplant (FMT) is a procedure in which healthy colon contents of a
      carefully screened donor is inserted into the colon of a compromised patient. FMT is a
      procedure to replace beneficial bacteria that has been killed or suppressed, most commonly by
      use of antibiotics. Currently it is utilized as an experimental treatment for Clostridium
      difficile infection (CDI). This procedure is predicted to reduce the cost both financially
      and physically for the CDI patient and facility.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Methodist Health System wishes to offer transplant services to our CDI populations which meet
      all criteria for recurrent intractable disease. The objective is to reduce the cost both
      financially and physically to patients and the facility, of living with chronic or recurrent
      CDI disease. This study is to provide treatment and demonstrate documented outcomes and
      success rates in a manner that protects both the patients and the facility. Of note this
      treatment is currently being provided by many facilities in Texas, under the FDA
      Investigational New Drug (IND) enforcement discretion.

      The study will provide data to show the effectiveness of Fecal Microbiota Transplant in
      patients with recurrent Clostridium difficile infection. This study will only examine FMT as
      it is the only available therapy beyond antibiotic treatment. When patients are considered
      for FMT they have already failed traditional therapeutic medications.

      Patients will be required to meet a specified criteria set forth for chronic or severe CDI
      infection. Chronic infection is defined as the third or greater episode of C Difficile
      infection, proven by a positive stool assay with previous documented treatments. Patients
      must be first treated with first line drug therapies which include vancomycin, metronidazole
      or fidaxomicin without cure. They must have been treated with at least one course of drugs
      over a six to eight week period of a vancomycin taper or vancomycin treatment followed by
      rifaximin for two weeks. Severe CDI infection is defined as refractory moderate to severe CDI
      diarrhea, with failing vancomycin drug therapy.

      Patients with contraindicated co-morbidities will be excluded. Comorbidities include severe
      bowel disease which would preclude colonoscopy, severe underlying immune suppression or
      decompensated liver cirrhosis.

      Patients will be under the care of a physician who is an identified investigator
      (sub-investigator) of this study for preparation, procedure and follow up care. Patients will
      be counseled by this physician regarding the risks and side effects of the procedure and
      transplant. Staff will only reinforce details from written materials given to patients.
      Questions outside of the written materials will be directed to the investigators for follow
      up.

      Risks include, but are not limited to the following.

        -  Transplant making no improvement in the course of their CDI.

        -  Common side effects including transient gas, bloating and rectal irritation

        -  Surgical risks which can include blood clots, excessive bleeding, allergic reactions and
           death. More common surgical risks are infection, drug reactions, bleeding, and
           perforation.

        -  Transmission of antibiotic-resistant bacteria: These are resistant to one or more
           antibiotics. These bacteria could be transmitted through FMT and cause a serious
           infection. The FMT that you will receive is provided by a company called OpenBiome,
           where donors who provide stool for the FMT treatments undergo screening for certain
           antibiotic-resistant bacteria and clinical risk factors that would make their exposure
           to antibiotic resistant bacteria more likely. Individuals who test positive for these
           bacteria or have these risk factors are excluded from donating.

      Patients will sign three informed consents. The first consent is to acknowledge the basis of
      the treatment is part of a research study (exhibit 1). The second consent) specifies that FMT
      is experimental in nature, and reviews the potential risks and benefits of the transplant.
      The third is the Methodist Health System &quot;Disclosure and Consent&quot; that is used for
      colonoscopy procedures.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Enrolling by invitation</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 5, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2026</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2024</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>treatment date</measure>
    <time_frame>eight weeks following transplant.</time_frame>
    <description>date of treatment</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>material volume</measure>
    <time_frame>eight weeks following transplant.</time_frame>
    <description>volume of material</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>severity and type of CDI</measure>
    <time_frame>eight weeks following transplant.</time_frame>
    <description>severity and type of CDI</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>serious adverse reactions</measure>
    <time_frame>eight weeks following transplant.</time_frame>
    <description>serious adverse reactions</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>repeat transplant, colectomy and antibiotics</measure>
    <time_frame>eight weeks following transplant.</time_frame>
    <description>patients who require additional treatment</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Clostridium Difficile Infection</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Clostridium difficile infection</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Clostridium difficile infection (CDI) is due to a toxin-producing bacteria that causes a more severe form of antibiotic associated diarrhea. The disease ranges from mild diarrhea to severe colon inflammation that can even be fatal.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Fecal Microbiota Transplant</intervention_name>
    <description>Fecal Microbiota Transplant (FMT) is a procedure to replace beneficial bacteria which has been killed or suppressed in the colon.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Clostridium difficile infection</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>FMT</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Recurring CDI after three episodes of mild to moderate C Diff infections and failure
             to respond to appropriate antimicrobial treatment of six to eight weeks.

          -  Metronidazole

          -  Vancomycin

          -  At least two episodes of severe C diff infection that have required hospitalization
             and significant morbidity within one year

          -  Severe C Diff infection requiring hospitalization and non- responsive to maximal
             medication therapy

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  advanced Human Immunodeficiency Virus (HIV) or Acquired Immunodeficiency Syndrome
             (AIDS)

          -  cirrhosis of the liver

          -  recent bone marrow transplants

          -  medication suppressed immune systems (allowed per physician discretion if benefit
             outweighs risk)

          -  pregnancy

          -  Toxic megacolon or ileus present
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Muhammad Memon, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Methodist Mansfield Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Methodist Health System</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dallas</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>75203</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>August 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 12, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 12, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 16, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 30, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 30, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 2, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>CDiff</keyword>
  <keyword>Fecal Microbiota Transplant</keyword>
  <keyword>Infection Control</keyword>
  <keyword>Antibiotic Stewardship</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Clostridium Infections</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

