<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04095221</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>19-120</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04095221</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study of the Drugs Prexasertib, Irinotecan, and Temozolomide in People With Desmoplastic Small Round Cell Tumor and Rhabdomyosarcoma</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase I/II Dose Escalation/Dose Expansion Study of Prexasertib in Combination With Irinotecan in Patients With Relapsed or RefractoryDesmoplastic Small Round Cell Tumor and Rhabdomyosarcoma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to test whether the study drug prexasertib is a safe and
      effective treatment for people with DSRCT or RMS when given in combination with the standard
      drugs irinotecan and temozolomide. The study will test different doses of prexasertib in
      combination with irinotecan and temozolomide to find the highest dose of prexasertib that
      causes few or mild side effects in participants.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 17, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>This is a single institution study to determine the recommended phase 2 dose of prexasertib when given in combination with irinotecan and temozolomide. Patients with relapsed or refractory desmoplastic small round cell tumor or rhabdomyosarcoma of any subtype will receive prexasertib using the 3+3 dose-escalation schema.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>recommended phase II does of Prexasertib</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>The RP2D is defined as the highest dose level associated with not more than 1 DLT out of 6 patients. A total of 5 dose levels are planned, including 2 back up levels. The DLT's will be graded according to the NCI Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE) version 5.0. The dose escalation will follow a 3+3 design.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>response</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>will be evaluated in this study using the criteria proposed by the Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors (RECIST) guideline, version 1.1 (Primary response criteria)54. Changes in the largest diameter (unidimensional measurement) of the tumor lesions and the shortest diameter in the case of malignant lymph nodes are used in the RECIST criteria.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Desmoplastic Small Round Cell Tumor</condition>
  <condition>Rhabdomyosarcoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Prexasertib and Irinotecan</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients will have extent of disease scans following every 2 cycles (every 6 weeks on dose levels 0-3, and every 8 weeks on dose level -1 (if required). Patients will be allowed to continue therapy as long as they do not experience dose-limiting toxicities or progression of disease.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Prexasertib</intervention_name>
    <description>DOSE LEVELS FOR PATIENTS &gt; 21 YEARS OF AGE, Dose Level -1, prexasertib 105 mg/ m2 once every 14 days in 28 day cycles Dose Level 0, 60 mg/m2 prexasertib once every 21 days Dose Level 1, (STARTING) 80 mg/m2 prexasertib once every 21 days Dose Level 2, 105 mg/m2 prexasertib once every 21 days Dose Level 3, 105 mg/m2 prexasertib once every 21 days
DOSE LEVELS FOR PATIENTS ≤ 21 YEARS OF AGE Dose Level -1, prexasertib 150 mg/ m2 once every 14 days in 28 day cycles, Dose Level 0, 60 mg/m2 prexasertib once every 21 days, Dose Level 1, (STARTING) 80 mg/m2 prexasertib once every 21 days, Dose Level 2, 150 mg/m2 prexasertib once every 21 days, Dose Level 3, 150 mg/m2 prexasertib once every 21 days</description>
    <arm_group_label>Prexasertib and Irinotecan</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Irinotecan</intervention_name>
    <description>15 mg/m2 IV daily x 10 days in 21 day cycles</description>
    <arm_group_label>Prexasertib and Irinotecan</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Consent/Assent: all patients and/or their parents or legally authorized
             representatives must sign written informed consent; assent, when appropriate, will be
             obtained according to institutional guidelines

          -  Age: patients must be ≥12 months of age at the time of study enrollment

          -  Diagnosis: patients must have histologically documented locally advanced or metastatic
             desmoplastic small round cell tumor or rhabdomyosarcoma (confirmed at MSK)

          -  Therapeutic options: patient's current disease state must be one which has failed
             standard therapy and for which there is no known curative therapy

          -  Disease Status: patients must have measurable disease based on RECIST 1.1

          -  Performance level: Karnofsky ≥ 50% for patients &gt; 16 years of age and Lansky ≥ 50 for
             patients ≤ 16 years of age

          -  Prior Therapy: patients may have had any number of prior therapies, but must have
             recovered from the acute toxic effects of all prior anti-cancer therapy (other than
             alopecia) as described below and must meet the following minimum duration from prior
             anti-cancer directed therapy prior to enrollment

             °patients who have previously received irinotecan and/or temozolomide will be allowed

               -  21 days must have elapsed after the last dose of cytotoxic or myelosuppressive
                  chemotherapy

               -  7 days must have elapsed after the last dose of anti-cancer agents not known to
                  be myelosuppressive

               -  14 days must have elapsed after radiation therapy, and toxicity related to prior
                  radiation therapy must be recovered to grade ≤ 1

               -  21 days must have elapsed after the last dose of antibody therapy, and toxicity
                  related to prior antibody therapy must be recovered to grade ≤ 1

          -  Organ Function Requirements: Adequate bone marrow function defined as:

               -  absolute neutrophil count (ANC) ≥ 1500/mm^3

               -  platelet count ≥ 100,000/ mm^3

               -  hemoglobin ≥ 8 g/dl

          -  Adequate renal function defined as:

               -  Creatinine clearance or radioisotope glomerular filtration rate ≥ 70
                  mL/min/1.73m2 OR

               -  Serum creatinine based on age/gender derived from the Schwartz formula for
                  estimating GFR53

          -  Adequate liver function defined as:

               -  Bilirubin (sum of conjugated + unconjugated) ≤ 1.5 x upper limit of normal for
                  age

               -  AST or ALT ≤ 5 x upper limit of normal for patients with liver metastases

               -  Serum albumin ≥ 2.5 g/dl

          -  Adequate cardiac function defined as:

               -  echocardiogram with left ventricular ejection fraction (LVEF) &gt;45%

               -  QTc &lt; 470 ms on screening 12 lead electrocardiogram

          -  Pregnancy/Contraception

               -  post-menarchal females must have a negative urine or serum pregnancy test at
                  screening and ≤ 24 hours prior to study treatment

               -  males or females of reproductive potential must be willing to use a barrier
                  method of contraception throughout the course of the study and for 6 months after
                  participation

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients for whom the investigator deems that irinotecan and temozolomide are not
             appropriate are not eligible.

          -  Patients who have an uncontrolled infection are not eligible.

          -  Patients who are pregnant or breast feeding are not eligible.

          -  Patients who have a history of Torsades de Pointes, carry a diagnosis of congestive
             heart failure, or have a family history of prolonged QT syndrome are not eligible.

          -  Patients who, in the opinion of the investigator, may not be able to comply with the
             safety monitoring requirements of the study are not eligible.

          -  Patients with known hypersensitivity to irinotecan or its excipients are not eligible.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>12 Months</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Emily Slotkin, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Emily Slotkin, MD</last_name>
    <phone>212-639-8856</phone>
    <email>slotkine@mskcc.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Williiam Tap, MD</last_name>
    <phone>646-888-4163</phone>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10065</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Emily Slotkin, MD</last_name>
      <phone>212-639-8856</phone>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>William Tap, MD</last_name>
      <phone>646-888-4163</phone>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Emily Slotkin, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.mskcc.org/mskcc/html/44.cfm</url>
    <description>Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>January 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 17, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 17, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 19, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 27, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 27, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 29, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Prexasertib</keyword>
  <keyword>Irinotecan</keyword>
  <keyword>Temozolomide</keyword>
  <keyword>19-120</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Rhabdomyosarcoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Desmoplastic Small Round Cell Tumor</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Irinotecan</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center supports the international committee of medical journal editors (ICMJE) and the ethical obligation of responsible sharing of data from clinical trials. The protocol summary, a statistical summary, and informed consent form will be made available on clinicaltrials.gov when required as a condition of Federal awards, other agreements supporting the research and/or as otherwise required. Requests for deidentified individual participant data can be made beginning 12 months after publication and for up to 36 months post publication. Deidentified individual participant data reported in the manuscript will be shared under the terms of a Data Use Agreement and may only be used for approved proposals. Requests may be made to: crdatashare@mskcc.org.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

