<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04099498</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>POCI-01-0145-FEDER-028302</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04099498</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>In-person and Online Healthy Eating Promotion Through Self-regulation (HEP-S)</brief_title>
  <acronym>HEP-S</acronym>
  <official_title>In-person and Online Healthy Eating Promotion Through Self-regulation (HEP-S): Assessing the Efficacy of a Narrative-based Intervention</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Minho</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Fundação para a Ciência e a Tecnologia</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Minho</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Obesity has more than doubled worldwide since 1980. The challenge with obesity, as with many
      other modern diseases, is that the solution may not rely on the medical side of the chain but
      rather on the individual via modifiable factors and behavioral changes such as eating habits
      and physical activity.

      The main goals of Healthy Eating Promotion with Self-regulation (HEP-S) are to design,
      implement, and evaluate the efficacy of an online intervention that promotes healthy eating
      among elementary school children using narratives involving self-regulation themes and
      skills. Self-regulation (SR) refers to the processes that allow individuals to proactively
      control the personal, behavioral, and environmental influences that impact their behavior,
      including eating. The focus of this project is not on delivering knowledge per se about
      healthy eating but rather on promoting and developing a set of transversal skills and
      strategies on the healthy habits' domain. We chose this focus because we recognized that
      beliefs about healthy eating have a stronger influence on eating behavior than factual
      knowledge about food. At the core of this intervention are the narratives, an important
      educational tool that favors child development; they allow readers to reflect on themselves
      and their behavior through the characters presented. Narratives also instigate the debate and
      the uncovering of different perspectives on how to cope with daily dilemmas. By using stories
      to initiate discussion and reflection, it is expected that a change of beliefs will occur,
      thus prompting a behavioral change.

      In today's world, there is an increasing need to dematerialise procedures so interventions
      can reach more people at a lower cost. Thus, it is important to test the feasibility of the
      online version of the intervention.

      Overall, it is expected that children taking part of the intervention will, at the end of the
      intervention, increase their use of SR strategies for healthy eating, enhance their sense of
      self-efficacy for healthy eating, and increase their consumption of healthy foods.
      Additionally, it is expected that their knowledge on the topic will increase, that their food
      preferences become healthier, and that they will display more positive perceptions and
      attitudes about the topic. Lastly, it is expected that participants enrolled in the
      enhanced-online-intervention group will be more engaged in the intervention than the
      online-intervention group.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      HEP-S program is grounded on the Self-regulation (SR) approach, which has several features
      that make it unique when it comes to health promotion. Grounded on Social Cognitive Theory,
      SR subsumes the processes that allow individuals to proactively control the personal,
      behavioural, and environmental influences that impact human behavior, including eating. These
      processes are intrinsically cyclic and interdependent, open and dynamic, and proceed through
      three main phases: the preceding phase, the performance or volitional control phase, and the
      self-reflection phase (or Planning, Execution, and Evaluation). The SR process is under the
      influence of the individual and can, therefore, be taught and improved. Thus, the agent role
      of the individual throughout the process is key to become in control and autonomous.

      Although individuals may be influenced and regulated by external factors and agents,
      exclusively relying on external regulation does not allow for the individual to develop
      adaptive competences and skills, such as choosing a healthy snack. Thus, to self-regulate
      their behaviour and become increasingly autonomous, individuals must progressively shift from
      external regulation to a model that supports and provides feedback. SR can be essential in
      the processes of healthy eating as individuals who SR their behavior are likely to plan and
      systematically use a set of cognitive and metacognitive strategies to meet self-set goals.
      Thus, the effective use of SR strategies to achieve one's goal is part of a key process in
      maintaining an individual's motivation to reach a self-set goal, such as eating healthily.

      In several studies, researchers have successfully implemented self-management programs among
      individuals with various health conditions, such as heart disease, or obesity. With the help
      of these programs, individuals were able to manage their health conditions and improve their
      quality of life and wellbeing. Still, these programs focused on health promotion within a
      disease management context, not on prevention and promotion of a healthy lifestyle. Thus, the
      current proposal will address this gap by focusing on healthy eating promotion among
      children.

      The HEP-S is a 20-week narrative-based intervention designed to promote healthy eating
      through the teaching and development of a set of transversal skills and strategies within
      that domain. The program will be implemented online using the online tool Canvas®. Canvas® is
      a learning management system that allows, among other things, to create modules of content,
      attach files, share materials, create discussion forums, and conduct videoconferences. Each
      child will be provided with a unique login to the Canvas® of the class. The program has two
      main components: i) the weekly synchronous session, which includes the reading of the
      chapter, the discussion and reflection about the lessons conveyed in the chapter, and the
      strengthening of learning through a consolidation activity; and ii) the weekly parental
      involvement activity, which is conceived to consolidate learning of the SR processes and
      skills.

      At the core of this intervention are the narratives. Narratives, or story-tools, are
      important educational tools that favor child development. They allow readers to reflect on
      themselves and their own behaviour through the characters; they instigate the debate and the
      uncovering of different perspectives of how to cope with every-day dilemmas. Through the
      characters and plots, these story-tools create opportunities from which the readers can
      experience and develop autonomous behaviors and promote SR in a given domain (e.g., learning,
      healthy eating). Extensive extant research has examined and demonstrated the efficacy of
      using story-tools to promote SR strategies. In this study, excerpts of two narratives will be
      used as the prompt for, and instigate, discussion and reflection about healthy eating.
      Specifically, Yellow's Trials and Tribulations, and The Hill of the Bald Trees and Other
      Stories.

      There will be two intervention groups: the online-intervention and
      enhanced-online-intervention. What differentiates these groups is that the
      enhanced-online-intervention group counts with the inclusion of gamification strategies
      within the dynamic of the program. Gamification consists in the use of game design elements
      in a non-game context. Non-game contexts can be education, health, and business. Examples of
      game design elements are the narrative context, feedback, reputation, ranks, levels,
      competition, relational support. Considering the engaging nature of games, it is expected
      that embedding some of their design and motivational features will contribute to the: i)
      creation of more engaging and fun contexts or environments; ii) enhancement of the degree and
      depth of participants' engagement; iii) promotion of learning opportunities; and iv) motivate
      individuals to engage in the task at hand.

      Goals and expected outcomes:

      The main purpose of this study is to evaluate the efficacy of an online intervention designed
      to promote healthy eating by fostering the use of SR strategies among school-aged children.
      Thus, the major goals are to promote children's use of SR strategies for healthy eating, to
      strengthen their sense of self-efficacy regarding healthy eating, to increase consumption and
      knowledge about healthy eating; to contribute to healthier food preferences; and contribute
      to more positive attitudes and perceptions about healthy eating. Concomitantly, we want to
      assess the feasibility of conducting an online intervention with this population and examine
      the advantages of embedding the program with gamification strategies.

      Overall, it is expected that children taking part of the intervention will increase their use
      of SR strategies for healthy eating, enhance their sense of self-efficacy for healthy eating,
      and increase their consumption of healthy foods. Additionally, it is expected that their
      knowledge on the topic will increase, and that they will display more positive perceptions
      and attitudes about the topic. Lastly, it is expected that participants enrolled in the
      enhanced-online-intervention group will be more engaged in the intervention than the
      online-intervention group.

      Participants:

      Children from the 5th and 6th grades will be recruited by first contacting Portuguese
      elementary and middle schools and inviting them to participate. Orientation sessions will be
      held at schools for all parents of children in the target grades to explain the project and
      its rationale, and to invite them to enroll their child. The study will be introduced as a
      program to promote healthy lifestyles among school-aged children, which aims to monitor
      relevant engagement variables and examine children's, parents', and teachers' perceptions of
      the utility and feasibility of these interventions.

      Retention and incentives for the participants:

      The following strategies will be undertaken to minimize attrition. First, prior to the
      intervention, the researchers will organize orientation sessions with parents to present the
      project and explain its pertinence and rationale. Second, parents who agree to let their
      child participate in the program will sign a participation agreement detailing their
      responsibility as guarantors of their child's involvement in the program. Third, the
      registration e-mail for children to log in into the platform will be of their parents, and
      reminder emails will be sent whenever there is an activity or task available in the platform.
      Lastly, check-up sessions with parents will be carried mid-through the program.

      Informed consent and randomization:

      During the orientation session, parents who allow their child to participate in the program
      will complete the first assessment protocol in loco, as well as complete the informed consent
      form. In the informed consent, the following aspects will be covered: i) description of the
      program, accompanied by a timeline; ii) duties of the parents as guarantors of their child's
      involvement in the program; and iii) what it is expected from them in terms of their
      involvement with the program and its activities. Genuine randomization at the individual
      level will not be possible as participants originating from the same class and school will
      have to be allocated to the same treatment condition to prevent between-group contamination.
      To address this difficulty, each school that accepts to enroll in the study will be randomly
      attributed a number associated with one of the conditions (i.e. control, intervention, and
      enhanced-intervention) in a 1:1:1 basis.

      Proposed sample size:

      Considering this longitudinal design, the sample size was computed using G*Power software. In
      the calculation of the sample, we considered a 0.2 effect size, an alpha level of 0.05, a
      desired statistical power of 0.8, five measures, three research groups (i.e. control,
      online-intervention, enhanced-online-intervention), and a 20% dropout rate. This analysis
      suggested that a total of 150 participants will be recruited, with 50 participants per group.

      Statistics:

      Descriptive analyses will be computed to describe all participants' characteristics.
      Specifically, we will use chi-square tests and independent t-tests to compare groups on the
      distributions according to sex, age group, BMI classification and others. To assess the
      effectiveness of the HEP-S intervention program, we will develop linear mixed-effect models
      to specifically assess groups differences over time. All analyses will be conducted using
      SPSS, and p values below .05 will be considered statistically significant.

      Blinding and data access:

      The assessment protocol will be completed by children and will not be available for parents
      to consult or to the educational psychologist conducting the sessions. Each child will be
      attributed a unique code. Moreover, data will be analyzed by an external statistician who
      will be blind to the treatment conditions of each data set. Lastly, only the principal
      investigator and the statistician will have access to the full data set.

      The standard procedure to conduct studies in the Portuguese school context requires an a
      priori evaluation and validation of the project by the Ministry of Education and by the
      Ethics Committee of the University of Minho before researchers can invite schools to
      participate. Participation in the program is entirely voluntary, and parents and children are
      informed that their involvement in the school's activities will not be affected by their
      decision on whether or not to participate. Parents and children are informed they can
      withdraw from the program at any time. We fully recognize our responsibilities for child
      protection, so the project will ensure an environment where children feel secure, feel free
      to either participate or leave the study at any time, are encouraged to talk, and are
      listened to. In order to work with children, researchers must present their criminal records
      during the job application. This protocol will be held to meet high ethical standards.

      Lastly, the procedures for personal data storage, handling, and protection will comply with
      the newest General Data Protection Regulation policies. Particularly, to ensure privacy and
      anonymity, pseudonymisation will be carried out. This is a process that transforms personal
      data into a data set that cannot be linked to a particular subject unless other piece of
      information is added (e.g., decryption key). Usually, these data are stored in different
      locations.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 27, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>A three-armed randomized controlled trial will be conducted and will include: a standard control group, with no intervention; an online-intervention group, with the program for 20-weeks; and an enhanced-online-intervention group, with the program for 20-weeks embedded with gamification strategies throughout.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Socio-demographic Questionnaire.</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline</time_frame>
    <description>The participants will be asked about their gender, age and grade.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of Self-Regulation Processes towards Healthy Eating at 20 weeks from baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>20 weeks after baseline</time_frame>
    <description>An adapted version of the Self-Regulation for Health Scale. (Mattos, et. al. 2018) was used to evaluate the self-regulation processes towards healthy eating that participants are guided by. The scale has nine statements regarding the participant's self-regulation towards healthy eating (e.g., I pay attention to information on healthy eating, I apply that knowledge on a daily basis). Responses are scored from 1 (never) to 5 (always) on a Likert-like scale and summed to create a composite score from nine to 45, with higher scores implying more self-regulation.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of Self-Regulation Processes towards Healthy Eating at 3 months from the end of the intervention</measure>
    <time_frame>3-months after end of the intervention</time_frame>
    <description>An adapted version of the Self-Regulation for Health Scale. (Mattos, et. al. 2018) was used to evaluate the self-regulation processes towards healthy eating that participants are guided by. The scale has nine statements regarding the participant's self-regulation towards healthy eating (e.g., I pay attention to information on healthy eating, I apply that knowledge on a daily basis). Responses are scored from 1 (never) to 5 (always) on a Likert-like scale and summed to create a composite score from nine to 45, with higher scores implying more self-regulation.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of Self-Regulation Processes towards Healthy Eating at 6-months after the last assessment</measure>
    <time_frame>6-months after the last assessment</time_frame>
    <description>An adapted version of the Self-Regulation for Health Scale. (Mattos, et. al. 2018) was used to evaluate the self-regulation processes towards healthy eating that participants are guided by. The scale has nine statements regarding the participant's self-regulation towards healthy eating (e.g., I pay attention to information on healthy eating, I apply that knowledge on a daily basis). Responses are scored from 1 (never) to 5 (always) on a Likert-like scale and summed to create a composite score from nine to 45, with higher scores implying more self-regulation.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of Students' Attitudes and Perceptions on Healthy Eating at 20 weeks from the baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>20 weeks after baseline</time_frame>
    <description>An adaptation of the Students' Attitudes and Perceptions on the Health Instrument (Mattos et al., 2018) will be used. This instrument has 17 statements about student's attitudes and perceptions of the importance of healthy eating (e.g., Eating fruit and vegetables will help me growing up). Responses are scored as true or false, and the correct answers will be summed to create a composite score that ranged from 0 to 17, with higher scores implying more positive attitudes through healthy eating.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of Students' Attitudes and Perceptions on Healthy Eatingat 3 months from the end of the intervention</measure>
    <time_frame>3-months after end of the intervention</time_frame>
    <description>An adaptation of the Students' Attitudes and Perceptions on the Health Instrument (Mattos et al., 2018) will be used. This instrument has 17 statements about student's attitudes and perceptions of the importance of healthy eating (e.g., Eating fruit and vegetables will help me growing up). Responses are scored as true or false, and the correct answers will be summed to create a composite score that ranged from 0 to 17, with higher scores implying more positive attitudes through healthy eating.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of Students' Attitudes and Perceptions on Healthy Eating at 6-months after the last assessment</measure>
    <time_frame>6-months after the last assessment</time_frame>
    <description>An adaptation of the Students' Attitudes and Perceptions on the Health Instrument (Mattos et al., 2018) will be used. This instrument has 17 statements about student's attitudes and perceptions of the importance of healthy eating (e.g., Eating fruit and vegetables will help me growing up). Responses are scored as true or false, and the correct answers will be summed to create a composite score that ranged from 0 to 17, with higher scores implying more positive attitudes through healthy eating.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of Knowledge of Healthy Eating at 20 weeks from the baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>20 weeks from the baseline</time_frame>
    <description>This questionnaire was developed to assess school-age children's (six to 17 years old) declarative knowledge about healthy eating (Pereira, et al. 2018). The questionnaire was built by a team comprised by several specialists (psychologists, teachers, medical doctors, and nurses) and the items were based on the directives by the Portuguese General Directorate for Health (DGS, 2017). The questionnaire consists of 15 statements and participants had to rate their agreement regarding each statement (e.g., &quot;our meal should contain varied and colourful foods&quot;; &quot;going to school without having breakfast does not interfere with my school performance&quot;). Responses to individual items were scored from one (totally disagree) to five (totally agree) in a Likert-like format. The alpha of Cronbach was .73. Responses of each participant were summed to create a composite score ranging from 15 to 75, with higher scores implying more knowledge of healthy eating.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change od Knowledge of Healthy Eating at 3 months from the end of the intervention</measure>
    <time_frame>3-months after end of the intervention</time_frame>
    <description>This questionnaire was developed to assess school-age children's (six to 17 years old) declarative knowledge about healthy eating (Pereira, et al. 2018). The questionnaire was built by a team comprised by several specialists (psychologists, teachers, medical doctors, and nurses) and the items were based on the directives by the Portuguese General Directorate for Health (DGS, 2017). The questionnaire consists of 15 statements and participants had to rate their agreement regarding each statement (e.g., &quot;our meal should contain varied and colourful foods&quot;; &quot;going to school without having breakfast does not interfere with my school performance&quot;). Responses to individual items were scored from one (totally disagree) to five (totally agree) in a Likert-like format. The alpha of Cronbach was .73. Responses of each participant were summed to create a composite score ranging from 15 to 75, with higher scores implying more knowledge of healthy eating.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of Knowledge of Healthy Eating at 6-months after the last assessment</measure>
    <time_frame>6-months after the last assessment</time_frame>
    <description>This questionnaire was developed to assess school-age children's (six to 17 years old) declarative knowledge about healthy eating (Pereira, et al. 2018). The questionnaire was built by a team comprised by several specialists (psychologists, teachers, medical doctors, and nurses) and the items were based on the directives by the Portuguese General Directorate for Health (DGS, 2017). The questionnaire consists of 15 statements and participants had to rate their agreement regarding each statement (e.g., &quot;our meal should contain varied and colourful foods&quot;; &quot;going to school without having breakfast does not interfere with my school performance&quot;). Responses to individual items were scored from one (totally disagree) to five (totally agree) in a Likert-like format. The alpha of Cronbach was .73. Responses of each participant were summed to create a composite score ranging from 15 to 75, with higher scores implying more knowledge of healthy eating.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of Self-Efficacy to Regulate Eating Habits for Children at 20 weeks from the baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>20 weeks after baseline</time_frame>
    <description>We will use an adaptation of the questionnaire &quot;Self-Efficacy to Regulate Eating Habits&quot; developed by Bandura (2005) in this project. The measure will assess the perceived capability to regulate and to adopt healthy eating habits in different daily situations (e.g., &quot;While watching television&quot;). This version consists in 15 adapted situations, in which participants will have to respond if they can choose healthy food choices or not in a Likert-like format, scored from one (not capable) to six (capable, for sure).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of Self-Efficacy to Regulate Eating Habits for Children at 3 months from the end of the intervention</measure>
    <time_frame>3-months after end of the intervention</time_frame>
    <description>We will use an adaptation of the questionnaire &quot;Self-Efficacy to Regulate Eating Habits&quot; developed by Bandura (2005) in this project. The measure will assess the perceived capability to regulate and to adopt healthy eating habits in different daily situations (e.g., &quot;While watching television&quot;). This version consists in 15 adapted situations, in which participants will have to respond if they can choose healthy food choices or not in a Likert-like format, scored from one (not capable) to six (capable, for sure).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of Self-Efficacy to Regulate Eating Habits for Children at 6 months after the end of the last assessment</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months after the end of the last assessment</time_frame>
    <description>We will use an adaptation of the questionnaire &quot;Self-Efficacy to Regulate Eating Habits&quot; developed by Bandura (2005) in this project. The measure will assess the perceived capability to regulate and to adopt healthy eating habits in different daily situations (e.g., &quot;While watching television&quot;). This version consists in 15 adapted situations, in which participants will have to respond if they can choose healthy food choices or not in a Likert-like format, scored from one (not capable) to six (capable, for sure).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of Healthy Eating and Physical Activity Self-Efficacy in children at 20 weeks after baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>20 weeks after baseline</time_frame>
    <description>This measure was developed to assess self-efficacy related to enacting healthy eating and activity behaviours in children (Lassetter et al., 2017). An adapted version of the HEPASEQ-C was developed and consists of nine items with response options on a 6-point Likert-type scale, ranging from &quot;There is no way I can do this&quot; to &quot;I believe I can do this&quot;. Seven items focus on self-efficacy related to healthy eating. For example, one item says, &quot;I will eat healthy food even when my friends eat food that is not healthy.&quot;</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of Healthy Eating and Physical Activity Self-Efficacy in children at 3 months after the end of the intervention</measure>
    <time_frame>3-months after end of the intervention</time_frame>
    <description>This measure was developed to assess self-efficacy related to enacting healthy eating and activity behaviours in children (Lassetter et al., 2017). An adapted version of the HEPASEQ-C was developed and consists of nine items with response options on a 6-point Likert-type scale, ranging from &quot;There is no way I can do this&quot; to &quot;I believe I can do this&quot;. Seven items focus on self-efficacy related to healthy eating. For example, one item says, &quot;I will eat healthy food even when my friends eat food that is not healthy.&quot;</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of Healthy Eating and Physical Activity Self-Efficacy in children at 6 months after the end of the last assessment</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months after end of the last assessment</time_frame>
    <description>This measure was developed to assess self-efficacy related to enacting healthy eating and activity behaviours in children (Lassetter et al., 2017). An adapted version of the HEPASEQ-C was developed and consists of nine items with response options on a 6-point Likert-type scale, ranging from &quot;There is no way I can do this&quot; to &quot;I believe I can do this&quot;. Seven items focus on self-efficacy related to healthy eating. For example, one item says, &quot;I will eat healthy food even when my friends eat food that is not healthy.&quot;</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of the Healthy Eating and Physical Activity Behaviour Recall for Children at 20 weeks after baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>20 weeks after baseline</time_frame>
    <description>This measure was developed as a complement to the previous questionnaire and aimed to recall 'children's behaviors in terms of healthy eating and physical activity (Lassetter et al., 2017). The Portuguese version of this questionnaire consists of 9 items, two of which are in an open response format allowing children to write the actual foods they ate. For example, one of these two items states, &quot;The last time I ate a snack at a friend's house, I ate __________.&quot; The other seven items include two yes/no items, and the remaining six items had response options that were presented using an ordinal scale.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of Healthy Eating and Physical Activity Behaviour Recall for Children at 3-months after end of the intervention</measure>
    <time_frame>3-months after end of the intervention</time_frame>
    <description>This measure was developed as a complement to the previous questionnaire and aimed to recall 'children's behaviors in terms of healthy eating and physical activity (Lassetter et al., 2017). The Portuguese version of this questionnaire consists of 9 items, two of which are in an open response format allowing children to write the actual foods they ate. For example, one of these two items states, &quot;The last time I ate a snack at a friend's house, I ate __________.&quot; The other seven items include two yes/no items, and the remaining six items had response options that were presented using an ordinal scale.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of Healthy Eating and Physical Activity Behaviour Recall for Children at 6 months after end of the last assessment</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months after end of the last assessment</time_frame>
    <description>This measure was developed as a complement to the previous questionnaire and aimed to recall 'children's behaviors in terms of healthy eating and physical activity (Lassetter et al., 2017). The Portuguese version of this questionnaire consists of 9 items, two of which are in an open response format allowing children to write the actual foods they ate. For example, one of these two items states, &quot;The last time I ate a snack at a friend's house, I ate __________.&quot; The other seven items include two yes/no items, and the remaining six items had response options that were presented using an ordinal scale.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Weekly Diary</measure>
    <time_frame>20 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Each child will use a weekly diary to set goals, plan activities, and monitor his or her own performance. This will allow monitoring the individual progress of children in the program and, simultaneously, to create another moment to reflect about, and consolidate, the learning acquired in the program. Questions will invite children to reflect on what they have learn with the narrative, the synchronous session, and the parental involvement activity of that week. Additionally, questions regarding participants' engagement in the program that week will also be included. Lastly, concrete questions about their food intake will also be covered in the weekly journal.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Satisfaction Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>20 Weeks after the baseline</time_frame>
    <description>The research team will develop a satisfaction questionnaire based on previous satisfaction instruments used with this population. The questionnaire will address aspects of utility and feasibility of the program and perceived support by the educational psychologist from the students' perspective.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Engagement Assessment</measure>
    <time_frame>20 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Engagement in the program will be assessed through the analysis of the interactions of children in the online platform. Examples include number of activities completed, comments to peers' posts.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">150</enrollment>
  <condition>Healthy Eating</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Standard Control group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>This group will not partake in the intervention but will be assessed with the same protocol at the same moments.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Online-Intervention group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>This group will take part of the 20-week long online intervention to promote healthy eating. The program will be developed to promote self-regulation skills and strategies about healthy eating among elementary school-aged children and each week will include: i) a narrative embedded with self-regulation skills and strategies; ii) a weekly parental involvement activity; and iii) a weekly group synchronous videoconference session with a trained educational psychologist serving as a mediator.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Enhanced-online-Intervention Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>This group will take part of the 20-week long online intervention to promote healthy eating. The program will be developed to promote self-regulation skills and strategies about healthy eating among elementary school-aged children and each week will include: i) a narrative embedded with self-regulation skills and strategies; ii) a weekly parental involvement activity; and iii) a weekly group synchronous videoconference session with a trained educational psychologist serving as a mediator. In addition, gamification strategies (e.g., points for each complete activity, feedback) will be implemented in order to promote engagement with the program and activities.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Online Program: Healthy Eating Promotion with Self-regulation</intervention_name>
    <description>Online-Intervention group</description>
    <arm_group_label>Online-Intervention group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Enhanced Online Program: Healthy Eating Promotion with Self-regulation</intervention_name>
    <description>Enhanced-online-Intervention Group</description>
    <arm_group_label>Enhanced-online-Intervention Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Access to a computer equipped with camera and speakers at home;

          -  Internet access at home;

          -  Children have to read, speak and write Portuguese fluently;

          -  Parents have to provide a written consent for their children to participate;

          -  Children have to provide a written agreement of willingness to participate;

          -  Parent have to sign the informed consent;

          -  Parents have to be willing to participate in the parental involvement activities;

          -  Parents have to have an e-mail account or be willing to create one;

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Any acute or chronic condition, or learning disabilities that would limit the ability
             of the patient to participate in the study

          -  Refusal to give informed consent
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>10 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>12 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Paula Magalhaes, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Psychology Research Cente r (CIPsi) of University of Minho</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Paula Magalhaes, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>912546250</phone>
    <email>pcsmagalhaes@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Pedro Rosário, PhD</last_name>
    <email>prosario@psi.uminho.pt</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>School of Psychology, University of Minho</name>
      <address>
        <city>Braga</city>
        <country>Portugal</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Paula Magalhães, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Portugal</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.guia-psi.com/hep-s.html</url>
    <description>Research group website</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bandura A. Health promotion by social cognitive means. Health Educ Behav. 2004 Apr;31(2):143-64.</citation>
    <PMID>15090118</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zimmerman BJ. Self-Efficacy: An Essential Motive to Learn. Contemp Educ Psychol. 2000 Jan;25(1):82-91.</citation>
    <PMID>10620383</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Clark NM, Zimmerman BJ. A social cognitive view of self-regulated learning about health. Health Educ Behav. 2014 Oct;41(5):485-91. doi: 10.1177/1090198114547512.</citation>
    <PMID>25270173</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rosário P, Mourao R, Núñez JC, González-Pienda J, Solano P, Valle A. [Evaluating the efficacy of a program to enhance college students' self-regulation learning processes and learning strategies]. Psicothema. 2007 Aug;19(3):422-7. Spanish.</citation>
    <PMID>17617980</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>November 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 17, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 20, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 23, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 23, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 23, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 24, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Minho</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Paula Cristina Soares de Magalhães da Silva Correia</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Junior Researcher</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Self-regulation</keyword>
  <keyword>Healthy eating</keyword>
  <keyword>Online</keyword>
  <keyword>Promotion</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

