<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04099017</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IPM&amp;R/DUHS-19/</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04099017</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Mulligan Manual Therapy and Trunk Stabilization Exercises Versus Isometric Knee Strengthening on Knee Osteoarthritis</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effectiveness of Mulligan Joint Mobilizations and Trunk Stabilization Exercises Versus Isometric Knee Strengthening in the Management of Knee Osteoarthritis: a Randomized Controlled Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Dow University of Health Sciences</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Dow University of Health Sciences</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Knee joint arthritis posses a serious health problem and caring for an individual with knee
      osteoarthritis (KOA) produces a great burden on society. Knee joint pain is associated with
      physical activity while performing various activities of daily living (ADL) in patients with
      early and severe osteoarthritis (OA). In addition to knee pain, physical function or daily
      activity is strongly influenced by the severity of Osteoarthritis of the knee. Mulligan joint
      mobilization with movement provides evident effects on decreasing the pain and restoring the
      joint biomechanics. Trunk stabilization exercise will improve the stability of trunk which
      distributes the weight of body evenly on both feets. The aim of this study is to determine
      the effects of mulligan joint mobilization and trunk stabilization exercise on pain,
      disability and submaximal exercise performance in KOA.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      A randomized control trial will be conducted at IPM&amp;R on 60 subjects with knee osteoarthritis
      and age between 40-60 years. Initial screening of the subjects will be carried out by the
      referring consultant. Subjects who fulfilled the study criteria will be recruited using
      computer generated random sampling after explaining the study objective and taken written
      informed consent. All participants will be evaluated using visual analogue scale, Knee injury
      and Osteoarthritis Outcome Score and 6-minute walk test for pain severity, functional
      limitation and submaximal exercise capacity at 1st, 3rd and 6th week. The subjects will be
      allocated into three groups through computer generated random allocation. Group 1 will
      receive mulligan mobilization with kinesiotaping and knee strengthening. Group 2 will receive
      trunk stabilization exercise, knee strengthening and Kinesiotaping. Group 3 will receive knee
      strengthening along with kinesiotaping. A drop-out rate of 9 will be taken. Recorded data
      will be entered and analysed using SPSS version 21. Mean and SD will be calculated of
      quantitative variables like age, pain, knee related function, submaximal exercise capacity
      and stair climb by using repeated measure ANOVA. For pair wise comparison, post hoc tukey
      will be applied. Value of equal to or less than 0.05 will be considered significant.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 20, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>After confirming eligibility, the physiotherapist performing intervention obtained treatment assignment (S.S. Ali). The subject will not be aware of the group allocation and different time slot will be given for the intervention. Another physiotherapist who will not be aware of allocation concealment, record the reading of outcomes at the baseline, after three and six weeks</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline Knee injury and Osteoarthritis Outcome Score (KOOS) at 6 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and post intervention (week 6 - the analysis will be conducted on the first week immediately after the end of the training</time_frame>
    <description>The Knee injury and Osteoarthritis Outcome Score (KOOS) is a self reported specific joint measure developed to assess a broad spectrum of patients with knee injuries and OA, for pain and other symptoms, function in daily life, function in sports and recreation, and quality of knee-related life, being easy to use, evaluating the short- and long-term health problems related to the knee joint.
The KOOS contains 42 items covering five subscales: pain, other symptoms, activities of daily living, sport and leisure activities and quality of life. A score of 0 (extreme problems) 100 (smoothly) can be obtained separately for each sub-range.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Visual Analogue Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 3 weeks and 6 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>It measures the subjective of pain ranges from 10-cm lines with defined cut off scores. The correlation between vertical and horizontal orientations of the VAS is 0.99 . Aggregate score ranges for this screening tool starting with 0-10. Scores between 0-4 means mild pain. Scores between 4-7 indicates moderate pain. Scores between 7-10 means severe pain. pain severity will be assessed at rest and during stairs ascending and descending</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Knee injury and Osteoarthritis Outcome Score (KOOS)</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 3 weeks and 6 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The Knee injury and Osteoarthritis Outcome Score (KOOS) is a self reported specific joint measure developed to assess a broad spectrum of patients with knee injuries and OA, for pain and other symptoms, function in daily life, function in sports and recreation, and quality of knee-related life, being easy to use, evaluating the short- and long-term health problems related to the knee joint.
The KOOS contains 42 items covering five subscales: pain, other symptoms, activities of daily living, sport and leisure activities and quality of life. A score of 0 (extreme problems) 100 (smoothly) can be obtained separately for each sub-range.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>6 Minute Walk Test</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 3 weeks and 6 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The 6-min walk test (6 MWT) is a submaximal exercise test that entails measurement of distance walked over a span of 6 minutes. Bright colour tapes will be used to mark the 12m walkway at each end. It will be ensured that the environment will be free from hazards and readings will be recorded by blind assessor. Participant will be instructed to wear comfortable shoes.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Stairs Climb Test</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 3 weeks and 6 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Stair climb test is used to measure the total time taken by the participant to ascend and descend stair onto with a step length of 16-cm (ICC=0.90). If safety is of concern, the assessor should guard behind the participant going up the stairs and to the side coming down the stairs. If there is no concern for safety, the tester should remain at the start/finish position on the ground landing</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Osteoarthritis, Knee</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Mulligan mobilization group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>This study ARM will received Mulligan joint mobilization and concomitant therapies in this group.
The following are the brief detail of therapy
Mulligan joint mobilization in Non-weight bearing (NWB):
Knee strengthening
Kinesiotaping</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Trunk stabilization group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>This study ARM will received Trunk stabilization exercises and concomitant therapies in this group.
The following are the brief detail of therapy:
Trunk stabilization i. modified supermen extension exercise ii. Back bridge: iii. Unilateral back bridge:
Iv. lateral step up:
Knee strengthening i. Isometric quadriceps exercise: ii. Straight leg raising (SLR) exercise:
Kinesiotaping:</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Knee strengthening group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>This study ARM will received Knee strengthening exercises and concomitant therapies in this group.
The following are the brief detail of therapy:
Knee strengthening i. Isometric quadriceps exercise ii. Straight leg raising (SLR) exercise:
Kinesio-taping:</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Mulligan Joint mobilization</intervention_name>
    <description>This study ARM will received Mulligan joint mobilization and concomitant therapies in this group.
The following are the brief detail of therapy
Mulligan joint mobilization in Non-weight bearing (NWB) to weight-bearing (WB) 6 -10 Reps and 3 sets/ session.
Procedural detail:
Joint mobilization will be performed in sagittal, frontal and transverse direction, following glide will be preferred will depend on patient adherence to the joint mobilization. Mobilization will be progress from NWB to WB according to patient compliance 27
Knee strengthening Type of exercise: Knee Isometric Strengthening exercises. Intensity: 10 reps Frequency: At 1st week one set of all knee exercise will be performed then it will be progressed to 2 sets at 3 weeks, and these exercises will be progressed to three sets until the 6 weeks
Kinesiotaping:</description>
    <arm_group_label>Mulligan mobilization group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Trunk stabilization group</intervention_name>
    <description>This study ARM will received Trunk stabilization exercises and concomitant therapies in this group.
The following are the brief detail of therapy:
Trunk stabilization Area: Trunk Type of exercise: Stabilization exercise Intensity: 6-8 reps Frequency: 3 sets per session and 30 second duration break between sets
Procedural detail:
i. modified supermen extension exercise ii. Back bridge: iii. Unilateral back bridge:
Iv. lateral step up:
Knee strengthening Area: Knee Joint Type of exercise: Knee Isometric Strengthening exercises. Intensity: 10 reps Frequency: At 1st week one set of all knee exercise will be performed then it will be progressed to 2 sets at 3 weeks, and these exercises will be progressed to three sets until the 6 weeks
Procedural detail:
i. Isometric quadriceps exercise: ii. Straight leg raising (SLR) exercise:
Kinesiotaping:</description>
    <arm_group_label>Trunk stabilization group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Knee strengthening group</intervention_name>
    <description>This study ARM will received Knee strengthening exercises and concomitant therapies in this group.
The following are the brief detail of therapy:
Knee strengthening Area: Knee Joint Type of exercise: Knee Isometric Strengthening exercises. Intensity: 10 reps Frequency: At 1st week one set of all knee exercise will be performed then it will be progressed to 2 sets at 3 weeks, and these exercises will be progressed to three sets until the 6 weeks
Procedural detail:
i. Isometric quadriceps exercise ii. Straight leg raising (SLR) exercise:
Kinesio-taping:
Muscle stretch method will be applied which involves one Y and two I straps: The Y-shaped tape base will be affixed over the top of patella then pulls up his/her knee to its maximum bending capacity then both end of Y strip is placed around the patella ending on the tibial tuberosity. Then reinforcing I-tape will be affixed at the origin and insertion of MCL and LCL. Tape will be change in every session.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Knee strengthening group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  - Both gender (female and male) patients

          -  Age between 40 - 60

          -  Knee osteoarthritis Grade I &amp; II on Kellgren and Lawrence (K/L) criteria

          -  Prediagnosed case of knee OA as per the American College of Rheumatology (ACR).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Known skin allergies

          -  Sensory-motor dysfunction of lower extremity

          -  Severe joint deformity of lower extremity

          -  Post Traumatic Arthritis

          -  Constitutional Symptoms (Fever, Malaise, Weight Loss and high blood pressure)

          -  Knee Intraarticular injection in past 3 months

          -  Acute low back pain

          -  History of spinal surgery

          -  Subject using assistive devices for ambulation i.e. cane, walkers, sticks

          -  Refused to give consent

          -  Body Mass Index &gt; 30 kg/m2

          -  Received physiotherapy treatment in the past 3 months

          -  Visual Analogue Scale &lt;4

          -  Patellofemoral joint arthritis will be excluded
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>40 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>60 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>SHAIKH NABI B NAZIR, MSAPT</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Dow University of Health Sciences</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>SHAIKH NABI B NAZIR, MSAPT</last_name>
    <phone>03432883538</phone>
    <email>nabibux_903@hotmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Dow University of Health Sciences &amp; Institute of Physical Medicine and Rehabilitation</name>
      <address>
        <city>Karachi</city>
        <state>Sindh</state>
        <zip>74200</zip>
        <country>Pakistan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>SHAIKH NABI BUKHSH NAZIR, DPT,MSAPT*</last_name>
      <phone>03432883538</phone>
      <email>nabibux_903@hotmail.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Pakistan</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nam CW, Park SI, Yong MS, Kim YM. Effects of the MWM Technique Accompanied by Trunk Stabilization Exercises on Pain and Physical Dysfunctions Caused by Degenerative Osteoarthritis. J Phys Ther Sci. 2013 Sep;25(9):1137-40. doi: 10.1589/jpts.25.1137. Epub 2013 Oct 20.</citation>
    <PMID>24259931</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 18, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 19, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 23, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 20, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 20, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 21, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Dow University of Health Sciences</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Shaikh Nabi Bukhsh Nazir</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>manual therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>kinesiotape</keyword>
  <keyword>Excercise therapies</keyword>
  <keyword>isometric contraction</keyword>
  <keyword>muscle strength</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Osteoarthritis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Osteoarthritis, Knee</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>All of the individual participant data collected during the trial, after deidentification.</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Statistical Analysis Plan (SAP)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Informed Consent Form (ICF)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Clinical Study Report (CSR)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Analytic Code</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>Beginning 3 months and ending 3 years following article publication.</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>Researchers who provide a methodologically sound proposal.</ipd_access_criteria>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

