<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04096053</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>00036238</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04096053</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Transgender Education for Affirmative and Competent HIV and Healthcare</brief_title>
  <acronym>TEACHH</acronym>
  <official_title>'Transgender Education for Affirmative and Competent HIV and Healthcare (TEACHH)': Protocol of Community-based Participatory Intervention Development and a Non-randomized Multi-site Pilot Study With Pre- Post-test Design</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Toronto</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Toronto</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Educational workshops are an efficacious strategy to increase healthcare providers' ability
      to provide gender-affirming care for transgender (trans) people. This strategy may also
      reduce healthcare providers' stigma towards trans people and people living with HIV. There is
      less evidence, however, of educational workshops that address HIV prevention and care among
      trans women. This protocol details the development and pilot testing of the TEACHH:
      Transgender Education for Affirmative and Competent HIV and Healthcare intervention that aims
      to increase gender-affirming HIV care competency among healthcare providers.This
      community-based research (CBR) project involves intervention development and implementation
      of a non-randomized multi-site pilot study with pre- post-test design. First, the
      investigators will conduct a qualitative formative phase involving focus groups with 30 trans
      women and individual interviews with 12 providers to understand HIV care access barriers for
      trans women and elicit feedback on a proposed workshop. Second, the investigators will pilot
      test the intervention with 90-150 providers (n=30-50x3 in-person settings). Primary outcomes
      include feasibility (e.g., completion rate), workshop satisfaction, and willingness to attend
      another workshop. Secondary pre- and post-intervention outcomes, assessed directly preceding
      and following the workshop, include perceived competency, intention to provide
      gender-affirming HIV care, and attitudes/biases towards trans women with HIV. Primary
      outcomes will be summarized as frequencies and proportions (categorical variables) and means
      and standard deviations (continuous variables). The investigators will conduct paired-sample
      t tests to assess pre- and post-intervention differences for secondary outcomes.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 1, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 31, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 31, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Health Services Research</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Workshop Recruitment Rate</measure>
    <time_frame>3 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Number of people who participate in the workshop / Number of people invited to participate in the workshop</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Workshop Completion Rate</measure>
    <time_frame>3 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Number of people who finish all 3 hours of the workshop / Number of people who start the workshop</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Survey completion rate</measure>
    <time_frame>3 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Number of people who complete the post-survey/Number of people who complete the pre-survey</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Satisfaction with the workshop</measure>
    <time_frame>3 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Measured in two ways - satisfaction scale and willingness to attend another workshop on trans women with HIV</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>attitudes/biases, perceived competency, and behavioral intention to provide gender- affirming HIV care to trans women living with HIV</measure>
    <time_frame>3 hours</time_frame>
    <description>a scale adapted from (1) Nyblade et al.'s brief, standardized tool for measuring HIV- related stigma among health facility staff and (2) trans-specific questions from Bidell's Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual, and Transgender Development of Clinical Skills Scale (LGBT-DOCSS), an interdisciplinary self-assessment for health providers</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">150</enrollment>
  <condition>Stigma, Social</condition>
  <condition>HIV/AIDS</condition>
  <condition>Health Care Acceptability</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>TEACHH</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The training workshop is designed as a 3-hour session for care providers. The training will be delivered by trans women. During this training, we plan to have providers: 1) discuss human rights for trans women; 2) teach providers about common words with which to discuss gender identity and expression, and develop a basic understanding of trans healthcare, HIV prevention, and HIV treatment, and how these types of healthcare affect trans women living with and affected by HIV; 3) discuss what it means to be trans-affirming in their work and how they can make their organizations more trans- affirming; and 4) have participants complete a case study to apply what they have learned to practice. These case studies will address issues affecting trans women who are immigrants/newcomers, trans women who are living with HIV, and trans women who experience other vulnerabilities.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>TEACHH</intervention_name>
    <description>See arm/group description.</description>
    <arm_group_label>TEACHH</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Workshop participants must be 18 years or older and identify as working at a location
             that provides health or social services to trans women or being in-training to work in
             health or social services (e.g., medical student, social work student). Workshop
             participants may include a mix of HIV- and non-HIV service providers.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Not fitting the above criteria.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Carmen H Logie</last_name>
    <phone>(416) 946-3365</phone>
    <email>carmen.logie@utoronto.ca</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Factor-Inwentash Faculty of Social Work, University of Toronto</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toronto</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>M5S1V4</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Carmen H Logie, PhD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 16, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 17, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 19, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 17, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 17, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">September 19, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Toronto</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Carmen Logie, MSW, PhD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Acquired Immunodeficiency Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>HIV Infections</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

