<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04099511</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2015868</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>R01HD097283</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04099511</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Metacognitive-Strategy Training in Sub-Acute Stroke</brief_title>
  <official_title>Efficacy of Metacognitive-Strategy Training to Improve Activity Performance and Reduce Motor Impairment in Sub-Acute Stroke</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Missouri-Columbia</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Eunice Kennedy Shriver National Institute of Child Health and Human Development (NICHD)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Michigan</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Missouri-Columbia</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The long-term goal of this research is to improve activity performance and reduce motor
      impairment in individuals with stroke. Contemporary stroke rehabilitation focuses on
      remediation of post-stroke impairments with a false assumption that reduction in impairments
      will automatically lead to improvements in activity performance. Specifically, stroke
      rehabilitation is focused primarily on the use of task-specific training (TST), which recent
      research has found to yield negligible improvement in upper extremity motor function often
      consistent with or less than control conditions. These protocols are time intensive and often
      do not lead to transfer of training effects to improvement in activity performance. This is a
      common issue that has been evidenced in longitudinal studies of individuals with stroke; over
      half of stroke survivors continue to be dependent on others for the most basic of life
      activities after rehabilitation. Decreases in activity performance further contribute to
      lower life satisfaction, quality of life, and participation in daily life. The goal of this
      proposed project is to evaluate the efficacy of a clinically-feasible metacognitive strategy
      training (MCST) intervention, the Cognitive Orientation to daily Occupational Performance
      (CO-OP) approach, to improve activity performance and reduce stroke impairment for
      individuals with sub-acute stroke.

      Recent evidence highlights two primary issues in stroke rehabilitation. 1) Interventions are
      needed that directly target activity performance. Gains in upper extremity function, even
      using the most contemporary approaches, are not translating to meaningful gains in activity
      performance. 2) Interventions need to be clinically feasible for future implementation. In
      recent stroke rehabilitation clinical trials, participants received an average of over 30
      hours of therapy in only one treatment modality. Individuals in stroke rehabilitation receive
      a median of only 6 outpatient visits across all health care specialties combined (OT, PT,
      SLP, physiatrist).

      Metacognitive strategy training (MCST), specifically the Cognitive Orientation to daily
      Occupational Performance (CO-OP) approach, is a potential solution to address both of these
      gaps. CO-OP is a performance-based, problem-solving approach that enables participants to
      improve task performance through cognitive strategy use. In the exploratory clinical trial
      for individuals with sub-acute stroke (n=26), the study compared ten, 45-minute sessions of
      MCST (CO-OP) with dose-matched outpatient usual care outpatient occupational therapy (OT).
      The MCST (CO-OP) group demonstrated a large effect over usual care on objective measures of
      trained functional activities (d=1.6) and untrained functional activities (d = 1.1). The MCST
      group also demonstrated a moderate effect over usual care outpatient OT on improving motor
      function (r = 0.3).

      The goal of this proposed project is to determine the efficacy of MCST to improve activity
      performance and to reduce motor impairments in individuals with subacute stroke. A
      single-blind, parallel, randomized clinical trial will be conducted with individuals with
      sub-acute stroke. Participants will be randomized to a 10-session MCST (CO-OP) treatment
      group or to a dose matched usual care outpatient OT control group. Data will be collected
      pre-intervention, post-intervention, and at 3-months post-intervention assessment. Our
      central research hypothesis is that MCST will produce a significant improvement on objective
      and subjective measures of activity performance (trained and untrained goals) and reduce
      motor impairment in comparison to a usual care OT group.

      Objective 1: Evaluate the efficacy of MCST to improve subjective and objective activity
      performance in individuals with subacute stroke.

      Primary Endpoint: MCST will have a greater positive effect compared to usual care OT on
      subjective and objective activity performance of trained goals.

      Primary Endpoint: MCST will have a greater positive effect compared to usual care OT on
      subjective and objective activity performance of untrained activity goals to demonstrate
      transfer of the treatment effect.

      Secondary Endpoint: MCST will have a greater positive effect compared to usual care OT on
      subjective stroke recovery (participation and role functioning) Objective 2: Evaluate the
      efficacy of MCST to improve motor function in individuals with subacute stroke.

      Primary Endpoint: MCST group will have a greater positive effect compared to usual care OT on
      reducing motor impairment.

      Secondary Endpoint: MCST will have a greater positive effect compared to usual care OT on
      subjective stroke recovery (physical functioning)
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 21, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 30, 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>A single-blind, parallel, randomized clinical trial design will be used in this study. Randomization will be conducted using stratified randomization. Randomization will be stratified by age (50-68 v 69-85) and stroke severity (NIHSS total score 1-16 v &gt;16). Within each strata randomization will be blocked to help ensure an equal number of participants have been assigned to each intervention group.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>Blind raters will be used to collect all outcomes measures</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Canadian Occupational Performance Measure (COPM)</measure>
    <time_frame>Change in baseline to follow-up (12 weeks after post-intervention assessment)</time_frame>
    <description>The COPM is a semi-structured interview guide for establishing a subject's activity performance levels within self-care, leisure, and productivity. The subject will set a minimum of 5 activity goals, providing a self-rating of 1-10 for level of performance and satisfaction with performance on each. An average score across goals for performance and satisfaction will be used in analysis</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Performance Quality Rating Scale (PQRS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Change in baseline to follow-up (12 weeks after post-intervention assessment)</time_frame>
    <description>The PQRS is an observational, objective method of scoring subject activity performance of goals set via the COPM. A blind, trained rater external to the research study team will view video recordings of each subject performing goals. Each goal is rated on a scale of 1 (no activity criteria were met) to 10 (all activity criteria were met). The final score used in the analysis will be an average of all 5 goals.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The Life Space Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>Change in baseline to follow-up (12 weeks after post-intervention assessment)</time_frame>
    <description>The Life Space Questionnaire is a self-reported measure of community mobility and social participation. It is comprised of 9 yes/no questions related to places visited in the previous three days. Total number of &quot;yes&quot; responses (range 0-9) will be used in the analysis.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Upper Extremity Fugl-Meyer</measure>
    <time_frame>Change in baseline to follow-up (12 weeks after post-intervention assessment)</time_frame>
    <description>The Fugl-Meyer is a well-established measure of upper extremity motor performance in individuals with post-stroke hemiparesis. Each item is scored either a 0 (cannot perform), 1 (performs partially), or 2 (performs fully) with a maximum score of 66. In the present study, the upper extremity scaled scored will be used in analysis.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient Health Questionnaire (PHQ-9)</measure>
    <time_frame>Change in baseline to follow-up (12 weeks after post-intervention assessment)</time_frame>
    <description>The PHQ-9 is a self-report measure of depressive symptoms. The subject identifies how often over the previous 2 weeks they have experienced 9 depressive symptoms. The total score reflects the severity of depressive symptoms. A score of 21 or greater indicates severe depressive symptoms. Total score will be used in analysis.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>NIH Toolbox (NIH-TB)-Cognition Battery</measure>
    <time_frame>Change in baseline to follow-up (12 weeks after post-intervention assessment)</time_frame>
    <description>The NIH-TB will be used to evaluate subjects' crystallized intelligence. In contrast to the primary outcome of fluid intelligence, crystalized intelligence is more dependent upon previous learning experience. A crystalized intelligence composite T-score and fluid intelligence T-score will be used in analysis</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Stroke Impact Scale (SIS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Change in baseline to follow-up (12 weeks after post-intervention assessment)</time_frame>
    <description>The SIS is a self-report measure of stroke recovery. Specifically, the measure assesses physical, cognitive, psychosocial, community mobility, and general activity performance on a 5 point Likert scale. There is an additional item for overall recovery rated on a scale of 0 (no recovery) to 100 (full recovery). Domain scores will be used in analysis.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient-Reported Outcomes Measurement Information System (PROMIS): Satisfaction with Social Roles and Activities (Item Bank v2.0)</measure>
    <time_frame>Change in baseline to follow-up (12 weeks after post-intervention assessment)</time_frame>
    <description>The PROMIS Satisfaction with Social Roles and Activities item bank assesses satisfaction with performing one's usual social roles and activities. The T-score for this assessment will be used in the analysis.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">135</enrollment>
  <condition>Stroke</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Usual Care Occupational Therapy-Outpatient</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cognitive Orientation to daily Occupational Performance</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Usual Care Occupational Therapy-Outpatient</intervention_name>
    <description>The control group in the proposed study will receive usual care occupational therapy services. The dosage between the experimental group and usual care will be identical with each group receiving ten 45- minute treatment sessions. The treating therapists will be unfamiliar with the experimental group intervention to avoid contamination. Each therapist will be instructed to provide care in the same manner as they typically provide in day-to-day practice for patients with similar characteristics as those in the study. The therapists will be encouraged to provide home action plans to participants. Usual care services will be monitored through a log of number of sessions, time spent in each session, and what activities were the focus of each session. The therapists will be instructed that they can address any participant goals they wish other than transfer goals identified by the participant.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Usual Care Occupational Therapy-Outpatient</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cognitive Orientation to daily Occupational Performance</intervention_name>
    <description>The Cognitive Orientation to daily Occupational Performance (CO-OP) approach was developed within the field of occupational therapy and is a performance-based, problem-solving approach to address activity performance limitations. Subjects will be taught to use the global problem-solving strategy of Goal-Plan-Do-Check: identifying a specific goal (Goal), outlining a practical plan for reaching that goal (Plan), accurately performing the plan (Do), and analyzing whether the plan led to achievement of the goal and altering the plan accordingly (Check). The Goal-Plan-Do-Check process will be iteratively applied to each of the activity goals. Therapists will use guided discovery to allow the subject to self-identify their own potential solutions within an activity (develop the plan). The therapists will be instructed that they can address any participant goals they wish other than transfer goals identified by the participant.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cognitive Orientation to daily Occupational Performance</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  less than 9 months post-stroke

          -  adults age 50-85

          -  completed inpatient rehabilitation services (if recommended)

          -  living in the community with or without caregiver support (i.e., not living in a
             skilled nursing facility)

          -  ability to read, write, and speak English

          -  self-identified activity performance goals per the Canadian Occupational Performance
             Measure (COPM)

          -  upper extremity hemiparesis as indicated by a score of 1-3 on the NIHSS motor arm
             score or documented in acute therapy evaluation

          -  absence of moderate or severe aphasia as indicated by a National Institutes of Health
             Stroke Scale (NIHSS) aphasia score of 1 or less or documented in acute therapy
             evaluation

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  inability to provide informed consent

          -  severe depressive symptoms as indicated by a score &gt;21 on the Patient Health
             Questionnaire (PHQ-9)

          -  dementia symptoms as indicated by a score of &lt;23 on the Montreal Cognitive Assessment
             (MoCA)

          -  additional neurological diagnoses identified by medical chart review (e.g., brain
             malignancy)

          -  no voluntary movement in affected upper extremity as indicated by a score of 4 on the
             NIHSS motor arm score or documented in acute therapy evaluation

          -  anosognosia as indicated by an inability to identify activity performance problems on
             the COPM

          -  any other condition not otherwise specified that the PI determines would render
             participation in this study as unsafe

          -  any medical condition that the medial monitor determines would render participation in
             this study as unsafe
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>50 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>85 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Timothy J Wolf, OTD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Missouri-Columbia</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Meredith Spiers, MA</last_name>
    <phone>573-882-7085</phone>
    <email>spiersme@health.missouri.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Samantha Shea-Lemoins, BS</last_name>
    <phone>573-882-3988</phone>
    <email>sheasn@health.missouri.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Missouri: Department of Occupational Therapy</name>
      <address>
        <city>Columbia</city>
        <state>Missouri</state>
        <zip>65211</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Meredith Spiers, MA</last_name>
      <phone>573-882-7085</phone>
      <email>spiersme@health.missouri.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Timothy Wolf, OTD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 19, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 20, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 23, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 4, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 4, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">December 5, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Missouri-Columbia</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Timothy J Wolf</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor and Chair</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Stroke</keyword>
  <keyword>Occupational therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Rehabilitation</keyword>
  <keyword>Participation</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Stroke</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>All de-identified clinical outcome assessment data with accompanying key will be deposited in MOspace Institutional Repository, the University of Missouri's digital institutional repository. MOspace is based on MIT's DSpace technology and is a joint venture of the University of Missouri's Division of Information Technology and the University Libraries. MOspace items will include appropriate metadata and a permanent URL. Items will be freely available via the MOspace web site and will be searchable via Google and other search engines.</ipd_description>
    <ipd_time_frame>After completion of study and publication of primary results manuscript. The data will be available indefinitely.</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_url>https://mospace.umsystem.edu/xmlui/</ipd_url>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

