<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04090268</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>284 BIONDI</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04090268</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Precision Exercise in Children With Malignant Hemopathies</brief_title>
  <acronym>SportTherapy</acronym>
  <official_title>Precision Exercise Program in Children With Malignant Hemopathies Undergoing Therapy and/or Hematopoietic Stem Cell Transplantation: The &quot;Sport Therapy&quot; Project</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Milano Bicocca</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Comitato Maria Letizia Verga,Italy</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Milano Bicocca</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      In the early years of life and during adolescence, physical activity is crucial for good
      development of motor skills. It is even more so for those children and young people who are
      forced to undergo anti-cancer therapies and therefore undergo long periods of hospitalization
      (often bedridden) and prolonged periods of physical inactivity.

      The research project &quot;Sport Therapy&quot; was born with the aim of demonstrating that, through
      targeted physical activity administered by the sports physician in collaboration with the
      pediatrician hematologist, it is possible to facilitate the full recovery of these patients,
      avoiding the high risk of chronic diseases related to a sedentary lifestyle and allowing them
      to better reintegrate, once healed, in their community of origin (school, sport and social
      relations).

      The research project &quot;Sport Therapy&quot; was born within the Maria Letizia Verga Center at the
      Pediatric Clinic of the University of Milan Bicocca, at the Foundation for the Mother and Her
      Child, San Gerardo Hospital in Monza. Every year, around 80 children and adolescents with
      leukemia, lymphoma or blood disorders leading to bone marrow transplantation are treated
      here.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      State of the art. Today, thanks to the progress made in the early diagnosis and treatment of
      cancer, there are more than 300 thousand young patients in Europe who have been cured of
      pediatric cancer, and by 2020 there will be almost half a million . For these children and
      young people, having the opportunity to perform targeted physical activity during treatment
      plays a key role in preventing diseases due to physical inactivity, which are one of the
      worst and most widespread consequences for healed patients.

      Children and adolescents suffering from cancer of the blood, because of the therapies to
      which they are subjected, suffer a progressive reduction in respiratory and cardiac capacity,
      as well as muscle strength. Targeted physical exercise is a possible therapeutic approach to
      solving their significant problems of reduced ability to perform exercise. It is possible to
      administer this type of therapy thanks to the synergy created by the collaboration between
      pediatricians, hematologists, and sports physicians.

      Why is this research important? For at least three reasons:

        1. the results of the &quot;Sport Therapy&quot; research project will launch precision training as
           one of the therapeutic weapons available to combat the consequences of hematological
           diseases in childhood;

        2. by increasing the physical capacity of children and adolescents with malignant
           hemopathies during the phases of cancer treatment, the investigators will reduce the
           heavy legacy left by treatment, thus bridging the gap regarding their disadvantage
           towards healthy peers and ensuring their full reintegration into their communities
           (school, sport, social relations);

        3. a standardization of the methodology for using precision exercise in hospitalized
           children and adolescents will facilitate the monitoring of the progress of these type of
           interventions at the international level and the data from the &quot;Sport Therapy&quot; project
           will allow governments and concerned bodies not to further postpone the establishment of
           strategies necessary to improve the health and welfare of people cured of cancer
           diseases.

      Innovative aspects of research. At the end of the research project &quot;Sport Therapy&quot;:

        -  new strategies will be available to combat cardiopulmonary and skeletal muscle damage
           resulting from anticancer therapies;

        -  it will be definitively demonstrated how, from the very beginning of the disease,
           physical exercise can be a therapeutic option and not just a decorative element in the
           critical process of caring for children and adolescents suffering from oncological blood
           diseases, from the beginning of the disease;

        -  the possibility of introducing new technical figures in the hospital context will be
           clear. Sports medicine physician and exercise physiologists will be part of the
           multidisciplinary team that connects the hospital environment to the territory;

        -  the future perspective, once the experimentation has been completed and the
           effectiveness of the precision training intervention on the psycho-physical health of
           children and adolescents suffering from cancer has been demonstrated, will be to make
           &quot;Sport Therapy&quot; a permanent care service during the treatment of patients of developing
           age.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">April 3, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 3, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 3, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Sequential Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Analytical study, stratified, evaluating the impact of a non-pharmacological treatment (training)</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline oxidative metabolism at 12 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Maximal O2 uptake and skeletal muscle O2 extraction</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline strength of upper and lower limbs (1RM) at 12 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>1 repetition maximal</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline balance at 12 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Stabilometry</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline Quality of Life questionnaire at 12 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The PedsQL Measurement Model is a modular approach to measuring health-related quality of life in healthy children and adolescents and those with acute and chronic health conditions. The PedsQL Measurement Model integrates seamlessly both generic core scales and disease-specific modules into one measurement system. The 23-item PedsQL Generic Core Scales were designed to measure the core dimensions of health as delineated by the World Health Organization, as well as role (school) functioning. The 4 Multidimensional Scales (physical, emotional, social, school) and 3 Summary Scores (physical health, psycho-social health and total). Each item has a score between 0 and 4, so the scale score is between 0-100. Higher scores indicate a better QoL.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline Satisfaction at 12 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Visual analog scale (VAS), from 0 to 10, where 0 is any satisfaction and 10 maximal satisfaction.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline 6 minute walking test at 12 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>6 minute walking test</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline Time up and down stairs test at 12 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Time up and down stairs test</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline yo yo test at 12 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Shuttle incremental walking/run test</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline MOON test at 12 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>MOON test</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">380</enrollment>
  <condition>Leukemia, Myeloid, Acute</condition>
  <condition>Leukemia, B-cell</condition>
  <condition>Leukemia, T Cell</condition>
  <condition>Lymphoma, Hodgkin</condition>
  <condition>Lymphoma, Non-Hodgkin</condition>
  <condition>Drepanocytosis</condition>
  <condition>Thalassemia Major</condition>
  <condition>Adrenoleukodystrophy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Children with malignant hemopathies</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Children with malignant hemopathies attending a precision exercise training</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Healthy children</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Healthy children</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sport Therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>Children and adolescent with malignant hemopathies will attend a 3 days/weekly combined training</description>
    <arm_group_label>Children with malignant hemopathies</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Precision exercise program</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Children with malignant hemopathies attending the Maria Letizia Verga Center

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Children under 2 years
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>2 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>18 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Andrea Biondi, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Milano Bicocca</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Francesca Lanfranconi, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+39 0392336868</phone>
    <email>francesca.lanfranconi@unimib.it</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Adriana Balduzzi, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <email>adriana.balduzzi@unimib.it</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Maria Letizia Verga Center, Pediatric Clinic, University of Milan Bicocca, at the Foundation for the Mother and Her Child</name>
      <address>
        <city>Monza</city>
        <state>MB</state>
        <zip>20900</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Francesca Lanfranconi, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>+39 0392336868</phone>
      <email>francesca.lanfranconi@unimib.it</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Adriana Balduzzi</last_name>
      <email>adriana.balduzzi@unimib.it</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Italy</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://comitatomarialetiziaverga.it/care-and-therapy/sport-therapy/</url>
    <description>Sport Therapy project page</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lanfranconi F, Pollastri L, Ferri A, Fraschini D, Masera G, Miserocchi G. Near infrared spectroscopy (NIRS) as a new non-invasive tool to detect oxidative skeletal muscle impairment in children survived to acute lymphoblastic leukaemia. PLoS One. 2014 Jun 23;9(6):e99282. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0099282. eCollection 2014.</citation>
    <PMID>24956391</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Aricò M, Valsecchi MG, Rizzari C, Barisone E, Biondi A, Casale F, Locatelli F, Lo Nigro L, Luciani M, Messina C, Micalizzi C, Parasole R, Pession A, Santoro N, Testi AM, Silvestri D, Basso G, Masera G, Conter V. Long-term results of the AIEOP-ALL-95 Trial for Childhood Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia: insight on the prognostic value of DNA index in the framework of Berlin-Frankfurt-Muenster based chemotherapy. J Clin Oncol. 2008 Jan 10;26(2):283-9. doi: 10.1200/JCO.2007.12.3927.</citation>
    <PMID>18182669</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Aznar S, Webster AL, San Juan AF, Chamorro-Viña C, Maté-Muñoz JL, Moral S, Pérez M, García-Castro J, Ramírez M, Madero L, Lucia A. Physical activity during treatment in children with leukemia: a pilot study. Appl Physiol Nutr Metab. 2006 Aug;31(4):407-13.</citation>
    <PMID>16900230</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bangsbo J, Iaia FM, Krustrup P. The Yo-Yo intermittent recovery test : a useful tool for evaluation of physical performance in intermittent sports. Sports Med. 2008;38(1):37-51. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18081366</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Geiger R, Strasak A, Treml B, Gasser K, Kleinsasser A, Fischer V, Geiger H, Loeckinger A, Stein JI. Six-minute walk test in children and adolescents. J Pediatr. 2007 Apr;150(4):395-9, 399.e1-2.</citation>
    <PMID>17382117</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gohar SF, Comito M, Price J, Marchese V. Feasibility and parent satisfaction of a physical therapy intervention program for children with acute lymphoblastic leukemia in the first 6 months of medical treatment. Pediatr Blood Cancer. 2011 May;56(5):799-804. doi: 10.1002/pbc.22713. Epub 2011 Jan 16.</citation>
    <PMID>21370414</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Götte M, Kesting S, Albrecht C, Worth A, Bös K, Boos J. MOON-test - determination of motor performance in the pediatric oncology. Klin Padiatr. 2013 May;225(3):133-7. doi: 10.1055/s-0033-1343411. Epub 2013 Apr 18.</citation>
    <PMID>23599231</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hartman A, te Winkel ML, van Beek RD, de Muinck Keizer-Schrama SM, Kemper HC, Hop WC, van den Heuvel-Eibrink MM, Pieters R. A randomized trial investigating an exercise program to prevent reduction of bone mineral density and impairment of motor performance during treatment for childhood acute lymphoblastic leukemia. Pediatr Blood Cancer. 2009 Jul;53(1):64-71. doi: 10.1002/pbc.21942.</citation>
    <PMID>19283791</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Haupt R, Spinetta JJ, Ban I, Barr RD, Beck JD, Byrne J, Calaminus G, Coenen E, Chesler M, D'Angio GJ, Eiser C, Feldges A, Gibson F, Lackner H, Masera G, Massimo L, Magyarosy E, Otten J, Reaman G, Valsecchi MG, Veerman AJ, Penn A, Thorvildsen A, van den Bos C, Jankovic M; International Berlin-Frankfurt-Münster Study Group Early and Late Toxicity Educational Committee (I-BFM-SG ELTEC). Long term survivors of childhood cancer: cure and care. The Erice statement. Eur J Cancer. 2007 Aug;43(12):1778-80. Epub 2007 May 31.</citation>
    <PMID>17543517</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hogarty AN, Leahey A, Zhao H, Hogarty MD, Bunin N, Cnaan A, Paridon SM. Longitudinal evaluation of cardiopulmonary performance during exercise after bone marrow transplantation in children. J Pediatr. 2000 Mar;136(3):311-7.</citation>
    <PMID>10700686</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jenney ME, Faragher EB, Jones PH, Woodcock A. Lung function and exercise capacity in survivors of childhood leukaemia. Med Pediatr Oncol. 1995 Apr;24(4):222-30.</citation>
    <PMID>7700166</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>San Juan AF, Fleck SJ, Chamorro-Viña C, Maté-Muñoz JL, Moral S, Pérez M, Cardona C, Del Valle MF, Hernández M, Ramírez M, Madero L, Lucia A. Effects of an intrahospital exercise program intervention for children with leukemia. Med Sci Sports Exerc. 2007 Jan;39(1):13-21.</citation>
    <PMID>17218878</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>San Juan AF, Fleck SJ, Chamorro-Viña C, Maté-Muñoz JL, Moral S, García-Castro J, Ramírez M, Madero L, Lucia A. Early-phase adaptations to intrahospital training in strength and functional mobility of children with leukemia. J Strength Cond Res. 2007 Feb;21(1):173-7.</citation>
    <PMID>17313277</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lucia A, Ramírez M, San Juan AF, Fleck SJ, García-Castro J, Madero L. Intrahospital supervised exercise training: a complementary tool in the therapeutic armamentarium against childhood leukemia. Leukemia. 2005 Aug;19(8):1334-7.</citation>
    <PMID>15931268</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Maggiani A, Tremolizzo L, Della Valentina A, Mapelli L, Sosio S, Milano V, Bianchi M, Badi F, Lavazza C, Grandini M, Corna G, Prometti P, Lunetta C, Riva N, Ferri A, Lanfranconi F; ME&amp;SLA Study #. Osteopathic Manual Treatment for Amyotrophic Lateral Sclerosis: A Feasibility Pilot Study. Open Neurol J. 2016 Aug 26;10:59-66. doi: 10.2174/1874205X01610010059. eCollection 2016.</citation>
    <PMID>27651843</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nagashima T, Sato F, Chuma T, Mano Y, Sasaki I, Mori M, Higa T, Masauji N, Kasai M, Orba Y, Shinohara T, Nagashima K. Chronic demyelinating polyneuropathy in graft-versus-host disease following allogeneic bone marrow transplantation. Neuropathology. 2002 Mar;22(1):1-8.</citation>
    <PMID>12030409</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tan SY, Poh BK, Chong HX, Ismail MN, Rahman J, Zarina AL, Juraida AR, Tahir A, Ruzita AT, Roslee R, Shanita SN, Hamidah A, Shah MI, Norimah AK. Physical activity of pediatric patients with acute leukemia undergoing induction or consolidation chemotherapy. Leuk Res. 2013 Jan;37(1):14-20. doi: 10.1016/j.leukres.2012.09.005. Epub 2012 Oct 23.</citation>
    <PMID>23099236</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zaino CA, Marchese VG, Westcott SL. Timed up and down stairs test: preliminary reliability and validity of a new measure of functional mobility. Pediatr Phys Ther. 2004 Summer;16(2):90-8.</citation>
    <PMID>17057533</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>September 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 2, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 11, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 16, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 26, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 26, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">September 30, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>exercise</keyword>
  <keyword>children</keyword>
  <keyword>adolescent</keyword>
  <keyword>cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>malignant hemopathies</keyword>
  <keyword>leukemia</keyword>
  <keyword>lymphoma</keyword>
  <keyword>hematopoietic stem cell transplant</keyword>
  <keyword>survivor</keyword>
  <keyword>oxidative metabolism</keyword>
  <keyword>strength</keyword>
  <keyword>balance</keyword>
  <keyword>flexibility</keyword>
  <keyword>quality of life</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, Non-Hodgkin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Myeloid</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Myeloid, Acute</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, B-Cell</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hodgkin Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, T-Cell</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Adrenoleukodystrophy</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Thalassemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>beta-Thalassemia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Oxidative metabolism and MOON test variables will be shared with other colleagues involved in similar research protocols</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Statistical Analysis Plan (SAP)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Informed Consent Form (ICF)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>In July 2019 data will be shared, forever</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>Invitation of a common folder in google drive</ipd_access_criteria>
    <ipd_url>https://drive.google.com/drive/u/0/folders</ipd_url>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

