<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04096079</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PEACE Study</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04096079</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Post-ROSC Electrocardiogram After Cardiac arrEst</brief_title>
  <acronym>PEACE</acronym>
  <official_title>Post-ROSC Electrocardiogram After Cardiac arrEst</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>IRCCS Policlinico S. Matteo</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Nicosia General Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Cardiocentro Ticino</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Medical University of Vienna</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>IRCCS Policlinico S. Matteo</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      PEACE study retrospectively evaluate patients who suffered an out-hospital cardiac arrest
      (OHCA) and who underwent a coronary angiography, enrolled in the registry of the Province of
      Pavia (Italy), Ticino Region (Switzerland), Wien region (Austria) and Nicosia area (Cyprus)
      to comprehend the best timing for post-ROSC ECG acquisition in order to reduce the number of
      false positive and to select the best candidates for emergency coronary angiography.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Twelve leads electrocardiogram (ECG) represents an essential step of the diagnostic workflow
      after ROSC as stated by both the European and the American guidelines. Actually about 80% of
      patients showing an ST segment elevation after return of spontaneous circulation (ROSC) have
      a coronary lesion documented by coronary angiography. In those patients, early coronary
      angiography has been shown to improve survival with good neurologic outcome. More
      controversial is the scene for patients without an ST segment elevation. Even in the absence
      of ST segment elevation an acute coronary syndrome can be at the basis of cardiac arrest.
      However, the prognostic role of early coronary angiography in such patients is still a matter
      of debate. In 2014 a consensus document by the European Association for Percutaneous
      Cardiovascular Interventions (EAPCI) recommended elevation to consider early coronary
      angiography only in the case of hemodynamic instability or of recurrent ventricular
      arrhythmias for patients without ST segment as in the case of NSTEMI patients without cardiac
      arrest. At the light of these considerations the correct diagnosis of ST segment elevation is
      of pivotal importance for the right treatment in the right time and in the right hospital for
      this type of patients. Moreover, during cardiac arrest and during resuscitation the heart is
      suffering of ischemia deriving both from a coronary occlusion if present and from low
      systemic perfusion. Post-ROSC ECG could reflect both these types of ischemia, so the ST
      elevation could be not specific for a coronary occlusion. However, some time after ROSC, in
      case of absence of a coronary occlusion, the heart perfusion should improve, the ischemia
      should decrease and the ST segment elevation should regress. Nevertheless, current guidelines
      do not provide any indication about the best timing for ECG acquisition after ROSC. We
      believe that address this issue could be important in order to correctly discriminate the
      appropriate candidate for emergency coronary angiography in the post-ROSC phase of a cardiac
      arrest.

      A preliminary analysis performed on a population of patients suffering an OHCA in the
      Province of Pavia supported this hypothesis. It was pointed out that early detection of ST
      segment elevation, within ten minutes from ROSC, was associated to a high number of false
      positives that is to say patients without an identifiable coronary culprit lesion. ST segment
      elevation was found to be an independent predictor of coronary angioplasty only if detected
      after ten minutes from ROSC.

      The PEACE study aimed to confirm our preliminary results on a larger and multicentric sample
      of post ROSC patients.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 1, 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 31, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 31, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Retrospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Primary endpoint - PCI</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 14 days after OHCA (hospital discharge)</time_frame>
    <description>To assess the number of patients requiring a coronary angioplasty in the presence of ST segment elevation according to the ROSC-ECG time</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Primary endpoint - Time</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 14 days after OHCA (hospital discharge)</time_frame>
    <description>To identify the ROSC-ECG time associated to the lowest rate of false positive</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Secondary outcome - PCI in STEMI patients</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 14 days after OHCA (hospital discharge)</time_frame>
    <description>to assess the number of patients requiring a coronary angioplasty in the absence of ST segment elevation</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Secondary outcome - PCI in BBB patients</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 14 days after OHCA (hospital discharge)</time_frame>
    <description>to assess the number of patients requiring a coronary angioplasty in the presence of left or right bundle branch block</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">1000</enrollment>
  <condition>Out-Of-Hospital Cardiac Arrest</condition>
  <condition>Infarction, Myocardial</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>OHCA patients</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients who suffered an out-of-hospital cardiac arrest between 2015 and 2018 in Province of Pavia (Italy), Ticino Region (Switzerland), Wien area (Austria) and Nicosia area (Cyprus) who underwent a coronary angiography.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        OHCA patients
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  All the patients older than 18 years old resuscitated from an out-of-hospital cardiac
             arrest with an available post-ROSC twelve leads ECG who underwent to a coronary
             angiography during hospital stay.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  From the present study are excluded all the patients with a non-medical aetiology of
             the cardiac arrest (trauma, drowning, electrocution, drug or abuse substance overdose,
             asphyxia)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <verification_date>February 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 14, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 17, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 19, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 11, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 11, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 12, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>IRCCS Policlinico S. Matteo</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Simone Savastano</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>MD</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Out-Of-Hospital Cardiac Arrest, STEMI, coronary angiography, post-ROSC ECG</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Heart Arrest</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Out-of-Hospital Cardiac Arrest</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myocardial Infarction</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Infarction</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

