<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04099368</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>1R01DC018701-01</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04099368</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Music Appreciation After Cochlear Implantation</brief_title>
  <acronym>MACI</acronym>
  <official_title>Music Appreciation After Cochlear Implantation</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Southern California</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Ohio State University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of California, Merced</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Southern California</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This project aims to characterize the emergence of music appreciation in people who have
      suffered hearing loss and have been provided with partial restoration of hearing through
      cochlear implantation. Music appreciation is complex and transverses multiple domains
      including hearing acuity, speech and language acquisition, and quality of life. By studying
      these relationships in people who have been given partial hearing restoration, the
      investigators will clarify the role of music for promoting recovery from debilitating loss.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Cochlear implants are medical devices that restore a remarkable degree of hearing to people
      who would otherwise be profoundly deaf. These devices generally restore enough hearing that
      recipients can understand spoken speech even in noisy environments. However, most recipients
      express dissatisfaction with music. This proposal centers on understanding the challenges
      that implant users face and the strategies that they adopt as they learn to appreciate music
      with this new way of hearing.

      The proposed research is organized into three aims:

      Aim 1: Characterize music appreciation after cochlear implantation. The proposed research
      balances qualitative and quantitative methods to examine the emergence of music appreciation
      after cochlear implantation. Qualitative methods will include semi-structured interviews and
      focus groups designed to clarify the obstacles that implant users face as they learn to
      appreciate music with their new sense of hearing. Quantitative methods include surveys of
      music appreciation and quality of life, and auditory assessments of music and speech
      perception. The primary hypothesis is that music appreciation is predictive of key domains of
      quality of life including positive affect and well-being, and satisfaction with social roles
      and activities.

      Aim 2: Determine if pitch training improves cochlear implant speech comprehension. The
      proposed research tests for a causal relationship between pitch salience and key features of
      speech perception including talker discrimination, prosody detection, and speech recognition
      in competing speech. Cochlear implant users and their normal-hearing peers will take part in
      a crossover study to determine if pitch training improves aspects of music and speech
      perception compared to a visual task used as a control. The primary hypothesis is that pitch
      training will improve speech comprehension for cochlear implant users, but not for their
      normal-hearing peers.

      Aim 3: Test the limits of pitch coding in cochlear implants. The proposed research bypasses
      conventional sound processing to study the salience of pitch provided by electrode location
      and stimulation rate. These two stimulation cues are the primary cues for providing a sense
      of pitch to cochlear implant users. New research has shown that implant users are able to
      learn to use this information to hear pitch with better resolution far better than previously
      thought. The primary hypothesis is that cochlear implant users have a latent ability to hear
      pitch associated with stimulation rate, but that they require experience to learn how to hear
      this new information.

      In each aim, psychophysical methods are combined with measures of EEG and near-infrared
      spectroscopy. The results will establish the importance of music training for improving
      cochlear implant outcomes, both in terms of hearing abilities and quality of life. The
      results will lead to changes in how music is encoded into implant stimulation, providing
      better outcomes for recipients. More generally, this project will shape understanding of
      neural coding of music and its role in social adjustment following traumatic experiences.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 1, 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 1, 2024</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational [Patient Registry]</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Crossover</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <target_duration>4 Years</target_duration>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Pitch Discrimination measured using Psychophysical Procedures</measure>
    <time_frame>Measure collected at 0, 4, and 8 week mark to examine change in discrimination thresholds.</time_frame>
    <description>Change in auditory resolution of fundamental frequency is measured using psychophysical procedures.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Speech Recognition Thresholds measured using Psychophysical Procedures</measure>
    <time_frame>Measure collected at 0, 4, and 8 week mark to examine change in speech recognition thresholds.</time_frame>
    <description>Speech recognition thresholds measured using adaptive procedures for speech recognition in different types of background noise.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">120</enrollment>
  <condition>Hearing Loss</condition>
  <condition>Cochlear Implants</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Auditory</arm_group_label>
    <description>Group receives training on listening to musical pitch differences between sounds as the first component of a crossover trial. The intervention is the listening exercises. Exercises are completed daily as 30-minute sessions for 4 weeks. Hearing assessment outcomes of speech comprehension in background noise and of musical pitch sensitivity are conducted at baseline and at midpoint and endpoint.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Visual</arm_group_label>
    <description>Group receives training on visual differences between objects on a computer screen as the first component of a crossover trial. This is a control measure for the auditory training exercises. Exercises are completed daily as 30-minute sessions for 4 weeks. Hearing assessment outcomes of speech comprehension in background noise and of musical pitch sensitivity are conducted at baseline and at midpoint and endpoint.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Musical pitch training</intervention_name>
    <description>Crossover design with one group receiving musical training as rehabilitation, second group receiving visual training first as a control rehabilitation.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Auditory</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Auditory rehabilitation</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Open enrollment for teenagers and adults across the lifespan will allow characterization of
        how age and hearing loss history interact with aspects of music appreciation and quality of
        life. Efforts will be made to enroll participants prior to implantation. Non-native English
        language speakers will be included, and language use will be factored into analyses. For
        this prospective cohort study seeking to broadly characterize music appreciation and its
        multifaceted associations with hearing history and quality of life, a large cohort is
        desired. A total of 120 participants to complete the surveys and psychophysical procedures.
        A total of 20 to 30 participants to complete qualitative assessments and neuroimaging
        procedures.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Teenage and adult cochlear implant users

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Children younger than 13
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>13 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Ray Goldsworthy</last_name>
    <phone>2132223384</phone>
    <email>raymond.goldsworthy@med.usc.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Keck School of Medicine of USC</name>
      <address>
        <city>Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90033</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 17, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 19, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 23, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 28, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 28, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 30, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Southern California</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Raymond Goldsworthy</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hearing Loss</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

