<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04099147</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NASHAI</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04099147</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Diagnosis and Characterization of Non-Alcoholic Fatty Liver Disease Based on Artificial Intelligence.</brief_title>
  <acronym>NASHAI</acronym>
  <official_title>Diagnosis and Characterization of Non-Alcoholic Fatty Liver Disease Based on Artificial Intelligence.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Instituto de Investigación Marqués de Valdecilla</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Servicio Cántabro de Salud</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Instituto de Investigación Marqués de Valdecilla</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      A key element in the diagnosis of non-alcoholic fatty liver disease (NAFLD) is the
      differentiation of non-alcoholic steatohepatitis (NASH) from non-alcoholic fatty liver (NAFL)
      and the staging of the liver fibrosis, given that patients with NASH and advanced fibrosis
      are those at greatest risk of developing hepatic complications and cardiovascular disease.
      There are still no available non-invasive methods that allow for correct diagnosis and
      staging of NAFLD. The implementation of Artificial Intelligence (AI) techniques based on
      artificial neural networks and deep learning systems (Deep Learning System) as a tool for
      medical diagnoses represents a bona fide technological revolution that introduces an
      innovative approach to improving health processes.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The objectives of this observational study are the following:

        1. To design a predictive model of significant liver disease due to NAFLD, based on
           clustering or clustering algorithms (AI)

        2. To apply and validate this model to classify patients according to the severity of the
           disease in such a manner as to provide more effective management of these patients from
           Primary Care to Hospital Care through process and resource optimization

        3. To develop a Deep Learning System based on convolutional neuronal networks for automatic
           recognition of images in a cohort of subjects with digitized liver biopsies, and to
           undertake pairwise analysis that allows for correct and exact classification of biopsies
           from subjects with NASH.

      Design:

      An observational study of the determination and validation of diagnostic predictive models of
      NAFLD.

      The study has four phases:

      Phases I and II refer to both unsupervised and supervised artificial intelligence learning to
      identify clusters and build diagnostic algorithms. They will be carried out on data generated
      from the ETHON cohort (see below).

      Phase III will consist on applying deep learning system technology as a support strategy to
      stratify liver biopsies in NALFD patients according to their grade of necro-inflammation and
      stage of fibrosis. Liver biopsies collected in the Spanish registry of NAFLD up to the
      beginning of the study will be used.

      Finally, a phase IV of validation will be performed with data from patients that are going to
      be registered in the Spanish registry of NAFLD.

      Population:

        1. - Study cohort (Phases I-III):

           A. Subjects from the general population identified in the ETHON (Epidemiological Study
           of Hepatic Infections) cohort* that has already been created (12,246 subjects between
           19-74 years of age) and B. Subjects belonging to the Spanish registry of NAFLD (HEPAmet)
           (1,800 subjects already collected at the beginning of the study)

           *The ETHON cohort was recruited between 2015 and 2017 to study the hepatitis C
           prevalence in the Spanish general population aged 19-74 years old. Lavin AC, Llerena S,
           Gomez M, Escudero MD, Rodriguez L, Estebanez LA, Gamez B, Puchades L, Cabezas J, Serra
           MA, Calleja JL, Crespo J. Prevalence of hepatitis C in the spanish population. The
           PREVHEP study (ETHON cohort). J Hepatol. 2017;66:S272.

        2. - Validation cohort (Phase IV):

      Patients diagnosed with NAFLD by hepatic biopsy recruited in the Spanish and European
      registers from the beginning of the study.

      -Inclusion and exclusion criteria:

      Inclusion criteria: subjects aged 19-74 belonging to the ETHON cohort or registered in the
      Hepamet Spanish registry of NAFLD or the European NAFLD registry

      Exclusion criteria: subjects that not fulfill the inclusion criteria and those who did not
      sign informed consent to participate in the ETHON cohort or to be registered in the mentioned
      registers.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">September 30, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 30, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Other</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of subjects diagnosed with NAFLD and NASH in the ETHON cohort after applying Artificial Intelligence algorithms</measure>
    <time_frame>From october of 2019 to march of 2021</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of subjects diagnosed with NAFLD and NASH in the ETHON cohort after applying Artificial Intelligence algorithms</measure>
    <time_frame>From october of 2019 to march of 2021</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Sensitivity in terms of NASH diagnosis of AI algorithms with respect to histologic diagnosis compared with the Hepamet non-invasive score</measure>
    <time_frame>From october of 2019 to march of 2021</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Specificity in terms of NASH diagnosis of AI algorithms with respect to histologic diagnosis compared with the Hepamet non-invasive score</measure>
    <time_frame>From october of 2019 to march of 2021</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Positive predictive value in terms of NASH diagnosis of AI algorithms with respect to histologic diagnosis compared with the Hepamet non-invasive score.</measure>
    <time_frame>From october of 2019 to march of 2021</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Negative predictive Value in terms of NASH diagnosis of AI algorithms with respect to histologic diagnosis compared with the Hepamet non-invasive score.</measure>
    <time_frame>From october of 2019 to march of 2021</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Kappa coefficient of concordance about NASH diagnosis between AI algorithms and histologic diagnosis.</measure>
    <time_frame>From october of 2019 to march of 2021</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Kappa coefficient of concordance about NASH diagnosis between AI algorithms and the Hepamet non-invasive score.</measure>
    <time_frame>From october of 2019 to march of 2021</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>ROC curve at various threshold settings obtained through the algorithms for NASH diagnosis and staging</measure>
    <time_frame>From october of 2019 to march of 2021</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">14046</enrollment>
  <condition>Non-alcoholic Fatty Liver Disease (NAFLD)</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>ETHON</arm_group_label>
    <description>Subjects from the general population identified in the ETHON</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>HEPAmet</arm_group_label>
    <description>Subjects belonging to the Spanish registry of NAFLD (HEPAmet)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>This is an observational study.</intervention_name>
    <description>This is an observational study. No intervention is planned outside of usual clinical practice.</description>
    <arm_group_label>ETHON</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>HEPAmet</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        The study has four phases: Phases I and II refer to both unsupervised and supervised
        artificial intelligence learning to identify clusters and build diagnostic algorithms. They
        will be carried out on data generated from the ETHON cohort. Phase III will consist on
        applying deep learning system technology as a support strategy to stratify liver biopsies
        in NALFD patients according to their grade of necro-inflammation and stage of fibrosis.
        Liver biopsies collected in the Spanish registry of NAFLD up to the beginning of the study
        will be used. Finally, a phase IV of validation will be performed with data from patients
        that are going to be registered in the European and Spanish registries of NAFLD.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects aged 19-74 belonging to the ETHON cohort or registered in the Hepamet Spanish
             registry of NAFLD or the European NAFLD registry

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects that not fulfill the inclusion criteria and those who did not sign informed
             consent to participate in the ETHON cohort or to be registered in the mentioned
             registers.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>19 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>74 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Antonio Cuadrado Lavín</last_name>
    <phone>+34942204089</phone>
    <email>antonio.cuadrado@scsalud.es</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Lucía Lavín Alconero</last_name>
    <phone>+34942204089</phone>
    <email>eclinicos5@idival.org</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <verification_date>September 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 20, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 20, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 23, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 20, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 20, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">September 23, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>non-alcoholic fatty liver disease</keyword>
  <keyword>NAFLD</keyword>
  <keyword>Artificial Intelligence</keyword>
  <keyword>Deep Learning System</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Liver Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fatty Liver</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Non-alcoholic Fatty Liver Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

