<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04099290</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>LCCC 1835</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04099290</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Circulating Tumor DNA (ctDNA) in Locally Advanced Head and Neck Squamous Cell Carcinoma</brief_title>
  <official_title>Circulating Tumor DNA (ctDNA) in Locally Advanced Head and Neck Squamous Cell Carcinoma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>UNC Lineberger Comprehensive Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>UNC Lineberger Comprehensive Cancer Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Circulating tumor DNA (ctDNA) is a blood-based test that measures dying or dead cancer cells
      that are already circulating in the blood. In this study, the investigators will enroll
      patients who are planning to receive surgery to remove their head and neck cancer. The
      investigators are interested to learn how ctDNA levels change with surgery and over the
      course of time. The investigators also want to determine if there are certain features of the
      tumor or the patient themselves that might cause ctDNA to be higher than other patients.
      Also, the investigators want to explore if the detection of ctDNA following surgery is
      related to cancer recurrence.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The investigators will take a piece of the tumor from the surgery and determine if they can
      identify mutations, or changes in the genetic makeup of the cells due to cancer, that are
      specific to the tumor. Based on this information, the investigators will design a test using
      PCR, which is a technology that allows for the amplification of the DNA, that is specific to
      the mutation identified in the tumor. Once verified, the presence (or absence) of ctDNA in
      the blood can be measured. The investigators will measure this blood test prior to surgery
      and at multiple time points following surgery. Specimens will be collected at the time of
      planned clinical assessments.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 14, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 30, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 30, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of tumor-specific mutation in pre-operative circulating tumor DNA of patients with locally-advanced HNSCC who are receiving surgery for treatment of their primary tumor</measure>
    <time_frame>Time of consent</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of tumor-specific mutation in post-operative circulating tumor DNA in patients with locally-advanced HNSCC who received surgery for treatment of their primary tumor</measure>
    <time_frame>Post-surgery/pre-treatment, post-surgery/post-treatment (approximately 6 weeks following initiation of treatment and every 3 months up to 2 years), and at disease recurrence if applicable (up to 5 years)</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in ctDNA levels (i.e., copies per mL plasma) over time</measure>
    <time_frame>Time of consent, post-operatively (approximately 1-4 weeks after surgery), post-adjuvant treatment (approximately 6 weeks following initiation of treatment) and follow-up (every 3 months up to 2 years)/recurrence if applicable (up to 5 years)</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Description of tumor-specific mutations in surgical specimens by NGS</measure>
    <time_frame>Surgery and post-treatment biopsy/recurrence if applicable(up to 5 years)</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Correlation between post-operative plasma ctDNA levels and surgical margins</measure>
    <time_frame>Post-operatively (approximately 1-4 weeks after surgery)</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Correlation between post-operative plasma ctDNA levels and extra-capsular extension</measure>
    <time_frame>Post-operatively (approximately 1-4 weeks after surgery)</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Head and Neck Neoplasm</condition>
  <condition>Carcinoma, Squamous Cell</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Blood and tumor samples</intervention_name>
    <description>Blood samples to be obtained at consent, post-operatively, post-adjuvant treatment, and at follow-up or recurrence. Tumor samples to be obtained at surgery and at time of recurrence or post-treatment biopsy, if applicable.</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients with Head and Neck Cancer
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Written informed consent obtained to participate in the study and HIPAA authorization
             for release of personal health information. Consent for the use of any residual
             material from biopsy and/or surgical resection (archival tissue) and serial blood
             draws will be required for enrollment.

          -  Age ≥ 18 years of age on day of signing informed consent

          -  Newly diagnosed, histologically confirmed squamous cell carcinoma of the head and
             neck, including the following subtypes: oral cavity, oropharynx, larynx

          -  Must be planning to undergo gross total resection of the primary tumor with curative
             intent at UNC-CH hospital

          -  No prior, definitive therapy to primary tumor. Must meet one of the following clinical
             stages: T3-T4 (if T1/T2 must have nodal involvement), Any N, M0

          -  Patient must be amenable to receiving adjuvant therapy with radiotherapy +/- systemic
             therapy, as clinically indicated, based on either standard of care (SOC) or
             appropriate clinical trial.

          -  Diagnostic tumor material must be available for correlative analysis

          -  Subject is willing and able to comply with study procedures based on the judgement of
             the investigator or protocol designee

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Has known evidence of metastatic disease based on clinical or radiographic studies

          -  Women who are pregnant or nursing

          -  History of another primary malignancy in the last 5 years prior to registration.
             Patients with history of in situ cancer or basal or localized squamous cell skin
             cancers are eligible.

          -  Patients with primary skin cancers of the head and neck, including basal or squamous
             cell cancers

          -  Prior chemotherapy, IP, biologic, or hormonal therapy for HNSCC treatment. Concurrent
             use of hormonal therapy for non-cancer-related conditions (e.g., hormone replacement
             therapy) is acceptable.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Siddharth Sheth, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>UNC Health Care</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Gaorav Gupta, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Siddharth Sheth, MD</last_name>
    <phone>(919) 966-3856</phone>
    <email>Siddharth.Sheth@unchealth.unc.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Rebecca Green, MSW</last_name>
    <phone>(984) 974-8440</phone>
    <email>rlgreen@med.unc.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chapel Hill</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27599</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Siddharth Sheth, MD</last_name>
      <email>siddharth.sheth@unchealth.unc.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Rebecca Green, MSW</last_name>
      <phone>984-974-8440</phone>
      <email>rlgreen@med.unc.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 17, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 19, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 23, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 17, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 17, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 18, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Squamous Cell Carcinoma</keyword>
  <keyword>Circulating Tumor DNA</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Squamous Cell</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Squamous Cell Carcinoma of Head and Neck</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Head and Neck Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

