<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04093414</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2019-191</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04093414</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Left Bundle Area Versus Selective His Bundle Pacing</brief_title>
  <acronym>LEFTBASH</acronym>
  <official_title>Left Bundle Area Versus Selective His Bundle Pacing (LEFTBASH): Single Center, Open Label, Randomized Pilot Study to Evaluate Capture Thresholds and Acute Echocardiographic Hemodynamic Characteristics</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>David Haines, MD</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>William Beaumont Hospitals</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a voluntary research study to find out which location in the heart a pacemaker wire
      is the most efficient for a patient's heart and for battery life. Patients who volunteer and
      are eligible for the study will be randomized to receive one of two positions for the wire to
      be screwed into, in addition to studying multiple positions in the heart during the pacemaker
      insertion. Enrolled patients will be in the study for 1 year. They will also have an
      Ultrasound of their heart performed to assess how the pacemaker wire is affecting their
      heart. Pacemakers are connected to the heart by wires that are screwed into the heart. The
      wires can be connected to the heart in different places, which can affect how well the heart
      beats over time. The typical position is at the tip of the heart. This position may cause the
      heart to beat inefficiently. Over time, this could lead to weakened heart muscle, irregular
      heart rhythm, and more hospitalizations. The heart has special muscle cells and fibers that
      carry electrical signals through and around the heart. An alternative spot to place the
      pacemaker wire is in an area where these special cells are grouped together (called the HIS
      bundle). The pacemaker wire can be connected to the heart at a location which may allow the
      heart to beat more efficiently when compared to putting the wire at traditional spots in the
      heart (called HIS bundle pacing). However, sometimes connecting the wire into the HIS bundle
      may cause the pacemaker battery to wear out faster. Physicians can also connect the pacemaker
      wired near the HIS bundle (called Left left Bundle bundle area pacing). The study physicians
      hope this will allow the heart to beat more efficiently without causing the battery to wear
      out faster. The study physicians would like to study how different wire positions change
      heart beat efficiency and how long the pacemaker battery lasts when the wires are placed in
      different locations. This study will connect the pacemaker wire at either the HIS Bundle or
      the left bundle area pacing, to see how effectively the heart pumps and how much battery is
      being used.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a single center, open label, prospective randomized pilot study to evaluate the
      capture threshold of His Bundle versus left bundle area pacing. Secondary analysis will focus
      on inter-patient electrocardiographic and echocardiographic hemodynamic parameters of
      intrinsic conduction, versus pacing at three different pacing sites. Symptomatic
      bradyarrhythmias are effectively treated with cardiac pacemakers.The amount of pacing by the
      lead positioned in the bottom chamber of the heart at traditional sites such as the right
      ventricular apex have been associated with increased rates of atrial fibrillation, heart
      failure, and mortality. Traditional pacing sites result in cardiac electromechanical
      dyssynchrony, for which alternate pacing sites to minimize these untoward effects have been
      sought. HIS bundle pacing, which utilizes a patient's native conduction, has demonstrated
      improved electrical synchrony and left ventricular function when compared to traditional
      pacing at the tip of the bottom chamber. Barriers to wide spread application to this
      technique include the His bundle anatomic location and its attendant difficulties associated
      with implant, as well as higher capture thresholds leading to decreased battery duration of
      the pacemaker. An alternative to HIS bundle pacing is placing the lead just past the HIS
      bundle area, which is further in the heart, and to actively fixate the lead into the
      interventricular septum. This is referred to as Left Bundle Pacing, as it may electrically
      capture the left bundle, which would simulate a patient's native conduction. The researchers
      will evaluate the two different pacing sites (HIS bundle and Left Bundle area sites) to
      determine how effectively the heart pumps with each pacing site. The researchers will compare
      these to traditional pacing sites (apex) and to non paced parameters.

      Patients requiring pacemaker implant will be screened for study eligibility and approached
      for informed consent. Baseline assessments including echocardiogram and ECG will be obtained.
      Once enrolled, the researchers will randomize patients to one of two arms. One arm will
      fixate the ventricular pacemaker lead to the HIS bundle area while the other arm will have
      the leads fixed into the left bundle area. Baseline assessments including echocardiogram and
      ECG. Before the pacing wires are inserted, pacing at three positions (traditional, HIS bundle
      and left bundle area) will be evaluated and echocardiographic images obtained. The pacemaker
      wires will be connected in accordance with randomization group. The day after the procedure,
      a chest x-ray, EKG and pacemaker evaluation will be performed. An echocardiogram will be
      obtained at 3 months post procedure. At 6 and 12 months post procedure, EKG rhythm strips
      will be obtained from patients' standard of care remote pacemaker monitoring systems.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 7, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Single center, open label, randomized, prospective</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Ventricular Capture Threshold, 3 months unipolar or Bipolar</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Ventricular capture threshold is the minimum amplitude that consistently results in capture of the ventricular myocardium with a 1.0 millisecond pulse width setting in unipolar or Bipolar output, measured in volts. The measurement is automatically captured and will be interrogated from the pacemaker device at 3 months post implantation.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Left Ventricular Ejection Fraction (LVEF) - intrinsic conduction</measure>
    <time_frame>at index procedure prior to lead fixation</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of blood pumped from the left ventricle of the heart at each beat with no pacing applied</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Stroke Volume - intrinsic conduction</measure>
    <time_frame>at index procedure prior to lead fixation</time_frame>
    <description>Volume of blood in milliliters pumped from the left ventricle of the heart at each beat with no pacing applied</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mechanical dyssynchrony of anterior left ventricle myocardial wall- intrinsic conduction</measure>
    <time_frame>at index procedure prior to lead fixation</time_frame>
    <description>Time to peak systolic velocity of the anterior left ventricle myocardial wall in milliseconds with no pacing applied, elicited by tissue Doppler</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mechanical dyssynchrony of inferior left ventricle myocardial wall- intrinsic conduction</measure>
    <time_frame>at index procedure prior to lead fixation</time_frame>
    <description>Time to peak systolic velocity of the inferior left ventricle myocardial wall in milliseconds with no pacing applied, elicited by tissue Doppler</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mechanical dyssynchrony of inferior-septal left ventricle myocardial wall- intrinsic conduction</measure>
    <time_frame>at index procedure prior to lead fixation</time_frame>
    <description>Time to peak systolic velocity of the inferior-septal left ventricle myocardial wall in milliseconds with no pacing applied, elicited by tissue Doppler</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mechanical dyssynchrony of left ventricle anterior-septal myocardial wall- intrinsic conduction</measure>
    <time_frame>at index procedure prior to lead fixation</time_frame>
    <description>Time to peak systolic velocity of the left ventricle anterior-septal myocardial wall in milliseconds with no pacing applied, elicited by tissue Doppler</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mechanical dyssynchrony of lateral left ventricle myocardial wall- intrinsic conduction</measure>
    <time_frame>at index procedure prior to lead fixation</time_frame>
    <description>Time to peak systolic velocity of the lateral left ventricle myocardial wall in milliseconds with no pacing applied, elicited by tissue Doppler</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mechanical dyssynchrony of inferior-lateral left ventricle myocardial wall- intrinsic conduction</measure>
    <time_frame>at index procedure prior to lead fixation</time_frame>
    <description>Time to peak systolic velocity of the inferior-lateral left ventricle myocardial wall in milliseconds with no pacing applied, elicited by tissue Doppler</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>QRS Duration - intrinsic conduction</measure>
    <time_frame>at index procedure prior to lead fixation</time_frame>
    <description>Duration (time in milliseconds) of the QRS wave complex interval measured from the end of the PR interval to the end of the S wave measured on a 12-lead electrocardiogram, with intrinsic conduction</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Left Ventricular Ejection Fraction (LVEF) - selective or non selective His Pacing</measure>
    <time_frame>at index procedure prior to lead fixation</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of blood pumped from the left ventricle of the heart at each beat with selective His bundle pacing applied</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Stroke Volume - selective or non selective His Pacing</measure>
    <time_frame>at index procedure prior to lead fixation</time_frame>
    <description>Volume of blood in milliliters pumped from the left ventricle of the heart at each beat with selective His bundle pacing applied</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mechanical dyssynchrony of anterior left ventricle myocardial wall - selective or non selective His Pacing</measure>
    <time_frame>at index procedure prior to lead fixation</time_frame>
    <description>Time to peak systolic velocity of the anterior left ventricle myocardial wall in milliseconds with selective His bundle pacing applied, elicited by tissue Doppler</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mechanical dyssynchrony of inferior left ventricle myocardial wall - selective or non selective His Pacing</measure>
    <time_frame>at index procedure prior to lead fixation</time_frame>
    <description>Time to peak systolic velocity of the inferior left ventricle myocardial wall in milliseconds with selective His bundle pacing applied, elicited by tissue Doppler</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mechanical dyssynchrony of anterior-septal left ventricle myocardial wall - selective or non selective His Pacing</measure>
    <time_frame>at index procedure prior to lead fixation</time_frame>
    <description>Time to peak systolic velocity of the anterior-septal left ventricle myocardial wall in milliseconds with selective His bundle pacing applied, elicited by tissue Doppler</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mechanical dyssynchrony of inferior-septal left ventricle myocardial wall - selective or non selective His Pacing</measure>
    <time_frame>at index procedure prior to lead fixation</time_frame>
    <description>Time to peak systolic velocity of the inferior-septal left ventricle myocardial wall in milliseconds with selective His bundle pacing applied, elicited by tissue Doppler</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mechanical dyssynchrony of lateral left ventricle myocardial wall - selective or non selective His Pacing</measure>
    <time_frame>at index procedure prior to lead fixation</time_frame>
    <description>Time to peak systolic velocity of the lateral left ventricle myocardial wall in milliseconds with selective His bundle pacing applied, elicited by tissue Doppler</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mechanical dyssynchrony of inferior-lateral left ventricle myocardial wall - selective or non selective His Pacing</measure>
    <time_frame>at index procedure prior to lead fixation</time_frame>
    <description>Time to peak systolic velocity of the inferior-lateral left ventricle myocardial wall in milliseconds with selective His bundle pacing applied, elicited by tissue Doppler</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>QRS duration - selective or non selective His Pacing</measure>
    <time_frame>at index procedure prior to lead fixation</time_frame>
    <description>Duration (time in milliseconds) of the QRS wave complex interval measured from the end of the PR interval to the end of the S wave, measured on a 12-lead electrocardiogram, with selective His pacing</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Left Ventricular Ejection Fraction (LVEF) - left bundle area pacing</measure>
    <time_frame>at index procedure prior to lead fixation</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of blood pumped from the left ventricle of the heart at each beat with left bundle area pacing applied</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Stroke Volume - left bundle area pacing</measure>
    <time_frame>at index procedure prior to lead fixation</time_frame>
    <description>Volume of blood in milliliters pumped from the left ventricle of the heart at each beat with left bundle area pacing applied</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mechanical dyssynchrony of anterior left ventricle myocardial wall - left bundle area pacing</measure>
    <time_frame>at index procedure prior to lead fixation</time_frame>
    <description>Time to peak systolic velocity of the anterior left ventricle myocardial wall in milliseconds with left bundle area pacing applied, elicited by tissue Doppler</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mechanical dyssynchrony of inferior left ventricle myocardial wall - left bundle area pacing</measure>
    <time_frame>at index procedure prior to lead fixation</time_frame>
    <description>Time to peak systolic velocity of the inferior left ventricle myocardial wall in milliseconds with left bundle area pacing applied, elicited by tissue Doppler</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mechanical dyssynchrony of left ventricle anterior-septal myocardial wall - left bundle area pacing</measure>
    <time_frame>at index procedure prior to lead fixation</time_frame>
    <description>Time to peak systolic velocity of the left ventricle anterior-septal myocardial wall in milliseconds with left bundle area pacing applied, elicited by tissue Doppler</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mechanical dyssynchrony of left ventricle inferior-septal myocardial wall - left bundle area pacing</measure>
    <time_frame>at index procedure prior to lead fixation</time_frame>
    <description>Time to peak systolic velocity of the left ventricle inferior-septal myocardial wall in milliseconds with left bundle area pacing applied, elicited by tissue Doppler</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mechanical dyssynchrony of lateral left ventricle myocardial wall - left bundle area pacing</measure>
    <time_frame>at index procedure prior to lead fixation</time_frame>
    <description>Time to peak systolic velocity of the lateral left ventricle myocardial wall in milliseconds with left bundle area pacing applied, elicited by tissue Doppler</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mechanical dyssynchrony of inferior-lateral left ventricle myocardial wall - left bundle area pacing</measure>
    <time_frame>at index procedure prior to lead fixation</time_frame>
    <description>Time to peak systolic velocity of the inferior-lateral left ventricle myocardial wall in milliseconds with left bundle area pacing applied, elicited by tissue Doppler</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>QRS duration - left bundle area pacing</measure>
    <time_frame>at index procedure prior to lead fixation</time_frame>
    <description>Duration (time in milliseconds) of the QRS wave complex interval measured from the end of the PR interval to the end of the S wave measured on a 12-lead electrocardiogram, with left bundle area pacing</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Left Ventricular Ejection Fraction (LVEF) - right ventricular pacing</measure>
    <time_frame>at index procedure prior to lead fixation</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of blood pumped from the left ventricle of the heart at each beat with right ventricular pacing applied</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Stroke Volume - right ventricular pacing</measure>
    <time_frame>at index procedure prior to lead fixation</time_frame>
    <description>Volume of blood in milliliters pumped from the left ventricle of the heart at each beat with right ventricular pacing applied</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mechanical dyssynchrony of anterior left ventricle myocardial wall - right ventricular pacing</measure>
    <time_frame>at index procedure prior to lead fixation</time_frame>
    <description>Time to peak systolic velocity of the anterior left ventricle myocardial wall in milliseconds with right ventricular pacing applied, elicited by tissue Doppler</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mechanical dyssynchrony of inferior left ventricle myocardial wall - right ventricular pacing</measure>
    <time_frame>at index procedure prior to lead fixation</time_frame>
    <description>Time to peak systolic velocity of the inferior left ventricle myocardial wall in milliseconds with right ventricular pacing applied, elicited by tissue Doppler</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mechanical dyssynchrony of left ventricle anterior- septal myocardial wall - right ventricular pacing</measure>
    <time_frame>at index procedure prior to lead fixation</time_frame>
    <description>Time to peak systolic velocity of the left ventricle anterior-septal myocardial wall in milliseconds with right ventricular pacing applied, elicited by tissue Doppler</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mechanical dyssynchrony of left ventricle inferior-septal myocardial wall - right ventricular pacing</measure>
    <time_frame>at index procedure prior to lead fixation</time_frame>
    <description>Time to peak systolic velocity of the left ventricle inferior-septal myocardial wall in milliseconds with right ventricular pacing applied, elicited by tissue Doppler</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mechanical dyssynchrony of lateral left ventricle myocardial wall - right ventricular pacing</measure>
    <time_frame>at index procedure prior to lead fixation</time_frame>
    <description>Time to peak systolic velocity of the lateral left ventricle myocardial wall in milliseconds with right ventricular pacing applied, elicited by tissue Doppler</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mechanical dyssynchrony of inferior-lateral left ventricle myocardial wall - right ventricular pacing</measure>
    <time_frame>at index procedure prior to lead fixation</time_frame>
    <description>Time to peak systolic velocity of the inferior-lateral left ventricle myocardial wall in milliseconds with right ventricular pacing applied, elicited by tissue Doppler</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>QRS duration - right ventricular pacing</measure>
    <time_frame>at index procedure prior to lead fixation</time_frame>
    <description>Duration (time in milliseconds) of the QRS wave complex interval measured from the end of the PR interval to the end of the S wave, measured on a 12-lead electrocardiogram, with right ventricular pacing</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Left Ventricular Ejection Fraction (LVEF) after lead fixation</measure>
    <time_frame>at index procedure following final lead fixation</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of blood pumped from the left ventricle of the heart at each beat after final pacing lead fixation</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Stroke Volume - after lead fixation</measure>
    <time_frame>at index procedure following final lead fixation</time_frame>
    <description>Volume of blood in milliliters pumped from the left ventricle of the heart at each beat after final pacing lead fixation</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mechanical dyssynchrony of anterior left ventricle myocardial wall after lead fixation</measure>
    <time_frame>at index procedure following final lead fixation</time_frame>
    <description>Time to peak systolic velocity of the anterior left ventricle myocardial wall in milliseconds after final pacing lead fixation, elicited by tissue Doppler</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mechanical dyssynchrony of inferior left ventricle myocardial wall after lead fixation</measure>
    <time_frame>at index procedure following final lead fixation</time_frame>
    <description>Time to peak systolic velocity of the inferior left ventricle myocardial wall in milliseconds after final pacing lead fixation, elicited by tissue Doppler</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mechanical dyssynchrony of left ventricle anterior-septal myocardial wall after lead fixation</measure>
    <time_frame>at index procedure following final lead fixation</time_frame>
    <description>Time to peak systolic velocity of the left ventricle anterior-septal myocardial wall in milliseconds after final pacing lead fixation, elicited by tissue Doppler</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mechanical dyssynchrony of left ventricle inferior-septal myocardial wall after lead fixation</measure>
    <time_frame>at index procedure following final lead fixation</time_frame>
    <description>Time to peak systolic velocity of the left ventricle inferior-septal myocardial wall in milliseconds after final pacing lead fixation, elicited by tissue Doppler</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mechanical dyssynchrony of lateral left ventricle myocardial wall after lead fixation</measure>
    <time_frame>at index procedure following final lead fixation</time_frame>
    <description>Time to peak systolic velocity of the lateral left ventricle myocardial wall in milliseconds after final lead fixation, elicited by tissue Doppler</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mechanical dyssynchrony of inferior-lateral left ventricle myocardial wall after lead fixation</measure>
    <time_frame>at index procedure following final lead fixation</time_frame>
    <description>Time to peak systolic velocity of the inferior-lateral left ventricle myocardial wall in milliseconds after final lead fixation, elicited by tissue Doppler</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>QRS duration after lead fixation</measure>
    <time_frame>at index procedure following final lead fixation</time_frame>
    <description>Duration (time in milliseconds) of the QRS wave complex interval measured from the end of the PR interval to the end of the S wave, measured on a 12-lead electrocardiogram, after final pacing lead fixation</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Capture Threshold - 6 months, unipolar or bipolar</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Ventricular capture threshold is the minimum amplitude that consistently results in capture of the ventricular myocardium, elicited with a unipolar or bipolar output 1.0 millisecond pulse width, whichever value is lower, measured in volts.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Capture Threshold - 12 months, unipolar or bipolar</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Ventricular capture threshold is the minimum amplitude that consistently results in capture of the ventricular myocardium, elicited with a unipolar or bipolar output 1.0 millisecond pulse width, whichever value is lower, measured in volts.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">26</enrollment>
  <condition>Bradycardia</condition>
  <condition>Sinus Node Dysfunction</condition>
  <condition>Atrioventricular Block</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Selective His Bundle Pacing</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Pacemaker wires placed in Bundle of His</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Left Bundle Area Pacing</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Pacemaker wires placed in Left Bundle Branch</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Select Secure pacing lead</intervention_name>
    <description>A Select Secure pacing lead is placed in the bundle of His or left bundle branch, based upon randomization</description>
    <arm_group_label>Left Bundle Area Pacing</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Selective His Bundle Pacing</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>3830, 69 cm, Medtronic</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Over 18 years old.

          2. With signed consent.

          3. Pacemaker indication according to 2018 American College of Cardiology/American Heart
             Association/Heart Rhythm Society Guideline on the Evaluation and Management of
             Patients with Bradycardia and Cardiac Conduction Delay. With one or both of the
             following:

               1. Symptomatic sinus node dysfunction.

               2. Symptomatic Atrioventricular (AV) block or high degree AV block.

               3. Tachy-Brady syndrome

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Previously implanted cardiac pacing devices.

          2. Those with persistent or permanent atrial tachy-arrhythmia.

          3. Patients who are eligible for appropriate Cardiac resynchronization (CRT) or
             Implantable cardioverter defibrillator (ICD) implantation.

          4. Patients with prior septal myectomy.

          5. Patients with prior surgical or transcatheter aortic valve replacement.

          6. Anatomy precluding implant, evaluated during the screening research Echocardiogram, or
             identified during the procedure.

          7. Unable to achieve selective or non-selective His bundle pacing, identified during the
             procedure.

          8. Pregnant women and fetuses.

          9. Inadequate thoracic windows, identified during the screening echocardiogram.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>19 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>David Haines, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Beaumont</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Christopher Bradley, MD</last_name>
    <phone>248-551-5580</phone>
    <email>Christopher.Bradley2@beaumont.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Diedre Brunk, BSN, MBA</last_name>
    <phone>248-551-5580</phone>
    <email>Diedre.Brunk@beaumont.org</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Beaumont Health System</name>
      <address>
        <city>Royal Oak</city>
        <state>Michigan</state>
        <zip>48073</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 16, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 16, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 18, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 6, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 6, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 8, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>William Beaumont Hospitals</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>David Haines, MD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Director, Electrophysiology and Heart Rhythm Centre</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Pacemaker</keyword>
  <keyword>Bundle of His</keyword>
  <keyword>Left Bundle Branch</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Bradycardia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Atrioventricular Block</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sick Sinus Syndrome</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

