<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04098679</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>REB14-2146_MOD2</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04098679</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Childhood Adiposity and Neurodevelopmental Outcomes Among Offspring of Women With Type 1 Diabetes (CONCEPTT Kids)</brief_title>
  <official_title>CONCEPTT Kids Childhood Adiposity and Neurodevelopmental Outcomes Among Offspring of Women With Type 1 Diabetes: A Follow up Study of the CONCEPTT Randomized Control Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Calgary</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>SRI International</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Juvenile Diabetes Research Foundation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Calgary</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a follow-up study of children born to mothers who participated in the CONCEPTT Trial.
      CONCEPTT (a multicentre randomized controlled trial of continuous glucose monitoring (CGM) in
      women with Type 1 diabetes during pregnancy).

      The purpose of this study is to examine the association of maternal glycemic measures on
      childhood intelligence quotient (IQ), behavioural outcomes, language scores and weight
      measures. The children of the women who participated in CONCEPTT will be assessed.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The assessments will occur between the children's ages of 3-7 years. The assessment will
      include obtaining consent and child measurements including weight, height, waist
      circumference and skinfold thickness (at the triceps, subscapular, flank and quadriceps).
      Body mass index (BMI) and Waist-Height ratio will be calculated.

      The other procedures will include:

        1. the Wechsler Preschool and Primary Scale of Intelligence-Fourth Edition (1);

        2. ADHD Rating Scale IV (2) and ADHD Rating Scale-IV Preschool Version (3);

        3. Social Responsiveness Scale-2 for ASD behaviours (4);

        4. Children's performance on the Speed Naming and Phonological Processing subscales of the
           NEPSY-II (5)

        5. Parent reported language development on the Children's Communication Checklist-2 for
           children over four years of age (6) or the Language Use Inventory (LUI) for children 36
           to 47 months of age (7).

      Basic demographic questions will be asked regarding the child's mother and father including
      age, ethnicity, education, occupation, family arrangement, presence of major illnesses, and
      diabetes complications. Questions regarding maternal diabetes, maternal and paternal family
      history of diabetes and risk factors for heart disease will be collected at the clinic visit.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 30, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 31, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>IQ</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>IQ assessed by the Wechsler Preschool and Primary Scale of Intelligence - Fourth Edition (WPPSI-IV)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>ADHD</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Attention Deficit Hyperactive Disorder (ADHD) Rating Scale-IV and Attention Deficit Hyperactive Disorder Rating Scale-IV Preschool Version. It is an 18-item questionnaire that requires the respondent to rate the frequency of occurrence of ADHD symptoms. The respondent rates each item on a scale of 0 (not at all) to 3 (very often).
The scale yields scores for an Inattentive, Hyperactive/Impulsive and Total Scale. The subscales are Inattention Factor and Hyperactive/Impulsive Factor.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>ASD</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Social Responsiveness Scale-2 questionnaire results for Autism Spectrum Disorder behaviours. It is an 65-item questionnaire that requires the respondent to describe the child's behaviour. The respondent rates each item on a scale of 1 (not true) to 4 (almost always true). The scale yields scores for autism spectrum disorders for total score discussion of social behaviour and social interactions.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>NEPSY-II</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>The NEPSY-II stands for &quot;A Developmental NEuroPSYchological Assessment&quot;. Children's language skills assessed using the Speed Naming and Phonological Processing subscales of the NEPSY-II testing results. Phonological Processing is a subtest composed of phonological processing tasks designed to assess phonemic awareness. Speed Naming is a timed subtest designed to assess rapid semantic access to and production of names of colors, shapes, sizes, letters, or numbers.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>CCC-2/LUI</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Parent reported language development on the Children's Communication Checklist-2 (CCC_2) for children over four years of age or the Language Use Inventory (LUI) for children 36 to 47 months of age questionnaire results. The Children's Communication Checklist - Seconda Edition has 70 Statements that refer to difficulties children may have that affect their ability to communicate. Rating key is 0 (less than once a week or never) to 3 (several times, more than twice, a day, or always). Total score is used.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Demographics</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Data form to be completed by parents will ask about their level of education, sex, gender, socioeconomic status, height, and any neurodevelopmental or other medical diagnoses in their enrolled child</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adiposity</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Childhood adiposity measures: weight, height, waist circumference and skinfold thickness (at the triceps, subscapular, flank and quadriceps). Body mass index (BMI) and Waist-Height ratio will be calculated using standardized procedures</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">174</enrollment>
  <condition>Neurologic Disorder</condition>
  <condition>Adiposity</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Participants, aged 3 to 7 years
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Children of women who participated in the CONCEPTT trial at selected recruiting sites.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Children (of women who participated in the CONCEPTT trial) with major congenital
             anomalies will be assessed on a case by case basis to determine eligibility.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>3 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>7 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jennifer Yamamoto, MD MSc FRCPC</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Calgary</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Sonya Mergler, BA</last_name>
    <phone>416-480-5627</phone>
    <email>conceptt@sunnybrook.ca</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Gail Klein, MSc</last_name>
    <phone>416-480-5632</phone>
    <email>gail.klein@sunnybrook.ca</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Calgary</name>
      <address>
        <city>Calgary</city>
        <state>Alberta</state>
        <zip>T2T 5C7</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Lois Donovan, MD FRCPC</last_name>
      <phone>403 955-8358</phone>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Lois Donovan, MD FRCPC</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Feig DS, Donovan LE, Corcoy R, Murphy KE, Amiel SA, Hunt KF, Asztalos E, Barrett JFR, Sanchez JJ, de Leiva A, Hod M, Jovanovic L, Keely E, McManus R, Hutton EK, Meek CL, Stewart ZA, Wysocki T, O'Brien R, Ruedy K, Kollman C, Tomlinson G, Murphy HR; CONCEPTT Collaborative Group. Continuous glucose monitoring in pregnant women with type 1 diabetes (CONCEPTT): a multicentre international randomised controlled trial. Lancet. 2017 Nov 25;390(10110):2347-2359. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(17)32400-5. Epub 2017 Sep 15. Erratum in: Lancet. 2017 Nov 25;390(10110):2346.</citation>
    <PMID>28923465</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>September 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 19, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 19, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 23, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 30, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 30, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 2, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Type 1 diabetes</keyword>
  <keyword>Offspring</keyword>
  <keyword>Continuous glucose monitoring</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus, Type 1</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Obesity</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Nervous System Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>There is no plan for individual level data to be shared with other researchers</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

