<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04093765</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MAL17011</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04093765</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Mass Screening and Treatment for Reduction of Falciparum Malaria</brief_title>
  <acronym>MSAT</acronym>
  <official_title>Operational Evaluation of Mass Screening and Treatment Using Ultrasensitive Rapid Detection Tests to Reduce P. Falciparum Incidence in a Malaria Elimination Program in Eastern Kayin State, Myanmar</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Oxford</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Oxford</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      In this project, the investigators aim at an operational research deployment of
      Ultrasensitive Rapid Diagnostic Test (URDT) -based Mass Screening and Treatment (MSAT) in the
      Malaria Elimination Task Force (METF) elimination program. This intervention will be tested
      in two types of setting. In group 1, MSAT will be used in a programmatic setting in order to
      decrease the reservoir of asymptomatic carriers in high incidence villages (following the
      same principles and objective as previously deployed MDA interventions). In group 2, the
      investigators take advantage of the lighter framework of MSAT to use it as a reactive
      intervention in order to respond to malaria outbreaks in low to intermediate incidence
      villages. The MSAT intervention will be preceded with community-level consent and community
      engagement (CE) activities. MSAT will be conducted over a period of approximately 1 week in
      each hamlet, village or group of villages, and will consist in administering a P. falciparum
      URDT to all individuals agreeing to participate. A limited subgroup (expected 5-25%) will be
      found positive and receive supervised treatment over 3 days for the standard regimen (DP to
      cure asexual stage infection + single low-dose primaquine to destroy gametocytes). After this
      intervention, the incidence of clinical falciparum episodes will be monitored by the village
      MP. In group 1, a comparison of the prevalence at baseline and 12 months after MSAT
      intervention will be performed through a second URDT survey, in addition to which both
      baseline and 12-month surveys will include the collection of a 200µL capillary blood sample
      for reference detection in the laboratory.

      The intervention will be evaluated primarily on its ability to reduce yearly cumulative
      incidence of clinical falciparum malaria compared to year before intervention. Additional
      evaluations of the impact of MSAT will include: in group 1, comparison of asymptomatic
      infection prevalence; and in group 2, modifications of the shape of the incidence curve
      following intervention.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      STUDY DESIGN

      Stepped-wedge open-label, non-randomized, cluster intervention.

      This study will be performed in clusters (hamlet (isolated group of household, village, or
      group of village). The intervention will be conducted in two types of clusters, both
      corresponding to locations where an excess of case was detected.

      Group 1: Sustained high incidence clusters, characterized by a yearly cumulative incidence
      &gt;84 cases/1000/year

      Villages in group 1 will be attributed an intervention a given year based on the cumulative
      incidence over the previous 12 months (METF stratification January, including the last 2
      transmission seasons). The order of intervention will be decided based on logistic
      constraints and highest incidence.

      Group 2: Focal transmission clusters, corresponding to locations where an epidemic alert has
      been signalled and confirmed (see definition of thresholds).

      Villages in group 2 will be attributed an intervention based on P. falciparum incidence in
      the previous 4 weeks. In near-0 transmission area, an intervention will be conducted in each
      likely source location of transmission of a locally acquired case. In the other areas
      (METF1+METF2), the intervention will be triggered when the incidence is above the pre-defined
      epidemic threshold.

      In each cluster, all inhabitants will be invited to undergo an URDT test to identify their
      infection status, and will receive the appropriate treatment according to their
      characteristics. Information on village inhabitants absent during the MSAT activities will be
      obtained from village population lists provided by the village headman and from household
      member declarations. During the URDT screening, all individuals will receive a unique
      identifying number that will be used to record demographic data in the MSAT paper logbook and
      to label URDT and reference sample.

      Before and after MSAT intervention, incidence of clinical malaria episodes will be recorded
      at the MP (1 or several) serving the cluster receiving the intervention. No individual data
      will be collected to link clinical case participation, infection status and incidence of
      clinical episodes.

      Participants from group 1 clusters will be invited to participate in a prevalence survey
      during MSAT and 12 months after, in order to evaluate the impact of the MSAT campaign on the
      asymptomatic carriage prevalence. This will require collection of a 200µL sample during the
      MSAT campaign and a second round of URDT screening with the collection of a 200µL sample, 12
      months after MSAT.

      STUDY PARTICIPANTS

      Populations of villages with high P. falciparum incidence located in Eastern Kayin State,
      Myanmar.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 1, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 30, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 30, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Screening</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Adjusted incidence rate ratio before/after MSAT</measure>
    <time_frame>12 month</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Prevalence of P. falciparum infection measured in the village by URDT and by reference method (group 1)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in the incidence dynamics over the transmission season (group 2)</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The percentage of participant among village resident tested by URDT.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>% of P. falciparum positive samples by reference method which were positive by URDT and treated; % of P. falciparum negative samples by reference method which were positive by URDT and treated (group 1)</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Cumulative incidence of falciparum malaria episodes before and after MDA/MSAT; prevalence of falciparum infection before and after MDA/MSAT</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">120</enrollment>
  <condition>Plasmodium Falciparum Malaria</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sustained high incidence villages</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Villages classified as high incidence, low probability of elimination (P. falciparum cumulative incidence &gt;84 cases/1000/year, in spite of &gt;1 year of functioning malaria post) will be eligible to be included in group 1. Villages in this group will be addressed by MSAT waves of 10-15 villages. Interventions will consist of 1 Ultrasensitive Rapid Diagnostic Test (URDT) and antimalarials drugs.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Seasonal focal transmission villages/locations</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>This group will follow the NMCP case/and foci investigation guidelines, but use URDT instead of standard RDT for screening. MSAT group 2 locations will be cluster of houses, villages or clusters of villages selected based on the results of case or foci/outbreak investigation. Interventions will consist of 1 Ultrasensitive Rapid Diagnostic Test (URDT) and antimalarials drugs.
Village inclusion after case investigation
Village inclusion after outbreak investigation</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ultrasensitive Rapid Diagnostic Test (URDT)</intervention_name>
    <description>Investigation will consist in 1 URDT.
For P. falciparum URDT positive:
collection of 3x1cm dried blood spots on filter paper
administration of a supervised antimalarial treatment course to individuals for which a P. falciparum will have been detected by URDT.
Specifically in group 1, a population list will be collected in each village prior to MSAT campaign and all participants will undergo:
collection of a 200 µL-aliquot of capillary blood for each participant to the screening during the MSAT intervention.
1 URDT + collection of a 200µL-aliquot of capillary blood for each participant to the follow-up survey at M12.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Seasonal focal transmission villages/locations</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Sustained high incidence villages</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Antimalarials</intervention_name>
    <description>A safe, recommended treatment of P. falciparum malaria will be administered to URDT positive individuals based on participant's characteristics:
The standard regimen for participants without known antimalarial allergy, not pregnant and not breastfeeding, will be a 3-day supervised weight-adjusted DP course and a single low dose PMQ. The single low dose PMQ will be administered on the first day.
Pregnant women and in their 2nd or 3rd trimester, and breastfeeding mothers, will receive a DP course but no PMQ.
Pregnant women in their first trimester will receive an oral course of quinine+clindamycin (7 days).
Individuals with known drug allergy to piperaquine will be treated with AL (+/- sld PMQ as per their pregnancy/breastfeeding status)
Specific/complex cases will be assessed by a medic and referred to a health facility for treatment if necessary.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Seasonal focal transmission villages/locations</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Sustained high incidence villages</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  All persons living in the village or cluster of villages will be eligible for MSAT
             intervention.

          -  Individuals living in smaller settlements (permanent or temporary) within walking
             distance of a selected intervention village will also be eligible.

          -  Large &quot;work-related&quot; settlements in the vicinity of a targeted village (military
             camps, logging camp, mining site) will be approached by the team to be included in the
             screening and treatment activity. They will be included in the analysis as a unit
             within a cluster of villages if all the study information can be collected (including
             follow-up survey for Group 1).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Individuals who do not provide informed consent for both URDT screening and treatment
             in case of positive result. Individuals will be given the possibility to refuse the
             collection of the 200µL reference sample or the DBS collection but participate to URDT
             screening and treatment.

          -  Children &lt;1 year old

          -  Individuals with a documented Pf-positive malaria RDT who received treatment (AL+sld
             PMQ) during the previous 7 days.

        NB: Individuals who were diagnosed infected with PF and received a treatment between 7 and
        30 days before the intervention are still likely to be URDT positive due to the persistence
        of HRP2, and this will result in treatment of individuals who are likely uninfected.
        However, in a high prevalence area or in an outbreak context, previous infection signals
        exposure, and DP will provide a protection against a likely re-infection.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>1 Year</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>francois Nosten, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Shoklo Malaria Research Unit</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Khin Maung Lwin</last_name>
    <phone>+95-997-265-6330</phone>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Francois Nosten, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+66 08 1881 3350</phone>
    <email>francois@tropmedres.ac</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Shoklo Malaria Research Unit</name>
      <address>
        <city>Mae Sot</city>
        <state>Tak</state>
        <zip>63110</zip>
        <country>Thailand</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Francois Nosten, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>+6655534179</phone>
      <email>francois@tropmedres.ac</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Thailand</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 2, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 17, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 18, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 17, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 17, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">September 18, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Ultrasensitive Rapid Diagnostic Test</keyword>
  <keyword>Mass Screening and Treatment</keyword>
  <keyword>Greater Mekong Subregion</keyword>
  <keyword>Malaria Elimination Task Force</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Malaria</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Malaria, Falciparum</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Antimalarials</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

