<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04096222</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>3012</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04096222</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Prospective Analysis of the Th17 Cellular Response in Pemphigus Vulgaris Patients</brief_title>
  <official_title>Prospective Analysis of the Th17 Cellular Response in Pemphigus Vulgaris Patients Treated With Corticosteroids and Optional Adjuvants</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Instituto Nacional de Ciencias Medicas y Nutricion Salvador Zubiran</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Hospital General de Mexico</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Hospital General Dr. Manuel Gea González</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Instituto Nacional de Ciencias Medicas y Nutricion Salvador Zubiran</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will evaluate the pattern of Th17 immune response throughout pemphigus treatment.
      Skin and serum samples will be taken at the moment of enrollment and at the moment the
      subject reaches a 75% improvement on disease activity.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Pemphigus is an autoimmune disease characterized by production of autoantibodies against
      desmogleins 1 and 3, which are part of the epidermis desmosomes. The first line of treatment
      are corticosteroids with or without the use of adjuvants (e.g. azathioprine, mycophenolate or
      rituximab). T lymphocytes are responsible for the initiation and maturation of the humoral
      response and the B cell activation required for the production of autoantibodies. In the last
      decade, the Th17 immune response has been implicated in the pathogenesis of pemphigus.
      Recently, the existence of tertiary lymphoid organ-like structures within the skin lesions
      was suggested. This structures contain T lymphocytes, B lymphocytes and plasma cells; these
      cells interact and create a local microenvironment for the production of autoantibodies. Most
      of the T cells in this structures are T helper CD4+ and express IL-21, and half of them
      produce IL-17.

      In this study the investigators aim to evaluate prospectively the Th17 and T regulatory
      immune response in the lesional skin and serum of active pemphigus subjects that are treated
      with corticosteroids with or without adjuvants. The investigators will study skin and serum
      due to the difference of lymphocytes and cytokines in both tissues. The primary hypothesis
      is: &quot;the subjects who receive corticosteroids with or without adjuvants and who reach a 75%
      of improvement (measured by the pemphigus disease area index) in comparison to the enrollment
      visit will have a decrease in Th17 immune response (IL-23).

      The investigators will use descriptive statistics, association and correlation test of
      hypothesis.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">September 15, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 28, 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 28, 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Other</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>percentage change of IL-23 level in skin lesions</measure>
    <time_frame>variable, 1 month to 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>The level of IL-23 mRNA from skin biopsies at the time of enrollment and when the subject reaches 75% of PDAI improvement or after a year of follow-up (termination visit). The percentage of change in these two determinations will be calculated.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Pemphigus Disease Area Index (PDAI)</measure>
    <time_frame>variable, 1 month to 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>PDAI has a total of 0-263 points, 250 are related to activity and 13 to damage. Disease severity is considered as follows: 1) moderate &lt;= 14 points; b) significative 15-44 points; and c) extensive &gt;=45</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Disease activity</measure>
    <time_frame>variable, 1 month to 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Measured with Pemphigus Disease Area Index (PDAI) and Autoimmune Bullous Skin Disorder Intensity Score (ABSIS). PDAI has a total of 0-263 points, 250 are related to activity and 13 to damage. ABSIS has a total score of 0-206.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>variable, 1 month to 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>The medications and doses used since the diagnosis and during the study</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>percentage change of TH17 cytokines levels</measure>
    <time_frame>variable, 1 month to 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>The level of IL-17a, IL-21, IL-22 and IL-23 mRNA from skin biopsies and luminometry determination of serum levels at the time of enrollment and when the subject reaches 75% of PDAI improvement or after a year of follow-up (termination visit). The percentage of change in these two determinations will be calculated.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>percentage change of Th17 chemokines levels</measure>
    <time_frame>variable, 1 month to 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>The level of CCL20 and CXCL8 mRNA from skin biopsies and luminometry determination of serum levels at the time of enrollment and when the subject reaches 75% of PDAI improvement or after a year of follow-up (termination visit). The percentage of change in these two determinations will be calculated.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of Th17 and Treg populations on skin biopsies</measure>
    <time_frame>variable, 1 month to 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Enrollment and termination biopsies will be processed for immunohistochemistry for TH17 subsets (CD+IL17a+) and Treg subset (CD25+Foxp3+). The proportion of both subsets will be quantified with specialized software.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Level of Th17 cytokines</measure>
    <time_frame>variable, 1 month to 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Determinations at the moment of enrollment and at the termination visit in skin (RT-PCR) and serum (luminometry)</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Level of Treg cytokines</measure>
    <time_frame>variable, 1 month to 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Determinations at the moment of enrollment and at the termination visit in skin (RT-PCR) and serum (luminometry)</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Morisky scale of medication adherence</measure>
    <time_frame>variable, 1 month to 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>On every visit the patient will answer the Morisky scale of medication adherence with 8 items. Every item has a value of one. The degree of adherence is considered as follows: a) low 0-5 points; b) moderate 6-7 points; c) high 8 points.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>P-glycoprotein transporter activity in mononuclear peripheral cells</measure>
    <time_frame>variable, 1 month to 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>The activity will be a measure of the percentage of efflux of daunorubicin ar 37°C. It will be measured at the moment of enrollment and at the termination visit</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Th17 peripheral cells with expression of P-glycoprotein on the surface</measure>
    <time_frame>variable, 1 month to 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Cells with the phenotype IL-17a+CCR6+CXR3hiCCR4loCCR10-CD161+PGP+ will be measured with flow cytometry at the moment of enrollment and at the termination visit</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Levels of anti-desmogleins 1 and 3</measure>
    <time_frame>variable, 1 month to 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Levels will be measures with an ELISA assay at the moment of enrollment and at the termination visit</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Autoimmune Bullous Skin Disorder Intensity Score (ABSIS)</measure>
    <time_frame>variable, 1 month to 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>ABSIS has a total score of 0-206. Disease severity is considered as follows: 1) moderate &lt;= 16 points; b) significative 17-52 points; and c) extensive &gt;=53</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Level of Treg chemokines</measure>
    <time_frame>variable, 1 month to 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Determinations at the moment of enrollment and at the termination visit in skin (RT-PCR) and serum (luminometry)</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Level of Th17 chemokines</measure>
    <time_frame>variable, 1 month to 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Determinations at the moment of enrollment and at the termination visit in skin (RT-PCR) and serum (luminometry)</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Pemphigus Vulgaris</condition>
  <condition>Bullous Dermatoses</condition>
  <condition>Autoimmune Diseases</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Pemphigus subjects</arm_group_label>
    <description>Subjects with the diagnosis of pemphigus and with active disease in the skin will be invited to participate. After informed consent, at the enrollment visit the following interventions will be done: 1) two 4 mm punch biopsies in a target lesion, 2) A 10 ml blood sample will be taken, 3) photographs of the subject, 4) demographic, disease, comorbidity and treatment data will be documented, 5) PDAI and ABSIS,6) Morisky medication adherence measure with 8 items (MMAS-8). The subject will come to follow-up visits every 6 weeks +- 2 weeks. In these visits we will take photographs, perform activity scales, document treatment and MMAS-8. The termination visit will take place when the subject reaches a 75% in PDAI scale or after one year of follow up and the following interventions will be done: 1) two 4 mm punch biopsies in the same target lesion, 2) A 10 ml blood sample will be taken, 3) photographs of the subject, 4) treatment data will be documented, 5) PDAI and ABSIS, and 6) MMAS-8</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Subjects with the diagnosis of pemphigus who are 18 or older and who have curent skin
        activity and will receive treatment with corticosteroids with or without adjuvants. At the
        moment of enrollment subjects shoould not be pregnant, have concurrent autoimmune diseases
        with skin lesions (eg cutaneous lupus), cancer or infectious diseases.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Current cutaneous activity of pemphigus

          2. Subjects will be treated with corticosteroids with or without adjuvants

          3. Accept and sign the informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Pregnancy

          2. Concurrent autoimmune diseases with skin lesions

          3. Concurrent diagnosis of cancer

          4. Concurrent active infectious disease
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Luis Guillermo Llorente Peters, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Instituto Nacional de Ciencias Medicas y Nutricion Salvador Zubiran</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Luis Guillermo Llorente Peters, MD</last_name>
    <phone>525554870900</phone>
    <phone_ext>2603</phone_ext>
    <email>luisllorentepeters57@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Alba Cicero Casarrubias, MD</last_name>
    <phone>525554870900</phone>
    <phone_ext>2604</phone_ext>
    <email>albcicero@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital General de Mexico</name>
      <address>
        <city>Mexico City</city>
        <zip>06720</zip>
        <country>Mexico</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital General Dr. Manuel Gea González</name>
      <address>
        <city>Mexico City</city>
        <zip>14080</zip>
        <country>Mexico</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Instituto Nacional de Ciencias Medicas y Nutricion Salvador Zubiran</name>
      <address>
        <city>Mexico City</city>
        <zip>14080</zip>
        <country>Mexico</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Luis Guillermo Llorente Peters, MD</last_name>
      <phone>525554870900</phone>
      <phone_ext>2603</phone_ext>
      <email>luisllorentepeters57@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Alba Cicero Casarrubias, MD</last_name>
      <phone>525554870900</phone>
      <phone_ext>2604</phone_ext>
      <email>albcicero@gmail.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Mexico</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Agarwal V, Mittal SK, Misra R. Expression of multidrug resistance-1 protein correlates with disease activity rather than the refractoriness to methotrexate therapy in rheumatoid arthritis. Clin Rheumatol. 2009 Apr;28(4):427-33. doi: 10.1007/s10067-008-1071-1. Epub 2009 Jan 10.</citation>
    <PMID>19137355</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Almugairen N, Hospital V, Bedane C, Duvert-Lehembre S, Picard D, Tronquoy AF, Houivet E, D'incan M, Joly P. Assessment of the rate of long-term complete remission off therapy in patients with pemphigus treated with different regimens including medium- and high-dose corticosteroids. J Am Acad Dermatol. 2013 Oct;69(4):583-8. doi: 10.1016/j.jaad.2013.05.016. Epub 2013 Jul 12.</citation>
    <PMID>23850258</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Arakawa M, Dainichi T, Yasumoto S, Hashimoto T. Lesional Th17 cells in pemphigus vulgaris and pemphigus foliaceus. J Dermatol Sci. 2009 Mar;53(3):228-31. doi: 10.1016/j.jdermsci.2008.09.008. Epub 2008 Nov 5.</citation>
    <PMID>18980832</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Asothai R, Anand V, Das D, Antil PS, Khandpur S, Sharma VK, Sharma A. Distinctive Treg associated CCR4-CCL22 expression profile with altered frequency of Th17/Treg cell in the immunopathogenesis of Pemphigus Vulgaris. Immunobiology. 2015 Oct;220(10):1129-35. doi: 10.1016/j.imbio.2015.06.008. Epub 2015 Jun 17.</citation>
    <PMID>26093920</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Baron JM, Höller D, Schiffer R, Frankenberg S, Neis M, Merk HF, Jugert FK. Expression of multiple cytochrome p450 enzymes and multidrug resistance-associated transport proteins in human skin keratinocytes. J Invest Dermatol. 2001 Apr;116(4):541-8.</citation>
    <PMID>11286621</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bauer B, Hartz AM, Miller DS. Tumor necrosis factor alpha and endothelin-1 increase P-glycoprotein expression and transport activity at the blood-brain barrier. Mol Pharmacol. 2007 Mar;71(3):667-75. Epub 2006 Nov 28.</citation>
    <PMID>17132686</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Borst P, Elferink RO. Mammalian ABC transporters in health and disease. Annu Rev Biochem. 2002;71:537-92. Epub 2001 Nov 9. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>12045106</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bystryn JC. Adjuvant therapy of pemphigus. Arch Dermatol. 1984 Jul;120(7):941-51. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>6375579</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bystryn JC, Steinman NM. The adjuvant therapy of pemphigus. An update. Arch Dermatol. 1996 Feb;132(2):203-12. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>8629830</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cañete JD, Celis R, Yeremenko N, Sanmartí R, van Duivenvoorde L, Ramírez J, Blijdorp I, García-Herrero CM, Pablos JL, Baeten DL. Ectopic lymphoid neogenesis is strongly associated with activation of the IL-23 pathway in rheumatoid synovitis. Arthritis Res Ther. 2015 Jul 9;17:173. doi: 10.1186/s13075-015-0688-0.</citation>
    <PMID>26156866</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cholera M, Chainani-Wu N. Management of Pemphigus Vulgaris. Adv Ther. 2016 Jun;33(6):910-58. doi: 10.1007/s12325-016-0343-4. Epub 2016 Jun 10. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>27287854</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cordon-Cardo C, O'Brien JP, Boccia J, Casals D, Bertino JR, Melamed MR. Expression of the multidrug resistance gene product (P-glycoprotein) in human normal and tumor tissues. J Histochem Cytochem. 1990 Sep;38(9):1277-87.</citation>
    <PMID>1974900</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cordon-Cardo C, O'Brien JP, Casals D, Rittman-Grauer L, Biedler JL, Melamed MR, Bertino JR. Multidrug-resistance gene (P-glycoprotein) is expressed by endothelial cells at blood-brain barrier sites. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 1989 Jan;86(2):695-8.</citation>
    <PMID>2563168</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>de la Fuente H, Baranda L, Hernández MI, Torres-Alvarez B, Llorente L, Layseca E, González-Amaro R. Lack of involvement of P-glycoprotein (P-gp) in pemphigus patients with poor response to steroid therapy. J Dermatol Sci. 2002 Apr;28(3):219-26.</citation>
    <PMID>11912009</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Murrell DF, Peña S, Joly P, Marinovic B, Hashimoto T, Diaz LA, Sinha AA, Payne AS, Daneshpazhooh M, Eming R, Jonkman MF, Mimouni D, Borradori L, Kim SC, Yamagami J, Lehman JS, Saleh MA, Culton DA, Czernik A, Zone JJ, Fivenson D, Ujiie H, Wozniak K, Akman-Karakaş A, Bernard P, Korman NJ, Caux F, Drenovska K, Prost-Squarcioni C, Vassileva S, Feldman RJ, Cardones AR, Bauer J, Ioannides D, Jedlickova H, Palisson F, Patsatsi A, Uzun S, Yayli S, Zillikens D, Amagai M, Hertl M, Schmidt E, Aoki V, Grando SA, Shimizu H, Baum S, Cianchini G, Feliciani C, Iranzo P, Mascaró JM Jr, Kowalewski C, Hall R, Groves R, Harman KE, Marinkovich MP, Maverakis E, Werth VP. Diagnosis and management of pemphigus: Recommendations of an international panel of experts. J Am Acad Dermatol. 2020 Mar;82(3):575-585.e1. doi: 10.1016/j.jaad.2018.02.021. Epub 2018 Feb 10.</citation>
    <PMID>29438767</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Diaz-Borjon A, Richaud-Patin Y, Alvarado de la Barrera C, Jakez-Ocampo J, Ruiz-Argüelles A, Llorente L. Multidrug resistance-1 (MDR-1) in rheumatic autoimmune disorders. Part II: Increased P-glycoprotein activity in lymphocytes from systemic lupus erythematosus patients might affect steroid requirements for disease control. Joint Bone Spine. 2000 Jan;67(1):40-8.</citation>
    <PMID>10773967</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Drach J, Gsur A, Hamilton G, Zhao S, Angerler J, Fiegl M, Zojer N, Raderer M, Haberl I, Andreeff M, Huber H. Involvement of P-glycoprotein in the transmembrane transport of interleukin-2 (IL-2), IL-4, and interferon-gamma in normal human T lymphocytes. Blood. 1996 Sep 1;88(5):1747-54.</citation>
    <PMID>8781431</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Farrell RJ, Murphy A, Long A, Donnelly S, Cherikuri A, O'Toole D, Mahmud N, Keeling PW, Weir DG, Kelleher D. High multidrug resistance (P-glycoprotein 170) expression in inflammatory bowel disease patients who fail medical therapy. Gastroenterology. 2000 Feb;118(2):279-88.</citation>
    <PMID>10648456</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fojo AT, Ueda K, Slamon DJ, Poplack DG, Gottesman MM, Pastan I. Expression of a multidrug-resistance gene in human tumors and tissues. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 1987 Jan;84(1):265-9.</citation>
    <PMID>2432605</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ford JM. Modulators of multidrug resistance. Preclinical studies. Hematol Oncol Clin North Am. 1995 Apr;9(2):337-61. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>7642467</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>García-Carrasco M, Mendoza-Pinto C, Macias Díaz S, Vera-Recabarren M, Vázquez de Lara L, Méndez Martínez S, Soto-Santillán P, González-Ramírez R, Ruiz-Arguelles A. P-glycoprotein in autoimmune rheumatic diseases. Autoimmun Rev. 2015 Jul;14(7):594-600. doi: 10.1016/j.autrev.2015.02.006. Epub 2015 Feb 21. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25712147</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Giordano CN, Sinha AA. Cytokine networks in Pemphigus vulgaris: An integrated viewpoint. Autoimmunity. 2012 Sep;45(6):427-39. doi: 10.3109/08916934.2012.697593. Epub 2012 Jul 13. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22686612</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gottesman MM, Pastan I. Biochemistry of multidrug resistance mediated by the multidrug transporter. Annu Rev Biochem. 1993;62:385-427. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>8102521</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Grogan JL, Ouyang W. A role for Th17 cells in the regulation of tertiary lymphoid follicles. Eur J Immunol. 2012 Sep;42(9):2255-62. doi: 10.1002/eji.201242656. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22949324</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hartz AM, Bauer B, Fricker G, Miller DS. Rapid modulation of P-glycoprotein-mediated transport at the blood-brain barrier by tumor necrosis factor-alpha and lipopolysaccharide. Mol Pharmacol. 2006 Feb;69(2):462-70. Epub 2005 Nov 8.</citation>
    <PMID>16278373</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hashimoto N, Nakamichi N, Yamazaki E, Oikawa M, Masuo Y, Schinkel AH, Kato Y. P-Glycoprotein in skin contributes to transdermal absorption of topical corticosteroids. Int J Pharm. 2017 Apr 15;521(1-2):365-373. doi: 10.1016/j.ijpharm.2017.02.064. Epub 2017 Feb 24.</citation>
    <PMID>28242377</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Heaphy MR, Albrecht J, Werth VP. Dapsone as a glucocorticoid-sparing agent in maintenance-phase pemphigus vulgaris. Arch Dermatol. 2005 Jun;141(6):699-702.</citation>
    <PMID>15967915</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Herbst A, Bystryn JC. Patterns of remission in pemphigus vulgaris. J Am Acad Dermatol. 2000 Mar;42(3):422-7.</citation>
    <PMID>10688711</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Higgins CF. ABC transporters: from microorganisms to man. Annu Rev Cell Biol. 1992;8:67-113. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>1282354</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Horio M, Gottesman MM, Pastan I. ATP-dependent transport of vinblastine in vesicles from human multidrug-resistant cells. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 1988 May;85(10):3580-4.</citation>
    <PMID>3368466</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ito K, Nguyen HT, Kato Y, Wakayama T, Kubo Y, Iseki S, Tsuji A. P-glycoprotein (Abcb1) is involved in absorptive drug transport in skin. J Control Release. 2008 Nov 12;131(3):198-204. doi: 10.1016/j.jconrel.2008.08.004. Epub 2008 Aug 12.</citation>
    <PMID>18725258</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Johnstone RW, Ruefli AA, Smyth MJ. Multiple physiological functions for multidrug transporter P-glycoprotein? Trends Biochem Sci. 2000 Jan;25(1):1-6. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>10637601</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kappelmayer J, Karászi E, Telek B, Jakab K. &quot;Pros and cons&quot; on how to measure multidrug resistance in leukemias. Leuk Lymphoma. 2002 Apr;43(4):711-7. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>12153155</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Klimecki WT, Futscher BW, Grogan TM, Dalton WS. P-glycoprotein expression and function in circulating blood cells from normal volunteers. Blood. 1994 May 1;83(9):2451-8.</citation>
    <PMID>7513198</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kneisel A, Hertl M. Autoimmune bullous skin diseases. Part 1: Clinical manifestations. J Dtsch Dermatol Ges. 2011 Oct;9(10):844-56; quiz 857. doi: 10.1111/j.1610-0387.2011.07793.x. Review. English, German.</citation>
    <PMID>21955378</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Liu W, Li H, Zhang D, Lv M, Li Y, Hao Y, Chen Y, Liu X, Xue F, Zhang L, Yang R. Effects of the multidrug resistance-1 gene on drug resistance in primary immune thrombocytopenia. Autoimmunity. 2016 Nov;49(7):486-495. Epub 2016 Jun 3.</citation>
    <PMID>27258931</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Llorente L, Richaud-Patin Y, Díaz-Borjón A, Alvarado de la Barrera C, Jakez-Ocampo J, de la Fuente H, Gonzalez-Amaro R, Diaz-Jouanen E. Multidrug resistance-1 (MDR-1) in rheumatic autoimmune disorders. Part I: Increased P-glycoprotein activity in lymphocytes from rheumatoid arthritis patients might influence disease outcome. Joint Bone Spine. 2000 Jan;67(1):30-9.</citation>
    <PMID>10773966</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ludescher C, Thaler J, Drach D, Drach J, Spitaler M, Gattringer C, Huber H, Hofmann J. Detection of activity of P-glycoprotein in human tumour samples using rhodamine 123. Br J Haematol. 1992 Sep;82(1):161-8.</citation>
    <PMID>1358171</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Maillefert JF, Maynadie M, Tebib JG, Aho S, Walker P, Chatard C, Dulieu V, Bouvier M, Carli PM, Tavernier C. Expression of the multidrug resistance glycoprotein 170 in the peripheral blood lymphocytes of rheumatoid arthritis patients. The percentage of lymphocytes expressing glycoprotein 170 is increased in patients treated with prednisolone. Br J Rheumatol. 1996 May;35(5):430-5.</citation>
    <PMID>8646432</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Masjedi M, Esmaeil N, Saffaei A, Abtahi-Naeini B, Pourazizi M, Haghjooy Javanmard S, Asilian A. Cytokine Indexes in Pemphigus Vulgaris: Perception of Its Immunpathogenesis and Hopes for Non-Steroidal Treatment. Iran J Pharm Res. 2017 Summer;16(3):1223-1229.</citation>
    <PMID>29201111</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>McClean S, Hill BT. Evidence of post-translational regulation of P-glycoprotein associated with the expression of a distinctive multiple drug-resistant phenotype in Chinese hamster ovary cells. Eur J Cancer. 1993;29A(16):2243-8.</citation>
    <PMID>7906532</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Morisky DE, Ang A, Krousel-Wood M, Ward HJ. Predictive validity of a medication adherence measure in an outpatient setting. J Clin Hypertens (Greenwich). 2008 May;10(5):348-54.</citation>
    <PMID>18453793</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Morisky DE, Green LW, Levine DM. Concurrent and predictive validity of a self-reported measure of medication adherence. Med Care. 1986 Jan;24(1):67-74.</citation>
    <PMID>3945130</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mortazavi H, Esmaili N, Khezri S, Khamesipour A, Vasheghani Farahani I, Daneshpazhooh M, Rezaei N. The effect of conventional immunosuppressive therapy on cytokine serum levels in pemphigus vulgaris patients. Iran J Allergy Asthma Immunol. 2014 Jun;13(3):174-83.</citation>
    <PMID>24659121</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Murrell DF, Dick S, Ahmed AR, Amagai M, Barnadas MA, Borradori L, Bystryn JC, Cianchini G, Diaz L, Fivenson D, Hall R, Harman KE, Hashimoto T, Hertl M, Hunzelmann N, Iranzo P, Joly P, Jonkman MF, Kitajima Y, Korman NJ, Martin LK, Mimouni D, Pandya AG, Payne AS, Rubenstein D, Shimizu H, Sinha AA, Sirois D, Zillikens D, Werth VP. Consensus statement on definitions of disease, end points, and therapeutic response for pemphigus. J Am Acad Dermatol. 2008 Jun;58(6):1043-6. doi: 10.1016/j.jaad.2008.01.012. Epub 2008 Mar 14.</citation>
    <PMID>18339444</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Osman-Ponchet H, Boulai A, Kouidhi M, Sevin K, Alriquet M, Gaborit A, Bertino B, Comby P, Ruty B. Characterization of ABC transporters in human skin. Drug Metabol Drug Interact. 2014;29(2):91-100. doi: 10.1515/dmdi-2013-0042.</citation>
    <PMID>24558228</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Perez-Guerrero EE, Gonzalez-Lopez L, Muñoz-Valle JF, Vasquez-Jimenez JC, Ramirez-Villafaña M, Sanchez-Rodriguez EN, Gutierrez-Ureña SR, Cerpa-Cruz S, Aguilar-Chavez EA, Cardona-Muñoz EG, Vazquez-Villegas ML, Saldaña-Cruz AM, Rodriguez-Jimenez NA, Fajardo-Robledo NS, Gamez-Nava JI. Serum P-glycoprotein level: a potential biomarker of DMARD failure in patients with rheumatoid arthritis. Inflammopharmacology. 2018 Sep 12. doi: 10.1007/s10787-018-0529-2. [Epub ahead of print]</citation>
    <PMID>30209762</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Peters A, Pitcher LA, Sullivan JM, Mitsdoerffer M, Acton SE, Franz B, Wucherpfennig K, Turley S, Carroll MC, Sobel RA, Bettelli E, Kuchroo VK. Th17 cells induce ectopic lymphoid follicles in central nervous system tissue inflammation. Immunity. 2011 Dec 23;35(6):986-96. doi: 10.1016/j.immuni.2011.10.015. Epub 2011 Dec 15.</citation>
    <PMID>22177922</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pfütze M, Niedermeier A, Hertl M, Eming R. Introducing a novel Autoimmune Bullous Skin Disorder Intensity Score (ABSIS) in pemphigus. Eur J Dermatol. 2007 Jan-Feb;17(1):4-11. Epub 2007 Feb 27. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>17324820</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pisanti S, Sharav Y, Kaufman E, Posner LN. Pemphigus vulgaris: incidence in Jews of different ethnic groups, according to age, sex, and initial lesion. Oral Surg Oral Med Oral Pathol. 1974 Sep;38(3):382-7.</citation>
    <PMID>4528670</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ramesh R, Kozhaya L, McKevitt K, Djuretic IM, Carlson TJ, Quintero MA, McCauley JL, Abreu MT, Unutmaz D, Sundrud MS. Pro-inflammatory human Th17 cells selectively express P-glycoprotein and are refractory to glucocorticoids. J Exp Med. 2014 Jan 13;211(1):89-104. doi: 10.1084/jem.20130301. Epub 2014 Jan 6.</citation>
    <PMID>24395888</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Randolph GJ, Beaulieu S, Pope M, Sugawara I, Hoffman L, Steinman RM, Muller WA. A physiologic function for p-glycoprotein (MDR-1) during the migration of dendritic cells from skin via afferent lymphatic vessels. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 1998 Jun 9;95(12):6924-9.</citation>
    <PMID>9618515</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Richaud-Patin Y, Vega-Boada F, Vidaller A, Llorente L. Multidrug resistance-1 (MDR-1) in autoimmune disorders IV. P-glycoprotein overfunction in lymphocytes from myasthenia gravis patients. Biomed Pharmacother. 2004 Jun;58(5):320-4.</citation>
    <PMID>15194168</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ruiz-Soto R, Richaud-Patin Y, López-Karpovitch X, Llorente L. Multidrug resistance-1 (MDR-1) in autoimmune disorders III: increased P-glycoprotein activity in lymphocytes from immune thrombocytopenic purpura patients. Exp Hematol. 2003 Jun;31(6):483-7.</citation>
    <PMID>12829023</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sakaguchi S, Ono M, Setoguchi R, Yagi H, Hori S, Fehervari Z, Shimizu J, Takahashi T, Nomura T. Foxp3+ CD25+ CD4+ natural regulatory T cells in dominant self-tolerance and autoimmune disease. Immunol Rev. 2006 Aug;212:8-27. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>16903903</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schmidt E, Goebeler M, Hertl M, Sárdy M, Sitaru C, Eming R, Hofmann SC, Hunzelmann N, Kern JS, Kramer H, Orzechowski HD, Pfeiffer C, Schuster V, Sporbeck B, Sticherling M, Worm M, Zillikens D, Nast A. S2k guideline for the diagnosis of pemphigus vulgaris/foliaceus and bullous pemphigoid. J Dtsch Dermatol Ges. 2015 Jul;13(7):713-27. doi: 10.1111/ddg.12612. English, German.</citation>
    <PMID>26110729</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sinha AA. Constructing immunoprofiles to deconstruct disease complexity in pemphigus. Autoimmunity. 2012 Feb;45(1):36-43. doi: 10.3109/08916934.2011.606445. Epub 2011 Sep 19. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21923617</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Solís-Arias MP, Rodríguez-Gutiérrez G, Rodríguez-Carreón AA, Vega-Memije E, Domínguez-Soto L. [Epidemiology of bullous pemphigoid in 32 years]. Gac Med Mex. 2013 May-Jun;149(3):344-8. Spanish.</citation>
    <PMID>23807337</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Steinman L. A brief history of T(H)17, the first major revision in the T(H)1/T(H)2 hypothesis of T cell-mediated tissue damage. Nat Med. 2007 Feb;13(2):139-45. Review. Erratum in: Nat Med. 2007 Mar;13(3):385.</citation>
    <PMID>17290272</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sugiyama H, Matsue H, Nagasaka A, Nakamura Y, Tsukamoto K, Shibagaki N, Kawamura T, Kitamura R, Ando N, Shimada S. CD4+CD25high regulatory T cells are markedly decreased in blood of patients with pemphigus vulgaris. Dermatology. 2007;214(3):210-20.</citation>
    <PMID>17377382</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Takahashi H, Amagai M, Nishikawa T, Fujii Y, Kawakami Y, Kuwana M. Novel system evaluating in vivo pathogenicity of desmoglein 3-reactive T cell clones using murine pemphigus vulgaris. J Immunol. 2008 Jul 15;181(2):1526-35.</citation>
    <PMID>18606708</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Timoteo RP, da Silva MV, Miguel CB, Silva DA, Catarino JD, Rodrigues Junior V, Sales-Campos H, Freire Oliveira CJ. Th1/Th17-Related Cytokines and Chemokines and Their Implications in the Pathogenesis of Pemphigus Vulgaris. Mediators Inflamm. 2017;2017:7151285. doi: 10.1155/2017/7151285. Epub 2017 Feb 22.</citation>
    <PMID>28321152</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tsujimura S, Tanaka Y. Treatment strategy based on targeting P-glycoprotein on peripheral lymphocytes in patients with systemic autoimmune disease. Clin Exp Nephrol. 2012 Feb;16(1):102-8. doi: 10.1007/s10157-011-0520-3. Epub 2011 Aug 17. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21847519</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tsujimura S, Saito K, Nawata M, Nakayamada S, Tanaka Y. Overcoming drug resistance induced by P-glycoprotein on lymphocytes in patients with refractory rheumatoid arthritis. Ann Rheum Dis. 2008 Mar;67(3):380-8. Epub 2007 Jul 27.</citation>
    <PMID>17660216</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ueda K, Cornwell MM, Gottesman MM, Pastan I, Roninson IB, Ling V, Riordan JR. The mdr1 gene, responsible for multidrug-resistance, codes for P-glycoprotein. Biochem Biophys Res Commun. 1986 Dec 30;141(3):956-62.</citation>
    <PMID>2880583</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Valencia-Monsalvez F, Mendoza-Parra S, Luengo-Machuca L. [Evaluation of Morisky medication adherence scale (mmas-8) in older adults of a primary health care center in Chile]. Rev Peru Med Exp Salud Publica. 2017 Apr-Jun;34(2):245-249. doi: 10.17843/rpmesp.2017.342.2206. Spanish.</citation>
    <PMID>29177383</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>van de Ven R, Oerlemans R, van der Heijden JW, Scheffer GL, de Gruijl TD, Jansen G, Scheper RJ. ABC drug transporters and immunity: novel therapeutic targets in autoimmunity and cancer. J Leukoc Biol. 2009 Nov;86(5):1075-87. doi: 10.1189/jlb.0309147. Epub 2009 Sep 10. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19745159</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wolking S, Schaeffeler E, Lerche H, Schwab M, Nies AT. Impact of Genetic Polymorphisms of ABCB1 (MDR1, P-Glycoprotein) on Drug Disposition and Potential Clinical Implications: Update of the Literature. Clin Pharmacokinet. 2015 Jul;54(7):709-35. doi: 10.1007/s40262-015-0267-1. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25860377</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Xu RC, Zhu HQ, Li WP, Zhao XQ, Yuan HJ, Zheng J, Pan M. The imbalance of Th17 and regulatory T cells in pemphigus patients. Eur J Dermatol. 2013 Nov-Dec;23(6):795-802. doi: 10.1684/ejd.2013.2177.</citation>
    <PMID>24192290</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Xu T, Stewart KM, Wang X, Liu K, Xie M, Ryu JK, Li K, Ma T, Wang H, Ni L, Zhu S, Cao N, Zhu D, Zhang Y, Akassoglou K, Dong C, Driggers EM, Ding S. Metabolic control of T(H)17 and induced T(reg) cell balance by an epigenetic mechanism. Nature. 2017 Aug 10;548(7666):228-233. doi: 10.1038/nature23475. Epub 2017 Aug 2.</citation>
    <PMID>28783731</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Xue J, Su W, Chen Z, Ke Y, Du X, Zhou Q. Overexpression of interleukin-23 and interleukin-17 in the lesion of pemphigus vulgaris: a preliminary study. Mediators Inflamm. 2014;2014:463928. doi: 10.1155/2014/463928. Epub 2014 May 11.</citation>
    <PMID>24899786</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yuan H, Zhou S, Liu Z, Cong W, Fei X, Zeng W, Zhu H, Xu R, Wang Y, Zheng J, Pan M. Pivotal Role of Lesional and Perilesional T/B Lymphocytes in Pemphigus Pathogenesis. J Invest Dermatol. 2017 Nov;137(11):2362-2370. doi: 10.1016/j.jid.2017.05.032. Epub 2017 Jun 22.</citation>
    <PMID>28647348</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zhao M, Huang W, Zhang Q, Gao F, Wang L, Zhang G, Su Y, Xiao R, Zhang J, Tang M, Cheng W, Tan Y, Lu Q. Aberrant epigenetic modifications in peripheral blood mononuclear cells from patients with pemphigus vulgaris. Br J Dermatol. 2012 Sep;167(3):523-31. doi: 10.1111/j.1365-2133.2012.11007.x. Epub 2012 Aug 10.</citation>
    <PMID>22512277</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>July 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 15, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 18, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 19, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 18, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 18, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">September 19, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>pemphigus</keyword>
  <keyword>Th17</keyword>
  <keyword>IL-23</keyword>
  <keyword>IL-17</keyword>
  <keyword>autoimmune bullous disease</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pemphigus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Skin Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Skin Diseases, Vesiculobullous</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Autoimmune Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

