<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04094545</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ThirdXiangyaJHY</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04094545</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Intestinal Flora Sequencing for Nasopharyngeal Carcinoma</brief_title>
  <official_title>Intestinal Flora Disruption and a Novel Intestinal Biomarker Associated With Nasopharyngeal Carcinoma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>The Third Xiangya Hospital of Central South University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>The Third Xiangya Hospital of Central South University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study investigated the correlation between the changes in the intestinal flora and NPC
      by an examination of the intestinal flora and multiple clinical indicators of the blood of 8
      carefully screened patients of familial NPC, 24 patients of sporadic NPC and 27 healthy
      controls and a comparison of the differences in their intestinal flora structures and
      biological functions. By analyzing the function of the intestinal floras of NPC patients, we
      aimed to provide a better biological marker for patients with familial and sporadic NPC and
      constructed a disease prediction model for high-risk populations.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Nasopharyngeal carcinoma (NPC) is a malignant nasopharyngeal disease with a complicated
      etiology that occurs mostly in southern China. Intestinal flora imbalance is believed to be
      associated with a variety of organ malignancies. Currently, the relationship between
      intestinal flora and NPC is not clear, although many studies have shown that intestinal flora
      can be used as a biomarker for many cancers and to predict cancer.

      To compare the differences in intestinal flora compositions and biological functions among
      patients with familial NPC (NPC_F), patients with sporadic NPC (NPC_S) and healthy controls
      (NOR), we compared the intestinal flora DNA sequencing and hematological testing results
      between every two groups using bioinformatic methods.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">August 1, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 30, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 31, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Other</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>family NPC patients</measure>
    <time_frame>through study completion, an average of 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>NPC patients with a first degree NPC family history</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>sporadic NPC patients</measure>
    <time_frame>through study completion, an average of 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>NPC patients without any tumor family history</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">568</enrollment>
  <condition>Nasopharyngeal Carcinoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Nasopharyngeal carcinoma(NPC)</arm_group_label>
    <description>The patients (1) were diagnosed with NPC; 2)18&lt; Age &lt;75.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Health adults</arm_group_label>
    <description>(1) 18&lt; Age &lt;75, and Han Chinese residents living in Hunan more than 3 years. (2) Health examination population who physical examination, assistant examination and serological examination were normal; None of the patients had rhinitis or used any antibiotics during the three months last 3 months.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      The faeces and the sera of the recruited participants
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        We recruited 481 NPC patients and staged their tumor status with the AJCC 7th edition
        staging criteria，at the same time, 87 healthy volunteers were recruited.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  NPC patients with a first degree family history of NPC

          -  NPC patients without any kind of tumor family history

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Informed refusal.

          -  Lack of necessary tests and patient test information is not detailed
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>the Third Xiangya Hospital of Central South University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Changsha</city>
        <state>Hunan</state>
        <zip>410006</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Bei JX, Li Y, Jia WH, Feng BJ, Zhou G, Chen LZ, Feng QS, Low HQ, Zhang H, He F, Tai ES, Kang T, Liu ET, Liu J, Zeng YX. A genome-wide association study of nasopharyngeal carcinoma identifies three new susceptibility loci. Nat Genet. 2010 Jul;42(7):599-603. doi: 10.1038/ng.601. Epub 2010 May 30.</citation>
    <PMID>20512145</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Bhatt AP, Redinbo MR, Bultman SJ. The role of the microbiome in cancer development and therapy. CA Cancer J Clin. 2017 Jul 8;67(4):326-344. doi: 10.3322/caac.21398. Epub 2017 May 8. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>28481406</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Bokulich NA, Kaehler BD, Rideout JR, Dillon M, Bolyen E, Knight R, Huttley GA, Gregory Caporaso J. Optimizing taxonomic classification of marker-gene amplicon sequences with QIIME 2's q2-feature-classifier plugin. Microbiome. 2018 May 17;6(1):90. doi: 10.1186/s40168-018-0470-z.</citation>
    <PMID>29773078</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Bray F, Ferlay J, Soerjomataram I, Siegel RL, Torre LA, Jemal A. Global cancer statistics 2018: GLOBOCAN estimates of incidence and mortality worldwide for 36 cancers in 185 countries. CA Cancer J Clin. 2018 Nov;68(6):394-424. doi: 10.3322/caac.21492. Epub 2018 Sep 12.</citation>
    <PMID>30207593</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Chung H, Pamp SJ, Hill JA, Surana NK, Edelman SM, Troy EB, Reading NC, Villablanca EJ, Wang S, Mora JR, Umesaki Y, Mathis D, Benoist C, Relman DA, Kasper DL. Gut immune maturation depends on colonization with a host-specific microbiota. Cell. 2012 Jun 22;149(7):1578-93. doi: 10.1016/j.cell.2012.04.037.</citation>
    <PMID>22726443</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Escobar JS, Klotz B, Valdes BE, Agudelo GM. The gut microbiota of Colombians differs from that of Americans, Europeans and Asians. BMC Microbiol. 2014 Dec 14;14:311. doi: 10.1186/s12866-014-0311-6.</citation>
    <PMID>25495462</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Ferlay J, Colombet M, Soerjomataram I, Mathers C, Parkin DM, Piñeros M, Znaor A, Bray F. Estimating the global cancer incidence and mortality in 2018: GLOBOCAN sources and methods. Int J Cancer. 2019 Apr 15;144(8):1941-1953. doi: 10.1002/ijc.31937. Epub 2018 Dec 6.</citation>
    <PMID>30350310</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Goodrich JK, Waters JL, Poole AC, Sutter JL, Koren O, Blekhman R, Beaumont M, Van Treuren W, Knight R, Bell JT, Spector TD, Clark AG, Ley RE. Human genetics shape the gut microbiome. Cell. 2014 Nov 6;159(4):789-99. doi: 10.1016/j.cell.2014.09.053.</citation>
    <PMID>25417156</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>September 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 17, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 17, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 19, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 17, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 17, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">September 19, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Biomarker</keyword>
  <keyword>nasopharyngeal carcinoma</keyword>
  <keyword>familial</keyword>
  <keyword>sporadic</keyword>
  <keyword>intestinal flora</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Nasopharyngeal Carcinoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

