<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03697291</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Si 548/2018</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03697291</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Self-invented Intracavitary ECG Wire VS the Commercial System - Certodyn®</brief_title>
  <acronym>iECG</acronym>
  <official_title>Comparison of the Self-invented Intracavitary ECG Wire With the Commercial System - Certodyn®</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Mahidol University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Mahidol University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Peripherally Inserted Central Catheter (PICC) is considered a central venous line placement
      (CVL) which mandates the confirmation of the tip's location. At present, most CVL's position
      are confirmed by radiographic method either by in-procedure fluoroscopy or post-insertion
      x-ray. For CVLs placed from upper body (from internal jugular vein, subclavian veins or upper
      arm veins), the intracavitary electrocardiogram (iECG) can also be used.

      Intracavitary ECG are proven effective for tip confirmation and provide some benefits i.e.
      lower cost, decrease exposure to harmful radiation for care providers and also the patients,
      require less personals and equipments, provide real-time confirmation as comparable to
      fluoroscopy, etc. There are several devices and makes of iECG apparatus but B.Braun-Certodyn®
      remains the only available system in our institution. The limitation is the availability of
      the Certodyn devices on each locations where CVL will be placed i.e. operating theater,
      intensive care unit, bedside placement, radiology suite, etc. Since the connecting wire is
      only supplied in the certain CVL kits under B.Braun brand, this has rendered iECG for other
      types or makes of CVL or PICC line become even more difficult.

      Self-invented connector wire for iECG (PS wire) has been made and used effectively in the
      past few years at Siriraj hospital. The patent registration is underway and the author seek
      to compare this PS wire against the commercial Certodyn system.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Objective

        1. To evaluate the success rate of iECG CVL tip confirmation by self-invented iECG
           connector wire.

        2. To compare quality of iECG tracing produced from both of self-invented iECG wire versus
           the Certodyn system.

      Materials, participants and study method

      Equipments required:

      1) Self-invented iECG wire (PS wire) 2) Commercial iECG system which consists of the Certodyn
      and the wire. 3) Standard ECG monitoring system which can display and printout the ECG
      tracing. 4) A digital ECG caliper which can measure P wave amplitude and noise segment in
      millimeter up to 2 decimal points. Study method

        1. Patient presented for PICC line from upper torso will be screened and assessed for
           eligibility.

        2. Exclusion criteria includes children younger than 18 yo, patient with atrial
           fibrillation or other rhythms not generated from intrinsic SA node i.e. pacer, unstable
           hemodynamic, patient with history arrhythmias, HR &gt; 120 bpm, patients with
           hypercoagulable state, allergy to heparin or patients with known heparin induced
           thrombocytopenia, patients with known Creutzfeldt-Jakob Disease

        3. Obtain informed consent.

        4. Patient will be monitored with standard 3-lead ECG, the baseline lead II ECG will be
           printed out and tagged with a serial number.

        5. Patient will undergo the standard PICC line placement using Seldinger or modified
           Seldinger technique. The catheter will be pre-flushed with 10 units/mL heparinized NSS.
           When catheter is inserted into the proximal SVC (guided by landmark measurement), the
           wire will be retracted to the marked location where the tip of the wire is at the end of
           the catheter. The iECG connection by Certodyn will be applied. The catheter and wire
           will be adjusted until the giant P wave (highest P) was detected on screen, this ECG
           tracing will be printed out and tagged with another non-sequential serial number. The
           iECG will then switched to the PS wire and the iECG tracing will be printed out again
           and tagged with another non-sequential serial number. All 3 ECG printouts will be
           stapled together for measurement by cardiologist who is blind to the intervention later.

        6. The intervention related to research study is considered ended at this point. The
           patient will have their CVL/PICC line adjusted to the proper position (mid to distal SVC
           for mid-long term and long term catheter). The CVL or PICC will be secured, flushed and
           locked per standard protocol.

        7. Portable CXR will be routinely obtained when patients arrived to the ward. The
           information of the tip of the catheter will be recorded as well.

      Data analysis

        1. Demographic data, type of catheter, depth of catheter where giant P wave obtained and
           final position of catheter will be recorded.

        2. Each study patient produce 3 ECG print outs which are -baseline surface lead II ECG

             -  iECG produced by Certodyn system

             -  iECG produced by PS wire Each ECG tracing will be evaluated and measured by a
                cardiologist who is blind to the intervention. The 2 measured parameters includes:

             -  The amplitude of P wave in mm from baseline surface ECG of each cardiac cycle. -The
                amplitude of giant P wave in mm from iECG from both Certodyn and PS wire.

        3. All 3 ECG print outs will be compared for quality and the length noisy ECG segment
           (determined as the ECG with interference artifact of baseline &gt; 1 mm) will also be
           measured in mm.

      6) All measurement will be analyzed statistically to determine the differences between the 2
      systems.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">August 1, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 31, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Single center, prospective, cross over study</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>unlabeled ECG print</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Signal noise ratio</measure>
    <time_frame>10 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>Measuring the segment of ECG noise (if exists) in millimeters compare to the total ECG segment. Compare this signal noise ratio between the baseline surface ECG, the self-invented wire derived iECG and the Certodyn derived iECG.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The amplitude of giant P Wave</measure>
    <time_frame>5 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>Measure the amplitude of each giant P wave obtained from ECG print out from iECG derived from both certodyn and self-invented iECG wire.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">36</enrollment>
  <condition>Central Line Complication</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>PS wire</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>self-invented iECG wire</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Certodyn</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Commercially available iECG system - Certodyn</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>PS wire</intervention_name>
    <description>The wiring connection used to convey ECG signal from inside the body</description>
    <arm_group_label>Certodyn</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>PS wire</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Self-invented iECG wire</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patient age 18 years and above.

          -  Requires PICC line insertion from upper torso.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Children younger than 18 years.

          -  Patient with atrial fibrillation or other rhythms not generated from intrinsic SA node
             i.e. pacer, atrial fibrillation, etc.

          -  Unstable hemodynamic.

          -  Patient with history arrhythmias.

          -  Patient with HR &gt; 120 bpm.

          -  Patients with hypercoagulable state.

          -  Allergy to heparin.

          -  Patients with known heparin induced thrombocytopenia.

          -  Patients with known Creutzfeldt-Jakob Disease.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Prasert Sawasdiwipachai, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Anesthesiology department Siriraj hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Prasert Sawasdiwipachai, MD</last_name>
    <phone>66874147409</phone>
    <email>prasert.saw@mahidol.ac.th</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Vithaya Chaithiraphan, MD</last_name>
    <phone>6687414708</phone>
    <email>vithayac@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Siriraj hospital, Mahidol university</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bangkok Noi</city>
        <state>Bangkok</state>
        <zip>10700</zip>
        <country>Thailand</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Prasert Sawasdiwipachai, MD</last_name>
      <phone>Vithaya</phone>
      <email>vithayac@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Vithaya Chaithiraphan, MD</last_name>
      <phone>66874147408</phone>
      <email>vithayac@gmail.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of Anesthesiology, Faculty of Medicine, Siriraj Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bangkok</city>
        <zip>10700</zip>
        <country>Thailand</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Prasert Sawasdiwipachai, MD</last_name>
      <phone>6624113256</phone>
      <email>sipswp@mahidol.ac.rh</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Sirilak Suksompong, MD</last_name>
      <phone>6624113256</phone>
      <email>sirilak.suk@mahidol.ac.th</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Thailand</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>1. Oster, D.D. &quot;Improving ECG trace quality.&quot; Biomedical Instrumentation &amp; Technology, 2000; 34: 219-222. 2. Corsten SA, van Dijk B, Bakker NC, de Lange JJ, Scheffer GJ. Central venous catheter placement using the ECG-guided Cavafix-Certodyn SD catheter. J Clin Anesth. 1994; 6(6): 469-72. 3. Pittiruti M, La Greca A, Scoppettuolo G. The electrocardiographic method for positioning the tip of central venous catheters. J Vasc Access. 2011; 12(4): 280-91. 4. Pittiruti M, Bertollo D, Briglia E, Buononato M, Capozzoli G, De Simone L, La Greca A, Pelagatti C, Sette P. The intracavitory ECG method for positioning the tip of central venous catheters: results of an italian multicenter study. J Vasc Access. 2012; 13(3):357-65. 5. Wang G, Guo L, Jiang B, Huang M, Zhang J, Qin Y. Factors Influencing Intracavitory Electrocardiographic P-Wave Changes during Central Venous Catheter Placement. PLoS One. 201510(4):e0124846. 6. Yuan L, Li R, Meng A, Feng Y, Wu X, Yang Y, et al. Superior success rate of intracavitory electrocardiogram guidance for peripherally inserted central catheter placement in patients with cancer: A randomized open-label controlled multi center study. PLoO One. 2017; 12(3):e0171630.</citation>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>October 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 1, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 3, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 5, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 4, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 4, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 9, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Mahidol University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Prasert Sawasdiwipachai</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Self invented iECG wire</keyword>
  <keyword>PS wire</keyword>
  <keyword>Certodyn</keyword>
  <keyword>intracavitary ECG</keyword>
  <keyword>PICC line</keyword>
  <keyword>giant P wave</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

