<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03696602</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>enf4327</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03696602</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>More Relaxation by Deep Breath on Methacholine</brief_title>
  <acronym>SouProvocBro</acronym>
  <official_title>More Relaxation by Deep Breath on Methacholine- Than on Exercise-Induced Bronchoconstriction During the Routine Testing of Asthmatic Children</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Central Hospital, Nancy, France</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Central Hospital, Nancy, France</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Deep inhalation (DI) dilates normal airway precontracted with methacholine. The fact that
      this effect is diminished or absent in asthma could be explained by the presence of bronchial
      inflammation. The hypothesis tested was that DI induces more relaxation in methacholine
      induced bronchoconstriction—solely determined by the smooth muscle contraction—than in
      exercise induced bronchoconstriction, which is contributed to by both smooth muscle
      contraction and airway wall inflammation.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Children were referred to the lung function department by their pediatric pulmonologist.
      Asthma was defined by a complaint of wheezing, cough, dyspnoea or chest tightness at rest or
      on exercising and a positive response to methacholine or exercise challenge.

      The response to exercise was considered positive when Forced Expiratory Volume in 1 s (FEV1)
      decreased at least 8% from Baseline.

      The response to methacholine was considered positive when FEV1 decreased at least 20% or Rrs
      increased at least 50% from baseline, at or below a cumulated dose of 1,200 μg.

      Bronchodilator medications were discontinued at least 12 hours prior to the testing and
      provocation allowed when the child had been free of respiratory symptoms for at least 2 weeks
      and baseline FEV1 was larger than 70% pred. Exercise and methacholine groups were matched for
      age, height, baseline FEV1 z-score, a moderate level of airway response to challenge and DI
      amplitude ranging 40-60% of the predicted Forced Vital Capacity (FVC). Written informed
      consent was obtained from the children and their parents for the procedures. Procedures for
      spirometry, exhaled fraction of NO (FENO), GrsDI (Respiratory conductance response to a deep
      inhalation) and challenges have been described previously. Acceptable GrsDI's were analyzed
      at a 10-20% FEV1 decrease from baseline. Statistics were performed using Mann-Whitney, Chi
      square tests and multiple regression as required. Data are median and interquartile range.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 1, 2006</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">September 30, 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 30, 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Other</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Retrospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Grs change between before deep breath and after deep breath in exercise and metacholine groups</measure>
    <time_frame>through study completion, an average of 1 hour</time_frame>
    <description>GrsDI represents Grs measured after deep breath reported to Grs before deep breath (bronchial provocation test)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">78</enrollment>
  <condition>Childhood Asthma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>test with methacholine</arm_group_label>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>test with exercise</arm_group_label>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>bronchial provocation test</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>test with exercise</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>test with methacholine</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Seventy-three asthmatic children (48 boys) were selected, 37 underwent exercise challenge
        and 36 methacholine.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Children referred to the lung function department by their pediatric pulmonologist.

          -  Asthma defined by a complaint of wheezing, cough and dyspnoea.

          -  Positive response to methacholine or exercise challenge.

          -  Bronchodilator medications discontinued at least 12 h prior to the testing

          -  Provocation allowed when the child had been free of respiratory symptoms for at least
             2 weeks and baseline FEV1 larger than 70% pred.

        Exclusion Criteria:

        - Other respiratory diseases than asthma
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>6 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>14 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <verification_date>September 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 21, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 28, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 4, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 28, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 28, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 4, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>airway smooth muscle, asthma, bronchial test, lung function</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Asthma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

