<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03697889</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CO-171115092223-PACT</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03697889</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study to Assess Bioquivalence Between a Novel Naproxen Sodium 275 mg Film-coated Tablet and Nalgesin Naproxen Sodium 275 mg Film-coated Tablet in Healthy Adult Volunteers</brief_title>
  <official_title>An Open-label, Randomized, Single-dose, Two-treatment, Crossover Bioequivalence Study Comparing a Novel Naproxen Sodium 275 mg Film-coated Tablet (BILIM ILAC SANAYII VE TICARET A.S., TURKEY) and Nalgesin® 275 mg Naproxen Sodium Film-coated Tablet (JSC &quot;KRKA, D.D., NOVO MESTO&quot;, SLOVENIA), in Healthy Adult Volunteers</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>McNeil AB</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Johnson &amp; Johnson Consumer and Personal Products Worldwide</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a research study designed to evaluate the rate and extent of absorption of Naproxen
      from a novel Naproxen sodium tablet and Nalgesin naproxen sodium 275 mg.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The study has an open-label, randomized, two-way crossover design. 28 healthy participants
      will be included. Single-doses of 1 tablet of Naproxen sodium 275 mg and Nalgesin 275 mg will
      be given on separate treatment visits to healthy adult participants under fasting conditions.
      A crossover design is chosen in order to allow within-subject comparisons of treatments. To
      minimize the risk of carry-over effect, the washout period between the study drug
      administrations is set to 7 days. The study is open-label because the primary data collected
      are concentration measurements that cannot be expected to be affected by a participant's
      knowledge of the product administered.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">December 3, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">January 21, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 17, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The maximum observed plasma concentrations (Cmax) of Naproxen Sodium</measure>
    <time_frame>15, 30, 45 minutes, and at 1, 1.25, 1.5, 1.75, 2, 2.25, 2.5, 3, 4, 6, 8, 12, 16, 24, 48 and 72 hours after drug administration</time_frame>
    <description>The maximum observed plasma concentration (Cmax)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The area under the plasma concentration-vs.-time curves from start of Naproxen sodium administration until the time of the last measurable concentration (AUCt)</measure>
    <time_frame>15, 30, 45 minutes, and at 1, 1.25, 1.5, 1.75, 2, 2.25, 2.5, 3, 4, 6, 8, 12, 16, 24, 48 and 72 hours after drug administration</time_frame>
    <description>AUCt is defines as area under the plasma concentration versus time curves from start of drug administration until the last measureable concentration.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The area under the plasma concentration-vs.-time curve from the start of Naproxen sodium administration extrapolated to infinity (AUC∞)</measure>
    <time_frame>15, 30, 45 minutes, and at 1, 1.25, 1.5, 1.75, 2, 2.25, 2.5, 3, 4, 6, 8, 12, 16, 24, 48 and 72 hours after drug administration</time_frame>
    <description>AUC∞ is defined as area under the plasma concentration versus time curves from start of drug administration until the nicotine plasma concentration is negligible (infinity).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The extrapolated part of AUC∞, AUCExtrap</measure>
    <time_frame>15, 30, 45 minutes, and at 1, 1.25, 1.5, 1.75, 2, 2.25, 2.5, 3, 4, 6, 8, 12, 16, 24, 48 and 72 hours after drug administration</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The time at which maximum Naproxen sodium concentraton (Cmax) is observed (Tmax)</measure>
    <time_frame>15, 30, 45 minutes, and at 1, 1.25, 1.5, 1.75, 2, 2.25, 2.5, 3, 4, 6, 8, 12, 16, 24, 48 and 72 hours after drug administration</time_frame>
    <description>Tmax is defined as the time point at which the maximum nicotine concentration (Cmax) occurs</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The terminal elimination rate constant (lambda-z) for Naproxen sodium</measure>
    <time_frame>15, 30, 45 minutes, and at 1, 1.25, 1.5, 1.75, 2, 2.25, 2.5, 3, 4, 6, 8, 12, 16, 24, 48 and 72 hours after drug administration</time_frame>
    <description>The rate at which the drug is removed from the body system.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The terminal elimination half-life (t1/2) of Naproxen sodium</measure>
    <time_frame>15, 30, 45 minutes, and at 1, 1.25, 1.5, 1.75, 2, 2.25, 2.5, 3, 4, 6, 8, 12, 16, 24, 48 and 72 hours after drug administration</time_frame>
    <description>The time taken for the Naproxen sodium plasma concentration to fall to half its original value.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with Adverse Events</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 26 days</time_frame>
    <description>An AE is any untoward from a medical standpoint event occurred in patient or subject of clinical study after the use of a medicinal product which may or may not have a causal relationship with its use.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">28</enrollment>
  <condition>Healthy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment Sequence AB</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will receive Treatment A (test product Naproxen sodium tablet, 1 x 275 mg) at dosing period 1 followed by Treatment B (reference product Nalgesin, 1 x 275 mg) dosing period 2. There is a wash-out period of 7 days between the two dosing periods.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment Sequence BA</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will receive Treatment B (reference product Nalgesin, 1 x 275 mg) at dosing period 1 followed by Treatment A (test product Naproxen sodium tablet, 1 x 275 mg) at dosing period 2. There is a wash-out period of 7 days between the two dosing periods.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Naproxen sodium (test product)</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will be administered single doses of 275 mg Naproxen sodium (test product) tablet orally.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment Sequence AB</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment Sequence BA</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Naproxen sodium (reference product)</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will be administered single doses of 275 mg Naproxen sodium (reference product - Nalgesin) tablet orally.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment Sequence AB</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment Sequence BA</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Nalgesin</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Healthy male or female subject between the ages of 18 and 45 years, inclusive. Healthy
             is defined as the absence of any disease or abnormalities (including positive test for
             human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) 1 or 2 antibodies, hepatitis B surface antigen
             (HBsAg), or hepatitis C antibodies (anti-HCV) or syphilis (RW)) as judged by the
             investigator on the basis of a detailed medical history, physical examination, blood
             pressure, pulse rate measurements, 12-lead electrocardiogram, as well as clinical
             laboratory tests. The responsible investigator may request additional investigations
             or analyses if necessary

          -  Non- or ex-tobacco user, being defined as someone who completely stopped smoking or
             using any form of tobacco or nicotine-containing product for at least 12 months before
             1st dose of the study drug in this study.

          -  Females: Postmenopausal state (absence of menstrual discharge for at least two years
             and a follicle stimulating hormone (FSH) serum level exceeding 30 IU/L) or
             premenopausal/perimenopausal state with an effective means of contraception (oral,
             injected, implanted, or transdermal hormonal contraceptives, vaginal contraceptive
             ring, intrauterine device, or status after operative sterilization) during the study
             and 30 days thereafter, single male partner who has had a vasectomy, or abstinence
             from heterosexual intercourse, during the study and 30 days thereafter.

          -  Males: No pregnant spouse or partner at screening and willingness to protect potential
             spouse or partner from becoming pregnant during the study and 30 days thereafter.

          -  Body Mass Index (BMI) ≥ 18.5 and ≤ 30.0 kg/m2 with a total body weight &gt;50 kg.

          -  A personally signed and dated informed consent document, indicating that the subject
             has been informed of all pertinent aspects of the study.

          -  Willingness and ability to comply with scheduled visits, treatment plan, laboratory
             tests, and other study procedures specified in the protocol.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Use of medications other than contraceptives specified in Inclusion criterion 3 or
             occasional use of other medications approved by the Investigator.

          -  Use of any vitamins, dietary and herbal supplements within 7 days before each dose of
             study drugs.

          -  Use of any nonprescription or prescription medications, including naproxen
             medications, other than contraceptives, within 5 times the drug's half-life before
             each dose of study drug.

          -  Depot injection or an implant of any drug within 3 months prior to dosing.

          -  History of any allergy or hypersensitivity (e.g. skin reaction, asthma, angioedema) to
             naproxen, ibuprofen, ASA, other NSAIDs or any related products (including excipients
             of the formulations).

          -  Females: Confirmed pregnancy or a positive pregnancy test at the screening visit, or
             planning to become pregnant during the duration of the study, and/or breast-feeding

          -  Has a history of peptic ulcers, gastrointestinal bleeding of any etiology, bleeding
             disorders, gastrointestinal disease (including chronic heartburn or gastroesophageal
             reflux disease), inflammatory bowel disease (ulcerative colitis, Crohn's disease), or
             gastrointestinal surgery other than appendectomy.

          -  Has asthma, hypertension, fluid retention, or heart disease either by history or by
             the medically qualified principal investigator's medical judgment; has hemophilia and
             other disorders of blood clotting and hemostasis disorders, has cerebrovascular
             hemorrhage or other hemorrhages;

          -  Has renal or hepatic impairment; according to the medically qualified investigator
             discretion;

          -  Acute infectious disease within 4 weeks prior to screening.

          -  Treatment with an investigational drug within 3 months preceding the first dose of
             study treatment.

          -  Preplanned surgical procedures during the study period, if this may interfere with the
             conduct of the study.

          -  History of alcoholism defined as alcohol consumption in the 6 months before screening
             that exceeds weekly limits of 10 alcohol units (2 L of wine or 5 L of beer or 0.5 L of
             spirits) or substance abuse, as judged by the Investigator, within the past 6 months
             preceding this study.

          -  Consumed alcohol beverage(s) within 48 hours prior to the first scheduled dose of the
             study drug, positive respiratory alcohol test at screening, or inability to abstain
             from alcohol consumption during the entire study period.

          -  Positive urine screen for drug abuse.

          -  Use of xanthine containing products (e.g., coffee, tea, chocolate or cola drink)
             within 48 hours before each dose of study drug.

          -  Ingestion of food or beverages containing grapefruit, Chinese grapefruit (pomelo) or
             Seville oranges (including marmalade) within 10 days before the first dose of study
             drug and throughout the study.

          -  Donation or loss of blood within 3 months prior to the first dose of study drug if the
             estimated lost blood volume equaled or exceeded 450 mL.

          -  Abnormal results of laboratory and instrumental methods of examinations, including
             electrocardiogram (ECG) at screening;

          -  Heart rate &lt;60 or &gt;90 per minute at rest, or systolic blood pressure &lt;100 or &gt;130 mm
             Hg, or diastolic blood pressure &lt;70 or &gt;90 mm Hg measured at screening visit.

          -  Has any acute or chronic, medical or psychiatric condition(s) that may increase the
             risk associated with study participation or investigational product administration or
             may interfere with the interpretation of study results and, in the judgment of the
             medically qualified investigator, would make the subject inappropriate for entry into
             this study;

          -  Relationship to persons involved directly in the conduct of the study (i.e., principal
             investigator, subinvestigators,study coordinators, other study personnel, employees or
             contractors of the sponsor or Johnson &amp; Johnson subsidiaries, and the family of each).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>45 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Konstantin A. Zacharov, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>LLC &quot;Scientific and Research centre Eco-safety&quot;</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>LLC &quot;Scientific and Research centre Eco-safety&quot;</name>
      <address>
        <city>St.Petersburg</city>
        <zip>196143</zip>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Russian Federation</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://filehosting-v2.pharmacm.com/api/Attachment/Download?tenantId=80217051&amp;amp;parentIdentifier=CO-171115092223-PACT&amp;amp;attachmentIdentifier=f8a0d9d8-c13a-4ad7-9ebb-b24720e90711&amp;amp;fileName=Redacted_bluefish_synopsis.pdf&amp;amp;versionIdentifier=</url>
    <description>Synopsis to support result registration for a clinical study performed within the Russian federation.</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>January 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 4, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 4, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 5, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 21, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 21, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 23, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Bioequivalence</keyword>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Naproxen</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

