<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03699748</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>40447</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>K23MD013474-01</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03699748</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Lay Health Worker Engage, Educate, and Encourage Patients to Share</brief_title>
  <acronym>LEAPS</acronym>
  <official_title>Lay Health Worker Engage, Educate, and Encourage Patients to Share</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Stanford University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institutes of Health (NIH)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute on Minority Health and Health Disparities (NIMHD)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Stanford University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of the LEAPS program is to understand how a trained lay health worker who engages
      with newly diagnosed patients after a diagnosis of an advanced stage of cancer can help to
      engage patients in advance care planning, improve patient satisfaction with their
      decision-making, activation, quality of life, and healthcare resource utilization.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Unite Here Health proposes to implement and evaluate several critical elements to be in
      alignment with the mission of the organization to provide high value care to their members.
      The Lay Health Worker Engages, Educates, and Encourages Patients to Share intervention is an
      innovative program that will strengthen provider-patient relationship and facilitate whole
      person care about matters important to Unite Here Health members who are diagnosed with
      cancer and important to support network and family. The project is intended to help establish
      Goals of Care Plan with appropriate documentation, develop, deploy, and evaluate a model of
      care for persons with cancer that is intended to improve clinical outcomes and experience of
      care for individuals. The intervention provides patients with lay health coaches who assist
      patients and their families in discussing goals of care and engage in shared-decision making.
      The goal of the project is to demonstrate that there is improved documentation of goals of
      care, patient experiences, patient activation and quality of life outcomes, and that the
      program helps to reduce utilization of health care resources at the end of life.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 1, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 28, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Health Services Research</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Patient Quality of Life Using the Functional Assessment of Cancer Therapy - General Survey [ Time Frame: Change in Quality of Life from baseline to 6 months. ]</measure>
    <time_frame>4 months after patient enrollment</time_frame>
    <description>Each patient will receive a quality of life survey (Functional Assessment of Cancer Therapy - General Survey) at baseline and 4 months. We will measure the change in quality of life at baseline to 4 months. Scores for quality of life will be assessed using the Functional Assessment of Cancer Therapy - General Survey-General survey.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient Satisfaction With Decision-Making Using the Satisfaction With Decision Survey</measure>
    <time_frame>4 months after patient enrollment</time_frame>
    <description>Each patient will receive a validated satisfaction with decision-making survey (The Satisfaction with Decision Survey) at 4 months after study enrollment.Satisfaction with Decision was assessed with the use of the 6-question Satisfaction with Decision Scale, on which scores range from 0 to 5, with higher scores indicating better satisfaction with decision-making. Scores for each group are averaged at 4 months after study enrollment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient activation using the Patient Activation Measure survey</measure>
    <time_frame>4 months after patient enrollment</time_frame>
    <description>Each patient will receive a validated patient activation survey using the Patient Activation Measure at 4 months after study enrollment. Responses are: disagree strongly, disagree, agree, agree strongly with higher activation correlated with responses of agree and agree strongly. Scores for each group will be averaged at 4 months after study enrollment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient activation using the Patient Activation Measure survey</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months after study enrollment</time_frame>
    <description>Each patient will receive a validated patient activation survey using the Patient Activation Measure at 12 months after study enrollment. Responses are: disagree strongly, disagree, agree, agree strongly with higher activation correlated with responses of agree and agree strongly. Scores for each group will be averaged 12 months after study enrollment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Emergency Department Visit (Chart Review)</measure>
    <time_frame>4 months after patient enrollment</time_frame>
    <description>Emergency Department Use for each patient will be abstracted by electronic medical record chart review for each patient at 4 months after enrollment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Emergency Department Visit (Chart Review)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months after patient enrollment</time_frame>
    <description>Emergency Department Use for each patient will be abstracted by electronic medical record chart review for each patient at 12 months after enrollment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hospitalization Visit (Chart Review)</measure>
    <time_frame>4 months after patient enrollment</time_frame>
    <description>Hospitalization use for each patient will be abstracted by electronic medical record chart review for each patient at 4 months after enrollment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hospitalization Visits (Chart Review)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months after study enrollment</time_frame>
    <description>Hospitalization use for each patient will be abstracted by electronic medical record chart review for each patient at 12 months after enrollment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Advance Directive Documentation (Chart Review)</measure>
    <time_frame>4 months after patient enrollment</time_frame>
    <description>Advance Directive documentation for each patient will be abstracted by electronic medical record chart review for each patient at 4 months after enrollment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Advance Directive Documentation (Chart Review)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months after patient enrollment</time_frame>
    <description>Advance Directive documentation for each patient will be abstracted by electronic medical record chart review for each patient at 12 months after enrollment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Goals of Care Documentation (Chart Review)</measure>
    <time_frame>4 months after patient enrollment</time_frame>
    <description>Goals of Care documentation for each patient will be abstracted by electronic medical record chart review for each patient at 4 months after enrollment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Goals of Care Documentation (Chart Review)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months after patient enrollment</time_frame>
    <description>Goals of Care documentation for each patient will be abstracted by electronic medical record chart review for each patient at 12 months after enrollment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">120</enrollment>
  <condition>End of Life</condition>
  <condition>Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention Group Arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients randomized into the intervention will be assigned a lay health worker who will contact the patient to begin the intervention. The intervention includes: education on early advance care planning, documenting goals of care, assessing symptoms, and coordinating community services (such as home health, home visits, and home hospice).
The intervention arm will also receive usual care as provided by Unite Here Health and their local oncologists.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control Group Arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The control group arm will receive usual care as provided by Unite Here Health and their local oncologists.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Lay Health Worker Intervention</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients randomized into the intervention will be assigned a lay health worker who will contact the patient to begin the intervention. The intervention includes: education on early advance care planning, documenting goals of care, assessing symptoms, and coordinating community services (such as home health, home visits, and home hospice). The intervention is provided along with usual care as provided by Unite Here Health and local oncologists.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention Group Arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Usual Care</intervention_name>
    <description>Usual care as provided by Unite Here Health and local oncologists</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control Group Arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention Group Arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Newly diagnosed patients with a cancer diagnosis.

          2. Patients with any relapse or progressive disease (any cancer diagnosis) as identified
             by imaging or biopsy and confirmed by physician.

          3. The patients must be 18 years or older.

          4. Patients must have the capacity to verbally consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Inability to consent to the study due to lack of capacity as documented by the referring
        physician.

        Patients without a newly diagnosed malignancy or patients without relapse of disease.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Manali I Patel, MD MPH MS</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Stanford University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Manali I Patel, MD MPH MS</last_name>
    <phone>650-723-4000</phone>
    <email>manalip@stanford.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Stanford University School of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Stanford</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94305</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Manali I Patel, MD MPH MS</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Manali I Patel, MD MPH MS</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 5, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 5, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 9, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 27, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 27, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 28, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Stanford University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Manali Indravadan Patel</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>end of life</keyword>
  <keyword>patient-centered</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

