<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03699358</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>GaziUniversity15</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03699358</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Physical Impairments Related to Myeloid and Lymphoid Malignancies</brief_title>
  <official_title>Does Myeloid or Lymphoid Origin of Hematologic Neoplasm Affect Pulmonary Functions, Muscle Strength, Exercise Capacity, Fatigue and Quality of Life?</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Gazi University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Gazi University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Hematologic malignancies may arise from myeloid and lymphoid blood cells lineages affecting
      blood, bone marrow and lymph nodes. Accordingly, negative effects of malignancies on body
      systems vary. As known, muscle strength, exercise capacity, fatigue and quality of life
      deteriorate during allogeneic hematopoietic stem cell transplantation (HSCT). However,
      impacts of myeloid and lymphoid type disorders on pulmonary functions, muscle strength,
      exercise capacity, fatigue and quality of life in allogeneic-HSCT who diagnosed with
      hematologic malignancies. Therefore, current study aimed to comparatively investigate
      physical impairments between recipients with hematologic malignancies according to myeloid
      and lymphoid type disorder.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Hematologic malignancies affecting blood, bone marrow and lymph nodes comprise neoplasm of
      either myeloid or lymphoid blood stem cells origin. While a lymphoid stem cell becomes a
      white blood cell, a myeloid stem cell becomes one of the red blood cells, white blood cells
      or platelets types. Due to the this reason, defects in myeloid stem cells result in acute and
      chronic myelogenous leukemia, myelodysplastic syndromes or myeloproliferative diseases,
      whereas defects in lymphoid stem cells result in lymphomas, lymphocytic leukemias or myeloma.
      On the other hand, most of these hematologic malignancies are characterized with high rate of
      morbidity and mortality because of both the nature and various toxic treatments of neoplasm
      including chemotherapy with multiple agents, corticosteroids and hematopoietic stem cell
      transplantation (HSCT). Especially after allogeneic-HSCT, recipients experience more
      impairments in pulmonary functions, respiratory and peripheral muscle strength, exercise
      capacity, perception of fatigue and quality of life scores which make their lives difficult
      in terms of actively trying to return to the their life. However, although it has been known
      that each hematologic disease has a different negative impact on varied body systems or
      organs after HSCT, little attention has been paid to the comparatively investigation of
      impacts of myeloid and lymphoid hematological malignancies on pulmonary functions, muscle
      strength, exercise capacity, fatigue and quality of life in allogeneic-HSCT recipients.
      Hence, current study aimed to comparatively investigate physical impairments between
      recipients with hematologic malignancies according to myeloid and lymphoid type disorder.

      Recipients undergone allogeneic-HSCT (˃100 days post-HSCT status) were included. Hematologic
      malignancies were grouped as myeloid and lymphoid. Pulmonary functions (spirometry),
      peripheral (dynamometer) and respiratory muscle strength (MIP-MEP) (mouth pressure device),
      exercise capacity (Modified Incremental Shuttle Walk Test (ISWT)), and quality of life
      (European Organization for Research and Treatment of Cancer Quality of Life Questionnaire)
      were evaluated.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">August 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">April 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Retrospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximal exercise capacity evaluation</measure>
    <time_frame>15-20 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>Modified-Incremental Shuttle Walk Test (ISWT) test was used to evaluate maximal exercise capaciity.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>pulmonary function test</measure>
    <time_frame>5 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>This test was evaluated using a spirometry</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Inspiratory and expiratory muscle strength (MIP, MEP)</measure>
    <time_frame>5-10 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>Respiratory muscle strength was evaluated with a mouth pressure device</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quadriceps femoris muscle strength</measure>
    <time_frame>5 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>Peripheral muscle strength was evaluated with a hand-held dynamometer</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of life level</measure>
    <time_frame>2 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>The Turkish version of European Organization for Research and Treatment of Cancer Quality of Life Questionnaire C30 version3.0 (EORTC QLQ-C30) was carried out to the recipients for evaluation of aspects of quality of life impairment which is a valid and reliable questionnaire for patients with cancer in the whole world.Self-administered questionnaire incorporates five functional scales including social functioning subscale, three symptom scales including fatigue subscale, and a global health status as well as several single items. All item scores are transformed to percents (0-100). Higher values represent higher functional/healthy level in functional scales, a higher quality of life level in global health status and increased presence of symptoms in symptom scales.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">57</enrollment>
  <condition>Stem Cell Transplantation</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group 1: Myeloid recipients</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients diagnosed with hematologic malignancy were recipients who undergone allogeneic-HSCT. Recipients were included in the current study and grouped as myeloid and lymphoid according to origin of their diagnosis. Recipients who had myeloid type disorders were included in myeloid group as well as recipients who had lymphoid type disorders were included in lymphoid group.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group 2: Lymphoid recipients</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients diagnosed with hematologic malignancy were recipients who undergone allogeneic-HSCT. Recipients were included in the current study and grouped as myeloid and lymphoid according to origin of their diagnosis. Recipients who had myeloid type disorders were included in myeloid group as well as recipients who had lymphoid type disorders were included in lymphoid group.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        All patients in Bone Marrow Transplantation Unit of University were referred for
        participation in rehabilitation program as outpatient to Faculty of Health Science of
        University, Department of Physiotherapy and Rehabilitation, cardiopulmonary rehabilitation
        unit. Patients diagnosed with hematologic malignancy were recipients who undergone
        allogeneic-HSCT. Recipients who had myeloid type disorders were included in myeloid group
        as well as recipients who had lymphoid type disorders were included in lymphoid group. A
        physiotherapist conducted all measurements in the same day for all recipients individually.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  18-65 years of age,

          -  being an allogeneic-HSCT recipient who was at minimum 100 days status after
             transplantation

          -  receiving optimal standard medical therapy including immunosuppressive agents,
             antibiotics, supplements and other drugs.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  having cognitive disorders, orthopedic or neurological disease with a potential to
             affect assessment of exercise capacity, visual impairments and mucositis which may
             prevent measurements, comorbidities such as asthma, chronic obstructive pulmonary
             disease (COPD), acute respiratory or other infections, acute hemorrhage, low
             hemoglobin values (≤8 g/L) and low platelet count (≤10.000 mm3).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Gülşah Barğı, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Gazi Üniversitesi</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Meral Boşnak Güçlü, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Gazi Üniversitesi</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Gülsan Türköz Sucak, PhD.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Bahçeşehir University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Gazi University Faculty of Health Science Department of PhysioTherapy</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ankara</city>
        <zip>06560</zip>
        <country>Turkey</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Turkey</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Paul KL. Rehabilitation and exercise considerations in hematologic malignancies. Am J Phys Med Rehabil. 2011 May;90(5 Suppl 1):S88-94. doi: 10.1097/PHM.0b013e31820be055. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21765268</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bergenthal N, Will A, Streckmann F, Wolkewitz KD, Monsef I, Engert A, Elter T, Skoetz N. Aerobic physical exercise for adult patients with haematological malignancies. Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2014 Nov 11;(11):CD009075. doi: 10.1002/14651858.CD009075.pub2. Review. Update in: Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2019 Jan 31;1:CD009075.</citation>
    <PMID>25386666</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Steinberg A, Asher A, Bailey C, Fu JB. The role of physical rehabilitation in stem cell transplantation patients. Support Care Cancer. 2015 Aug;23(8):2447-60. doi: 10.1007/s00520-015-2744-3. Epub 2015 May 14. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25971213</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Barğı G, Boşnak Güçlü M, Türköz Sucak AG. Differences in pulmonary and extra-pulmonary characteristics in severely versus non-severely fatigued recipients of allogeneic hematopoietic stem cell transplantation: a cross-sectional, comparative study. Hematology. 2019 Dec;24(1):112-122. doi: 10.1080/10245332.2018.1526441. Epub 2018 Sep 27.</citation>
    <PMID>30261831</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 5, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 5, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 9, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 27, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 27, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 1, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Gazi University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Meral Boşnak Güçlü</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>hematopoietic stem cell transplantation</keyword>
  <keyword>respiratory function test</keyword>
  <keyword>respiratory muscles</keyword>
  <keyword>muscle strength</keyword>
  <keyword>exercise</keyword>
  <keyword>walk test</keyword>
  <keyword>quality of life</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>There is not a plan to make individual participant data but when the statistical analyses of all data are made, all results will be shared.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

