<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03693144</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HUM00083980</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>1R21HD093835-01</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03693144</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Improving Nutritional Choices in Adolescents</brief_title>
  <acronym>LIITA3H</acronym>
  <official_title>Location Initiated Individualized Texts for African American Adolescent Health</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Michigan</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Eunice Kennedy Shriver National Institute of Child Health and Human Development (NICHD)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Michigan</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The goal of this project is to test whether the mobile application helps Black adolescents
      make healthy food choices at the point of purchase.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The epidemic of excess weight in childhood is impacted by exposure to, and consumption of,
      fast food and calorie dense foods prepared outside of the home. Black youth are more likely
      than their peers to live in communities with a high density of fast food restaurants. There
      is a need for interventions to help adolescents make healthy choices in these obesogenic
      environments.

      Previous research revealed that adolescents welcomed health-related text messages (based on
      Self Determination Theory and Motivational Interviewing) if they viewed them as personally
      relevant and if they were received at times when they faced dietary choices. Based on these
      findings, the following is hypothesized: that delivering messages (tailored to users'
      preferences and values) at a time and place when they are making a dietary choice (e.g., in a
      restaurant) will positively influence their choices.

      Thus, the Location Initiated Individualized Texts for African American Adolescent Health
      (LIITA3H) mobile application was developed. This app identifies when users were in a
      restaurant, automatically sends culturally relevant messages (based on focus group input from
      the target population) tailored to user preferences and the menu options at their location
      with the aim of prompting users to make a healthy choice, and allows users to submit an
      annotated photo response about their food choice.

      For this R21 project the following will be achieved: 1) the LIITA3H app will be enhanced by
      incorporating user input regarding its design and by allowing greater automation in the
      identification of eating venues, and 2) the impact of the app on the number of visits by
      users to restaurants, and on the number of calories users consume from these venues will be
      tested. This will provide data regarding effect size and will form the foundation for a large
      randomized trial in a larger population and including a greater range of eating venues. A
      better understanding of how 'just in time&quot; personalized cues to action, made possible by new
      location-based technology, might alter behavior among a high risk population, will help
      future efforts to address obesity and other illnesses impacted by lifestyle choices.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 25, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 30, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 30, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Visits to fast food restaurants</measure>
    <time_frame>Over 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Change in number of weekly visits to fast food restaurants</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Calories purchased from fast food restaurants</measure>
    <time_frame>Over 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Change in number of calories purchased per week at fast food restaurants</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of times app identifies presence in fast food restaurant</measure>
    <time_frame>Over 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of times the app correctly identifies that a participant is in a registered fast food restaurant</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of times app delivers appropriate tailored message</measure>
    <time_frame>Over 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of times the app delivers a tailored message for a menu item at the fast food restaurant in which the participant is located</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Participants' perception of the experience of using the app</measure>
    <time_frame>At the completion of 6 months in the study</time_frame>
    <description>Participants' perception of the acceptability of the app's content and design via qualitative assessment</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">150</enrollment>
  <condition>Overweight and Obesity</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention Group 1 Full LIITA3H App</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will be given the LIITA3H app, which is a combination product consisting of 3 main features that will track their visits to fast food restaurants (using the ELI feature), send tailored text messages to prompt healthy choices when they are in a fast food restaurant (using the POP feature), and allow them to submit pictures of their food (using the SNAP feature).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control Group 2 Partial LIITA3H App</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will be given the LIITA3H app that will track their visits to fast food restaurants (using the ELI feature) and they will submit pictures of their food (using the SNAP feature). However, they will not receive tailored text messages.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control Group 3 LIITA3H Location only</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will be given the LIITA3H app that will track their visits to fast food restaurants (using the ELI feature) but they will not receive tailored messages or submit pictures of their food.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Full LIITA3H App</intervention_name>
    <description>This is the full version of the LIITA3H mobile app that will use the Enhanced Location Identification (ELI) technology to identify when a user is in an eating venue and then deliver culturally and individually tailored point of purchase prompts (POP) to encourage healthy choices and will allow participants to take pictures of the food they purchase using the Self-report of Nutrients with Annotated Photos (SNAP) function.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention Group 1 Full LIITA3H App</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Partial LIITA3H App</intervention_name>
    <description>This is a version of the LIITA3H mobile app that will track participants' location and allow them to submit photos of their food.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control Group 2 Partial LIITA3H App</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>LIITA3H Location only</intervention_name>
    <description>This is a version of the LIITA3H mobile app that will only track participants' location.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control Group 3 LIITA3H Location only</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Self identification as African American

          -  BMI at or above 85th percentile

          -  Eat at fast food restaurants at least 3 times per week at baseline

        Exclusion Criteria:

        -
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>13 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>17 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Susan J Woolford, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Michigan</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Susan J Woolford, MD</last_name>
    <phone>7349041455</phone>
    <email>swoolfor@med.umich.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Theresa Kowalski-Dobson, MPH</last_name>
    <phone>(734) 232-2455</phone>
    <email>|tkowals@med.umich.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Michigan</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ann Arbor</city>
        <state>Michigan</state>
        <zip>48109</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Theresa Kowalski Dobson, MPH</last_name>
      <phone>734-232-2455</phone>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Susan J Woolford, MD, MPH</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 28, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 28, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 2, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 2, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 2, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">December 3, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Michigan</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Susan J Woolford, MD, MPH</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Overweight</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

