<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03699397</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NL65939.018.18</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03699397</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>EEG Controlled Triage in the Ambulance for Acute Ischemic Stroke</brief_title>
  <acronym>ELECTRA-STROKE</acronym>
  <official_title>EEG Controlled Triage in the Ambulance for Acute Ischemic Stroke</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Academisch Medisch Centrum - Universiteit van Amsterdam (AMC-UvA)</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Academisch Medisch Centrum - Universiteit van Amsterdam (AMC-UvA)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      RATIONALE Endovascular thrombectomy (EVT) is standard treatment for acute ischemic stroke
      (AIS) if there is a large vessel occlusion in the anterior circulation (LVO-a). Because of
      its complexity, EVT is performed in selected hospitals only. Currently, approximately half of
      EVT eligible patients are initially admitted to hospitals that do not provide this therapy.
      This delays initiation of treatment by approximately an hour, which decreases the chance of a
      good clinical outcome. Direct presentation of all patients with a suspected AIS in EVT
      capable hospitals is not feasible, since only approximately 7% of these patients are eligible
      for EVT. Therefore, an advanced triage method that reliably identifies patients with an LVO-a
      in the ambulance is necessary. Electroencephalography (EEG) may be suitable for this purpose,
      as preliminary studies suggest that slow EEG activity in the delta frequency range correlates
      with lesion location on cerebral imaging. Use of dry electrode EEG caps will enable
      relatively unexperienced paramedics to perform a reliable measurement without the EEG
      preparation time associated with 'wet' EEGs. Combined with algorithms for automated signal
      analysis, the investigators expect the time of EEG recording and analysis to eventually be
      below five minutes, which would make stroke triage in the ambulance by EEG logistically
      feasible.

      HYPOTHESIS The investigators hypothesize that dry electrode cap EEG can be used in patients
      with a suspected AIS to identify patients with an LVO-a in the ambulance.

      OBJECTIVE To develop and validate an algorithm based on dry electrode cap EEG data that
      accurately determines the likelihood of an LVO-a in patients with a suspected AIS in the
      ambulance.

      STUDY DESIGN

      This diagnostic study consists of four phases:

      Phase 1: Optimization of measurement time and software settings of the dry electrode cap EEG
      in a non-emergency setting in patients in whom a regular EEG is/will be performed for
      standard medical care.

      Phase 2: Optimization of measurement time and software settings of the dry electrode cap EEG
      in patients close to our target population in a non-emergency setting.

      Phase 3: Validation of several existing algorithms and development of one or more new
      algorithms; selection of algorithm with best diagnostic accuracy for validation in phase 4.

      Phase 4: Validation of the algorithm selected in phase 3 in patients with a suspected AIS in
      the ambulance, as well as assessment of technical and logistical feasibility of performing
      EEG with dry electrode caps in patients with a suspected AIS in the ambulance. This phase is
      the only multicenter phase of this study.

      STUDY POPULATION Phase 1: Patients in the outpatient clinic of the Clinical Neurophysiology
      department of the AMC, in whom a regular EEG has been/will be performed for standard medical
      care.

      Phase 2: Patients with an AIS admitted to the Neurology ward of the coordinating hospital
      with an LVO-a (after reperfusion therapy).

      Phase 3: Patients with a suspected AIS in the emergency room (ER) of the coordinating
      hospital (before reperfusion therapy).

      Phase 4: Patients with a suspected AIS in the ambulance.

      INTERVENTION Performing a dry electrode cap EEG (in phase 1 in the outpatient clinic, in
      phase 2 during hospital admission, in phase 3 in the ER and in phase 4 in the ambulance).

      MAIN END POINTS

        -  Primary end point: specificity of dry electrode cap EEG for diagnosis of LVO-a in
           suspected AIS patients in the ambulance;

        -  Secondary end points:

             -  Developing an algorithm with optimal diagnostic accuracy for LVO-a detection with
                ambulant EEG;

             -  Sensitivity, positive predictive value (PPV) and negative predictive value (NPV) of
                dry electrode cap EEG for diagnosis of LVO-a in suspected AIS patients in the
                ambulance;

             -  Technical and logistical feasibility of performing dry electrode cap EEGs on
                patients with a suspected AIS in the ambulance;

             -  Diagnostic accuracy of dry electrode cap EEG for diagnosis of LVO-a in the
                ambulance in an 'enriched' population (a population with a higher incidence of
                LVO-a compared to the primary target population because it includes, alongside
                patients with a suspected AIS, patients with a known LVO-a).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 4, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Specificity of dry electrode cap EEG for diagnosis of LVO-a</measure>
    <time_frame>The presence or absence of an LVO-a, which will ultimately determine the specificity, will be assessed at arrival in the emergency department (within 24 hours after inclusion in the study)</time_frame>
    <description>Specificity of dry electrode cap electroencephalography (EEG) for diagnosis of large vessel occlusion of the anterior circulation (LVO-a) in patients with a suspected acute ischemic stroke in the ambulance</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Algorithm with optimal diagnostic accuracy for LVO-a detection with dry electrode EEG</measure>
    <time_frame>EEG-data for development of the algorithm will be recorded at the first (and only) visit for each patient, through completion of the first three phases of the study (estimated approximately six months in total).</time_frame>
    <description>Developing an algorithm with optimal diagnostic accuracy for large vessel occlusion of the anterior circulation (LVO-a) with dry electrode EEG.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Sensitivity of dry electrode EEG for diagnosis of LVO-a</measure>
    <time_frame>The presence or absence of an LVO-a, which will ultimately determine the sensitivity, will be assessed at arrival in the emergency department (within 24 hours after inclusion in the study)</time_frame>
    <description>Sensitivity of dry electrode electroencephalography (EEG) for diagnosis of large vessel occlusion of the anterior circulation (LVO-a) in patients with a suspected acute ischemic stroke in the ambulance</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Positive predictive value of dry electrode EEG for diagnosis of LVO-a</measure>
    <time_frame>The presence or absence of an LVO-a, which will ultimately determine the positive predictive value, will be assessed at arrival in the emergency department (within 24 hours after inclusion in the study)</time_frame>
    <description>Positive predictive value of dry electrode electroencephalography (EEG) for diagnosis of large vessel occlusion of the anterior circulation (LVO-a) in patients with a suspected acute ischemic stroke in the ambulance</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Negative predictive value of dry electrode EEG for diagnosis of LVO-a</measure>
    <time_frame>The presence or absence of an LVO-a, which will ultimately determine the negative predictive value, will be assessed at arrival in the emergency department (within 24 hours after inclusion in the study)</time_frame>
    <description>Negative predictive value of dry electrode electroencephalography (EEG) for diagnosis of large vessel occlusion of the anterior circulation (LVO-a) in patients with a suspected acute ischemic stroke in the ambulance</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Technical feasibility of performing dry electrode EEGs in the ambulance</measure>
    <time_frame>Feedback on technical issues by the paramedic that performs the EEG and by the EEG-expert, will be collected directly at arrival in the emergency department (within 24 hours after the patient is included in the study).</time_frame>
    <description>Technical feasibility of performing dry electrode cap EEGs on patients with a suspected acute ischemic stroke in the ambulance</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Logistical feasibility of performing dry electrode EEGs in the ambulance</measure>
    <time_frame>Feedback on logistical issues by the paramedic that performs the EEG, will be collected directly at arrival in the emergency department (within 24 hours after the patient is included in the study).</time_frame>
    <description>Logistical feasibility of performing dry electrode cap EEGs on patients with a suspected acute ischemic stroke in the ambulance</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Diagnostic accuracy of dry electrode EEG for diagnosis of LVO-a in an 'enriched' population</measure>
    <time_frame>The presence or absence of an LVO-a, which will ultimately determine the diagnostic accuracy, will be assessed at arrival in the emergency department (within 24 hours after inclusion in the study).</time_frame>
    <description>Diagnostic accuracy of dry electrode cap EEG for diagnosis of large vessel occlusion in the anterior circulation (LVO-a) in the ambulance in an 'enriched' population (a population with a higher incidence of LVO-a compared to the primary target population because it includes, alongside patients with a suspected acute ischemic stroke, patients with a known LVO-a that are being transferred to the coordinating hospital to undergo endovascular thrombectomy).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">362</enrollment>
  <condition>Stroke, Ischemic</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Dry electrode cap EEG</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>In this diagnostic accuracy study, all patients that are included in the study will undergo a dry electrode electroencephalography (EEG).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Dry electrode EEG</intervention_name>
    <description>A single dry electrode electroencephalography (EEG) will be performed in each patient that is included in this study. To do this, the investigators will use the WaveguardTM dry electrode EEG cap and compatible eegoTM amplifier, developed by ANT Neuro B.V. Netherlands and both CE marked as medical devices in the European Union (see appendices 1 and 2). Both products will be used within the intended use as described in the user manuals. The dry electrode cap is put on the patients head and records the EEG signal for several minutes; the amplifier is used to amplify the EEG signal and reduce artefacts.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Dry electrode cap EEG</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        STUDY PHASE 1

        Inclusion criteria:

          -  Age of 18 years or older;

          -  Patient is in the outpatient clinic of the Clinical Neurophysiology department of the
             AMC, because a regular EEG has been/will be performed on him/her for standard medical
             care;

          -  Written informed consent by patient.

        Exclusion criteria:

        - Injury or active infection of electrode cap placement area.

        STUDY PHASE 2

        Inclusion criteria:

          -  A diagnosis of acute ischemic stroke caused by a large vessel occlusion in the
             anterior circulation (intracranial carotid artery or proximal (M1/M2) middle cerebral
             artery confirmed by neuro-imaging (CTA or MRA);

          -  Stroke onset &lt;72 hours before expected time of performing EEG;

          -  Age of 18 years or older;

          -  Written informed consent by patient or legal representative.

        Exclusion criteria:

        - Injury or active infection of electrode cap placement area.

        STUDY PHASE 3

        Inclusion criteria:

          -  Suspected acute ischemic stroke, as judged by the paramedic presenting the patient to
             the ER or known AIS with an LVO-a;

          -  Onset of symptoms or, if onset was not witnessed, last seen well &lt;24 hours ago;

          -  Age of 18 years or older;

          -  Written informed consent by patient or legal representative (deferred).

        Exclusion criteria:

        - Injury or active infection of electrode cap placement area.

        STUDY PHASE 4

        Inclusion criteria:

          -  Suspected acute ischemic stroke as judged by the attending paramedic or known AIS with
             an LVO-a;

          -  Onset of symptoms or, if onset not witnessed, last seen well &lt;24 hours ago;

          -  Age of 18 years or older;

          -  Written informed consent by patient or legal representative (deferred).

        Exclusion criteria:

        - Injury or active infection of electrode cap placement area.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Laura CC van Meenen, MD</last_name>
    <phone>0031 20 566 3447</phone>
    <email>l.c.vanmeenen@amc.uva.nl</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Jonathan Coutinho, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>0031 20 566 2004</phone>
    <email>j.coutinho@amc.uva.nl</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Amsterdam University Medical Centers, location AMC</name>
      <address>
        <city>Amsterdam</city>
        <state>Noord-Holland</state>
        <zip>1105AZ</zip>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Laura van Meenen, MD</last_name>
      <phone>0031205663447</phone>
      <email>l.c.vanmeenen@amc.nl</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Netherlands</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 3, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 5, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 9, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 14, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 14, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 15, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Academisch Medisch Centrum - Universiteit van Amsterdam (AMC-UvA)</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Jonathan Coutinho</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Stroke</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ischemia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <provided_document_section>
    <provided_document>
      <document_type>Study Protocol and Statistical Analysis Plan</document_type>
      <document_has_protocol>Yes</document_has_protocol>
      <document_has_icf>No</document_has_icf>
      <document_has_sap>Yes</document_has_sap>
      <document_date>August 28, 2018</document_date>
      <document_url>https://ClinicalTrials.gov/ProvidedDocs/97/NCT03699397/Prot_SAP_000.pdf</document_url>
    </provided_document>
    <provided_document>
      <document_type>Informed Consent Form</document_type>
      <document_has_protocol>No</document_has_protocol>
      <document_has_icf>Yes</document_has_icf>
      <document_has_sap>No</document_has_sap>
      <document_date>September 17, 2018</document_date>
      <document_url>https://ClinicalTrials.gov/ProvidedDocs/97/NCT03699397/ICF_001.pdf</document_url>
    </provided_document>
  </provided_document_section>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

