<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03695393</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>H-38069</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>R00DA041245</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03695393</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Stigma, Risk Behaviors and Health Care Among HIV-infected Russian People Who Inject Drugs</brief_title>
  <acronym>SCRIPT</acronym>
  <official_title>Stigma, Risk Behaviors and Health Care Among HIV-infected Russian People Who Inject Drugs</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Boston Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute on Drug Abuse (NIDA)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Boston Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study is a randomized controlled trial (RCT) among 100 HIV-positive people with
      injection drug use, which aims to test the feasibility of the SCRIPT intervention and
      evaluate its effectiveness on the reduction of internalized stigma, as well as entry into
      substance use treatment or initiation of antiretroviral therapy.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      People who inject drugs often experience multiple layers of stigma when they are living with
      HIV. Stigma is defined as the social exclusion and dehumanization of individuals in an
      undesirable social category. Interventions to help affected people who inject drugs living
      with HIV cope with the dual stigma related to HIV and substance use have not been studied
      specifically in this population. Among people living with HIV, stigma adversely impacts all
      aspects of the care cascade: timely HIV testing, diagnosis, treatment, adherence and
      retention in care. Among people who inject drugs, drug use may add to adverse social factors
      and create particular stigma vulnerability. Russia is a country where people who inject drugs
      and other HIV key populations are highly stigmatized and face discrimination. Further
      qualitative findings suggest that in the absence of public anti-stigma campaigns in Russia,
      stigma reduction interventions should address internalized stigma and their determinants to
      help affected people cope with the dual stigma. Stigma interventions should be adapted to
      address not only affected people's shame and guilt, but also their felt hopelessness. These
      emotions and related feelings such as avoidance and fear of being rejected may negatively
      affect people's agency and mental health. We are proposing Acceptance and Commitment Therapy
      (ACT) as a potential behavioral intervention to target the emotions underlying internalized
      stigma and thus empower affected people. ACT has been shown to increase engagement in
      addiction care. Its use and efficacy to reduce stigma has not yet been explored among
      HIV-positive people who inject drugs. The objective of this study, &quot;Stigma, Risk Behaviors
      and Health Care among HIV-positive Russian People Who Inject Drugs (SCRIPT),&quot;is to implement
      and evaluate, the feasibility of ACT as an intervention to reduce dual HIV and substance use
      stigma via a two-armed randomized controlled trial among 100 HIV-positive people who inject
      drugs. The central hypothesis is that SCRIPT is feasible and can be delivered to decrease HIV
      and substance use stigma scores.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Suspended</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Currently suspended due to COVID-19 policies.
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 10, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Satisfaction with the intervention</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month</time_frame>
    <description>Assessed via 17-item Likert scale (1-5), developed by the study team. Higher scores indicate greater satisfaction with the intervention.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in HIV Stigma Score from baseline to 1 month</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 1 month</time_frame>
    <description>Measured via an HIV Stigma Scale, a 10-item questionnaire developed by Berger et al., with an 11th question added about drug partners. Higher scores correspond to higher HIV stigma.
Measured via a modified HIV internalized stigma scale, a 7-item questionnaire developed by Leickness et al. Higher scores correspond to higher HIV stigma.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Substance Use Stigma measured via Modified Substance Abuse Self-Stigma Scale from baseline to 1 month</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 1 Month</time_frame>
    <description>Measured via Modified Substance Abuse Self-Stigma Scale, a 16-item questionnaire developed by Luoma et al. Higher scores correspond to higher substance use stigma.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Participation in intervention</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month</time_frame>
    <description>Defined as participation in three ACT intervention sessions</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Fidelity to intervention measured using the Adherence Raters' Manual for Stigma Treatment Study</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month</time_frame>
    <description>Defined using the Adherence Raters' Manual for Stigma Treatment Study (Kohlenberg et al, 2004) to rate the recorded intervention videos/tapes, with a focus on frequency of occurrence and depth of coverage for specific ACT processes and contraindicated processes, as well as overall adherence and competence.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Initiation of HIV care</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Defined as self-report of ART initiation, measured via modified AACTG ART questions. Participants will be asked if they have taken any antiretroviral medications and the date of when they started ART. Participants will also be asked questions about health care utilization to measure recent HIV care visits.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Injection Drug Use from baseline to 1 month</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 1 month</time_frame>
    <description>Defined as self-report of any injection drug use in the previous 30 days, measured via a modified Risk Behavior Survey.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Mental Health (depression) measured using the Patient Health Questionnaire-9 from baseline to 1 month</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 1 month</time_frame>
    <description>Measured via the Patient Health Questionnaire-9, a 9-item questionnaire with higher scores corresponding to greater depression severity.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Injection Drug Use from baseline to 6 months</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Defined as self-report of any injection drug use in the previous 30 days, measured via a modified Risk Behavior Survey.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Injection Drug Use from 1 month to 6 months</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month, 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Defined as self-report of any injection drug use in the previous 30 days, measured via a modified Risk Behavior Survey</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Mental Health (depression) measured using the Patient Health Questionnaire-9 from baseline to 6 months</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Measured via the Patient Health Questionnaire-9, a 9-item questionnaire with higher scores corresponding to greater depression severity.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Mental Health (depression) measured using the Patient Health Questionnaire-9 from 1 month to 6 months</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month, 6 month</time_frame>
    <description>Measured via the Patient Health Questionnaire-9, a 9-item questionnaire with higher scores corresponding to greater depression severity.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Mental Health (anxiety) measured using the Generalized Anxiety Disorder-7 scale from baseline to 1 month</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 1 month</time_frame>
    <description>Measured via the Generalized Anxiety Disorder-7 scale, a 7-item questionnaire with higher scores corresponding to greater anxiety severity.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change Mental Health (anxiety) measured using the Generalized Anxiety Disorder-7 scale from 1 month to 6 months</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month, 6 month</time_frame>
    <description>Measured via the Generalized Anxiety Disorder-7 scale, a 7-item questionnaire with higher scores corresponding to greater anxiety severity.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change Mental Health (anxiety) measured using the Generalized Anxiety Disorder-7 scale from baseline to 6 months</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Measured via the Generalized Anxiety Disorder-7 scale, a 7-item questionnaire with higher scores corresponding to greater anxiety severity.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in intersectional stigma measured via Modified Substance Abuse Self-Stigma Scale and HIV stigma measure from baseline to 1 month</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 1 month</time_frame>
    <description>Measured via Modified Substance Abuse Self-Stigma Scale, a 16-item questionnaire developed by Luoma et al. Higher scores correspond to higher substance use stigma.
Measured via an HIV Stigma Scale, a 10-item questionnaire developed by Berger et al., with an 11th question added about drug partners. Higher scores correspond to higher HIV stigma.
Measured via a modified HIV internalized stigma scale, a 7-item questionnaire developed by Leickness et al. Higher scores correspond to higher HIV stigma</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Psychological Flexibility measured via Acceptance and Action Questionnaire - Substance Abuse from baseline to 1 month</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 1 month</time_frame>
    <description>Measured via Acceptance and Action Questionnaire - Substance Abuse, an 18-item questionnaire developed by Luoma et al. Higher scores correspond to higher psychological flexibility</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>HIV Infections</condition>
  <condition>Stigmatization</condition>
  <condition>Substance Use</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention- ACT Therapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants randomized to this group will receive three ACT sessions over 1 month</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Standard of Care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants in the control group will receive standard care as normally provided to patients by civil society organizations.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ACT Therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>The ACT intervention will consist of three 2-hour group sessions of culturally adapted ACT (intervention) to reduce stigma and related manifestations.Participants are recruited from a civil society organization and all other study procedures take place at a rehabilitation center. The ACT sessions will be scheduled to take place at the rehabilitation center following randomization.The First St. Petersburg Pavlov State Medical University is an alternative location where sessions can be conducted. Sessions will be planned to occur in weekly succession, with a goal of 3 sessions within the first month of study participation.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention- ACT Therapy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  18 years or older

          -  HIV-positive

          -  Current injection drug use (past 30 days)

          -  Not currently on ART

          -  Provision of contact information for two contacts to assist with follow-up

          -  Address within 100 kilometers of St. Petersburg

          -  Possession of a telephone (home or cell)

          -  Able and willing to comply with all study protocols and procedures over 6 months

          -  Available at the specific days of the week and times that the group sessions will be
             occurring for the subsequent 3-4 weeks (to ensure that participants randomized into
             the intervention arm will be able to receive the intervention)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Not fluent in Russian

          -  Cognitive impairment resulting in ability to provide informed consent based on
             research assessor (RA) assessment

          -  Acute severe psychiatric illness (i.e., answered yes to any of the following: past
             three month active hallucinations; mental health symptoms prompting a visit to the ED
             or hospital; mental health medication changes due to worsening symptoms; presence of
             suicidal plans) and research assessor clinical observation (i.e. clinical observation
             or prior knowledge of severe personality disorder; past three months active mania;
             past three months active psychosis)

          -  Enrolled in another research study

          -  Participated in the pilot portion of the study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Karsten Lunze, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Boston Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>First St. Petersburg Pavlov State Medical University</name>
      <address>
        <city>St. Petersburg</city>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Russian Federation</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 1, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 2, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 4, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 13, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 13, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 14, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Injection drug use</keyword>
  <keyword>Stigma</keyword>
  <keyword>HIV</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>HIV Infections</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

