<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03696004</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>SAMuhammad</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03696004</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Outcome of Neo-adjuvant Chemotherapy Followed by Breast Conservative Surgery in Breast Cancer in Upper Egypt</brief_title>
  <official_title>Outcome of Neo-adjuvant Chemotherapy Followed by Breast Conservative Surgery in Breast Cancer in Upper Egypt</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Assiut University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Assiut University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Systemic chemotherapy along with radiotherapy has been successfully used to post-operatively
      manage patients following tumour resection in breast cancer.

      This was further supported with clinical trials conducted in the 1970s and 1980s which shows
      significant improvement in progression-free of tumours and overall survival rates in patients
      who undergo chemotherapy for operable breast cancer.(1)-(2) Neoadjuvant chemotherapy on the
      other hand, involves the administration of the chemotherapeutic agents some weeks before
      appropriate breast surgery. This induces reduction in the tumour size and allows for breast
      conservative surgery instead of mastectomy in some cases.

      Techniques for tumour localization in neoadjuvant chemotherapy using metallic markers
      allowing lower excision of breast tissue without compromising margins and breast conservation
      being feasible in many patients have evolved over time.(3)-(7)-(9) However, there are recent
      concerns questioning the increase use of neoadjuvant chemotherapy in breast cancer it as it
      may not be beneficial to patients in the long run.(10)
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This will consist of six cycles of FEC-100 regimen followed by surgery. The decision on the
      type of surgery (breast conservative surgery or mastectomy) will be taken on the final
      assessment of the disease after the six cycle.

      Neoadjuvant chemotherapy regimen will consist of six cycles of fluorouracil 500mg/m2 ,
      epirubicin 75mg/m2 and cyclophosphamide 500mg/m2 administered intravenously at three week
      interval.

      Surgery was planned to be performed within 4-6 weeks after the six course of chemotherapy.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">December 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2/Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Tumour size measurement</measure>
    <time_frame>18 WEEKS</time_frame>
    <description>Measurement of tumuor size before and after six courses of FEC-100</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">45</enrollment>
  <condition>Breast Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Retros FEC-100 +BRS</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Contains record of already treated patients with six cycles of FEC-100 Fluorouracil ,Epirubicin and Cyclophosphamide and later had Breast conservative Surgery(BRS)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>PROS 30 FEC-100 +BRS</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>These are new patients who will be treated with six cycles of FEC-100 (Flourouracil,Epirubicin and Cyclophosphamide) and will undergo Breast Conservative Surgery (BRS)after 6 weeks</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>FEC-100</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients will recieve six cycles of FEC-100 and Breast conservative surgery after 4-6 weeks</description>
    <arm_group_label>PROS 30 FEC-100 +BRS</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Retros FEC-100 +BRS</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Breast Conservative Surgery</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:1- female patients diagnosed with breast cancer and are attending
        oncology or surgical unit of Assiut university hospital .

        2- breast cancer will be diagnosed by core-needle biopsy. 3- all patients must have
        complete history and physical examination (including careful assessment of breast and
        axillary lymph nodes).

        4- All patients must have routine laboratory tests (CBC, liver and renal function tests,
        and alkaline phosphatase) and radiological tests (chest x-ray, pelvic-abdominal ultrasound,
        bilateral mammography with confirmatory ultrasound and complete echocardiography to assess
        the cardiac function).

        5- written consent from patients.

        -

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  1- Elderly patients more than 70years old. 2- Previous treatment for breast cancer. 3-
             Presence of co-existing malignancies. 4- Pregnancy or lactation at time of diagnosis.
             5- Severe renal, hepatic or haematological abnormalities. 6- Bilateral breast cancer.
             7- advanced breast cancer
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <gender_based>Yes</gender_based>
    <gender_description>Female patients diagnosed with breast cancer</gender_description>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>69 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Hisham A Riad, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Assiut University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Samir S Mohamed, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Assiut University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Sammani A Muhammad, MBBCh</last_name>
    <phone>+201111971589</phone>
    <email>sammaniali66@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Mohamed K Ewies, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+201001808518</phone>
    <email>mohamed5korany@aun.edu.eg</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Assiut University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Assiut</city>
        <zip>71515</zip>
        <country>Egypt</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Egypt</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Espinosa-Bravo M, Sao Avilés A, Esgueva A, Córdoba O, Rodriguez J, Cortadellas T, Mendoza C, Salvador R, Xercavins J, Rubio IT. Breast conservative surgery after neoadjuvant chemotherapy in breast cancer patients: comparison of two tumor localization methods. Eur J Surg Oncol. 2011 Dec;37(12):1038-43. doi: 10.1016/j.ejso.2011.08.136. Epub 2011 Sep 21.</citation>
    <PMID>21940138</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bobin JY, Al-Khaledi K, Ahmad J. Breast conservative surgery for operable invasive ductal carcinoma after neoadjuvant chemotherapy or hormonal therapy- a challenge for breast surgeon: a review based on literature and experience. Gulf J Oncolog. 2011 Jan;(9):45-51. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21177208</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schwartz GF, Meltzer AJ, Lucarelli EA, Cantor JP, Curcillo PG 2nd. Breast conservation after neoadjuvant chemotherapy for stage II carcinoma of the breast. J Am Coll Surg. 2005 Sep;201(3):327-34.</citation>
    <PMID>16125064</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Van Praagh I, Cure H, Leduc B, Charrier S, Le Bouedec G, Achard JL, Ferriere JP, Feillel V, De Latour M, Dauplat J, Chollet P. Efficacy of a primary chemotherapy regimen combining vinorelbine, epirubicin, and methotrexate (VEM) as neoadjuvant treatment in 89 patients with operable breast cancer. Oncologist. 2002;7(5):418-23.</citation>
    <PMID>12401904</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kuerer HM, Singletary SE, Buzdar AU, Ames FC, Valero V, Buchholz TA, Ross MI, Pusztai L, Hortobagyi GN, Hunt KK. Surgical conservation planning after neoadjuvant chemotherapy for stage II and operable stage III breast carcinoma. Am J Surg. 2001 Dec;182(6):601-8.</citation>
    <PMID>11839324</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Vaidya JS, Massarut S, Vaidya HJ, Alexander EC, Richards T, Caris JA, Sirohi B, Tobias JS. Rethinking neoadjuvant chemotherapy for breast cancer. BMJ. 2018 Jan 11;360:j5913. doi: 10.1136/bmj.j5913.</citation>
    <PMID>29326104</PMID>
  </reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Abdel-Bary N, El-Kased A, Aiad H. Does neoadjuvant chemotherapy increase breast conservation in operable breast cancer: an Egyptian experience. Ecancermedicalscience. 2009;3:104. doi: 10.3332/ecancer.2008.104. Epub 2009 Apr 9.</citation>
    <PMID>22275993</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Inaji H, Komoike Y, Motomura K, Kasugai T, Sawai Y, Koizumi M, Nose T, Koyama H. Breast-conserving treatment after neoadjuvant chemotherapy in large breast cancer. Breast Cancer. 2002;9(1):20-5. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>12196717</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>May 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 3, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 3, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 4, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 3, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 3, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 4, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Assiut University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Sammani Ali Muhammad</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>General Surgery Resident</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

