<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03693664</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>GO 18206/24</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03693664</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>6-Minute Pegboard and Ring Test Unsupported Arm Function Exercise Test in Asthma Patients</brief_title>
  <official_title>Validity and Reliability of the 6-Minute Pegboard and Ring Test Unsupported Arm Function Exercise Test in Controlled and Partially Controlled Asthma Patients</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Hacettepe University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Hacettepe University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Exercise intolerance is one of the most problems in chronic obstructive pulmonary disease
      (COPD) and occurs not only in performing lower body tasks but also in performing arm
      activities. During arm exercise, auxiliary respiratory muscles are used for arm duty and
      cannot contribute to breathing. This increases the respiratory load of the diaphragm, which
      is mechanically disadvantageous, and results in thoracoabdominal synchronization disorder and
      severe dyspnea. Although the relationship between activity limitation and quality of life is
      clear in patients with exertional activity, the literature on physical activity is
      insufficient. Exercise and physical activity can also and exercise-related respiratory
      symptoms are known to have adverse effects on daily living activities (ADLs). There is no
      gold standard for objective assessment of activity limitation and exertional dyspnea in
      patients with asthma. Therefore, the results obtained by evaluating the validity and
      reliability of the 6PRT test in asthmatic patients in this study will increase the use of
      this test to test both arm endurance and arm exercise capacity in adult asthmatic patients,
      to estimate the effect on ADLs and to demonstrate the development obtained with pulmonary
      rehabilitation. .
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Objective: The aim of the study was to evaluate the validity and reliability of the
      six-minute pegboard and ring test in patients with controlled and partially controlled
      asthma.

        -  Demographic information: Name, age, diagnosis, occupation, body weight, height, The
           symptoms of the dominant and affected side, CV, family history, obstructive pulmonary
           diseases (dyspnoea, cough, incontinence frequency), clinical findings and respiratory
           function test parameters will be recorded.

        -  Assessment of Respiratory Muscle Strength: With intraoral pressure measurement
           instrument will be measured.

        -  Evaluation of Hand Grip Force: It will be measured by hand dynamometer.

        -  Unarmed Arm Exercise Capacity and Arm Function / Endurance Evaluation: '6 minute
           Pegboard and Ring Test-6PRT'. During the test, the patient is asked to sit in front of a
           perforated panel and to carry as many rings as possible for six minutes to the two upper
           holes using two hands at the same time. Participants are attached to the test by
           installing a few rings before the test. Standardized encouragement is given every minute
           during the test. The number of rings carried for 6 minutes constitutes the final score.
           Before and after the test, pulse oximetry and heart rate and oxygen saturation, modified
           Borg scale, dyspnea, general fatigue and arm fatigue are questioned. For the validity of
           the test, the test will be repeated in the same patient under the same conditions every
           one week.

           -Evaluation of Maximal Arm Exercise Capacity: With arm ergometer limited exercise test
           with maximal symptoms will be evaluated and used as a criterion for the reliability of
           6PRT test.

        -  Daily life activities of dyspnea and breathlessness Evaluation of its Effect: The
           Modified Medical Research Council Scale will be evaluated with an objective measurement
           of 3 minutes breathing exercise test and London Chest Daily Living Activities Scale.

        -  Evaluation of Postural Awareness: The validity of the Turkish version developed by
           Shields, Mallory &amp; Simon in 1989 will be evaluated by the Body Awareness Survey (VFA).

        -  Evaluation of Daily Living Activities: London Chest GYA Scale (25) and Milliken GYA
           Scale will be evaluated.

        -  Assessment of Quality of Life: Disease-specific Asthma Quality of Life Scale and Health
           Assessment Questionnaire.

        -  Asthma Control Assessment: Asthma Control Test will be evaluated.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 3, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">February 3, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">February 3, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Other</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>6 minute Pegboard and Ring Test-6PRT</measure>
    <time_frame>one year</time_frame>
    <description>Total number of rings installed within six minutes</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">34</enrollment>
  <condition>Asthma</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Validity and reliability
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  To have a controlled or partially controlled asthma diagnosis, Have not experienced
             acute exacerbation in the last 3 months, Being between 18-80 years of age, Volunteer
             for research, To be able to walk and cooperate.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  To have a neurological disease or another clinical diagnosis that may affect cognitive
             status,

          -  To have musculoskeletal and neurological disease, symptomatic heart disease, previous
             lung surgery and malignant disease that may affect exercise performance.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ebru Calik Kutukcu, Phd</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Hacettepe University Physiotherapy and Rehabilitation</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hacettepe University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ankara</city>
        <state>State</state>
        <zip>06100</zip>
        <country>Turkey</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Turkey</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 1, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 2, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 3, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 2, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 2, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 5, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Hacettepe University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Ebru Calik Kutukcu</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>principal investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Asthma</keyword>
  <keyword>Daily Living Activities</keyword>
  <keyword>6 Minute Pegboard and Ring Test</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Asthma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

