<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03695939</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2018P001839</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03695939</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluation of Safety of Xeno-Skin™ for Treatment of Severe and Extensive, Partial and Full Thickness Burns</brief_title>
  <official_title>An Open-label Phase 1 Study to Evaluate the Safety and Tolerability of Xeno-Skin™ for Temporary Coverage of Severe and Extensive, Deep Partial and Full Thickness Burn Wounds</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>XenoTherapeutics, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Massachusetts General Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>XenoTherapeutics, Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To assess the Safety and Tolerability of Xeno-Skin™ for the treatment of severe and
      extensive, deep partial and full thickness burn wounds as a first-line treatment, and
      temporary coverage prior to definitive wound closure.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This Phase 1 Study is a 2 cohort, open-label, non-randomized trial, to assess the safety and
      tolerability of Xeno-Skin™ for the treatment of severe and extensive, deep partial and full
      thickness burn wounds as a first-line treatment, and temporary coverage prior to definitive
      wound closure.

      Subjects who meet eligibility criteria and provide informed consent will receive placement of
      Xeno-Skin™ on a single burn wound site.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 15, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 15, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 15, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety and Tolerability: Number of Participants with Adverse Events as a Measure of Safety and Tolerability</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Number of Participants with Adverse Events as a Measure of Safety and Tolerability</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinically Relevant Response</measure>
    <time_frame>daily through 4 weeks, 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>To assess the quality and duration of temporary barrier function afforded by Xeno-Skin™(as determined by the Clinical Wound Assessment Scale, adapted from Branski et al 2011). Six characteristics are assessed: Graft dislocation; Graft adherence, Granulation tissue; Hyper-granulation; Hematoma; and Fibrin deposit. Each characteristic is assessed on an independent 0-5 scale and subscale scores are reported. It is expected that some characteristics may not be assessible at all stages of the grafting process and NA may be recorded.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Time of Graft Adherence.</measure>
    <time_frame>daily through 4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>To assess the duration of temporary barrier function afforded by Xeno-Skin™</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">6</enrollment>
  <condition>Burn Wound</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Xeno-Skin™</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Single arm trial</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Xeno-Skin™</intervention_name>
    <description>3+3 Dose-escalation Study Design; 2 dosage strengths will be utilized during this Phase 1 Trial</description>
    <arm_group_label>Xeno-Skin™</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. The subject or, when applicable, the subject's legally authorized representative,
             provides written informed consent to participate in this study

          2. Age greater than 18 years old

          3. Male or female of non-childbearing potential. Females must be:

             a. Naturally postmenopausal defined as ≥1 year without menses and: i. ≥55 years, or
             ii. &lt;55 years with follicle-stimulating hormone (FSH) ≥40.0 IU/L; or iii. Surgically
             sterile including hysterectomy, bilateral oophorectomy, and/or tubal ligation.

          4. Total Burn Surface Area (TBSA) &lt;30% to include deep partial thickness or full
             thickness burn wound

          5. Burn injury requiring excision

          6. Burn injury requiring temporary allograft coverage of wound based on clinical
             judgement prior to definitive wound closure with autologous skin grafts

          7. Sufficient area of burn wound for Xeno-Skin™ placement, not previously treated with
             allograft, and not located on face or hands.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Pregnant or lactating women

          2. Documented history of infection with human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) or other
             condition(s) that in the opinion of the Investigator may compromise patient safety or
             study objectives.

          3. Immunosuppressive medication regimens e.g. antineoplastics, high dose steroids (&gt; 10
             mg prednisone/day), TNF alpha inhibitors, calcineurin inhibitors (cyclosporine,
             tacrolimus), antiproliferative agents, and other immunomodulators

          4. Known allergy to penicillin, aminoglycosides (such as streptomycin) or amphotericin B.

          5. Active malignancy, including those requiring surgery, chemotherapy, and/or radiation
             in the past 5 years. Non-metastatic basal or squamous cell carcinoma of the skin and
             cervical carcinoma in situ are allowed

          6. Use of any experimental or investigational drugs within 30 days prior to placement of
             Xeno-Skin™

          7. Previously received a porcine or other xenogeneic tissue product, including but not
             limited to:

             glutaraldehyde fixed porcine or bovine bioprosthetic heart valve replacements and
             glutaraldehyde fixed porcine dermal matrix

          8. BMI &gt; 40 kg/m2

          9. HbA1c ≥ 7.0%

         10. Treatment with systemic corticosteroids within 30 days before screening (not including
             inhaled steroids)

         11. Electrical or chemical burns

         12. History of chronic end stage renal disease defined as an MDRD CrCl &lt; 15 mL/min, or
             receiving chronic dialysis

         13. History of chronic liver disease or cirrhosis (Child-Pugh Score C). Evidence of acute
             or chronic hepatitis B infection based on documented HBV serology testing

         14. Known documented history of Hepatitis B, Hepatitis C, Treponema pallidum,
             Cytomegalovirus, herpes or varicella zoster Note: Successfully treated hepatitis C
             patients without evidence of end stage liver disease is allowed. If HCV antibody
             reactive, then HCV RNA must be undetectable.

         15. Recent (within 3 months prior to study enrollment) MI, unstable angina leading to
             hospitalization, uncontrolled, CABG, PCI, carotid surgery or stenting, cerebrovascular
             accident, transient ischemic attack, endovascular procedure or surgical intervention
             for peripheral vascular disease or plans to undergo a major surgical or interventional
             procedure (e.g., PCI, CABG, carotid or peripheral revascularization)

         16. Presence of venous or arterial vascular disorder directly affecting the area of burn
             wound

         17. Pre-existing haemolytic anemia

         18. Chronic malnourishment as determined by Investigator

         19. Significant pulmonary compromise

         20. Systemic anticoagulation at the time of treatment or INR &gt; 2

         21. Documented evidence of wound infection prior to treatment

         22. Evidence of sepsis and/or end organ damage

         23. Acute lung injury

         24. Life expectancy of less than 180 days
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jeremy Goverman, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Massachusetts General Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Paul Holzer</last_name>
    <phone>(617) 939-7892</phone>
    <email>clinicaltrials@xenotherapeutics.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Krysta Moulton</last_name>
    <phone>(617) 939-7892</phone>
    <email>clinicaltrials@xenotherapeutics.org</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Massachusetts General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02114</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jeremy Goverman, MD</last_name>
      <phone>617-726-3712</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Albritton A, Leonard DA, Leto Barone A, Keegan J, Mallard C, Sachs DH, Kurtz JM, Cetrulo CL Jr. Lack of cross-sensitization between α-1,3-galactosyltransferase knockout porcine and allogeneic skin grafts permits serial grafting. Transplantation. 2014 Jun 27;97(12):1209-15. doi: 10.1097/TP.0000000000000093.</citation>
    <PMID>24798308</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bruccoleri RE, Matthew MK, Schulz JT. Methods in obtaining split-thickness skin grafts from skin reduction surgery specimens. Springerplus. 2016 May 25;5(1):690. doi: 10.1186/s40064-016-2330-2. eCollection 2016.</citation>
    <PMID>27350924</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Burd A, Chiu T. Allogenic skin in the treatment of burns. Clin Dermatol. 2005 Jul-Aug;23(4):376-87. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>16023933</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Denner J. Paving the Path toward Porcine Organs for Transplantation. N Engl J Med. 2017 Nov 9;377(19):1891-1893. doi: 10.1056/NEJMcibr1710853.</citation>
    <PMID>29117497</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Deschamps JY, Roux FA, Saï P, Gouin E. History of xenotransplantation. Xenotransplantation. 2005 Mar;12(2):91-109.</citation>
    <PMID>15693840</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ericsson TA, Takeuchi Y, Templin C, Quinn G, Farhadian SF, Wood JC, Oldmixon BA, Suling KM, Ishii JK, Kitagawa Y, Miyazawa T, Salomon DR, Weiss RA, Patience C. Identification of receptors for pig endogenous retrovirus. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2003 May 27;100(11):6759-64. Epub 2003 May 9.</citation>
    <PMID>12740431</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fishman JA. Screening of source animals and clinical monitoring for xenotransplantation. Xenotransplantation. 2007, 349-352.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fishman JA, Scobie L, Takeuchi Y. Xenotransplantation-associated infectious risk: a WHO consultation. Xenotransplantation. 2012 Mar-Apr;19(2):72-81. doi: 10.1111/j.1399-3089.2012.00693.x.</citation>
    <PMID>22497509</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Godehardt AW, Rodrigues Costa M, Tönjes RR. Review on porcine endogenous retrovirus detection assays--impact on quality and safety of xenotransplants. Xenotransplantation. 2015 Mar-Apr;22(2):95-101. doi: 10.1111/xen.12154. Epub 2015 Jan 31. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25641488</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Herndon DN. Total Burn Care, Expert Consult - Online. Elsevier Health Sciences; 2012.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Johnson RM, Richard R. Partial-thickness burns: identification and management. Adv Skin Wound Care. 2003 Jul-Aug;16(4):178-87; quiz 188-9. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>12897674</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kitala D, Kawecki M, Klama-Baryła A, Łabuś W, Kraut M, Glik J, Ryszkiel I, Kawecki MP, Nowak M. Allogeneic vs. Autologous Skin Grafts in the Therapy of Patients with Burn Injuries: A Restrospective, Open-label Clinical Study with Pair Matching. Adv Clin Exp Med. 2016 Sep-Oct;25(5):923-929. doi: 10.17219/acem/61961.</citation>
    <PMID>28028957</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Leonard DA, Mallard C, Albritton A, Torabi R, Mastroianni M, Sachs DH, Kurtz JM, Cetrulo CL Jr. Skin grafts from genetically modified α-1,3-galactosyltransferase knockout miniature swine: A functional equivalent to allografts. Burns. 2017 Dec;43(8):1717-1724. doi: 10.1016/j.burns.2017.04.026. Epub 2017 Jun 8.</citation>
    <PMID>28602591</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Leto Barone AA, Mastroianni M, Farkash EA, Mallard C, Albritton A, Torabi R, Leonard DA, Kurtz JM, Sachs DH, Cetrulo CL Jr. Genetically modified porcine split-thickness skin grafts as an alternative to allograft for provision of temporary wound coverage: preliminary characterization. Burns. 2015 May;41(3):565-74. doi: 10.1016/j.burns.2014.09.003. Epub 2014 Oct 16.</citation>
    <PMID>25406888</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Organ Procurement and Transplantation Network. (n.d.). Retrieved May 01, 2017, from https://optn.transplant.hrsa.gov/</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Martin SI, Wilkinson R, Fishman JA. Genomic presence of recombinant porcine endogenous retrovirus in transmitting miniature swine. Virol J. 2006 Nov 2;3:91.</citation>
    <PMID>17081300</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Meije Y, Tönjes RR, Fishman JA. Retroviral restriction factors and infectious risk in xenotransplantation. Am J Transplant. 2010 Jul;10(7):1511-6. doi: 10.1111/j.1600-6143.2010.03146.x.</citation>
    <PMID>20642677</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Morozov VA, Wynyard S, Matsumoto S, Abalovich A, Denner J, Elliott R. No PERV transmission during a clinical trial of pig islet cell transplantation. Virus Res. 2017 Jan 2;227:34-40. doi: 10.1016/j.virusres.2016.08.012. Epub 2016 Sep 24.</citation>
    <PMID>27677465</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Paradis K, Langford G, Long Z, Heneine W, Sandstrom P, Switzer WM, Chapman LE, Lockey C, Onions D, Otto E. Search for cross-species transmission of porcine endogenous retrovirus in patients treated with living pig tissue. The XEN 111 Study Group. Science. 1999 Aug 20;285(5431):1236-41.</citation>
    <PMID>10455044</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Patience C, Takeuchi Y, Weiss RA. Infection of human cells by an endogenous retrovirus of pigs. Nat Med. 1997 Mar;3(3):282-6.</citation>
    <PMID>9055854</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sachs DH. The lure of transplantation. Clin Transpl. 2008:287-305.</citation>
    <PMID>19708462</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schaffer A. Cadaver Skin Fills the Gap in Burn Cases. New York Times. May 2, 2006.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sen CK, Gordillo GM, Roy S, Kirsner R, Lambert L, Hunt TK, Gottrup F, Gurtner GC, Longaker MT. Human skin wounds: a major and snowballing threat to public health and the economy. Wound Repair Regen. 2009 Nov-Dec;17(6):763-71. doi: 10.1111/j.1524-475X.2009.00543.x.</citation>
    <PMID>19903300</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sheridan RL, Tompkins RG. Skin substitutes in burns. Burns. 1999 Mar;25(2):97-103. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>10208382</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shi M, Wang X, Okamoto M, Takao S, Baba M. Inhibition of porcine endogenous retrovirus (PERV) replication by HIV-1 gene expression inhibitors. Antiviral Res. 2009 Aug;83(2):201-4. doi: 10.1016/j.antiviral.2009.04.011. Epub 2009 May 3.</citation>
    <PMID>19414036</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Thorton JF and Gosman AA. Skin Grafts and Skin Substitutes. Baylor University Medical Center. 2004 10(1): 2-78</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Weiner J, Yamada K, Ishikawa Y, Moran S, Etter J, Shimizu A, Smith RN, Sachs DH. Prolonged survival of GalT-KO swine skin on baboons. Xenotransplantation. 2010 Mar-Apr;17(2):147-52. doi: 10.1111/j.1399-3089.2010.00576.x.</citation>
    <PMID>20522247</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wilhelm M, Fishman JA, Pontikis R, Aubertin AM, Wilhelm FX. Susceptibility of recombinant porcine endogenous retrovirus reverse transcriptase to nucleoside and non-nucleoside inhibitors. Cell Mol Life Sci. 2002 Dec;59(12):2184-90.</citation>
    <PMID>12568344</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wood JC, Quinn G, Suling KM, Oldmixon BA, Van Tine BA, Cina R, Arn S, Huang CA, Scobie L, Onions DE, Sachs DH, Schuurman HJ, Fishman JA, Patience C. Identification of exogenous forms of human-tropic porcine endogenous retrovirus in miniature Swine. J Virol. 2004 Mar;78(5):2494-501.</citation>
    <PMID>14963150</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>World Health Organization Burn Fact Sheet. http://www.who.int/en/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/burns. March 6, 2018.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wynyard S, Nathu D, Garkavenko O, Denner J, Elliott R. Microbiological safety of the first clinical pig islet xenotransplantation trial in New Zealand. Xenotransplantation. 2014 Jul-Aug;21(4):309-23. doi: 10.1111/xen.12102. Epub 2014 May 7.</citation>
    <PMID>24801820</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yue S, Zhang Y, Gao Y. A study on the susceptibility of allogeneic human hepatocytes to porcine endogenous retrovirus. Eur Rev Med Pharmacol Sci. 2015 Sep;19(18):3486-91.</citation>
    <PMID>26439047</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Holzer PW, Leonard DA, Shanmugarajah K, Moulton KN, Ng ZY, Cetrulo CL Jr, Sachs DH. A Comparative Examination of the Clinical Outcome and Histological Appearance of Cryopreserved and Fresh Split-Thickness Skin Grafts. J Burn Care Res. 2017 Jan/Feb;38(1):e55-e61. doi: 10.1097/BCR.0000000000000431.</citation>
    <PMID>27606556</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 28, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 3, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 4, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 6, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 6, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 7, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>xenograft, allograft, burns, severe burns, temporary coverage, porcine.</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Burns</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>XenoTherapeutics plans to share the Individual Participant Dataset of all collected individual participant data. The following supporting information will also be shared.</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Statistical Analysis Plan (SAP)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Informed Consent Form (ICF)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Clinical Study Report (CSR)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_url>http://www.xenotherapeutics.org</ipd_url>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

