<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03696199</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>H00014155</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03696199</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Randomized Controlled Trial for Ankle Fracture Pain Control</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Prospective, Randomized Trial Evaluating Regional Anesthesia, Long-Acting Local Anesthesia, and Traditional Care for Pain Control of Operatively Treated Ankle Fractures</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Massachusetts, Worcester</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Kentucky</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Massachusetts, Worcester</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>Yes</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This project is a multicenter, three armed, prospective randomized control trial studying the
      effectiveness of a long-acting local anesthetic &quot;cocktail&quot; in patients undergoing operative
      fixation of ankle fractures.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study is a multicenter, three armed, prospective randomized control trial studying the
      effect of a long-acting local anesthetic &quot;cocktail&quot; in patients undergoing operative fixation
      of ankle fractures.

      Primary Hypothesis Driven Aims:

        1. Determine the effectiveness of a local anesthesia &quot;cocktail&quot; compared to regional block
           or standard of care in controlling pain in operatively treated ankle fractures. Nearly
           one out of ten fractures treated by both orthopaedic traumatologists and general
           orthopaedic surgeons taking call are ankle fractures. As such, effective pain control in
           this group of patients represents an opportunity to make a large impact, especially in
           the context of the current opioid epidemic. Improved pain control can help improve
           patient satisfaction, outcomes, decrease length of stay, cost of care, and complications
           associated with traditional narcotic use.

             -  Hypothesis 1A: Patients receiving the intraoperative cocktail will have improved
                post-operative pain control compared to those receiving a peri-operative nerve
                block or standard of care.

             -  Hypothesis 1B: Patients receiving the intraoperative cocktail or peri-operative
                nerve block will have improved post-operative pain control when compared to
                standard of care.

             -  Null Hypothesis 1: There will be no difference in post-operative pain control
                between all treatment arms.

        2. Determine the economic impact of cocktail and regional blocks in ankle fractures. A
           common concern with the use of regional blocks is the cost of the additional procedure,
           along with logistic delays which are associated with coordinating a separate procedure.
           This study would provide valuable data about the additional costs associated with
           regional blocks and with cocktail administration which could help aid in making
           economically conscious treatment decisions.

             -  Hypothesis 2: Local cocktail administration will have significantly lower costs
                than regional block, and not be significantly more expensive than standard of care.

             -  Null Hypothesis 2: There is no difference in cost between the modalities.

      Secondary Aim:

      Demonstrate the use of long-acting local anesthetic as a viable pain management strategy in
      fracture surgery. Although long-acting local anesthetics have an established track record in
      arthroplasty, there is a paucity of evidence guiding their use in fractures. Small case
      series in trauma and foot/ankle patients have been encouraging, but a rigorously conducted,
      prospective trial in a relatively homogeneous group could generate pilot data to validate the
      use of long acting local anesthetics in fracture surgery. This knowledge may be translatable
      to other extremity injuries as well, having a greater impact than the scope of the proposed
      trial.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 1, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 1, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Oral Narcotics / Morphine Milligram Equivalents (MME) given</measure>
    <time_frame>72 postoperative hours</time_frame>
    <description>The medical record (EPIC) will be used to determine the total morphine equivalents given to the patient post-surgery, including recovery unit administration of narcotics in the immediate post-operative period.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">70</enrollment>
  <condition>Ankle Fractures</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Traditional Pain Control Care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Standard of care post-operative pain control with oral narcotics</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Regional Anesthesia</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Single injection perioperative peripheral nerve block + followed by administration of oral narcotics on a need-based system</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Long-Acting Local Anesthesia</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subcutaneous local cocktail injection + followed by administration of oral narcotics on a need-based system</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Long-Acting Local Anesthesia</intervention_name>
    <description>The cocktail consists of:
0.5% Ropivicaine, 24.6 mL
Clonidine 100 mcg/mL, 0.4mL
Epinephrine 1mg/mL, 0.5mL
Saline to total volume of 50 mL (24.5mL of saline)
The total amount of solution prepared is 50mL, but typically 30mL is used based on the size of the incision. The total volume administered will be recorded.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Long-Acting Local Anesthesia</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Local Cocktail</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Regional Anesthesia</intervention_name>
    <description>0.5% ropivicaine - 30mL each sciatic and femoral/saphenous nerve, ultrasound guided</description>
    <arm_group_label>Regional Anesthesia</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Ropivicaine</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Sustained a bimalleolar ankle fracture (OTA/AO type 44 A2, B2, C1, and C2 fracture)
             with surgery indicated and an approach with medial and lateral incisions planned
             Syndesmotic injuries will be included, due to the practical difficulty of reliably
             determining the presence of a syndesmotic injury preoperatively Trimalleolar ankle
             fractures where fixation of the posterior malleolus is not planned will also be
             included

          -  Isolated Injury

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Unifocal malleolar fractures

          -  Bimalleolar fractures where fixation of only one malleolus is planned

          -  Posterior malleolus fractures requiring fixation

          -  Patients ineligible for a peripheral nerve block (e.g. concern for compartment
             syndrome)

          -  Open injury

          -  Patients treated with external fixation

          -  Neurologic condition that would confound results (e.g. peripheral neuropathy)

          -  Inability to consent

          -  Chronic opioid use

          -  History of opiate abuse

          -  Polytrauma as defined as additional boney injury, visceral injury or moderate soft
             tissue injury (requiring suture repair or other invasive procedure)

          -  Prisoners (unlikely to be accessible for follow-up)

          -  Pregnant patients

          -  Non-English-speaking subjects (post-operative data collection procedure involves
             conversations via phone calls. As we do not have access to translators for this
             research project, we will work exclusively with English-speaking subjects).

          -  Subjects unable to take the standard post-operative pain regimen that consists of
             gabapentin, oxycodone, acetaminophen, and ibuprofen.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>89 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Eric Swart, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>UMass Memorial Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Paul Matuszewski, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Kentucky</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Eric Swart, MD</last_name>
    <phone>508-334-2145</phone>
    <email>eric.swart@umassmemorial.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Ryan Fredette, BS</last_name>
    <phone>508-334-2145</phone>
    <email>ryan.fredette@umassmemorial.org</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Kentucky</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lexington</city>
        <state>Kentucky</state>
        <zip>40536</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Paul Matuszewski, MD</last_name>
      <phone>859-257-1000</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UMass Memorial Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Worcester</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>01655</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Eric Swart, MD</last_name>
      <phone>508-334-1000</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Barrington JW, Olugbode O, Lovald S, Ong K, Watson H, Emerson RH Jr. Liposomal Bupivacaine: A Comparative Study of More Than 1000 Total Joint Arthroplasty Cases. Orthop Clin North Am. 2015 Oct;46(4):469-77. doi: 10.1016/j.ocl.2015.06.003. Epub 2015 Aug 6. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26410636</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bramlett K, Onel E, Viscusi ER, Jones K. A randomized, double-blind, dose-ranging study comparing wound infiltration of DepoFoam bupivacaine, an extended-release liposomal bupivacaine, to bupivacaine HCl for postsurgical analgesia in total knee arthroplasty. Knee. 2012 Oct;19(5):530-6. doi: 10.1016/j.knee.2011.12.004. Epub 2012 Jan 28.</citation>
    <PMID>22285545</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ng FY, Ng JK, Chiu KY, Yan CH, Chan CW. Multimodal periarticular injection vs continuous femoral nerve block after total knee arthroplasty: a prospective, crossover, randomized clinical trial. J Arthroplasty. 2012 Jun;27(6):1234-8. doi: 10.1016/j.arth.2011.12.021. Epub 2012 Feb 8.</citation>
    <PMID>22325963</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lonner J. Role of liposomal bupivacaine in pain management after total joint arthroplasty. J Surg Orthop Adv. 2014 Spring;23(1):37-41. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24641895</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hutchinson HL. Local infiltration of liposome bupivacaine in orthopedic trauma patients: case-based reviews. Am J Orthop (Belle Mead NJ). 2014 Oct;43(10 Suppl):S13-6. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25303455</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Herbst SA. Local infiltration of liposome bupivacaine in foot and ankle surgery: case-based reviews. Am J Orthop (Belle Mead NJ). 2014 Oct;43(10 Suppl):S10-2. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25303454</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Stein BE, Srikumaran U, Tan EW, Freehill MT, Wilckens JH. Lower-extremity peripheral nerve blocks in the perioperative pain management of orthopaedic patients: AAOS exhibit selection. J Bone Joint Surg Am. 2012 Nov 21;94(22):e167. doi: 10.2106/JBJS.K.01706. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23172334</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wang J, Liu GT, Mayo HG, Joshi GP. Pain Management for Elective Foot and Ankle Surgery: A Systematic Review of Randomized Controlled Trials. J Foot Ankle Surg. 2015 Jul-Aug;54(4):625-35. doi: 10.1053/j.jfas.2014.05.003. Epub 2014 Jun 18. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24954920</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Compton P, Athanasos P. Chronic pain, substance abuse and addiction. Nurs Clin North Am. 2003 Sep;38(3):525-37. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>14567207</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>De Maeyer J, Vanderplasschen W, Broekaert E. Quality of life among opiate-dependent individuals: A review of the literature. Int J Drug Policy. 2010 Sep;21(5):364-80. doi: 10.1016/j.drugpo.2010.01.010. Epub 2010 Feb 20. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20172706</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Morrone LA, Scuteri D, Rombolà L, Mizoguchi H, Bagetta G. Opioids Resistance in Chronic Pain Management. Curr Neuropharmacol. 2017 Apr;15(3):444-456. doi: 10.2174/1570159X14666161101092822. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>28503117</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Holman JE, Stoddard GJ, Higgins TF. Rates of prescription opiate use before and after injury in patients with orthopaedic trauma and the risk factors for prolonged opiate use. J Bone Joint Surg Am. 2013 Jun 19;95(12):1075-80. doi: 10.2106/JBJS.L.00619.</citation>
    <PMID>23783203</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Manchikanti L. National drug control policy and prescription drug abuse: facts and fallacies. Pain Physician. 2007 May;10(3):399-424. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>17525776</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Elkassabany N, Cai LF, Mehta S, Ahn J, Pieczynski L, Polomano RC, Picon S, Hogg R, Liu J. Does Regional Anesthesia Improve the Quality of Postoperative Pain Management and the Quality of Recovery in Patients Undergoing Operative Repair of Tibia and Ankle Fractures? J Orthop Trauma. 2015 Sep;29(9):404-9. doi: 10.1097/BOT.0000000000000344.</citation>
    <PMID>25882965</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cometa MA, Esch AT, Boezaart AP. Did continuous femoral and sciatic nerve block obscure the diagnosis or delay the treatment of acute lower leg compartment syndrome? A case report. Pain Med. 2011 May;12(5):823-8. doi: 10.1111/j.1526-4637.2011.01109.x.</citation>
    <PMID>21564511</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mar GJ, Barrington MJ, McGuirk BR. Acute compartment syndrome of the lower limb and the effect of postoperative analgesia on diagnosis. Br J Anaesth. 2009 Jan;102(1):3-11. doi: 10.1093/bja/aen330. Epub 2008 Nov 19. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19022795</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Goldstein RY, Montero N, Jain SK, Egol KA, Tejwani NC. Efficacy of popliteal block in postoperative pain control after ankle fracture fixation: a prospective randomized study. J Orthop Trauma. 2012 Oct;26(10):557-61. Erratum in: J Orthop Trauma. 2013 Mar;27(3):181.</citation>
    <PMID>22732860</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ding DY, Manoli A 3rd, Galos DK, Jain S, Tejwani NC. Continuous Popliteal Sciatic Nerve Block Versus Single Injection Nerve Block for Ankle Fracture Surgery: A Prospective Randomized Comparative Trial. J Orthop Trauma. 2015 Sep;29(9):393-8. doi: 10.1097/BOT.0000000000000374.</citation>
    <PMID>26165259</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>White PF, Issioui T, Skrivanek GD, Early JS, Wakefield C. The use of a continuous popliteal sciatic nerve block after surgery involving the foot and ankle: does it improve the quality of recovery? Anesth Analg. 2003 Nov;97(5):1303-9. Erratum in: Anesth Analg. 2003 Dec;97(6):1557.</citation>
    <PMID>14570643</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schroer WC, Diesfeld PG, LeMarr AR, Morton DJ, Reedy ME. Does Extended-Release Liposomal Bupivacaine Better Control Pain Than Bupivacaine After Total Knee Arthroplasty (TKA)? A Prospective, Randomized Clinical Trial. J Arthroplasty. 2015 Sep;30(9 Suppl):64-7. doi: 10.1016/j.arth.2015.01.059. Epub 2015 Jun 3.</citation>
    <PMID>26117072</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bagsby DT, Ireland PH, Meneghini RM. Liposomal bupivacaine versus traditional periarticular injection for pain control after total knee arthroplasty. J Arthroplasty. 2014 Aug;29(8):1687-90. doi: 10.1016/j.arth.2014.03.034. Epub 2014 Apr 4.</citation>
    <PMID>24793570</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Joshi GP, Cushner FD, Barrington JW, Lombardi AV Jr, Long WJ, Springer BD, Stulberg BN. Techniques for periarticular infiltration with liposomal bupivacaine for the management of pain after hip and knee arthroplasty: a consensus recommendation. J Surg Orthop Adv. 2015 Spring;24(1):27-35.</citation>
    <PMID>25830260</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kelley TC, Adams MJ, Mulliken BD, Dalury DF. Efficacy of multimodal perioperative analgesia protocol with periarticular medication injection in total knee arthroplasty: a randomized, double-blinded study. J Arthroplasty. 2013 Sep;28(8):1274-7. doi: 10.1016/j.arth.2013.03.008. Epub 2013 Apr 20. Erratum in: J Arthroplasty. 2014 Oct;29(10):2057.</citation>
    <PMID>23608085</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zhao X, Qin J, Tan Y, Mohanan R, Hu D, Chen L. Efficacy of steroid addition to multimodal cocktail periarticular injection in total knee arthroplasty: a meta-analysis. J Orthop Surg Res. 2015 May 22;10:75. doi: 10.1186/s13018-015-0214-8.</citation>
    <PMID>25994175</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Busch CA, Shore BJ, Bhandari R, Ganapathy S, MacDonald SJ, Bourne RB, Rorabeck CH, McCalden RW. Efficacy of periarticular multimodal drug injection in total knee arthroplasty. A randomized trial. J Bone Joint Surg Am. 2006 May;88(5):959-63.</citation>
    <PMID>16651569</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Myles PS, Reeves MD, Anderson H, Weeks AM. Measurement of quality of recovery in 5672 patients after anaesthesia and surgery. Anaesth Intensive Care. 2000 Jun;28(3):276-80.</citation>
    <PMID>10853209</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 24, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 3, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 4, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 27, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 27, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 28, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Massachusetts, Worcester</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Eric Swart</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Fractures, Bone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ankle Fractures</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Anesthetics</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <provided_document_section>
    <provided_document>
      <document_type>Study Protocol</document_type>
      <document_has_protocol>Yes</document_has_protocol>
      <document_has_icf>No</document_has_icf>
      <document_has_sap>No</document_has_sap>
      <document_date>June 1, 2018</document_date>
      <document_url>https://ClinicalTrials.gov/ProvidedDocs/99/NCT03696199/Prot_000.pdf</document_url>
    </provided_document>
  </provided_document_section>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

