<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03696732</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>450-18</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03696732</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Anxiety and Phenylephrine Dosage</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Effect of Preoperative Anxiety on Phenylephrine Dosage During Cesarean Delivery Under Spinal Anesthesia, A Prospective Observational Study.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Rabin Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Rabin Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Spinal anesthesia is considered gold standard anesthetic technique of choice for cesarean
      delivery (1). However its use is frequently associated with maternal hypotension, which
      occurs in up to 71% of cases, without prophylactic treatment(2) Spinal hypotension can lead
      to unpleasant maternal side effects such as nausea, vomiting and dizziness. In addition,
      adverse effects on the neonate occur because of reduced uteroplacental blood flow resulting
      in impaired fetal oxygenation and fetal acidosis. As such, current research recommends the
      prophylactic use of vasopressors for improved maternal and fetal outcomes(3).

      The international consensus statement on the management of hypotension during cesarean
      delivery states, that a prophylactic phenylephrine infusion is superior to bolus
      administration and should be dose titrated according to blood pressure parameters (4). In
      according to the international guidelines, in our obstetric anesthesia unit, we use a
      standardized spinal anesthetic regime protocol with a standardized prophylactic phenylephrine
      infusion at a rate of 50 mcg/min, with the vasopressor dose titrated according to every
      minute blood pressure parameters.

      Spinal anesthesia causes maternal hypotension, resulting from a blockade of sympathetic
      efferent neurons. Patients with higher baseline sympathetic activation have been known to
      have more marked hypotension after spinal anesthesia (5, 6) Anxiety causes generalized
      sympathetic activation (7). In a previous research the investigators showed that preoperative
      anxiety assessed by VAS had a significant effect on hypotension after spinal anesthesia (8).

      Study objective:

      In this study the investigators aim to evaluate the effect of anxiety on the cumulative
      phenylephrine dosage in women undergoing cesarean delivery under spinal anesthesia with
      prophylactic phenylephrine infusion. The primary hypothesis is that parturients who suffer
      from preoperative anxiety measured by a verbal numerical scale (VNS) anxiety score and
      Spielberger State-Trait Inventory questionnaire, will receive higher cumulative doses of
      phenylephrine (resulting from higher incidence of maternal hypotension).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Methods:

      This is a prospective, observational, single center study, which will be conducted at the
      Rabin Medical Center (Beilinson campus), Petach Tikva, Israel, a tertiary university
      hospital. This study Is a purely observational study, with no implication on the medical
      treatment provided.

      Two hundred women aged 18 and above undergoing cesarean section delivery under spinal
      anesthesia will be enrolled after filling out an informed consent prior to surgery. Women
      will be requested to fill out an informed consent in the women's surgery waiting room on the
      day of surgery, when they aren't under any pain.

      The parturients preoperative anxiety will be assessed in the women's waiting room, on the day
      of the surgery using two previously validated direct psychological measures of anxiety:
      verbal numerical scale (VNS) anxiety score (9, 10), and the Spielberger. State-Trait
      Inventory questionnaire (13).

      Women will also be asked about nausea and vomiting during the surgery and in the post
      anesthesia care unit.

      In according to standard departmental clinical practice, baseline blood pressure will be
      determined in the preoperative holding area by recording 3 times ≥ 3 minutes apart using an
      automated oscillometric blood pressure cuff on the arm with the patient supine with left
      uterine displacement, with the mean of the 3 values taken as a baseline systolic and
      diastolic blood pressure. Women will undergo spinal anesthesia and blood pressure will be
      measured evert minute during labor. Hypotension will be treated by titrating the
      phenylephrine infusion and by phenylephrine boluses, using a standardized algorithm according
      to departmental protocol. At the time of spinal injection, a phenylephrine infusion will be
      started at 50 mcg/min. The automated blood pressure cuff will be programmed to cycle each
      minute. When each new blood pressure result will appear, the phenylephrine infusion will be
      adjusted based on the systolic blood pressure by a standard algorithm.

      Parturient's obstetric history, obstetric data and anesthetic data will be collected from
      each of the participant's medical file, in an anonymized way.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 20, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 20, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 20, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Total cumulative phenylephrine dosage in women undergoing cesarean delivery under spinal anesthesia with prophylactic phenylephrine infusion.</measure>
    <time_frame>During surgery -2 hours</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Phenylephrine</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Women undergoing cesarean section</arm_group_label>
    <description>Women undergoing cesarean section under spinal anesthesia with prophylactic phenylephrine drip.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Anxiety questionnaire</intervention_name>
    <description>Spielberger. State-Trait Inventory questionnaire</description>
    <arm_group_label>Women undergoing cesarean section</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>VAS questionnaire</intervention_name>
    <description>verbal numerical scale (VNS) anxiety score</description>
    <arm_group_label>Women undergoing cesarean section</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Two hundred healthy term parturients, over 18 years old, with healthy singleton pregnancy,
        undergoing cesarean delivery under spinal anesthesia in Beilinson Hospital, following
        obtaining written informed consents forums with the ability to comply with the study
        requirements will be included in our study.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Healthy parturients undergoing cesarean delivery under spinal anesthesia in Beilinson
        Hospital.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Women in active labor

          2. Women with a twin pregnancy

          3. Women with chronic hypertension or hypertension or preeclampsia.

          4. Active medical or psychiatric disorders requiring regular medication.

          5. Women who have any contraindication for spinal anesthesia.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <gender_based>Yes</gender_based>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Beilinson hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Petach tikvah</city>
        <country>Israel</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sharon Orbach, MD</last_name>
      <phone>972-54-538-3093</phone>
      <email>sharonorbach@yahoo.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Sharon Orbach-zinger</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Eran Danon</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Israel</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Klöhr S, Roth R, Hofmann T, Rossaint R, Heesen M. Definitions of hypotension after spinal anaesthesia for caesarean section: literature search and application to parturients. Acta Anaesthesiol Scand. 2010 Sep;54(8):909-21. doi: 10.1111/j.1399-6576.2010.02239.x. Epub 2010 Apr 23. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20455872</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Reynolds F, Seed PT. Anaesthesia for Caesarean section and neonatal acid-base status: a meta-analysis. Anaesthesia. 2005 Jul;60(7):636-53. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>15960713</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Higgins N, Fitzgerald PC, van Dyk D, Dyer RA, Rodriguez N, McCarthy RJ, Wong CA. The Effect of Prophylactic Phenylephrine and Ephedrine Infusions on Umbilical Artery Blood pH in Women With Preeclampsia Undergoing Cesarean Delivery With Spinal Anesthesia: A Randomized, Double-Blind Trial. Anesth Analg. 2018 Jun;126(6):1999-2006. doi: 10.1213/ANE.0000000000002524.</citation>
    <PMID>28953494</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kinsella SM, Carvalho B, Dyer RA, Fernando R, McDonnell N, Mercier FJ, Palanisamy A, Sia ATH, Van de Velde M, Vercueil A; Consensus Statement Collaborators. International consensus statement on the management of hypotension with vasopressors during caesarean section under spinal anaesthesia. Anaesthesia. 2018 Jan;73(1):71-92. doi: 10.1111/anae.14080. Epub 2017 Nov 1.</citation>
    <PMID>29090733</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hanss R, Bein B, Ledowski T, Lehmkuhl M, Ohnesorge H, Scherkl W, Steinfath M, Scholz J, Tonner PH. Heart rate variability predicts severe hypotension after spinal anesthesia for elective cesarean delivery. Anesthesiology. 2005 Jun;102(6):1086-93.</citation>
    <PMID>15915018</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hanss R, Ohnesorge H, Kaufmann M, Gaupp R, Ledowski T, Steinfath M, Scholz J, Bein B. Changes in heart rate variability may reflect sympatholysis during spinal anaesthesia. Acta Anaesthesiol Scand. 2007 Nov;51(10):1297-304.</citation>
    <PMID>17944631</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Roth WT, Doberenz S, Dietel A, Conrad A, Mueller A, Wollburg E, Meuret AE, Barr Taylor C, Kim S. Sympathetic activation in broadly defined generalized anxiety disorder. J Psychiatr Res. 2008 Feb;42(3):205-12. Epub 2007 Jan 23.</citation>
    <PMID>17250853</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Orbach-Zinger S, Ginosar Y, Elliston J, Fadon C, Abu-Lil M, Raz A, Goshen-Gottstein Y, Eidelman LA. Influence of preoperative anxiety on hypotension after spinal anaesthesia in women undergoing Caesarean delivery. Br J Anaesth. 2012 Dec;109(6):943-9. doi: 10.1093/bja/aes313. Epub 2012 Sep 10.</citation>
    <PMID>22964265</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Vogelsang J. The Visual Analog Scale: an accurate and sensitive method for self-reporting preoperative anxiety. J Post Anesth Nurs. 1988 Aug;3(4):235-9.</citation>
    <PMID>2457102</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kindler CH, Harms C, Amsler F, Ihde-Scholl T, Scheidegger D. The visual analog scale allows effective measurement of preoperative anxiety and detection of patients' anesthetic concerns. Anesth Analg. 2000 Mar;90(3):706-12.</citation>
    <PMID>10702461</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>September 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 3, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 3, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 5, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 19, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 19, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">September 20, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Rabin Medical Center</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>sharonorbach</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

