<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03694912</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>4-2018-0753</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03694912</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Development and Evaluation of High Risk Group Prediction Model in T1 Stage Renal Cell Cancer Using Molecular Biomarkers</brief_title>
  <official_title>Development and Evaluation of High Risk Group Prediction Model in T1 Stage Renal Cell Cancer Using Molecular Biomarkers</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Yonsei University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Yonsei University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      For the appropriate individualized treatment of T1-stage renal cell carcinoma with
      heterogeneous biological features, the expression of PBRM1, SETD2, BAP1, KDM5C and the newly
      proposed FOXC2 and CLIP4, are compared with clinical features. The investigators evaluated
      the efficacy of FOXC2 and CLIP4 as prognostic biomarkers and developed a high risk prediction
      model based on these results. In a previous study, the investigators evaluated the efficacy
      of FOXC2 and CLIP4 as prognostic biomarkers and reported their association with synchronous
      metastasis in renal cell carcinomas less than 7 cm in size. The investigators analyzed the
      expression level of renal cell carcinoma according to the size and malignancy (Fuhrman grade)
      of renal cell carcinoma in T1-stage clear cell type renal cell carcinoma of tumor size less
      than 7cm. The aim of this study was to analyze the association of tumor recurrence or
      metastasis, cancer specific survival rate, overall survival rate, tumor size, malignancy and
      T stage in postoperative biopsy. For expression analysis, PCR amplification and bidirectional
      Sanger sequencing and mRNA expression analysis (qRT-PCR) were used. For statistical analysis,
      Fisher exact test, Wilcoxon exact 2-tailed test, Cox proportional hazard regression analysis
      and competing risk method were used. In this study, the investigators compared the expression
      of PBRM1, SETD2, BAP1, and KDM5 with newly proposed biomarkers, FOXC2 and CLIP4 and
      demonstrate the prognostic value of FOXC2 and CLIP4 as new prognostic biomarkers and compared
      the clinical outcomes with the clinical outcome. Based on these results, the investigators
      propose a high risk prediction model for individualized treatment of T1-stage renal cell
      carcinoma. This study is expected to establish a new prediction model and molecular biologic
      stage for risk stratification of T1-stage renal cell carcinoma patients and apply genetic
      test for selection of optimal tailored treatment for T1-stage renal cell carcinoma. In
      addition, it will be an important basic data of the molecular biologic mechanism of
      metastasis in early renal cell carcinoma and may be used as a basic data for the development
      and selection of customized therapeutic agents in patients with distant metastasis.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      -  collection of FFPE samples: collection of primary or metastatic site

        -  micro-dissection: only when the tumor contents are more than 90% are analyzed.

      B. Data analysis and model development

        -  Development goals - Analysis of prospective biomarker expression in FFPE, and frozen
           tissue specimens

           - Development of a high-risk prediction model for post-surgical morbidity in T1-stage
           RCC

             -  Contents and scope

                  1. Expression analysis of prospective biomarkers in FFPE and frozen tissue
                     samples of T1-stage clear cell type RCC

                       -  PBRM1, SETD2, BAP1, and KDM5C expressed as prognostic biomarkers of renal
                          cell carcinoma in other studies

                       -  The newly proposed FOXC2, CLIP4

                          1) Mutational analysis (Transcriptome sequencing with variant calling) 2)
                          mRNA expression analysis (qRT-PCR) - only when the tumor contents are
                          more than 90% are analyzed.

                          - Analysis of tumor size and malignancy as a prognostic predictor of RCC

                          - The expression of primary and metastatic lesions was analyzed by
                          considering intratumor heterogeneity in RCC (Fisher exact test, Wilcoxon
                          exact 2-tailed test)

                            -  Analysis of association with postoperative local recurrence or
                               distant metastasis, cancer-specific survival, and overall survival
                               (Cox proportional hazard regression analysis: Time to recurrence and
                               distant metastasis, overall survival, competing risk method: cancer
                               specific survival)

                  2. Development of predictive model for high-risk molecular disease in T1-Stage
                     RCC (survival rate)

                     - elastic net Cox model in glmnet, version 1.7.3

                       -  prediction accuracy was evaluated using Harrel concordance probability
                          (C-index), internal validation was performed using bootstrap

                  3. Development of predictive model for preoperative molecular high risk in T1-
                     Stage RCC (for Poor Pathologic Findings)

                       -  multivariate logistic/linear regression model

                       -  prediction accuracy was evaluated using Harrel concordance probability
                          (C-index), internal validation was performed using bootstrap
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 1, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 22, 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 22, 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Assessment of gene expression of biomarkers using reverse-transcription polymerase chain reaction (qRT-PCR) according to groups</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week after the procedure</time_frame>
    <description>Assessment of gene expression of biomarkers using reverse-transcription polymerase chain reaction (qRT-PCR) according to groups</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>association of tumor size</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week after the procedure</time_frame>
    <description>association of tumor size (Fuhrman grade 1-2: low, 3-4: high)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>association of tumor malignancy</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week after the procedure</time_frame>
    <description>association of tumor malignancy (Fuhrman grade 1-2: low, 3-4: high)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">426</enrollment>
  <condition>Clear Renal Cell Cancer (&lt; 7cm Size)</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Aggressive RCC Group</arm_group_label>
    <description>RCC with synchronous metastasis, recurrence, or cancer-specific death</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Non-aggressive RCC Group</arm_group_label>
    <description>RCC without synchronous metastasis, recurrence, or cancer-specific death</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Partial or radical nephrectomy</intervention_name>
    <description>The investigators perform partial or radical nephrectomy those diagnosed as RCC.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Aggressive RCC Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Non-aggressive RCC Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <biospec_retention>Samples Without DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      FFPE (formalin-fixed paraffin-embedded), frozen tissue, blood, and urine samples
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients who have undergone partial or radical nephrectomy in Severance Hospital(Sinchon)
        from 2018.11 and 2019.10 were selected.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients diagnosed as clear cell renal cell caner T1 stage

          -  Patients who have undergone partial or radical nephrectomy in Severance Hospital,
             Sinchon from 2018.11 and 2019.10

          -  Those who agree to give permission to use their human source information

          -  Those who agree with this study

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Vulnerable Participants

          -  Those who don't agree with this study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>20 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of Urology, Urological Science Institute, Yonsei University, Colleage of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seoul</city>
        <zip>03722</zip>
        <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Won Sik Ham, MD</last_name>
      <phone>82-2-2228-2313</phone>
      <email>uroham@yuhs.ac</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 28, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 2, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 3, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 15, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 15, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">September 17, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>renal cell cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>high risk group</keyword>
  <keyword>bio-marker</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Renal Cell</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>The investigators are going to share study protocol of our study, statistical analysis plan, informed consent form, and clinical study report.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

