<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03690414</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>VCRTC-2018-01</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03690414</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluation of Short Term Use of Experimental Eye Drops BHVI2, 0.02% Atropine and BHVI2 Plus 0.02% Atropine Eye Drops</brief_title>
  <official_title>A One-month, Randomized, Single Centre, Double-masked, Comparative Study to Evaluate the Short-term Ocular Effects of Experimental BHVI2 and 0.02% Atropine Eye Drops Either Alone or in Combination</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Hai Yen Eye Care</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Brien Holden Vision</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Hai Yen Eye Care</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To assess the one-month ocular effects of nightly application of experimental BHVI2 and 0.02%
      atropine eye drops either alone or in combination, in children aged between 6 to 13 years old
      with myopia and randomized to use of experimental BHVI2 eye drops, 0.02% atropine eye drops,
      experimental BHVI2 plus 0.02% atropine eye drops.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Atropine was proven to be effective in controlling myopia. 7-methylxanthine was considered to
      play a role in slowing myopia. The experimental BHVI2 eye drops were proven to be safe for
      in-eye use in the trial that was conducted in Sydney, Australia. The investigators wish to
      evaluate the effects of experimental BHVI2 and 0.02% atropine eye drops either alone or in
      combination mainly on the pupillary and accommodative responses in children aged between 6 to
      13 years old over a one-month period.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 1, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">June 30, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">February 2, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Children aged between 6 to 13 years old. Myopia with spherical equivalent of -0.50D or worse with cylinder of -2.00D or less</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>The study treatments will be labelled as A, B and C at the Pharmacy. The masked study products will then be sent to the study coordinator to dispense</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in pupillary diameter</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline, at two-week and one-month visits</time_frame>
    <description>Measure and compare the photopic and mesopic pupil size (milimeters) before and after instillation of eye drops</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in accommodative amplitude</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline, at two-week and one-month visits</time_frame>
    <description>Measure and compare the accommodative amplitude (diopters) before and after instillation of eye drops</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">52</enrollment>
  <condition>Myopia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Experimental BHVI2 eye drops</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>20 participants will receive one drop per eye every night for four weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>0.02% Atropine eye drops</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>20 participants will receive one drop per eye every night for four weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Experimental BHVI2 plus 0.02% atropine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>20 participants will receive one drop per eye every night for four weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Experimental BHVI2</intervention_name>
    <description>Experimental BHVI2 eye drops</description>
    <arm_group_label>Experimental BHVI2 eye drops</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Atropine sulfate 0.02% eye drops</intervention_name>
    <description>Atropine eye drops</description>
    <arm_group_label>0.02% Atropine eye drops</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Combination Product</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Combination eye drops</intervention_name>
    <description>Combination eye drops with experimental BHVI2 plus 0.02% atropine</description>
    <arm_group_label>Experimental BHVI2 plus 0.02% atropine</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  be accompanied by a parent or guardian who is able to read and comprehend
             Vietnamese/English and give informed consent as demonstrated by signing a record of
             informed consent;

          -  at baseline, be within the age range of 6 to 13 years old inclusive;

          -  be diagnosed as myopic having spherical equivalent between -0.50 diopter and-6.00
             diopter.

          -  willing to comply with the applying eye drops once nightly at bedtime and follow the
             clinical trial visit schedule as directed by the Investigator.

          -  be willing to comply with the wearing and clinical trial visit schedule as directed by
             the investigator;

          -  have ocular findings deemed to be normal

          -  vision correctable to at least 20/25 or better in each eye with spectacles

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Subjects enrolled in the trial must NOT have:

          -  Any pre-existing ocular irritation, allergic conjunctivitis, injury or condition,
             including infection or disease.

          -  Any systemic disease that adversely affects ocular health e.g. diabetes, Graves
             disease, and auto-immune diseases such as ankylosing spondylitis, multiple sclerosis,
             Sjögrens syndrome and systemic lupus erythematosus. Conditions such as systemic
             hypertension and arthritis do not automatically exclude prospective participants.

          -  Use of or a need for concurrent category S3 and above ocular medication at enrolment
             and/or during the clinical trial.

          -  Use of or a need for any systemic medication or topical medications which may alter
             normal ocular findings / are known to affect a participant's ocular health /
             physiology or contact lens performance either in an adverse or beneficial manner at
             enrolment and/or during the clinical trial.

          -  NB: Systemic antihistamines are allowed on an &quot;as needed basis&quot;, provided they are not
             used prophylactically during the trial and at least 24 hours before the clinical trial
             product is used.

          -  History of eye trauma

          -  History of use of myopia control interventions such as Orthokeratology or eye surgery.

          -  Contraindications to atropine and caffeine such as pulmonary disease, heart conditions
             and ADHD

          -  Known allergy or intolerance to ingredients to atropine eye-drops, xanthines and other
             derivatives of anti-muscarinic receptor agents.

          -  Currently enrolled in another clinical trial.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>6 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>13 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Huy D.M Tran, MD, MSc</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Hai Eye Eye Care</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of Ophthalmology - An Sinh Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ho Chi Minh City</city>
        <zip>700000</zip>
        <country>Vietnam</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Vietnam</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bruce A. Re: Holden et al.: Global prevalence of myopia and high myopia and temporal trends from 2000 through 2050 (Ophthalmology 2016;123:1036-1042). Ophthalmology. 2017 Mar;124(3):e24-e25. doi: 10.1016/j.ophtha.2016.06.066.</citation>
    <PMID>28219507</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sankaridurg PR, Holden BA. Practical applications to modify and control the development of ametropia. Eye (Lond). 2014 Feb;28(2):134-41. doi: 10.1038/eye.2013.255. Epub 2013 Dec 6. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24310242</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Huang J, Wen D, Wang Q, McAlinden C, Flitcroft I, Chen H, Saw SM, Chen H, Bao F, Zhao Y, Hu L, Li X, Gao R, Lu W, Du Y, Jinag Z, Yu A, Lian H, Jiang Q, Yu Y, Qu J. Efficacy Comparison of 16 Interventions for Myopia Control in Children: A Network Meta-analysis. Ophthalmology. 2016 Apr;123(4):697-708. doi: 10.1016/j.ophtha.2015.11.010. Epub 2016 Jan 27.</citation>
    <PMID>26826749</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shih YF, Chen CH, Chou AC, Ho TC, Lin LL, Hung PT. Effects of different concentrations of atropine on controlling myopia in myopic children. J Ocul Pharmacol Ther. 1999 Feb;15(1):85-90.</citation>
    <PMID>10048351</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Clark TY, Clark RA. Atropine 0.01% Eyedrops Significantly Reduce the Progression of Childhood Myopia. J Ocul Pharmacol Ther. 2015 Nov;31(9):541-5. doi: 10.1089/jop.2015.0043. Epub 2015 Jul 28.</citation>
    <PMID>26218150</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chatzistefanou KI, Mills MD. The role of drug treatment in children with strabismus and amblyopia. Paediatr Drugs. 2000 Mar-Apr;2(2):91-100. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>10937461</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chen AM, Cotter SA. The Amblyopia Treatment Studies: Implications for Clinical Practice. Adv Ophthalmol Optom. 2016 Aug;1(1):287-305. doi: 10.1016/j.yaoo.2016.03.007.</citation>
    <PMID>28435934</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chia A, Lu QS, Tan D. Five-Year Clinical Trial on Atropine for the Treatment of Myopia 2: Myopia Control with Atropine 0.01% Eyedrops. Ophthalmology. 2016 Feb;123(2):391-399. doi: 10.1016/j.ophtha.2015.07.004. Epub 2015 Aug 11.</citation>
    <PMID>26271839</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tran HDM, Tran YH, Tran TD, Jong M, Coroneo M, Sankaridurg P. A Review of Myopia Control with Atropine. J Ocul Pharmacol Ther. 2018 Jun;34(5):374-379. doi: 10.1089/jop.2017.0144. Epub 2018 May 1. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>29715053</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shih KC, Chan TC, Ng AL, Lai JS, Li WW, Cheng AC, Fan DS. Use of Atropine for Prevention of Childhood Myopia Progression in Clinical Practice. Eye Contact Lens. 2016 Jan;42(1):16-23. doi: 10.1097/ICL.0000000000000189. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26340385</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chia A, Chua WH, Cheung YB, Wong WL, Lingham A, Fong A, Tan D. Atropine for the treatment of childhood myopia: safety and efficacy of 0.5%, 0.1%, and 0.01% doses (Atropine for the Treatment of Myopia 2). Ophthalmology. 2012 Feb;119(2):347-54. doi: 10.1016/j.ophtha.2011.07.031. Epub 2011 Oct 2.</citation>
    <PMID>21963266</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chia A, Chua WH, Wen L, Fong A, Goon YY, Tan D. Atropine for the treatment of childhood myopia: changes after stopping atropine 0.01%, 0.1% and 0.5%. Am J Ophthalmol. 2014 Feb;157(2):451-457.e1. doi: 10.1016/j.ajo.2013.09.020. Epub 2013 Dec 4.</citation>
    <PMID>24315293</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chua WH, Balakrishnan V, Chan YH, Tong L, Ling Y, Quah BL, Tan D. Atropine for the treatment of childhood myopia. Ophthalmology. 2006 Dec;113(12):2285-91. Epub 2006 Sep 25.</citation>
    <PMID>16996612</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shih YF, Hsiao CK, Chen CJ, Chang CW, Hung PT, Lin LL. An intervention trial on efficacy of atropine and multi-focal glasses in controlling myopic progression. Acta Ophthalmol Scand. 2001 Jun;79(3):233-6.</citation>
    <PMID>11401629</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>North RV, Kelly ME. A review of the uses and adverse effects of topical administration of atropine. Ophthalmic Physiol Opt. 1987;7(2):109-14. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>2958765</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kennedy RH, Dyer JA, Kennedy MA, Parulkar S, Kurland LT, Herman DC, McIntire D, Jacobs D, Luepker RV. Reducing the progression of myopia with atropine: a long term cohort study of Olmsted County students. Binocul Vis Strabismus Q. 2000;15(3 Suppl):281-304.</citation>
    <PMID>11486796</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Syniuta LA, Isenberg SJ. Atropine and bifocals can slow the progression of myopia in children. Binocul Vis Strabismus Q. 2001;16(3):203-8.</citation>
    <PMID>11511287</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wu PC, Yang YH, Fang PC. The long-term results of using low-concentration atropine eye drops for controlling myopia progression in schoolchildren. J Ocul Pharmacol Ther. 2011 Oct;27(5):461-6. doi: 10.1089/jop.2011.0027. Epub 2011 Aug 4.</citation>
    <PMID>21815829</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 27, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 27, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 1, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 11, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 11, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 12, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Myopia control</keyword>
  <keyword>Atropine eye drops</keyword>
  <keyword>Caffeine eye drops</keyword>
  <keyword>Pupillary diameter</keyword>
  <keyword>Accommodative responses</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Myopia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Atropine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ophthalmic Solutions</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

