<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03690687</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Postoperative peritonitis</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03690687</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Delayed Small-Bowel Anastomosis in Patients With Postoperative Peritonitis</brief_title>
  <acronym>Peritonitis</acronym>
  <official_title>Delayed Small-Bowel Anastomosis in Patients With Postoperative Peritonitis Due to Nontraumatic Small-Bowel Perforation and Anastomotic Leak: Cohort Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Andrey Nikolayevich Zharikov</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Altai State Medical University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Surgical management results for 114 patients with postoperative peritonitis due to
      small-bowel perforations, necrosis, and anastomotic leakage were comparatively analyzed.
      Using the APACHE-II (Acute Physiology, Age, Chronic Health Evaluation) and MPI (Mannheim
      Peritonitis Index) scoring systems, different surgical approaches were examined in three
      patient groups (primary anastomosis, delayed anastomosis, and enterostomy).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      One hundred and fourteen (114) participants with postoperative peritonitis resulted from
      small-bowel perforations or small-bowel anastomotic leaks were divided prior to surgery into
      3 groups following the APACHE-II (Acute Physiology, Age, Chronic Health Evaluation) and MPI
      (Mannheim Peritonitis Index) scores, and different surgical approaches were applied to the
      groups: group I underwent resection of the small intestine to place primary anastomosis;
      group II was subjected to resection of the small intestine to place delayed anastomosis; and
      group III went through resection of the small intestine with enterostomy. The surgeon used
      minimization (including a random element) and stratification by gender, age, and small-bowel
      pathology.

      The patients received resection of the small bowel to place primary small-bowel anastomosis,
      or as depending on their grouping:

        -  Resection of the small bowel to place primary anastomosis: resection of the small bowel
           to place primary anastomosis into small intestine or transverse colon were performed by
           routine practice during relaparotomy.

        -  Resection of the small intestine to place delayed anastomosis: resection of the small
           bowel was performed by routine practice. After the closure of the afferent and efferent
           loops of the small intestine, anastomosis was not applied. A decompression probe was
           introduced into the upper small intestine. In 24-36 hours, delayed anastomosis into
           small intestine or transverse colon was performed during the planned relaparotomy with
           arrested postoperative peritonitis.

        -  Resection of the small intestine with enterostomy: resection of the small intestine was
           performed by routine practice. In case there was no postoperative peritonitis relief and
           was organ dysfunction progression, anastomosis was not placed. The surgery was completed
           with enterostomy to perform open abdomen.

      The specificity of each operation, including a decision to make changes in the planned
      anastomosis after assessing the severity of illness and the severity of postoperative
      peritonitis, was at the discretion of the surgeon.

      All of the patients were followed up after operations. The patients were supervised in the
      clinic for 60 days post-surgery. During the postoperative period, complications in the three
      patient groups were assessed in terms of newly emerged small-bowel perforations, the number
      of anastomotic leaks, the number of programmed relaparotomies and on-demand relaparotomies,
      and mortality rate.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 1, 2010</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 1, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Cross-Sectional</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Patients with recurrent anastomotic leakage</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 2 months</time_frame>
    <description>Number of patients in groups 1 and 2</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>3</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">114</enrollment>
  <condition>Postoperative Peritonitis</condition>
  <condition>Anastomotic Leakage</condition>
  <condition>Intestinal Perforation Small</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group I. Primary anastomosis</arm_group_label>
    <description>Resection of the small bowel to place primary anastomosis into small intestine or transverse colon during relaparotomy.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group II. Delayed anastomosis</arm_group_label>
    <description>Resection of the small intestine to place delayed anastomosis. After the closure of the afferent and efferent loops of the small intestine, anastomosis was not applied. A decompression probe was introduced into the upper small intestine. In 24-36 hours, delayed anastomosis was placed into the small intestine or transverse colon during the planned relaparotomy with arrested postoperative peritonitis.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group III. Enterostomy</arm_group_label>
    <description>Resection of the small intestine with enterostomy. In case there was no postoperative peritonitis relief and was organ dysfunction progression, anastomosis was not placed. The surgery was completed with enterostomy to perform open abdomen.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Primary anastomosis</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Group I. Primary anastomosis</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Delayed anastomosis</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Group II. Delayed anastomosis</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Enterostomy</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Group III. Enterostomy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Local patients admitted to the clinic from around Altai Krai cities, suffering from
        postoperative peritonitis due to small-bowel perforations and small-bowel anastomotic leaks
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Clinical diagnosis of postoperastive peritonitis

          -  Conducting relaparotomy

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Peritoneal cancer

          -  Multiple organ dysfunction syndrome
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>19 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>76 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zharikov AN, Lubyansky VG, Aliev AR. Surgical techniques for open abdomen in patients with postoperative peritonitis. Bulletin of Medical Science 2(10):76-80, 2018. URL: http://www.agmu.ru/files/%E2%84%962(10)2018.pdf</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zharikov AN, Lubyansky VG, Aliev AR et al. Staged surgical treatment with temporary laparostomy in patients with postoperative peritonitis. Moscow Surgical Journal 1(41):10-14, 2015. URL: http://mossj.ru/journal/MOSSJ_2015/MXG_2015_01.pdf</citation>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>September 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 26, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 27, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 1, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 28, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 28, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 2, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Altai State Medical University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Andrey Nikolayevich Zharikov</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Surgical Anastomosis</keyword>
  <keyword>Enterostomy</keyword>
  <keyword>Mortality</keyword>
  <keyword>Morbidity</keyword>
  <keyword>Abdominal Closure Techniques</keyword>
  <keyword>APACHE II</keyword>
  <keyword>Secondary Peritonitis</keyword>
  <keyword>Delayed Anastomosis</keyword>
  <keyword>Primary Anastomosis</keyword>
  <keyword>Mannheim Peritonitis Index</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Peritonitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Intestinal Perforation</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Anastomotic Leak</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>The first group included 47 patients (41.2%) who underwent conventional surgical management during relaparotomy, taking into account APACHE-II severity of illness and MPI severity of peritonitis. This surgical treatment involved suturing the intestinal wall defects or small-bowel resection to place primary anastomosis. The second patient group included 55 patients (48.2%) to which the delayed anastomosis technique was applied during relaparotomy, taking account the APACHE-II and MPI scores. The third patient group included 12 patients (10.5%) who had the highest risk of small-bowel suture failure when closing the defects in either primary or delayed anastomosis, as well as the risk of new small-bowel perforations to occur. In these cases, resection of the intestine was performed with enterostomy, along with planned relaparotomies and Open Abdomen management.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

