<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03697551</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>D-FR-01070-003</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2018-000028-33</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03697551</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Define the Optimal Uptake Time of 68Ga-OPS202 When Used as a PET (Positron Emission Tomography) Imaging Agent in Subjects With Newly Diagnosed Breast Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Non-Randomised Phase II Study to Evaluate the Optimal Uptake Time of 68GA-OPS202 as a sstr2 Positive PET Imaging Agent in Subjects With Newly Diagnosed Breast Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Ipsen</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Ipsen</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this clinical research is to define the optimal uptake time of 68Ga-OPS202 as
      a PET imaging agent to be used to detect and localize breast cancer somatostatin receptor
      subtype 2 (SSTR2) positive lesions.

      68Ga-OPS202 is a radiolabelled imaging agent to be used in association with PET. 68Ga-OPS202
      is made of two main components: 1) OPS202, an antagonistic somatostatin analogue which binds
      to the somatostatin receptor (type 2) present on the surface of the tumor cells and 2)
      Gallium 68, a radioisotope that, combined with OPS202, can be seen in the PET scanner.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Recruitment challenges and overlap with D-FR-01072-002 (SSTR2+ study)
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 8, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">January 2, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 19, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of subjects with sufficiently avid lesion(s) to be identified as a sstr2 positive lesion.</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from 0.5 to 1 and to 2 hours after injection on Day 1</time_frame>
    <description>Avid is defined by the blinded readers at one of the timepoints as an easily identifiable lesion radiologically, where there has been clear focal uptake of 68GA-OPS202.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Differences in the number of lesions detected by 68Ga-OPS202 between the three PET acquisition timepoints (0.5, 1 and 2 hours) in primary breast lesions.</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from 0.5 to 1 and to 2 hours after injection on Day 1</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Differences in the number of lesions detected by 68Ga-OPS202 between the three PET acquisition timepoints (0.5, 1 and 2 hours) in nodular and metastatic lesions.</measure>
    <time_frame>0.5, 1 and 2 hours after injection on Day 1</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Differences at each of the three timepoints in mean standardised uptake value (SUVmean) and maximum standardised uptake value (SUVmax)</measure>
    <time_frame>0.5, 1 and 2 hours after injection on Day 1</time_frame>
    <description>As measured by the tumour-to-background ratio in the primary tumour and each of the major anatomic sites (liver, lymph nodes, bone, lungs and brain).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Differences in relative lesion counts as a ratio of the number of lesions detected by 68Ga-OPS202 at 0.5, 1 and 2 hours post dose respectively, compared to the number of lesions assessed by standard-of-truth (descriptive analyses).</measure>
    <time_frame>0.5, 1 and 2 hours after injection on Day 1</time_frame>
    <description>The standard-of-truth is the 18F-fluorodeoxyglucose (18F-FDG) PET/CT scan images acquired at any time during the study period (including the Screening period). This will be calculated by (number of lesions detected by 68Ga-OPS202)/(number of lesions detected by 18F-FDG-PET).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Differences of absolute number of lesions between the three PET acquisition timepoints detected in each of the following anatomic sites: - Lymph nodes - Liver - Axial/appendicular skeleton - Lungs - Brain</measure>
    <time_frame>0.5, 1 and 2 hours after injection on Day 1</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Preliminary diagnostic sensitivity of 68Ga-OPS202 imaging of breast cancer expressing sstr2 positive by both subject-based and lesion-based analysis compared to standard-of-truth</measure>
    <time_frame>0.5, 1 and 2 hours after injection on Day 1</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Signal-to-noise ratio (SNR) calculated from lesion-free volume of interest (VOI) in the liver: SUVmean/SUVstandard deviation at the three PET acquisition timepoints</measure>
    <time_frame>0.5, 1 and 2 hours after injection on Day 1</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Estimated correlation in terms of number of avid lesions between 68Ga-OPS202 PET at the agreed &quot;optimum timepoint&quot; and 18F-FDG-PET</measure>
    <time_frame>0.5, 1 and 2 hours after injection on Day 1</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Estimated correlation between 68Ga-OPS202 PET uptake and results of immunohistochemistry staining of sstr2 of the primary tumour.</measure>
    <time_frame>0.5, 1 and 2 hours after injection on Day 1</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of subjects experiencing at least one AE of any grade according to the National Cancer Institute-Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (NCICTCAE) version 4.03, including any serious AEs including suspected unexpected serious adverse</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Day 14 +/-3 (end of study)</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of subjects experiencing at least one AE of grade ≥3 according to NCI CTCAE.</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Day 14 +/-3 (end of study)</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">4</enrollment>
  <condition>Breast Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>68Ga-OPS202</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>A single dose of Satoreotide trizoxetan will be administered as a slow intravenous (i.v.) bolus injected over 1 minute at Baseline/Day 1.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Satoreotide trizoxetan</intervention_name>
    <description>Subjects will receive a single dose of Satoreotide trizoxetan consisting of a peptide mass up to 45 μg, with a radioactivity range of 150-200 MBq. Satoreotide trizoxetan is intended for diagnostic use as a Positron emission tomography/computed tomography (PET/CT) tracer for the imaging of tumours expressing SSTR2.</description>
    <arm_group_label>68Ga-OPS202</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>68Ga-OPS202</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Women aged 18 years or older

          -  Subjects with newly diagnosed (early or advanced) breast cancer

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status ≤2

          -  Adequate bone marrow, liver and renal function, with:

               -  Calculated glomerular filtration rate (GFR): ≥45 mL/min

               -  Albumin: &gt;30 g/L

               -  Alanine aminotransferase (ALT), aspartate aminotransferase (AST), alkaline
                  phosphatase (AP): ≤5 times upper limit of normal (ULN)

               -  Bilirubin: ≤3xULN (3×1.1 mg/dL)

               -  Leukocytes: ≥3x109/L, and neutrophils: ≥1x109/L

               -  Erythrocytes: ≥3.5x1012/L

               -  Platelets: ≥90x109/L

          -  Signed written informed consent prior to any study-related procedures.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Subject with resected primary tumour

          -  Subjects with confirmed ductal carcinoma in situ

          -  Men with breast cancer

          -  Presence of an active infection at screening or history of a serious infection within
             the previous 6 weeks prior to the first 68Ga-OPS202 administration that might
             interfere with the PET and/or CT analysis

          -  Subjects who have received any therapy for breast cancer

          -  Prior or planned administration of a radiopharmaceutical within 8 half-lives of the
             radionuclide

          -  Clinically relevant trauma within 2 weeks prior to first 68Ga-OPS202 administration

          -  Any condition that precludes the proper performance of PET and/or CT scan:

               -  Subjects who are not able to tolerate the CT contrast agent

               -  Subjects with metal implants or arthroplasty, or any other objects that might
                  interfere with the PET and/or CT analysis

               -  Subjects unable to raise arms for prolonged imaging purposes

               -  Subjects unable to lie still for the entire imaging time

               -  Subjects weighing greater than 110 kg (243 lb)

          -  Known hypersensitivity to radiolabelled NODAGA (1,4,7- triazacyclononane,1-glutaric
             acid 4,7 acetic acid), to Gallium-68, to somatostatin analogue peptide JR11 or to any
             of the excipients of 68Ga- OPS202

          -  History of, or current active allergic or autoimmune disease, including asthma or any
             condition requiring long-term use of systemic corticosteroids

          -  Known human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) or positive serology for HIV, hepatitis B or
             C

          -  Administration of another investigational medicinal product within 30 days prior to
             first 68Ga-OPS202 administration

          -  Subjects who are pregnant, breast feeding or of childbearing potential not willing to
             practice effective contraceptive techniques during the study treatment period and for
             30 days after the last dose of 68Ga-OPS202 administration; pregnancy test must be
             performed at the start of the study and prior to 68Ga-OPS202 administration

          -  Subjects who have any severe and/or uncontrolled medical conditions or other
             conditions that could affect their participation in the study, including any mental
             condition rendering the subject unable to understand the nature, scope, and possible
             consequences of the study, and/or evidence of an uncooperative attitude

          -  Subject who experienced a previous cancer (except basocellular carcinoma of the skin
             and/or in situ carcinoma of the cervix/uterus), and/or subjects treated with curative
             intent and free from disease for more than 5 years
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ipsen Medical Director</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Ipsen</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Medical University Innsbruck</name>
      <address>
        <city>Innsbruck</city>
        <zip>A-6020</zip>
        <country>Austria</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Austria</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 12, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 3, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 5, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 24, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 24, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 28, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <pending_results>
    <submitted>July 17, 2020</submitted>
  </pending_results>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

