<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03699826</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>201808852</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03699826</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Experimental Tinnitus Treatment With Transcranial Magnetic Stimulation</brief_title>
  <official_title>Experimental Tinnitus Treatment With Transcranial Magnetic Stimulation</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Aaron Boes</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Iowa</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      There are numerous conditions that may benefit from TMS but they lack definitive data from
      clinical trials with sufficient scientific rigor, which includes large, multi-site,
      randomized sham-controlled trials. This is the status for a variety of psychiatric and
      neurological disorders such as tinnitus, central pain, movement disorders, stroke
      rehabilitation, obsessive compulsive disorders, anxiety, schizophrenia, and addiction. In
      certain instances there may be sufficient evidence supporting the treatment efficacy of TMS
      that it is reasonable to offer TMS as an off-label treatment, a term for clinical treatments
      that have not received FDA approval but may nonetheless be helpful for patients. In other
      cases there is such a paucity of clinical trial data that the use of therapeutic TMS is less
      appropriate as a clinical treatment that the patient is charged for out of pocket and may
      cost several thousand dollars, but is better suited for clinically-oriented research. This
      has the added benefit of potentially helping the patient and providing investigators with
      additional information from which to inform future clinical trials. In this study the
      investigators propose to use TMS to treat tinnitus, for which few other treatments currently
      exist. Tinnitus affects approximately 1% of the population and can be debilitating for
      patients. Recent studies have shown some promise in reducing symptoms through
      neuromodulation, but results are variable and more research is needed to improve treatment
      protocols. The investigators plan to contribute to this body of research by taking an
      evidence-based approach to test whether TMS is effective at reducing symptoms of tinnitus.
      Each subject's MRI will be used to perform neuronavigated TMS stimulations while documenting
      changes in symptom severity with self-report questionnaires and symptom severity scales. If
      it is determined that a stimulation protocol is effective, 1-2 weeks of daily treatments will
      be scheduled as part of that subject's personalized treatment plan.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      1. Consent patients that have been referred to the Noninvasive Brain Stimulation Clinic at
           the University of Iowa.

        2. Patients will complete the following before any treatments occur: Tinnitus Intake
           Questionnaire, Tinnitus Functional Index, Tinnitus Questionnaires, Iowa Tinnitus Primary
           Function, Clinical Global Improvement Scale.

        3. Patients may undergo audiological assessment if they have not already been tested prior
           to the study.

        4. Patients will be required to obtain an MRI prior to treatment to aid in neuronavigated
           stimulation unless there is have access to a previous clinical MRI for this purpose.

        5. MRI images will be loaded into BrainSight or Localite, which are both frameless
           stereotactic systems for MRI-guided TMS localization. If no MRI is acquired, the
           subject's head will be transformed to MNI standard space within the software.
           Neuronavigation allows us to place specific stimulation targets onto each subjects's
           MRI. For this study, the investigators will be targeting left dorsolateral prefrontal
           cortex, auditory cortices, and auditory association cortices; all targets are placed
           anatomically by a neurologist. Infrared trackers on the subject's head and TMS coil
           allow for neuronavigated stimulation of anatomical targets on the cortex with millimeter
           precision.

        6. The motor threshold of the subject will be assessed, which is the intensity of TMS
           required to elicit motor evoked potentials from the hand 50% of the time.

        7. Subjects will be fitted with an EEG cap to record neural activity before, during, and
           after the initial test session.

        8. Single TMS pulses or brief trains of repetitive TMS lasting a few seconds will be
           administered at 80 - 120% of motor threshold to targeted regions of the cerebral cortex
           and cerebellum. A typical experiment will last 30 minutes to 2 hours. The patients are
           told they can stop the experiment at any time.

        9. After each stimulation, patients will be asked to rate any changes in symptom severity
           and whether any side effects were experienced (Tinnitus Questionnaires, Clinical Global
           Improvement Scale).

       10. After the treatment session, the TMS pulse locations will be related to changes in
           symptom severity as measured by self-report. If any stimulation treatments were
           successful in reducing symptom severity, a treatment plan for that target will be
           discussed and follow-up treatments may be scheduled.

       11. Follow up treatments will vary between patients but will typically consist of daily
           treatments for up to 4 weeks or until treatment response is sustained. The patient can
           withdraw from follow treatments at any time. Patients will be asked to complete the
           following at these visits: Tinnitus Functional Index, Tinnitus Questionnaires, Iowa
           Tinnitus Primary Function, Clinical Global Improvement Scale.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Enrolling by invitation</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">December 10, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical Improvement</measure>
    <time_frame>2 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Clinical Global Improvement Scale (0-7 scale where 0=not assessed, 1=Very much improved, and 7= Very much worse</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">4</enrollment>
  <condition>Tinnitus</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>TMS</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>TMS for tinnitus</intervention_name>
    <description>Targeted stimulation to decrease tinnitus symptom severity.</description>
    <arm_group_label>TMS</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  tinnitus diagnosis

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  have epilepsy or a family history of epilepsy

          -  have implanted metal in or near their head

          -  have any history of brain injury or stroke

          -  have a tinnitus handicap inventory score of &lt;38 (less than moderate handicap)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Aaron D Boes, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Iowa</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Iowa</name>
      <address>
        <city>Iowa City</city>
        <state>Iowa</state>
        <zip>52242</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 5, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 5, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 9, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 11, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 11, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">September 13, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Iowa</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Aaron Boes</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>transcranial magnetic stimulation</keyword>
  <keyword>neuromodulation</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Tinnitus</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

