<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04029155</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>UTB2019</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04029155</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Conventional vs Ultrathin Bronchoscopy for Peripheral Pulmonary Lesions</brief_title>
  <official_title>Conventional vs Ultrathin Bronchoscopy With Transbronchial Needle Aspiration for the Diagnosis of Peripheral Pulmonary Lesions: a Randomized Controlled Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Stefano Gasparini</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Università Politecnica delle Marche</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study's purpose is to evaluate whether the use of an ultra-thin bronchoscope can improve
      sensitivity and diagnostic yield in peripheral pulmonary nodules. The ultra-thin probe is
      expected to reach further bronchi and allow to reach peripheral lesions. Moreover, the
      ability to identify molecular pattern of lung cancer is essential nowadays, and it will be
      therefore evaluated.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      142 patients with at least one peripheral pulmonary nodule will be enrolled. They will
      underwent randomization in 2 arms: patients in the first arm will undergo transbronchial
      needle aspiration with a conventional bronchoscope patients in the second arm will undergo
      transbronchial needle aspiration with a ultra-thin bronchoscope. Every bronchoscopy will be
      performed by the same operator and will contemplate 3 passes for each nodule, followed by
      Rapid On-Site Evaluation (ROSE) assessed by a dedicated cytologist. If the cytological
      on-site evaluation is negative in patients in the first arm, they will be shifted to the
      second arm. Histological and molecular diagnosis will be assessed by a dedicated pathologist.
      Data will be collected and analyzed.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">August 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 1, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 1, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Assess if sensitivity is higher in the &quot;ultrathin&quot; arm than in the &quot;conventional&quot; arm</measure>
    <time_frame>through study completion, an average of 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>percentage</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assess if diagnostic yield is higher in the &quot;ultrathin&quot; arm than in the &quot;conventional&quot; arm</measure>
    <time_frame>through study completion, an average of 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>percentage</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Assess if sensitivity is similar in both arms</measure>
    <time_frame>through study completion, an average of 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>percentage</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">142</enrollment>
  <condition>Lung Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>TBNA with Conventional bronchoscope</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>patients in this arm will undergo bronchoscopy by a conventional probe</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>TBNA with a Ultrathin bronchoscope</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients in this arm will undergo bronchoscopy by a ultra thin probe</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Lung biopsy</intervention_name>
    <description>Transbronchial Needle Aspiration performed via a ultra thin bronchoscope</description>
    <arm_group_label>TBNA with Conventional bronchoscope</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>TBNA with a Ultrathin bronchoscope</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  age ≥ 18years;

          -  presence of at least one peripheral pulmonary lesion ≤ 3 cm on CT scan;

          -  ability to give an informed consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  coagulopathy or bleeding diathesis that cannot be corrected;

          -  severe refractory hypoxemia;

          -  unstable hemodynamic status;

          -  inability to give an informed consent.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Stefano Gasparini, Professor</last_name>
    <phone>071-5964352</phone>
    <email>s.gasparini@univpm.it</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Martina Bonifazi, Professor</last_name>
    <phone>071-5965538</phone>
    <email>m.bonifazi@staff.univpm.it</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <reference>
    <citation>Haponik EF, Shure D. Underutilization of transbronchial needle aspiration: experiences of current pulmonary fellows. Chest. 1997 Jul;112(1):251-3.</citation>
    <PMID>9228384</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Harrow EM, Abi-Saleh W, Blum J, Harkin T, Gasparini S, Addrizzo-Harris DJ, Arroliga AC, Wight G, Mehta AC. The utility of transbronchial needle aspiration in the staging of bronchogenic carcinoma. Am J Respir Crit Care Med. 2000 Feb;161(2 Pt 1):601-7.</citation>
    <PMID>10673206</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gasparini S, Silvestri GA. Usefulness of transbronchial needle aspiration in evaluating patients with lung cancer. Thorax. 2005 Nov;60(11):890-1.</citation>
    <PMID>16263944</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Patelli M, Lazzari Agli L, Poletti V, Trisolini R, Cancellieri A, Lacava N, Falcone F, Boaron M. Role of fiberscopic transbronchial needle aspiration in the staging of N2 disease due to non-small cell lung cancer. Ann Thorac Surg. 2002 Feb;73(2):407-11.</citation>
    <PMID>11845850</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Trisolini R, Tinelli C, Cancellieri A, Paioli D, Alifano M, Boaron M, Patelli M. Transbronchial needle aspiration in sarcoidosis: yield and predictors of a positive aspirate. J Thorac Cardiovasc Surg. 2008 Apr;135(4):837-42. doi: 10.1016/j.jtcvs.2007.11.011.</citation>
    <PMID>18374764</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Iyoda A, Baba M, Shibuya K, Moriya Y, Yasufuku K, Sekine Y, Iizasa T, Hiroshima K, Nakatani Y, Fujisawa T. Transbronchial fine needle aspiration cytological examination: a useful tool for diagnosing primary lung cancer. Thorac Cardiovasc Surg. 2006 Mar;54(2):117-9.</citation>
    <PMID>16541353</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Roth K, Hardie JA, Andreassen AH, Leh F, Eagan TM. Predictors of diagnostic yield in bronchoscopy: a retrospective cohort study comparing different combinations of sampling techniques. BMC Pulm Med. 2008 Jan 26;8:2. doi: 10.1186/1471-2466-8-2.</citation>
    <PMID>18221551</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mondoni M, Sotgiu G, Bonifazi M, Dore S, Parazzini EM, Carlucci P, Gasparini S, Centanni S. Transbronchial needle aspiration in peripheral pulmonary lesions: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Eur Respir J. 2016 Jul;48(1):196-204. doi: 10.1183/13993003.00051-2016. Epub 2016 May 12. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>27174878</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Oki M, Saka H, Ando M, Asano F, Kurimoto N, Morita K, Kitagawa C, Kogure Y, Miyazawa T. Ultrathin Bronchoscopy with Multimodal Devices for Peripheral Pulmonary Lesions. A Randomized Trial. Am J Respir Crit Care Med. 2015 Aug 15;192(4):468-76. doi: 10.1164/rccm.201502-0205OC.</citation>
    <PMID>26039792</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gasparini S. It is time for this 'ROSE' to flower. Respiration. 2005 Mar-Apr;72(2):129-31.</citation>
    <PMID>15824520</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gasparini S, Zuccatosta L, De Nictolis M. Transbronchial needle aspiration of mediastinal lesions. Monaldi Arch Chest Dis. 2000 Feb;55(1):29-32.</citation>
    <PMID>10786422</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gasparini S. GPS may help drivers reach their destination, but the capability to drive a car is still necessary. Traditional and technology-guided transbronchial needle aspiration. Respiration. 2007;74(4):379-81.</citation>
    <PMID>17641483</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gasparini S. Evolving role of interventional pulmonology in the interdisciplinary approach to the staging and management of lung cancer: bronchoscopic mediastinal staging of lung cancer. Clin Lung Cancer. 2006 Sep;8(2):110-5. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>17026811</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>July 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 18, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 22, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 23, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 22, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 22, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 23, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Università Politecnica delle Marche</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Stefano Gasparini</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>peripheral pulmonary nodules</keyword>
  <keyword>ultrathin bronchoscope</keyword>
  <keyword>transbronchial needle aspiration</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

