<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04025931</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>SunYat-senU-chidamide</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04025931</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Single-arm, Open, Phase II Study of Chidamide Combined With Toripalimab in Refractory and Advanced Soft-tissue Sarcoma</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Single-arm, Open, Phase II Study of Chidamide Combined With Toripalimab in Refractory and Advanced Soft-tissue Sarcoma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Sun Yat-sen University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Sun Yat-sen University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Soft tissue sarcoma is a relatively rare malignant tumor with an incidence of about
      1-2/100,000. The best way to obtain evidence-based medical evidence is to participate in
      clinical trials with new drugs (especially targeted drugs and immunotherapy). Chidamide, an
      oral subtype-selective histone deacetylase inhibitor monotherapy was effective on the
      patients with hematological tumors by inhibiting HDAC activity and other ways, showing good
      anti-tumor activity. Histone deacetylase inhibitors (HDACi) may also reverse drug resistance
      or inefficiency of immunoassay inhibitors, and combination therapy has shown preliminary
      efficacy in a variety of tumors.Because of the poor prognosis of advanced soft tissue
      sarcoma, there is no standard second-line treatment. Therefore, we think it is necessary to
      explore the feasibility of combination of chidamide and Toripalimab monoclonal antibody in
      advanced, refractory and progressive soft tissue sarcoma after failure of standard treatment,
      and look forward to further improving the efficacy of soft tissue sarcoma.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Histone deacetylase inhibitor (HDACI) can inhibit many kinds of hematological tumors by
      inhibiting HDAC activity and other ways, showing good anti-tumor activity. Chidamide is a new
      chemical structure benzamide HDAC inhibitor developed independently in China. It has the
      selectivity of HDAC subtypes and unique efficacy. In a phase II clinical study of Chidamide
      in the treatment of peripheral T-cell lymphoma in China in 2009, 79 patients with recurrent
      or refractory lymphoma had ORR of 27.9%. The 2016 edition of the Chinese Expert Consensus on
      Chidamide in the Treatment of PTCL discussed in detail the treatment of Chidamide alone or in
      combination with other drugs.

      The representative drug of immunological checkpoint inhibitors is programmed death 1
      (PD-1/PD-L1). PD-1/PD-L1 immunotherapy activates the body's own immune system to attack
      cancer cells by blocking the PD-1/PD-L1 pathway with drugs. Immunotherapy show its long-term
      control of cancer and its effectiveness in a variety of cancers.

      In a multicenter phase II clinical trial, 80 patients with bone and soft tissue sarcoma were
      treated with single drug of PD-1 antibody Pembrolizumab. The results showed that all the
      patients with soft tissue sarcoma achieved therapeutic effect were undifferentiated
      pleomorphic sarcoma and liposarcoma. The overall objective remission rate was 18% (7/40),
      suggesting that Pembrolizumab alone does not fully activate suppressed T cells, and may need
      to be combined to improve the efficacy.

      Recent studies have shown that combination of epigenetic regulators, such as histone
      deacetylase inhibitors (HDACi), can overcome some major drug resistance constraints and
      ensure patient safety. Pre-clinical data based on mouse models strongly support the
      feasibility and effectiveness of combination therapy. In vitro and in vivo studies, combined
      use of pan- or class I selective HDACi can benefit further. Chidamide is mainly targeted at
      subtypes 1, 2, 3 and 10 of HDAC class I and class II B. It has a regulatory effect on the
      abnormal epigenetic function of tumors. By inhibiting the related HDAC subtypes to increase
      the acetylation level of chromatin histone, chromatin remodeling is initiated, which changes
      the gene expression of multiple signal transduction pathways (i.e. epigenetic changes),
      thereby inhibiting the cell cycle of tumors, inducing apoptosis of tumors, and having overall
      regulatory activity on cellular immunity. Induction and enhancement of natural killer cells
      (NK) and antigen-specific cytotoxic T cells (CTL) mediated tumor killing. Chidamide can also
      enhance the mechanism of dendritic cells presenting and maturing tumor antigens, inhibiting
      regulatory T cells (Treg) and MDSC cells, and promote the anti-tumor immune function through
      regulating the micro-environment of tumor immunosuppression.

      Because of the poor prognosis of advanced soft tissue sarcoma, there is no standard treatment
      for second-line treatment. Therefore, we think it is necessary to explore the feasibility of
      combination of chidamide and Toripalimab in advanced, refractory and progressive soft tissue
      sarcoma after failure of standard treatment, and look forward to further improving the
      efficacy of soft tissue sarcoma.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">December 25, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 15, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 1, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Objective Response Rate</measure>
    <time_frame>each 42 days up to intolerance the toxicity or PD (up to 24 months)</time_frame>
    <description>Objective response rate is defined as the percentage of subjects with evidence of a confirmed complete response (CR) or partial response (PR) as per Response Evaluation Criteria In Solid Tumors (RECIST) Version 1.1.prior to progression or any further therapy.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progress free survival</measure>
    <time_frame>until Progressive Disease(PD) or death(up to 24 months)</time_frame>
    <description>Progress free survival defined as the time from first dose of study treatment until the first date of either objective disease progression or death due to any cause.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall Survival</measure>
    <time_frame>From randomization until death (up to 24 months)</time_frame>
    <description>Overall survival is defined as the time until death due to any cause.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Disease Control Rate</measure>
    <time_frame>each 42 days up to intolerance the toxicity or PD (up to 24 months)</time_frame>
    <description>Defined as the proportion of patients with a documented complete response, partial response, and stable disease (CR + PR + SD) based on RECIST 1.1.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">53</enrollment>
  <condition>Sarcoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>chidamide combined with Toripalimab</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>chidamide 30mg orally twice a week;
240 mg of toripalimab (fixed dose) every three weeks.
Repeat every three weeks. Patients with disease control (CR + PR + SD) and tolerable adverse reactions continued to take medication until the researchers concluded that patients were not suitable to continue medication or the efficacy evaluation was disease progression (PD). No other antineoplastic treatment can be given during the treatment.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>chidamide and toripalimab</intervention_name>
    <description>The eligible patients with advanced soft tissue sarcoma were treated with chidamide combined with toripalimb. Chidamide 30mg orally twice a week;
Toripalimab 240 mg (fixed dose) every three weeks.
Repeat every three weeks. Patients with disease control (CR + PR + SD) and tolerable adverse reactions continued to take medication until the researchers concluded that patients were not suitable to continue medication or the efficacy evaluation was disease progression (PD). No other antineoplastic treatment can be given during the treatment.</description>
    <arm_group_label>chidamide combined with Toripalimab</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients voluntarily participated in this study and signed the informed consent;

          2. The pathology diagnosed with at least one measurable lesion according to RECIST 1.1
             standard. The pathology includes synovial sarcoma, leiomyosarcoma, angiosarcoma,
             undifferentiated pleomorphic sarcoma/malignant fibrous histiocytoma, liposarcoma,
             fibrosarcoma, clear cell sarcoma, epithelioid sarcoma, malignant peripheral nerve
             sheath tumor, undifferentiated sarcoma, rhabdomyosarcoma, dermatofibrosareoma
             promberans, ewing's sarcoma /primary neural ectoderm tumors, desmoplastic small round
             cell tumor, inflammatory myofibroblastic sarcoma, malignant solitary fibroma. Except
             for chondrosarcoma, osteosarcoma, malignant mesothelioma, alveolar soft tissue
             sarcoma, gastrointestinal stromal tumor;

          3. Advanced sarcoma patients with refractory or distant metastasis after failure of
             first-line standard therapy;

          4. 18 ~ 70 years old; ECOG PS score: 0~1; Expected survival beyond 3 months; 5．Adequate
             organ and bone marrow function, no serious hematopoietic dysfunction or heart, lung,
             liver, kidney, thyroid dysfunction and immune deficiency (no blood transfusion,
             granulocyte colony stimulating factor or other medical support was received within 14
             days before the use of the research drug):

        6. Major organs functions should meet the following standards within 7 days before
        treatment:

        Blood routine examination standard (without blood transfusion within 14 days) :

        Hemoglobin (HB) ≥90g/L; The absolute value of neutrophils (ANC) ≥1.5×109/L; Platelet (PLT)
        ≥80 ×109/L.

        Biochemical examination shall meet the following standards:

        Total bilirubin (TBIL) ≤ 1.5 times ULN (Upper Limit Of Normal); alanine aminotransferase
        （ALT）and aspartate aminotransferase AST≤2.5 times ULN. If accompanied by liver metastasis,
        ALT and AST≤5 times ULN；Serum creatinine（Cr）≤1.5 times ULN or creatinine clearance rate
        (CCr)≥ 60ml/min； Doppler ultrasound evaluation: left ventricular ejection fraction (LVEF) ≥
        normal low limit (50%).

        7. Thyrotropin (TSH) or free thyroxine (FT4) or free triiodothyronine (FT3) were all within
        the normal range (+10%).

        8. Women of reproductive age should agree to use contraceptives (such as intrauterine
        devices, contraceptives or condoms) during and within 6 months after the study; Negative
        serum or urine pregnancy test within 7 days prior to study enrollment and must be
        non-lactating; 9. Men should agree to use contraceptives during and within 6 months after
        the study period.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients who have previously used chidamide or other histone deacetylase inhibitors;

          2. Previous treatment with immunological checkpoint inhibitors (PD-1, PD-L1, CTLA-4,
             etc.);

          3. Other malignancies that have occurred or are present at the same time within 5 years,
             except for cured cancers including carcinoma in situ of the cervix, non-melanoma skin
             cancer and superficial bladder tumor [Ta (non-invasive tumor), Tis (carcinoma in situ)
             and T1 (tumor infiltrating basement membrane)];

          4. Start the study of systemic anti-cancer therapy within 28 days before treatment,
             including chemotherapy, immunotherapy, biotherapy (cancer vaccine, cytokines, or
             growth factors that control cancer).

          5. The patients received Chinese herbal medicine or Chinese patent medicine treatment
             within 7 days before the start of the study.

          6. Systemic anti-tumor therapy, including cytotoxic therapy, signal transduction
             inhibitors, and immunotherapy (or mitomycin C administration within 6 weeks before the
             treatment with the experimental drug), is planned within 4 weeks before enrollment or
             during the medication period of this study. In the first 4 weeks of enrollment, the
             patients were treated with field expanding radiotherapy (ef-rt) or the limited field
             radiotherapy designed to evaluate tumor lesions in the first 2 weeks of enrollment.

          7. Accompanied by pleural effusion or ascites, causing respiratory syndrome (CTCAE grade
             2 dyspnea [grade 2 dyspnea refers to shortness of breath when there is a small amount
             of activity; it affects instrumental daily life activities]);

          8. Unrelieved toxic reactions caused by any previous treatment higher than CTCAE (4.1)
             level 1 or above, excluding hair loss;

          9. Patients with brain metastases with symptoms or with symptoms for less than 2 months;

         10. Patients with any severe and/or uncontrolled disease, including:

        1)Patients with unsatisfactory blood pressure control (systolic blood pressure 150 mmHg,
        diastolic blood pressure 100 mmHg); 2)Patients with grade I or above myocardial ischemia or
        myocardial infarction, arrhythmia (including QTC 480ms) and grade II congestive heart
        failure (NYHA classification); 3)Active or uncontrolled severe infection (CTCAE grade 2
        infection); 4)Cirrhosis, decompensated liver disease, active hepatitis or chronic hepatitis
        require antiviral treatment; 5) Renal failure requires hemodialysis or peritoneal dialysis;
        6) Have a history of immunodeficiency, including HIV positive or other acquired or
        congenital immunodeficiency diseases, or have a history of organ transplantation; 7)Poor
        control of diabetes mellitus (FBG) &gt; 10mmol/L); 8)Urine routine test indicated urine
        protein ++, and confirmed the 24-hour urine protein quantitative &gt; 1.0g; 9)Patients with
        seizures requiring treatment;

        11. Received major surgical treatment, open biopsy or obvious traumatic injury within 28
        days before enrollment;

        12. Patients with any signs of bleeding constitution or medical history, regardless of the
        severity; Patients with any bleeding or bleeding event CTCAE level 3 within 4 weeks before
        enrollment have unhealed wounds, ulcers or fractures;

        13. Hyperactive/venous thrombosis events within 6 months, such as cerebrovascular accidents
        (including temporary ischemic attack), deep venous thrombosis and pulmonary embolism;

        14. Patients with active ulcer, intestinal perforation and intestinal obstruction;

        15. Have a history of mental drug abuse and cannot quit or have mental disorder;

        16. Participated in clinical trials of other anti-tumor drugs within 28 days before
        enrollment;

        17.According to the judgment of the researcher, there are those who seriously endanger the
        safety of patients or affect the patients' completion of the study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Xing Zhang, professor</last_name>
    <phone>020-87343383</phone>
    <email>zhangxing@sysucc.org.cn</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sun Yat-Sen Univerisity</name>
      <address>
        <city>Guangzhou</city>
        <state>Guangdong</state>
        <zip>510000</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Xing Zhang, PhD,MD</last_name>
      <phone>86-020-87343192</phone>
      <email>zhangxing@sysucc.org.cn</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Xing Zhang</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 17, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 17, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 19, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 24, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 24, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">December 27, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Sun Yat-sen University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Xing Zhang</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Vice director of department of medical sarcoma and melanoma,Principal Investigator,Clinical Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Sarcoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

