<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04021563</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>SR419-101</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04021563</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Safety, Tolerability, Pharmacokinetics(PK) of SR419 in Healthy Volunteers</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase I Study to Evaluate the Safety, Tolerability, Pharmacokinetics of SR419 in Healthy Volunteers</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>SIMR (Australia) Biotech Pty Ltd</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Syneos Health</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>SIMR (Australia) Biotech Pty Ltd</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study is to evaluate the safety, tolerability, PK of SR419 in healthy volunteers.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a Phase I study to evaluate the safety, tolerability, PK of SR419 in healthy
      volunteers. The study will include 3 parts.

      Part A is a double-blind, randomized, placebo-controlled, single-dose escalation study of
      SR419 in healthy young subjects.

      Part B is a double-blind, randomized, placebo-controlled, repeated-dose escalation study of
      SR419 in healthy young subjects.

      Part C is a double-blind, randomized, placebo-controlled, repeated dose study of SR419 in
      healthy elderly subjects.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 26, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 10, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 10, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Sequential Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The frequency and severity of AEs in healthy volunteers adminstrated with single and repeated oral doses of SR419</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Day14 for the safety follow up since Day1</time_frame>
    <description>AE: adverse event</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Heart rate changes since baseline (categorized as normal; abnormal, not clinically significant; and abnormal, clinically significant)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Day14 for the safety follow up since Day1</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>PR interval changes since baseline (categorized as normal; abnormal, not clinically significant; and abnormal, clinically significant)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Day14 for the safety follow up since Day1</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>QRS duration changes since baseline (categorized as normal; abnormal, not clinically significant; and abnormal, clinically significant)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Day14 for the safety follow up since Day1</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>QT interval changes since baseline (categorized as normal; abnormal, not clinically significant; and abnormal, clinically significant)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Day14 for the safety follow up since Day1</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>QTcF changes since baseline (categorized as normal; abnormal, not clinically significant; and abnormal, clinically significant)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Day14 for the safety follow up since Day1</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Systolic blood pressure changes since baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Day14 for the safety follow up since Day1</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Diastolic blood pressure changes since baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Day14 for the safety follow up since Day1</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pulse rate changes since baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Day14 for the safety follow up since Day1</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Respiratory rate changes since baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Day14 for the safety follow up since Day1</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Oral temperature changes since baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Day14 for the safety follow up since Day1</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cmax</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Day 9</time_frame>
    <description>Peak plasma concentration</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Tmax</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Day 9</time_frame>
    <description>Time of peak plasma concentration</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>AUC</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Day 9</time_frame>
    <description>Area under the plasma concentration-time curve</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>CL/F</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Day 9</time_frame>
    <description>Apparent total clearance</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>t1/2</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Day 9</time_frame>
    <description>Terminal half-life</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>R0</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Day 9</time_frame>
    <description>Accumulation ratio</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Ae</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Day 9</time_frame>
    <description>The amount of drug excreted unchanged in the urine</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>CLr</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Day 9</time_frame>
    <description>Renal clearance</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">64</enrollment>
  <condition>Healthy Volunteers</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>SR419</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Ascending single and multiple doses of SR419 orally</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Ascending single and multiple doses of placebo orally</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>SR419</intervention_name>
    <description>Ascending single and multiple doses of SR419 orally</description>
    <arm_group_label>SR419</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Ascending single and multiple doses of placebo orally</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Healthy males and females who are 18 to 64 years of age inclusive are eligible for
             Parts A and B.

          2. Healthy males and females who are 65 to 80 years of age inclusive, defined as elderly
             subjects in this study, are eligible for Part C only.

          3. Average of triplicate QTcF values must be &lt; 450 msec for males and &lt; 470 msec for
             females at Screening and Day -1.

          4. Bodyweight &gt; 50 kg (110 pounds) and body mass index (BMI) between 18 and 30 kg/m2

          5. The participants must agree to use contraception methods (outlined in Appendix 1)

          6. Capable of giving written informed consent, which includes compliance with the
             requirements and restrictions listed in the consent form.

          7. Male subjects must agree to use contraception methods (outlined in Appendix 1) if they
             have a female partner of childbearing potential and must agree not to donate sperm.
             This criterion must be followed from the time of the first dose of investigational
             medicinal product (IMP) until at least 90 days after the last dose of IMP. This
             requirement does not apply to subjects in a same-sex relationship and female partners
             of non-childbearing potential.

          8. A female subject is eligible to participate if she is:

             a. of non-childbearing potential, defined as: i. Pre- menopausal females with a
             documented tubal ligation, tubal occlusion procedure followed by a hysterosalpingogram
             that confirmed bilateral tubal occlusion, bilateral salpingectomy, hysterectomy or
             other documented medical conditions which cause infertility and are considered to be
             of non-childbearing potential; ii. Postmenopausal defined as 12 months of spontaneous
             amenorrhea (in questionable cases a blood sample with follicle stimulating hormone
             [FSH] &gt;40 mIU/mL is confirmatory). b. of childbearing potential, and one of the
             following applies: i. Is willing to practice true abstinent from the time of consent
             until at least 30 days after the last dose of IMP or 5× half-lives of the IMP,
             whichever is longer; ii. Agrees to comply with the protocol defined contraception
             requirements outlined in Appendix 1 from at least 1 month before her first dose of
             IMP, and until at least 30 days after her last dose of IMP or 5× half-lives of the
             IMP, whichever is longer.

          9. Capable of giving written informed consent, which includes compliance with the
             requirements and restrictions listed in the consent form.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Clinically significant history of central nervous system (CNS) disease, such as
             cognitive disorder and seizures. History of non-clinically significant mild anxiety
             (related to social stressors) or situational sleep disturbance &gt; 6 months ago could be
             enrolled under the discretion of the Investigators.

          2. Known history of renal dysfunction or creatinine clearance &lt; 90 mL/min or ≥ 150 mL/min
             (calculated using the Cockcroft-Gault formula) at Screening.

          3. Current or chronic history of liver disease or known hepatic or biliary abnormalities
             (with the exception of Gilbert's syndrome [indirect bilirubin &lt; 5 mg/dL with no other
             clinically significant abnormalities seen] or asymptomatic gallstones).

          4. History of regular alcohol consumption within 6 months of screening defined as: an
             average weekly intake of &gt;21 units for males or &gt;14 units for females. One unit is
             equivalent to 8 g of alcohol: a half-pint (~285 mL) of beer, 1 glass (125 mL) of wine
             or 1 measure (25 mL) of spirits.

          5. History of significant drug abuse within one year of screening or use of soft drugs
             (such as marijuana) within 3 months prior to screening or hard drugs (such as cocaine,
             methamphetamine, crack) within 1 year prior to screening.

          6. History of sensitivity to any of the IMPs, or components thereof or a history of drug
             or other allergy that, in the opinion of the Investigator or Medical Monitor,
             contraindicates participation.

          7. History of asthma (excluding resolved childhood asthma), anaphylaxis or anaphylactoid
             reactions, severe allergic responses.

          8. History of hypercoagulable state or history of thrombosis.

          9. A history of biliary tract disease including a history of liver disease with elevated
             liver function tests of known or unknown etiology (with the exception of Gilbert's
             syndrome).

         10. A positive pre-study Hepatitis B surface antigen or positive Hepatitis C antibody
             result within 3 months of screening.

         11. Use of tobacco- or nicotine-containing products:

               1. Parts A and B: positive urinary cotinine test at Screening or Day -1 or history
                  of regular use of tobacco- or nicotine-containing products (more than 4 products
                  per month within 6 months prior to screening) or unwilling to refrain from use of
                  such products from Screening until completion of the final study visit;

               2. Part C: positive urinary cotinine test at Screening or Day -1 or history of
                  regular use of tobacco- or nicotine-containing products (more than 4 products per
                  month within 6 months prior to screening) or unwilling to give up these products
                  from Screening until discharge from the study unit.

         12. A positive pre-study drug/alcohol result at Screening or Day -1.

         13. A positive test for human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) antibody.

         14. Donation or lost in excess of 500 mL of blood within 56 days of Day 1 or donation of
             plasma within 14 days of Day 1.

         15. The subject has participated in a clinical trial and has received an investigational
             product within the following time period prior to the first dosing day in the current
             study: 30 days, 5 half-lives or twice the duration of the biological effect of the
             investigational product (whichever is longer).

         16. Exposure to more than four new chemical entities within 12 months prior to the first
             dosing day.

         17. Use of medication other than topical products without significant systemic absorption:

               1. prescription within 14 days and over-the-counter (OTC) medications within 7 days,
                  or 5× half-lives (whichever is longer) prior to the first dose of IMP, with the
                  exception of the occasional use of paracetamol (up to 2 g daily)

               2. natural health products (e.g. food supplements and herbal supplements) within 7
                  days prior to the first dose of IMP;

               3. a depot injection or an implant of any drug within 3 months prior to the first
                  dose of IMP.

               4. vaccine within 1 month prior to the first dose of IMP.

         18. Unable to refrain from consumption of Seville oranges, grapefruit or grapefruit juice
             within 7 days prior to the first dose of IMP until the Safety Follow-up visit.

         19. A positive pre-study pregnancy test at Screening or Day -1.

         20. Breast-feeding and/or lactating subject.

         21. Any reason which, in the opinion of the Investigator, would prevent the subject from
             participating in the study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Dr.Hatchuel</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Linear Clinical Research</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Linear Clinical Research</name>
      <address>
        <city>Perth</city>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Australia</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 9, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 15, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 16, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 9, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 9, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 13, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

