<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04029779</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>02_D012_81520</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04029779</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluation of Immediately Placed Dental Implants With Local Application of Injectable PRF in Periodontally Compromised Sites</brief_title>
  <acronym>PRF</acronym>
  <official_title>Evaluation of Immediately Placed Dental Implants With Local Application of Injectable-Platelet Rich Fibrin in Periodontally Compromised Sites. A Randomized Controlled Split Mouth Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Krishnadevaraya College of Dental Sciences &amp; Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Krishnadevaraya College of Dental Sciences &amp; Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The present study is a human, prospective, parallel, randomised controlled clinical trial
      conducted to explore the efficacy of injectable PRF around dental implants. The trial is in
      accordance with the Consolidated Standards of Reporting Trials (CONSORT) criteria, 2010.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Ten healthy individuals satisfying the inclusion and exclusion criteria were recruited for
      the study. A detailed, thorough medical and dental history was obtained and each patient was
      subjected to comprehensive clinical and radiological examination. All patients were informed
      about the nature of the study, the surgical procedure involved, potential benefits and risks
      associated with the surgical procedure and written informed consent were obtained from all
      patients.

      All the patients were treated with immediate implants. The injectable -PRF was coated on
      implants as well as injected in the socket in both the maxillary and mandibular anterior
      region. The clinical and radiographic parameters were recorded at baseline, three months and
      six months postoperatively.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 11, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">November 30, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">November 30, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Two groups were made one test and control. All the subjects were treated with immediate implants. In the test group subjects, injectable platelet-rich fibrin was coated around dental implants and was also injected in the socket. The control group received only dental implants.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Crestal bone level</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Measured using CBCT scan both on mesial and distal sides .The coronal surface of the implant will be taken as reference line from where two perpendicular lines are dropped on both mesial and distal aspect of implants to first bone to implant contact.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Bone density</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>measured using CBCT scan using Hounsfield units at mid point of the implant both on mesial and distal side with coronal portion of implant as reference line.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Angular bleeding index</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>A periodontal probe passed along the buccal margin at 60 degrees angulation in gingival sulcus. The resultant bleeding is recorded as present (+) or absent (-).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Peri-implant Probing pocket depth</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>measured mesially and distally using a UNC-15 probe (university of North Carolina-15 periodontal probe- Hu-Friedy, Chicago, IL, USA).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pink esthetic score</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Digital photographs will be used for evaluation of the pink esthetic score(PES). Charts containing the seven variables will be designed. These include: mesial papilla, distal papilla, soft tissue level, soft tissue contour, alveolar process deficiency, soft tissue colour and texture. Each variable will be recorded with a 2-1-0 score, where 2 is the best and 0 is the poorest score.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">10</enrollment>
  <condition>Bone Density</condition>
  <condition>Bone Loss, Alveolar</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Immediate implant placement coated with I-PRF</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The test group received implants coated with injectable platelet-rich fibrin and also the sockets were injected with injectable- platelet rich fibrin</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>immediate implant only</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>The control group received immediate dental implants only after extraction of the teeth without any local coating.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>I-PRF</intervention_name>
    <description>Local anaesthesia was administered and mucoperiosteal flap was reflected. Atraumatic tooth extraction was performed. Socket was curetted to remove the granulation tissue present in the socket with the help of curettes. The socket was well irrigated with saline. Implant osteotomies wasl performed with sequential drilling with standardized drills.I-PRF was freshly prepared 600rpm for 7 min(50g). 1ml of the i-PRF was applied in to the osteotomy site and the implant surface will be thoroughly coated followed by placing of the implant. The surgical site was thoroughly irrigated and debrided. Flap closure was achieved using 3-0 silk sutures to protect the implant site.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Immediate implant placement coated with I-PRF</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>injectable platelet rich fibrin coated to dental implants.</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        1. Cooperative patients willing to participate in the study 2. At least two maxillary or
        mandibular anterior teeth indicated for extraction due to chronic periodontitis (chronic or
        aggressive) 3. Patients above 18 years of age 4. Patients with esthetic concerns 5.
        Patients with good oral hygiene maintenance 6. Adequate bone height apical to alveolus of
        the failing teeth (more than or equal to 5mm) to accommodate an implant

        -

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Persistent &amp; unresolved infection at implant site

          2. Teeth with close proximity to anatomical structure and adjacent roots

          3. Patients on radiotherapy

          4. Patients with systemic disorders

          5. Patients with parafunctional habits

          6. Patients with history of alcohol, drug dependency and smoking
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>55 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Krishnadevaraya college of dental sciences</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bangalore</city>
        <state>Karnataka</state>
        <zip>562157</zip>
        <country>India</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>India</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 19, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 22, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 23, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 11, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 11, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">December 12, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Injectable platelet rich fibrin</keyword>
  <keyword>Bone density</keyword>
  <keyword>Crestal bone loss</keyword>
  <keyword>Immediate implants</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Alveolar Bone Loss</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

