<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04029207</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ASOS-2 Maternal Mortality</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04029207</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The ASOS-2 Trial Maternal Mortality Sub-study</brief_title>
  <official_title>The African Surgical OutcomeS-2 (ASOS-2) Trial Maternal Mortality Sub-study. A Mixed-methods Analysis of a Prospective Case-series Describing Factors Contributing to Maternal Mortality Associated With Caesarean Delivery in Africa</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Cape Town</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Bill and Melinda Gates Foundation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Cape Town</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This sub-study is a mixed-methods analysis of a prospective case-series of maternal deaths
      within the African Surgical OutcomeS-2 trial cohort. The aims of the sub-study are i) to
      describe the contextual factors that contribute towards maternal deaths after caesarean
      delivery in Africa using a conceptual framework of &quot;transport-treatment-training&quot; and ii) to
      classify the maternal deaths in the ASOS-2 trial according to the WHO ICD-10 maternal
      mortality reporting standard. Data will be extracted from the ASOS-2 trial database. A
      sub-study case report form (CRF) and semi-structured telephonic interviews will be used to
      gather additional information from clinicians who were experienced a maternal death during
      the trial.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This sub-study is a mixed-methods analysis of a prospective case-series of maternal deaths
      within the African Surgical OutcomeS-2 trial cohort. The aims of the sub-study are i) to
      describe the contextual factors that contribute towards maternal deaths after caesarean
      delivery in Africa using a conceptual framework of &quot;transport-treatment-training&quot; and ii) to
      classify the maternal deaths in the ASOS-2 trial according to the WHO ICD-10 maternal
      mortality reporting standard. Data will be extracted from the ASOS-2 trial database. When a
      maternal death is captured on the trial database, the data manager will flag the event. The
      hospital that registered the death will be contacted and invited to take part in the
      sub-study. A sub-study case report form (CRF) and semi-structured telephonic interviews will
      be used to gather additional information from clinicians who were experienced a maternal
      death during the trial.

      This study uses 2 a priori frameworks for describing maternal deaths:

      i) The &quot;transport-treatment-training&quot; framework developed by Dr Andrew Shennan (personal
      communication). This framework suggests that the important determinants (modifiable
      contextual factors) of maternal mortality can be classified as being related to transport,
      treatment and training factors.

        -  Transport refers to the manner in which the patient accesses existing care. This
           includes decision to seek help, modes of transportation to the hospital, and
           inter-facility transportation. We consider the healthcare access network in this
           category.

        -  Treatment refers to the manner in which the case was managed at the healthcare facility.
           It includes delays in diagnosis and decision making as well as delays between decision
           making and physical intervention (e.g. time from decision for caesarean delivery to time
           of delivery of the infant). Treatment also includes appropriateness of treatment
           decisions and the availability of resources needed to provide recommended treatment.

        -  Training refers to the availability of skilled health care providers and the need for
           training / upskilling of existing health care providers.

      ii) The WHO application of ICD-10 codes to deaths during pregnancy, childbirth and puerperium
      (ICD MM) classification. Within this framework, deaths are described as having a final direct
      cause, an underlying cause that leads to the final cause, and contributory causes that did
      not directly cause death, but worsened physiological status or accelerated the underlying
      event.

      The underlying cause of death is defined as the disease or condition that initiated the
      morbid chain of events leading to death or the circumstances of the accident or violence that
      produced a fatal injury. Underlying causes will be specified in as much detail as available.
      The underlying cause will be classified into one of 8 categories:

        1. Hypertensive disorders in pregnancy

        2. Obstetric haemorrhage

        3. Pregnancy-related infection

        4. Other obstetric complications

        5. Unanticipated complications of management (iatrogenic)

        6. Non-obstetric complications (non-obstetric disease, e.g. cardiac disease, malaria)

        7. Unknown / Undetermined

        8. Coincidental external causes (e.g. interpersonal violence)
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Enrolling by invitation</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 6, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 31, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 31, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Only</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Transport: Mode of transport</measure>
    <time_frame>On the day of hospital admission</time_frame>
    <description>Nominal: walking, private transport, ambulance, public transport</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Transport: Distance</measure>
    <time_frame>On the day of hospital admission</time_frame>
    <description>Continuous: distance in kilometers from patient's home to hospital</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Transport: Time</measure>
    <time_frame>On the day of hospital admission</time_frame>
    <description>Continuous: time in hours from patient's home to hospital</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Transport: Delay in seeking healthcare</measure>
    <time_frame>On the day of hospital admission</time_frame>
    <description>Binary: Obstetrician opinion whether there was a clinically important delay in seeking care</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Transport: Delay in transport to healthcare</measure>
    <time_frame>On the day of hospital admission</time_frame>
    <description>Binary: Obstetrician opinion whether there was a clinically important delay in transport</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Transport: Inter-facility delay</measure>
    <time_frame>At time of death (death recorded in-hospital, censored at 30 days)</time_frame>
    <description>Binary: Did the patient die while waiting for inter-facility transfer?</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Treatment: Referral to high level of care</measure>
    <time_frame>In-hospital censored at 30 days</time_frame>
    <description>Binary: Whether or not referral to higher level of care took place</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Treatment: Prophylactic uterotonic use</measure>
    <time_frame>On day of caesarean section, at time of caesarean section</time_frame>
    <description>Nominal: Oxytocin, Ergometrine, Misoprostil, Carbetocin, None</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Treatment: Therapeutic uterotonic use</measure>
    <time_frame>On day of caesarean section, at time of caesarean section</time_frame>
    <description>Nominal: Oxytocin, Ergometrine, Misoprostil, Carbetocin, None</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Treatment: Surgical safety checklist</measure>
    <time_frame>On day of caesarean section, at time of caesarean section</time_frame>
    <description>Binary: Whether or not a surgical safety checklist was used</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Treatment: Type of anaesthetic</measure>
    <time_frame>On day of caesarean section, at time of caesarean section</time_frame>
    <description>Nominal: Regional, general with endotracheal intubation, general without endotracheal intubation.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Treatment: Airway aspiration</measure>
    <time_frame>On day of caesarean section, at time of caesarean section</time_frame>
    <description>Binary: Whether or not airway aspiration occurred</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Treatment: Desaturation</measure>
    <time_frame>On day of caesarean section, at time of caesarean section</time_frame>
    <description>Binary: Whether or not desaturation below 90% occurred during management of the airway</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Treatment: Spinal hypotension</measure>
    <time_frame>On day of caesarean section, at time of caesarean section</time_frame>
    <description>Binary: Whether or not spinal hypotension occured; systolic BP &lt;= 90mmHg</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Treatment: Interventions to arrest bleeding</measure>
    <time_frame>In hospital, censored at 30 days</time_frame>
    <description>Nominal: Which techniques were used? over-sowing, uterine compression suture, uterine artery ligation, uterine tourniquet, intrauterine balloon, hysterectomy, uterine artery embolisation</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Treatment: Blood products</measure>
    <time_frame>In hospital, censored at 30 days</time_frame>
    <description>Nominal: Which products were given? Red blood cells, fresh frozen plasma, freeze dried plasma, cryoprecipitate, platelets, whole blood.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Treatment: Availability of medications</measure>
    <time_frame>On day of caesarean section</time_frame>
    <description>Nominal: Oxygen, Propofol, Thiopentone, Etomidate, Ketamine, Suxamethonium, Rocuronium, Nitrous Oxide, Halothane, Isoflurane, Sevoflurane, Oxytocin, Ergometrine, Syntometrine, Misoprostil, Prostaglandin F2alpha, Carbetocin, Phenylephrine, Ephedrine, Adrenalin, Noradrenalin, Morphine, Fentanyl, Pethidine, Lignocaine, Bupivacaine, Tranexamic Acid</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Treatment: Availability of blood products</measure>
    <time_frame>On day of caesarean section</time_frame>
    <description>Nominal: Red blood cells, Plasma, Platelets, Cryoprecipitate</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Treatment: Availability of resuscitation equipment</measure>
    <time_frame>On day of caesarean section</time_frame>
    <description>Nominal: Airway suction, endotracheal intubation equipment, mechanical ventilator, supraglottic airway devices, defibrillator,</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Treatment: Availability of monitoring equipment</measure>
    <time_frame>On day of caesarean section</time_frame>
    <description>Nominal: Which monitoring equipment are available in the recovery area and the postoperative ward? O2 saturation, blood pressure, heart rate monitor, thermometer</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Treatment: Recovery area</measure>
    <time_frame>On day of caesarean section</time_frame>
    <description>Binary: Is there a dedicated area where the patient is monitored during recovery from anaesthesia for caesarean section?</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Treatment: Provider-patient ratio</measure>
    <time_frame>On day of caesarean section</time_frame>
    <description>Interval: Nurse-to-patient ratio in postoperative ward (during the day, during the night)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Treatment: Delay in diagnosis</measure>
    <time_frame>On day of caesarean section</time_frame>
    <description>Binary: Obstetrician opinion whether a clinical important delay in diagnosis occurred</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Treatment: Delay between diagnosis and caesarean section</measure>
    <time_frame>On day of caesarean section</time_frame>
    <description>Binary: Obstetrician opinion whether a clinical important delay between diagnosis and caesarean section occurred</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Treatment: Access to hospital resources</measure>
    <time_frame>On day of caesarean section</time_frame>
    <description>Nominal: Obstetrician opinion whether delayed access or lack of hospital resources contributed to the death: water supply, electricity, medications, telephone, anaesthetic equipment, surgical equipment, monitoring equipment, operating theatre, nursing or assistant, on-call senior obstetric doctor, on-call senior anaesthetic doctor, advice from referral center.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Training: Level of training</measure>
    <time_frame>At time of caesarean section</time_frame>
    <description>Nominal: Provider level of training at caesarean seciton (for anaesthesia and surgery): Specialist, specialist trainee, non-specialist doctor, non-doctor</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cause of death</measure>
    <time_frame>Maternal death is recorded in-hospital, censored at 30 days.</time_frame>
    <description>WHO ICD-10 maternal mortality reporting standard</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Maternal Mortality</condition>
  <condition>Cesarean Section</condition>
  <condition>Africa</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>African Surgical OutcomeS-2 Trial</arm_group_label>
    <description>The ASOS-2 Trial is a cluster randomised trial purposively recruiting hospitals across Africa. To be eligible for inclusion a hospital must perform at least 20 cases of adult in-patient surgery with anaesthesia per week, have local ethics approval for the trial, have local hospital management approval and have established a local hospital study team. The trial excludes hospitals with lower surgical volume. The trial aims to include all consecutive adult in-patient surgical cases at participating hospitals (both elective and emergency surgery). Patients under the age of 18 and patients who have already been recruited into the trial are excluded from recruitment. Follow-up is in-hospital, censored at 30 days.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cesarean section</intervention_name>
    <description>Abdominal, operative delivery of the fetus</description>
    <arm_group_label>African Surgical OutcomeS-2 Trial</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        African mothers who die during or after caesarean delivery. The primary study is a cluster
        randomised trial which samples hospitals across Africa purposively.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  adult patients

          -  aged 18 years and over,

          -  admitted to participating hospitals

          -  undergoing elective and non-elective caesarean delivery

          -  who die following their operation before leaving hospital and within 30 days after the
             operation.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  prior participation in ASOS-2

          -  caesarean delivery at a hospital other than the study hospital (left censored)

          -  patients who are transferred to another hospital before death (right censored)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Professor Bruce M Biccard</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Cape Town</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Groote Schuur Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Observatory</city>
        <state>Western Cape</state>
        <zip>7925</zip>
        <country>South Africa</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>South Africa</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 25, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 22, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 23, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 27, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 27, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 29, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Cape Town</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Bruce Biccard</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Maternal Death</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>The Principle Investigator will receive requests to share individual participant data and will decide on a case by case basis.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

