<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04027426</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>UTK IRB-18-04910-XP</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>1R01DK121360</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04027426</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Families Becoming Healthy Together</brief_title>
  <official_title>Families Becoming Healthy Together</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>The University of Tennessee, Knoxville</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases (NIDDK)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>The Miriam Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Memphis</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University at Buffalo</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>The University of Tennessee, Knoxville</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The investigators plan to implement a novel limited RED (high-energy-dense) food variety
      prescription within a 18-month FBT to examine its effect on 18-month body mass index (BMI).
      This will be the first randomized control trial to examine how habituation rate, assessed via
      salivary habituation, mediates reduction in RED food intake, overall energy intake, and
      reductions in BMI over time, as well as if baseline habituation rate is a behavioral
      phenotype that moderates BMI outcomes. One hundred fifty-six children aged 8 to 12 years at &gt;
      85th percentile BMI will be randomized to one of two, 18-month interventions compared in our
      6-month pilot study: FBT (family-based behavioral obesity treatment) or FBT+Variety. Child
      and adult caregiver assessments will occur at 0, 6, 12, and 18 months on anthropometrics,
      dietary intake (RED food variety, energy, and diet quality), habituation, and physical
      activity.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Identifying successful methods for reducing long-term energy intake continues to be a
      challenge in obesity treatment. Basic behavioral research has found that the rate of
      habituation (i.e., rate of reduction in physiological and behavioral responding) to food is
      related to amount of food consumed, and faster habituation rates reduce food intake. The rate
      of habituation to food can be accelerated when variety in foods is limited, producing
      decreased intake. Thus, a dietary prescription that limits variety of high-energy-dense (HED)
      foods may boost ability to reduce long-term energy intake, enhancing long-term weight loss.

      Furthermore, habituation rates to food show large individual variability. For example,
      individuals with overweight habituate slower to food than individuals with a healthy weight,
      and slower habituation rates predict greater increases in child standardized body mass index
      (ZBMI). Thus, slower habituation rates to food may be a behavioral phenotype for increased
      risk of suboptimal weight outcomes. Obesity interventions that accelerate habituation to food
      may then be more beneficial for those with this behavioral phenotype.

      The investigators have been conducting a line of translational research that applies
      habituation theory to obesity treatment involving: 1) studies systematically testing basic
      concepts to better inform intervention development; 2) &quot;proof-of-concept&quot; testing; and 3)
      efficacy trials. The long-term goal of this research is to develop a dietary prescription
      that harnesses habituation as a mechanism for reducing long-term energy intake. This research
      has culminated in piloting a limited variety prescription (variety of both HED snack foods
      and entrees at dinner were limited) within a 6-month family-based behavioral obesity
      treatment (FBT) for children. Twenty-four families, with a child &gt; 85th percentile BMI and
      aged 8 to 12 years, were randomized to FBT that included the Traffic Light Diet (1000-1500
      kcal/day, &lt; 2 servings/day of RED [HED] foods) and a &gt; 60 min/day of moderate- to
      vigorous-intensity physical activity prescription or to FBT that included a limited dietary
      variety prescription (one RED snack food and dinner entrée were chosen; families regularly
      consumed these foods as compared to other RED snack foods and entrees) (FBT+Variety). At
      6-months children in FBT+Variety had a significantly greater reduction in percent overweight
      than those in FBT (−15.4% vs.− 8.9%), and families in FBT+Variety had a lower daily intake of
      kcal from fat (351 kcal vs. 494 kcal). This limited dietary variety prescription shows
      promise for enhancing weight outcomes in FBT. However, research is needed to examine if
      limiting variety improves long-term weight loss, if this improvement is due to enhanced
      habituation, and explore if there is a behavioral phenotype that more greatly benefits from
      this dietary approach.

      The investigators plan to implement a novel limited RED food variety prescription within an
      18-month FBT to examine its effect on 18-month body mass index (BMI). This will be the first
      RCT to examine how habituation rate, assessed via salivary habituation, mediates reduction in
      RED food intake, overall energy intake, and reductions in BMI over time, as well as if
      baseline habituation rate is a behavioral phenotype that moderates BMI outcomes. One hundred
      fifty-six children aged 8 to 12 years at &gt; 85th percentile BMI will be randomized to one of
      two, 18-month interventions compared in our 6-month pilot study: FBT or FBT+Variety. Child
      and adult caregiver assessments will occur at 0, 6, 12, and 18 months on anthropometrics,
      dietary intake (RED food variety, energy, and diet quality), habituation, and physical
      activity. The investigation was designed for all intervention sessions and assessments to be
      conducted in person. Due to COVID-19, the University Institutional Review Board (IRB) decided
      that in-person contact had to be halted, so all meetings and assessments were moved to occur
      remotely via Zoom. When the University IRB does allow in-person contact, families will be
      able to choose between attending meetings and assessments in person or remotely via Zoom.

      The primary aims are to determine for children:

        1. Influence of FBT+Variety on long-term weight loss.

        2. Influence of FBT+Variety on long-term habituation to RED foods. The habituation rate
           will mediate differences in dietary intake and BMI between conditions.

      An exploratory aim is to examine in children:

      1) Influence of habituation rate on moderating outcomes in FBT+Variety and FBT (identifying a
      behavioral phenotype that bests benefits from a limited variety prescription).

      Comparisons will also be made between the conditions on all child dietary and activity
      measures. Additionally, adult caregiver measures will be examined, with outcomes anticipated
      to be similar to child outcomes.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 29, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 31, 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 31, 2024</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>Outcomes assessor will be blinded to randomization. Participants and providers will be blinded to study hypothesis.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Child and adult body mass index</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from 0 to 6, and 6 to 18 months</time_frame>
    <description>Child's and adult caregiver's weight will be assessed by an electronic scale and height will be measured by a stadiometer.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Child and adult salivary habituation</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from 0 to 6, and 6 to 18 months</time_frame>
    <description>To assess habituation of salivary responses to food cues, whole mouth parotid salivary flow will be measured using the Strongin-Hinsie Peck method. Two measures will be taken, one with juice and one with food.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Child and adult dietary Intake</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from 0 to 6, and 6 to 18 months</time_frame>
    <description>Dietary intake for both the child and adult caregiver will be assessed by 3 (2 weekdays and 1 weekend day) 24-hour dietary phone recalls, using the five-step, multiple-pass method. Variables of interest will be the variety of RED foods consumed over the three days; and the mean over the three days of daily servings and kcal from RED foods, kcal, energy density (kcal/g), and Healthy Eating Index (HEI)-2015. Adherence to the prescriptions in the two conditions will be examined. At 6, 12, and 18 months, the percentage of goals met each day will be calculated, with a mean percentage calculated. We will also provide a detailed list of snack foods to participants, and they will be asked to indicate which of the foods on the list were eaten during the previous month, regardless of quantity consumed.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Child and adult physical activity via wGT3X-BT</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from 0 to 6, and 6 to 18 months</time_frame>
    <description>The wGT9x (ActiGraph, LLC, Pensacola, FL) will objectively measure time spent in MVPA (physical activity at &gt; 3.0 metabolic equivalents units).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Child percent overweight</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from 0 to 6, and 6 to 18 months</time_frame>
    <description>Percent overweight (%OW) will also be calculated (100*[BMI/50th percentile BMI for child age and sex]).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Child and adult waist circumference</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from 0 to 6, and 6 to 18 months</time_frame>
    <description>Waist circumference (WC) will be measured using standard procedures.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Meal planning, preparation, and grocery shopping</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from 0 to 6, and 6 to 18 months</time_frame>
    <description>Parent time scarcity and fatigue as barriers to planning and preparing meals will measure frequency of occurrence of these barriers.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Child eating pathology</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from 0 to 6, and 6 to 18 months</time_frame>
    <description>Child eating pathology will be assessed using the Kid's Eating Disorder Survey</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Home Food Inventory</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from 0 to 6, and 6 to 18 months</time_frame>
    <description>Self-reported inventory of foods available in the household will be assessed</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Child and Adult Sleep Habits</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from 0 to 6, and 6 to 18 months</time_frame>
    <description>Usual sleeping and waking time will be collected</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Child Routines</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from 0 to 6, and 6 to 18 months</time_frame>
    <description>Parent-report measure of commonly occurring routines in school-aged children will measure the frequency of occurrence of routines in children.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Compliance and process data</measure>
    <time_frame>6, 12, and 18 months</time_frame>
    <description>Total number of weekly, and type, of self-monitoring records (hard copy or electronic) completed will be assessed. Number of treatment sessions attended will be recorded.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">156</enrollment>
  <condition>Obesity</condition>
  <condition>Childhood Obesity</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>FBT (family-based behavioral treatment)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>This condition will be prescribed the Traffic Light Diet (1000-1500 kcal/day, &lt; 2 servings/day of RED [non-nutrient-dense, energy-dense] foods) and a &gt; 60 min/day of MVPA prescription for children and &gt; 30 min/day of MVPA for adults at least 5 days/week. FBT will receive a family-based, behavioral intervention to assist the targeted child and a participating adult caregiver with making changes in energy balance behaviors.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>FBT+Variety</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The FBT+Variety condition will receive FBT along with a limited variety prescription. In this prescription families will identify two RED foods, a dinner entree and snack food, and develop meal plans that reduce variety of RED foods by regularly consuming these foods and limiting consumption of other RED entrees and snack foods.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>FBT</intervention_name>
    <description>FBT will receive a family-based, behavioral intervention for childhood obesity, consisting of group meetings once a week for months 1 to 4, twice a month for months 5 to 6, once a month for months 7 to 12, and once every two months for months 13 to 18 (29 sessions). For all meetings, the child and adult caregiver will be weighed and be provided with feedback, homework will be reviewed, and a behavioral lesson will be presented. At the 60-min meetings, the child and adult will attend separate 40 min group meetings, and then for the last 20 min of the meetings they will meet together with an individual therapist to address specific family-issues by developing behavioral action plans. No goals on variety in RED foods will be provided.</description>
    <arm_group_label>FBT (family-based behavioral treatment)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>FBT+Variety</intervention_name>
    <description>This condition is FBT with a limited variety prescription. The limited variety prescription reduces the number of different RED foods consumed.</description>
    <arm_group_label>FBT+Variety</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  age between 8 and 12 years

          -  &gt; 85th percentile BMI

          -  one adult caregiver (&gt; 18 years) living in the household with a BMI &gt; 25 kg/m2 willing
             to attend treatment meetings

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  child and adult caregiver report living in two separate households for &gt; 2 days per
             week

          -  child or adult caregiver report a heart condition, chest pain during periods of
             activity or rest, or loss of consciousness on the Physical Activity Readiness
             Questionnaire (PAR-Q) (individuals reporting joint problems, prescription medication
             usage, or other medical conditions that could limit exercise will be required to
             obtain written physician consent to participate)

          -  child or adult caregiver report being unable to walk for 2 blocks (1/4 mile) without
             stopping

          -  child or adult caregiver report major psychiatric diseases or organic brain syndromes

          -  child or adult caregiver report currently participating in a weight loss program
             and/or taking weight loss or appetite regulation medication or lost &gt; 5% of body
             weight during the past 6 months

          -  child report having bariatric surgery for weight loss/planning to have bariatric
             surgery in the next 18 months, adult caregiver having bariatric surgery in the
             previous two years or planning to have bariatric surgery in the next 18 months

          -  adult caregiver reports being pregnant, lactating, less than 6 months post-partum or
             plans to become pregnant in the next 18 months

          -  child or adult caregiver report planning to move outside of the metropolitan area
             within the time frame of the investigation

          -  child or adult caregiver report dietary restrictions for medical reasons

          -  child or adult caregiver report allergies to lemon or lime juice (used in habituation
             measures)

          -  child is not able to read at a third-grade reading level.

          -  do not have reliable internet access.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>8 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>12 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Hollie Raynor, PhD RD LDN</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Tennessee Knoxville</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Hollie Raynor, PhD RD LDN</last_name>
    <phone>865-974-6259</phone>
    <email>hraynor@utk.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Healthy Eating and Activity Lab, University of Tennessee</name>
      <address>
        <city>Knoxville</city>
        <state>Tennessee</state>
        <zip>37996</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Hollie A Raynor, PhD RD LDN</last_name>
      <phone>865-974-6259</phone>
      <email>hraynor@utk.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Altman M, Wilfley DE. Evidence update on the treatment of overweight and obesity in children and adolescents. J Clin Child Adolesc Psychol. 2015;44(4):521-37. doi: 10.1080/15374416.2014.963854. Epub 2014 Dec 12. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25496471</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Epstein LH, Temple JL, Roemmich JN, Bouton ME. Habituation as a determinant of human food intake. Psychol Rev. 2009 Apr;116(2):384-407. doi: 10.1037/a0015074. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19348547</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Epstein LH, Robinson JL, Temple JL, Roemmich JN, Marusewski AL, Nadbrzuch RL. Variety influences habituation of motivated behavior for food and energy intake in children. Am J Clin Nutr. 2009 Mar;89(3):746-54. doi: 10.3945/ajcn.2008.26911. Epub 2009 Jan 28.</citation>
    <PMID>19176724</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Temple JL, Giacomelli AM, Roemmich JN, Epstein LH. Dietary variety impairs habituation in children. Health Psychol. 2008 Jan;27(1S):S10-9. doi: 10.1037/0278-6133.27.1.S10.</citation>
    <PMID>18248101</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Epstein LH, Fletcher KD, O'Neill J, Roemmich JN, Raynor H, Bouton ME. Food characteristics, long-term habituation and energy intake. Laboratory and field studies. Appetite. 2013 Jan;60(1):40-50. doi: 10.1016/j.appet.2012.08.030. Epub 2012 Oct 22.</citation>
    <PMID>23085682</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Epstein LH, Robinson JL, Temple JL, Roemmich JN, Marusewski A, Nadbrzuch R. Sensitization and habituation of motivated behavior in overweight and non-overweight children. Learn Motiv. 2008 Aug;39(3):243-255.</citation>
    <PMID>19649135</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bond DS, Raynor HA, McCaffery JM, Wing RR. Salivary habituation to food stimuli in successful weight loss maintainers, obese and normal-weight adults. Int J Obes (Lond). 2010 Mar;34(3):593-6. doi: 10.1038/ijo.2009.267. Epub 2009 Dec 15.</citation>
    <PMID>20010900</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bond DS, Raynor HA, Vithiananthan S, Sax HC, Pohl D, Roye GD, Ryder BA, Wing RR. Differences in salivary habituation to a taste stimulus in bariatric surgery candidates and normal-weight controls. Obes Surg. 2009 Jul;19(7):873-8. doi: 10.1007/s11695-009-9861-3. Epub 2009 May 20.</citation>
    <PMID>19455371</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Epstein LH, Carr KA, Cavanaugh MD, Paluch RA, Bouton ME. Long-term habituation to food in obese and nonobese women. Am J Clin Nutr. 2011 Aug;94(2):371-6. doi: 10.3945/ajcn.110.009035. Epub 2011 May 18.</citation>
    <PMID>21593492</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Temple JL, Giacomelli AM, Roemmich JN, Epstein LH. Overweight children habituate slower than non-overweight children to food. Physiol Behav. 2007 Jun 8;91(2-3):250-4. Epub 2007 Mar 16.</citation>
    <PMID>17459429</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Aspen VA, Stein RI, Wilfley DE. An exploration of salivation patterns in normal weight and obese children. Appetite. 2012 Apr;58(2):539-42. doi: 10.1016/j.appet.2011.11.027. Epub 2011 Dec 3.</citation>
    <PMID>22172456</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Epstein LH, Kilanowski C, Paluch RA, Raynor H, Daniel TO. Reducing variety enhances effectiveness of family-based treatment for pediatric obesity. Eat Behav. 2015 Apr;17:140-3. doi: 10.1016/j.eatbeh.2015.02.001. Epub 2015 Feb 13.</citation>
    <PMID>25706950</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 13, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 16, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 22, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 7, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 7, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 9, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>The University of Tennessee, Knoxville</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Hollie Raynor</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Interim Assistant Dean of Research</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Habituation</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Obesity</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pediatric Obesity</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <provided_document_section>
    <provided_document>
      <document_type>Informed Consent Form</document_type>
      <document_has_protocol>No</document_has_protocol>
      <document_has_icf>Yes</document_has_icf>
      <document_has_sap>No</document_has_sap>
      <document_date>May 26, 2020</document_date>
      <document_url>https://ClinicalTrials.gov/ProvidedDocs/26/NCT04027426/ICF_002.pdf</document_url>
    </provided_document>
  </provided_document_section>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

