<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04020484</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>6558</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04020484</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Making Mindfulness Matter in Children With Epilepsy</brief_title>
  <acronym>M3Epilepsy</acronym>
  <official_title>Making Mindfulness Matter in Children With Epilepsy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Lawson Health Research Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Canadian Institutes of Health Research (CIHR)</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Lawson Health Research Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Epilepsy is a debilitating condition characterized by spontaneous, unprovoked seizures. Up to
      80% of children with epilepsy (CWE) may face cognitive, psychiatric, and/or behavioral
      comorbidities with significant unmet mental health needs. Mindfulness-based interventions may
      provide an ideal vector to target unmet mental healthcare needs in patients with epilepsy and
      their families. The investigators propose the Making Mindfulness Matter (M3) program as an
      intervention to improve health related quality of life and mental-health for CWE and their
      parents. M3 is a community-based, concurrent parent and child program that incorporates
      mindful awareness, social-emotional learning skills, neuroscience, and positive psychology.
      This pilot RCT is needed to refine the implementation of the intervention to families with a
      child with epilepsy, and collect information pertaining to the feasibility and effectiveness
      of the intervention in preparation for a subsequent multi-centred trial across Canada.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Recognizing that medical management for chronic illness such as epilepsy does not address the
      stress and co-occurring psychological issues experienced by many patients, mindfulness-based
      interventions have been increasingly utilized. Mindfulness-based interventions are effective,
      well-validated interventions for several adult outcomes including physical and mental health,
      social and emotional well-being, and cognition. Meta-analyses report overall medium effect
      sizes of 0.50 to 0.59 across these outcomes. In a recent Cochrane review of psychological
      interventions for people with epilepsy, three studies specifically examined mindfulness-based
      techniques for adults with epilepsy and determined positive outcomes on mental health, HRQOL
      and seizure outcomes. There has been far less research on mindfulness with children and youth
      than in adults; studies that have been done have been plagued with methodological limitations
      including small numbers, lack of randomization or control groups. However, evidence to-date
      indicates that mindfulness interventions for children and youth are feasible, accepted and
      enjoyed by participants. The few well conducted studies on mindfulness interventions in
      children without physical health issues have reported reduced symptoms of anxiety,
      depression, and stress, reduced maladaptive coping and rumination, and improved behavioural
      and emotional self-regulation and focus. Furthermore, a recent systematic review and
      meta-analysis found that mindfulness interventions were three times more effective in
      alleviating psychological symptoms among children with clinically diagnosed psychological
      disorders (such as anxiety, learning disability and externalizing disorders), compared with
      healthy controls. This suggests that mindfulness interventions may be particularly relevant
      for those with clinical levels of psychological disorders, a particularly relevant finding
      for our study given that children with epilepsy experience greater levels of depression,
      anxiety, learning disability and behavioural comorbidities.

      In addition to the benefits of programs that deliver mindfulness interventions directly to
      children, programs that target parents and parents appear to be effective in improving
      parental functioning and in turn, promote child outcomes. Furthermore, studies are indicating
      that mindfulness-based interventions for parents of children with chronic issues (attention
      deficit hyperactivity disorder, developmental delays, autism) are effective for lessening
      parental stress and mental health problems. Improvements in parent-child relationship and
      improved youth behaviour management have also been found.

      Neither the Cochrane review on the impact of psychological treatments for people with
      epilepsy, nor a recent systematic review on mindfulness interventions in youth found studies
      investigating mindfulness management techniques for CWE. Despite the paucity of studies of
      mindfulness interventions in childhood epilepsy, there is converging evidence to suggest
      studying a mindfulness-based intervention in children and families with epilepsy is
      warranted. There is research pointing to the effectiveness of mindfulness-based interventions
      on psychological symptoms in adults and children, especially in those with relevant clinical
      issues similar to CWE. The investigators believe the M3 program is ideally suited for use
      with CWE and their parents for a number of reasons. The program was developed from the
      validated, widely used, and successful Mind UP program for use in the community and augmented
      to integrate a parent component, and has been shown to be successful in our cohort of young
      children and their parents facing adversity. Importantly, M3 is suitable for children as
      young as 4 years of age, which is particularly important as evidence to date suggests that
      early identification and treatment of epilepsy comorbidities is essential as there may be a
      window of opportunity for early intervention in some children. Interventions must be
      implemented early before problems become entrenched and interfere with the development of
      basic cognitive, behavioral, and social skills crucial for long-term educational, vocational,
      and interpersonal adaptation. The low-cost, group delivery and facilitation by non-clinician
      staff also allows the program to be scalable to communities across Canada and increases its
      likely sustainability.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">December 2, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 20, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 20, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>This is a parallel, individually-randomized controlled trial (RCT) comparing an intervention and treatment-as-usual (i.e. wait-list control). This study will not interfere with patients' clinical care. The intervention will be delivered to groups on a rolling basis to minimize wait-times and allow for timely access to the intervention for the waitlist controls. Sample size calculations showed that 76 child-parent dyads will be required (38 intervention, 38 control), and to account for a liberal 24% attrition rate, 100 child-parent dyads will be recruited.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Care Provider)</masking>
    <masking_description>Blinding of participants and program facilitators (i.e. the staff delivering the M3 program) will be difficult to completely achieve given the nature of the intervention. The investigators will attempt to ameliorate bias by explaining to participants and program facilitators that the study is interested in evaluating the intervention to be given to all participants, however, in planning the logistics of the intervention, some participants will receive the intervention in the very near future, whereas others will receive the intervention in approximately 12 weeks. In so doing, the investigators hope to eliminate any biases associated with the participants' and program facilitators' perception or biases of being assigned to the treatment or control group.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Feasibility of Making Mindfulness Matter (M3) as a family treatment for children with epilepsy and their parents</measure>
    <time_frame>Throughout the study enrollment period and over the 8 weeks of intervention.</time_frame>
    <description>The investigators will track the number of patients contacted, response rate, attrition and reasons for non-participation and attrition. At the start of each session, parents will complete a one-page (12-item) semi-structured questionnaire evaluating treatment fidelity, at home utilization of M3 skills. At the end of each session, parents will complete an overall feedback form on the intervention. Facilitators will complete a two-page questionnaire providing feedback on the session. At the start and end of the M3 program, children will be asked to complete a feeling face questionnaire rated on a 3-point scale about topics discussed in the group such as how our brain works when upset and what is mindfulness.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Effect of M3 on Health Related Quality of Life of children with epilepsy</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 8 weeks, 17 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The Quality of Life in Childhood Epilepsy Questionnaire (QOLCE-55) is a 55-item measure that emphasizes a functional approach to quality of life. QOLCE-55 generates an overall quality of life score, and four subscale scores: cognitive, emotional, social and physical functioning. Scores range from 0 to 100, with higher scores indicative of better quality of life.
Although the QOLCE is a widely used HRQOL scale, no study has calculated the minimum clinically important difference (MCID). To calculate the MCID for the QOLCE, the Patient Centred Global Ratings of Change will be used, a 5-item scale where respondents indicate the amount of change relative to baseline. Rating from −7 (much worse) through 0 (no change) to +7 (much better). This information will allow us to calculate the MCID for the QOLCE-55, and thereby identify the proportion of patients who experience a clinically meaningful change following intervention.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Effect of M3 on Health Related Quality of Life of parents</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 8 weeks, 17 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The Short Form Health Survey (SF12v2), a 12-item self-reported measure evaluating physical and mental health components of health-related quality of life over the past 4 weeks will be used. The measures generates two composite scales relating to the physical and mental health components of health related quality of life. This measure is the most frequently used patient reported outcome in clinical trials, and has been used most frequently in studies evaluating quality of life of parents of children with epilepsy.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Does M3 have a positive effect on children's externalizing problems</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 8 weeks, 17 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Behavior Assessment System for Children (BASC-3) 139-175-item comprehensive scale evaluating children's adaptive and problem behaviors in community and home settings. The BASC composite scale 'externalizing problems' will be used. Persons with T-score above 59 in a given scale are categorized as 'at-risk' for that domain.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Does M3 have a positive effect on children's internalizing problems</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 8 weeks, 17 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Behavior Assessment System for Children (BASC-3) 139-175-item comprehensive scale evaluating children's adaptive and problem behaviors in community and home settings. The BASC composite scale 'internalizing problems' will be used. Persons with T-score above 59 in a given scale are categorized as 'at-risk' for that domain.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Does M3 have a positive effect on children's adaptive skills</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 8 weeks, 17 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Behavior Assessment System for Children (BASC-3) 139-175-item comprehensive scale evaluating children's adaptive and problem behaviors in community and home settings. The BASC composite scale 'adaptive skills' will be used. Persons with T-score above 59 in a given scale are categorized as 'at-risk' for that domain.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Does M3 have a positive effect on children's executive function</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 8 weeks, 17 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Behavioral Rating Inventory of Executive Function 2 (BRIEF) 86-item scale measuring parent-rated executive function and self-regulation in children. Generates a global executive composite, cognitive regulation index, emotion regulation index, behavior regulation index. Persons with T-score above 60 in a given scale are categorized as 'at-risk' for that domain.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Does M3 have a positive effect on children's severity of epilepsy</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 8 weeks, 17 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Parents will rate the child's epilepsy severity using the Global assessment of the severity of epilepsy (GASE), a single item measure scale measured on a 7-point Likert type scale. Seizure frequency will be rated by parents through two questions asking the number of seizures and number of seizure-free days in the past 30 days.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Does M3 have a positive effect on parents' depression</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 8 weeks, 17 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Center for Epidemiological Studies Depression Scale (CES-D) 20-item scale evaluating the level of depressive symptoms, and is one of the most widely used instruments in the field of psychiatric epidemiology. Generates an overall score for depressive symptoms, with scores above 16 indicative of risk for depression.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Does M3 have a positive effect on parents' anxiety</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 8 weeks, 17 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Generalized Anxiety Disorder 7-item (GAD-7) scale evaluating generalized anxiety. Generates an overall anxiety score, with scores above 10 indicative of moderate-severe anxiety.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Does M3 have a positive effect on parents' stress</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 8 weeks, 17 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Parenting Stress Index 4 - short form 36-item scale that helps identify sources of stress. Focused on three major domains of stress: child characteristics, parent characteristics, and situational/demographic factors. A summary and 3 subscale (Parental Distress, Parent-Child Dysfunctional Interaction and Difficult Child) scores are generated. Scores in the 81st percentile or higher are indicative of high stress.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Epilepsy in Children</condition>
  <condition>Mindfulness</condition>
  <condition>Quality of Life</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The program will be delivered in groups of 4 to 8, for 1.5 hours each week. Once 4 to 8 dyads are assigned to the intervention group, participants will be given the baseline questionnaires and start the intervention in the following week.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Waitlist Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Once 4 to 8 dyads are assigned to the control group, participants will be given the baseline questionnaires, followed by another set of questionnaires 8 weeks after, and then start the intervention in the following week.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Making Mindfulness Matter (M3)</intervention_name>
    <description>Making Mindfulness Matter (M3) is a community-based, concurrent parent and child program that incorporates mindful awareness, social-emotional learning skills, neuroscience, and positive psychology. This program was modelled after the school-based MindUP™ program for use in the community and augmented to integrate a parent component. M3 is a facilitator-led program that integrates attitudes, skills, and behaviours related to mindfulness and social-emotional learning (SEL). During the 8-week concurrent parent and child manualized program, parents learn the same core principles as children: how our brains work, stress and the brain, mindful breathing, mindful sensing, mindful movement, perspective taking, optimism, and gratitude/acts of kindness.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Waitlist Control</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>M3</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        No age restriction on parent participating in parent/child dyad

        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Children aged 4 to 10 years diagnosed with epilepsy a minimum of 6 months ago, as per
             the International League Against Epilepsy (ILAE) 2014 operational definition*

          2. Children have reasonable comprehension of spoken language and can follow simple
             instructions

          3. Children with epilepsy and their parents** are willing to attend all intervention
             sessions

          4. Children with epilepsy and parents have an adequate understanding of English

               -  Operational (practical) clinical definition of epilepsy (Fisher et al. 2014):

                    1. At least two unprovoked (or reflex) seizures occurring&gt;24 h apart, or

                    2. One unprovoked (or reflex) seizure and a probability of further seizures
                       similar to the general recurrence risk (at least 60%) after two unprovoked
                       seizures, occurring over the next 10 years, or

                    3. Diagnosis of an epilepsy syndrome

                         -  Parents: refers to parent or guardian self-identifying as most
                            responsible for child's day-to-day care

        Exclusion criteria are:

          1. Progressive or degenerative neurological disorder;

          2. Other major co-morbid non-neurological disorders (e.g. cystic fibrosis, Crohn's
             disease, diabetes, renal failure);

          3. Concurrent enrollment in other intervention trials

          4. Child or parent regularly practice complementary health interventions such as
             meditation

          5. Scheduled to undergo epilepsy surgery during study period
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>4 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>10 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Kathy Speechley, Ph.D</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Western University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Kathy Speechley, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <phone>519-685-8500</phone>
    <phone_ext>52182</phone_ext>
    <email>kathy.speechley@lhsc.on.ca</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Karen Bax, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <email>kbax@uwo.ca</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Epilepsy Southwestern Ontario</name>
      <address>
        <city>London</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>N5W 6A8</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Mary Secco, MSc cand.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Reilly C, Agnew R, Neville BG. Depression and anxiety in childhood epilepsy: a review. Seizure. 2011 Oct;20(8):589-97. doi: 10.1016/j.seizure.2011.06.004. Epub 2011 Jul 7. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21741277</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Speechley KN, Ferro MA, Camfield CS, Huang W, Levin SD, Smith ML, Wiebe S, Zou G. Quality of life in children with new-onset epilepsy: a 2-year prospective cohort study. Neurology. 2012 Oct 9;79(15):1548-55. doi: 10.1212/WNL.0b013e31826e25aa. Epub 2012 Sep 26.</citation>
    <PMID>23019268</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kanner AM. Is it time to train neurologists in the management of mood and anxiety disorders? Epilepsy Behav. 2014 May;34:139-43. doi: 10.1016/j.yebeh.2014.02.029.</citation>
    <PMID>24780394</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ferro MA, Speechley KN. Depressive symptoms among mothers of children with epilepsy: a review of prevalence, associated factors, and impact on children. Epilepsia. 2009 Nov;50(11):2344-54. doi: 10.1111/j.1528-1167.2009.02276.x. Epub 2009 Aug 19. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19694788</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Savage S, Spencer T, Crooks C, Lapp A, Bax K. Findings from the 2016-2017 Pilot of MindUP in LDCSB Kindergarten Classes.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schonert-Reichl KA, Oberle E, Lawlor MS, Abbott D, Thomson K, Oberlander TF, Diamond A. Enhancing cognitive and social-emotional development through a simple-to-administer mindfulness-based school program for elementary school children: a randomized controlled trial. Dev Psychol. 2015 Jan;51(1):52-66. doi: 10.1037/a0038454.</citation>
    <PMID>25546595</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Grossman P, Niemann L, Schmidt S, Walach H. Mindfulness-based stress reduction and health benefits. A meta-analysis. J Psychosom Res. 2004 Jul;57(1):35-43.</citation>
    <PMID>15256293</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Perry-Parrish C, Copeland-Linder N, Webb L, Sibinga EM. Mindfulness-Based Approaches for Children and Youth. Curr Probl Pediatr Adolesc Health Care. 2016 Jun;46(6):172-8. doi: 10.1016/j.cppeds.2015.12.006. Epub 2016 Mar 8. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26968457</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Creswell JD. Mindfulness Interventions. Annu Rev Psychol. 2017 Jan 3;68:491-516. doi: 10.1146/annurev-psych-042716-051139. Epub 2016 Sep 28. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>27687118</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Michaelis R, Tang V, Wagner JL, Modi AC, LaFrance WC Jr, Goldstein LH, Lundgren T, Reuber M. Psychological treatments for people with epilepsy. Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2017 Oct 27;10:CD012081. doi: 10.1002/14651858.CD012081.pub2. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>29078005</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 24, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 11, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 16, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 6, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 6, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 9, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Epilepsy</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

