<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04025736</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>A-BR-106-017</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04025736</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Arthroscopic Shoulder Surgery With Administration of Intravenous Tranexamic Acid</brief_title>
  <official_title>Intravenous Administration of Tranexamic Acid Significantly Improved Clarity of Visual Field in Arthroscopic Shoulder Surgery. A Prospective, Double-blind and Randomized Controlled Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Cheng-Kung University Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Cheng-Kung University Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Purpose: The study aimed to determine whether intravenous administration of tanexamic acid
      (TXA) before shoulder arthroscopic rotator cuff repair surgery can improve arthroscopy visual
      clarity. Methods: This is a prospective, double-blinded, randomized and placebo-controlled
      study. From May 2016 to April 2018, patients requiring arthroscopic rotator cuff repair were
      enrolled and randomly assigned to either the TXA group that received 1000mg tranexamic acid
      intravenously 10 minutes before surgery or the placebo group that received the same volume of
      plain saline. Patients with pre-existing liver/renal disease, coagulopathy, or concurrent use
      of anti-coagulation medications were excluded. The visual clarity was rated by a numeric
      rating scale from grade

      1(poor) to grade 3(clear) every 15 minutes throughout the surgery. Secondary outcomes
      included estimated perioperative blood loss, operative time, degree of shoulder swelling,
      postoperative subjective pain score, inpatient duration and associated comorbidities were
      recorded. Both parametric and nonparametric methods were used for statistical analysis.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 7, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">February 28, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">February 28, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Inclusion criteria were Patients who were diagnosed with rotator cuff tear and failure of conservative treatment for more than 3 months. The tear size was measured by MRI and must be repairable. We excluded patients who did not provide permit, those had history of coagulopathy, who were under anticoagulation therapy before surgery, who had abnormal coagulation profile (prothrombin time or activated partial thromboplastin time) before surgery, who had renal or liver disorder, those who had uncontrolled hypertension (systolic pressure &amp;gt;180 mmHg), or who were allergy to local anesthetic agent or Tranexamic acid.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Visual clarity during shoulder arthroscopic surgery.</measure>
    <time_frame>Measure the percentage of grade 3 visual clarity after surgery through study completion, an average of 1 year.</time_frame>
    <description>We use 3-grades visual clarity. grade 1 means poor visual clarity; 2 means fair clarity and 3 means good clarity. The visual clarity was scored in every 15 minutes during the operation scoring system to evaluate visual clarity during arthroscopic surgery. 4 Grade 1 means poor visibility (active bleeding that the vision was too poor to perform the operation); Grade 2 means fair visibility (minor bleeding that can interfere vision but surgery can still perform); Grade 3 means good visibility (clear vision without obvious blood).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Visual clarity during shoulder arthroscopic surgery.</measure>
    <time_frame>Measure the whole surgery's mean visual clarity grade after surgery through study completion, an average of 1 year.</time_frame>
    <description>We use 3-grades visual clarity. grade 1 means poor visual clarity; 2 means fair clarity and 3 means good clarity. The visual clarity was scored in every 15 minutes during</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>patients' visual analog scale (VAS ) pain score on postoperative day 1</measure>
    <time_frame>measure on post operative day one's morning through study completion, an average of 1 year.</time_frame>
    <description>The visual analog scale(VAS) for pain is a continuous scale comprised of a horizontal line, which was 10 centimeters (100 mm) in length, anchored by 2 verbal descriptors, one for each symptom extreme (from 0 cm means no pain to 10cm means worst pain possible) for patients self-assessment of pain.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>post operation shoulder swelling</measure>
    <time_frame>measure on post operative day one's morning through study completion, an average of 1 year.</time_frame>
    <description>(compared the circumference of shoulder post op day 1 to the day of admission which were measured at two sites: axillary and deltoid),</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>change of serum hemoglobin before and after operation</measure>
    <time_frame>measure on post operative day one's morning through study completion, an average of 1 year.</time_frame>
    <description>use the change of Hb to calculate estimate blood loss by Gross formula.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">72</enrollment>
  <condition>Rotator Cuff Tears</condition>
  <condition>Shoulder Arthorscopy Surgery</condition>
  <condition>Surgical Blood Loss</condition>
  <condition>Tranexamic Acid</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Patients received Tranexamic acid</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The patient was assigned as intervention group, TXA will be aspirated into a syringe. In TXA group, TXA 1000 mg (20 mL) was given intravenously 10 minutes before surgery.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Patients received same volume of saline</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>In the control group, the patient received 20ml saline intravenous also 10 min before surgery.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Tranexamic Acid 100Mg/Ml Inj Vil 10Ml</intervention_name>
    <description>Tranexamic acid (TXA) is a synthetic analog of the amino acid lysine which acts by competitively blocking the plasminogen lysine-binding site and inhibiting fibrinolysis. Several studies showed that TXA could reduce both blood loss and the amount of blood transfusion after shoulder arthroplasty surgeries.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Patients received Tranexamic acid</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>0.9% Sodium Chloride Injection</intervention_name>
    <description>Normal saline is a mixture of sodium chloride in water and has a number of uses in medicine. We use the same volume of normal saline as placebo.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Patients received same volume of saline</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients who were diagnosed with rotator cuff tear and failure of conservative
             treatment for more than 3 months. The tear size was measured by MRI and must be
             repairable.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Acute traumatic rotator cuff tear.

          -  History of coagulopathy

          -  Under anticoagulation therapy before surgery

          -  Abnormal coagulation profile (prothrombin time or activated partial thromboplastin
             time) before surgery

          -  Renal or liver disorder

          -  Uncontrolled hypertension (baseline systolic pressure &amp;gt;180 mmHg)

          -  Allergy to local anesthetic agent or TXA.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Cheng Kung University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tainan</city>
        <zip>704</zip>
        <country>Taiwan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Taiwan</country>
  </location_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>van Montfoort DO, van Kampen PM, Huijsmans PE. Epinephrine Diluted Saline-Irrigation Fluid in Arthroscopic Shoulder Surgery: A Significant Improvement of Clarity of Visual Field and Shortening of Total Operation Time. A Randomized Controlled Trial. Arthroscopy. 2016 Mar;32(3):436-44. doi: 10.1016/j.arthro.2015.08.027.</citation>
    <PMID>26524933</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Karaaslan F, Karaoğlu S, Yurdakul E. Reducing Intra-articular Hemarthrosis After Arthroscopic Anterior Cruciate Ligament Reconstruction by the Administration of Intravenous Tranexamic Acid: A Prospective, Randomized Controlled Trial. Am J Sports Med. 2015 Nov;43(11):2720-6. doi: 10.1177/0363546515599629. Epub 2015 Sep 2.</citation>
    <PMID>26337246</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Felli L, Revello S, Burastero G, Gatto P, Carletti A, Formica M, Alessio-Mazzola M. Single Intravenous Administration of Tranexamic Acid in Anterior Cruciate Ligament Reconstruction to Reduce Postoperative Hemarthrosis and Increase Functional Outcomes in the Early Phase of Postoperative Rehabilitation: A Randomized Controlled Trial. Arthroscopy. 2019 Jan;35(1):149-157. doi: 10.1016/j.arthro.2018.07.050.</citation>
    <PMID>30611343</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Kirsch JM, Bedi A, Horner N, Wiater JM, Pauzenberger L, Koueiter DM, Miller BS, Bhandari M, Khan M. Tranexamic Acid in Shoulder Arthroplasty: A Systematic Review and Meta-Analysis. JBJS Rev. 2017 Sep;5(9):e3. doi: 10.2106/JBJS.RVW.17.00021. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>28902659</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>July 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 14, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 17, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 19, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 17, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 17, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 19, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Tranexamic Acid</keyword>
  <keyword>Shoulder Arthroscopy</keyword>
  <keyword>Visual Clarity</keyword>
  <keyword>Hemostasis</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Blood Loss, Surgical</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Rotator Cuff Injuries</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Tranexamic Acid</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Statistical Analysis Plan (SAP)</ipd_info_type>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

