<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04022187</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PGRC 001 GREEN</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04022187</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Assessment of the Excitability of Spinal Motoneurons Using Stimulus-response Curves of the Bulbocavernosus Reflex</brief_title>
  <official_title>Assessment of the Excitability of Spinal Motoneurons Using Stimulus-response Curves of the Bulbocavernosus Reflex</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Pierre and Marie Curie University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Pierre and Marie Curie University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Spasticity is commonly observed in neurological conditions such as Multiple Sclerosis and
      spinal cord injury. &quot;Peripheral&quot; spasticity, concerning in particular the striated muscles of
      the limbs is nowadays well known and studied with clinical scales (Ashworth, Taridieu...) or
      even electrophysiological methods (H-reflex, T-reflex...). However, this spasticity can also
      affect the perineal muscles and more generally the pelvic muscles. However, there is to date
      no validated and standardized method for evaluating this pelvi-perineal spasticity.

      The aim of the study will be to assess the spinal motoneurons excitability by using the
      stimulus-response curves of the bulbocavernosus reflex.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Spasticity defined by Lance in 1980 is &quot;a motor disorder characterized by a velocity
      dependent increase in the tonic stretch reflexes (muscle tone) with exaggerated tendon jerks,
      resulting from hyperexcitability of the stretch reflexes as one component of the upper motor
      neuron syndrome&quot;. The occurrence of spasticity, which is common in neurology when the
      pyramidal tract is affected, is commonly observed in the &quot;peripheral&quot; striated muscles.
      However, spasticity also concerns the perineal musculature, with &quot;the exaggeration of the
      stretching reflex of the muscles accessible to pelvic touches&quot;. Although there are
      measurement scales commonly used in clinical practice, such as the Ashworth and Tardieu
      scales, or electrophysiological instrumental techniques (H reflex , T reflex), there is
      actually no objective and standardized measurement technique for pelvic spasticity. An
      interesting tool could be the bulbocavernosus reflex (BCR) which is a polysynaptic reflex
      with sacral integration. In addition to its diagnostic and topographical value due to its
      sacral integration, BCR could testify, by its modulation, to the control of the alpha motor
      neuron pool. It could therefore allow to assess motoneuronal excitability, whose increase may
      lead in central patients with supra-connal lesions (spinal cord injuries (SCI), multiple
      sclerosis (MS)), to a release of sacral automatism with exacerbation of reflex responses
      whether bladder (detrusor overactivity), sphincter (detrusor-sphincter dysynergia) or rectal
      (rectal overactivity).

      The aim of the study will be to assess the sacral spinal motor neuron excitability using the
      stimulus-response curves of the BCR.

      The investigators will conduct a prospective monocentric observational study in a specialized
      neuro-urology department. The main objective of this study will be to evaluate the spinal
      motoneuron excitability according to the degree of bladder repletion by modelling recruitment
      slopes (stimulus-response curves) of the BCR.

      First of all, the investigators will assess the feasibility of conducting an analysis of BCR
      stimulus-response curves during a perineal electrophysiological exploration performed in a
      diagnostic context in patients referred for urinary, anorectal or genito-sexual disorders.
      BCR will be recorded after electrical stimulation of the dorsal nerve of the penis or the
      dorsal nerve of the clitoris, using a concentric needle electrode inserted into the left and
      then right bulbcavernous muscle. Stimulations will be performed at progressively increasing
      intensities and each response will be recorded. Acquisition will be performed using a Dantec™
      Keypoint® G4 EMG device, Natus®. The initial stimulation intensity will be at the motor
      threshold, i.e. the degree of stimulation that determines a stable latent motor response and
      will then be increased by 10 to 10 mA to obtain the following 4 reflex responses. Once the
      acquisition will be completed, the curves will be analyzed allowing the analysis of the area
      under the curve (AUC) and the construction of the stimulus-response curves.

      In a second step, the investigators will evaluate the possibility of modelling these
      stimulus-response curves after EMG recording using pre-gelled disposable surface electrodes
      placed on the external anal sphincter (EAS) during a cystometry performed in patients
      consulting for urinary disorders. The stimulation technique will be identical as described
      previously. Finally, the modulation of spinal motoneurons excitability according to the
      degree of bladder filling will be assessed by modelling the BCR stimulus-response curves,
      before and during a cystometry.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 11, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 30, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">July 11, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Other</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Variation of the recruitment slope according to the degree of bladder repletion</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day</time_frame>
    <description>For each patient, an assessment of spinal motoneuron excitability by using the area under the motor response curve of the bulbocavernous reflex will be performed before starting the cystometry (empty bladder) and during urgent urination needs (also during the cystometry) to determine an alpha angle of the recruitment curve. The primary outcome is the variation in this alpha coefficient.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Comparison of the variation of recruitment slope according to the bladder repletion : (empty bladder - B1) versus (B1-B3) variation</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Influence of neurological disease on spinal motoneuron excitability</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day</time_frame>
    <description>comparison of the variation of the recruitment slope observed in neurological subjects versus non-neurological subjects.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Spasticity, Muscle</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Bulbocavernosus reflex assessment</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients over 18 years old, consulting in neuro-urology department for urinary, anorectal or genito-sexual disorders.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Observational study : no intervention</intervention_name>
    <description>Observational study : no intervention, only exporting data</description>
    <arm_group_label>Bulbocavernosus reflex assessment</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Adult patients who will be referred to our specialized neuro-urology service for
        electrophysiological and urodynamic explorations
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  18 years old minimum

          -  Subjects with spinal cord injury or multiple sclerosis, requiring an
             electrophysiological and urodynamic explorations in our neuro-urology specialized
             department, with a strictly supra-sacral central neurological condition.

          -  Subjects with stress urinary incontinence (SUI) requiring perineal explorations
             including a cystometry and a perineal EMG.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects with peripheral neurological impairment (cauda equina syndrome, medullary
             cone syndrome, advanced diabetes)

          -  Subjects who received a treatment by injection of intra-detrusorian botulinum toxin in
             the last 6 months.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>90 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Gérard Amarenco, PHD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Sorbonne Université, GRC 001, GREEN, AP-HP, Hôpital Tenon, Paris, France</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Gabriel Miget, MD</last_name>
    <phone>0156017500</phone>
    <phone_ext>33</phone_ext>
    <email>greengrc01@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Gérard Amarenco, PHD</last_name>
    <phone>0156017500</phone>
    <phone_ext>33</phone_ext>
    <email>greengrc01@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of neuro-urology, hôpital Tenon</name>
      <address>
        <city>Paris</city>
        <zip>75020</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Gabriel Miget, MD</last_name>
      <phone>0156017500</phone>
      <phone_ext>33</phone_ext>
      <email>greengrc01@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Gérard Amarenco, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>0156017500</phone>
      <phone_ext>33</phone_ext>
      <email>greengrc01@gmail.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Gérard Amarenco, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Gabriel Miget, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 13, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 13, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 17, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 16, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 16, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 18, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Pierre and Marie Curie University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Gérard Amarenco</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Head of Neuro-Urology department, Tenon Hospital</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Bulbocavernosus reflex</keyword>
  <keyword>Spasticity assessment</keyword>
  <keyword>Motoneurone excitability</keyword>
  <keyword>Stimulus-response curves</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Muscle Spasticity</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

