<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04024384</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>APHP180470</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04024384</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Daratumumab as Maintenance After Peripheral Blood Stem Cell Transplantation From HLA-identical or Haploidentical Family Donor in the Treatment of Refractory or Relapsed Multiple Myeloma: a Phase 2 Trial</brief_title>
  <acronym>DARALLO</acronym>
  <official_title>Daratumumab as Maintenance After Peripheral Blood Stem Cell Transplantation From HLA-identical or Haploidentical Family Donor in the Treatment of Refractory or Relapsed Multiple Myeloma: a Phase 2 Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Assistance Publique - Hôpitaux de Paris</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Assistance Publique - Hôpitaux de Paris</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The present protocol aims to test, whether an approach using (i) a reduced-toxicity TBF
      followed by a (ii) Daratumumab maintenance and (iii) prophylactic infusion of donor
      lymphocytes (pDLI), will be able to improve progression-free survival of patients with
      refractory or relapsed MM. This trial represents the first prospective protocol aiming to
      test the use of Daratumumab maintenance after HLA-identical or haploidentical allo-SCT in
      patients with MM.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Allogeneic stem cell transplantation in patients with multiple myeloma (MM) Outcomes for
      patients with MM who are resistant to proteasome inhibitors (bortezomib) and immunomodulatory
      drugs (lenalidomide, thalidomide) are dramatically poor. The median expected overall survival
      (OS) in these patients is 9 months. New drugs such as pomalidomide or carfilzomib, when used
      in monotherapy, can only offer a median progression free survival (PFS) of 3.8 months and OS
      of 11.9 and 13.4 months, respectively.

      Allogeneic stem cell transplantation (allo-SCT) remains the most reasonable treatment option,
      apart from palliative care, in patients with refractory or relapsed MM. No other strategy is
      able to offer any chance of cure for a patient at this stage. However, in the context of
      standard myeloablative (MAC) allo-SCT, results are limited in terms of feasibility in the
      larger patients' population who is in need, and by both a relatively high relapse incidence
      (RI) and especially high non-relapse mortality (NRM). Also, in the last decade, the advent of
      reduced intensity conditioning (RIC) allo-SCT and the improvement in supportive care
      management regarding infectious complications allowed a significant reduction of NRM. RIC
      expanded the transplant option to those patients who are ineligible for standard MAC allo-SCT
      either because of age or because of pre-existing comorbid conditions. While NRM is over 40%
      with MAC, relapse incidence remains high with either RIC or MAC. The major reason for
      treatment failure after allo-SCT for MM has become relapse, which is between 38% and 55%.
      Median PFS ranges from 10% to 32%. Thus, strategies to prevent relapse after allo-SCT for MM
      remain an unmet medical need.

      Post-transplant maintenance therapy Consolidation/maintenance post-transplantation for MM has
      demonstrated to not only upgrade but also deepen the response, which translates into improved
      PFS. Studies investigated immunomodulatory drugs, thalidomide or lenalidomide, as maintenance
      therapy after allo-SCT. The observed activation of natural killer and regulatory T cells
      induced by immunomodulatory drugs provides an attractive rationale for its use
      post-transplant. But some concerns are raised by a high rate of graft-versus-host disease
      (GVHD) induction. In the prospective HOVON 76 trial, 43% patients stopped lenalidomide
      maintenance because of development of GVHD, 17% patients because of other adverse events, and
      17% patients because of progression. Thus, lenalidomide maintenance after RIC allo-SCT in MM
      patients is not feasible, mainly because of the toxicity and the induction of acute GVHD.

      Daratumumab, a human IgG1 monoclonal antibody that binds CD38-expressing malignant cells with
      high affinity and induces tumor cell death, has recently shown promising results in a phase 2
      trial. Daratumumab was well tolerated, median PFS was 3.7 months and median duration of
      response was 7.4 months in patients who were refractory to both proteasome inhibitors and
      immunomodulatory drugs. Our first pilot experience, based on 3 patients with refractory MM
      suggests that Daratumumab maintenance is feasible. No grade 3-4 toxicities were observed.
      None of the patients experienced GVHD. After a median follow-up of 12 months, none of these
      patients relapsed. Thus, Daratumumab appears to be the ideal candidate to propose
      immunotherapy maintenance and reinforce the post-transplant immunomodulation strategy.

      Prophylactic donor lymphocyte infusions Given that relapsed or refractory patients are at
      very high risk of relapse, prophylactic donor lymphocyte infusion (pDLI) is a promising
      approach to prevent relapse after allo-SCT. pDLI can improve remission status in 54% of the
      patients and result in 5-year PFS of 79%. The incidence and severity of acute GVHD remains
      manageable.

      Type of donor Haploidentical family donors allow finding a quickly available donor for a
      majority of patients. T-cell replete haploidentical allo-SCT has now become feasible with the
      use of post-graft Cyclophosphamide, which reduces the risk of GVHD. In patients with relapsed
      or refractory hematologic malignancies, studies show no significant difference in terms of
      toxicity and outcomes between patients undergoing allo-SCT from a HLA-identical sibling and a
      haploidentical donor. Compared with unrelated donors, the outcomes are improved in
      haploidentical recipients. Thus, for these advanced patients, one should look first for a
      related donor, either matched or haploidentical. Searching for an unrelated donor may delay
      the procedure, with a risk of losing the opportunity for transplantation, and may be
      associated with worse outcomes compared with haploidentical allo-SCT.

      Few studies have reported the outcomes of patients with MM after haploidentical allo-SCT. The
      most encouraging results have been reported with the RIC associating thiotepa, busulfan and
      fludarabine (TBF) in patients with heavily pretreated MM. The median 18-month PFS, OS and NRM
      were 33%, 63% and 10%, respectively.

      The present protocol aims to test, whether an approach using (i) a reduced-toxicity TBF
      followed by a (ii) Daratumumab maintenance and (iii) prophylactic infusion of donor
      lymphocytes (pDLI), will be able to improve progression-free survival of patients with
      refractory or relapsed MM. This trial represents the first prospective protocol aiming to
      test the use of Daratumumab maintenance after HLA-identical or haploidentical allo-SCT in
      patients with MM.

      This is a prospective, multicenter, open, non-randomized Phase II study that will include a
      total number of 38 patients included over a period of 2 years.

      The population of the study is women and men adults (18-70 years) with refractory or relapsed
      multiple myeloma.

      Treatment period will be 12 months Duration of inclusions will be 24 months So, total study
      duration (eg. 12 months after inclusion of last patient)will be 36 months

      Each patient will receive: Daratumumab, 16 mg/kg, once a week for 8 weeks (cycles 1 and 2);
      then every 2 weeks for 16 weeks (cycles 3-6), then every 4 weeks thereafter (cycles 7-12).

      A Patient is only eligible if:

        -  Absolute neutrophil count &gt; 1 G/L

        -  Haemoglobin concentration &gt; 7.5 g/dL

        -  Platelets &gt; 50 G/L

        -  Estimated glomerular filtration rate &gt; 20 mL/min according to CDK-EPI

        -  Is free of grade 2-4 acute GVHD since &gt;30 days

        -  Is free of active infections

      Is an interim analysis planned, if yes, list and specify timing(s): no Final study report
      timing after Last Patient, Last Visit: 3 months Publication submission timing after final
      study report: 3 months

      The primary objective is to demonstrate that PFS at 12 months is higher than 40%. The trial
      would be designed to test the hypothesis P &lt; 20% versus P&gt;40% with one sided type I error
      rate 5% and power 80%. Using a one step A'Hern procedure, 35 patients should be transplanted.
      The analysis will be based on a binomial test comparing the observed 12 months PFS to 40%. In
      all, 38 patients will be included (taking into account that after registration, there is a
      risk of dropout i.e. patients, who will not receive a transplant due to rapidly progressive
      disease, infection or other events occurring after identification of a donor, but before
      start of conditioning).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Withdrawn</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Promotor decision
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">July 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2024</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>safety and efficacy of Daratumumab assessed by free survival</measure>
    <time_frame>1-year progression free survival in such patients</time_frame>
    <description>The primary objective is to assess the 1-year progression free survival in such patients. If the smallest response proportion (pnew=0.4) could be achieved compare to the lowest response probability of interest (phypo=0.2), the treatment strategy would worth to be developed further.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Disease response rate</measure>
    <time_frame>day +30, day +90 and 12 months after transplantation</time_frame>
    <description>Disease response rate at day +30, day +90 and 12 months after transplantation</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months after transplantation</time_frame>
    <description>Overall survival, at 12 months after transplantation</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>GVHD-free</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months after transplantation</time_frame>
    <description>GVHD-free, at 12 months after transplantation</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Relapse-free survival</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months after transplantation</time_frame>
    <description>Relapse-free survival at 12 months after transplantation</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cumulative incidence of relapse, death from disease, and non-relapse mortality</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months after transplantation.</time_frame>
    <description>Cumulative incidence of relapse, death from disease, and non-relapse mortality within the first 12 months after transplantation.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cumulative incidence of chronic GVHD as assessed by NIH Consensus Criteria</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months after transplantation.</time_frame>
    <description>Cumulative incidence of chronic GVHD as assessed by NIH Consensus Criteria within the first 12 months after transplantation.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Serious adverse events of Daratumumab and number of infusion per patient</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months after transplantation.</time_frame>
    <description>Serious adverse events of Daratumumab and number of infusion per patient</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Serious adverse events of prophylactic donor lymphocytes infusion (pDLI) and number of infusion per patient</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months after transplantation.</time_frame>
    <description>Serious adverse events of prophylactic donor lymphocytes infusion (pDLI) and number of infusion per patient</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of Life</measure>
    <time_frame>at day-7, +30, +90, +180 and +360</time_frame>
    <description>Quality of Life at day-7, +30, +90, +180 and +360</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>immune response analysis</measure>
    <time_frame>(before transplant, 30 days after transplant, 1 year after transplant and in case of disease relapse)</time_frame>
    <description>immune response analysis (before transplant, 30 days after transplant, 1 year after transplant and in case of disease relapse)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">0</enrollment>
  <condition>Multiple Myeloma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Daratumumab</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Daratumumab as maintenance after peripheral blood stem cell transplantation from HLA-identical or haploidentical family donor in the treatment of refractory or relapsed multiple myeloma</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Daratumumab</intervention_name>
    <description>Daratumumab, 16 mg/kg, once a week for 8 weeks (cycles 1 and 2); then every 2 weeks for 16 weeks (cycles 3-6), then every 4 weeks thereafter (cycles 7-12).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Daratumumab</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Confirmed diagnosis of multiple myeloma

          -  Disease who progressed on salvage therapy or progressed within 60 days of the last
             treatment in patients who previously achieved at least a minimal response to treatment

          -  Stable disease or better 1 month before transplantation

          -  Age &gt; 18 and &lt; 70 years.

          -  Availability of an HLA-haploidentical or HLA-identical family donor

          -  Written informed consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Presence in the patient of donor HLA-specific antibodies (DSA) directed against the
             HLA haplo-identical family donor

          -  Karnofsky score &lt;70%

          -  HIV positive patient, chronic or active Hepatitis B or Hepatitis C

          -  Life expectancy less than one month according to the attending physician

          -  Acute or chronic heart failure (Cardiac ejection fraction &lt; 40%)

          -  Pulmonary function - diffusion capacity &lt; 50% predicted

          -  Estimated glomerular filtration rate &lt; 30 ml/min (CKD-EPI)

          -  Severe neurological or psychiatric disorders

          -  Any circumstances that preclude the use of the drugs used within the protocol

          -  Prior allogeneic stem cell transplantation

          -  Pregnancy or denied of effective contraceptive method
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Rémy Dulery, PHD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Assistance Publique - Hôpitaux de Paris</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Service d'hématologie clinique et thérapie cellulaire</name>
      <address>
        <city>Paris</city>
        <zip>75012</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 1, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 16, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 18, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 25, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 25, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 27, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Myeloma</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Multiple Myeloma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms, Plasma Cell</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Daratumumab</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

