<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04024657</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PHT/2018/71</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04024657</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Cross Sectional, Diagnostic Accuracy Study to Validate the Use of a New Device(Inflammacheck™) in Diagnosing COPD</brief_title>
  <acronym>EXHALE 1V</acronym>
  <official_title>A Cross Sectional, Diagnostic Accuracy Study to Validate the Use of a New Device(Inflammacheck™) in Diagnosing COPD by Measuring the Level of Exhaled Breath Condensate Hydrogen Peroxide (EBC H2O2)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Portsmouth Hospitals NHS Trust</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Portsmouth Hospitals NHS Trust</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      A cross-sectional, diagnostic accuracy study to evaluate the use of the 'Inflammacheck™'
      device in the diagnosis of COPD.

      Participants will be asked to provide an exhaled breath sample for measurement of their EBC
      H2O2 using 'Inflammacheck™'. The result will be correlated with spirometry (FEV1/ FVC ratio)
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      A key component of COPD is airway inflammation. Current tools for assessing airway
      inflammation and oxidative stress, such as fibre-optic bronchoscopy with bronchial wall
      biopsy and bronchial fluid lavage, are invasive procedures not suitable for routine clinical
      practice or regular repeat sampling. Sample analysis requires a series of laboratory
      measurements and results can take over 24 hours to become available.

      Non-invasive methods of measuring airway inflammation assess exhaled gases. Fractional
      exhaled Nitric Oxide (FeNO) measures eosinophilic airway inflammation. However, FeNO does not
      provide information about neutrophilic airway inflammation, a recognised component of Chronic
      Obstructive Pulmonary Disease (COPD).

      In contrast, measurement of Exhaled Breath Condensate Hydrogen Peroxide (EBC H2O2) is
      performed during normal tidal breathing, and is well tolerated even in patients with severe
      airways obstruction and those unable to perform a consistent controlled exhalation. It is
      also not limited to inflammatory cell specific inflammation. It has the potential to diagnose
      COPD and to give information about the degree of airway inflammation.

      Exhalation Technology Ltd. Have developed a novel, handheld device (Inflammacheck™) which can
      produce a measurement of EBC H2O2 levels at the patient's side. By detecting EBC H2O2 levels
      immediately, Inflammacheck™ could tell potentially clinicians and patients the current level
      of global airway inflammation in a simple, effort independent manner. This could be used by
      clinicians to diagnose COPD both in hospital and in the community. Previous studies using the
      'Inflammacheck™' device have shown that there is a difference in the EBC H2O2 between
      participants with COPD and those with no underlying lung disease. It has the potential to
      further measure increased levels of airway inflammation that may indicate an exacerbation of
      a persons' respiratory disease.

      The 'Inflammacheck™' device now requires a study in a clinical setting to validate its use in
      accurately diagnosing COPD.

      The investigators hypothesise that the The 'Inflammacheck™' device will be able to accurately
      diagnose patients with COPD using EBC H2O2 as compared to the gold standard of Spirometry.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">December 17, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Retrospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Level of exhaled breath condensate hydrogen peroxide (EBC H2O2)</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day study visit</time_frame>
    <description>Respiratory outcome EBC H202 as measured by the inflammacheck sensor</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety outcome</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day study visit</time_frame>
    <description>incidence of adverse events reported during the study procedures</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Experience outcome</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day study visit</time_frame>
    <description>Rating of ease of use test assessed by Self Completion Questionnaire</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Experience outcome</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day study visit</time_frame>
    <description>Rating of whether test is acceptable to participant assessed by Self Completion Questionnaire</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Experience outcome</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day study visit</time_frame>
    <description>Participants' perception of the device assessed by Self Completion Questionnaire</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">260</enrollment>
  <condition>COPD Exacerbation</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        COPD patients and healthy controls
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Male or Female, aged ≥40 years.

          -  A confirmed, clinician made diagnosis of COPD supported by spirometric evidence of
             fixed airflow limitation (post-bronchodilator ratio of FEV1/FVC &lt;0.7) recorded at any
             time.

          -  OR no known history of lung disease (defined as no current clinical diagnosis of, or
             be receiving treatment for, a lung disease) and be a current non-smoker. Ex-smokers
             with a less than 5 pack year history of smoking (cigarettes and cannabis) and who have
             stopped smoking ≥6 months ago can be included.

          -  Willing and able to give informed consent for participation in the study.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Existing co-morbidities that may prevent them from performing spirometry (at the
             discretion of the clinical investigator).

          -  Known other lung, chest wall, neuromuscular, or cardiac disease (including end-stage
             disease or cancer) that would confound Inflammacheck™ measurements and spirometry (at
             the discretion of the clinical investigator).

          -  Has received treatment for an exacerbation of their COPD within the last 2 weeks.

          -  In the opinion of the clinical investigator, participant could be put at risk of harm
             by having to perform any of the study procedures.

          -  Unable to comprehend the study and provide informed consent e.g. insufficient command
             of English in the absence of someone to adequately interpret.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>40 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Anoop Chauhan</last_name>
    <phone>02392286000</phone>
    <phone_ext>6263</phone_ext>
    <email>anoop.chauhan@porthosp.nhs.uk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Elaine Baddeley</last_name>
    <phone>02392286000</phone>
    <phone_ext>6263</phone_ext>
    <email>research.office@porthosp.nhs.uk</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Portsmouth Hospitals NHS Trust</name>
      <address>
        <city>Portsmouth</city>
        <state>Hampshire</state>
        <zip>PO6 3LY</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Alice Mortlock</last_name>
      <phone>02392 286000</phone>
      <phone_ext>6236</phone_ext>
      <email>research.office@porthosp.nhs.uk</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 3, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 17, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 18, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 17, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 17, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 18, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

