<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04027972</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>KOR-18-16</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04027972</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Pharmacokinetics of Neostigmine and Glycopyrrolate</brief_title>
  <official_title>Pharmacokinetics of Neostigmine and Glycopyrrolate After Intravenous and Transcutaneous Administration by Iontophoresis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>James J. Peters Veterans Affairs Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>James J. Peters Veterans Affairs Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      A group of 6 able-bodied healthy volunteers will receive Neostigmine (NEO) and Glycopyrrolate
      (GLY) intravenously and via 3 different methods of Iontophoresis (ION) with subsequent blood
      draws over 1 hour in order to measure the pharmacokinetic behavior of the drugs en-vivo.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The maximum dose of NEO is limited to 10.0 mg and the dose of GLY to 2.0 mg per subject per
      administration. Subjects will be asked to arrive at the Spinal Cord Research Center at the
      JJP VAMC (Room 7A-13) on the day of their appointment. On Day 1, following the obtainment the
      subject's consent, filling out a MoCA cognitive assessment and establishing an IV access
      point, administration of the medications via IV will be performed. The study design will
      consist of a Day 1to determine the pharmacokinetic profiles of the IV doses of NEO and GLY.
      During the second visit, at least 24 hours later, two patches with separately-applied NEO
      (0.035mg/kg) and GLY (0.007mg/kg) on separate patches will be simultaneously delivered by
      transdermal administration by ION for 20 minutes. Due to the doubling of cumulative current
      delivered, the dosage applied has been halved in an attempt to deliver approximately the same
      dose of medications systemically. During the third and final visit, at least 24 hours
      following the second visit, a single patch containing 0.07mg/kg of NEO and 0.0014mg/kg of GLY
      will be applied to the skin and delivered by transdermal administration by ION for 20
      minutes..

      Heart rate, bowel sounds, blood pressure and symptoms will be recorded at 0, 2, 4, 7, 10, 20,
      40, 60 minutes of the initiation of the IV push and at 0, 10, 20, 40 and 60 minutes after the
      initiation of ION. Bowel evacuation time and time after the completion of delivery (by either
      ION or IV) will be recorded throughout the study visit, as described in Table 2. The subject
      will assume his/her normal bowel evacuation (BE) position until a bowel movement occurs;
      privacy draping and privacy will be provided at the time of BE. The subjects will be
      monitored for a minimum of 60 minutes. A minimum of two research personnel will be present
      during the study visit to record all of data and perform the tasks required.

      After the start a 30 second IV push of NEO which will be followed by a NS flush (12mL), and
      then a 30 second IV push of GLY which will be followed by a NS flush (12mL), venous blood (2
      mL) will be drawn into a gold-topped vial at 2, 4, 7, 10, 20, 40 and 60 minutes. Identical
      technique blood draws will be performed at 10, 20, 30, 40 and 60 minutes after the start of
      ION. Upon drawing, the blood will be placed in an ice bath and spun using a cooled centrifuge
      within 5 minutes of collection. Upon completion of 5 minutes of centrifugation, the resulting
      serum will be aliquoted into two separate vials, with equal volumes and labelled with date,
      time of draw, associated procedure, NEO or GLY testing destination and the subject's unique
      identifier. The transfer vials will be inserted into dry ice for at least 10 minutes, after
      which they will be placed into the -80 degrees Celsius freezer. Plasma levels of NEO and of
      GLY will be batched and measured at a later date. A file designating the tubes with random
      numbers associated with the draw times will be created for each subject to conceal the
      sequence of draw and to attempt the removal of possible bias during the measurement and
      recording of the concentrations of NEO (SUNY Downstate Albany Research Laboratory using GE
      LC-MRM detector) and GLY (JJPVAMC SCI Research Laboratory by ELISA).

      Proposed Doses:

      Day 1.: 0.02 mg/kg NEO and 0.004 mg/kg GLY via IV Day 2.: 0.035mg/kg NEO and 0.007mg/kg GLY
      via ION Day 3.: 0.07 mg/kg NEO and 0.014 mg/kg GLY via ION Day 4.: 0.07 mg/kg NEO and 0.014
      mg/kg GLY via ION
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">April 22, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 30, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 28, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Early Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Same group receives all 4 treatments but in a randomized order after the IV phase.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetic profile of Neostigmine and Glycopyrrolate within 1 hour post-administration via the measurement of the concentrations of Neostigmine and Glycopyrrolate in the serum of human subjects</measure>
    <time_frame>Within Two Hours</time_frame>
    <description>Measurement of serum concentration of Neostigmine and of Glycopyrrolate</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety (Presence of and graded severity of headache, dry mouth, muscle twitching and abdominal cramps.)</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 1 hour of administration</time_frame>
    <description>Presence of and graded severity of headache, dry mouth, muscle twitching and abdominal cramps as reported by the subjects on the scale of 0 to 10</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">6</enrollment>
  <condition>Pharmacokinetic Behavior of Neostigmine and Glycopyrrolate After Administration Via Different Routes</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Primary</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>6 Subjects will receive all 4 types of medication administration in random sequence</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Combination of Neostigmine and Glycopyrrolate</intervention_name>
    <description>Intravenous or transdermal</description>
    <arm_group_label>Primary</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>I-Box by Dynatronics</intervention_name>
    <description>Electric field conducting drugs through the skin without compromising its integrity</description>
    <arm_group_label>Primary</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Iontophoresis</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Male or Female

          -  Age 18-70 years

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Previous adverse reaction or hypersensitivity to electrical stimulation,

          -  Known sensitivity to neostigmine or glycopyrrolate,

          -  History of mechanical obstruction of the GI or urinary tract,

          -  Myocardial infarction within 6 months of trial,

          -  Malignant and/or Uncontrollable Hypertension Defined by a blood pressure reading of
             160/100 mmHg or higher with or without taking 3 or more different classes of
             anti-hypertensive medications,

          -  Organ damage (heart &amp; kidney) and/or TIA-CVA as a result of hypertension,

          -  Known past history of coronary artery disease or bradyarrhythmia,

          -  Symptomatic orthostatic hypotension

          -  Deep brain stimulation

          -  Pregnancy (women who are sexually active and of childbearing potential must utilize a
             method of contraception and agree to maintain a contraceptive method until completion
             of the study),

          -  Lactating, nursing females

          -  Inability to provide informed consent signaled by MoCA cognitive test score of 20 or
             less,

          -  History of ingrown hair folliculitis,

          -  Concurrent illness and fever,

          -  Concurrent participation in a research study,

          -  VA employee.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Anton Sabiev, MD</last_name>
    <phone>917 717 4643</phone>
    <email>anton.sabiev@va.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Mark Korsten, MD</last_name>
    <phone>718 584 5000</phone>
    <phone_ext>6753</phone_ext>
    <email>mark.korsten@va.gov</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>James J Peters VA Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bronx</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10468</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Anton Sabiev</last_name>
      <phone>917-717-4643</phone>
      <email>sabiev@hotmail.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 19, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 19, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 22, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 19, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 19, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 22, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Bronx VA Medical Center</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Dr. Mark Korsten</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Chief of Gastroenterology</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Neostigmine, Glycopyrrolate, Transdermal, Intravenous, Pharmacokinetic, Constipation, Bowel Control, Mass Spectroscopy, Stool Incontinence</keyword>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Glycopyrrolate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neostigmine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

