<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04025671</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>1098030</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04025671</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Usability Assessment of Naloxone Administration by Untrained Community Members</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Usability Assessment of Intramuscular, Atomized Intranasal, and Nasal Spray Administration of Naloxone by Untrained Community Members</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>State University of New York - Upstate Medical University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Binghamton University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>State University of New York - Upstate Medical University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This will be a randomized, open-label, usability assessment of intramuscular, intranasal, and
      nasal spray administration of naloxone using two different instruction sets by laypersons.

        -  Design: Single site, open-label, randomized usability assessment of intramuscular,
           intranasal, and nasal spray administration of simulated naloxone. A convenience sample
           of participants will consent to volunteer in the study at a public venue. Participants
           will provide verbal consent and will be randomly assigned a simulated naloxone kit
           containing either intramuscular, intranasal, or nasal spray administration materials
           with either standard or study team designed instructions for use. Participants will
           enter a use scenario station and be asked to assemble and administer the simulated
           naloxone kit to a mannequin (intranasal and nasal spray) or simulated flesh pad
           (intramuscular). The participant will be instructed to start and will be timed until the
           simulated naloxone has been successfully administered or 7 minutes has elapsed. The
           participant will be observed by one trained investigator who will assess for successful
           administration of the simulated naloxone and critical errors. The environment will
           contain distractors.Once the participant has successfully administered simulated
           naloxone or 7 minutes elapses the timer will be stopped. Successful administration of
           simulated naloxone will be defined as administration of the agent without any critical
           errors occurring (defined below). Data collected will include demographics (defined
           below), successful administration of simulated naloxone, time to successful
           administration of simulated naloxone, and Likert-item data assessing the ease of use of
           the device and instructions.

        -  Participants: adults (18 years of age and older) at a public venue will be asked to
           volunteer. Participants with severe visual or hearing impairment (defined as: legally
           deaf, legally blind, unable to read print size provided on instructional handout, or
           unable to hear video audio), that have previous naloxone administration training, that
           are not English proficient, that are pregnant, or that have previously participated in
           the trial will be excluded.

        -  Kits:

             1. Intranasal: simulated naloxone vial, bristoject, administration instructions
                (standard or study team designed)

             2. Intramuscular: sterile single use needle, sterile single use 3 mL syringe,
                simulated naloxone vial, administration instructions (standard or study team
                designed)

             3. Nasal spray: simulated naloxone spray, administration instructions (standard or
                study team designed)

        -  Objectives:

             1. Primary: successful administration of simulated naloxone in the time allowed. A
                successful administration will be defined as administration of the simulated
                naloxone to the mannequin head of simulated flesh pad within 7 minutes and without
                any critical errors (defined below).

             2. Secondary: time required to successfully administer the simulated naloxone and
                Likert-item assessment of ease of use of both the device and instructions.

        -  Data and Analysis:

             1. The usability trial will be conducted using a convenience sample so no power
                analysis will be conducted or minimum sample size defined

             2. Demographics: age, gender, handedness, level of education, and presence or absence
                of opioid at risk contacts.

             3. Data: successful administration, time to administration, and Likert-item assessment
                of both the device and instructions. Failure to administer the medication due to a
                critical use error will be recorded and the specific error reported for all
                participants.

        -  Critical Errors:

             1. Intranasal: failure to remove both yellow caps from bristoject, failure to remove
                cap from simulated naloxone, failure to attach atomizer, failure to attach
                simulated naloxone, drug leak prior to administration, administration in only one
                nostril, and failure to administer within 7 minutes.

             2. Intramuscular: failure to attach the needle to the syringe, failure to remove cap
                from simulated naloxone, failure to draw up &gt;90% (0.9 mL) of the simulated
                naloxone, failure to puncture simulated flesh pad with needle, failure to push
                entire volume of fluid in the syringe into the simulated flesh pad, and failure to
                administer within 7 minutes.

             3. Intranasal: failure to place the tip of the device into one nostril, failure to
                depress the device and release the simulated naloxone, failure to administer within
                7 minutes.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Background: Opioid abuse and addiction is a growing epidemic both in the United States and
      globally. It impacts the health, social welfare, and economic stability of those directly
      affected and society as a whole. According to the National Institute on Drug Abuse there are
      approximately 2.1 million people in the United States with substance use disorders related to
      prescription opioid medications and another 467,000 addicted to heroin. Data from the Center
      for Disease Control National Vital Statistics System demonstrated that the number of drug
      poisonings involving opioid analgesics tripled from 2000 to 2014, and in 2010 opioid pain
      relievers were responsible for 82.8% of all unintentional deaths in the United States.1 In an
      attempt to combat this epidemic many states have implemented community-based opioid overdose
      prevention programs aimed at increasing resources to combat addiction and distributing
      naloxone to community members. These programs increase knowledge of overdose prevention and
      the factors that increase a person's risk for overdose. Evaluations of these programs have
      also demonstrated that nonmedical bystanders are able to administer naloxone effectively
      after completing training.2 Naloxone can be administered intravenously, intramuscularly, or
      via inhalation. Opioid overdose prevention programs are typically initiated by local and
      state governments, which allows for interprogram variability regarding the route of naloxone
      administration used by community members. Pre-hospital data has demonstrated that intranasal
      naloxone is a safe and effective alternative to intravenous naloxone.3 A usability assessment
      comparing a naloxone auto-injector (Evzio®) to the use of a nasal atomizer suggested that the
      route of administration did impact the rate of successful naloxone administration by
      nonmedical community members.4 Opioid overdose prevention programs typically utilize
      intranasal atomizers, nasal inhalers, or intramuscular administration routes. In 2016 the
      investigators conducted a usability assessment of naloxone administered by community members
      who received training on how to use the naloxone device that was assigned. Our data supported
      that intranasal administration with an atomizer or spray resulted in a higher administration
      success rate when compared to intramuscular injection. Recently, New York, along with many
      other states, passed legislation allowing individuals to purchase naloxone over-the-counter
      without a prescription. This legislation has drastically expanded access to naloxone, but has
      reduced the opportunity to train community members purchasing the medication. The
      investigators plan to conduct a usability assessment of simulated naloxone in community
      members in the absence of training to assess the rate of successful administration and time
      to successful administration.

      Objectives:

      Primary: The successful administration of simulated naloxone without training. A successful
      administration will be defined as administration of the simulated naloxone to the mannequin
      head or simulated flesh pad within 7 minutes and without any critical errors (defined below).

      Secondary:

        -  Total time required to successfully administer the simulated naloxone without training.

        -  Comparison of successful administration with standard and simplified instructions

        -  Comparison of total time required for successful administration with standard and
           simplified instructions

        -  Likert-item assessment of the usability of the simulated naloxone product

        -  Likert-item assessment of usability of the naloxone administration instructions

      Design: Single site, open-label, randomized usability assessment of intramuscular,
      intranasal, and nasal spray administration of simulated naloxone using standard
      (package-insert) or simplified (developed by study team) instructions. A convenience sample
      of participants will consent to volunteer in the study at a public venue. Participants will
      provide verbal consent and will be randomly assigned a simulated naloxone kit containing
      either intramuscular standard, intramuscular simplified, intranasal standard, intranasal
      simplified, nasal spray standard, or nasal spray simplified administration materials. The
      participant will enter a use scenario station and will be asked to assemble and administer
      the simulated naloxone kit to a mannequin (intranasal and nasal spray) or simulated flesh pad
      (intramuscular). The participant will be instructed to start and will be timed until the
      simulated naloxone has been successfully administered or 7 minutes has elapsed. The
      participant will be observed by one trained investigator who will assess for successful
      administration of the simulated naloxone and critical errors. The environment will contain
      distracters to mimic a community based setting. Once the participant has successfully
      administered the simulated naloxone or 7 minutes has elapsed the timer will be stopped.
      Successful administration of simulated naloxone will be defined as administration of the
      agent without any critical errors occurring (defined below). Data collected will include
      demographics (defined below), successful administration of simulated naloxone, product
      assessment information, instruction assessment information, and time to successful
      administration of simulated naloxone.

      Eligibility: healthy adults (18 years of age and older) at a public venue will be asked to
      participate in the study. Participants with severe visual or hearing impairment (defined as:
      legally deaf, legally blind, unable to read print size provided on instructional handout, or
      unable to hear instructions from a research staff member), that have previous naloxone
      administration training, that are not English proficient, that are pregnant, or that have
      previously participated in the trial will be excluded.

      Statistical Methods: All data will be analyzed using IBM SPSS Statistics software.
      Demographics data will be analyzed using descriptive statistics for continuous measures and
      percentages for categorical measures. The successful administration of naloxone will be
      compared between groups using the Chi-square test and a significant difference will be
      defined as a p-value of less than 0.05 for the result. The time to administration between
      groups will be assessed using a one-way ANOVA and a significant difference will be defined as
      a p-value of less than 0.05 for the result. The Likert-item data will be reported as
      percentage of response level and analyzed using a one-way ANOVA with a significant difference
      defined as a p-value of less than 0.05 for comparison between administration methods and
      instruction methods.

      Data Analysis/Interpretation: As stated above data will be collected to assess both the
      successful administration of and time to administration of naloxone. The rate of successful
      administration will be reported as a percentage for each of the three groups and analyzed
      using the Chi-square test. Successful administration is defined as administration of the
      simulated naloxone within 7 minutes without committing any critical errors. Critical errors
      are as follows:

        -  Intranasal (atomizer): failure to remove both yellow caps from bristoject, failure to
           remove cap from simulated naloxone, failure to attach atomizer, failure to attach
           simulated naloxone, drug leak prior to administration, administration in only one
           nostril, and failure to administer within 7 minutes.

        -  Intramuscular: failure to attach the needle to the syringe, failure to remove cap from
           simulated naloxone, failure to draw up &gt;90% (0.9 mL) of the simulated naloxone, failure
           to puncture simulated flesh pad with needle, failure to push entire volume of fluid in
           the syringe into the simulated flesh pad, and failure to administer within 7 minutes.

        -  Intranasal (spray): failure to place the tip of the device into one nostril, failure to
           depress the device and release the simulated naloxone, failure to administer within 7
           minutes.

      Time to successful administration will be reported using descriptive statistics (mean time to
      administration) and analyzed using a one-way ANOVA. Times for participants who commit a
      critical error or who do no administer the simulated naloxone within 7 minutes will not be
      included in the analysis. The Likert-item data will be reported as a median with an
      inter-quartile range and analyzed using a one-way ANOVA.

      A route of administration will be considered to be more user-friendly if it demonstrates a
      statistically significantly higher rate of successful administration compared to another
      route of administration. Additionally, a route or instruction type will be considered user
      preferred if the Likert-item data demonstrates a significantly better score on usability.

      Study Procedures: No study procedures will be performed on study participants.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">August 23, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">September 3, 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">September 3, 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of participants who successfully administer the naloxone device</measure>
    <time_frame>7 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>Successfully administering the randomly assigned device within 7 minutes and without any critical errors.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time needed to successfully administer the naloxone device</measure>
    <time_frame>7 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>The time required to successfully administer the randomly assigned device. This outcome will only be assessed in participants who successfully administer their device (primary outcome).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Ease of use of the naloxone device according to each participant</measure>
    <time_frame>10 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>Participants will assess the ease of use of their randomly assigned device using a 10-item Likert scale. The scale has anchors of 1, 5, and 10. Participants will be instructed that 1 indicates extremely difficult to use, 5 indicates not difficult or easy to use, and 10 indicates extremely easy to use. The mean and median rating for each device will be recorded. No sub-scales will be assessed. A higher value will indicate that a device is perceived by participants as easier to use.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">208</enrollment>
  <condition>Harm Reduction</condition>
  <condition>Opioid-use Disorder</condition>
  <condition>Naloxone</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Nasal Spray Naloxone</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>This arm will be randomized to administer a nasal spray naloxone device in a simulated overdose setting.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intramuscular</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>This arm will be randomized to administer a intramuscular naloxone device in a simulated overdose setting.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Improvised Nasal Atomizer</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>This arm will be randomized to administer an improvised nasal atomizer naloxone device in a simulated overdose setting.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Nasal Spray Naloxone</intervention_name>
    <description>Nasal spray naloxone device.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Nasal Spray Naloxone</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Narcan Nasal Spray</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Intramuscular Naloxone</intervention_name>
    <description>A vial of simulated naloxone and syringe with attached needle.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intramuscular</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Improvised Nasal Atomizer</intervention_name>
    <description>A naloxone bristoject dose and nasal atomizer device.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Improvised Nasal Atomizer</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  18 years of age

          -  Able to provide verbal consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  less than 18 years of age

          -  pregnant

          -  had previous experience with naloxone administration or naloxone training
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>SUNY Upstate Medical University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Syracuse</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>13210</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 11, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 16, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 19, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 16, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 16, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 19, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>naloxone</keyword>
  <keyword>opioid use disorder</keyword>
  <keyword>harm reduction</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Substance-Related Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Naloxone</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>No participant identifiers will be collected, however we will share any data or protocol information by request. Data will not be made available on a publicly available site.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <provided_document_section>
    <provided_document>
      <document_type>Study Protocol and Statistical Analysis Plan</document_type>
      <document_has_protocol>Yes</document_has_protocol>
      <document_has_icf>No</document_has_icf>
      <document_has_sap>Yes</document_has_sap>
      <document_date>July 11, 2017</document_date>
      <document_url>https://ClinicalTrials.gov/ProvidedDocs/71/NCT04025671/Prot_SAP_000.pdf</document_url>
    </provided_document>
  </provided_document_section>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

