<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04024891</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>OPI-NYXRM-201 (MIRA-1)</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04024891</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Safety and Efficacy of Ophthalmic Phentolamine Mesylate to Reverse Pharmacologically Induced Mydriasis</brief_title>
  <official_title>Randomized, Cross-Over, Double-Masked, Placebo-Controlled Study of the Safety and Efficacy of Phentolamine Mesylate Ophthalmic Solution to Reverse Pharmacologically Induced Mydriasis in Normal Healthy Subjects</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Ocuphire Pharma, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Ocuphire Pharma, Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The objectives of this study are:

        -  To evaluate the efficacy of Nyxol (phentolamine mesylate ophthalmic solution 1%) to
           expedite the reversal of pharmacologic mydriasis

        -  To evaluate the safety of Nyxol

        -  To evaluate the effect of Lumify® to suppress conjunctival hyperemia (redness)
           potentially associated with administration of Nyxol
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Randomized, 2-arm cross-over, double-masked Phase 2b study in approximately 32 healthy
      subjects, evaluating safety and efficacy of Nyxol in subjects with pharmacologically induced
      mydriasis.

      At the first visit subjects will be screened for study eligibility.

      After screening, eligible subjects will be randomized 1:1 to one of the two treatment
      sequences:

      Treatment sequence 1: Placebo (Visit 1), Nyxol (Visit 2).

      Treatment sequence 2: Nyxol (Visit 1), Placebo (Visit 2).

      Randomization will be stratified by mydriatic agent (2.5% phenylephrine or 1% tropicamide).
      Approximately one half of the randomized subjects will receive 2.5% phenylephrine and one
      half will receive 1% tropicamide. Subjects will receive their mydriatic agent 1 hour before
      treatment. Each subject will receive the same mydriatic agent throughout the study.

      At each visit, pupil diameter (PD), accommodation, near and distance visual acuity (VA) and
      redness in each eye will be measured before (-1 hour/baseline) and 1 hour after (maximum/0
      minutes) the mydriatic agent instillation in each eye (i.e., right before the study treatment
      is administered), and at 30 minutes, 1 hour, 2 hours, 4 hours and 6 hours after treatment
      dosing.

      As needed, two hours post treatment, subjects may request the administration of Lumify® in
      the non-study eye.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">August 13, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">September 17, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">September 17, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pupil Diameter (Change from Max)</measure>
    <time_frame>2 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Change in pharmacologically-induced mydriatic (maximum) pupil diameter at 2 hours post-treatment in the study eye.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pupil Diameter (Change from Max)</measure>
    <time_frame>30 min, 1 hours, 4 hours, 6 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Change in pharmacologically-induced mydriatic (maximum) pupil diameter at remaining timepoints (30 min, 1 hours, 4 hours, 6 hours)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Accommodation Measured by the Near Point Rule (Diopters) (Change from Baseline)</measure>
    <time_frame>0 min, 30 min, 1 hour, 2 hours, 4 hours, 6 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Change from baseline (-1 hour) in accommodation at each timepoint (0 min, 30 min, 1 hour, 2 hours, 4 hours, 6 hours)
Worsening of accommodation is defined as an amplitude decrease of greater than 1 diopter compared to baseline</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Best Corrected Distance Visual Acuity (BCDVA) Measured by Early Treatment Diabetic Retinopathy Study (ETDRS) Light Box Chart (Letters) at 4 Meters (Change from Baseline)</measure>
    <time_frame>0 min, 30 min, 1 hour, 2 hours, 4 hours, 6 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Change from baseline (-1 hour) in BCDVA at each timepoint (0 min, 30 min, 1 hour, 2 hours, 4 hours, 6 hours)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Distance-Corrected Near Visual Acuity (DCNVA) Measured by Standard Reading Card (Original Series Sloan Letter ETDRS Card at 16 Inches, LogMAR Units) (Change from Baseline)</measure>
    <time_frame>0 min, 30 min, 1 hour, 2 hours, 4 hours, 6 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Change from baseline (-1 hour) in DCNVA at each timepoint (0 min, 30 min, 1 hour, 2 hours, 4 hours, 6 hours)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Conjunctival Hyperemia (Eye Redness) Assessed Visually with the Brien Holden Vision Institute (formerly Corneal and Contact Lens Research Unit, or CCLRU) Bulbar Redness Scale (0-3) (Change from Baseline)</measure>
    <time_frame>0 min, 30 min, 1 hour, 2 hours, 4 hours, 6 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Change from baseline (-1 hour) in conjunctival hyperemia at each timepoint (0 min, 30 min, 1 hour, 2 hours, 4 hours, 6 hours), for study eye and non-study eye; in all subjects, in subjects taking Lumify®, and in subjects not taking Lumify®</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">32</enrollment>
  <condition>Mydriasis</condition>
  <condition>Dilation</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Phentolamine Mesylate Ophthalmic Solution 1%</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>1 drop in each eye, 1 hour post medically-induced mydriasis</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Phentolamine Mesylate Ophthalmic Solution Vehicle</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>1 drop in each eye, 1 hour post medically-induced mydriasis</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Phentolamine Mesylate Ophthalmic Solution 1%</intervention_name>
    <description>1% phentolamine mesylate ophthalmic solution (Nyxol), a non-selective alpha-1 and alpha-2 adrenergic antagonist</description>
    <arm_group_label>Phentolamine Mesylate Ophthalmic Solution 1%</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Nyxol®</other_name>
    <other_name>Nyxol</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Phentolamine Mesylate Ophthalmic Solution Vehicle (Placebo)</intervention_name>
    <description>Topical Sterile Ophthalmic Solution</description>
    <arm_group_label>Phentolamine Mesylate Ophthalmic Solution Vehicle</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Males or females ≥ 18 and ≤ 45 years of age with brown irides (irises) only

          2. Otherwise healthy and well controlled subjects

          3. Able to comply with all protocol mandated procedures and to attend all scheduled
             office visits

          4. Willing to give written informed consent to participate in this study

        Exclusion Criteria

          1. Clinically significant ocular disease as deemed by the Investigator (e.g., cataract,
             glaucoma, corneal edema, uveitis, severe keratoconjunctivitis sicca) that might
             interfere with the study

          2. Unwilling or unable to discontinue use of contact lenses during treatment visits

          3. Ocular trauma, ocular surgery or non-refractive laser treatment within the 6 months
             prior to screening

          4. Ocular medication of any kind within 30 days of screening, with the exception of a)
             lid scrubs (which may have been used prior to, but not after screening) or b)
             lubricating drops for dry eye (preservative-free artificial tears), which may be used
             in between the study treatment days

          5. Recent or current evidence of ocular infection or inflammation. Current evidence of
             clinically significant blepharitis, conjunctivitis, or a history of herpes simplex or
             herpes zoster keratitis at screening

          6. History of diabetic retinopathy

          7. Closed or very narrow angles that in the Investigator's opinion are potentially
             occludable if the subject's pupil is dilated

          8. History of any traumatic (surgical or nonsurgical) or non-traumatic condition
             affecting the pupil or iris (e.g., irregularly shaped pupil, neurogenic pupil
             disorder, iris atrophy, iridotomy)

          9. Known allergy or contraindication to any component of the mydriatic agents or the
             vehicle formulation

         10. Known hypersensitivity or contraindication to α- and/or β-adrenoceptor antagonists
             (e.g., chronic obstructive pulmonary disease or bronchial asthma; abnormally low blood
             pressure (BP) or heart rate (HR); second- or third-degree heart blockage or Congestive
             Heart Failure (CHF); severe diabetes)

         11. Clinically significant systemic disease (e.g., uncontrolled diabetes, myasthenia
             gravis, cancer, hepatic, renal, endocrine or cardiovascular disorders) that might
             interfere with the study

         12. Initiation of treatment with or any changes to the current dosage, drug or regimen of
             any topical or systemic adrenergic or cholinergic drugs up to 7 days prior to
             screening, or during the study

         13. Participation in any investigational study within 30 days prior to screening

         14. Women of childbearing potential who are pregnant, nursing, planning a pregnancy, or
             not using a medically acceptable form of birth control. Acceptable methods include the
             use of at least one of the following: intrauterine device (IUD), hormonal (oral,
             injection, patch, implant, ring), barrier with spermicide (condom, diaphragm), or
             abstinence. An adult woman is considered to be of childbearing potential unless she is
             1 year postmenopausal or 3 months post-surgical sterilization. All females of
             childbearing potential must have a negative urine pregnancy test result at Visit
             1/Screening and Visit 2 examinations and must intend to not become pregnant during the
             study

         15. Resting heart rate (HR) outside the normal range (50-110 beats per minute) at the
             Screening Visit. HR may be repeated only once if outside the normal range following at
             least a 5-minute rest period in the sitting position

         16. Hypertension with resting diastolic BP &gt; 105 mmHg or systolic BP &gt; 160 mmHg at the
             Screening Visit. BP may be repeated only once if outside the specified range following
             at least a 5-minute rest period in the sitting position
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>45 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Kannar Eye Care</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pittsburg</city>
        <state>Kansas</state>
        <zip>66762</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Kentucky Eye Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lexington</city>
        <state>Kentucky</state>
        <zip>40517</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Athens Eye Care</name>
      <address>
        <city>Athens</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>45701</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>West Bay Eye Associates</name>
      <address>
        <city>Warwick</city>
        <state>Rhode Island</state>
        <zip>02888</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>August 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 11, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 16, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 18, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 10, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 10, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 14, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Nyxol</keyword>
  <keyword>Pharmacologically Induced Mydriasis</keyword>
  <keyword>Dilation</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Mydriasis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dilatation, Pathologic</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Phentolamine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ophthalmic Solutions</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pharmaceutical Solutions</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

