<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04029454</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2017-083</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04029454</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Neovac 2 Burkina Faso: Impact of the Integration of Hepatitis B Birth Dose Vaccine Into the Infant Immunization Schedule</brief_title>
  <acronym>NEOVAC2BK</acronym>
  <official_title>Neovac 2 Burkina Faso: Impact of the Integration of Hepatitis B Birth Dose Vaccine Into the Infant Immunization Schedule: a Mixed Methods Study Including a Cluster-randomized Trial, an Anthropological Study and an Economic Evaluation</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Institut Pasteur</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Agence de Médecine Préventive, France</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Centre Muraz</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Institut National de la Santé Et de la Recherche Médicale, France</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Institut Pasteur</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Hepatitis B virus (HBV) infection is an important global health problem, and the WHO adopted
      a strategy to eliminate HBV infection as a public health threat by the year 2030. In order to
      eliminate, it is critical to prevent the mother-to-child transmission (MTCT) of hepatitis B.
      Since 2009, the WHO recommends to administer hepatitis B vaccine within 24 hours of birth to
      prevent MTCT.2 However, in Africa, the majority of countries provide hepatitis B vaccine as a
      combined vaccine (pentavalent or hexavalent) at the age of 6-10-14 weeks or 8-12-16 weeks
      after the birth, and only 10 sub-Saharan African countries integrated birth dose vaccine into
      their national immunization program. This is because, the GAVI, the Vaccine Alliance, does
      not support monovalent hepatitis B vaccine, and also about half of babies in Africa are born
      at home without the immediate access to vaccination. Moreover, the evidence base to support
      this WHO's recommendation to start immunizing immediately at birth, rather than later at 6-8
      weeks of life, is not strong.

      Through a multidisciplinary approach comprising epidemiological, anthropological and economic
      components, the primary objective of the study is to measure the impact of the introduction
      of birth dose hepatitis B vaccine into the infant immunization program in Burkina Faso.

      Expected results will be to develop strong evidence base (effectiveness &amp; cost-effectiveness)
      to recommend the integration of birth dose hepatitis B vaccine into the current vaccination
      schedule (8-12-16 weeks as a combined vaccine), to facilitate the Burkinabé Government to
      include the birth dose hepatitis B vaccine in their national vaccination program, to inform
      other African countries which have not yet integrated the birth dose hepatitis B vaccine in
      their national program and to imply whether additional strategy (e.g., maternal screening and
      antiviral therapy during pregnancy) might be necessary in order to eliminate the risk of
      mother-to-child transmission of hepatitis B.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The study combines mixed methods to achieve its aim of evaluating the impact of the
      introduction of birth dose hepatitis B vaccine into the infant immunisation program in
      Burkina Faso. It is composed of 3 components:

      Workpackage (WP1): Stepped Wedge Cluster randomized controlled trial:

        -  to measure the impact of the introduction of birth dose hepatitis B vaccine into the
           infant immunization program on the mother-to-child transmission (primary objective)

        -  To examine a dose-dependent effect of hepatitis B vaccine (according to the total number
           of doses from one to four doses)

        -  To examine a time-dependent effect of the first dose of hepatitis B vaccine

        -  To study the impact of birth dose vaccine in infants aged at 9 months according to
           maternal HBsAg and HBeAg status

        -  To compare immunological responses in both groups by titration of anti-HBs antibodies in
           children at 9 months

        -  To describe vaccine coverage and its timeliness of birth dose hepatitis B vaccine and
           other routine infant vaccines in Burkina Faso

        -  To estimate the prevalence of HBV infection in mothers of 9-month-old children

      WP2: Anthropological study • To evaluate the acceptability of healthcare workers and people
      in the community about the integration of hepatitis B birth dose vaccine in the infant
      vaccination program in Burkina Faso

      WP3: Economic evaluation

      • To evaluate the cost-effectiveness of the integration of hepatitis B birth dose vaccine in
      the infant vaccination program, compared to the conventional vaccine schedule (8-12-16 weeks)
      in Burkina Faso

      All the pregnant women attending the antenatal care in the rural health centres of two health
      districts (Dafra and Dô) in Hauts Bassins Region in Burkina Faso, and their infants will be
      asked to participate.

      Practical sequence of the cluster randomised trial. Even though the evidence is weak and the
      implementation has been suboptimal, the WHO currently recommends the universal administration
      of hepatitis B vaccine at birth. For this reason, a &quot;stepped-wedge&quot; design rather than a
      parallel group design has been selected. Of 24 rural health centers (Centre de santé et de
      promotion sociale : CSPS) in the districts of Dafra and Dô, introduce monovalent birth dose
      vaccine will be introduced in a phased manner on a centre by centre basis until all the 24
      CSPSs integrate the birth dose vaccines in the program. The rural area of these districts
      were selected given the proximity to our collaborative study center (Centre Muraz and AMP in
      Bobo Dioulasso). One of the 24 centers will be randomly selected as the first one to start
      integrating the birth dose in the program. Then, four weeks later, the second center will be
      randomly selected to start providing the birth dose vaccine. This will be continued until all
      24 CSPSs integrate birth dose vaccine in the program. At the end, this study design will
      generate two groups of infants in the study area during the study period: those born in
      centres which already implemented birth dose vaccine, and those born before the introduction
      of this vaccine.

      Informed consent will be obtained from pregnant women who visited routine antenatal care.
      Subsequently, babies born in a CSPS which is in the intervention period will receive birth
      dose vaccine whilst those born in a CSPS which is in the control period will not receive the
      birth dose. For those born at home in the intervention period will receive the monovalent
      hepatitis B vaccine at the first contact with CSPS, until 8 weeks after the birth when the
      first dose of pentavalent vaccine (DPT-Hib-HepB) is scheduled. All the infants, irrespective
      of study period, will receive three doses of pentavalent vaccine as scheduled in the national
      immunization program.

      Case report forms will be used (CRFs to collect basic demographic data of mothers and
      infants; time and place of birth; type of vaccines administered and its date Laboratory data:
      HBsAg for all infants and mothers; HBV DNA, HBeAg, AST/ALT for infants and mothers tested
      positive for HBsAg; anti-HBs for infants tested negative for HBsAg Paper CRFs filled by
      healthcare workers will be transferred to the study centre (AMP/Centre Muraz). The data will
      be entered independently by two operators to electronic database (RedCAP) that will be
      developed on the secured server of the Institut Pasteur.

      The risk of HBV infection (HBsAg-positivity) in infants at the age of 9 months between two
      groups will be compared using an intention-to-treat analysis, in order to assess the
      effectiveness of adding birth dose vaccine compared to the current vaccine schedule in
      preventing the mother-to-child transmission in Burkina Faso. To adjust for the calendar time
      and clustering in the data, A logistic regression model will fit with random effect for
      cluster and fixed effect for each step.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">September 29, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Sequential Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Pragmatic Stepped-wedge cluster randomized trial</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of positive HBV infection in 9-month-old children vaccinated at birth compared to children receiving their first vaccination at 8 weeks.</measure>
    <time_frame>at 9 months old</time_frame>
    <description>Capillary blood obtained by finger-prick will be used for a rapid diagnostic test for HBsAg detection in order to identify positive hepatitis B surface antigen (HBsAg) in infants and their mother then compare immunological responses by study arm (children who received the birth dose versus those who did not receive it) on titration of anti-HBs antibodies.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Prevalence rate of HBV infection in pregnancy from HBsAg and HBeAg profiles in mothers of 9-month-old children</measure>
    <time_frame>at 9 months</time_frame>
    <description>Positive hepatitis B surface antigen (capillary blood obtained by finger-prick) and positive hepatitis B e surface antigen (blood sample).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">8500</enrollment>
  <condition>Hepatitis B</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention period</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Intervention : birth dose vaccination against hepatitis B strategy Birth dose of vaccine against hepatitis B + routine Expended Programme on Imunisation (EPI) vaccination schedule starting at 8 weeks of life</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control period</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Routine Expended Programme on Imunisation (EPI) vaccination schedule starting at 8 weeks of life</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>birth dose vaccination against hepatitis B strategy</intervention_name>
    <description>Complex intervention targeting healthcare workers and involving:
training on hepatitis B awareness and management
training on EPI vaccination and cold chain
training on the modalities for the birth dose administration
the use of a monovalent unidose vaccine against Hepatitis B</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention period</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Pregnant woman

          -  Living in the study area

          -  Visited study health centre for the antenatal care or child delivery

          -  Provided a written informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Miscarriage, abortion, stillborn, neonatal defect incompatible with life

          -  Any mother or child condition incompatible with the research activities
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>15 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>55 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Haoua TALL, PharmD, MPH</last_name>
    <phone>+226 771 703 66</phone>
    <email>htall@aamp.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Kania Dramane, PharmD, PHD</last_name>
    <phone>+226 20 97 01 02</phone>
    <email>diebakane@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>District sanitaire de Dafra</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bobo-Dioulasso</city>
        <state>Dafra</state>
        <country>Burkina Faso</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Alkadri BOKOUM, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+226 62 63 73 37</phone>
      <email>mailto:alkadria1@yahoo.fr</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>District sanitaire de Do</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bobo-Dioulasso</city>
        <state>Do</state>
        <country>Burkina Faso</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ghislain BOUDA, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+226 71 81 74 40</phone>
      <email>mailto:ghislainbouda@yahoo.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Burkina Faso</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.un.org/fr/africa/osaa/peace/sdgs.shtml</url>
    <description>ONU. Le Programme de développement durable à l'horizon 2030 | Bureau du Conseiller spécial pour l'Afrique (OSAA)</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.who.int/hepatitis/strategy2016-2021/ghss-hep/en/</url>
    <description>Global health sector strategy on viral hepatitis 2016-2021</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.who.int/immunization/sage/meetings/2016/october/presentations_background_docs/en/</url>
    <description>World Health Organization. Systematic Review of Safety and Efficacy of Childhood Schedules Using Hepatitis B Containing Vaccines</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.who.int/immunization/documents/general/ISBN9789241509831/en/</url>
    <description>WHO. Preventing Perinatal Hepatitis B Virus Transmission: A Guide for Introducing Hepatitis B Birth Dose Vaccination</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.consort-statement.org/downloads</url>
    <description>Consort Statement</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.who.int/hepatitis/publications/hepatitis-b-guidelines/en/</url>
    <description>WHO. Guidelines for the prevention, care and treatment of persons with chronic hepatitis B infection</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schweitzer A, Horn J, Mikolajczyk RT, Krause G, Ott JJ. Estimations of worldwide prevalence of chronic hepatitis B virus infection: a systematic review of data published between 1965 and 2013. Lancet. 2015 Oct 17;386(10003):1546-55. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(15)61412-X. Epub 2015 Jul 28. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26231459</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>MacLachlan JH, Cowie BC. Hepatitis B virus epidemiology. Cold Spring Harb Perspect Med. 2015 May 1;5(5):a021410. doi: 10.1101/cshperspect.a021410. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25934461</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>World Health Organization. Hepatitis B vaccines: WHO position paper, July 2017 - Recommendations. Vaccine. 2019 Jan 7;37(2):223-225. doi: 10.1016/j.vaccine.2017.07.046. Epub 2017 Jul 22.</citation>
    <PMID>28743487</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Burk RD, Hwang LY, Ho GY, Shafritz DA, Beasley RP. Outcome of perinatal hepatitis B virus exposure is dependent on maternal virus load. J Infect Dis. 1994 Dec;170(6):1418-23.</citation>
    <PMID>7995980</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tamandjou CR, Maponga TG, Chotun N, Preiser W, Andersson MI. Is hepatitis B birth dose vaccine needed in Africa? Pan Afr Med J. 2017 Jun 22;27(Suppl 3):18. doi: 10.11604/pamj.supp.2017.27.3.11546. eCollection 2017.</citation>
    <PMID>29296153</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pan CQ, Zou HB, Chen Y, Zhang X, Zhang H, Li J, Duan Z. Cesarean section reduces perinatal transmission of hepatitis B virus infection from hepatitis B surface antigen-positive women to their infants. Clin Gastroenterol Hepatol. 2013 Oct;11(10):1349-55. doi: 10.1016/j.cgh.2013.04.026. Epub 2013 Apr 29.</citation>
    <PMID>23639606</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Edmunds WJ, Medley GF, Nokes DJ, O'Callaghan CJ, Whittle HC, Hall AJ. Epidemiological patterns of hepatitis B virus (HBV) in highly endemic areas. Epidemiol Infect. 1996 Oct;117(2):313-25.</citation>
    <PMID>8870629</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Barin F, Perrin J, Chotard J, Denis F, N'Doye R, Diop Mar I, Chiron JP, Coursaget P, Goudeau A, Maupas P. Cross-sectional and longitudinal epidemiology of hepatitis B in Senegal. Prog Med Virol. 1981;27:148-62.</citation>
    <PMID>6972051</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kiire CF. The epidemiology and prophylaxis of hepatitis B in sub-Saharan Africa: a view from tropical and subtropical Africa. Gut. 1996;38 Suppl 2:S5-12. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>8786055</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Edmunds WJ, Medley GF, Nokes DJ, Hall AJ, Whittle HC. The influence of age on the development of the hepatitis B carrier state. Proc Biol Sci. 1993 Aug 23;253(1337):197-201.</citation>
    <PMID>8397416</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shimakawa Y, Yan HJ, Tsuchiya N, Bottomley C, Hall AJ. Association of early age at establishment of chronic hepatitis B infection with persistent viral replication, liver cirrhosis and hepatocellular carcinoma: a systematic review. PLoS One. 2013 Jul 19;8(7):e69430. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0069430. Print 2013. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23894479</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shimakawa Y, Lemoine M, Bottomley C, Njai HF, Ndow G, Jatta A, Tamba S, Bojang L, Taal M, Nyan O, D'Alessandro U, Njie R, Thursz M, Hall AJ. Birth order and risk of hepatocellular carcinoma in chronic carriers of hepatitis B virus: a case-control study in The Gambia. Liver Int. 2015 Oct;35(10):2318-26. doi: 10.1111/liv.12814. Epub 2015 Mar 11.</citation>
    <PMID>25728498</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shimakawa Y, Lemoine M, Njai HF, Bottomley C, Ndow G, Goldin RD, Jatta A, Jeng-Barry A, Wegmuller R, Moore SE, Baldeh I, Taal M, D'Alessandro U, Whittle H, Njie R, Thursz M, Mendy M. Natural history of chronic HBV infection in West Africa: a longitudinal population-based study from The Gambia. Gut. 2016 Dec;65(12):2007-2016. doi: 10.1136/gutjnl-2015-309892. Epub 2015 Jul 16.</citation>
    <PMID>26185161</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Feldstein LR, Mariat S, Gacic-Dobo M, Diallo MS, Conklin LM, Wallace AS. Global Routine Vaccination Coverage, 2016. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep. 2017 Nov 17;66(45):1252-1255. doi: 10.15585/mmwr.mm6645a3.</citation>
    <PMID>29145357</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kramvis A, Clements CJ. Implementing a birth dose of hepatitis B vaccine for home deliveries in Africa--too soon? Vaccine. 2010 Sep 7;28(39):6408-10. doi: 10.1016/j.vaccine.2010.07.042. Epub 2010 Jul 29.</citation>
    <PMID>20673825</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lee C, Gong Y, Brok J, Boxall EH, Gluud C. Hepatitis B immunisation for newborn infants of hepatitis B surface antigen-positive mothers. Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2006 Apr 19;(2):CD004790. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>16625613</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ekra D, Herbinger KH, Konate S, Leblond A, Fretz C, Cilote V, Douai C, Da Silva A, Gessner BD, Chauvin P. A non-randomized vaccine effectiveness trial of accelerated infant hepatitis B immunization schedules with a first dose at birth or age 6 weeks in Côte d'Ivoire. Vaccine. 2008 May 23;26(22):2753-61. doi: 10.1016/j.vaccine.2008.03.018. Epub 2008 Mar 31.</citation>
    <PMID>18436354</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Marion SA, Tomm Pastore M, Pi DW, Mathias RG. Long-term follow-up of hepatitis B vaccine in infants of carrier mothers. Am J Epidemiol. 1994 Oct 15;140(8):734-46.</citation>
    <PMID>7942775</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pan CQ, Duan Z, Dai E, Zhang S, Han G, Wang Y, Zhang H, Zou H, Zhu B, Zhao W, Jiang H; China Study Group for the Mother-to-Child Transmission of Hepatitis B. Tenofovir to Prevent Hepatitis B Transmission in Mothers with High Viral Load. N Engl J Med. 2016 Jun 16;374(24):2324-34. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa1508660.</citation>
    <PMID>27305192</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hemming K, Haines TP, Chilton PJ, Girling AJ, Lilford RJ. The stepped wedge cluster randomised trial: rationale, design, analysis, and reporting. BMJ. 2015 Feb 6;350:h391. doi: 10.1136/bmj.h391. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25662947</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Copas AJ, Lewis JJ, Thompson JA, Davey C, Baio G, Hargreaves JR. Designing a stepped wedge trial: three main designs, carry-over effects and randomisation approaches. Trials. 2015 Aug 17;16:352. doi: 10.1186/s13063-015-0842-7.</citation>
    <PMID>26279154</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Baio G, Copas A, Ambler G, Hargreaves J, Beard E, Omar RZ. Sample size calculation for a stepped wedge trial. Trials. 2015 Aug 17;16:354. doi: 10.1186/s13063-015-0840-9. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26282553</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hussey MA, Hughes JP. Design and analysis of stepped wedge cluster randomized trials. Contemp Clin Trials. 2007 Feb;28(2):182-91. Epub 2006 Jul 7. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>16829207</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hemming K, Taljaard M. Sample size calculations for stepped wedge and cluster randomised trials: a unified approach. J Clin Epidemiol. 2016 Jan;69:137-46. doi: 10.1016/j.jclinepi.2015.08.015. Epub 2015 Sep 5.</citation>
    <PMID>26344808</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>van den Ende C, Marano C, van Ahee A, Bunge EM, De Moerlooze L. The immunogenicity of GSK's recombinant hepatitis B vaccine in children: a systematic review of 30 years of experience. Expert Rev Vaccines. 2017 Aug;16(8):789-809. doi: 10.1080/14760584.2017.1338569. Epub 2017 Jul 3. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>28586278</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jourdain G, Ngo-Giang-Huong N, Harrison L, Decker L, Khamduang W, Tierney C, Salvadori N, Cressey TR, Sirirungsi W, Achalapong J, Yuthavisuthi P, Kanjanavikai P, Na Ayudhaya OP, Siriwachirachai T, Prommas S, Sabsanong P, Limtrakul A, Varadisai S, Putiyanun C, Suriyachai P, Liampongsabuddhi P, Sangsawang S, Matanasarawut W, Buranabanjasatean S, Puernngooluerm P, Bowonwatanuwong C, Puthanakit T, Klinbuayaem V, Thongsawat S, Thanprasertsuk S, Siberry GK, Watts DH, Chakhtoura N, Murphy TV, Nelson NP, Chung RT, Pol S, Chotivanich N. Tenofovir versus Placebo to Prevent Perinatal Transmission of Hepatitis B. N Engl J Med. 2018 Mar 8;378(10):911-923. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa1708131.</citation>
    <PMID>29514030</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Collenberg E, Ouedraogo T, Ganamé J, Fickenscher H, Kynast-Wolf G, Becher H, Kouyaté B, Kräusslich HG, Sangaré L, Tebit DM. Seroprevalence of six different viruses among pregnant women and blood donors in rural and urban Burkina Faso: A comparative analysis. J Med Virol. 2006 May;78(5):683-92.</citation>
    <PMID>16555290</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hyams KC. Risks of chronicity following acute hepatitis B virus infection: a review. Clin Infect Dis. 1995 Apr;20(4):992-1000. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>7795104</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Njai HF, Shimakawa Y, Sanneh B, Ferguson L, Ndow G, Mendy M, Sow A, Lo G, Toure-Kane C, Tanaka J, Taal M, D'alessandro U, Njie R, Thursz M, Lemoine M. Validation of rapid point-of-care (POC) tests for detection of hepatitis B surface antigen in field and laboratory settings in the Gambia, Western Africa. J Clin Microbiol. 2015 Apr;53(4):1156-63. doi: 10.1128/JCM.02980-14. Epub 2015 Jan 28.</citation>
    <PMID>25631805</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Riou J, Aït Ahmed M, Blake A, Vozlinsky S, Brichler S, Eholié S, Boëlle PY, Fontanet A; HCV epidemiology in Africa group. Hepatitis C virus seroprevalence in adults in Africa: a systematic review and meta-analysis. J Viral Hepat. 2016 Apr;23(4):244-55. doi: 10.1111/jvh.12481. Epub 2015 Oct 19. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26477881</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Vray M, Debonne JM, Sire JM, Tran N, Chevalier B, Plantier JC, Fall F, Vernet G, Simon F, Mb PS. Molecular epidemiology of hepatitis B virus in Dakar, Sénégal. J Med Virol. 2006 Mar;78(3):329-34.</citation>
    <PMID>16419106</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lemoine M, Shimakawa Y, Njie R, Taal M, Ndow G, Chemin I, Ghosh S, Njai HF, Jeng A, Sow A, Toure-Kane C, Mboup S, Suso P, Tamba S, Jatta A, Sarr L, Kambi A, Stanger W, Nayagam S, Howell J, Mpabanzi L, Nyan O, Corrah T, Whittle H, Taylor-Robinson SD, D'Alessandro U, Mendy M, Thursz MR; PROLIFICA investigators. Acceptability and feasibility of a screen-and-treat programme for hepatitis B virus infection in The Gambia: the Prevention of Liver Fibrosis and Cancer in Africa (PROLIFICA) study. Lancet Glob Health. 2016 Aug;4(8):e559-67. doi: 10.1016/S2214-109X(16)30130-9.</citation>
    <PMID>27443781</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Duffy D, Mottez E, Ainsworth S, Buivan TP, Baudin A, Vray M, Reed B, Fontanet A, Rohel A, Petrov-Sanchez V, Abel L, Theodorou I, Miele G, Pol S, Albert ML. An in vitro diagnostic certified point of care single nucleotide test for IL28B polymorphisms. PLoS One. 2017 Sep 6;12(9):e0183084. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0183084. eCollection 2017.</citation>
    <PMID>28877177</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Posuwan N, Payungporn S, Tangkijvanich P, Ogawa S, Murakami S, Iijima S, Matsuura K, Shinkai N, Watanabe T, Poovorawan Y, Tanaka Y. Genetic association of human leukocyte antigens with chronicity or resolution of hepatitis B infection in thai population. PLoS One. 2014 Jan 23;9(1):e86007. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0086007. eCollection 2014.</citation>
    <PMID>24465836</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Démolis R, Botão C, Heyerdahl LW, Gessner BD, Cavailler P, Sinai C, Magaço A, Le Gargasson JB, Mengel M, Guillermet E. A rapid qualitative assessment of oral cholera vaccine anticipated acceptability in a context of resistance towards cholera intervention in Nampula, Mozambique. Vaccine. 2018 Oct 22;36(44):6497-6505. doi: 10.1016/j.vaccine.2017.10.087. Epub 2017 Nov 27.</citation>
    <PMID>29174106</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Janzen J. The Social Fabric of Health: An Introduction to Medical Anthropology. McGraw-Hill; 2002.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Winkelman M. Culture and Health: Applying Medical Anthropology. Jossey-Bass. 2008.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Giles-Vernick T, Traoré A, Bainilago L. Incertitude, Hepatitis B, and Infant Vaccination in West and Central Africa. Med Anthropol Q. 2016 Jun;30(2):203-21. doi: 10.1111/maq.12187. Epub 2016 Mar 31.</citation>
    <PMID>25624042</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Scott S, Odutola A, Mackenzie G, Fulford T, Afolabi MO, Lowe Jallow Y, Jasseh M, Jeffries D, Dondeh BL, Howie SR, D'Alessandro U. Coverage and timing of children's vaccination: an evaluation of the expanded programme on immunisation in The Gambia. PLoS One. 2014 Sep 18;9(9):e107280. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0107280. eCollection 2014.</citation>
    <PMID>25232830</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Briggs AH, Goeree R, Blackhouse G, O'Brien BJ. Probabilistic analysis of cost-effectiveness models: choosing between treatment strategies for gastroesophageal reflux disease. Med Decis Making. 2002 Jul-Aug;22(4):290-308.</citation>
    <PMID>12150595</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>July 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 5, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 22, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 23, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 22, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 22, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 23, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Infectious Disease Transmission, Vertical</keyword>
  <keyword>immunization programs</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis A</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis B</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Vaccines</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

