<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04025294</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2000026033</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04025294</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Evaluation of a School Climate Videogame Intervention</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Evaluation of a School Climate Videogame Intervention</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Yale University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Yale University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      A randomized control trial of a videogame intervention to assess and improve school climate.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      To assess the acceptability and preliminary efficacy of a videogame intervention designed to
      teach teens the skills in restructuring thoughts and then empowering them to take action and
      improve their school climate.

      For this project, the play2PREVENT Lab aims to assess the acceptability and preliminary
      efficacy of a videogame intervention designed to teach teens the skills in restructuring
      thoughts and then empowering them to take action and improve their school climate. Program
      and school staff will enroll participants between the ages of 14-19 years old to play our
      videogame during their after school programs. Before and after gameplay, participants will
      answer assessment questions related to self-efficacy, cognitive reappraisal, and dimensions
      of school climate. Questions will also assess participants' feedback on the videogame.
      Students not randomly assigned to the videogame intervention will only respond to assessment
      questions. The data will be transmitted electronically via Qualtrics data collection platform
      to the Lab for further analysis.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 30, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 30, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Measuring self-efficacy at baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Participants will complete a pre-survey through a secured, data collection website (Qualtrics), before playing the videogame. Items from the general self-efficacy questionnaire will assess participants' self-efficacy at baseline. This scale uses a 5-point Likert response scale (1=Never, 2=Almost Never, 3=Sometimes, 4=Fairly Often, 5=Very Often). Total self-efficacy score ranges from 10-50.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in self-efficacy from baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>immediately after playing the videogame</time_frame>
    <description>Participants will complete a post-survey through a secured, data collection website (Qualtrics), immediately after playing the videogame. Items from the general self-efficacy questionnaire will assess participants' self-efficacy at baseline. This scale uses a 5-point Likert response scale (1=Never, 2=Almost Never, 3=Sometimes, 4=Fairly Often, 5=Very Often). Total self-efficacy score ranges from 10-50.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Measuring emotional self-efficacy at baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Participants will complete a pre-survey through a secured, data collection website (Qualtrics), at baseline. Items from the Self-Efficacy Questionnaire for Children (SEQ-C) will assess participants' emotional self-efficacy immediately before playing the game. Each of the 6 items used in the study has to be scored on a 5-point scale with 1 = not at all and 5 = very well.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in emotional self-efficacy from baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>immediately after playing the videogame</time_frame>
    <description>Participants will complete a post-survey through a secured, data collection website (Qualtrics), at baseline. Items from the Self-Efficacy Questionnaire for Children (SEQ-C) will assess participants' emotional self-efficacy immediately after playing the game. Each of the 6 items used in the study has to be scored on a 5-point scale with 1 = not at all and 5 = very well.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Cognitive reappraisal scores at baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>at baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Participants will complete a pre-survey through a secured, data collection website (Qualtrics), at baseline.
The ERQ-CA includes 6 items assessing participants' cognitive appraisal. The scale length ranges up to five points with the following options: 1) strongly disagree; 2) disagree, 3) half and half, 4) agree, 5) strongly agree. The range of scores for each scale was 6 to 30.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Cognitive reappraisal scores at baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>immediately after playing the videogame</time_frame>
    <description>Participants will complete a post-survey through a secured, data collection website (Qualtrics), immediately after playing the videogame. Items from the Emotional Regulation Questionnaire for Children and Adolescents (ERQ-CA) will assess participants' cognitive reappraisal immediately after playing the tool/game.
The ERQ-CA includes 6 items assessing participants' cognitive appraisal. The scale length ranges up to five points with the following options: 1) strongly disagree; 2) disagree, 3) half and half, 4) agree, 5) strongly agree. The range of scores for each scale was 6 to 30.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Gameplay post-assessment</measure>
    <time_frame>immediately after playing the game</time_frame>
    <description>Participants will complete a post-survey through a secured, data collection website (Qualtrics), immediately after playing the game. Twelve items will assess intervention experience and satisfaction from items designed by members of the study team (e.g., How likely do you think completing any of the activities will help you improve how you feel about yourself, others, or social situations? Response options include very likely, likely, might or might not, unlikely, very unlikely.) These questions are not part of a larger scale.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>School Climate</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Participants will complete a pre-survey through a secured, data collection website (Qualtrics), immediately before playing the videogame. Items from the National School Climate Center will be adapted and used to assess dimensions of participants' school climate, including safety, support for learning, environment, social media, and relationships. Response options include yes, no, not applicable. These questions are not part of a larger scale.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>School Fear</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Students playing videogame</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The experimental group will consist of our videogame intervention including the five mini-games.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Students receiving school climate assessment</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The control group differs from the experimental group as it includes the school climate assessment tool but excludes the mini-games</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>videogame</intervention_name>
    <description>A videogame intervention that is interactive and engaging that teaches adolescents how to restructure negative automatic thoughts through an adapted thought record (a technique used in cognitive behavioral therapy to improve moods) by modeling how to do so and then empower them through real-life activities to improve their school climate. The videogame intervention is comprised of five mini-games, each containing a short narrative that models how to restructure negative automatic thoughts and navigate through challenging situations that often take place in school settings. The topics of each mini-game are informed by the constructs of school climate according to the National School Climate Center. Students using the videogame intervention will be prompted to think deeply and reflect on the narratives presented in each mini-game.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Students playing videogame</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>School Climate Assessment Survey</intervention_name>
    <description>A school climate assessment survey will include items adapted from questions developed by the National School Climate Center. Items will assess various dimensions of school climate including safety, social media, relationships, support for learning, and environment.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Students receiving school climate assessment</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Must be a current high school student

          -  English-speaking

          -  Willing to provide minor assent

          -  Willing to provide parental consent (if under 18 years old)

          -  Willing to play/use the game/tool for about 45 minutes to 1 hour after school

          -  Willing to answer questions about their experiences in playing the game, questions
             around school climate, and questions around self-efficacy on an iPad for about 30
             minutes

          -  Willing to participate in an optional focus group for about 30 minutes

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Those that do not meet the criteria above
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>14 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>19 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Lynn E Fiellin, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Yale University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Claudia-Santi Fernandes, EdD</last_name>
    <phone>203-737-6101</phone>
    <email>claudiasanti.fernandes@yale.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Yale Center for Health &amp; Learning Games</name>
      <address>
        <city>New Haven</city>
        <state>Connecticut</state>
        <zip>06510</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Claudia-Santi F Fernandes, Ed.D., LPC</last_name>
      <phone>203-737-3347</phone>
      <email>ychl.games@yale.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 16, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 16, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 18, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 17, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 17, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 22, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

