<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04021641</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ChineseUHK_CREC2018.639</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04021641</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Construction and Validation of CanSRINT</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Construction and Validation of Cantonese Sentence Recognition in Noise Test</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Chinese University of Hong Kong</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Chinese University of Hong Kong</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      An open-set sentence speech recognition in noise test in Cantonese Chinese, which is
      applicable on children and adults with hearing impairment, is proposed to be developed in
      this project.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      INTRODUCTION: Speech recognition in noise is an important aspect of human communication.
      One's speech recognition ability in noise is inevitably affected by any hearing impairment,
      and may only be quantified with specific language at an appropriate difficulty.

      There is a niche among clinically available test materials between word recognition and 10-
      syllable sentence recognition in noise in Cantonese Chinese. Ten-syllable sentence items are
      commented to be too challenging to young children and elderly population. An assessment tool
      for pediatric patients, and the whole spectrum of patients with significant hearing
      impairment, compromised language or cognitive abilities, is deemed necessary. Both the
      research and clinical audiology communities need a valid and reliable outcome measurement
      tool for sentence recognition abilities in noise of the specific population.

      An open-set sentence speech recognition in noise test in Cantonese Chinese, which is
      applicable on children and adults with hearing impairment, is proposed to be developed in
      this project to bridge the gap.

      METHODS: Thirty three participants with typical hearing, from each of the 5 age groups from
      their 6 years of age to adulthood, will be recruited to contribute to the normative data of
      the proposed test. One hundred participants with various degree of hearing impairment will be
      recruited for the validation of the proposed new test as well.

      A sentence pool of at least 150 sentence items will be constructed based on the basic
      sentence syntax in Cantonese Chinese. Each sentence item will be 7 syllables in length on
      average. The words used in the sentences will be words frequently used in daily life by both
      persons with typical hearing and hearing impairment. A 4-talker babble in Cantonese Chinese
      will be generated as the competing noise in this proposed new test.

      OUTCOMES: By Rasch modelling, sentence items with high probability of consistently and
      accurately estimating sentence recognition ability in noise across different participants
      will be selected and distributed to a few parallel lists.

      Rater and test-retest reliability of the test items and lists will be established.

      Content-related and construct-related evidence of validity of lists will also be supported by
      psychometric analyses as well as expert consultation.

      APPLICATION: A valid and reliable assessment tool, of sentence recognition ability in noise
      in Cantonese, applicable to persons with hearing sensitivity ranging from profound impairment
      to typical, in both the research and clinical audiology fields, will be constructed.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 29, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 31, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Control</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Cross-Sectional</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Person Ability of Participants in Sentence Recognition in Noise</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 1 month</time_frame>
    <description>In accordance with Item Response Theory, the ability of individual participants in sentence recognition in noise, measured by the proposed new test, is generated through Rasch modelling or other relevant models.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Item Difficulty of Test Items in Sentence Recognition in Noise</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 3 years</time_frame>
    <description>In accordance with Item Response Theory, the difficulty of individual proposed test items in sentence recognition in noise, contributed by all participants, is generated through Rasch modelling or other relevant models.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Internal Consistency of Test Items</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Cronbach's alpha or other relevant measurements will be used to estimate the consistency of the items on measuring the same dimension.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Rater Reliability of Test Items</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 1 month</time_frame>
    <description>A portion of the test sessions will be scored twice by more than one raters. The intra-class correlation (ICC) or other relevant measurements will be employed to estimate rater reliability.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Test-Retest Reliability of Test Items</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 1 month</time_frame>
    <description>A portion of participants will be tested twice. Pearson's coefficient of correlation or other relevant measurements will be computed to measure the correlation between the first and the second test results.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Content-related Evidence of Validity of Test Items</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Construction of sentence test items with elements from various relevant language corpus, based on the basic sentence syntax in Cantonese Chinese, and evaluated with reference to expert opinions, will be regarded as content-related evidence of the test item validity.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Construct-related Evidence of Validity of Test Items</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Unidimensionality and local independence, or other relevant measurements, in accordance with Item Response Theory, will be regarded as construct-related evidence of the test item validity.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>A New Sentence Recognition in Noise Test Tool Titled CanSRINT</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 4 years</time_frame>
    <description>A valid and reliable assessment tool, of sentence recognition ability in noise in Cantonese, applicable to persons with hearing sensitivity ranging from profound impairment to typical, in both the research and clinical audiology fields, will be published.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">265</enrollment>
  <condition>Hearing Loss</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Participants with Typical Hearing</arm_group_label>
    <description>From 5 age groups from their 6 years of age to adulthood</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Participants with Hearing Impairment</arm_group_label>
    <description>Participants with various degree of hearing impairment</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Speech recognition in noise</intervention_name>
    <description>Measurement of speech recognition performance in noise</description>
    <arm_group_label>Participants with Hearing Impairment</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Participants with Typical Hearing</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Participants with typical hearing, from each of the 5 age groups from their 6 years of age
        to adulthood, will be recruited to contribute to the normative data of the proposed test.

        One hundred participants with various degree of hearing impairment will be recruited for
        the validation of the proposed new test.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Native in Catonese

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Have overall cognitive and developmental impairment
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>6 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Iris HY NG, Dr.</last_name>
    <phone>+85239439609</phone>
    <email>irisng@ent.cuhk.edu.hk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Wilson YU, Mphil.</last_name>
    <phone>+85239439609</phone>
    <email>wilsonyu@ent.cuhk.edu.hk</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The Chinese University of Hong Kong</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hong Kong</city>
        <zip>0000</zip>
        <country>Hong Kong</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Wilson YU, Mphil.</last_name>
      <phone>85239439609</phone>
      <email>wilsonyu@ent.cuhk.edu.hk</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Hong Kong</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 11, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 14, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 16, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 30, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 30, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">August 1, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Chinese University of Hong Kong</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Iris H.-Y. NG</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor, Department of Otorhinolaryngology, Head and Neck Surgery</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hearing Loss</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

