<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04020835</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>253660</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04020835</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Understanding Abdominal Pain in IBD and IBS</brief_title>
  <official_title>Exploring Biopsychosocial Mechanisms of Abdominal Pain in Inflammatory Bowel Disease and Irritable Bowel Syndrome</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Guy's and St Thomas' NHS Foundation Trust</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>King's College London</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Guy's and St Thomas' NHS Foundation Trust</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Abdominal pain is a central symptom of Inflammatory Bowel Disease (IBD) and Irritable Bowel
      Syndrome (IBS). IBD is an autoimmune disease characterized by inflammation of the
      gastrointestinal tract. IBS does not have clear biomarkers and is diagnosed based on symptom
      reports. The aim of this study is to explore biopsychosocial factors which may perpetuate
      and/or increase the severity of pain in these conditions. The main focus will be on the role
      of top-down brain processes in the experience of abdominal pain.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      It remains unclear why a large proportion of people with inflammatory bowel disease (IBD)
      report ongoing abdominal pain during remission or why people with irritable bowel syndrome
      (IBS) develop abdominal pain. One theory is that people with chronic pain have somehow grown
      more sensitive.

      It is assumed that such heightened sensitivity depends both on bottom-up processing and
      top-down processing. Bottom-up processing refers to information that is relayed to the brain
      along so-called afferent fibres. Top-down processing refers to feedback provided by the brain
      to lower areas along efferent fibres.

      The investigators will (1) measure the capacity of people to inhibit pain through top-down
      processing, (2) test if the human pain experience is enhanced due to sustained activation of
      certain afferents, and (3) assess to what extent people are impacted by psychosocial
      inhibition and activation factors. Results of people with IBS in remission will be compared
      with the results of two groups of people with IBD (those with pain and those without) and the
      investigators will explore if their measurements differentiate between groups.

      It is hypothesized that (1) IBS patients and IBD patients with abdominal pain will be less
      able to inhibit their pain compared to IBD patients without abdominal pain (2) IBS patients
      and IBD patients with abdominal pain will score higher on psychosocial inhibition factors and
      lower on psychosocial activation factors when compared to IBD patients without abdominal
      pain. (3) In the total cohort, laboratory measures of pain inhibition will correlate with
      self-reported psychosocial inhibition and activation factors. (4) IBS patients and IBD
      patients with abdominal pain will show more temporal summation compared to IBD patients
      without abdominal pain.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 20, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 31, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 31, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Control</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Cross-Sectional</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Efficiency of inhibitory pain modulation, comparing patients with IBS or quiescent IBD</measure>
    <time_frame>January 31, 2020</time_frame>
    <description>Measured with Conditioned Pain Modulation test.
Two inflatable pressure cuffs are secured around the caffs of subjects and then inflated. Pressure pain detection threshold (PDT) and pressure pain tolerance (PTT) are assessed on a subject's dominant leg. PDT is the first sensation of pain and PTT is defined as the point a subject no longer want the cuff to inflate. A VAS device allows participants to report their pain levels by moving a sliding button along a continuous line between two endpoints (0=no pain to 10=worst pain imaginable).
After a second baseline measure on the non-dominant leg CPM is assessed: the cuff on the non-dominant leg is inflated to 70% of the subject's PTT, then after 15 seconds the cuff on the dominant leg is inflated. If pain modulation is achieved, the subject will show increased threshold and tolerance levels during CPM. The CPM-effect is defined as the difference between baseline and conditioning measurements of both PDT and PTT.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Contribution of socio-demographic, clinical and psychosocial factors to the efficiency of inhibitory pain modulation</measure>
    <time_frame>January 31, 2020</time_frame>
    <description>Measured with a range of questionnaires, i.e.: Brief Pain Inventory Short Form (BPI), painDETECT questionnaire, Patient Health Questionnaire-9, Generalized Anxiety Disorder-7, Visceral Sensitivity Index, Pain Catastrophising Scale, Cognitive and Behavioural Response to Symptoms Questionnaire, Pain Self Efficacy Questionnaire, Chronic Pain Acceptance Questionnaire-8, and Mental Health Continuum Short-Form</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pain facilitation, comparing patients with IBS and quiescent IBD</measure>
    <time_frame>January 31, 2020</time_frame>
    <description>Measured with Temporal Summation (TS) test.
TS will be carried out on the dominant leg dominant. A series of 10 rapid stimuli will be given at a rate of 0.5 Hz (1-second of pressure at 1-second intervals). The cuff pressure-level of the stimuli will be determined by the pressure pain tolerance level of the subject. In each instance the subject will rate the painfulness of the stimulus using the VAS. The VAS rating for each stimulus will be relative to the painfulness of the previous stimulus in the train of stimuli, i.e. the subject does not return the VAS scale to zero after each stimulation. In other words, if the painfulness of a stimulus is more intense than the previous stimulus, the VAS scale is increased. If the painfulness of stimulus is less intense than the previous stimulus, the VAS scale is decreased. If the sensation remains the same between stimuli, then the VAS scale is not changed.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">90</enrollment>
  <condition>Abdominal Pain</condition>
  <condition>Inflammatory Bowel Diseases</condition>
  <condition>Irritable Bowel Syndrome</condition>
  <biospec_retention>Samples Without DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      stool sample (faecal calprotectin)
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients with quiescent Inflammatory Bowel Disease or Irritable Bowel Syndrome
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        General inclusion criteria:

          -  Aged 18 and over

          -  Sufficient command of written and spoken English

        IBD in remission inclusion criteria:

          -  Proof of diagnosis of IBD (Crohn's disease or ulcerative colitis) for more than 6
             months - - Clear indicators of remission: on faecal calprotectin (≤200 µg/g) or
             measurements of C-reactive protein (CRP; ≤10 mg/dl) within the last 3 months or as
             part of recruitment

          -  No previous episodes of acute or sub-acute obstruction

        IBS inclusion criteria:

          -  Current diagnosis of IBS measured with Rome IV criteria

          -  No serious other bowel diseases

        Exclusion criteria:

          -  Major abdominal surgery in the last 6 months, or 3 or more previous major abdominal
             surgeries

          -  Pregnancy or childbirth in the last 6 months

          -  Any other diagnosed medical condition that may explain abdominal pain, including but
             not limited to known gynaecological conditions such as endometriosis and known
             post-surgical adhesions

          -  Any diagnosed co-morbid medical conditions associated with known neuropathy, such as
             diabetic neuropathy, renal neuropathy, multiple sclerosis

          -  Use of opioids in the last week

          -  Use of anti-depressants used as pain medication in the last month
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Danielle Huisman</last_name>
    <phone>+442071880188</phone>
    <email>danielle.huisman@kcl.ac.uk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Reza Razavi</last_name>
    <phone>+442078486390</phone>
    <email>reza.razavi@kcl.ac.uk</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Barts Health NHS Trust</name>
      <address>
        <city>London</city>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>King's College Hospital NHS Foundation Trust</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Guy's and St Thomas' NHS Foundation Trust</name>
      <address>
        <city>London</city>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Consultant Gastroenterologist</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>King's College Hospital NHS Foundation Trust</name>
      <address>
        <city>London</city>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Consultant Gastroenterologist</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 12, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 12, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 16, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 16, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 16, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 18, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Intestinal Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Inflammatory Bowel Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Irritable Bowel Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Abdominal Pain</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

