<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04026321</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>LV-SQ001-01</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04026321</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Single-dose Escalation Study of SQ-001 Infusion to Characterize the PK Profiles of Major Sentinel Compounds in Healthy Adult Volunteers in US</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Double-blind, Single-dose Escalation Study of SQ-001 Infusion at a Single Center to Characterize the PK Profiles of Major Sentinel Compounds, Astragaloside IV, Calycosin 7-O-beta-glucopyranoside, and Lobetyolin in the Plasma of Healthy Adult Volunteers in the United States</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Livzon Pharmaceutical Group Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Palm Beach CRO</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Keystone Bioanalytical, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Livzon Pharmaceutical Group Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a single-center, double-blind, single-dose escalation study in healthy volunteers.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a single-center, double-blind, single-dose escalation study in healthy volunteers
      consisting of a 14-day Screening Period, 1-day Predose period, a 2-day Dosing and Evaluation
      Period, and a 5-day Follow-up Period, with a single Follow-up call scheduled on Day 7 ± 1.
      Subjects will be confined to the study site for up to 3 days (admitted on Day -1 and
      discharged on Day 2 or 3, depending on cohort) and will be monitored for adverse events (AEs)
      and dose limiting toxicities (DLT) during the Dosing, Evaluation and Follow-up Periods.
      Subjects will also be monitored for concomitant medications and use of rescue medications
      throughout the study.

      Subjects will be allocated 1:4 to receive an infusion of saline control (0.9% saline for
      injection) or Shenqi Fuzheng Injection(SQ-001) continuously for about 1-4 hours. SQ 001 will
      be administered by intravenous route at a rate of 3 mL/min to one of four final dosages:
      Cohort 1 (125 mL/day/person), Cohort 2 (250 mL/day/person), Cohort 3 (500 mL/day/person), and
      Cohort 4 (625 mL/day/person). Each cohort will be enrolled sequentially. Per cohort, three
      subjects will be dosed initially on Day 1 and observed for 24 hours. If there are no observed
      AEs that meet the criteria under Stopping Rules, the remaining 7 subjects/cohort will be
      dosed. Dose escalation to the next higher dose will be based on the observation of results in
      safety and degree of AEs from the previous cohort and discussion between the Investigator and
      Sponsor.

      A maximum 17 PK samples will be collected over the course of the study in each cohort. The PK
      sampling time points will be grouped as (a) pre-infusion; (b) intra-infusion; (c) completion
      of infusion; and (d) post-infusion. See Table 10 for plasma PK sampling times. The last PK
      sample will be collected 24 hours after the end of infusion.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 3, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 11, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 6, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The maximum observed concentrations (Cmax)(ng/mL)</measure>
    <time_frame>On 1 and 2 days (dosing day and the following evaluation day)</time_frame>
    <description>To compare the Cmax of 3 major representative (sentinel) compounds astragaloside IV, calycosin 7-O-β-glucopyranoside, and lobetyolin in different experimental arms</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to reach Cmax (Tmax)(h)</measure>
    <time_frame>On 1 and 2 days (dosing day and the following evaluation day)</time_frame>
    <description>To compare the Tmax of 3 major representative (sentinel) compounds astragaloside IV, calycosin 7-O-β-glucopyranoside, and lobetyolin in different experimental arms</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Area under the concentration-time curve (AUC)(ng·h/mL)</measure>
    <time_frame>On 1 and 2 days (dosing day and the following evaluation day)</time_frame>
    <description>To compare the AUC of 3 major representative (sentinel) compounds astragaloside IV, calycosin 7-O-β-glucopyranoside, and lobetyolin in different experimental arms</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Elimination half-life (T1/2)(h)</measure>
    <time_frame>On 1 and 2 days (dosing day and the following evaluation day)</time_frame>
    <description>To compare the Cmax of 3 major representative (sentinel) compounds astragaloside IV, calycosin 7-O-β-glucopyranoside, and lobetyolin in different experimental arms</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Apparent clearance (CL)(mL/min/kg)</measure>
    <time_frame>On 1 and 2 days (dosing day and the following evaluation day)</time_frame>
    <description>To compare the CL of 3 major representative (sentinel) compounds astragaloside IV, calycosin 7-O-β-glucopyranoside, and lobetyolinin different experimental arms</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Volume of distribution at steady state (Vdss)(L/kg)</measure>
    <time_frame>On 1 and 2 days (dosing day and the following evaluation day)</time_frame>
    <description>To compare the Vdss of 3 major representative (sentinel) compounds astragaloside IV, calycosin 7-O-β-glucopyranoside, and lobetyolinin different experimental arms</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of treatment-related adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>From predose to up 5 days following the dosing and evaluation period</time_frame>
    <description>Incidence of treatment-related adverse events as assessed by CTCAE v4.03</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Frequency of treatment-related adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>From predose to up to 5 days following the dosing and evaluation period</time_frame>
    <description>Frequency of treatment-related adverse events as assessed by CTCAE v4.03</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Grade of treatment-related adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>From predose to up to 5 days following the dosing and evaluation period</time_frame>
    <description>Grade of treatment-related adverse events as assessed by CTCAE v4.03</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>5</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Solid Tumor Refractory to Standard Therapy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>SQ-001 125mL/day</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>SQ-001 250mL/day</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>SQ-001 500mL/day</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>SQ-001 625mL/day</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>saline(0.9% NaCl injection)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>SQ001 125mL/day</intervention_name>
    <description>SQ001 125mL/day will be administered by intravenous route at a rate of 3 mL/minute</description>
    <arm_group_label>SQ-001 125mL/day</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>SQ001 250mL/day</intervention_name>
    <description>SQ001 250mL/day will be administered by intravenous route at a rate of 3 mL/minute</description>
    <arm_group_label>SQ-001 250mL/day</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>SQ001 500mL/day</intervention_name>
    <description>SQ001 500mL/day will be administered by intravenous route at a rate of 3 mL/minute</description>
    <arm_group_label>SQ-001 500mL/day</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>SQ001 625mL/day</intervention_name>
    <description>SQ001 625mL/day will be administered by intravenous route at a rate of 3 mL/minute</description>
    <arm_group_label>SQ-001 625mL/day</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Saline 0.9%</intervention_name>
    <description>Saline 0.9% will be administered by intravenous route at a rate of 3 mL/minute</description>
    <arm_group_label>saline(0.9% NaCl injection)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Subjects must be medically documented as healthy at the time of screening as
             determined by their medical history, physical examination, vital signs, 12-lead ECG,
             and clinical laboratory tests, unless the Investigator considers an abnormality to be
             clinically irrelevant.

          2. Subjects must be within 18 to 65 years old and not currently using tobacco products.

          3. Subjects must have a BMI within 18 to 32 kg/m2.

          4. Females

               1. Surgically sterilized (e.g., hysterectomy or bilateral oophorectomy) for at least
                  6 months prior to screening or postmenopausal (postmenopausal women must have no
                  menstrual bleeding for at least 1 year prior to screening and menopause will be
                  confirmed by a plasma FSH level of &gt;30 IU/L) or

               2. Women of child-bearing potential must be non-lactating and agree to use a highly
                  effective acceptable form of birth control such as surgical sterilization (e.g.,
                  tubal ligation), or total abstinence from sexual intercourse with the opposite
                  sex, or established hormonal birth control (e.g. oral, implant or injection) plus
                  a barrier method, or a double barrier method (e.g. intrauterine device plus
                  condom or spermicidal gel plus condom or diaphragm plus condom) from 14 days
                  prior to dosing until 30 days after dosing.

               3. Women with a negative serum pregnancy test (βhCG assay) at screening and at Day
                  -1 (urine)

               4. For non-sexually active females, abstinence may be regarded as an adequate method
                  of birth control, but if the subject becomes sexually active during the study,
                  she must use adequate birth control as defined above for the remainder of the
                  study.

          5. Males Must be willing to use highly effective forms of acceptable birth control (e.g.,
             vasectomy, total abstinence from sexual intercourse with the opposite sex, sexual
             intercourse with a woman who is not of childbearing potential) from Day 1 dosing to
             Day 90 after dose.

          6. Subjects must be able to comply with the study and follow-up procedures.

          7. Subjects must provide a signed informed consent to participate in the study.

          8. Subjects must not have participated in any clinical trial within 30 days.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Any condition preventing reliable phlebotomy or infusion from the cubital fossa.

          2. Documented history of clinically significant unstable medical illness.

          3. History of clinically significant drug, food, or environmental allergy.

          4. Subjects with any uncontrolled medical condition deemed clinically significant by an
             Investigator.

          5. Clinically significant safety laboratory, 12-lead ECG, or vital sign abnormalities
             during screening or Day -1 that would place the subject at undue risk based on the
             Investigator's opinion, including but not limited to:

               1. History of cardiac conditions that might give a higher risk of an increase in
                  heart rate

               2. Fridericia's corrected QT interval (QTcF) interval of &gt;450 msec on 12-lead ECG

               3. Alanine aminotransferase (ALT) &gt;1.2 × upper limit of normal (ULN), aspartate
                  aminotransferase (AST) &gt;1.2 × ULN

               4. Blood urea nitrogen (BUN) or serum creatinine &gt;1.2 × ULN

          6. Subjects who are positive for HIV, HBV, and/or HCV.

          7. Subjects who have used prescription drugs, over-the-counter drugs, or herbal remedies
             within 14 days before Day 1 of study medication dosing.

          8. Women who are pregnant or breast feeding.

          9. Subjects who participated in a clinical trial within 30 days prior to Day 1 study
             medication dosing.

         10. Subjects with any condition that, in the judgment of the Principal Investigator, would
             place a subject at undue risk, or potentially compromise the results or interpretation
             of the study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Maria I. Bermudez, MD.CPI</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Clinical Pharmacology of Miami, Inc.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Clinical Pharmacology of Miami, Inc.</name>
      <address>
        <city>Miami</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33014-3616</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 14, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 17, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 19, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 17, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 17, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 19, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

