<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04026984</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CB-01-11/29</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04026984</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study to Evaluate Safety and Efficacy of Rifamycin SV MMX in the Treatment of Traveler's Diarrhea in Children Age 6 to 11 Years</brief_title>
  <official_title>Double Blind, Multi-center Study to Evaluate the Safety and Efficacy of 100 mg Twice Daily Rifamycin SV MMX® Added to Standard Oral Rehydration Therapy (ORT) Versus Placebo Plus ORT, in the Treatment of Traveler's Diarrhea in Children Age 6 to 11 Years</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Cosmo Technologies Ltd</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>CosmoTech</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This will be a double-blind comparative study, performed in pediatric subjects (Age 6-11)
      traveling to developing regions with a known high incidence of traveler's diarrhea. The
      subjects will be suffering from acute diarrhea for at least 12 hours, without symptoms of
      systemic infection.

      Approximately 142 subjects are expected to be enrolled in the study, 1:1 in the Rifamycin SV
      MultiMatrix (MMX) plus Oral Rescue Therapy (ORT) group and in the placebo tablets plus ORT
      group respectively. The day of randomization (Visit 1, Day 1), the subjects will start the
      treatment receiving ORT plus Rifamycin SV MMX 100 mg (as two tablets of 50 mg each) twice
      daily (morning and evening) or ORT plus placebo tablets (as two tablets) twice daily (morning
      and evening). The subjects will begin the treatment within 72 hours of onset of diarrhea.
      Treatment duration will last 72 hours. The total number of tablets for the entire treatment
      course will be 12 (4 × 50 mg tablets/day for 3 days). The administration of the ORT will
      follow the specification reported in the product label. The tablets will be orally
      administered during the day. No tablet administration will be done during the night.

      After enrollment, subjects/their parents/or guardians will complete Diary cards (PDC) in
      which will be daily recorded date, time of first tablets intake, time and consistency of each
      stool, presence of blood in stools, abdominal pain/cramps, flatulence, tenesmus, urgency,
      nausea, vomiting, fever, adverse events (AEs), and concomitant medications.

      During the study, the subjects will be assessed for safety and efficacy at Visit 2 (Day 2)
      and Visit 3 (Day 4/5) as final Study Visit.

      Stool samples for microbiological assessment will be collected at Visits 1 and 3. Stool will
      be examined and cultured at local labs for main enteropathogens and for the presence of
      protozoa, ova and yeasts.

      Blood and urine sampling for routine safety analyses will be collected at Visit 1 and at
      Visit 3.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">March 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical Cure</measure>
    <time_frame>120 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Passage of two or fewer soft stools and no watery stools, no fever (&gt; 100.4 ºF or 38 ºC), and no signs or symptoms of enteric infection (other than mild excess gas/flatulence) during a 24-hour interval in the 120-hour data collection period after the first dose of study drug or Passage of no stools or only formed stools and no fever during a 48-hour interval in the 120-hour data collection period after the first dose of study drug, with or without other signs or symptoms of enteric infection.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to last unformed stool (TLUS)</measure>
    <time_frame>120 hours</time_frame>
    <description>defined as the interval in hours between the first dose of study drug and the last unformed stool passed, after which clinical cure was declared. Subjects who meet the criteria for clinical cure immediately after the start of the study and prior to passing any unformed stools are defined as having a TLUS of 0 hours. Subjects who terminated the study early due treatment failure will have a censored TLUS of 120 hours.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Microbiological Cure</measure>
    <time_frame>120 hours</time_frame>
    <description>The proportion of subjects with an identified pathogen at baseline with microbiological eradication in the post-treatment stool sample.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Treatment Failure</measure>
    <time_frame>120 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Defined as either of the following: Worsening diarrhea and/or signs or symptoms of enteric infection or failure to improve 24 hours or more after the first dose of study drug that results in administration of rescue therapy and/or Not achieving Clinical Cure in the 120-hr data collection period after the first dose of study drug or use of antimicrobial prohibited concomitant medication. Occurrence of AEs.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetics (PK) in a subset population</measure>
    <time_frame>120 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Xf of fecal rifamycin SV after multiple dose of Rifamycin SV MMX 50 mg tablets.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetics (PK) in a subset population</measure>
    <time_frame>120 hours</time_frame>
    <description>ΣXf of fecal rifamycin SV after multiple dose of Rifamycin SV MMX 50 mg</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetics (PK) in a subset population</measure>
    <time_frame>120 hours</time_frame>
    <description>dXf/dt of fecal rifamycin SV after multiple dose of Rifamycin SV MMX 50 mg</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">142</enrollment>
  <condition>Traveler's Diarrhea</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Rifamycin SV MMX plus ORT</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo tablets plus ORT</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Placebo to Rifamycin SV-MMX® Placebo tablets correspond to active tablets with respect to size, taste, and appearance.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo tablets plus ORT</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Rifamycin SV-MMX</intervention_name>
    <description>2 Rifamycin SV-MMX® 50 mg tablets b.i.d. plus ORT</description>
    <arm_group_label>Rifamycin SV MMX plus ORT</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Diagnosis of acute bacterial diarrhea defined as at least 3 unformed stools within the
             24 hours preceding randomization, with a duration of illness ≤72 h. The bacterial
             origin of diarrhea will be confirmed &quot;a posteriori&quot; by stool microbiology sampling at
             the time of screening.

          -  Presence of one or more signs or symptoms of enteric infection, including nausea,
             vomiting, abdominal cramps or pain, tenesmus, urgency

          -  History of recent travel from an industrialized country to a developing region with a
             known high incidence of travelers' diarrhea

          -  Male or female 6-11 years of age, providing an unformed pre-treatment stool

          -  The parent or legally acceptable representative must provide informed consent for the
             subject. The Subject must also provide written informed assent and be accompanied by
             the parent or legal guardian at the time of assent/consent signing.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Fever (&gt;100.4ºF or 38ºC), or presence of signs and symptoms of systemic infection

          -  Known or suspected infection with non-bacterial pathogen

          -  Symptoms of acute diarrhea of &gt;72 hours duration

          -  Presence of grossly bloody stool

          -  Moderate to severe dehydration

          -  History of inflammatory bowel disease (IBD)

          -  Abdominal ileus

          -  Severe dehydration

          -  Greater than two doses of an antidiarrheal medication within 24 hours before
             randomization, or any symptomatic therapy within 2 hours before enrolment

          -  Receiving antimicrobial drug with expected activity against enteric bacterial
             pathogens within the week prior to enrolment

          -  Hypersensitivity to rifamycin-related antibiotics or to any excipient included in the
             study medications

          -  Subjects unable/unwilling to comply with study protocol

          -  Participation in a clinical trial within the last 30 days
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>6 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>11 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Richard Jones</last_name>
    <phone>+35318170370</phone>
    <email>rjones@cosmopharma.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Emma O'Shea</last_name>
    <phone>+35318170370</phone>
    <email>eoshea@cosmopharma.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <verification_date>July 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 12, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 18, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 19, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 18, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 18, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 19, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Dysentery</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diarrhea</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Rifamycins</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Rifamycin SV</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

