<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04028466</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>RP 19-007</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04028466</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effectiveness of Vonoprazan vs Omeprazole as Empiric Therapy for Gastroesophageal Reflux Disease (GERD) Patients Without Alarm Features</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effectiveness of Vonoprazan vs Omeprazole as Empiric Therapy for Gastroesophageal Reflux Disease (GERD) Patients Without Alarm Features in a Primary Care Setting: A Pragmatic, Randomized, Single Blind Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>St. Luke's Medical Center, Philippines</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>St. Luke's Medical Center, Philippines</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Gastroesophageal reflux disease is a commonly encountered disorder in daily practice. Proton
      pump inhibitor therapy has been the cornerstone of treatment for decades. Although it has
      been proven to be highly effective, there is still room for improvement. A local study showed
      that only 57.3% of subjects are asymptomatic after 4 weeks treatment with rabeprazole.
      Recently a new drug was developed with better absorption, higher bioavailability, more
      sustained increased pH in the stomach and more targeted action to the H-K ATPase pump.
      Vonoprazan, belongs to a new class of acid suppressant medications, the potassium-competitive
      acid blocker (P-CAB). Vonoprazan has been studied and used successfully in Japan for H pylori
      eradication therapy, GERD, gastric and duodenal ulcers with favorable safety profile.
      However, to the author's knowledge, no study yet exists comparing vonoprazan to a proton pump
      inhibitor in the treatment of GERD outside Japan. This study aims to determine whether
      vonoprazan is superior to omeprazole in relieving symptoms in treatment-naïve adult patients
      with GERD.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Gastroesophageal Reflux Disease (GERD) is globally defined as a condition that develops when
      the reflux of stomach contents causes troublesome symptoms and/or complications. The
      Philippine Clinical Practice Guideline on the Diagnosis and Treatment of GERD defined is as a
      condition resulting from recurrent backflow of gastric contents into the esophagus and
      adjacent structures causing troublesome symptoms and/or tissue injury. It is a commonly
      encountered disorder in the clinics and daily practice. A clinical diagnosis of GERD is
      acceptable with typical symptoms of acid regurgitation and/or heartburn is present. The
      Philippine guidelines state that empiric therapy can be started in GERD patients without
      alarm features and don't require further laboratory exam or workup. The guideline recommends
      standard dose proton pump inhibitor (PPI) therapy once daily for 8 weeks as cornerstone for
      treatment.

      Proton pump inhibitor (PPI) therapy has been used as first line therapy of reflux symptoms
      for more than a decade. Even though it has been proven to be highly effective for reflux
      symptoms, there are still unaddressed issues. A local study by Lontok et al in 2013 evaluated
      response of GERD patients to rabeprazole 20mg once daily using a locally validated Frequency
      Scale of Symptoms of GERD (FSSG) in a primary care setting. Their study showed that a 4 week
      rabeprazole therapy resulting in complete resolution of individual symptoms ranging from
      81.9-90.3%, with only 57.3% of all subjects being completely asymptomatic at the end of
      treatment. Proton pump inhibitors also have unmet issues needing improvement. PPIs usually
      takes 5 days for their maximal effect. Because of their slow onset of action, a significant
      number of patients are not sufficiently relieved after the first dose of PPI. Approximately
      half of patients still have symptoms after 3 days of treatment. PPIs are influenced by the
      cytochrome P450 (CYP) 2C19 polymorphism, with rapid metabolizers having the lowest
      intragastric pH compared with slow metabolizers. PPIs are also not sufficiently effective in
      controlling nocturnal heartburn symptoms because overnight recovery of gastric acid is
      frequently seen, therefore causing loss of sleep and health-related reductions in quality of
      life.

      Recently, a new drug that promises better pharmacokinetic and pharmacodynamics properties was
      developed. Its use has been mostly in Japan for the past 2 years. Vonoprazan, is a novel,
      potassium-competitive acid blocker (P-CAB) that binds and inhibits H-K ATPase, the final step
      in acid secretion from the parietal cells of the stomach. It can inhibit the proton pump in
      both acidic and neutral environments with high affinity. The drug is retained for a long time
      inside the parietal cells and can inhibit H-K ATPase that is activated by further stimulation
      of acid secretion. Vonoprazan offers the advantage of not being required to be taken before
      meals, compared to conventional PPIs where 30 minutes before a meal is required, and is
      unaffected by the CYP2C19 polymorphism. Vonoprazan is also effectively absorbed and quickly
      accumulates in parietal cells, therefore, acid inhibition is more pronounced after the first
      dose of vonoprazan, compared to conventional PPIs where it usually takes 3-5 days for maximal
      effect. Vonoprazan is therefore, a stronger acid blocker that has rapid, stable and
      longer-lasting effects. Of the author's knowledge only 2 large scale randomized controlled
      trial have been done with vonoprazan, both these studies were done in Japan and focus only on
      those with erosive esophagitis. Vonoprazan has been showed to be effective and noninferior to
      lansoprazole for curing erosive esophagitis, as well as PPI resistant erosive esophagitis,
      with healing rates more pronounced for Grade C and D erosive esophagitis. Other studies on
      the use of vonoprazan for GERD have been done only in Japan, and comprised of noninferiority
      and small retrospective open label trials.

      When vonoprazan is used for short term acid suppression, there are no problematic side
      effects. Treatment emergent adverse events irrespective of causal relationship to study
      medication are nasopharyngitis, diarrhea, constipation, upper respiratory infection, fall,
      gastroenteritis and eczema. Most of these treatment emergent adverse events were classified
      as mild in intensity. Studies are ongoing in Japan to assess the long term safety and
      efficacy of vonoprazan

      . The Philippine Clinical Practice Guideline for GERD recommends locally-validated
      standardized questionnaire to assess treatment response to GERD. Commonly used questionnaires
      in the Philippines are the Frequency Scale for Severity of GERD (FSSG) and the
      Gastroesophageal Reflux Disease Questionnaire (GERDQ); both have undergone local validation
      studies. FSSG has been shown to correlate with endoscopic severity of GERD and assess
      response to proton pump inhibitor therapy.2 The FSSG comprises 12 questions where patients
      would rate individual symptoms as never (0% of the time), occasionally (around 30% of the
      time), sometimes (50%), often (70%) or always (100%). GERD is diagnosed if the score is more
      than 8, with sensitivity of 62%, specificity of 59% and accuracy of 60% for endoscopic
      diagnosis of esophagitis.

      Vonoprazan was just recently introduced to the Philippine market recently. Whether or not
      this drug may replace conventional PPIs as first line therapy remains to be determined. This
      study aims to determine whether vonoprazan is superior to omeprazole in treating
      treatment-naïve adult patients with GERD. Data from this study will help formulate policies
      and recommendations on the treatment of GERD, as well as formulate new treatment strategies
      for patients with GERD.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 26, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 30, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 30, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Pragmatic, Randomized, Single Blind Study</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>Randomized, Single Blind Study. Only primary investigators are blinded. the primary investigator also are the outcome assessors</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of asymptomatic patients at Day 3</measure>
    <time_frame>day 3 of therapy</time_frame>
    <description>Asymptomatic patients is defined as a patient being free of symptoms of heartburn or acid regurgitation according to FSSG questionnaire (score &lt;8) Expressed in percentage</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of asymptomatic patients at Day 7</measure>
    <time_frame>day 7 of therapy</time_frame>
    <description>Asymptomatic patients is defined as a patient being free of symptoms of heartburn or acid regurgitation according to FSSG questionnaire (score &lt;8) Expressed in percentage</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of asymptomatic patients at Day 14</measure>
    <time_frame>day 14 of therapy</time_frame>
    <description>Asymptomatic patients is defined as a patient being free of symptoms of heartburn or acid regurgitation according to FSSG questionnaire (score &lt;8) Expressed in percentage</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of partial responders at Day 3</measure>
    <time_frame>day 3 of therapy</time_frame>
    <description>Partial responder are patients who still have GERD symptoms, but with partial improvement on reevaluation using the FSSG questionnaire; patients with at least 50% reduction from the baseline FSSG score Expressed in percentage</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of partial responders at Day 7</measure>
    <time_frame>day 7 of therapy</time_frame>
    <description>Partial responder are patients who still have GERD symptoms, but with partial improvement on reevaluation using the FSSG questionnaire; patients with at least 50% reduction from the baseline FSSG score Expressed in percentage</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of partial responders at Day 14</measure>
    <time_frame>day 14 of therapy</time_frame>
    <description>Partial responder are patients who still have GERD symptoms, but with partial improvement on reevaluation using the FSSG questionnaire; patients with at least 50% reduction from the baseline FSSG score Expressed in percentage</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of nonresponders at Day 14</measure>
    <time_frame>day 14 of therapy</time_frame>
    <description>Nonresponders are patients who reported no significant improvement in symptoms with treatment; patients with less than 50% reduction from the baseline FSSG score Expressed in percentage</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percent change in the symptom score from baseline (Vonoprazan Group) - Day 3</measure>
    <time_frame>day 3 of therapy</time_frame>
    <description>Difference in the symptom score from baseline using the FSSG questionnaire at each time point within Vonoprazan and omeprazole group; expressed in percentage</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percent change in the symptom score from baseline (Vonoprazan Group) - Day 7</measure>
    <time_frame>day 7 of therapy</time_frame>
    <description>Difference in the symptom score from baseline using the FSSG questionnaire at each time point within Vonoprazan and omeprazole group; expressed in percentage</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percent change in the symptom score from baseline (Vonoprazan Group) - Day 14</measure>
    <time_frame>day 14 of therapy</time_frame>
    <description>Difference in the symptom score from baseline using the FSSG questionnaire at each time point within Vonoprazan and omeprazole group; expressed in percentage</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference in percent change in the symptom score (between groups)</measure>
    <time_frame>day 3, 7, and 14 of therapy</time_frame>
    <description>Difference in the percent change of the FSSG score between groups will be analyzed using independent T test or Mann-Whitney U test between vonoprazan and omeprazole groups at one point in time</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Patients with Adverse Effects</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 14 of therapy</time_frame>
    <description>Safety and frequency of adverse effects experienced by patients (nasopharyngitis, diarrhea, constipation, upper respiratory tract infection, gastroenteritis, eczema/allergy, hypergastrinemia)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">224</enrollment>
  <condition>GERD</condition>
  <condition>Gastro Esophageal Reflux</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Vonoprazan</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients will be randomized to receiving vonoprazan, which will be taken 30 minutes before the first meal of the day for 14 days</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Omeprazole</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients will be randomized to receiving omeprazole, which will be taken 30 minutes before the first meal of the day for 14 days</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Vonoprazan</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients will be randomized to receiving vonoprazan 20mg tablet or omeprazole 40mg capsule, either of which will be taken 30 minutes before the first meal of the day for 14 days</description>
    <arm_group_label>Vonoprazan</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Investigational Arm</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Omeprazole</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients will be randomized to receving vonoprazan 20mg tablet or omeprazole 40mg capsule, either of which will be taken 30 minutes before the first meal of the day for 14 days</description>
    <arm_group_label>Omeprazole</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Control Arm</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  All Adult patients with clinically diagnosed with Gastroesophageal Reflux Disease
             (GERD) without alarm features (heartburn and acid regurgitation)

          -  Age more than 18 years at the time of written consent

          -  Those who provide written consent with their own free will

          -  Both treatment naïve and treatment experienced patients will be included. Treatment
             experienced patients should not be taking any proton pump inhibitors for 2 weeks to
             allow for washout period.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients that have alarm features as defined by the Philippines Guidelines for GERD
             (dysphagia, odynophagia, weight loss, anemia, hematemesis, family history of
             esophageal adenocarcinoma, nocturnal choking, abdominal mass, recurrent/frequent
             vomiting, chest pain)

          -  Patients with atypical GERD symptoms (cough, laryngitis, chest pain, etc.)

          -  Patients already taking proton pump inhibitors for the past 2 weeks

          -  Patients who scored less than 8 on the FSSG questionnaire

          -  Patients who have undergone gastroesophageal surgery

          -  Patients who are poorly compliant to medications

          -  allergy to PPI or vonoprazan

          -  With serious comorbidities, such as but not limited to: heart failure, renal failure,
             malignancy or hepatic failure

          -  Pregnant, breastfeeding or possibly pregnant

          -  Patients that would not provide consent

          -  Patients who are unable to complete the FSSG Questionnaire independently

          -  Patients who are unable to follow up at designated periods

          -  Patients taking rilpivirine or atazanavir.

          -  Patients with elevated baseline liver function tests (more than twice the upper limit
             of normal)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Nicodemus L Ong, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Institute of Digestive and Liver Diseases, St. Luke's Medical Center, Quezon City</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Sherrie Isabel Q De Ocampo, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Institute of Digestive and Liver Diseases, St. Luke's Medical Center, Quezon City</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Nicodemus L Ong, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+639176791018</phone>
    <email>nico.ongmd@yahoo.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Sherrie Isabel Q De Ocampo, MD</last_name>
    <phone>09338555954</phone>
    <email>sherrieq@hotmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>St. Luke's Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Quezon City</city>
        <state>National Capital Region</state>
        <zip>1112</zip>
        <country>Philippines</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Nicodemus L Ong, MD</last_name>
      <phone>9176791018</phone>
      <email>nico.ongmd@yahoo.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Sherrie Isabel Q de Ocampo, MD</last_name>
      <phone>9338555954</phone>
      <email>sherrieq@hotmail.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>NIcodemus L Ong, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Sherrie Isabel Q de Ocampo, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Philippines</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Vakil N, van Zanten SV, Kahrilas P, Dent J, Jones R; Global Consensus Group. The Montreal definition and classification of gastroesophageal reflux disease: a global evidence-based consensus. Am J Gastroenterol. 2006 Aug;101(8):1900-20; quiz 1943.</citation>
    <PMID>16928254</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cederberg C, Lind T, Röhss K, Olbe L. Comparison of once-daily intravenous and oral omeprazole on pentagastrin-stimulated acid secretion in duodenal ulcer patients. Digestion. 1992;53(3-4):171-8.</citation>
    <PMID>1291405</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dammann HG, Burkhardt F. Pantoprazole versus omeprazole: influence on meal-stimulated gastric acid secretion. Eur J Gastroenterol Hepatol. 1999 Nov;11(11):1277-82.</citation>
    <PMID>10563540</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bytzer P, Morocutti A, Kennerly P, Ravic M, Miller N; ROSE Trial Investigators. Effect of rabeprazole and omeprazole on the onset of gastro-oesophageal reflux disease symptom relief during the first seven days of treatment. Scand J Gastroenterol. 2006 Oct;41(10):1132-40.</citation>
    <PMID>16990197</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Peura DA, Riff DS, Snoddy AM, Fennerty MB. Clinical trial: lansoprazole 15 or 30 mg once daily vs. placebo for treatment of frequent nighttime heartburn in self-treating subjects. Aliment Pharmacol Ther. 2009 Sep 1;30(5):459-68. doi: 10.1111/j.1365-2036.2009.04064.x. Epub 2009 Jun 11.</citation>
    <PMID>19523177</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chong E, Ensom MH. Pharmacogenetics of the proton pump inhibitors: a systematic review. Pharmacotherapy. 2003 Apr;23(4):460-71. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>12680476</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Furuta T, Shirai N, Sugimoto M, Nakamura A, Hishida A, Ishizaki T. Influence of CYP2C19 pharmacogenetic polymorphism on proton pump inhibitor-based therapies. Drug Metab Pharmacokinet. 2005 Jun;20(3):153-67. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>15988117</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Katz PO, Castell DO, Chen Y, Andersson T, Sostek MB. Intragastric acid suppression and pharmacokinetics of twice-daily esomeprazole: a randomized, three-way crossover study. Aliment Pharmacol Ther. 2004 Aug 15;20(4):399-406.</citation>
    <PMID>15298633</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Johnson DA, Katz PO. Nocturnal gastroesophageal reflux disease: issues, implications, and management strategies. Rev Gastroenterol Disord. 2008 Spring;8(2):98-108. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18641592</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fass R, Chey WD, Zakko SF, Andhivarothai N, Palmer RN, Perez MC, Atkinson SN. Clinical trial: the effects of the proton pump inhibitor dexlansoprazole MR on daytime and nighttime heartburn in patients with non-erosive reflux disease. Aliment Pharmacol Ther. 2009 Jun 15;29(12):1261-72. doi: 10.1111/j.1365-2036.2009.04013.x. Epub 2009 Apr 8.</citation>
    <PMID>19392864</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kusano M, Shimoyama Y, Sugimoto S, Kawamura O, Maeda M, Minashi K, Kuribayashi S, Higuchi T, Zai H, Ino K, Horikoshi T, Sugiyama T, Toki M, Ohwada T, Mori M. Development and evaluation of FSSG: frequency scale for the symptoms of GERD. J Gastroenterol. 2004 Sep;39(9):888-91.</citation>
    <PMID>15565409</PMID>
  </reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Oshima T, Miwa H. Potent Potassium-competitive Acid Blockers: A New Era for the Treatment of Acid-related Diseases. J Neurogastroenterol Motil. 2018 Jul 30;24(3):334-344. doi: 10.5056/jnm18029. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>29739175</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Ashida K, Sakurai Y, Hori T, Kudou K, Nishimura A, Hiramatsu N, Umegaki E, Iwakiri K. Randomised clinical trial: vonoprazan, a novel potassium-competitive acid blocker, vs. lansoprazole for the healing of erosive oesophagitis. Aliment Pharmacol Ther. 2016 Jan;43(2):240-51. doi: 10.1111/apt.13461. Epub 2015 Nov 11.</citation>
    <PMID>26559637</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Iwakiri K, Sakurai Y, Shiino M, Okamoto H, Kudou K, Nishimura A, Hiramatsu N, Umegaki E, Ashida K. A randomized, double-blind study to evaluate the acid-inhibitory effect of vonoprazan (20 mg and 40 mg) in patients with proton-pump inhibitor-resistant erosive esophagitis. Therap Adv Gastroenterol. 2017 Jun;10(6):439-451. doi: 10.1177/1756283X17705329. Epub 2017 Apr 25.</citation>
    <PMID>28567114</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Shinozaki S, Osawa H, Hayashi Y, Sakamoto H, Kobayashi Y, Lefor AK, Yamamoto H. Vonoprazan 10 mg daily is effective for the treatment of patients with proton pump inhibitor-resistant gastroesophageal reflux disease. Biomed Rep. 2017 Sep;7(3):231-235. doi: 10.3892/br.2017.947. Epub 2017 Jul 20.</citation>
    <PMID>28894571</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Kinoshita Y, Sakurai Y, Shiino M, Kudou K, Nishimura A, Miyagi T, Iwakiri K, Umegaki E, Ashida K. Evaluation of the Efficacy and Safety of Vonoprazan in Patients with Nonerosive Gastroesophageal Reflux Disease: A Phase III, Randomized, Double-Blind, Placebo-Controlled, Multicenter Study. Curr Ther Res Clin Exp. 2016 Dec 21;81-82:1-7. doi: 10.1016/j.curtheres.2016.12.001. eCollection 2016.</citation>
    <PMID>28119763</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Mori H, Suzuki H. Role of Acid Suppression in Acid-related Diseases: Proton Pump Inhibitor and Potassium-competitive Acid Blocker. J Neurogastroenterol Motil. 2019 Jan 31;25(1):6-14. doi: 10.5056/jnm18139. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>30504527</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>July 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 6, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 19, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 22, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 19, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 19, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 22, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>St. Luke's Medical Center, Philippines</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Nicodemus Ong</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Fellow and Principal Investigator, Institute of Digestlve and Liver Diseases</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>GERD</keyword>
  <keyword>gastro esophageal reflux</keyword>
  <keyword>proton pump inhibitor</keyword>
  <keyword>Potassium-Competitive Acid Blocker</keyword>
  <keyword>H(+)-K(+)-Exchanging ATPase</keyword>
  <keyword>Randomized Controlled Trial</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Gastroesophageal Reflux</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Omeprazole</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Approval from the Institutional review board should be secured before IPD will be made available</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

