<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03170362</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>SDR 16-348</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03170362</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>PRIME Care (PRecision Medicine In MEntal Health Care)</brief_title>
  <acronym>PRIME Care</acronym>
  <official_title>PRIME Care (PRecision Medicine In MEntal Health Care)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>VA Office of Research and Development</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>VA Office of Research and Development</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The focus of this application is on the impact of providing depressed Veterans and their
      providers with the results of pharmacogenetic (PGx) testing for psychotropic medications. The
      project focuses on whether and how patients and providers use genetic test results given to
      them at the time an antidepressant is to be initiated to treat Major Depressive Disorder
      (MDD) and whether use of the test results improves patient outcomes. MDD is one of the most
      common conditions associated with military service and combat exposure, increases suicide
      risk, and worsens the course of common medical conditions, making it a leading cause of
      functional impairment and mortality. Validation of a PGx test to personalize the treatment of
      MDD represents an important opportunity to improve the healthcare of Veterans.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Background: In the last several years, commercial pharmacogenetic (PGx) testing for
      psychotropic medications has become widespread as a means of implementing &quot;precision
      medicine&quot;, with some insurers electing to cover the cost of testing. These developments have
      put increasing pressure on the Veterans Health Administration to implement a mental health
      focused PGxs program, especially for treating depression, but without sufficient scientific
      study to support the utility of clinical application.

      Objectives: The investigators propose a program of research to evaluate the utility of PGx
      testing in treating Major Depressive Disorder.

      Methods: The investigators plan a multi-site RCT (n=2000), patient/provider dyads will be
      randomly assigned to receive results of the PGx battery right after randomization (i.e.
      intervention group) or after 6 months of treatment as usual (i.e. delayed results group)The
      study will test the following hypotheses:

        1. Veterans with MDD whose care is guided by the results of the PGx battery (the
           intervention group) will have a higher rate of remission of depression than the delayed
           results group. (Primary Hypothesis)

        2. Provider/patient dyads in the intervention group will use fewer contraindicated
           medications based on established PGx criteria than the delayed results group. (Primary
           Hypothesis)
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Enrolling by invitation</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 15, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 31, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 30, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>The study intervention is the provision of pharmacogenetic test results which can then be used to choice appropriate medication.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Depression Severity</measure>
    <time_frame>24 weeks post randomization</time_frame>
    <description>The investigators will use the PHQ9 as a self assessed marker of depression severity.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Use of recommended medications</measure>
    <time_frame>Over the 24 week period</time_frame>
    <description>The investigators will examine the proportion of antidepressants used that conform to the recommendations from the pharmacogenetic testing. Medication dose and selection will be considered in determining if a proscription conforms to the recommendation of the testing.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Self-reported antidepressant side effects</measure>
    <time_frame>over the 24 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Self reported assessment of side effects related to antidepressants. Specific questions about nausea, headache, vomiting, GI distress, and sexual dysfunction. Each item rated as not present, mild, moderate, severe</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>VR -12 - Quality of life measure</measure>
    <time_frame>24 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The investigators will use the VR-12 as a self reported quality of life measure.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Provider attitudes</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and 24 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>This is a provider assessment of knowledge and attitudes regarding pharmacogenetic testing.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">2000</enrollment>
  <condition>Major Depression</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Pharmacogenetic test results will be provided to the provider within 72 hours of randomization in order to facilitate choice in selecting antidepressants.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Delay results group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>The comparator arm will not receive results at the time of randomization but will get results after the 24 week assessment (thus the results are delayed).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pharmacogenetic Test</intervention_name>
    <description>The intervention is a battery of pharmacogenetic test results that mostly affect the metabolism of antidepressants and other medications.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  PHQ-9 score 10 and a presumptive diagnosis of MDD per PHQ-9 criteria

          -  at least one prior treatment exposure for MDD (psychotherapy or antidepressant

          -  intent to start treatment of the MDD with an antidepressant, simple dose increases
             will not be considered inclusionary

          -  willingness to provide signed, informed consent to participate in the study

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  current serious co-occurring psychiatric illness, i.e.:

               -  schizophrenia

               -  bipolar disorder

               -  psychotic major depression

               -  borderline or antisocial personality disorder

               -  eating disorder

          -  active alcohol or other drug use disorder

          -  current use of an antipsychotic medication

          -  augmentation therapy, e.g.:

               -  use of two or more antidepressants at the time of randomization (trazodone at a
                  dosage &lt; 150 mg/day will not be considered augmentation and thus allowed)

          -  patients requiring urgent care or inpatient hospitalization at the time of consent

          -  currently incarcerated
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>David W. Oslin, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Corporal Michael J. Crescenz VA Medical Center, Philadelphia, PA</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Central Arkansas Veterans Healthcare System Eugene J. Towbin Healthcare Center, Little Rock, AR</name>
      <address>
        <city>North Little Rock</city>
        <state>Arkansas</state>
        <zip>72114-1706</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>VA Palo Alto Health Care System, Palo Alto, CA</name>
      <address>
        <city>Palo Alto</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94304-1290</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>San Francisco VA Medical Center, San Francisco, CA</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Francisco</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94121</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>VA Greater Los Angeles Healthcare System, West Los Angeles, CA</name>
      <address>
        <city>West Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90073</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Rocky Mountain Regional VA Medical Center, Aurora, CO</name>
      <address>
        <city>Aurora</city>
        <state>Colorado</state>
        <zip>80045</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>VA Connecticut Healthcare System West Haven Campus, West Haven, CT</name>
      <address>
        <city>West Haven</city>
        <state>Connecticut</state>
        <zip>06516</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Wilmington VA Medical Center, Wilmington, DE</name>
      <address>
        <city>Wilmington</city>
        <state>Delaware</state>
        <zip>19805</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Miami VA Healthcare System, Miami, FL</name>
      <address>
        <city>Miami</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33125</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Baltimore VA Medical Center VA Maryland Health Care System, Baltimore, MD</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21201</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>VA Boston Healthcare System Jamaica Plain Campus, Jamaica Plain, MA</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02130</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>VA Ann Arbor Healthcare System, Ann Arbor, MI</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ann Arbor</city>
        <state>Michigan</state>
        <zip>48105</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Minneapolis VA Health Care System, Minneapolis, MN</name>
      <address>
        <city>Minneapolis</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55417</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>VA Western New York Healthcare System, Buffalo, NY</name>
      <address>
        <city>Buffalo</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>14215</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Salisbury W.G. (Bill) Hefner VA Medical Center, Salisbury, NC</name>
      <address>
        <city>Salisbury</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>28144</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cincinnati VA Medical Center, Cincinnati, OH</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cincinnati</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>45220</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Louis Stokes VA Medical Center, Cleveland, OH</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cleveland</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>44106</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Corporal Michael J. Crescenz VA Medical Center, Philadelphia, PA</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19104</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>VA Pittsburgh Healthcare System University Drive Division, Pittsburgh, PA</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pittsburgh</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>15240</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ralph H. Johnson VA Medical Center, Charleston, SC</name>
      <address>
        <city>Charleston</city>
        <state>South Carolina</state>
        <zip>29401-5799</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Michael E. DeBakey VA Medical Center, Houston, TX</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>VA Salt Lake City Health Care System, Salt Lake City, UT</name>
      <address>
        <city>Salt Lake City</city>
        <state>Utah</state>
        <zip>84148</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hunter Holmes McGuire VA Medical Center, Richmond, VA</name>
      <address>
        <city>Richmond</city>
        <state>Virginia</state>
        <zip>23249</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>VA Puget Sound Health Care System Seattle Division, Seattle, WA</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seattle</city>
        <state>Washington</state>
        <zip>98108</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://www.mirecc.va.gov/visn4/PrimeCare/PRIME_Care.asp</url>
    <description>Click here for more information about this study: PRIME Care (PRecision medicine In MEntal health Care)</description>
  </link>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Polimanti R, Zhang H, Smith AH, Zhao H, Farrer LA, Kranzler HR, Gelernter J. Genome-wide association study of body mass index in subjects with alcohol dependence. Addict Biol. 2017 Mar;22(2):535-549. doi: 10.1111/adb.12317. Epub 2015 Oct 12.</citation>
    <PMID>26458734</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Stein MB, Chen CY, Jain S, Jensen KP, He F, Heeringa SG, Kessler RC, Maihofer A, Nock MK, Ripke S, Sun X, Thomas ML, Ursano RJ, Smoller JW, Gelernter J; Army STARRS Collaborators. Genetic risk variants for social anxiety. Am J Med Genet B Neuropsychiatr Genet. 2017 Jun;174(4):470-482. doi: 10.1002/ajmg.b.32541. Epub 2017 Apr 27.</citation>
    <PMID>28512750</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Lippard ETC, Jensen KP, Wang F, Johnston JAY, Spencer L, Pittman B, Gelernter J, Blumberg HP. Genetic variation of ANK3 is associated with lower white matter structural integrity in bipolar disorder. Mol Psychiatry. 2017 Sep;22(9):1225. doi: 10.1038/mp.2017.169.</citation>
    <PMID>28831200</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Stein MB, Chen CY, Jain S, Jensen KP, He F, Heeringa SG, Kessler RC, Maihofer A, Nock MK, Ripke S, Sun X, Thomas ML, Ursano RJ, Smoller JW, Gelernter J; Army STARRS Collaborators. Genetic risk variants for social anxiety. Am J Med Genet B Neuropsychiatr Genet. 2017 Mar;174(2):120-131. doi: 10.1002/ajmg.b.32520. Erratum in: Am J Med Genet B Neuropsychiatr Genet. 2017 Jun;174(4):470-482. Corrected and republished in: Am J Med Genet B Neuropsychiatr Genet. 2017 Jun;174(4):470-482.</citation>
    <PMID>28224735</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Post RM, Leverich GS, McElroy S, Kupka R, Suppes T, Altshuler L, Nolen W, Frye M, Keck P, Grunze H, Hellemann G. Prevalence of axis II comorbidities in bipolar disorder: relationship to mood state. Bipolar Disord. 2018 Jun;20(4):303-312. doi: 10.1111/bdi.12596. Epub 2018 Jan 25.</citation>
    <PMID>29369448</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Williams LM, Pines A, Goldstein-Piekarski AN, Rosas LG, Kullar M, Sacchet MD, Gevaert O, Bailenson J, Lavori PW, Dagum P, Wandell B, Correa C, Greenleaf W, Suppes T, Perry LM, Smyth JM, Lewis MA, Venditti EM, Snowden M, Simmons JM, Ma J. The ENGAGE study: Integrating neuroimaging, virtual reality and smartphone sensing to understand self-regulation for managing depression and obesity in a precision medicine model. Behav Res Ther. 2018 Feb;101:58-70. doi: 10.1016/j.brat.2017.09.012. Epub 2017 Oct 7.</citation>
    <PMID>29074231</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Gonzalez R, Suppes T, Zeitzer J, McClung C, Tamminga C, Tohen M, Forero A, Dwivedi A, Alvarado A. The association between mood state and chronobiological characteristics in bipolar I disorder: a naturalistic, variable cluster analysis-based study. Int J Bipolar Disord. 2018 Feb 19;6(1):5. doi: 10.1186/s40345-017-0113-5.</citation>
    <PMID>29457195</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Yatham LN, Kennedy SH, Parikh SV, Schaffer A, Bond DJ, Frey BN, Sharma V, Goldstein BI, Rej S, Beaulieu S, Alda M, MacQueen G, Milev RV, Ravindran A, O'Donovan C, McIntosh D, Lam RW, Vazquez G, Kapczinski F, McIntyre RS, Kozicky J, Kanba S, Lafer B, Suppes T, Calabrese JR, Vieta E, Malhi G, Post RM, Berk M. Canadian Network for Mood and Anxiety Treatments (CANMAT) and International Society for Bipolar Disorders (ISBD) 2018 guidelines for the management of patients with bipolar disorder. Bipolar Disord. 2018 Mar;20(2):97-170. doi: 10.1111/bdi.12609. Epub 2018 Mar 14.</citation>
    <PMID>29536616</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Vieta E, Berk M, Schulze TG, Carvalho AF, Suppes T, Calabrese JR, Gao K, Miskowiak KW, Grande I. Bipolar disorders. Nat Rev Dis Primers. 2018 Mar 8;4:18008. doi: 10.1038/nrdp.2018.8. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>29516993</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Post RM, Altshuler LL, Kupka R, McElroy SL, Frye MA, Rowe M, Grunze H, Suppes T, Keck PE Jr, Leverich GS, Nolen WA. Multigenerational transmission of liability to psychiatric illness in offspring of parents with bipolar disorder. Bipolar Disord. 2018 Jun 21. doi: 10.1111/bdi.12668. [Epub ahead of print]</citation>
    <PMID>29926532</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Nielsen DA, Spellicy CJ, Harding MJ, Graham DP. Apolipoprotein E DNA methylation and posttraumatic stress disorder are associated with plasma ApoE level: A preliminary study. Behav Brain Res. 2019 Jan 1;356:415-422. doi: 10.1016/j.bbr.2018.05.013. Epub 2018 May 26.</citation>
    <PMID>29807071</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Hull LE, Lynch KG, Oslin DW. VA Primary Care and Mental Health Providers' Comfort with Genetic Testing: Survey Results from the PRIME Care Study. J Gen Intern Med. 2019 Jun;34(6):799-801. doi: 10.1007/s11606-018-4776-0.</citation>
    <PMID>30604117</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Chanfreau-Coffinier C, Hull LE, Lynch JA, DuVall SL, Damrauer SM, Cunningham FE, Voight BF, Matheny ME, Oslin DW, Icardi MS, Tuteja S. Projected Prevalence of Actionable Pharmacogenetic Variants and Level A Drugs Prescribed Among US Veterans Health Administration Pharmacy Users. JAMA Netw Open. 2019 Jun 5;2(6):e195345. doi: 10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2019.5345.</citation>
    <PMID>31173123</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Ward RE, Cho K, Nguyen XT, Vassy JL, Ho YL, Quaden RM, Gagnon DR, Wilson PWF, Gaziano JM, Djoussé L; VA Million Veteran Program. Omega-3 supplement use, fish intake, and risk of non-fatal coronary artery disease and ischemic stroke in the Million Veteran Program. Clin Nutr. 2020 Feb;39(2):574-579. doi: 10.1016/j.clnu.2019.03.005. Epub 2019 Mar 13.</citation>
    <PMID>30914216</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Raghavan S, Vassy JL, Ho YL, Song RJ, Gagnon DR, Cho K, Wilson PWF, Phillips LS. Diabetes Mellitus-Related All-Cause and Cardiovascular Mortality in a National Cohort of Adults. J Am Heart Assoc. 2019 Feb 19;8(4):e011295. doi: 10.1161/JAHA.118.011295.</citation>
    <PMID>30776949</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Imran TF, Posner D, Honerlaw J, Vassy JL, Song RJ, Ho YL, Kittner SJ, Liao KP, Cai T, O'Donnell CJ, Djousse L, Gagnon DR, Gaziano JM, Wilson PW, Cho K. A phenotyping algorithm to identify acute ischemic stroke accurately from a national biobank: the Million Veteran Program. Clin Epidemiol. 2018 Oct 16;10:1509-1521. doi: 10.2147/CLEP.S160764. eCollection 2018.</citation>
    <PMID>30425582</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Hull LE, Chanfreau-Coffinier C, Tuteja S, Berlowitz D, Lehmann LS, Oslin DW, Pyne JM, DuVall SL, Lynch JA. Early adoption of pharmacogenetic testing for veterans prescribed psychotropic medications. Pharmacogenomics. 2019 Jul;20(11):781-789. doi: 10.2217/pgs-2019-0065. Epub 2019 Aug 8.</citation>
    <PMID>31393222</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Leroux AJ, Waid-Ebbs JK, Wen PS, Helmer DA, Graham DP, O'Connor MK, Ray K. An Investigation of Exposure Control Methods With Variable-Length CAT Using the Partial Credit Model. Appl Psychol Meas. 2019 Nov;43(8):624-638. doi: 10.1177/0146621618824856. Epub 2019 Jan 23.</citation>
    <PMID>31551640</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Roggenkamp HC, Abbass A, Town JM, Kisley S, Johansson R. Healthcare cost reduction and psychiatric symptom improvement in posttraumatic stress disorder patients treated with intensive short-term dynamic psychotherapy. European Journal of Trauma &amp; Dissociation. 2019 Sep 23; https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ejtd.2019.100122.</citation>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Vreeker A, Fears SC, Service SK, Pagani L, Takahashi JS, Araya C, Araya X, Bejarano J, Lopez MC, Montoya G, Montoya CP, Teshiba TM, Escobar J, Cantor RM, López-Jaramillo C, Macaya G, Molina J, Reus VI, Sabatti C, Ophoff RA, Freimer NB, Bearden CE. Genetic analysis of activity, brain and behavioral associations in extended families with heavy genetic loading for bipolar disorder. Psychol Med. 2019 Dec 9:1-9. doi: 10.1017/S0033291719003416. [Epub ahead of print]</citation>
    <PMID>31813409</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>de Zwarte SMC, Brouwer RM, Agartz I, Alda M, Aleman A, Alpert KI, Bearden CE, Bertolino A, Bois C, Bonvino A, Bramon E, Buimer EEL, Cahn W, Cannon DM, Cannon TD, Caseras X, Castro-Fornieles J, Chen Q, Chung Y, De la Serna E, Di Giorgio A, Doucet GE, Eker MC, Erk S, Fears SC, Foley SF, Frangou S, Frankland A, Fullerton JM, Glahn DC, Goghari VM, Goldman AL, Gonul AS, Gruber O, de Haan L, Hajek T, Hawkins EL, Heinz A, Hillegers MHJ, Hulshoff Pol HE, Hultman CM, Ingvar M, Johansson V, Jönsson EG, Kane F, Kempton MJ, Koenis MMG, Kopecek M, Krabbendam L, Krämer B, Lawrie SM, Lenroot RK, Marcelis M, Marsman JC, Mattay VS, McDonald C, Meyer-Lindenberg A, Michielse S, Mitchell PB, Moreno D, Murray RM, Mwangi B, Najt P, Neilson E, Newport J, van Os J, Overs B, Ozerdem A, Picchioni MM, Richter A, Roberts G, Aydogan AS, Schofield PR, Simsek F, Soares JC, Sugranyes G, Toulopoulou T, Tronchin G, Walter H, Wang L, Weinberger DR, Whalley HC, Yalin N, Andreassen OA, Ching CRK, van Erp TGM, Turner JA, Jahanshad N, Thompson PM, Kahn RS, van Haren NEM. The Association Between Familial Risk and Brain Abnormalities Is Disease Specific: An ENIGMA-Relatives Study of Schizophrenia and Bipolar Disorder. Biol Psychiatry. 2019 Oct 1;86(7):545-556. doi: 10.1016/j.biopsych.2019.03.985. Epub 2019 Jun 13.</citation>
    <PMID>31443932</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>van der Markt A, Klumpers UM, Draisma S, Dols A, Nolen WA, Post RM, Altshuler LL, Frye MA, Grunze H, Keck PE Jr, McElroy SL, Suppes T, Beekman AT, Kupka RW. Testing a clinical staging model for bipolar disorder using longitudinal life chart data. Bipolar Disord. 2019 May;21(3):228-234. doi: 10.1111/bdi.12727. Epub 2018 Dec 12.</citation>
    <PMID>30447123</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Hidalgo-Mazzei D, Berk M, Cipriani A, Cleare AJ, Florio AD, Dietch D, Geddes JR, Goodwin GM, Grunze H, Hayes JF, Jones I, Kasper S, Macritchie K, McAllister-Williams RH, Morriss R, Nayrouz S, Pappa S, Soares JC, Smith DJ, Suppes T, Talbot P, Vieta E, Watson S, Yatham LN, Young AH, Stokes PRA. Treatment-resistant and multi-therapy-resistant criteria for bipolar depression: consensus definition. Br J Psychiatry. 2019 Jan;214(1):27-35. doi: 10.1192/bjp.2018.257. Epub 2018 Dec 6. Erratum in: Br J Psychiatry. 2019 May;214(5):309.</citation>
    <PMID>30520709</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Kramer NE, Cosgrove VE, Dunlap K, Subramaniapillai M, McIntyre RS, Suppes T. A clinical model for identifying an inflammatory phenotype in mood disorders. J Psychiatr Res. 2019 Jun;113:148-158. doi: 10.1016/j.jpsychires.2019.02.005. Epub 2019 Feb 10. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>30954775</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Gonzalez R, Gonzalez SD, Mallawaarachchic I, Suppes P. The relationship between circadian gene single nucleotide polymorphisms and clinical and behavioral assessments of sleep and rhythms and course of illness characteristics in subjects with bipolar type I disorder. Personalized medicine. 2019 Feb 12; 2019(13-14):11-18.</citation>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>McIntyre RS, Subramaniapillai M, Lee Y, Pan Z, Carmona NE, Shekotikhina M, Rosenblat JD, Brietzke E, Soczynska JK, Cosgrove VE, Miller S, Fischer EG, Kramer NE, Dunlap K, Suppes T, Mansur RB. Efficacy of Adjunctive Infliximab vs Placebo in the Treatment of Adults With Bipolar I/II Depression: A Randomized Clinical Trial. JAMA Psychiatry. 2019 May 8. doi: 10.1001/jamapsychiatry.2019.0779. [Epub ahead of print]</citation>
    <PMID>31066887</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>April 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 26, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 26, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 31, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 22, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 22, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 24, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Treatment</keyword>
  <keyword>Pharmacogenetics</keyword>
  <keyword>Depression</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Depression</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Access to a final data set will be by request only. The investigators will set up a formal approval process which will include a request form. The investigators will require requests to include hypotheses and specify data variables requested. Requests will be reviewed by the Executive Committee for approval. If approved, the requestor will be given a user agreement specifying how the data may be used. Once the agreement is signed and returned, the investigators will provide the requester with an anonymized data set via secure transit method. The investigators will also publish a data dictionary and a primer of our research methods.</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Informed Consent Form (ICF)</ipd_info_type>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

