<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01011712</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>100014</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>10-I-0014</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01011712</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Natural History of Severe Viral Infections and Characterization of Immune Defects in Patients Without Known Immunocompromise</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Natural History of Severe Viral Infections and Characterization of Immune Defects</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

        -  Infections caused by viruses are common causes of illnesses: the common cold, many ear
           infections, sore throats, chicken pox, and the flu are caused by different viruses.
           Usually, these illnesses last only few days or, at most, a few weeks. Some virus
           infections like influenza are cleared from the body, and others such as the chicken pox
           virus remain in the body in an inactive state. However, some people may become quite ill
           when they are infected with a particular virus, possibly because part of their immune
           system does not respond properly to fight the virus.

        -  Researchers have discovered some reasons why a person may not be able to clear an
           infection caused by a virus. Some persons have changes in the genes that involve the
           immune system that result in the inability to properly control infection with a
           particular virus. Identifying changes in genes that involve the immune system should
           help scientists better understand how the immune system works to protect people from
           infection and may help develop new therapies.

      Objectives:

        -  To study possible immune defects that may be linked to a particular severe viral
           infection.

        -  To determine if identified immune defects are genetic in origin.

      Eligibility:

        -  Individuals of any age who have or have had a diagnosis of a virus infection that
           physicians consider to be unusually severe, prolonged, or difficult to treat.

        -  Relatives of the participants with a severe viral infection may also participate in the
           study. We will use their blood and/or skin specimens to try to determine if identified
           immune defects are hereditary.

      Design:

        -  Prior to the study, the participant's doctor will give researchers the details of the
           infection, along with medical records for review. Eligible participants will be invited
           to the NIH Clinical Center for a full evaluation as an outpatient or inpatient.

        -  At the Clinical Center, participants will be treated with the best available therapy for
           the particular viral infection, and researchers will monitor how the infection responds
           to the treatment.

        -  Researchers will take intermittent blood samples and conduct other tests (such as skin
           biopsies) to evaluate the immune system. - During and after the illness, researchers
           will conduct follow-up visits to determine the course of infection and response to
           therapy.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Viral infections in the normal host are usually self-limited as the innate and acquired
      immune systems mount successful antiviral responses. However, in some instances, apparently
      immunocompetent persons manifest infections with viruses that would otherwise be observed
      only in severely immunocompromised hosts. For example, cases of herpes simplex virus (HSV)
      encephalitis, esophagitis orgastritis, cytomegalovirus (CMV) colitis, adenovirus hepatitis or
      pneumonitis, recurrent or persistent skin infections caused by HSV or varicella zoster virus
      (VZV), severe warts caused by human papillomavirus (HPV), recurrent respiratory
      papillomatosis caused by HPV, severe influenza or respiratory syncytial virus pneumonia, and
      progressive multifocal leukoencephalopathy (PML) due to JC polyomavirus have been described
      in apparently immunocompetent patients. While a variety of case reports have described severe
      viral infections in immunocompetent hosts, the pathogenesis of the vast majority of these
      cases is not understood, and therapy can be unsuccessful.

      In this protocol, we will evaluate patients without known immunocompromise, who have severe,
      persistent, or treatment-refractory viral infections caused by herpesviruses, adenoviruses,
      polyoma viruses, papillomaviruses, or other viral infections. We will investigate whether
      certain host or virologic factors predispose these individuals to severe disease. We will
      also determine the usefulness of various microbiologic tests (e.g., cultures, serology,
      molecular assays) for following the course of infection in these patients. The physicians in
      the Clinical Center will provide optimal therapy for these patients, as part of standard of
      care. Identification of virologic or host factors that predispose these patients to severe
      viral infections may have important implications for elucidating the pathogenesis of
      infection and for the development of novel therapies.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 5, 2010</start_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Other</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To find immune and/or genetic defects that predispose individuals to severe or unusual viral infections.</measure>
    <time_frame>10 years</time_frame>
    <description>Patients under immune and genetic testing.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">325</enrollment>
  <condition>EBV</condition>
  <condition>HSV</condition>
  <condition>VZV</condition>
  <condition>HPV</condition>
  <condition>CMV</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        The study population will be drawn from referrals from the Clinical Center staff,
        physicians at outside medical facilities, and self-referrals. Patients or relatives who
        meet the inclusion and/or exclusion criteria, but who are not able to travel to the NIH
        Clinical Center, may be enrolled in the study and will be evaluated for immune defects
        using mailed-in blood samples or clinical specimens (i.e. previously obtained biopsy
        specimens).
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

        (Participants)

        Participants must meet all the following inclusion criteria in order to participate in this
        study:

          1. Children or adults (regardless of age) without a known or fully defined
             immunodeficiency and with a definitively diagnosed severe viral infection, including
             infection caused by herpesviruses (HSV-1, HSV-2, CMV, EBV, VZV, HHV-6, HHV-7, HHV-8),
             human papillomavirus (e.g., severe recalcitrant warts), adenovirus, polyomavirus (such
             as JC virus and BK virus), or influenza virus. Viral infections that would be
             considered &quot;opportunistic-like&quot;, such as herpesvirus esophagitis, herpesvirus
             encephalitis, CMV colitis, or progressive multifocal leukoencephalopathy (caused by
             the JC polyoma virus), will be of particular interest in this protocol.

             OR

             Children or adults with a well-documented prior, severe, persistent, or treatment
             refractory viral infection(s), who have clinically recovered from the viral infection.
             If such a patient is not able to visit the NIH for evaluation, his or her personal
             physician may mail-in blood or other clinical specimens to the NIH for analysis of
             possible immune defects and for analysis of the virus for mutations, if indicated.

          2. Ongoing care by a referring physician.

          3. Willingness to allow storage of blood and tissue samples for future analyses.

        (Relatives)

        Relatives (2 years or above) may be recruited to establish the genetic origin of immune
        defects that may be identified in the study subjects. We may obtain blood, buccal swabs or
        a skin biopsy from the relatives.

          1. Males and females will be accepted.

          2. Adult relatives or the guardians of minor relatives must be willing and capable of
             providing informed consent after review of protocol procedures that are described in
             the consent form with an appropriate study team member.

          3. Participating relatives agree to have blood stored for future studies of the immune
             system.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

        Participants meeting any of the following exclusion criteria at baseline will be excluded
        from study participation:

          1. Patients with previously diagnosed conditions associated with immunodeficiency (e.g.,
             a history of HIV infection or a positive test for HIV) or patients with conditions
             requiring either daily systemic corticosteroids exceeding a dose equivalent to10
             mg/day of prednisone or other significant immunosuppressant therapy (e.g., organ or
             stem cell transplant recipients).

             Note: Patients will be included if treatment with steroids or other immunosuppressive
             medication was begun to reduce disease associated with the infection and instituted
             AFTER the viral disease began.

          2. Women who are pregnant.

          3. Any condition or major comorbidity that the study investigators believe will
             compromise the patient's ability to comply with the requirements of the study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Lesia K Dropulic, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Krista S Gangler, R.N.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 761-6437</phone>
    <email>krista.gangler@nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Lesia K Dropulic, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 496-7675</phone>
    <email>dropulicl@mail.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>For more information at the NIH Clinical Center contact Office of Patient Recruitment (OPR)</last_name>
      <phone>800-411-1222</phone>
      <phone_ext>TTY8664111010</phone_ext>
      <email>prpl@cc.nih.gov</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?A_2010-I-0014.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dropulic LK, Ali MA, Ombrello AK, Cohen JI. Periodic Illness Associated With Epstein-Barr Virus: A New Diagnosis After a 22-Year Follow-up. Clin Infect Dis. 2016 Jun 15;62(12):1613-4. doi: 10.1093/cid/ciw197. Epub 2016 Mar 29.</citation>
    <PMID>27025823</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mace EM, Hsu AP, Monaco-Shawver L, Makedonas G, Rosen JB, Dropulic L, Cohen JI, Frenkel EP, Bagwell JC, Sullivan JL, Biron CA, Spalding C, Zerbe CS, Uzel G, Holland SM, Orange JS. Mutations in GATA2 cause human NK cell deficiency with specific loss of the CD56(bright) subset. Blood. 2013 Apr 4;121(14):2669-77. doi: 10.1182/blood-2012-09-453969. Epub 2013 Jan 30.</citation>
    <PMID>23365458</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dropulic LK, Cohen JI. Severe viral infections and primary immunodeficiencies. Clin Infect Dis. 2011 Nov;53(9):897-909. doi: 10.1093/cid/cir610. Epub 2011 Sep 29. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21960712</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 25, 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 10, 2009</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 10, 2009</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 11, 2009</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 11, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 11, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 14, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Genetics</keyword>
  <keyword>Virus</keyword>
  <keyword>Defense</keyword>
  <keyword>Immunity</keyword>
  <keyword>Immunodeficiency</keyword>
  <keyword>Respiratory Viruses</keyword>
  <keyword>Herpesvirus</keyword>
  <keyword>Cytomegalovirus</keyword>
  <keyword>Human Papillomavirus</keyword>
  <keyword>Adenovirus</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Virus Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

