<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04124783</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>E-19-779</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04124783</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study to Evaluate the Effects of the Cooling Bolero in Women With Menopause Symptoms</brief_title>
  <official_title>Pilot Study to Evaluate the Effects of the Nanoheath, Inc. Cooling Bolero in Women With Common Menopause Symptoms</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Englewood Hospital and Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Nanohealth, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Englewood Hospital and Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The Cooling Bolero is a vest filled with a new material (not ice or a gel) that provides
      controlled cooling by absorbed heat. The vest is manufactured by Nanohealth. It intended to
      provide moderate cooling (~15C/59F) through indirect contact with the skin. The material in
      the device is safe, non-toxic, and eco-friendly.

      Recent anecdotal studies of women with common peri-menopausal and menopausal symptoms (hot
      flashes, night sweats, flushing/sweating of face and neck, and intermittent sleep
      disturbances) have shown a reduction in both the frequency and intensity of those symptoms
      after using the Cooling Bolero. Specific (moderate) temperature cooling of the neck and upper
      torso appears to target and mitigate these common menopausal symptoms. This pilot study
      attempts to collect additional data on the effects of the Cooling Bolero.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Participants who have consented for this study will first be asked to complete a Baseline
      Assessment of their menopausal symptoms, including documentation of their baseline weight. If
      the assessment indicates that the participant has at least 'moderate' menopausal symptoms,
      then she will then enter the Run-In Period.

      During the two-week Run-In Period, participants will use a Symptom Diary for to document the
      frequency and severity of their menopausal symptoms. At the start of Week 3, participants
      will return their completed Run-In Period Symptom Diary and receive their Cooling Bolero with
      instructions on how to use the product during the Treatment Period.

      During the Treatment Period, participants should use the Cooling Bolero at least two times
      per day (morning and evening) for one hour. As feasible, the participant should start to wear
      the product 30 minutes prior to meal time for these two applications. The participant may
      also wear the product at additional times, as desired. All applications of the Cooling Bolero
      during the four-week Treatment Period are to be documented in the Product/Symptom Diary.
      During the Treatment Period, the participant will also continue to document the frequency and
      severity of their menopausal symptoms in the Product/Symptom Diary.

      At the end of Week 6, the participant will stop using the Cooling Bolero. She will be asked
      to complete a Product Assessment and have her weight documented.

      Participants will be contacted at Week 10 to ask about the status of menopausal symptoms
      after four weeks of not using the Cooling Bolero
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 23, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with a reduction in the frequency and/or intensity of menopause symptoms</measure>
    <time_frame>one month</time_frame>
    <description>Diaries will be used to capture data pre-intervention, during the intervention, and post-intervention</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Menopause Symptoms</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cooling Bolero</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cooling Bolero</intervention_name>
    <description>A vest filled with a new material (not ice or a gel) that provides controlled cooling by absorbing heat</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cooling Bolero</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Female who is at least 18 years old

          -  Self-reports having at least two (2) daily hot flashes associated with menopause

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Taking hormonal therapy (currently or within the last 3 months).

          -  Has another existing medical condition that would prevent study compliance.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>David Abramson, MD</last_name>
    <phone>(201) 568-6977</phone>
    <email>david.abramson@ehmchealth.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Jamie Ketas</last_name>
    <phone>201-894-3418</phone>
    <email>jamie.ketas@ehmchealth.org</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Englewood Health</name>
      <address>
        <city>Englewood</city>
        <state>New Jersey</state>
        <zip>07631</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jamie Ketas</last_name>
      <phone>201-894-3418</phone>
      <email>Jamie.Ketas@EHMCHealth.org</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 10, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 10, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 11, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 5, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 5, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 7, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

