<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04122014</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>H20190326180948</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04122014</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Exercise Program to Improve Balance in Hemophilic Patients</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effectiveness of an Exercise Program to Improve Balance and Dual Task in Hemophilic Patients. Clinical Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Valencia</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Valencia</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study evaluates the effectiveness of a program of physiotherapy exercises to train the
      balance and dual task in adults patients with hemophilia
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The objective of the study is to create an exercise program to improve the static and dynamic
      balance in hemophilic patient. In addition, the effect of the exercise program on dual task,
      functionality, proprioception, QoL, risk of falls and the kinesiophobia will be analyzed.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 10, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of postural balance: amplitude of Center of Pressure (CoP) displacements</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Amplitude of CoP displacements will be assessed in millimeters using a computerized balance system. Higher displacements indicate worse balance.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of postural balance: velocity of Center of Pressure (CoP) displacements</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Velocity of CoP displacements will be assessed in millimeters using a computerized balance system. Higher velocity indicate worse balance.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of postural balance: sway area of Center of Pressure (CoP) displacements</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Sway area of CoP displacements will be assessed in mm^2 using a computerized balance system. Higher sway area indicate worse balance.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of dual task balance: amplitude of Center of Pressure (CoP) displacements</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Amplitude of CoP displacements will be assessed in millimeters using a computerized balance system. Patient will perform a cognitive task (e.g. counting) while maintaining balance. Higher displacements indicate worse balance.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of dual task balance: velocity of Center of Pressure (CoP) displacements</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Velocity of CoP displacements will be assessed in millimeters using a computerized balance system. Patient will perform a cognitive task (e.g. counting) while maintaining balance. Higher velocity indicate worse balance.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of dual task balance: sway area of Center of Pressure (CoP) displacements</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Sway area of CoP displacements will be assessed in mm^2 using a computerized balance system. Patient will perform a cognitive task (e.g. counting) while maintaining balance. Higher sway area indicate worse balance.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Limits of Stability (LOS): success rate</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluations will be done by NedSVE/IBV balance platform. Indices: Max Excursions (%), Directional Control (%), Success (%), LOS rate (%) will be recorded during forward, backward, right and left side movements.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Limits of Stability (LOS): time</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluations will be done by NedSVE/IBV balance platform. Indices: Reaction Time (s), Confinement Time (s), will be recorded during forward, backward, right and left side movements.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The Berg Balance Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Balance will be assessed with the Berg Balance Scale (BBS), a 14-item physical performance measure of static and dynamic balance found to be reliable. Scoring ranges from 0-56, with higher scores indicating better balance. A score of &lt;46 identifies an individual at risk for falls after stroke.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Functional capacity: The Timed &quot;Up &amp; Go&quot; test</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Timed &quot;Up &amp; Go&quot; will be used to measure functional capacity. It is a simple test used to assess a person's mobility and requires both static and dynamic balance. Less time to complete the test in seconds implies better outcome.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Functional capacity: Sit-to-stand test</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Sit-to-stand test (3 repetitions) will be used to measure functional capacity. Less time to complete the test in seconds implies better outcome.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Functional capacity: 2-minutes walk test</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluation of functional capacity during walking by using 2 minutes walk test. More distance covered in 2 minutes implies better outcome.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Haemophilia Activities List (HAL)</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>The Haemophilia Activities List questionnaire measures the impact of hemophilia on self-perceived functional abilities in adults.
It contains 42 multiple choice questions in seven domains:
Lying/sitting/kneeling/standing (8 items) Functions of the legs (9 items) Functions of the arms (4 items) Use of transportation (3 items) Self-care (5 items) Household tasks (6 items) Leisure activities and sports (7 items) The most important outcomes are the overall sum score and three component scores relating to upper extremity activities, basic lower extremity activities, and complex lower extremity activities. The score is obtained using a Likert scale with 5 options: always=2, mostly=3, sometimes=4, rarely=5 and never=6 (complemented by the option &quot;impossible=1&quot; for those people who can not perform such activity). Subscales are summed, with a total score from 0- 252 and higher values represent a worse outcome (greater self-perceived difficulty in carrying out the activities).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Functional Independence Scale for Hemophilia (FISH)</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Observed activity limitations will be measured with the Functional Independence Scale for Hemophilia (FISH) as part of the Activity Domain.
The scale studies 8 activities (eating and grooming, bathing, dressing, chair, squatting, walking, stairs and running), which are classified into the three groups (Self care, Transfers and Locomotion) and their score ranges from 1 - 4 (1 being the highest dependency and 4 being the greatest independence to perform the exercises). Subscales are summed, with a total score from 8-32 and higher values represent a better outcome.
The FISH has been validated for use in developing countries. It consists of observed activities of daily living that are scored for quality.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of Life related with health: questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Measured by a Specific questionnaire for Quality of Life related with health evaluation for adults with haemophilia (A36Haemophilia-QoL), which explores 9 areas. Subscales and score range: Physical health: 0-32; Daily activities: 0-16; Joints: 0-12; Pain: 0-8; Treatment satisfaction: 0-8; Difficulties treatment: 0-16; Emotional functioning: 0-20; Mental health: 0-12; Social activity: 0-20. Subscales are summed, with a total score from 0-144 and higher values represent a better outcome (more Quality of Life perceived).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Kinesiophobia</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Kinesiophobia will be evaluated by Tampa Scale for Kinesiophobia (TSK-11SV) (Spanish adaptation. Gómez-Pérez, López-Martínez y Ruiz P., 2011). Scoring: Items are summed, with a total score from 11-44 and higher values represent a worse outcome (more pain interference in behavior).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Modified Falls Efficacy Scale (mFES)</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>MFES is a 14-item questionnaire related to daily indoor and outdoor physical activities. It is a 10-point visual analog scale of confidence level in completing a particular activity (item) without falling, rated from 0 to 10, where 0 denotes not confident or sure at all, and 10 denotes completely confident or sure. The total score for the 14 items ranges from 0 to 140.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Joint health status</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Joint clinical evaluation of elbows, knees and ankles by using The Hemophilia Joint Health Score 2.1 (HJHS). The full score range goes from 0 to 124 points (0-20 points for each of the six joints evaluated, plus 4 points for the overall assessment of gait. 0 means no joint damage, whereas the higher the value, the higher the degree of arthropathy.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">25</enrollment>
  <condition>Haemophilia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Usual daily activities</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Training group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Each subject will participate in 2 sessions each week during 3 months.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Progressive balance training</intervention_name>
    <description>Progressive balance training program</description>
    <arm_group_label>Training group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Normal daily activities</intervention_name>
    <description>Usual daily activities</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Diagnosis of haemophilia A or B

          -  Willingness to exercise twice a week during the training program and to complete the
             pre- and post-program evaluations

          -  Approval by their hematologist to participate in the exercise program

          -  With hemostatic coverage supervised by your hematologist.

          -  Age between 18 and 60 years

          -  Informed consent signed.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Non adherence to instruction on proper exercise technique

          -  Surgical procedures performed 6 months prior to or during the exercise program

          -  A major bleeding episode that posed a risk or prevented exercise

          -  Need for major surgery

          -  Suffer from dizziness

          -  Withdrawal of informed consent

          -  Acquired hemophilia
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>60 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Felipe Querol-Fuentes, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Valencia</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Valencia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Valencia</city>
        <zip>46010</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Spain</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 24, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 8, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 10, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 10, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 10, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 13, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Valencia</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Felipe Querol Fuentes</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

