<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04121741</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>35864</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04121741</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Impact of Singing Intervention</brief_title>
  <official_title>Evaluating the Impact of Singing Interventions on Markers of Cardiovascular Health in Older Patients With Cardiovascular Disease</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Medical College of Wisconsin</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Medical College of Wisconsin</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Cardiovascular disease (CVD) claims more lives each year than cancer and chronic respiratory
      disease combined. Participation in cardiac rehabilitation (CR) reduces mortality and risk of
      a major cardiovascular event in secondary prevention populations, including older adults.
      Older adults are less likely to participate in CR, as comorbidities in this population,
      including arthritis and chronic obstructive pulmonary disease, make participation difficult.
      Singing is a physical activity that involves components of the vagal nerves manifested as
      changes in cardiac autonomic regulation. Unlike physical exercise, the effects of singing on
      cardiovascular health has not been well-studied. The hypothesis for this project is that
      older patients with CVD will have favorable improvement in cardiovascular biomarkers,
      including, endothelial function and heart rate variability (HRV), after 30 minutes of
      singing.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This proposal seeks to create, optimize and test two different singing interventions in older
      patients with CVD. The study will consist of three arms, according to a randomized,
      single-blind, crossover, sham procedure-controlled design. Sixty-five total participants will
      each have three visits on three different occasions for the following interventions:

        1. a 30-minute period of guided singing from an in-person music therapist

        2. a 30-minute period of singing along to an instructional video including a professor of
           voice and &quot;inexperienced, older singing student&quot;

        3. a 30-minute sham intervention (subjects will undergo a hearing test)

      The goal will be to determine which singing intervention, if any, is superior to the other -
      as this would be important to guide longer and larger clinical trials in the field. Knowledge
      gained from this proposal will improve understanding of biologic mechanisms of singing
      behaviors, as it relates to CVD.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 17, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 30, 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 30, 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>change in vascular (endothelial) function</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline and after 30-minute singing and sham intervention(s)</time_frame>
    <description>Measure endothelial function and brachial artery flow-mediated dilation</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>change in vascular (endothelial) function</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline and after 30-minute singing and sham intervention(s)</time_frame>
    <description>Measure endothelial function (reactive hyperemia index, and PAT ratio) through finger plethysmography using EndoPAT</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>level of exertion achieved during singing</measure>
    <time_frame>after 30-minute singing (and sham) interventions</time_frame>
    <description>BORG Rating of Perceived Exertion</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>level of exertion achieved during singing</measure>
    <time_frame>after 30-minute singing (and sham) interventions</time_frame>
    <description>percent of maximum predicted heart rate achieved</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>cardiac hemodynamics</measure>
    <time_frame>at baseline and after 30-minute singing and sham intervention(s)</time_frame>
    <description>heart rate variability will be measured before, during and post singing</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>the change in TNF-alpha, IL-1 Beta, IL-6, and IL-8</measure>
    <time_frame>at baseline and 30 minutes later (after interventions or sham)</time_frame>
    <description>measure the change in TNF-alpha, IL-1 Beta, IL-6, and IL-8</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Visual Mood Score</measure>
    <time_frame>at baseline and 30 minutes later (after interventions or sham)</time_frame>
    <description>Arts Observation Scale to evaluate the effect of performing arts activities in healthcare settings. Two reactions (relaxation and distraction) will be scored by the research coordinator nurse based on direct observation of the subjects during the singing intervention. The qualitative portion of this instrument enables the collection of personal feedback and quotations from subjects. Observers (research team) can also gather more detailed accounts of subjects' responses to activities, including experience and perceptions</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">65</enrollment>
  <condition>Cardiovascular Diseases</condition>
  <condition>Cardiovascular Risk Factor</condition>
  <condition>Cardiovascular Health</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Singing intervention 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Instructional sing-a-long video. A video series will be created and recorded for the purposes of the study. Flow Mediated dilation (FMD) and EndoPAT will be measured before and after singing.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Singing intervention 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>In-person music therapy session. The music therapist will continue to coach throughout the 30-minute session. Flow Mediated dilation (FMD) and EndoPAT will be measured before and after singing.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control/sham intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Sham Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects will have a 30-minute period of rest sitting upright (as they would be positioned for the singing interventions). This arm is meant to isolate the specific effects of the treatment rather than the potential &quot;incidental&quot; effects related to the research setting and measurements. During this time, subjects will undergo hearing testing. Flow Mediated dilation (FMD) and EndoPAT will be measured before and after the 30 minute rest.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Singing with Music Therapist</intervention_name>
    <description>Music therapy sessions will begin with vocal and breathing warm-up exercises for about 10 minutes. The Music Therapist will play the songs (chosen from a list by the subject) to sing along to and will alter the characteristics of the music (volume, tempo, level of support) to ensure a successful experience for subjects and motivate them to put forth more effort into singing the song. The music therapist will continue to coach throughout the 30-minute session, reminding subjects of strategies practiced and how to implement those strategies while singing. Music therapy sessions will be led by Erica Flores, MT-BC, WMTR, Owner of Healing Harmonies Music Therapy, or a member of her team. Erica and her team of MTs were trained in Neurological Music Therapy.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Singing intervention 2</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Singing with Guided Video</intervention_name>
    <description>The videos will include a vocal warm-up (10 minutes long). The subject will then have the option to select and sing two songs (10 minutes each), with offerings in four music genres including Folk, Pop, Country, and a Hymn. Each piece will vary in tempo, melodic contour, and rhythm. The total duration of singing via this format will be 30 minutes.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Singing intervention 1</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Control Arm</intervention_name>
    <description>30 minute rest period, no singing will take place during this arm. During this rest period a member of the study team will assist the subject in a hearing test using headphones, a tablet, and a trumpet app. This is done to asses the current hearing level of the subject.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control/sham intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  English Speaking

          -  Have a history of coronary artery disease (defined as history of myocardial
             infarction, coronary stenosis &gt;50%, percutaneous coronary intervention with stent
             placement, balloon angioplasty, or coronary arterial bypass grafting)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects with a permanent pacemaker or implantable cardioverter defibrillator (ICD)
             implanted

          -  Patients with a history of atrial fibrillation, flutter or atrial tachycardia

          -  Parkinson's disease or a tremor

          -  Amputated upper extremity or presence of upper-arm (dialysis) fistula

          -  Fingernail onychomycosis (fungal infections resulting in thickening of the nails)

          -  Pregnancy

          -  Current illicit drug use (marijuana, tobacco, cocaine, amphetamines, etc.)

          -  Current excessive alcohol use (defined as more than 14 drinks/week for women, more
             than 28 drinks/week for men)

          -  Unstable coronary heart disease (active symptoms of chest discomfort)

          -  History of a Stroke or TIA or peripheral arterial disease

          -  Known history of cognitive impairment or inability to follow study procedures

          -  Cancer requiring systemic treatment within five years of enrollment.

          -  Subjects requiring supplemental oxygen use

          -  Non-English speaking subjects (video with lyrics are taped in English)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>55 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>79 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Amberly A Anger</last_name>
    <phone>414-805-3148</phone>
    <email>AANGER@MCW.EDU</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Jacquelyn P Kulinski</last_name>
    <phone>414-955-6896</phone>
    <email>jakulinski@mcw.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Medical College of Wisconsin</name>
      <address>
        <city>Milwaukee</city>
        <state>Wisconsin</state>
        <zip>53226</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Amberly A Anger, BS</last_name>
      <phone>414-805-3148</phone>
      <email>aanger@mcw.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Jacquelyn P Kulinski</last_name>
      <phone>414-955-6896</phone>
      <email>jakulinski@mcw.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 7, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 9, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 10, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 21, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 21, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 22, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Medical College of Wisconsin</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Jacquelyn Kulinski</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Singing</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cardiovascular Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

