<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04121962</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>1R34MH118178</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04121962</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Pilot Peer Mentor Intervention That Trains Black Men Who Have Sex With Men (BMSM) to Use and Promote Uptake of HIV/STI Self‐Testing to Peers and Sex Partners: STAR Study (Self‐Testing at Your Residence)</brief_title>
  <acronym>STAR</acronym>
  <official_title>Pilot Peer Mentor Intervention to Train Black MSM to Use and Promote Home-based HIV and STI Testing</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Johns Hopkins Bloomberg School of Public Health</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Johns Hopkins Bloomberg School of Public Health</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The objectives of the study are to assess the feasibility, reach and preliminary efficacy of
      a brief intervention that trains Black men who have sex with men [referred to as Index] (a)
      to use home-based testing for HIV and sexually transmitted infections and (b) promote
      home-based testing to their peers and sexual partners.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Sexually transmitted infections (STIs) increase one's risk of HIV infection, are serious
      co-infections that affect HIV clinical outcomes, and remain a risk for individuals using
      PrEP. Self-testing methods address barriers to clinic-based testing by offering convenience
      and privacy and have been shown to be well accepted by MSM. Therefore, use of self-testing is
      a potential approach through which to improve HIV and STI testing rates in MSM.
      Internet-based distribution (herein: web-based) of STI self-test kits enables an individual
      to request sampling kits via a website, mail biological specimens (e.g. urethral swabs) to a
      laboratory for testing, and view test results through a web-based account. Web-based self-HIV
      oral testing enables an individual to request a test kit, collect an oral specimen, and
      receive results within 20 minutes. Despite these potential benefits and reports of
      willingness to use free self-testing, uptake has been low due to barriers such as concerns
      about accuracy of the tests, apprehension to collect specimens, low risk perception, and the
      desire for counseling. In the proposed study, investigators will pilot test an intervention
      that address these barriers by training BMSM with information about the accuracy of the HIV
      rapid oral test kit, demonstrating how to properly collect specimens for HIV and STIs
      (gonorrhea, chlamydia and syphilis) self-testing, and providing resources for linkage to HIV
      and STI treatment and PrEP services. Study participants will utilize a secure website to
      request test kits.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 30, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 30, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 30, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants who completed at least 80% of the training sessions.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 month</time_frame>
    <description>Session attendance will be calculated as the ratio of number of sessions attended divided by the total number of sessions. We will consider greater than 80% attendance to indicate feasibility</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Risk characteristics of social network alters who request home-based testing kits.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 month</time_frame>
    <description>Assessment of sexual and drug/alcohol risk behaviors of social network alters who request the kits.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of individuals who request home-based testing kits.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 month</time_frame>
    <description>Compare the number of participants in each condition who request and return test kits</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Willingness and intention to initiate pre-exposure prophalaxis (PrEP)</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and 3 month</time_frame>
    <description>Assessment of changes to willingness and intention to initiate PrEP</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">140</enrollment>
  <condition>HIV/AIDS</condition>
  <condition>Sexually Transmitted Diseases</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Peer Mentor</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Peer Mentor Training is 5 groups with a 30 day reunion session. This condition is focused on training participants with communication skills to promote HIV and STI home-based testing and treatment and pre-exposure prophylaxis (PrEP) to individuals in their social networks. Participants will also learn how to use the Star website to request home-based testing kits. Peer Mentor training is conducted by a two health educators. The sessions are held once a week and will last approximately 90 minutes.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will receive information on how to use the website to request at-home test kits</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Peer Mentor</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will be trained to be Peer Mentors and promote home-based testing to their social network</description>
    <arm_group_label>Peer Mentor</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Website only</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will be given instructions on how to use the project website to request kits to test for HIV at home and collect specimens for lab testing.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  self-report male sex

          -  condomless anal sex with &gt;1 male in the prior 6 months

          -  self-report Black race

          -  aged 17 to 45

          -  internet use at least once a week.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  younger than 17 or older than 45 years
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <gender_based>Yes</gender_based>
    <gender_description>Biologic male who identifies as male</gender_description>
    <minimum_age>17 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>45 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Karin E Tobin, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>410-502-5368</phone>
    <email>ktobin2@jhu.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Melissa Davey-Rothwell, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>410-502-5368</phone>
    <email>mdavey@jhsph.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Lighthouse Studies @ Peer Point</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21205</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Karin E Tobin, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>410-502-5368</phone>
      <email>ktobin2@jhu.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Melissa Davey-Rothwell, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Charlotte Gaydos, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Joyce Jones, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Winiker AK, Tobin KE, Davey-Rothwell M, Latkin C. An examination of grit in black men who have sex with men and associations with health and social outcomes. J Community Psychol. 2019 Jun;47(5):1095-1104. doi: 10.1002/jcop.22176. Epub 2019 Mar 1.</citation>
    <PMID>30820988</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>October 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 4, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 8, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 10, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 8, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 8, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 10, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Black MSM</keyword>
  <keyword>Social network</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Sexually Transmitted Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Investigators will share data in a way that will protect participant confidentiality. Within 12 months of publication of the primary papers for this study, a dataset of aggregate values will be made available. Due to the highly sensitive nature of the data collected and the characteristics of this often stigmatized population, no client-level data will be shared until the entire cohort is accrued and completed, even that which is de-identified; this will reduce the risk of small numbers resulting in deductive identification.</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Statistical Analysis Plan (SAP)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Informed Consent Form (ICF)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>12 months after data collection is over</ipd_time_frame>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

