<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04129502</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>TAK-788-3001</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NL20191212</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>2019-001845-42</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>U1111-1232-6059</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04129502</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>TAK-788 as First-line Treatment Versus Platinum-Based Chemotherapy for Non-Small Cell Lung Cancer (NSCLC) With EGFR Exon 20 Insertion Mutations</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized Phase 3 Multicenter Open-label Study to Compare the Efficacy of TAK-788 as First-line Treatment Versus Platinum-Based Chemotherapy in Patients With Non-Small Cell Lung Cancer With EGFR Exon 20 Insertion Mutations</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Millennium Pharmaceuticals, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Takeda</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to compare the efficacy of TAK-788 as first-line treatment with
      that of platinum-based chemotherapy in participants with locally advanced or metastatic
      non-small cell lung cancer (NSCLC) whose tumors harbor epidermal growth factor receptor
      (EGFR) exon 20 insertion mutations.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The drug being tested in this study is called TAK-788. TAK-788 is being tested to evaluate
      the efficacy as a first line treatment compare with platinum-based chemotherapy in the
      participants with locally advanced or metastatic non-small cell lung cancer (NSCLC) whose
      tumors harbor EGFR exon 20 insertion mutations.

      The study will enroll approximately 318 patients. Participants will be randomly assigned to
      one of the two treatment groups—

        -  TAK-788 group (Arm A)

        -  Platinum-based chemotherapy group (Arm B)

      The participants will be administered with TAK-788 orally in arm A and Pemetrexed/Cisplatin
      or Pemetrexed/Carboplatin intravenously (IV) in arm B until the participants experience
      progressive disease (PD) as assessed by blinded independent review committee (IRC),
      intolerable toxicity or another discontinuation criteria. Participants in the chemotherapy
      group may cross over to treatment with TAK-788 after IRC-assessed PD is documented.
      Randomized treatment with TAK-788 or platinum-based chemotherapy may be continued after PD,
      at the discretion of the investigator and with the sponsor's approval, if there is still
      evidence of clinical benefit.

      This multi-center trial will be conducted in United States, Europe, and Asia. The overall
      time to participate in this study is until 3 years after the last participant is randomized.
      Participants will make multiple visits to the clinic and will be followed for survival,
      subsequent anticancer therapy, subsequent disease assessment outcome until disease
      progression on a subsequent anticancer therapy, and participant-reported health status
      (EQ-5D-5L) for 3 years after the last participant is randomized in the study and 30 days
      after the last dose of study drug for safety follow-up.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 6, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 30, 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression Free Survival (PFS) as Assessed by Blinded Independent Review Committee (IRC) per Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors (RECIST) Version 1.1</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to approximately 40 months after the first participant is randomized</time_frame>
    <description>PFS is defined as the time interval from the date of randomization until the first date at which the criteria for PD according to RECIST version 1.1 are met or death, whichever occurs first.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Confirmed Objective Response Rate (ORR) as Assessed by Blinded Independent Review Committee (IRC) per RECIST Version 1.1</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to approximately 40 months after the first participant is randomized</time_frame>
    <description>Confirmed ORR is defined as the proportion of participants who are confirmed to have achieved complete response (CR) or partial response (PR). Confirmed responses are responses that persist on repeat imaging ≥4 weeks after initial response.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall Survival (OS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to approximately 40 months after the first participant is randomized</time_frame>
    <description>OS is defined as the interval from the date of randomization until death.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression Free Survival (PFS) as Assessed by the Investigator</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to approximately 40 months after the first participant is randomized</time_frame>
    <description>PFS is defined as the time interval from the date of randomization until the first date at which the criteria for progressive disease (PD) according to RECIST version 1.1 are met or death, whichever occurs first.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Confirmed Objective Response Rate (ORR) as Assessed by the Investigator</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to approximately 40 months after the first participant is randomized</time_frame>
    <description>Confirmed ORR is defined as the proportion of participants who are confirmed to have achieved CR or PR. Confirmed responses are responses that persist on repeat imaging ≥4 weeks after initial response.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of Response, as Assessed by the Blinded Independent Review Committee (IRC) and the Investigator</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to approximately 40 months after the first participant is randomized</time_frame>
    <description>Duration of response is defined as the time interval from the time that the measurement criteria are first met for CR/PR (whichever is first recorded) until the first date that PD is objectively documented.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to Response, as Assessed by the Blinded Independent Review Committee (IRC) and the Investigator</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to approximately 40 months after the first participant is randomized</time_frame>
    <description>Time to response is defined as the time interval from the date of randomization until the initial observation of CR or PR.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Disease Control Rate (DCR) as Assessed by the Blinded Independent Review Committee (IRC) and the Investigator</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to approximately 40 months after the first participant is randomized</time_frame>
    <description>DCR is defined as the percentage of participants who have achieved CR, PR, or stable disease (SD) (in the case of SD, measurements must have met the SD criteria at least once after study entry at a minimum interval of 6 weeks) after the initiation of study drug.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient-reported Symptoms, Functioning, and Health-related Quality of Life (HRQoL) as Assessed by the European Organization for Research and Treatment of Cancer (EORTC) Quality of Life Questionnaire (QLQ)-C30</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to approximately 40 months after the first participant is randomized</time_frame>
    <description>EORTC QLQ-C30 is a cancer-specific questionnaire which comprises of 5 functional scales (physical, role, cognitive, emotional, and social functioning); 3 symptom scales (fatigue, pain, and nausea/vomiting); and a global health status/quality-of-life (QoL) scale. Six single-item scales are also included (dyspnea, insomnia, appetite loss, constipation, diarrhea, and financial difficulties). Raw scores will be converted into scale scores ranging from 0 to 100. For the functional scales and the global health status/QoL scale, higher scores represent better HRQoL, whereas for the symptom scales lower scores represent better HRQoL (i.e., a low level of symptomatology/problems).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Participant-reported Symptoms as Assessed by the European Organization for Research and Treatment of Cancer (EORTC) Quality of Life Questionnaire, Lung Cancer Module (QLQ-LC13)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to approximately 40 months after the first participant is randomized</time_frame>
    <description>EORTC QLQ-LC13 is a cancer-specific questionnaire which comprises of 13 questions assessing lung cancer-associated symptoms (cough, hemoptysis, dyspnea, and site-specific pain), treatment-related side effects (sore mouth, dysphagia, peripheral neuropathy, and alopecia), and use of pain medication. Raw scores will be converted into scale scores ranging from 0 to 100. Higher scores represent a high level of symptomatology/problems.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">318</enrollment>
  <condition>Advanced/Metastatic Non-Small Cell Lung Cancer (NSCLC)</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>TAK-788 Group (Arm A)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>TAK-788 160 mg, capsules, orally, once daily until the participants experience progressive disease (PD) as assessed by blinded independent review committee (IRC), intolerable toxicity, or another discontinuation criteria.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Platinum-based Chemotherapy Group (Arm B)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Pemetrexed 500 mg/m^2 plus Cisplatin 75 mg/m^2, infusion, intravenously, once on Day 1 of 21-day cycle pemetrexed 500 mg/m^2 plus Carboplatin, infusion, intravenously, once at a dose calculated to produce area under curve (AUC) of 5 mg*min/mL on Day 1 of 21-day cycle until the participants experience PD as assessed by blinded IRC, intolerable toxicity, or another discontinuation criteria. Pemetrexed/Cisplatin or pemetrexed/Carboplatin will be repeated every 3 weeks for 4 cycles, followed by maintenance treatment with pemetrexed 500 mg/m^2, on Day 1 of a 21-day cycle thereafter.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>TAK-788</intervention_name>
    <description>TAK-788 capsule</description>
    <arm_group_label>TAK-788 Group (Arm A)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>AP32788</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pemetrexed</intervention_name>
    <description>Pemetrexed IV infusion</description>
    <arm_group_label>Platinum-based Chemotherapy Group (Arm B)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Alimta</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cisplatin</intervention_name>
    <description>Cisplatin IV infusion</description>
    <arm_group_label>Platinum-based Chemotherapy Group (Arm B)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Carboplatin</intervention_name>
    <description>Carboplatin IV infusion</description>
    <arm_group_label>Platinum-based Chemotherapy Group (Arm B)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Histologically or cytologically confirmed nonsquamous cell locally advanced not
             suitable for definitive therapy, recurrent, or metastatic (Stage IV) non-small cell
             lung cancer (NSCLC)

          -  Documented epithelial growth factor receptor (EGFR) in-frame exon 20 insertion
             mutation assessed by a clinical laboratory improvements amendment (CLIA)-certified
             (United States [US] sites) or an accredited (outside of the US) local laboratory The
             EGFR exon 20 insertion mutation can be either alone or in combination with other EGFR
             or HER2 mutations except EGFR mutations for which there are approved anti-EGFR TKIs
             (ie, exon 19 del, L858R, T790M, L861Q, G719X, or S768I, where X is any other amino
             acid)

          -  Adequate tumor tissue available, either from primary or metastatic sites, for central
             laboratory confirmation of EGFR exon 20 insertion mutation

          -  At least 1 measurable lesion per response evaluation criteria in solid tumors (RECIST)
             version 1.1

          -  Life expectancy ≥3 months

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status of 0 to 1

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Received prior systemic treatment for locally advanced or metastatic disease

          -  Received radiotherapy ≤14 days before randomization or has not recovered from
             radiotherapy-related toxicities

          -  Received a moderate or strong cytochrome P-450 (CYP)3A inhibitor or moderate or strong
             CYP3A inducer within 10 days before randomization

          -  Have been diagnosed with another primary malignancy other than NSCLC

          -  Have current spinal cord compression or leptomeningeal disease

          -  Have uncontrolled hypertension. Participants with hypertension should be under
             treatment on study entry to control blood pressure

          -  Received a live vaccine within 4 weeks before randomization per Summary of product
             characteristics (SmPCs) for pemetrexed, cisplatin, and carboplatin
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Medical Director</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Millennium Pharmaceuticals, Inc.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Takeda Study Registration Call Center</last_name>
    <phone>1-866-835-2233</phone>
    <email>globaloncologymedinfo@takeda.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Pacific Shores Medical Group</name>
      <address>
        <city>Long Beach</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90813</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of California Irvine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Orange</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>92868</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Eastern CT Hematology and Oncology Associates</name>
      <address>
        <city>Norwich</city>
        <state>Connecticut</state>
        <zip>06360</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Massachusetts General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02114</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Beth Israel Deaconess Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02215</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Dana Farber Cancer Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02215</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sarah Cannon Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nashville</city>
        <state>Tennessee</state>
        <zip>37203</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Virginia Health System</name>
      <address>
        <city>Charlottesville</city>
        <state>Virginia</state>
        <zip>22908</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Krankenhaus Nord Klinik Floridsdorf</name>
      <address>
        <city>Wien</city>
        <zip>1210</zip>
        <country>Austria</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Grand Hopital de Charleroi asbl</name>
      <address>
        <city>Charleroi</city>
        <state>Hainaut</state>
        <zip>6000</zip>
        <country>Belgium</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>AZ Sint-Lucas</name>
      <address>
        <city>Gent</city>
        <zip>9000</zip>
        <country>Belgium</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Beijing Cancer Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Beijing</city>
        <state>Beijing</state>
        <zip>100142</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Guangdong Provincial People's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Guangzhou</city>
        <state>Guangzhou</state>
        <zip>510080</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sotiria Chest Hospital of Athens</name>
      <address>
        <city>Athens</city>
        <state>Attiki</state>
        <zip>11527</zip>
        <country>Greece</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Metaxa Cancer Hospital of Piraeus</name>
      <address>
        <city>Piraeus</city>
        <state>Attiki</state>
        <zip>18537</zip>
        <country>Greece</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Bioclinic Thessaloniki (Galinos clinic)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Thessaloniki</city>
        <zip>54622</zip>
        <country>Greece</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Chonnam National University Hwasun Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hwasun</city>
        <state>Jeollanam-do</state>
        <zip>58128</zip>
        <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Pusan National University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Busan</city>
        <zip>49241</zip>
        <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Chungbuk National University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cheongju-si</city>
        <zip>28644</zip>
        <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Goyang</city>
        <zip>10408</zip>
        <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Korea University Anam Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seoul</city>
        <zip>2841</zip>
        <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Seoul National University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seoul</city>
        <zip>3080</zip>
        <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Asan Medical Center - PPDS</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seoul</city>
        <zip>5505</zip>
        <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Samsung Medical Center PPDS</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seoul</city>
        <zip>6351</zip>
        <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Fundacao Champalimaud</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lisboa</city>
        <zip>1400-038</zip>
        <country>Portugal</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Centro Hospitalar de Lisboa Norte E.P.E Hospital Pulido Valente</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lisboa</city>
        <zip>1769-001</zip>
        <country>Portugal</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Cuf Porto</name>
      <address>
        <city>Porto</city>
        <zip>4100-180</zip>
        <country>Portugal</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>ICO lHospitalet Hospital Duran i Reynals</name>
      <address>
        <city>L'Hospitalet de Llobregat</city>
        <state>Barcelona</state>
        <zip>8908</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Universitario A Coruna</name>
      <address>
        <city>A Coruna</city>
        <zip>15006</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital General Universitario de Alicante</name>
      <address>
        <city>Alicante</city>
        <zip>3010</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Universitario Vall d'Hebron - PPDS</name>
      <address>
        <city>Barcelona</city>
        <zip>8035</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Clinic de Barcelona</name>
      <address>
        <city>Barcelona</city>
        <zip>8036</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>C.H. Regional Reina Sofia - PPDS</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cordoba</city>
        <zip>14004</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital General Universitario Gregorio Maranon</name>
      <address>
        <city>Madrid</city>
        <zip>28007</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Universitario Fundacion Jimenez Diaz</name>
      <address>
        <city>Madrid</city>
        <zip>28040</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Universitario 12 de Octubre</name>
      <address>
        <city>Madrid</city>
        <zip>28041</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Universitario La Paz - PPDS</name>
      <address>
        <city>Madrid</city>
        <zip>28046</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Universitario Puerta de Hierro - Majadahonda</name>
      <address>
        <city>Majadahonda</city>
        <zip>28222</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Regional Universitario de Malaga Hospital General</name>
      <address>
        <city>Malaga</city>
        <zip>29010</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Universitario Virgen del Rocio - PPDS</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sevilla</city>
        <zip>41013</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Universitari i Politecnic La Fe de Valencia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Valencia</city>
        <zip>46026</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Municipal Non-profit Enterprise SubCarpathian Clinical Oncological Centre of Ivano-Frankivsk RC</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ivano-Frankivsk</city>
        <zip>76018</zip>
        <country>Ukraine</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Communal Non-profit Enterprise Regional Center of Oncology</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kharkiv</city>
        <zip>61070</zip>
        <country>Ukraine</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Private Enterprise Private Manufacturing Company Acinus</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kropyvnytskyi</city>
        <zip>25006</zip>
        <country>Ukraine</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Austria</country>
    <country>Belgium</country>
    <country>China</country>
    <country>Greece</country>
    <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
    <country>Portugal</country>
    <country>Spain</country>
    <country>Ukraine</country>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 7, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 15, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 16, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 7, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 7, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 8, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Drug Therapy</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lung Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Non-Small-Cell Lung</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Carboplatin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pemetrexed</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Takeda makes patient-level, de-identified data sets and associated documents available for all interventional studies after applicable marketing approvals and commercial availability have been received (or program is completely terminated), an opportunity for the primary publication of the research and final report development has been allowed, and other criteria have been met as set forth in Takeda's Data Sharing Policy (see www.TakedaClinicalTrials.com for details). To obtain access, researchers must submit a legitimate academic research proposal for adjudication by an independent review panel, who will review the scientific merit of the research and the requestor's qualifications and conflict of interest that can result in potential bias. Once approved, qualified researchers who sign a data sharing agreement are provided access to these data in a secure research environment.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

