<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04127383</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>10-10400-98-001</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04127383</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effectiveness and Implementation of the Assessment of Burden of Chronic Conditions (ABCC)-Tool</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effectiveness, Cost-effectiveness and Implementation of the Assessment of Burden of Chronic Conditions (ABCC)-Tool in Patients With COPD, Asthma, Diabetes Mellitus Type 2 and Heart Failure: a Pragmatic Clustered Quasi-experimental Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Maastricht University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Netherlands Instititute for Health Services Research</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>TNO</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Twente</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Maastricht University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study is designed to evaluate the effectiveness and implementation of the Assessment of
      Burden of Chronic Conditions (ABCC)-tool for patients with COPD, asthma, diabetes mellitus
      type 2 or heart failure (and any combination of these conditions) in real-life routine
      practice. The ABCC-tool consists of a questionnaire, a visualisation using balloons that is
      based on cut-off points, and treatment advice. The ABCC-tool is intended to be used in daily
      healthcare practice, is designed to monitor a patient's integrated health status over time,
      to facilitate shared decision making, and to stimulate self-management. The study has a
      pragmatic clustered quasi-experimental design with two arms. The intervention group will use
      the ABCC-tool and the control group will receive usual care. The study will be implemented at
      a general practice-level, and has a follow-up period of 18 months. The primary outcome is
      change in perceived quality of care, as measured with the Patient Assessment of Chronic
      Illness Care (PACIC), as compared to usual care after 18 months. It is hypothesized that the
      change in perceived quality of care is significantly higher in the group using the ABCC-tool
      as compared to the group that receives usual care. Additionally the implementation of the
      ABCC-tool in general practices will be evaluated in 12 general practices. The implementation
      study will evaluate the context of caregivers with the Consolidated Framework for
      Implementation Research, the process of implementation with the RE-AIM framework, and
      fidelity to the intervention with the fidelity framework.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 1, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 1, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Pragmatic clustered quasi-experimental study</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>Blinding of healthcare providers and patients is not possible due to the nature of the intervention, but the study team will be blind to treatment arms in the data set during data cleaning, handling of missing data, statistical analyses and drawing of conclusions.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Perceived quality of care (PACIC): Patient Assessment of Chronic Illness Care</measure>
    <time_frame>18 months</time_frame>
    <description>Measured with the Patient Assessment of Chronic Illness Care, for total group. The scale has 20 items. Answers range from 1 to 5. Average scores (range 1-5) will be calculated. Higher scores mean more frequent presence of the aspect of structured chronic care.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Perceived quality of care (PACIC): Patient Assessment of Chronic Illness Care</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months, 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Measured with the Patient Assessment of Chronic Illness Care, for total group and for each condition separately. The scale has 20 items. Answers range from 1 to 5. Average scores (range 1-5) will be calculated. Higher scores mean more frequent presence of the aspect of structured chronic care.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Perceived quality of care (PACIC): Patient Assessment of Chronic Illness Care</measure>
    <time_frame>18 months</time_frame>
    <description>Measured with the Patient Assessment of Chronic Illness Care, for each condition separately. The scale has 20 items. Answers range from 1 to 5. Average scores (range 1-5) will be calculated. Higher scores mean more frequent presence of the aspect of structured chronic care.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of life (EQ-5D-5L)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months, 12 months, 18 months</time_frame>
    <description>Measured with the EuroQol-5D-5L, for total group and for each condition separately. The scale consists of the EQ-5D-5L descriptive system with 5 questions, and a VAS-scale. Answers range from 1 (best) to 5 (worst). EQ-5D-5L health states, defined by the EQ-5D-5L descriptive system, will be converted into a single index value (Dutch values). The EQ-5D-5L VAS will also be determined.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Capability well-being (ICECAP-A)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months, 12 months, 18 months</time_frame>
    <description>Measured with the ICEpop CAPability measure for Adults, for total group and for each condition separately. The questionnaire consists of 5 questions. Answers range from 4 (full capability for an attribute) to 1 (no capability). A tariff value for an overall state can be calculated by summing the values across the individual attributes. This code will allow calculation of ICECAP-A tariffs for each respondent in a study</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patients' activation (PAM)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months, 12 months, 18 months</time_frame>
    <description>Measured with the Patient Activation Measure, for total group and for each condition separately. The questionnaire consists of 13 questions on a 5-point scale. The scores range from 1 to 100. The higher the score, the more capable a person is in self-management.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Medical Consumption within Health Care</measure>
    <time_frame>3, 6, 9, 12, 15 and 18 months</time_frame>
    <description>Measured with the Medical Consumption Questionnaire (MCQ), for total group and for each condition separately. The questionnaire includes 16 questions related to frequently occurring contacts with health care providers. The items will be valued using standard cost prices in the Netherlands. The costs of medical consumption are calculated by multiplying the volumes of care by the cost per unit of care. This will be used for a cost-effectiveness analysis.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Productivity losses</measure>
    <time_frame>3, 6, 9, 12, 15 and 18 months</time_frame>
    <description>Measured with the Productivity Costs Questionnaire (MCQ), for total group and for each condition separately. The questionnaire includes 9 questions related to the impact of disease on the ability of a person to perform work. The items will be valued using standard cost prices in the Netherlands. Productivity lossess are calculated by multiplying the volumes by cost prices per unit. This will be used for a cost-effectiveness analysis.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">300</enrollment>
  <condition>Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease</condition>
  <condition>Asthma</condition>
  <condition>Diabetes Mellitus, Type 2</condition>
  <condition>Heart Failure</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>ABCC-tool</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The intervention group will use the ABCC-tool during consultation with their healthcare provider. Healthcare providers in the intervention group will receive a short instructional film about the ABCC-tool before the start of the study. Additionally, healthcare providers from 12 practices will be invited for interviews, evaluating the context and process of implementation.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Usual care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>The control group will receive usual care, and healthcare providers will not be instructed</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Assessment of Burden of Chronic Conditions (ABCC)-tool</intervention_name>
    <description>The tool consists of a questionnaire, a visualisation using balloons, and treatment advice. A patient will complete the questionnaire before consultation. The questionnaire measures the experienced burden of the chronic condition(s), and several risk factors. The questionnaire consists of a generic part and disease-specific parts. The generic questionnaire will be combined with any amount of disease-specific questionnaires (i.e. COPD, asthma, DM2 and heart failure), to form a single personalised scale and balloon chart for each individual patient. Outcomes of the questionnaire are visualised using balloons. The healthcare provider opens the visualisation during consultation. A balloon represents a domain, and the colour and height indicate a patient's score on that domain. If a patient and healthcare provider can select a balloon by clicking on it, treatment advice is shown by means of pop-ups. Based on the discussion following treatment advice, personal care plans can be determined.</description>
    <arm_group_label>ABCC-tool</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  diagnosis COPD, asthma, Diabetes Mellitus type 2 and/or heart failure

          -  can understand and read the Dutch language

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  COPD or asthma: used prednisone due to an exacerbation less than six weeks ago

          -  Heart failure or DM2: hospitalized less than six weeks ago

          -  Healthcare providers or patients who have already used the Assessment of Burden of
             COPD-tool are excluded from the control group

          -  Patients who have already used the Assessment of Burden of COPD-tool will be excluded
             from the intervention group
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Onno CP van Schayck, Prof.</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Maastricht University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Esther A Boudewijns</last_name>
    <phone>0433882336</phone>
    <email>esther.boudewijns@maastrichtuniversity.nl</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Danny Claessens</last_name>
    <phone>0433882836</phone>
    <email>danny.claessens@maastrichtuniversity.nl</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Maastricht University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Maastricht</city>
        <state>Limburg</state>
        <zip>6200MD</zip>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Esther A Boudewijns</last_name>
      <phone>0433882336</phone>
      <email>esther.boudewijns@maastrichtuniversity.nl</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Danny Claessens</last_name>
      <phone>0433882836</phone>
      <email>danny.claessens@maastrichtuniversity.nl</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Netherlands</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.ziektelastmeter.nl</url>
    <description>Related Info</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>February 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 10, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 14, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 15, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 19, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 19, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 20, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Maastricht University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Esther Boudewijns</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Asthma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lung Diseases, Obstructive</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pulmonary Disease, Chronic Obstructive</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Heart Failure</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus, Type 2</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

