<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04121182</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>RC31/17/0452</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04121182</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Prevention of pneumonIA in Nursing hOme</brief_title>
  <acronym>PIANO</acronym>
  <official_title>Prevention of pneumonIA in Nursing hOme</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University Hospital, Toulouse</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Ministry of Health, France</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University Hospital, Toulouse</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Infections in nursing home are associated with high morbidity and mortality. Pulmonary
      infections are known to be the most problematic. In our INCUR observational study of 773
      residents, 20.13% of residents had pneumonia during the year of follow-up. On average, the
      extra cost of pneumopathies was 4,467 euros / patient for the long-term care facility and
      3,044 euros for the hospital.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The pneumopathies in nursing home are the main cause of hospitalization of residents.
      Depending on the series, 9 to 50% of residents with pneumonia should be transferred. This
      reflects the difficulties faced by nursing home care teams in these situations. The
      respiratory symptomatology of nursing home residents is difficult to grasp and the prescribed
      antibiotic therapy is often considered inappropriate (25% to 75% of cases). Prevention of
      resident pneumonia, such as vaccination against pneumococcus remains poorly practiced,
      influenza vaccination teams or vitamin D supplementation.

      In addition to the risk of mortality, lung diseases are often the cause of a rapid functional
      decline. Preventing pneumonia in nursing homes is therefore an important issue in the
      prevention of dependence, the quality of life, the health care system (use of hospitalization
      and transfer to emergencies) and health expenditure. In this vulnerable population, a
      prevention intervention seems particularly relevant.

      In this research project, the investigators hypothesize that a multi-domain prevention
      intervention for pneumonia carried out by nursing teams in nursing homes can reduce the
      incidence of pneumonia. They also believe that this action would reduce emergency transfers
      and health expenditures.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">January 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Seven thousand residents will be recruited by 280 nursing home in 2 major regions in France (Occitanie and Auvergne-Rhônes-Alpes) and followed for 1 year.
At the end of the randomization, half of the institutions will benefit from an &quot;on-line&quot; training on the prevention and management of pulmonary disease in residents. Other institutions will continue their usual practice (routine care) and will not benefit from training during the study period.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The comparison of the incidence of lung disease number between the two groups</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>After the one-year : to compare of the incidence of lung disease between the two groups of Nursing home (the on-line formation/casual care) The diagnosis of pneumopathy will be defined on the criteria of the Infectious Risk Observatory in Geriatrics that are appropriate for nursing home residents, with at least two of the criteria defined for pneumonia</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Medical evidence of rattles or crepitates</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Medical evidence of rattles or crepitates on chest auscultation : rattles or crepitates are criteria for the diagnosis of pneumopathy</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Establish a differential cost-effectiveness ratio at 1 year of the care of the residents in nursing home</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Establish a differential cost-effectiveness ratio at 1 year of the care of the residents in nursing home by a healthcare team trained in the management of pneumonia in the context of E-learning training versus usual care.
The medico-economic analysis will consist in a cost-effectiveness evaluation of a training in the prevention of pneumopathies aimed at the carers in nursing homes, compared to the usual practice.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluation of the time spent by the health care team to support the patient between two groups</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Perform an evaluation of the time spent by the health care team to support the patient for Basic Activities of Daily Living (ADL), Instrumental Activities of Daily Living, supervision of care and patient monitoring. They will use the Questionnaire adapted from Resource Utilization in Dementia - Formal Care (RUD-FOCA)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluating the incidence of all-cause hospitalizations</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluating the incidence of number of all-cause hospitalizations to compare with the hospitalizations due to pneumonia</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluate the evolution of quality of care indicators in the nursing home</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Indicators of quality of care in the nursing home related to the risk of pneumonia will be reported at T-2 months and T12 months. These indicators will be provided by the coordinating physician :
Vaccination rate (Residents; Staff).
Presence in the nursing home of a protocol for taking care of the false route
In case of pneumopathy, the use of antibiotic therapy will be indicated</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Functional decline of residents</measure>
    <time_frame>1year</time_frame>
    <description>The degree of dependence of the residents will be evaluated by the carers of the nursing home by the Scale ADL (Basic Activity Daily Living) of Katz during 12 months On this scale of 0 (totally dependent) to 6 points (independent), a difference of 0.5 points would be considered clinically relevant.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">7000</enrollment>
  <condition>Pneumonia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Nursing home with On-line training</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>25 randomized residents will be included by nursing home Half of the institutions (randomized too) will benefit from an &quot;on-line&quot; training on the prevention and management of resident lung diseases</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Nursing home with usual practice</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>This group of Institutions continue their usual practice (routine care) and will not benefit from training during the study period.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>On-line training</intervention_name>
    <description>Nursing teams randomized in the intervention group will benefit from an intervention in the form of a specific training &quot;online&quot; on the prevention of pneumonia and their management in the nursing home This training focuses on prevention, and management during the infectious period (the false food route and the management of pneumonia).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Nursing home with On-line training</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Usual practice</intervention_name>
    <description>Nursing home with usual practice : The act of comparison is defined by the usual care, as they are performed in the nursing home at the time of the study. No restrictions are placed on residents or caregivers of any kind in the care of the resident.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Nursing home with usual practice</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Living in a nursing home for at least 30 days at the start of inclusions,

          -  Having received information concerning the study and having not expressed opposition
             to participate,

          -  For which an agreement in principle of the attending physician has been obtained.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Refusal of the resident (or of his legal representative) or of his treating physician
             after given information,

          -  Resident at the end of life (life expectancy evaluated within one month by the
             coordinating physician),

          -  Resident whose attending physician is already involved in the PIANO study under a
             resident of another nursing home.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>60 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Yves Rolland, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University Hospital, Toulouse</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Yves Rolland, MD</last_name>
    <phone>05 34 55 76 07</phone>
    <phone_ext>33</phone_ext>
    <email>rolland.y@chu-toulouse.fr</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Arnaud Lendrieux</last_name>
    <phone>05 61 77 83 50</phone>
    <email>lendrieux.a@chu-toulouse.fr</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Hospital Toulouse</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toulouse</city>
        <zip>31059</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Yves Rolland, MD</last_name>
      <phone>05 34 55 76 07</phone>
      <email>rolland.y@chu-toulouse.fr</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Arnaud Lendrieux</last_name>
      <phone>05 61 77 83 50</phone>
      <email>lendrieux.a@chu-toulouse.fr</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 19, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 8, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 9, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 7, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 7, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 9, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Nursing home</keyword>
  <keyword>Prevention</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pneumonia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

