<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04123951</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>0714</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04123951</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Home-based Exercise in Renal Transplant Recipients</brief_title>
  <acronym>ECSERT</acronym>
  <official_title>A Pilot Randomised Controlled Trial of the Effects of a Structured, Home-based Exercise Program on Cardiovascular StructurE and Function in Renal Transplant Recipients: The ECSERT Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Leicester</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Leicester</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Although patients who have received a kidney transplant have better health than patients on
      dialysis, heart problems are still the commonest cause of death for kidney transplant
      recipients. This is because diseases like high blood pressure and diabetes are more common in
      patients with kidney transplants as well as factors related to having kidney disease itself
      and the medications transplant recipients have to take to stop them rejecting their
      transplanted kidney. Exercise is known to help with heart disease in lots of conditions and
      improves many of the risk factors known to cause heart disease in kidney transplant
      recipients. This study will investigate whether an individualised, home-based, exercise
      program improves heart disease in kidney transplant recipients. The study is a randomised
      controlled trial, with half the patients completing the 12 week exercise programme and the
      other half continuing with their normal care. The investigators will use detailed MRI scans
      to assess patient's hearts and blood vessels at the start and end of the study. The
      investigators will also assess changes in physical function, exercise capacity, blood markers
      of heart disease, changes in body type and quality of life measures assessed with
      questionnaires.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Kidney transplantation confers a significant survival advantage over remaining on dialysis,
      but CVD remains the leading cause of death for RTRs and of graft loss. Acute myocardial
      infarction accounts for 15-20% of CVD-related deaths in RTRs, but sudden cardiac death, or
      death from fatal arrhythmia account for at least double this number, suggesting classical
      atheromatous coronary artery disease driven by traditional cardiometabolic risk factors, is
      not the dominant driving force of CVD in RTRs. Non-traditional cardiometabolic risk factors
      including endothelial dysfunction, systemic inflammation, acute rejection, anaemia and
      deranged bone-mineral metabolism are of at least equal importance in the pathogenesis of CVD
      in RTRs and drive pathological changes in cardiovascular structure and function that
      associate strongly with mortality. This is further illustrated by the fact that traditional
      CVD risk-stratification tools dramatically underestimate cardiovascular risk in patients with
      CKD, coronary revascularization does not improve outcomes for RTRs as it does in the general
      population and cardiac events are more likely to be fatal in RTRs than the general
      population. Immunosuppressive agents are well known to drive traditional CVD risk factors,
      but also drive non-traditional cardiometabolic risk factors. Cost-effective, deliverable
      interventions are needed to address the burden of CVD in RTRs by targeting traditional and
      non-traditional risk factors. Supervised exercise interventions in RTRs improve
      cardiorespiratory fitness and a variety of traditional and non-traditional risk factors for
      CVD, including metabolic profile, vascular stiffening, central adiposity and inflammatory
      cell and cytokine profiles, but are not realistically deliverable in the current financial
      climate. Home-based exercise training programs have been shown to be deliverable in patients
      on dialysis and patients undergoing cardiac rehabilitation, but the effectiveness and
      deliverability of home-based exercise interventions are largely untested in RTRs. It cannot
      be assumed such programs will be acceptable to RTRs, whose home-lives, social and
      occupational circumstances are significantly different to dialysis and cardiac patients. Many
      RTRs have had enforced sedentary lifestyles prior to transplantation as dialysis patients and
      their goals for rehabilitation as well as the disease processes at work are different to both
      dialysis and cardiac patients.

      There are limited data on whether exercise-induced improvements in cardiometabolic risk
      translate into improvements in cardiovascular structure and function in RTRs. CMR is able to
      measure multiple clinically pertinent aspects of CVD processes in RTRs that relate closely to
      outcome with great accuracy, including:

        -  left ventricular hypertrophy

        -  myocardial fibrosis

        -  aortic stiffness

        -  coronary artery function

        -  myocardial steatosis

        -  subclinical systolic and diastolic dysfunction

      This pilot randomised clinical trial will assess the deliverability of a combined aerobic and
      resistance, home-based, exercise intervention in RTRs. It will define recruitment and dropout
      rates from this newly designed, home-based, intervention and baseline values for CMR measures
      that assess prognostically important aspects of CVD in RTRs for the first time. Furthermore,
      it will test the effects of the intervention on traditional and novel CMR outcome measures
      that assess prognostically important aspects of CVD that relate directly to cardiovascular
      outcomes for the first time, providing estimates of effect-sizes on outcome measures. These
      data will be used to inform the design of a future, definitive study. This study will further
      the investigator's ability to make objective measures of cardiovascular health in RTRs, with
      the opportunity to compare CMR measures with traditional measures of cardiovascular fitness.
      The qualitative component of this study will refine the exercise intervention to maximize
      uptake in future studies and adoption into clinical practice.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 30, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 30, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 30, 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Left ventricular mass (g/m)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Measured using multi-parametric cardiac MRI (CMR)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in left/right ventricular volumes (ml)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Measured using multi-parametric cardiac MRI (CMR)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in ejection fractions (%)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Measured using multi-parametric cardiac MRI (CMR)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in native and post-contrast T1 mapping time (ms)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Measured using multi-parametric cardiac MRI (CMR)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Myocardial systolic-strain (%)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Measured using multi-parametric cardiac MRI (CMR)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in peak early-diastolic strain rate (%s-1)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Measured using multi-parametric cardiac MRI (CMR)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Aortic pulse wave velocity (m/s)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Measured using multi-parametric cardiac MRI (CMR)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in aortic distensibility (mmHg−1×10−3)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Measured using multi-parametric cardiac MRI (CMR)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Myocardial and hepatic triglyceride content (%)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Measured using multi-parametric cardiac MRI (CMR)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Recruitment Rate</measure>
    <time_frame>Post 12 week intervention</time_frame>
    <description>The feasibility of recruitment and interest of patients is an essential component of whether a full trial is feasible. The number of eligible patients and number of consented will be recorded. Monthly recruitment rate and the time taken to recruit 10 (25%), 20 (50%), 30 (75%), and 40 (100%) patients will be recorded.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants lost to follow up</measure>
    <time_frame>Post 12 week intervention</time_frame>
    <description>This is the number of participants leaving the trial due to being uncontactable</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of exercise sessions completed per week</measure>
    <time_frame>Post 12 week intervention</time_frame>
    <description>This will assess adherence to the intervention</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants dropping out of the trial</measure>
    <time_frame>Post 12 week intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Otherwise known as the attrition rate</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>Post 12 week intervention</time_frame>
    <description>This is a measure of the trial safety</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Aerobic Capacity (change)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 2 weeks, 4 weeks and 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Measured by cardiopulmonary exercise test which produces V02 (maximal oxygen uptake) in both l/min and ml/kg/min. This is a measure of a participants aerobic capacity.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Timed up and go test (TUAG)(change)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>To determine fall risk and measure the progress of balance, sit to stand and walking. Patient sits and then the time taken to stand up and walk 3 meters and return is measured. If a patient took 14 seconds or longer he or she was classified as high-risk for falling</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Habitual Physical Activity (change)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Via accelerometry</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Lower limb strength (change)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Dynamometry</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Upper Limb Strength (change)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Hand grip</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in circulation markers of systemic inflammation</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Blood Sampling including but not limited to IL-6, CRP, IL-10, TNF-Alpha</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Muscle quality using Ultrasound Imaging (change)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Cross-sectional area (cm2)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Muscle quality using Ultrasound Imaging (change)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>fat thickness (mm)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Muscle Elasticity (change)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Muscle elasticity will be measures using a MyotonPro device</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Lower limb endurance (change)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Sit to stand 60 test measuring how many 'sit to stands' can be performed in 60 seconds</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Balance (change)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Measured using a 'wii-fit' style board. Better balance is an idicator of falls risk</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Gait speed (change)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Gait speed is measure as the time taken to walk 4 meters. Slower speeds have been linked to higher mortality risk</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Height</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Height measured in meters</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Weight (change)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Weight measured in kg</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Body fat % (change)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Body fat measured using bio electrical impedance analysis</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Integrated Palliative care Outcome Scale for Renal (I-POS-Renal)(change)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>IPOS-Renal is a short measure (11 questions), combining the most common symptoms renal patients experience plus additional items from IPOS on concerns beyond symptoms, such as information needs, practical issues, family anxiety. IPOS has been validated in a mixed population of those with cancer and non-cancer diagnosis, including renal patients, and shows good content and construct validity, reliability, and responsiveness to change. Each symptom is rated on a scale of 0-4 for how much that symptom effects the participant. 0 is not at all and 4 is severely. Higher total scores indicate more symptom burden.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Short Form Health Survey (SF-12)(change)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Categorical questions that assess limitations in role functioning as a result of physical and emotional health. The survey also contains Likert response formats including those that are on a three-point scale (e.g., limited a lot, limited a little, or not limited at all) that assess limitations in physical activity and physical role functioning. A five-point scale (e.g., not at all, a little bit, moderately, quite a bit, and extremely) that assesses pain, and a five-point scale that assesses overall health (excellent, very good, good, fair, and poor) are included. The SF-12 also contains a six-point scale (e.g., all of the time, most of the time, a good bit of the time, some of the time, a little of the time, and none of the time) that assesses mental health, vitality, and social functioning. Two summary scores: mental health (MCS12), and physical health (PCS12). The scores are represented as t-scores that are linear transformations with a mean of 50 and a standard deviation of 10</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Patient Activation Measure (PAM)(Change)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Individuals are asked to complete a short survey and based on their responses, they receive a PAM score (between 0 and 100). The resulting score places the individual at one of four levels of activation, each of which reveals insight into a range of health-related characteristics, including behaviours and outcomes. The four levels of activation are:
Level 1: Individuals tend to be passive and feel overwhelmed by managing their own health. They may not understand their role in the care process.
Level 2: Individuals may lack the knowledge and confidence to manage their health.
Level 3: Individuals appear to be taking action but may still lack the confidence and skill to support their behaviours.
Level 4: Individuals have adopted many of the behaviours needed to support their health but may not be able to maintain them in the face of life stressors.
Particulars of the scoring system (and scales) are not disclosed by the license holder</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>(FACIT-F)(change)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The FACIT-fatigue scale is a 13-item patient-reported measure of fatigue with a 7-day recall period. Items are scored on a 0 - 4 response scale with anchors ranging from &quot;Not at all&quot; to &quot;Very much so&quot;. To score the FACIT-fatigue, all items are summed to create a single fatigue score with a range from 0 to 52. Items are reverse scored when appropriate to provide a scale in which higher scores represent better functioning or less fatigue</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index (PSQI)(change)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>In scoring the PSQI, seven component scores are derived, each scored 0 (no difficulty) to 3 (severe difficulty). The component scores are summed to produce a global score (range 0 to 21). Higher scores indicate worse sleep quality</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Kidney Transplant; Complications</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Home-based Exercise</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients in this arm will complete a 12 week home-based aerobic and resistance exercise training programme. There will be a 2 week period prior to this in which patients will complete up to 6 supervised sessions in order to learn about the home-based exercise training. There will be a 4 week return visit and an optional 8 week return visit in order to reassess fitness and aid the patients with any questions or queries they may have and to aid them in progressing their exercise.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>In this arm patients will continue 'as normal' with daily activities.
Patients in this arm will be offered the exercise intervention once they have completed post 12 week assessments.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Home-based Exercise</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients in the home-based exercise arm will complete a 12 week home-based aerobic and resistance exercise training programme. There will be a 2 week period prior to this in which patients will complete up to 6 supervised sessions in order to learn about the home-based exercise training. There will be a 4 week return visit and an optional 8 week return visit in order to reassess fitness and aid the patients with any questions or queries they may have and to aid them in progressing their exercise.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Home-based Exercise</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age great than 18 years old

          -  Prevalent RTR longer than 1year

          -  Able and willing to give informed consent

          -  Increased cardiometabolic risk, with at least one of:

        Diabetes mellitus Dyslipidaemia Hypertension History of ischaemic heart disease or
        cerebrovascular disease Obesity (BMI above 30)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Unable to undertake exercise due to physical or psychological barriers

          -  Unable to undergo CMR scanning (incompatible implants, claustrophobia, allergy to
             agents)

          -  Contraindication to exercise training (American College of Sports Medicine guidelines)

          -  Female participants who are pregnant, lactating, or planning pregnancy during the
             course of the study.

          -  Scheduled elective surgery or other procedures requiring general anaesthesia during
             the study.

          -  Any other significant disease or disorder (i.e. significant co-morbidity including
             unstable hypertension, potentially lethal arrhythmia, myocardial infarction within 6
             months, unstable angina, active liver disease, uncontrolled diabetes mellitus (HbA1c
             greater than or equal to 9%), advanced cerebral or peripheral vascular disease) which,
             in the opinion of the patient's own clinician the Principle Investigator may either
             put the participants at risk because of participation in the study, or may influence
             the result of the study, or the participant's ability to participate in the study.

          -  Inability to give informed consent or comply with testing and training protocol for
             any reason.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Matthew Graham-Brown</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Leicester</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Matthew Graham-Brown</last_name>
    <phone>0116 258 4346</phone>
    <email>mgb23@le.ac.uk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Roseanne Billany</last_name>
    <phone>0116 258 4346</phone>
    <email>roseanne.billany@bath.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Hospital Leicester NHS Trust</name>
      <address>
        <city>Leicester</city>
        <state>Leicestershire</state>
        <zip>LE5 4PW</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Matthew Graham-Brown</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 16, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 10, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 11, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 8, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 8, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 11, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Kidney Transplant</keyword>
  <keyword>Cardiovascular Disease</keyword>
  <keyword>Home-based Exercise</keyword>
  <keyword>Exercise</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

