<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04126161</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Pro00102976</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04126161</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>HIP: Hip Imaging Protocol</brief_title>
  <official_title>HIP: Hip Imaging Protocol: the Comparison of Muscle Ultrasound-derived Parameters With CT Imaging-derived Parameters in Primary Total Hip Arthroplasty Patients.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Duke University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Duke University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Objective measures of skeletal muscle features have previously been used to assess skeletal
      muscle quality. In certain clinical populations, such as intensive care (ICU) patients,
      specific features of the psoas muscle measured by abdominal CT have been used to assess the
      nutritional status of the patient. Abdominal CT is not performed routinely as it exposes the
      patient to ionizing radiation (X-rays) and can only be performed intermittently.

      The measurement of the thigh muscles (rectus femoris muscle, part of the quadriceps muscle)
      by handheld musculoskeletal (MSK) ultrasound is a simple, safe (no ionizing radiation) and
      repeatable (can be easily performed on a daily basis) technique. A correlation has been shown
      between muscle parameters of the psoas muscle (abdominal CT) and the rectus femoris muscle
      (MSK). A direct comparison between muscle parameters of the same skeletal muscle measured
      with both CT and MSK has not been done.

      Intramuscular adipose tissue (IMAT) is a measure of the extent of adipose tissue deposited
      within the muscle. It is a biomarker of muscle quality. The study objective is to compare
      muscle area and intramuscular adipose tissue (IMAT) content of rectus femoris muscle,
      measured by standard CT imaging with point of care handheld musculoskeletal (MSK) ultrasound
      in patients presenting for primary total hip arthroplasty. This patient group is chosen
      because they will have hip CT performed as standard of care prior to surgery.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      In our institution, all primary total hip arthroplasty patients receive abdominal CT that
      encompasses their hip as part of the standard clinical evaluation for hip surgery. This
      provides an opportunity to perform an MSK ultrasound at the same time.

      Both CT and MSK have established imaging techniques of soft tissue. Both techniques provide a
      2D digital slice representation. Although the image is black and white, there are a large
      number of intervals, up to 255, between the two extremes of black and white, termed
      grayscale. The application of an algorithm based upon the grayscale is used to define the
      different characteristics of the muscle, e.g. striated muscle versus fat infiltration. The
      algorithms used to measure muscle characteristics are entirely dependent on the originating
      imaging source. This means that an estimate of adipose using the CT algorithm is entirely
      independent of the algorithm applied to the MSK estimation of adipose.

      This study, therefore, aims to determine how well the two imaging techniques correlate with
      each other when IMAT is measured by the two separate techniques.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Suspended</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    COVID-19 Restrictions
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 1, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 1, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>All IMAT</measure>
    <time_frame>visit 1, up to 1 hour</time_frame>
    <description>CT-derived area of intramuscular adipose tissue in cm2</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>%IMAT</measure>
    <time_frame>visit 1, up to 1 hour</time_frame>
    <description>Ultrasound-derived area of intramuscular adipose tissue in %</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Metabolic Profiling Muscle</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>CT</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients have standard of care CT prior to primary hip replacement</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Ultrasound</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients have ultrasound scans together with standard of care CT prior to primary hip replacement</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>CT</intervention_name>
    <description>standard of care CT prior to primary hip replacement</description>
    <arm_group_label>CT</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ultrasound</intervention_name>
    <description>Ultrasound scan together with standard of care CT prior to primary hip replacement</description>
    <arm_group_label>Ultrasound</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Primary hip replacement

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Revision hip replacement

          -  Ipsilateral knee replacement
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>David MacLeod</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Duke University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Duke University Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Durham</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27710</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 11, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 11, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 15, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 20, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 20, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 22, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>muscle</keyword>
  <keyword>ultrasound</keyword>
  <keyword>CT</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

