<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04123769</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>GNI-F351-201901</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04123769</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study on PK of Hydronidone in Patients and Special Population</brief_title>
  <official_title>Pharmacokinetics of Hydronidone Capsules in Patients With Chronic Hepatitis B Complicated With Liver Fibrosis and Mild Hepatic Insufficiency</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Beijing Continent Pharmaceutical Co, Ltd.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Beijing Continent Pharmaceutical Co, Ltd.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      1. Evaluate the pharmacokinetic (PK) characteristics of Hydronidone capsule in target
           patients (patients with chronic viral hepatitis b with liver fibrosis) and special
           population (patients with mild liver dysfunction).

        2. To evaluate the effect of oral Hydronidone capsule on QT/QTc in patients with chronic
           viral hepatitis b accompanied by hepatic fibrosis and mild hepatic dysfunction.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 3, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 30, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Cmax</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 24 weeks</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Tmax</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 24 weeks</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>AUC</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 24 weeks</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>QT/QTc</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 24 weeks</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>CL/F</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 24 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">8</enrollment>
  <condition>Hepatitis b &amp; Liver Dysfunction</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Drug group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Hydronidone</intervention_name>
    <description>First take Hydronidone capsule, single-dose and then Multiple-dose</description>
    <arm_group_label>Drug group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Age 18-65 years (including 18 and 65 years);

          2. BMI 18-26 (including 18 and 26) [BMI= weight (kg)/height 2 (m2)];

          3. History of chronic hepatitis b, HBsAg positive ≥6 months;

          4. ALT &lt; 5 times ULN (standard upper limit);

          5. TBiL &lt; 2 times ULN (standard upper limit);

          6. ALP &lt; 1.5 times ULN (standard upper limit);

          7. Liver elastic hardness test confirmed significant liver fibrosis (LSM≥ 7.3kpa);

          8. Scores assessed by child-pugh system are 5 or 6;

          9. Patients currently receiving antiviral treatment with entecavir;

         10. The subject (or his/her partner) has no pregnancy plan during and within 6 months
             after the trial and voluntarily takes effective physical contraception and has no
             sperm or egg donation plan;

         11. Before the trial, I have had a detailed understanding of the nature, significance,
             possible benefits, possible inconveniences and potential risks of the trial, and I
             have volunteered to participate in the clinical trial. I am able to communicate well
             with the investigator, comply with the requirements of the whole study, and have
             signed a written informed consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Those who do not meet any of the inclusion criteria;

          2. (consultation) participants in clinical trials of other drugs in recent 3 months;

          3. (consultation) any drugs that inhibit or induce drug metabolism in the liver (common
             liver enzyme inducers: barbiturates (phenobarbital is the most common), carbamazepine,
             aminoximate, griseofulvin, aminopropyl ester, phenytoin, gromitol, rifampin,
             dexamethasone; Common liver enzyme inhibitors: chlorpromazine, cimetidine,
             ciprofloxacin, metronidazole, chloramphenicol, isoniazid, sulfonamide);

          4. (consultation) select those who drank excessive amounts of tea, coffee or caffeinated
             beverages (more than 8 cups a day, 1 cup =250mL) every day during the first three
             months; Or from the screening to -1 days after admission, intake of any food or drink
             containing caffeine and xanthine (such as coffee, strong tea, chocolate, etc.) and
             other special diet that affects the absorption, distribution, metabolism and excretion
             of drugs;

          5. (consultation) patients who had taken food or drinks containing enzymes that can
             induce or inhibit liver metabolism (e.g., grapefruit, mango, pitaya, grape juice,
             orange juice and other compounds rich in flavonoids or citrus glycosides) before
             admission were screened.

          6. (consultation) screening: drinking more than 14 standard units of alcohol per week in
             the first 3 months (1 standard unit contains 14g of alcohol, such as 360 mL beer or 45
             mL spirits with 40% alcohol or 150 mL wine); Or cannot abstain from alcohol during the
             test period; Or taking any alcohol products within 24 hours before the first dose of
             the study;

          7. (consultation) select those who smoke more than 5 cigarettes per day within the first
             3 months, or cannot stop using any tobacco products during the trial; Screening for
             smoking or using any tobacco products up to admission;

          8. (consultation) previous history of drug abuse and drug abuse;

          9. (consultation) patients with upper gastrointestinal massive bleeding or active peptic
             ulcer within the first 3 months were enrolled;

         10. (consultation) patients with serious diseases of cardiovascular, pulmonary, renal,
             endocrine, nervous and blood systems and mental disorders;

         11. (consultation) allergy: if allergic to two or more drugs or food; Lactose intolerant;

         12. AFP &gt; 100 μg /L;

         13. B ultrasound showed obvious space-occupying lesions in the liver, suggesting tumor;

         14. Patients with decompensated liver cirrhosis;

         15. Patients with malignant tumors;

         16. Received non-entecavir nucleoside analogues or interferon antiviral therapy within 3
             months before inclusion;

         17. Pregnant and/or lactating women;

         18. Subjects who are legally disabled according to the law of the People's Republic of
             China on the protection of disabled persons (April 2008);

         19. Alcohol breath test results greater than 0.0mg/100mL;

         20. Positive urine drug screening;

         21. Patients with suspected poor compliance;

         22. The investigator considers that there are any circumstances that may affect the
             subject's informed consent or adherence to the study protocol, or participation in the
             study may affect the results of the study or their own safety.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Medical ethics committee of wuhan infectious disease hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Wuhan</city>
        <state>Hubei</state>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ling Zhang</last_name>
      <phone>+86-13501209210</phone>
      <email>rlzhang1006@163.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>QingJing Zhu</last_name>
      <phone>+86-15907143302</phone>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 10, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 10, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 11, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 11, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 11, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 14, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis B</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Liver Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

