<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04126343</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>UP0050</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2019-002797-31</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04126343</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study to Test the Cardiac Effects of Padsevonil in Healthy Study Participants</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Single-Center, Randomized, Placebo-Controlled, 3 Treatment Period Crossover Study to Assess the Effect of Padsevonil on Cardiac Repolarization (QTc Interval) (Using Moxifloxacin as a Positive Control) in Healthy Study Participants</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>UCB Biopharma S.P.R.L.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>UCB Pharma</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of the study is to evaluate the effects on cardiac repolarization of high-dose
      padsevonil (PSL) in comparison to placebo in healthy study participants.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Based on available data, UCB has decided to stop development of padsevonil as adjunctive
    treatment of focal-onset seizures
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 23, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 22, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 22, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline in QTcF</measure>
    <time_frame>On Day 1 and Day 8 in Treatment Periods 1, 2, and 3</time_frame>
    <description>Placebo-corrected change from Baseline in corrected QT interval (QTc), based on Fridericia's correction (QTcF) method (ΔΔQTcF) evaluated during the Target Dose Day of the padsevonil and placebo Treatment Periods, using time point analysis.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline in QTcF after a single dose of moxifloxacin</measure>
    <time_frame>On Day 1 and Day 8 in Treatment Periods 1, 2, or 3</time_frame>
    <description>Placebo-corrected change from Baseline in QTcF after a single dose of moxifloxacin</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline for heart rate (HR) interval</measure>
    <time_frame>On Day 1 and Day 8 in Treatment Periods 1, 2, and 3</time_frame>
    <description>Placebo-corrected change from Baseline for HR interval</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline for PR interval</measure>
    <time_frame>On Day 1 and Day 8 in Treatment Periods 1, 2, and 3</time_frame>
    <description>Placebo-corrected changes from Baseline for PR interval</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline for QRS interval</measure>
    <time_frame>On Day 1 and Day 8 in Treatment Periods 1, 2, and 3</time_frame>
    <description>Placebo-corrected changes from Baseline for QRS interval</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Frequency of treatment-emergent changes for T-wave morphology and U-wave presence</measure>
    <time_frame>On Day 1 and Day 8 in Treatment Periods 1, 2, and 3</time_frame>
    <description>Frequency of treatment-emergent changes of electrocardiogram waveforms as T-waves and U-waves.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline in QTcF evaluated at drug-specific tmax for padsevonil</measure>
    <time_frame>On Day 1 and Day 8 in Treatment Periods 1, 2, or 3</time_frame>
    <description>Change from Baseline in QTcF (ΔQTcF) evaluated at drug-specific tmax (Δtmax) for padsevonil</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline in QTcF evaluated at drug-specific tmax for UCB1431322-000</measure>
    <time_frame>On Day 1 and Day 8 in Treatment Periods 1, 2, or 3</time_frame>
    <description>Change from Baseline in QTcF (ΔQTcF) evaluated at drug-specific tmax (Δtmax) for UCB1431322-000</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline in QTcF evaluated at drug-specific tmax for UCB1447499-000</measure>
    <time_frame>On Day 1 and Day 8 in Treatment Periods 1, 2, or 3</time_frame>
    <description>Change from Baseline in QTcF (ΔQTcF) evaluated at drug-specific tmax (Δtmax) for UCB1447499-000</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cmax for padsevonil at steady state (Cmax,ss)</measure>
    <time_frame>On Day 8 in Treatment Periods 1, 2, or 3</time_frame>
    <description>Cmax,ss: Maximum observed plasma concentration of padsevonil at steady state</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>tmax of padsevonil at steady state</measure>
    <time_frame>On Day 8 in Treatment Periods 1, 2, or 3</time_frame>
    <description>tmax: Time of observed maximum plasma concentration at steady state</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>AUCtau of padsevonil at steady state</measure>
    <time_frame>On Day 8 in Treatment Periods 1, 2, or 3</time_frame>
    <description>AUCtau: Area under the plasma concentration time curve over a dosing interval at steady state</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of Adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>From Screening to Safety Follow-up (up to Day 67)</time_frame>
    <description>An Adverse Event is any untoward medical occurrence in a subject or trial subject that is administered a drug or biologic (medicinal product) or that is using a medical device. The event does not necessarily have a causal relationship with that treatment or usage</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of Serious Adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>From Screening to Safety Follow-up (up to Day 67)</time_frame>
    <description>A Serious Adverse Event (SAE) is any untoward medical occurrence that at any dose:
Results in death
Is life-threatening
Requires in patient hospitalization or prolongation of existing hospitalization
Is a congenital anomaly or birth defect
Is infection that requires treatment parenteral antibiotics
Other important medical events which based on medical or scientific judgement may jeopardize the patients, or may require medical or surgical intervention to prevent any of the above</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of treatment related Adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>From Baseline to Safety Follow-up (up to Day 67)</time_frame>
    <description>An Adverse Event (AE) is any untoward medical occurrence in a patient or clinical investigation subject administered a pharmaceutical product, which does not necessarily have a causal relationship with this treatment. An AE could therefore be any unfavorable and unintended sign, symptom, or disease temporally associated with the use of a medicinal (investigational) product, whether or not related to the medicinal (investigational) product.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of Adverse events leading to discontinuation of the study</measure>
    <time_frame>From Baseline to Safety Follow-up (up to Day 67)</time_frame>
    <description>An Adverse Event is any untoward medical occurrence in a subject or trial subject that is administered a drug or biologic (medicinal product) or that is using a medical device. The event does not necessarily have a causal relationship with that treatment or usage. The results of this Primary Outcome Measure are summarized from the Adverse Event pages of the Case Report Forms.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">54</enrollment>
  <condition>Healthy Study Participants</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Padsevonil</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Study participants randomized to this arm will receive assigned doses of padsevonil twice daily. On Day 8 padsevonil will be administered in the morning, and placebo will administered in the evening.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Study participants randomized to this arm will receive placebo twice daily to maintain the blinding.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Moxifloxacin</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Study participants randomized to this arm will receive padsevonil-placebo twice daily. On Day 8 placebo will be administered in the morning, and moxifloxacin will administered in the evening.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Padsevonil</intervention_name>
    <description>Pharmaceutical form: Film-coated tablet
Route of administration: Oral use
Study participants will receive padsevonil in a pre-specified dosing sequence during the Treatment Period</description>
    <arm_group_label>Padsevonil</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Moxifloxacin</intervention_name>
    <description>Pharmaceutical form: Film-coated tablet
Route of administration: Oral use
Study participants will receive moxifloxacin once during the Treatment Period</description>
    <arm_group_label>Moxifloxacin</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Pharmaceutical form: Film-coated tablet
Route of administration: Oral use
Study participants will receive placebo in a pre-specified sequence during the Treatment Period to match padsevonil and maintain the blinding</description>
    <arm_group_label>Moxifloxacin</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Padsevonil</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Participant must be 18 to 55 years of age inclusive, at the time of signing the
             informed consent form (ICF)

          -  Participant who is overtly healthy as determined by medical evaluation including
             medical history, physical examination, laboratory tests, and cardiac monitoring

          -  Body weight of at least 50 kilogram (kg) (males) or 45 kg (females) and body mass
             index (BMI) within the range 18 to 30 kg/m2 (inclusive)

          -  Male and/or female:

        A male study participant must agree to use contraception during the Treatment Period and
        for at least 90 days after the last dose of study medication and refrain from donating
        sperm during this period

        A female participant is eligible to participate if she is not pregnant, not breastfeeding,
        and at least one of the following conditions applies:

        Not a woman of childbearing potential (WOCBP) OR A WOCBP who agrees to follow the
        contraceptive guidance during the Treatment Period and for at least 90 days after the last
        dose of study medication

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Participant has a known hypersensitivity to any components of the study medication or
             comparative drugs as stated in this protocol or history of tendon pathology secondary
             to use of quinolone antibiotics

          -  Participant has a history of unexplained syncope or a family history of sudden death
             due to long QT syndrome

          -  Participant has a present condition of respiratory or cardiovascular disorders, eg,
             cardiac insufficiency, coronary heart disease, hypertension, arrhythmia,
             tachyarrhythmia, or myocardial infarction

          -  Past or intended use of over-the-counter (OTC) or prescription medication including
             herbal medications within 2 weeks or 5 half-lives prior to dosing.

          -  Participant has used hepatic enzyme-inducing drugs (eg, glucocorticoids,
             phenobarbital, isoniazid, phenytoin, rifampicin, etc) within 2 months prior to the
             first dose of study medication

          -  Participant has previously received padsevonil (PSL) in this or any other study

          -  Participant has any clinically relevant electrocardiogram (ECG) finding at the
             Screening Visit or at Baseline. Participant has an abnormality in the 12-lead ECG
             that, in the opinion of the Investigator, increases the risks associated with
             participating in the study. In addition, any participant with any of the following
             findings will be excluded:

               1. QT interval corrected for heart rate using the Fridericia method (QTcF) ≥450 ms
                  (on mean of triplicate ECG recordings);

               2. Other conduction abnormalities (defined as PR interval &gt;220 ms);

               3. QRS interval &gt;109 ms;

               4. Any rhythm other than sinus rhythm;

               5. Any history of Wolff-Parkinson-White Syndrome, Brugada Syndrome, unexplained
                  syncope, or ventricular tachycardia;

               6. Family history of QTc prolongation or of unexplainable sudden death at &lt;50 years
                  of age

          -  Participant has made a blood or plasma donation or has had a comparable blood loss
             (&gt;450 mL) within 30 days prior to the Screening Visit. Blood donation during the study
             is not permitted
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>55 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>UCB Cares</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>001 844 599 2273 (UCB)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Up0050 001</name>
      <address>
        <city>London</city>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 11, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 11, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 15, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 9, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 9, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 11, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Healthy study participants</keyword>
  <keyword>Padsevonil</keyword>
  <keyword>Moxifloxacin</keyword>
  <keyword>Cardiac repolarization</keyword>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Moxifloxacin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Due to the small sample size in this trial, Individual Patient Data cannot be adequately anonymized and there is a reasonable likelihood that individual participants could be re-identified. For this reason, data from this trial cannot be shared.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

