<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04129437</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IRB2019172</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04129437</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Acute Low Back Pain in the Emergency Department Treated With Osteopathic Manipulative Treatment Versus NSAIDs</brief_title>
  <official_title>Osteopathic Manipulative Treatment Compared to Ibuprofen for the Treatment of Acute Low Back Pain in the Emergency Department: a Randomized Controlled Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Albert Einstein Healthcare Network</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Albert Einstein Healthcare Network</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Acute low back pain is the fifth most common presenting complaint to the emergency
      department, accounting for approximately 4.4% of annual visits. The treatment for acute low
      back pain is often NSAIDs or other analgesic medications. Osteopathic Manipulative Treatment
      (OMT) has been shown to be an effective treatment modality for acute low back pain, however,
      it's use in the emergency department setting is not well described. The adjunct of OMT has
      the potential to increase patient satisfaction, decrease length of stay and decrease the
      number of unnecessary prescription medications. We plan to investigate the use of OMT in the
      setting of acute complaints of low back pain in comparison to the use of nonsteroidal
      anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs) as primary treatment modality. The study will be a
      non-blinded randomized-control trial and will take place in an academic tertiary care center
      in urban Philadelphia, PA over an approximate one-year timespan. We will utilize
      osteopathic-trained attending and resident physicians to perform the manipulation. Patients
      will be randomized into one of three treatment groups: appropriately dosed NSAID therapy
      alone, OMT in addition to NSAID therapy, or OMT alone. The primary outcome will be the
      difference in pain score before and after treatment using a VAS scale. Secondary outcomes
      will include patient and physician satisfaction immediately following treatment. Results will
      be shared by means of publication to the osteopathic and allopathic communities.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The goal of this study is to describe the efficacy of Osteopathic Manipulative Treatment
      (OMT) compared to NSAIDs in decreasing pain in adults with acute low back pain in the
      emergency department (ED). This study would provide an additional novel adjunct for pain
      management of painful procedures in the emergency department. Currently in the emergency
      department the complaint of low back pain comprises 4.4% of visits annually and is an area of
      patient dissatisfaction surrounding the pain management.

      The primary aims of this project will be measure the level of pain pre and post procedure in
      adults receiving ibuprofen (NSAID), OMT, or OMT/ibuprofen for low back pain. Secondary aims
      include patient and physician post procedure satisfaction scores, length of stay in ED.

      AIM 1: Measure the level of pain pre and post procedures in adults receiving ibuprofen, OMT,
      or OMT/Ibuprofen. Hypothesis: The level of pain for patients receiving OMT will be decreased
      to a greater extent that those receiving only NSAIDs for low back pain.

      AIM2: Measure the patient and physician satisfaction with the adjunct of OMT in regard to
      ability to manage pain based on satisfaction scores from questionnaire. Hypothesis: There
      will be greater satisfaction in the patients receiving OMT and OMT/NSAIDs than those
      receiving only OMT alone.

      This study will be a prospective, randomized- controlled trial of patients with acute low
      back pain in the ED of an urban, tertiary, academic medical center. Subjects will be
      randomized to one of three groups: Ibuprofen (800 mg), Ibuprofen (800 mg)/OMT, or OMT only
      for the treatment of acute low back pain

      Recruitment Methods

      The research associates as well as the health care team (both residents and attending
      physicians) will screen patients who present to the ED with the chief complaint of back pain
      and may qualify for the study. Research associates will use the electronic medical record for
      screening, and they will be in charge of informed consent, enrollment, as well as data
      collection. The research study team (osteopathic emergency physicians) will be in charge of
      performing the OMT.

      Procedures Involved in the Research

      Initial medical assessment will be made in accordance with established clinical procedures,
      including the history, physical examination, and vital signs. If by clinical assessment the
      patient meets eligibility criteria, then they will be approached by a research associate for
      enrollment in the study and will obtain informed consent.

      After informed consent, the patient will fill out a pre intervention 100 mm VAS baseline pain
      scale. The patient will be randomized to one of the three treatment arms; NSAID (ibuprofen),
      OMT/NSAID (ibuprofen), or OMT alone by using a randomization scheme generated using the web
      site Randomization.com (http://www.randomization.com).

      Once randomized, subjects in the NSAID arm will be assessed using a VAS prior to medication
      administration. They will then be given 800 mg of ibuprofen and subjects' pain will be
      assessed using the VAS at 45 minutes after NSAID administration. Subjects in the NSAID/OMT
      arm will be assessed using a VAS prior to medication administration and OMT. They will then
      be given 800 mg of ibuprofen and within 10 minutes will receive OMT. The subject's pain will
      be assessed using the VAS at 45 minutes after NSAID administration and completion of OMT. The
      OMT only arm will be assessed using a VAS prior to any OMT. OMT will then be performed and
      subjects' pain will be assessed using the VAS at 45 minutes after OMT is completed. The
      method of OMT will be left to the discretion of the treating physician, but will be recorded
      in the data collection sheet.

      The subject's clinical data (refer to data management) will be entered into a standardized
      data collection form. Study will end 45-60 minutes after randomized intervention. Once the
      procedure is complete subjects will fill out a post procedure satisfaction questionnaire. The
      physician will also fill out a post procedure questionnaire.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 19, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Factorial Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pain score</measure>
    <time_frame>45 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>Difference in pain score before and after treatment using a Visual Analog Scale (VAS) scale (minimum 1, maximum 10, 10 being the worst)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient Satisfaction</measure>
    <time_frame>45 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>Patient satisfaction immediately following treatment with questionnaire</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Physician Satisfaction</measure>
    <time_frame>45 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>Physician satisfaction immediately following treatment with questionnaire</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">174</enrollment>
  <condition>Low Back Pain</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>NSAID</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Ibuprofen, 800 mg, one time dose</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>OMT/NSAID</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Ibuprofen, 800 mg, one time dose</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>OMT alone</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>low velocity osteopathic manipulative medicine</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ibuprofen</intervention_name>
    <description>Weight based ibuprofen dosing</description>
    <arm_group_label>NSAID</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>OMT/NSAID</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Motrin, Advil</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Osteopathic manipulative treatment</intervention_name>
    <description>Low velocity osteopathic manipulative treatment</description>
    <arm_group_label>OMT alone</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>OMT/NSAID</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>OMT, OMM</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  All patients 18 years of age or older with the chief complaint of acute low back pain
             defined as symptom duration no longer than four weeks prior to ED presentation and
             having clinical findings of somatic dysfunction (muscle edema, erythema, bogginess,
             hypertonic muscles, asymmetry of tissue, pain with movement, severe/sharp tenderness).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients will be excluded if they previously participated in the study, history of
             gastrointestinal bleed, allergies to NSAIDs, NSAID use 4 hours prior to arrival,
             history of or concern for spinal column fracture, current diagnosis of active
             malignancy or metastatic cancer, open skin wounds at the treatment location site,
             patients with neurological deficits related to acute back pain, pregnant women,
             individuals unable to take oral medications, temperature &gt;38C, prisoners, those unable
             to consent, subjects under police custody, nursing home residents, non-English
             speaking patients.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Joseph Herres, DO</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Einstein Healthcare Network</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Alexis Cates, DO</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Einstein Healthcare Network</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Alexis Cates, DO</last_name>
    <phone>985-630-0193</phone>
    <email>catesale@einstein.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Joseph Herres, DO</last_name>
    <phone>215-456-6666</phone>
    <email>herresjo@einstein.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>AEHN</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19147</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Beth Lynch</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 11, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 15, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 16, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 19, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 19, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 20, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Albert Einstein Healthcare Network</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Alexis Cates, DO</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Medical Toxicology Fellow</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Back Pain</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Emergencies</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Low Back Pain</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Ibuprofen</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

