<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04121884</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Pro00040159</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04121884</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Neurophysiological Mechanisms of Accelerated Resolution Therapy (ART)</brief_title>
  <acronym>M-ART</acronym>
  <official_title>Neurophysiological Mechanisms of Accelerated Resolution Therapy (ART)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of South Florida</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of South Florida</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      In brief, ART is an innovative &quot;mind-body&quot; (body-centric) psychotherapy that makes use of
      established core components of trauma-focused therapy including imaginal exposure and imagery
      rescripting to promote memory reconsolidation, all facilitated as the patient is directed by
      the therapist to perform sets of lateral left-right eye movements similar to rapid eye
      movements (REM). The investigators propose to investigate how ART may directly influence
      heart rate variability (HRV), EEG power spectral densities, and sleep architecture in three
      aims. At the broadest level, the investigators postulate that both within individual ART
      sessions, and across the full course of treatment (e.g. up to 4 sessions), ART results in a
      profound shift from sympathetic (arousal) to parasympathetic (rest) nervous system balance,
      and that this shift can be reliably measured by neurophysiological assessment using
      electrocardiogram (ECG) and electroencephalogram (EEG) measurement.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Our long-term goal is to understand, from a mechanistic perspective, how ART appears to
      result in rapid, successful treatment of PTSD and related comorbidities. This knowledge will
      help to identify target populations for treatment, and objective approaches in which to
      evaluate patient outcome response beyond conventional reliance on self-report measures. Thus,
      specific aims of our proposal, which will make use of wireless equipment for
      Electrocardiographic (ECG) measurement of Heart Rate Variability (HRV), and
      Electroencephalographic (EEG) measurements of power spectral densities and sleep
      architecture, are as follows:

        1. To quantify and characterize changes in HRV, EEG power spectral densities, sleep
           architecture, and ANS balance within individual sessions of ART, as well as before and
           at the end of treatment with ART (up to 4 sessions).

        2. To examine whether the aforementioned ART-induced changes in HRV, EEG power spectral
           densities, sleep architecture, and ANS balance vary substantially in the setting of
           primary treatment for symptoms of post- traumatic stress disorder (PTSD), depression,
           acute stress disorder, complicated grief, and/or alcohol abuse.

        3. To assess the degree of concordance between ART-induced objective measurement of changes
           in HRV, EEG power spectral densities, sleep architecture, and ANS balance and
           self-report changes in symptoms of PTSD, depression, acute stress disorder, complicated
           grief, and/or alcohol abuse.

      The investigators will accomplish these objectives using a prospective, longitudinal,
      descriptive design to achieve robust results. Subjects (n=40) will be enrolled in the study
      based on symptomatology. All subjects will receive Accelerated Resolution Therapy (ART) on a
      weekly basis for up to 4 sessions. The dose of up to 4 sessions has been selected to insure
      what is believed to be an effective dose based on previous studies of ART for treatment of
      PTSD. The investigators will collect data pre, during, and post each ART session. The sample
      of 40 subjects will be drawn from referrals at private practices of designated licensed
      mental health clinicians certified in ART, referrals from stakeholders and academic and
      community partners (e.g. USF student veterans referred through the USF Office of Student
      Veterans), and referrals of immediate family members of an individual who received hospice
      care prior to death at Suncoast Hospice or Chapters Health System. All subjects will undergo
      an intake assessment by a licensed clinical psychologist to determine study eligibility at
      USF.

      The investigators expect to obtain support for our central hypothesis that ART modulates
      neurophysiological mechanisms through neurophysiological biomarkers of the autonomic
      (parasympathetic) nervous system and improved sleep architecture. Knowledge from a
      mechanistic perspective, on how ART appears to result in rapid, successful treatment of
      symptoms of PTSD and related conditions will help to identify target populations for
      treatment, and objective approaches in which to evaluate patient outcome response beyond
      conventional reliance on self-report measures.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 31, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 30, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>A prospective, longitudinal, descriptive study design.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Autonomic Nervous System (ANS) Imbalance</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline pre first ART session at study day 1 and post 4th ART session at 5 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>HRV, EEG power spectral densities, and sleep architecture</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in ANS During ART</measure>
    <time_frame>During first ART session at 1 week and during 4th ART session at 5 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>HRV and EEG power spectral densities</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Degree of concordance between ART-induced changes in ANS and symptoms of PTSD, depression, ASD, complicated grief, and alcohol abuse</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline pre first ART session at study day 1 and post 4th ART session at 5 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>DSM-V PTSD Checklist (PCL-V)</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Depressive Symptoms</condition>
  <condition>Stress Disorder, Acute</condition>
  <condition>Prolonged Grief Disorder</condition>
  <condition>Alcohol Abuse</condition>
  <condition>Stress Disorders, Post-Traumatic</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>ART Treatment</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>A broad patient representation of male and female adults; aged &gt; 18 years; English speaking; and significant clinical symptoms of any of the following conditions: PTSD, Depression, ASD, Complicated Grief, and Alcohol Abuse.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Accelerated Resolution Therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>The ART protocol first uses the technique of imaginal exposure to elicit physiological reactions associated with patient recall from beginning to end (verbally or non-verbally) of a traumatic/distressing experience. As physiological reactions emerge, the participant is directed to focus their attention on the specific body-centric reactions while laterally performing smooth pursuit eye movements which are achieved by tracking the clinician's hand which oscillates from left-to-right at a short distance from the participant's eyes. Then the participant is directed to imagine a positive way in which they prefer to recall their experience(s), including emphasis on &quot;replacing&quot; negative images in the brain with positive images. This technique is based on the process of memory reconsolidation, which allows for &quot;adding&quot; of positive material to the recall of negative, highly emotional past experiences.</description>
    <arm_group_label>ART Treatment</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>ART</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Posttraumatic Stress Disorder (PTSD): Score of &gt; 33 on the 20-item DSM-V PTSD
             Checklist (PCL-V) or

          -  Depression: Score of &gt; 16 on the 20-item Center for Epidemiologic Depression Scale or

          -  Acute stress disorder: Presence of criterions A-E on the 19-item Acute Stress Disorder
             Scale or

          -  Complicated grief: Score of &gt; 25 on the 19-item Inventory of Complicated Grief or

          -  Alcohol abuse: Score of &gt; 10 on 10-item Alcohol Use Disorders Identification Test
             (AUDIT) and

          -  Corroboration of the above symptomatology through verification of the corresponding
             subscale of the 125-item Psychiatric Diagnostic Screening Questionnaire (PDSQ).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Currently engaged in another psychotherapy regimen including currently engaged in ART
             or another eye movement therapy, such as EMDR;

          -  Have a major psychiatric disorder (e.g. bipolar disorder) deemed likely to interfere
             with treatment delivery;

          -  Currently in a formal substance dependence treatment program (alcohol and/or drug)
             anticipated to interfere with treatment delivery (e.g. through detox and symptoms of
             physiological withdrawal). All persons recruited for potential study participation
             will undergo a clinical intake assessment, with completion of ART intake form, by a
             licensed clinical therapist, to determine study eligibility.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Kevin E Kip, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of South Florida</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Paula L Cairns, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of South Florida</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Paula L Cairns, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>8139749716</phone>
    <email>paulacairns@usf.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Kevin E Kip, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>8139749266</phone>
    <email>kkip@usf.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of South Florida</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tampa</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33612</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Paula L Cairns, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>727-543-8680</phone>
      <email>paulacairns@usf.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Kevin E Kip, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>8139749266</phone>
      <email>kkip@usf.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://report.nih.gov/NIHfactsheets/ViewFactSheet.aspx?csid=58</url>
    <description>PTSD Fact Sheet</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kip KE, Sullivan KL, Lengacher CA, Rosenzweig L, Hernandez DF, Kadel R, Kozel FA, Shuman A, Girling SA, Hardwick MJ, Diamond DM. Brief treatment of co-occurring post-traumatic stress and depressive symptoms by use of accelerated resolution therapy(®). Front Psychiatry. 2013 Mar 8;4:11. doi: 10.3389/fpsyt.2013.00011. eCollection 2013.</citation>
    <PMID>23482431</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kip KE, Hernandez DF, Shuman A, Witt A, Diamond DM, Davis S, Kip R, Abhayakumar A, Wittenberg T, Girling SA, Witt S, Rosenzweig L. Comparison of Accelerated Resolution Therapy (ART) for Treatment of Symptoms of PTSD and Sexual Trauma Between Civilian and Military Adults. Mil Med. 2015 Sep;180(9):964-71. doi: 10.7205/MILMED-D-14-00307.</citation>
    <PMID>26327548</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kip KE, Diamond DM. Clinical, Empirical, and Theoretical Rationale for Selection of Accelerated Resolution Therapy for Treatment of Post-traumatic Stress Disorder in VA and DoD Facilities. Mil Med. 2018 Sep 1;183(9-10):e314-e321. doi: 10.1093/milmed/usy027.</citation>
    <PMID>29635395</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kip KE, D'Aoust RF, Hernandez DF, Girling SA, Cuttino B, Long MK, Rojas P, Wittenberg T, Abhayakumar A, Rosenzweig L. Evaluation of brief treatment of symptoms of psychological trauma among veterans residing in a homeless shelter by use of Accelerated Resolution Therapy. Nurs Outlook. 2016 Sep-Oct;64(5):411-23. doi: 10.1016/j.outlook.2016.04.006. Epub 2016 May 7.</citation>
    <PMID>27601310</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kip KE, Shuman A, Hernandez DF, Diamond DM, Rosenzweig L. Case report and theoretical description of accelerated resolution therapy (ART) for military-related post-traumatic stress disorder. Mil Med. 2014 Jan;179(1):31-7. doi: 10.7205/MILMED-D-13-00229.</citation>
    <PMID>24402982</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hernandez DF, Waits W, Calvio L, Byrne M. Practice comparisons between accelerated resolution therapy, eye movement desensitization and reprocessing and cognitive processing therapy with case examples. Nurse Educ Today. 2016 Dec;47:74-80. doi: 10.1016/j.nedt.2016.05.010. Epub 2016 May 21.</citation>
    <PMID>27250615</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kip KE, Rosenzweig L, Hernandez DF, Shuman A, Diamond DM, Girling SA, Sullivan KL, Wittenberg T, Witt AM, Lengacher CA, Anderson B, McMillan SC. Accelerated Resolution Therapy for treatment of pain secondary to symptoms of combat-related posttraumatic stress disorder. Eur J Psychotraumatol. 2014 May 7;5. doi: 10.3402/ejpt.v5.24066. eCollection 2014.</citation>
    <PMID>24959325</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schimmels J, Waits W. A Tale of Two Compulsions - Two Case Studies Using Accelerated Resolution Therapy (ART) for Obsessive Compulsive Disorder (OCD). Mil Med. 2019 May 1;184(5-6):e470-e474. doi: 10.1093/milmed/usy257. Erratum in: Mil Med. 2019 Jan 1;184(1-2):59.</citation>
    <PMID>30295890</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Blechert J, Michael T, Grossman P, Lajtman M, Wilhelm FH. Autonomic and respiratory characteristics of posttraumatic stress disorder and panic disorder. Psychosom Med. 2007 Dec;69(9):935-43. Epub 2007 Nov 8.</citation>
    <PMID>17991823</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chalmers JA, Quintana DS, Abbott MJ, Kemp AH. Anxiety Disorders are Associated with Reduced Heart Rate Variability: A Meta-Analysis. Front Psychiatry. 2014 Jul 11;5:80. doi: 10.3389/fpsyt.2014.00080. eCollection 2014.</citation>
    <PMID>25071612</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Thayer JF, Yamamoto SS, Brosschot JF. The relationship of autonomic imbalance, heart rate variability and cardiovascular disease risk factors. Int J Cardiol. 2010 May 28;141(2):122-31. doi: 10.1016/j.ijcard.2009.09.543. Epub 2009 Nov 11. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19910061</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Thayer JF, Ahs F, Fredrikson M, Sollers JJ 3rd, Wager TD. A meta-analysis of heart rate variability and neuroimaging studies: implications for heart rate variability as a marker of stress and health. Neurosci Biobehav Rev. 2012 Feb;36(2):747-56. doi: 10.1016/j.neubiorev.2011.11.009. Epub 2011 Dec 8. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22178086</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kemp AH, Griffiths K, Felmingham KL, Shankman SA, Drinkenburg W, Arns M, Clark CR, Bryant RA. Disorder specificity despite comorbidity: resting EEG alpha asymmetry in major depressive disorder and post-traumatic stress disorder. Biol Psychol. 2010 Oct;85(2):350-4. doi: 10.1016/j.biopsycho.2010.08.001. Epub 2010 Aug 11.</citation>
    <PMID>20708650</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lobo I, Portugal LC, Figueira I, Volchan E, David I, Garcia Pereira M, de Oliveira L. EEG correlates of the severity of posttraumatic stress symptoms: A systematic review of the dimensional PTSD literature. J Affect Disord. 2015 Sep 1;183:210-20. doi: 10.1016/j.jad.2015.05.015. Epub 2015 May 15. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26025367</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Todder D, Levine J, Abujumah A, Mater M, Cohen H, Kaplan Z. The quantitative electroencephalogram and the low-resolution electrical tomographic analysis in posttraumatic stress disorder. Clin EEG Neurosci. 2012 Jan;43(1):48-53.</citation>
    <PMID>22423551</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lee SH, Yoon S, Kim JI, Jin SH, Chung CK. Functional connectivity of resting state EEG and symptom severity in patients with post-traumatic stress disorder. Prog Neuropsychopharmacol Biol Psychiatry. 2014 Jun 3;51:51-7. doi: 10.1016/j.pnpbp.2014.01.008. Epub 2014 Jan 19.</citation>
    <PMID>24447944</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Metzger LJ, Paige SR, Carson MA, Lasko NB, Paulus LA, Pitman RK, Orr SP. PTSD arousal and depression symptoms associated with increased right-sided parietal EEG asymmetry. J Abnorm Psychol. 2004 May;113(2):324-9.</citation>
    <PMID>15122952</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Harvey AG, Jones C, Schmidt DA. Sleep and posttraumatic stress disorder: a review. Clin Psychol Rev. 2003 May;23(3):377-407. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>12729678</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Germain A. Sleep disturbances as the hallmark of PTSD: where are we now? Am J Psychiatry. 2013 Apr;170(4):372-82. doi: 10.1176/appi.ajp.2012.12040432. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23223954</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Levendowski DJ, Popovic D, Berka C, Westbrook PR. Retrospective cross-validation of automated sleep staging using electroocular recording in patients with and without sleep disordered breathing. Int Arch Med. 2012 Jun 25;5(1):21. doi: 10.1186/1755-7682-5-21.</citation>
    <PMID>22726270</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Stepnowsky C, Levendowski D, Popovic D, Ayappa I, Rapoport DM. Scoring accuracy of automated sleep staging from a bipolar electroocular recording compared to manual scoring by multiple raters. Sleep Med. 2013 Nov;14(11):1199-207. doi: 10.1016/j.sleep.2013.04.022. Epub 2013 Aug 16.</citation>
    <PMID>24047533</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Modarres MH, Opel RA, Weymann KB, Lim MM. Strong correlation of novel sleep electroencephalography coherence markers with diagnosis and severity of posttraumatic stress disorder. Sci Rep. 2019 Mar 12;9(1):4247. doi: 10.1038/s41598-018-38102-4.</citation>
    <PMID>30862872</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>November 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 7, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 8, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 10, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 1, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 1, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 4, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of South Florida</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Kevin Kip</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Heart Rate Variability</keyword>
  <keyword>Sleep</keyword>
  <keyword>Electrocardiogram</keyword>
  <keyword>Electroencephlogram</keyword>
  <keyword>Alcohol Abuse</keyword>
  <keyword>Prolonged Grief Disorder</keyword>
  <keyword>Stress Disorder, Acute</keyword>
  <keyword>Stress Disorders, Post-Traumatic</keyword>
  <keyword>Depressive Symptoms</keyword>
  <keyword>Power Spectral Density</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Alcoholism</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Stress Disorders, Traumatic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depression</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Stress Disorders, Post-Traumatic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Stress Disorders, Traumatic, Acute</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

