<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04125173</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>1909975965</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04125173</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effect of Lower Pneumoperitoneum Pressure During Laparoscopic and Robotic Hysterectomy</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Effect of Lower Pneumoperitoneum Pressure During Laparoscopic and Robotic Hysterectomy: A Randomized Controlled Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Arizona</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Arizona</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      With the limited evidence that lower pneumoperitoneum pressures improve postoperative pain in
      laparoscopic or robotic hysterectomy for benign indications, we would like to determine if we
      can both further validate this idea but also show that it has minimal effect on physician
      satisfaction performing the surgery.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Minimally invasive hysterectomy, including conventional laparoscopic and robotic-assisted
      hysterectomy, is a commonly performed gynecologic surgery that universally results in
      postoperative pain for patients. Opioid medications are helpful to control postoperative pain
      and are routinely given to women who undergo minimally invasive hysterectomy. However, opioid
      abuse is on the rise in the United States, and there is increased awareness of misuse leading
      to abuse, overdose, and chronic opioid use. In addition to narcotic usage, postoperative pain
      also has negative effects on patient satisfaction and length of stay in the post-anesthesia
      care unit (PACU) leading to potential hospital admission. There is existing evidence that
      reducing the pressure used to create the pneumoperitoneum during laparoscopic surgery may
      affect pain scores that patients endorse in the PACU. Due to improved postoperative pain,
      patients may have decreased opioid use in the PACU and at home, shorter hospital stay, and
      improved overall patient satisfaction. If lower pneumoperitoneum pressures during
      laparoscopic surgery can be shown to reduce postoperative pain, then the ultimate question
      becomes whether there is ability to adapt this practice of using lower pressures to maintain
      pneumoperitoneum. It is unclear whether physician satisfaction will be affected.

      There are several publications investigating the effect of lower pneumoperitoneum pressures
      on postoperative pain. A systematic review in 2016 included 238 patients (three RCTs), showed
      pneumoperitoneum pressures of 8mmHg had a statistically significant although minimal decrease
      in postoperative pain compared to 12mmHg, although lower pressures were associated with worse
      visualization. The authors concluded that the systematic review was inconclusive and further
      studies were necessary. A randomized pilot study with 60 patients comparing low pressure
      (7mmHg) using the AirSeal System versus standard insufflation (15mmHg), showed lower
      postoperative shoulder pain in the group with lower pressure using the AirSeal system. Two
      abstracts in the Journal of Minimally Invasive Gynecology present retrospective studies
      showing decreased postoperative pain with lower pneumoperitoneum pressure. The first abstract
      is from 2015, included a sample size of 170 patients who underwent benign robotic gynecologic
      surgery, 85 patients in each arm (12mmHg and 15mmHg). They showed no difference in median
      recovery time in the PACU and significantly lower median first pain score (5 vs 6, p=.04).
      The second abstract is from 2018 and included a sample size of 598 patients who underwent
      benign robotic gynecologic surgery, 99 patients in 15mmHg arm, 100 patients in 12mmHg arm, 99
      patients in 10mmHg arm, and 300 patients in 8mmHg arm. They showed lower initial pain scores
      with each degree of lower pressure (5.9 vs 5.4 vs 4.4 vs 3.8, p=&lt;.0001) and shorter hospital
      stays with lower pressures. They showed no difference in operative times or blood loss in the
      four arms. Similar studies have been done with cholecystectomy patients that have shown
      improved postoperative shoulder pain with lower pneumoperitoneum pressures. There is also an
      ongoing clinical trial that is still recruiting patients that is studying this similar
      comparison using 9mmHg vs 15mmHg with and without the AirSeal system.

      However, the literature summarized here has never included blinding the intervention of lower
      pneumoperitoneum pressure to the surgeon to determine awareness of pressure and its effect on
      visualization and physician satisfaction.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 3, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 30, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 30, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Three arms including those with pneumoperitoneum pressure of 15mmgHg versus 12mmgHg vs 10 mmHg during laparoscopic or robotic hysterectomy for benign indications.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>Research coordinator will have randomized the patient into one of the 3 arms. The randomized pneumoperitoneum pressure will be set for the surgical procedure and blinded to the surgeon and first assistant, either fellow or resident.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Physician Satisfaction Part 1</measure>
    <time_frame>From completion of surgery to one hour postoperative</time_frame>
    <description>Physician satisfaction questionnaire completed immediately postoperative, 3 questions in length and measured with VAS score (0-5)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Physician Satisfaction Part 2</measure>
    <time_frame>From completion of surgery to one hour postoperative</time_frame>
    <description>Included in the physician satisfaction questionnaire is presumed pneumoperitoneum pressure, measured as 10mmHg, 12mmHg, or 15mmHg (circle one - 10mmHg, 12mmHg, 15mmHg)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Physician Satisfaction Part 3</measure>
    <time_frame>From completion of surgery to one hour postoperative</time_frame>
    <description>Included in the physician satisfaction questionnaire are two yes/no questions on effect of pneumoperitoneum on visualization and operative time (circle one - yes, no)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Postoperative Pain</measure>
    <time_frame>From completion of surgery to 24 hours postoperative</time_frame>
    <description>Self reported pain intensity in PACU (VAS 0-10) first reported and maximum pain score, pain score at 6 hours postoperative, and pain score at 24 hours postoperative</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Postoperative Shoulder Pain</measure>
    <time_frame>From completion of surgery to 24 hours postoperative</time_frame>
    <description>Self reported shoulder pain intensity (VAS 0-10) at 6 hours postoperative and pain score at 24 hours postoperative</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Narcotic usage</measure>
    <time_frame>From completion of surgery to 24 hours postoperative</time_frame>
    <description>Morphine equivalent units in PACU and at 24 hours postoperative</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Length of hospital stay</measure>
    <time_frame>From completion of surgery to hospital discharge time up to 7 days</time_frame>
    <description>Time in minutes of length of stay in hospital</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Patient Satisfaction</measure>
    <time_frame>From completion of surgery to 24 hours postoperative</time_frame>
    <description>Patient satisfaction questionnaire completed 24 hours postoperative over the phone, 2 questions in length, VAS score (0-5) on satisfaction with overall postoperative pain and shoulder postoperative pain</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Intraoperative Respiratory Parameters: Peak inspiratory pressure</measure>
    <time_frame>From start of surgery to end of surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Peak inspiratory pressure</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Intraoperative Respiratory Parameters: Tidal volume</measure>
    <time_frame>From start of surgery to end of surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Tidal volume</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Intraoperative Respiratory Parameters: End tidal CO2</measure>
    <time_frame>From start of surgery to end of surgery</time_frame>
    <description>End tidal CO2</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Hysterectomy</condition>
  <condition>Pneumoperitoneum</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>1. Pneumoperitoneum pressure = 15mmHg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>1. Pneumoperitoneum will be set at 15mmHg</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>2. Pneumoperitoneum pressure = 12mmHg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>2.Pneumoperitoneum will be set at 12mmHg</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>3. Pneumoperitoneum set at 10mmHg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>3. Pneumoperitoneum will be set at 10mmHg</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pneumoperitoneum pressure = 15mmHg</intervention_name>
    <description>Randomized pneumoperitoneum 1</description>
    <arm_group_label>1. Pneumoperitoneum pressure = 15mmHg</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pneumoperitoneum pressure = 12mm Hg</intervention_name>
    <description>Randomized pneumoperitoneum 2</description>
    <arm_group_label>2. Pneumoperitoneum pressure = 12mmHg</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pneumoperitoneum pressure = 10mmHg</intervention_name>
    <description>Randomized pneumoperitoneum 3</description>
    <arm_group_label>3. Pneumoperitoneum set at 10mmHg</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  female patients

          -  greater than or equal to 18 years old

          -  English-speaking

          -  undergoing laparoscopic or robotic total hysterectomy for benign indications by one of
             the two minimally invasive gynecologic surgeons at Banner University Medical Center -
             Phoenix

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  patients with body max index &gt;35

          -  American Society of Anesthesiologists (ASA) score III or IV

          -  preoperative uterine weight estimated to be greater than 500gm (measured by sonography
             and using the following formula: length x width x anteroposterior diameter x 0.52)

          -  patients on chronic opioids for chronic pain (defined as &gt; 3 months regular opioid
             use)

          -  patients who refuse participation in the study

          -  patients who do not provide informed consent
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>99 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Michael Foley, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Banner University Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Rachael Smith, DO</last_name>
    <phone>1-541-601-9106</phone>
    <email>rachael.smith@bannerhealth.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Regina Montero, MSN</last_name>
    <phone>480-239-8697</phone>
    <email>rmontero52@email.arizona.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Banner University Medical Center Phoenix</name>
      <address>
        <city>Phoenix</city>
        <state>Arizona</state>
        <zip>85006</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Regina Montero, MSN</last_name>
      <phone>480-239-8697</phone>
      <email>rmontero@email.arizona.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Elena Young, MS, CCRP</last_name>
      <phone>602-827-9963</phone>
      <email>elenay@email.arizona.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kyle EB, Maheux-Lacroix S, Boutin A, Laberge PY, Lemyre M. Low vs Standard Pressures in Gynecologic Laparoscopy: a Systematic Review. JSLS. 2016 Jan-Mar;20(1). pii: e2015.00113. doi: 10.4293/JSLS.2015.00113. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26955258</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bogani G, Uccella S, Cromi A, Serati M, Casarin J, Pinelli C, Ghezzi F. Low vs standard pneumoperitoneum pressure during laparoscopic hysterectomy: prospective randomized trial. J Minim Invasive Gynecol. 2014 May-Jun;21(3):466-71. doi: 10.1016/j.jmig.2013.12.091. Epub 2013 Dec 25.</citation>
    <PMID>24374246</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sroussi J, Elies A, Rigouzzo A, Louvet N, Mezzadri M, Fazel A, Benifla JL. Low pressure gynecological laparoscopy (7mmHg) with AirSeal(®) System versus a standard insufflation (15mmHg): A pilot study in 60 patients. J Gynecol Obstet Hum Reprod. 2017 Feb;46(2):155-158. doi: 10.1016/j.jogoh.2016.09.003. Epub 2017 Jan 30.</citation>
    <PMID>28403972</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>3. Kim DK, Cheong ILY, Lee GY, Cho JH. Low pressure (8 mm Hg) pneumoperitoneum does not reduce the incidence and severity of postoperative nausea and vomiting (PONV) following gynecologic laparoscopy. Korean J Anesthesiol. 2006.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Topçu HO, Cavkaytar S, Kokanalı K, Guzel AI, Islimye M, Doganay M. A prospective randomized trial of postoperative pain following different insufflation pressures during gynecologic laparoscopy. Eur J Obstet Gynecol Reprod Biol. 2014 Nov;182:81-5. doi: 10.1016/j.ejogrb.2014.09.003. Epub 2014 Sep 16.</citation>
    <PMID>25265495</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nasajiyan N, Javaherfourosh F, Ghomeishi A, Akhondzadeh R, Pazyar F, Hamoonpou N. Comparison of low and standard pressure gas injection at abdominal cavity on postoperative nausea and vomiting in laparoscopic cholecystectomy. Pak J Med Sci. 2014 Sep;30(5):1083-7. doi: 10.12669/pjms.305.5010.</citation>
    <PMID>25225531</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 29, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 11, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 14, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 26, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 26, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 30, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Arizona</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Rachael Bailey Smith</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Rachael Smith, DO Fellow Minimally Invasive Gynecology</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pneumoperitoneum</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>De-identifed individual participant data for all primary and secondary outcomes measures will be made available.</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Statistical Analysis Plan (SAP)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Informed Consent Form (ICF)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Clinical Study Report (CSR)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Analytic Code</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>Data will be available within 6 months of study completion</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>Data access requests will be reviewed by an external independent review panel. Requesters will be required to sign a data access agreement.</ipd_access_criteria>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

