<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04121234</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>070919CUAMM</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04121234</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Critically-Ill Women Admitted to an Obstetric High Dependency Unit in a Resource-Limited Setting</brief_title>
  <official_title>Pidemiology, Outcomes and Risk Factors for Mortality in Critically-Ill Women Admitted to an Obstetric High Dependency Unit in a Resource-Limited Setting</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Doctors with Africa - CUAMM</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Doctors with Africa - CUAMM</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Sierra Leone faces the highest maternal mortality ratio in the world. Despite this extreme
      burden, the potential roles of obstetric critical care and high dependency units (HDUs) in
      this and other resource-limited settings remain scarcely explored. This study investigated
      epidemiology, clinical outcomes and risk factors for mortality in critically-ill parturients
      admitted to an obstetric HDU in a high volume, urban resource-limited maternity hospital.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a retrospective observational study in women admitted to the HDU of Princess
      Christian Maternity Hospital (PCMH), Freetown, Sierra Leone, from 2nd October 2017 to 2nd
      October 2018. The study received ethical approval and waiver of informed consent from the
      Sierra Leone Ethics and Scientific Review Committee (18/12/18).

      A set of predefined variables was assessed at hospital admission, HDU admission and at
      discharge from HDU. The primary data source was the HDU patient chart, with data crosschecked
      with the hospital patient charts and the HDU admission book for quality control purpose. Data
      of hospital deliveries, admissions and mortality were form the hospital register and the
      maternal mortality hospital database. Data were retrospectively collected by a study
      physician (CM) and included: patient demographics; admission date and source; main reason for
      admission in hospital; main reason for admission to the HDU (classified as: haemodynamic
      instability; sepsis; haemorrhage; acute renal failure; neurological impairment; respiratory
      distress; severe malaria; coagulopathy; other diagnoses). These are clinical diagnoses
      included in the hospital checklist to facilitate communication of referral to HDU and are
      thus based on the clinical assessment of the attending physician rather than on a strict
      research definitions.

      Vital signs and treatments collected at admission included body temperature, heart rate,
      respiratory rate, neurological status according to the AVPU scale, systolic and diastolic
      blood pressure, transcutaneous saturation (SpO2). The ratio between SpO2 and fraction of
      inspired oxygen (SpO2/FiO2) was also measured. The obstetric modified early warning score
      (OEWS) was also calculated.

      Specific treatments received at any point during HDU stay were extracted from the patient
      file and included: oxygen supplementation, use of vasopressors, blood transfusions,
      antibiotic therapy, activation of the magnesium protocol for eclamptic seizures prevention
      and hypotensive treatment protocol with hydralazine. Point of care laboratory parameters such
      as capillary lactates levels and haemoglobin were collected when available. Time from PCMH
      admission to HDU admission was calculated. Length of stay and patient outcomes (classified as
      death in HDU, discharge to ward, or transfer to other facility) were reported at discharge.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 1, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">September 30, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 30, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Retrospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Morality in HDU</measure>
    <time_frame>one year</time_frame>
    <description>The primary endpoint was the association between modifiable and non-modifiable factors and mortality during HDU stay. HDU death was defined as death during HDU stay, i.e. from referral to HDU to discharge from HDU.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hospital mortality</measure>
    <time_frame>One year</time_frame>
    <description>Hospital mortality was death during the whole hospital stay.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Lenght of stay</measure>
    <time_frame>One year</time_frame>
    <description>Time between the hdu admission and the hdu discharge, in days.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>OEWS at the admission</measure>
    <time_frame>one year</time_frame>
    <description>coded as: red, yellow, green</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>reasons of admission</measure>
    <time_frame>One Year</time_frame>
    <description>classified as: haemodynamic instability; sepsis; haemorrhage; acute renal failure; neurological impairment; respiratory distress; severe malaria; coagulopathy; other diagnoses</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time of admission</measure>
    <time_frame>One year</time_frame>
    <description>Night/day and Working days/weeknd</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Treatments received</measure>
    <time_frame>One year</time_frame>
    <description>oxygen supplementation (yes/no), use of vasopressors (yes/no), blood transfusions (yes/no), antibiotic therapy (yes/no), activation of the magnesium protocol for eclamptic seizures prevention (yes/no) and hypotensive treatment protocol with hydralazine during the stay (yes/no).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">523</enrollment>
  <condition>Maternal Death</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Exposure: &quot; being admitted to HDU with a red code to OEWS&quot;</intervention_name>
    <description>High Dependency Unit, a set of predefined variables was assessed at hospital admission, HDU admission and at discharge from HDU with the aim to investigate epidemiology, clinical outcomes and risk factors for mortality in critically-ill parturients admitted to an obstetric HDU in a high volume, urban resource-limited maternity hospital</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        All women admitted at HDU of the PCMH from the 2nd October 2017 to the 2nd October 2018.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  All women admitted at HDU of the PCMH from the 2nd October 2017 to the 2nd October
             2018.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  none
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <gender_based>Yes</gender_based>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Princess Christian Maternity Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Freetown</city>
        <country>Sierra Leone</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Sierra Leone</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 7, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 8, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 9, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 8, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 8, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 10, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Doctors with Africa - CUAMM</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Claudia Marotta</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>MD, MPH</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>High dependency unit; critical care; obstetric critical care; maternal mortality.</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Maternal Death</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

