<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04129554</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CR108679</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>73763989PAHPB2002</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>2019-002674-31</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04129554</nct_id>
    <nct_alias>NCT04288310</nct_alias>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study of JNJ 73763989+JNJ 56136379+Nucleos(t)Ide Analog (NA) Regimen Compared to NA Alone in e Antigen Negative Virologically Suppressed Participants With Chronic Hepatitis B Virus Infection</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized, Double Blind, Placebo-controlled Phase 2b Study to Evaluate Efficacy, Pharmacokinetics, and Safety of 48-week Study Intervention With JNJ 73763989+JNJ 56136379+Nucleos(t)Ide Analog (NA) Regimen Compared to NA Alone in e Antigen Negative Virologically Suppressed Participants With Chronic Hepatitis B Virus Infection</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Janssen Sciences Ireland UC</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Janssen Sciences Ireland UC</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>Yes</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to evaluate the efficacy of 48-week study intervention with
      JNJ-73763989+JNJ-56136379+nucleos(t)ide analog (NA) regimen compared to NA alone assessed by
      HBsAg levels. This study is part of HepB Wings Platform Trial (PLATFORMPAHPB2001).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Hepatitis B virus (HBV) is a small deoxyribonucleic acid (DNA) virus that infects the liver
      and can cause either acute or chronic infection. It consists of a so-called nucleocapsid in
      which viral DNA is packed with hepatitis B core protein (HBc) and membranous envelope
      containing hepatitis B surface antigen (HBsAg). Chronic HBV infection may lead to serious
      illnesses like cirrhosis and hepatocellular carcinoma (HCC). Oral treatment with NAs is
      effective at suppressing viral DNA formation and lowering virus concentration in blood to
      levels below lower limit of quantification (LLOQ). JNJ-73763989 is a liver-targeted antiviral
      therapeutic for subcutaneous injection designed to treat chronic HBV infection via
      ribonucleic acid interference mechanism but rarely lead to functional cure defined as
      sustained loss of HBs Ag and HBV DNA in serum. JNJ-56136379 is an orally administered capsid
      assembly modulator that is being developed for treatment of chronic HBV infection. The aim of
      study is to evaluate efficacy of 48-week study intervention with JNJ-3989+JNJ-6379+NA regimen
      compared to NA alone, assessed by HBsAg seroclearance at Week 72 (i.e., 24 weeks after
      completion of all study interventions at Week 48) without restarting NA treatment in HBeAg
      negative virologically suppressed chronic hepatitis B (CHB) infected participants who
      received NA treatment for at least 2 years prior to screening. The study will be 2.3 years
      and will be conducted in 3 phases: a screening phase (4 weeks), a study intervention phase
      (48 weeks), and a follow-up phase (48 weeks). Safety will be evaluated by AEs including AEs
      of special interest to any of the study interventions, clinical laboratory tests, ECGs, vital
      signs, and physical examinations.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 6, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 15, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 31, 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Participants with Hepatitis B Surface Antigen (HBsAg) Seroclearance at Week 72 (24 weeks after completion of all study interventions at Week 48) Without Restarting NA Treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 72</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of participants with HBsAg seroclearance at week 72 (24 weeks after completion of all study interventions at Week 48) without restarting nucleos(t)ide analog (NA) treatment will be reported.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants with Adverse Events (AEs) and Serious AEs</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 102 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>An AE is any untoward medical occurrence in a clinical study participant administered a medicinal (investigational or non investigational) product. An AE does not necessarily have a causal relationship with the intervention. A SAE is an AE resulting in any of the following outcomes or deemed significant for any other reason: death; initial or prolonged inpatient hospitalization; life-threatening experience (immediate risk of dying); persistent or significant disability/incapacity; congenital anomaly.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants with Abnormalities in Clinical Laboratory Tests</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 102 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Number of participants with abnormalities in clinically significant laboratory findings (urine chemistry and renal biomarkers) will be reported.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Participants with HBsAg Seroclearance at Week 48</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 48</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of participants with HBsAg seroclearance at week 48 will be reported.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Participants with HBV DNA less than (&lt;) Lower Limit of Quantification (LLOQ) at Week 48</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 48</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of participants with hepatitis B virus (HBV) deoxyribonucleic acid (DNA) &lt;LLOQ at week 48 will be reported.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Participants with HBsAg Seroclearance at Week 96 (48 Weeks After Completion of all Study Intervention) Without Restarting NA Treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Week 96</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of participants with HBsAg seroclearance up to week 96 (48 weeks after completion of all study intervention) without restarting NA treatment will be reported.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Participants with (Sustained) Reduction, Suppression, and/or Seroclearance</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Week 96</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of participants with (sustained) reduction, suppression, and/or seroclearance considering single and multiple markers (such as hepatitis B surface antigen [HBsAg], hepatitis B e antigen [HBeAg], HBV DNA and alanine aminotransferase [ALT]) will be reported.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to Achieve First HBsAg Seroclearance</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Week 96</time_frame>
    <description>Time to achieve first HBsAg seroclearance will be reported.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of participants with HBV DNA levels with &lt;LLOQ</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Week 96</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of participants with HBV DNA levels with lower limit of quantification (&lt;LLOQ) assay will be reported.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Participants with Virologic Breakthrough</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Week 48</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of participants with virologic breakthrough defined as confirmed on-treatment HBV DNA increase by greater than (&gt;)1 log10 IU/mL from nadir level or confirmed on treatment level &gt;200 IU/mL in participants who had HBV DNA level below &lt;LLOQ of the HBV DNA assay will be reported.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Participants with Flares</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to week 96</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of participants with flares (virologic, biochemical and clinical flares) will be reported.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Participants Requiring NA Re-Treatment During Follow-up</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to week 96</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of participants requiring NA re-treatment during follow-up will be reported.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Association Between Baseline Characteristics and On-Treatment Viral Blood Markers with Selected Off-Treatment Responses</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to week 72</time_frame>
    <description>Identification of baseline characteristics and on treatment viral blood markers (e.g., HBV DNA, HBsAg, ALT) associated with sustained off-treatment responses will be reported.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Area Under the Plasma Concentration-time Curve over the Dosing Interval (tau) at Steady-state (AUCtau,ss) of JNJ-73763989</measure>
    <time_frame>Days 1, 29, 85, 169 and 337</time_frame>
    <description>The AUC (tau,ss) is the area under the plasma concentration time curve observed during a dosing interval (tau) at steady state.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Area Under the Plasma Concentration-time Curve over the Dosing Interval (tau) at Steady-state (AUCtau,ss) of JNJ-56136379</measure>
    <time_frame>Days 1, 29, 85, 169 and 337</time_frame>
    <description>The AUC (tau,ss) is the area under the plasma concentration time curve observed during a dosing interval (tau) at steady state.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Area Under the Plasma Concentration-time Curve over the Dosing Interval (tau) at Steady-state (AUCtau,ss) of NA</measure>
    <time_frame>Days 1, 29, 85, 169 and 337</time_frame>
    <description>The AUC (tau,ss) is the area under the plasma concentration time curve observed during a dosing interval (tau) at steady state.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">120</enrollment>
  <condition>Hepatitis B, Chronic</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>JNJ-73763989+ JNJ-56136379+ NA</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will receive fixed dose of JNJ-73763989 subcutaneous injection once every 4 weeks along with fixed dose of JNJ-56136379 tablet once daily and nucleos(t)ide analog (NA) treatment (either entecavir [ETV], tenofovir disoproxil fumarate [TDF], or tenofovir alafenamide [TAF]) once daily up to 48 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo for JNJ-73763989+ Placebo for JNJ-56136379+ NA</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will receive matching placebo for JNJ-73763989 subcutaneous injection once every 4 weeks with matching placebo for JNJ-56136379 once daily and NA treatment (either ETV, TDF or TAF) once daily up to 48 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>JNJ-73763989</intervention_name>
    <description>JNJ-73763989 injection will be administered subcutaneously once every 4 weeks up to 48 weeks.</description>
    <arm_group_label>JNJ-73763989+ JNJ-56136379+ NA</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>JNJ-56136379</intervention_name>
    <description>JNJ-56136379 tablets will be administered orally once daily up to 48 weeks.</description>
    <arm_group_label>JNJ-73763989+ JNJ-56136379+ NA</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo for JNJ-73763989</intervention_name>
    <description>Matching placebo for JNJ-73763989 will be administered as subcutaneous injection up to 48 weeks.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo for JNJ-73763989+ Placebo for JNJ-56136379+ NA</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo for JNJ-56136379</intervention_name>
    <description>Matching placebo for JNJ-56136379 tablets will be administered orally up to 48 weeks.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo for JNJ-73763989+ Placebo for JNJ-56136379+ NA</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Entecavir (ETV) monohydrate</intervention_name>
    <description>ETV tablet will be administered orally once daily up to 48 weeks as NA treatment.</description>
    <arm_group_label>JNJ-73763989+ JNJ-56136379+ NA</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo for JNJ-73763989+ Placebo for JNJ-56136379+ NA</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Tenofovir disoproxil fumarate (TDF)</intervention_name>
    <description>TDF will be administered orally once daily up to 48 weeks as NA treatment.</description>
    <arm_group_label>JNJ-73763989+ JNJ-56136379+ NA</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo for JNJ-73763989+ Placebo for JNJ-56136379+ NA</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Tenofovir alafenamide (TAF)</intervention_name>
    <description>TAF will be administered orally once daily up to 48 weeks as NA treatment.</description>
    <arm_group_label>JNJ-73763989+ JNJ-56136379+ NA</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo for JNJ-73763989+ Placebo for JNJ-56136379+ NA</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Medically stable based on physical examination, medical history, vital signs,
             electrocardiogram (ECG) at screening

          -  Chronic hepatitis B virus (HBV) infection with documentation at least 6 months prior
             to screening

          -  Hepatitis B e (antigen) (HBeAg)-negative on stable nucleotide analogue (NA) treatment
             for at least 24 months prior to screening

          -  Hepatitis B surface antigen (HBsAg) greater than (&gt;) 100 International Units per
             Milliliter (IU/mL) at screening

          -  Body mass index (BMI) between 18.0 and 35 kilogram per meter square (kg/m^2), extremes
             included

          -  Highly effective contraceptive measures in place for female participants of
             childbearing potential or male participants with female partners of childbearing
             potential

          -  Liver fibrosis stage 0-2 (Metavir) or Fibroscan less than (&lt;) 9 Kilopascal (kPa) at
             screening

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Evidence of infection with hepatitis A, C, D or E virus infection or evidence of human
             immunodeficiency, virus type 1 (HIV-1) or HIV-2 infection at screening

          -  History or evidence of clinical signs/symptoms of hepatic decompensation including but
             not limited to: portal hypertension, ascites, hepatic encephalopathy, esophageal
             varices or any laboratory abnormalities indicating a reduced liver function as defined
             in the protocol

          -  Evidence of liver disease of non-HBV etiology

          -  History or signs of cirrhosis or portal hypertension (nodules, no smooth liver
             contour, no normal portal vein, spleen size ≥12 cm) or signs of hepatocellular
             carcinoma (HCC)

          -  Significant laboratory abnormalities as defined in the protocol at screening

          -  Participants with a history of malignancy within 5 years before screening

          -  Abnormal sinus rhythm or ECG parameters at screening as defined in the protocol

          -  History of or current cardiac arrhythmia or history or clinical evidence of
             significant or unstable cardiac disease

          -  Participants with any current or previous illness for which, in the opinion of the
             investigator and/or sponsor, participation would not be in the best interest of the
             participant

          -  History of or current clinically significant skin disease or drug rash

          -  Known allergies, hypersensitivity, or intolerance to JNJ-73763989 and JNJ-56136379 or
             their excipients or to placebo content

          -  Contraindications to the use of entecavir (ETV), tenofovir disoproxil fumarate (TDF),
             or tenofovir alafenamide (TAF) per local prescribing information

          -  Participants who have taken any therapies disallowed per protocol
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Janssen Sciences Ireland UC Clinical Trial</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Janssen Sciences Ireland UC</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Study Contact</last_name>
    <phone>844-434-4210</phone>
    <email>JNJ.CT@sylogent.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>SGS Clinical Pharmacology Unit (located in ZNA Stuivenberg)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Antwerpen</city>
        <zip>2060</zip>
        <country>Belgium</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cliniques Universitaires Saint-Luc</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bruxelles</city>
        <zip>1200</zip>
        <country>Belgium</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UZ Antwerpen</name>
      <address>
        <city>Edegem</city>
        <zip>2650</zip>
        <country>Belgium</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Universitair Ziekenhuis Gent</name>
      <address>
        <city>Gent</city>
        <zip>9000</zip>
        <country>Belgium</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UZ Leuven</name>
      <address>
        <city>Leuven</city>
        <zip>3000</zip>
        <country>Belgium</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hôpital Beaujon</name>
      <address>
        <city>Clichy</city>
        <zip>92110</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hopital de La Croix Rousse</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lyon</city>
        <zip>69004</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hopital Saint Joseph</name>
      <address>
        <city>Marseille</city>
        <zip>13008</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hopital Cochin</name>
      <address>
        <city>Paris</city>
        <zip>75014</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Chu Rennes - Hopital Pontchaillou</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rennes</city>
        <zip>35033</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CHU Nancy Brabois</name>
      <address>
        <city>Vandoeuvre les Nancy</city>
        <zip>54511</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hopital Paul Brousse</name>
      <address>
        <city>Villejuif</city>
        <zip>94800</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>EPIMED GmbH</name>
      <address>
        <city>Berlin</city>
        <zip>12157</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Universitatsklinikum Essen</name>
      <address>
        <city>Essen</city>
        <zip>45147</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Universitätsklinikum Johann Wolfgang Goethe- Universität Frankfurt Medizinische Klinik 1</name>
      <address>
        <city>Frankfurt</city>
        <zip>60590</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Universitatsklinikum Freiburg</name>
      <address>
        <city>Freiburg</city>
        <zip>79106</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>ICH Study Center GmbH &amp; Co. KG</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hamburg</city>
        <zip>20146</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hamburg</city>
        <zip>D-20246</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Medizinische Hochschule Hannover</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hannover</city>
        <zip>30625</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Universitatsklinikum Leipzig</name>
      <address>
        <city>Leipzig</city>
        <zip>4103</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Universitätsmedizin der Johannes Gutenberg-Universität Mainz</name>
      <address>
        <city>Mainz</city>
        <zip>55121</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Azienda Ospedaliera Universitaria Policlinico G. Martino</name>
      <address>
        <city>Messina</city>
        <zip>98124</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Irccs Ospedale Maggiore Di Milano</name>
      <address>
        <city>Milano</city>
        <zip>20122</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Azienda Ospedaliero-Universitaria di Modena, Ospedale di Baggiovara</name>
      <address>
        <city>Modena</city>
        <zip>41126</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Azienda Ospedaliero Universitaria Pisana</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pisa</city>
        <zip>56124</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Universita degli Studi di Roma 'La Sapienza' - Umberto I Policlinico di Roma</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rome</city>
        <zip>00161</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Wojewodzki Szpital Obserwacyjno-Zakazny im. Tadeusza Browicza w Bydgoszczy</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bydgoszcz</city>
        <zip>85-030</zip>
        <country>Poland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Neutrum Lekarze M.Hlebowicz i Partnerzy spolka partnerska</name>
      <address>
        <city>Gdansk</city>
        <zip>80-462</zip>
        <country>Poland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>ID Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Myslowice</city>
        <zip>41-400</zip>
        <country>Poland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>SP ZOZ Wroclawskie Centrum Zdrowia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Wroclaw</city>
        <zip>50-136</zip>
        <country>Poland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hosp. Clinic I Provincial de Barcelona</name>
      <address>
        <city>Barcelona</city>
        <zip>8028</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hosp. Univ. Vall D'Hebron</name>
      <address>
        <city>Barcelona</city>
        <zip>8035</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hosp. Univ. 12 de Octubre</name>
      <address>
        <city>Madrid</city>
        <zip>28041</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hosp. Univ. Pta. de Hierro Majadahonda</name>
      <address>
        <city>Madrid</city>
        <zip>28222</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hosp. Univ. Marques de Valdecilla</name>
      <address>
        <city>Santander</city>
        <zip>39008</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hosp. Gral. Univ. Valencia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Valencia</city>
        <zip>46014</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Queen Elizabeth Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Birmingham</city>
        <zip>B15 2TH</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>North Manchester General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Crumpsall</city>
        <zip>M8 5RB</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Glasgow Royal Infirmary</name>
      <address>
        <city>Glasgow</city>
        <zip>G31 2ER</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Grahame Hayton Unit</name>
      <address>
        <city>London</city>
        <zip>E1 1BB</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Kings College Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>London</city>
        <zip>SE5 9RF</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>St George's, University of London and St George's University Hospitals NHS Foundation Trust</name>
      <address>
        <city>London</city>
        <zip>SW17 0RE</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Belgium</country>
    <country>France</country>
    <country>Germany</country>
    <country>Italy</country>
    <country>Poland</country>
    <country>Spain</country>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://pam.sylogent.com/cr/CR108679</url>
    <description>To learn how to participate in this trial please click here.</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>June 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 15, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 15, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 17, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 9, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 9, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 11, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis A</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis B</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis B, Chronic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Herpesviridae Infections</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Virus Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Tenofovir</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Entecavir</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>The data sharing policy of the Janssen Pharmaceutical Companies of Johnson &amp; Johnson is available at www.janssen.com/clinical-trials/transparency.
As noted on this site, requests for access to the study data can be submitted through Yale Open Data Access (YODA) Project site at yoda.yale.edu</ipd_description>
    <ipd_url>https://www.janssen.com/clinical-trials/transparency</ipd_url>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

