<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04124497</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>DEDALO</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04124497</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Trial for Relapsed and Relapsed/Refractory Multiple Myeloma Patients</brief_title>
  <acronym>DPd</acronym>
  <official_title>Daratumumab, Pomalidomide and Dexamethasone for Del(17p) Positive Relapsed and Relapsed/Refractory Multiple Myeloma Patients [DEDALO]</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Fondazione Neoplasie Sangue Onlus</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Fondazione Neoplasie Sangue Onlus</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Multiple myeloma (MM) with chromosome 17 deletion (del(17p) represents one of the most
      dangerous genetic variant of this disease, since it is associated with a high level of
      genomic instability. Del(17p) is present in approximately 10% of patients at diagnosis, and
      its frequency increases with disease evolution. The adverse prognosis of del(17p) has been
      observed in patients treated with conventional chemotherapy and new drugs. Only very few
      studies have suggested an advantage in treating del(17p) MM patients with specific therapies.
      In particular, several recent trials combining lenalidomide plus dexamethasone with a new
      agent, suggested that high risk cytogenetics patients may benefit from newest generation
      drugs. Yet, in all studies, outcome of patients with high risk genetic features have been
      derived from subgroup analyses, with all the limitations of this approach. To date no trial
      has been designed with the specific aim to test genotype-adapted therapies.

      The objective of the present study is to evaluate the combination of
      daratumumab-pomalidomide-dexamethasone (DPd) in relapsed or relapsed/refractory MM patients
      harboring del(17p).

      Treatment of relapsed or relapsed/refractory MM patients harbouring del(17p) is a relevant
      unmet medical need. A clinical trial designed to test a tailored treatment for this patient
      population would be a major improvement. In this perspective the combination DPd seems
      attractive since:

        -  both daratumumab and pomalidomide are therapies not interfering with DNA replication,
           thus not increasing the intrinsic genomic instability of del(17p) plasma cells.

        -  the POLLUX study has shown that daratumumab in combination with lenalidomide is highly
           effective in relapsed and relapsed/refractory MM patients.10

        -  the IFM 2010-02 trial has suggested that pomalidomide may be effective in del(17p)
           patients.

        -  the DPd combination has been successfully tested in MM patients with advanced disease.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Patients will undergo screening for protocol eligibility within 28 days (4 weeks) of
      enrolment.

      After providing written informed consent to participate in the study, patients will be
      evaluated for study eligibility. It is to note that patients can be enrolled based on the
      presence of del(17p), as per center evaluation. However, the presence of del(17p) should be
      confirmed by the central laboratory (University of Torino laboratory), which will perform the
      test in 5 working days.

      After registration, subjects who meet all the inclusion criteria will be treated according to
      the protocol, only after the presence of del(17p) has been confirmed by the central
      laboratory.

      Treatment period includes administration of 28-day cycles of treatment with DPd until any
      sign of progression or intolerance.

      The response will be assessed after each cycle. The LTFU period will start after development
      of confirmed progressive disease (PD) or treatment interruption due to toxicity. All patients
      are to be followed for survival during the LTFU period every 3 months via telephone or office
      visit.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 1, 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 1, 2024</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Minimal residual disease (MRD)</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Molecular minimal residual disease (MRD) 10-5 negativity rate assessed by means of next-generation sequencing (ClonoSEQ assay) in patients attaining a complete remission in the first year of treatment.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression-free survival (PFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Number of months from the date of randomization to the date of first observation of PD, or death from any cause as an event.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall response rate (ORR)</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Overall response rate will include complete response (CR), very good partial response (VGPR) and partial response (PR) using the International Response Criteria. Responders are defined as subjects with at least a PR.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression-free survival 2 (PFS2)</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Time from randomization to objective tumor progression on next-line treatment or death from any cause.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of response (DOR)</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Time between first documentation of response and PD. Responders without disease progression will be censored either at the time of lost to FU, at the time of death due to other cause than PD, or at the end of the study.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival (OS)</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Time between randomization and death. Subjects who die will be censored at time of death as an event, regardless cause of death.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety as incidence of toxicities</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Severity of the toxicities will be graded according to the NCI CTC v.5 whenever possible. Laboratory data will be graded according to NCI CTC v.5 severity grade.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to next therapy (TNT)</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Time to next therapy will be measured from the date of randomization to the date of next anti-myeloma therapy. Death due to any cause before starting therapy will be considered an event.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of patients with negative MRD and survival indices</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <description>MRD negativity rate and survival might significantly change in particular subgroups of patients, that are defined on prognostic factors [ISS stage, additional cytogenetic abnormalities, previous treatment, presence of del(17p)]. Hence, subgroup analyses will be conducted.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">45</enrollment>
  <condition>Multiple Myeloma</condition>
  <condition>Deletion 17P Syndrome</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>DPd</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Therapy consists in cycles of the DPd combination as follows:
Pomalidomide 4 mg once daily on days 1-21;
Oral or intravenous dexamethasone 40 mg/day (≤ 75 years old) or 20 mg/ day (&gt;75 years old) on days 1, 8, 15 and 22;
Daratumumab 16 mg/kg intravenously at following schedule:
cycle 1 and 2: days 1, 8, 15, and 22
cycle 3 through 6: days 1, and 15
from cycle 7 until disease progression: day 1.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Daratumumab</intervention_name>
    <description>Daratumumab 16 mg/kg intravenously at following schedule:
cycle 1 and 2: days 1, 8, 15, and 22
cycle 3 through 6: days 1, and 15
from cycle 7 until disease progression: day 1.</description>
    <arm_group_label>DPd</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pomalidomide</intervention_name>
    <description>4 mg once daily on days 1-21</description>
    <arm_group_label>DPd</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Dexamethasone</intervention_name>
    <description>Oral or intravenous dexamethasone 40 mg/day (≤ 75 years old) or 20 mg/ day (&gt;75 years old) on days 1, 8, 15 and 22</description>
    <arm_group_label>DPd</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patient has given voluntary written informed consent

          -  Subject must be at least 18 years of age.

          -  Subject must have documented MM.

          -  Subject must have del(17p) observed by FISH in at least 10% of bone marrow plasma
             cells at any time of MM history.

          -  Subject must have serum monoclonal paraprotein (M-protein) level &gt;=0.5 g/dL or urine
             M-protein, level &gt;=200 mg/24 hours, or light chain MM, or serum immunoglobulin free
             light chain ≥10 mg/dL and abnormal serum immunoglobulin kappa lambda free light chain
             ratio.

          -  Subject must have received at least 1 and no more than 3 prior lines of therapy for
             MM.

          -  Subject must have received at least 2 consecutive cycles of lenalidomide in a previous
             line of therapy.

          -  Subject must have achieved a response (PR or better) to at least one prior regimen.

          -  Subjects must have either refractory or relapsed and refractory disease defined as
             documented disease progression during or within 60 days of completing their last
             myeloma therapy.

          -  Subject must have an ECOG Performance Status score of 0, 1, or 2.

          -  Subject must have the following laboratory values:

               -  Platelet count &gt;=50 x 109/L (≥30 x 109 /L if myeloma involvement in the bone
                  marrow is &gt; 50%) within 14 days prior to drug administration).

               -  Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) &gt;= 1 x 109/L without the use of growth factors.

               -  Corrected serum calcium &lt;=14 mg/dL (3.5 mmol/L)

               -  Alanine transaminase (ALT): &lt;= 3 x the upper limit normal (ULN).

               -  Total bilirubin: &lt;= 2 x the ULN.

               -  Calculated or measured creatinine clearance: &gt;= 15 mL/minute

          -  Females of childbearing potential (FBCP) must follow the Pregnancy Prevention Plan and
             use a highly effective and an additional barrier contraception method simultaneously
             for 28 days before starting pomalidomide, during treatment and dose interruptions, for
             at least 28 days after the last dose of pomalidomide and 3 months after the last dose
             of daratumumab Males must use an effective barrier method of contraception if sexually
             active with FCBP for at least 28 days before starting pomalidomide, during the
             treatment and dose interruptions, for at least 28 days after the last dose of
             pomalidomide and 3 months after the last dose of daratumumab. Male subjects must agree
             to refrain from sperm donation for at least 3 months after the last dose of
             daratumumab.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Subject has received daratumumab or other anti-CD38 monoclonal antibody previously.

          -  Subject's disease shows evidence of refractoriness or intolerance to pomalidomide. If
             previously treated with a pomalidomide-containing regimen, the subject is excluded if
             he or she:

               -  Discontinued due to any adverse event related to prior pomalidomide treatment, or

               -  If, at any time point, the subject was refractory to any dose of pomalidomide.

        Refractory to pomalidomide is defined either:

          -  Subjects whose disease progresses within 60 days of pomalidomide; or

          -  Subjects whose disease is nonresponsive while on lenalidomide. Nonresponsive disease
             is defined as either failure to achieve at least an MR or development of PD while on
             pomalidomide.

               -  Subject has received anti-myeloma treatment within 2 weeks or 5 pharmacokinetic
                  half-lives of the treatment, whichever is longer, before the date of
                  randomization.

               -  Subjects who received an allogeneic bone marrow or allogeneic peripheral blood
                  stem cell transplant less than 12 months prior to initiation of study treatment
                  and who have not discontinued immunosuppressive treatment for at least 16 weeks
                  prior to initiation of study treatment and are currently dependent on such
                  treatment.

               -  Subjects unable or unwilling to undergo antithrombotic prophylactic treatment.

               -  Subject has a history of malignancy (other than multiple myeloma) within 3 years
                  before the date of randomization (exceptions are squamous and basal cell
                  carcinomas of the skin and carcinoma in situ of the cervix, or malignancy that in
                  the opinion of the investigator, in agreement with the medical monitor, is
                  considered cured with minimal risk of recurrence within 3 years).

               -  Subject has known chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD) (defined as a
                  forced expiratory volume in 1 second (FEV1) &lt;60% of predicted normal), asthma, or
                  a history of asthma within the last 2 years. Subjects with known or suspected
                  COPD must have a forced expiratory volume (FEV) test during Screening.

               -  Subject is known to be seropositive for human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) or
                  hepatitis B (defined by a positive test for hepatitis B surface antigen [HBsAg]
                  or antibodies to hepatitis B surface and core antigens [anti-HBs and anti-HBc,
                  respectively]) or hepatitis C (anti-HCV antibody positive or HCV-RNA quantitation
                  positive).

               -  Subject has any concurrent medical condition or disease (eg, active systemic
                  infection) that is likely to interfere with study procedures or results, or that
                  in the opinion of the investigator would constitute a hazard for participating in
                  this study.

               -  Subject has clinically significant cardiac disease, including:

          -  Myocardial infarction within 6 months before Cycle 1, Day 1, or unstable or

          -  uncontrolled disease/condition related to or affecting cardiac function (eg, unstable
             angina, congestive heart failure, New York Heart Association Class III-IV)

          -  Cardiac arrhythmia (Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events [CTCAE] Version 4
             Grade 2 or higher) or clinically significant ECG abnormalities.

          -  Screening 12-lead ECG showing a baseline QT interval as corrected by Fridericia's
             formula (QTcF) &gt;500 msec.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>FO.NE.SA.Onlus</name>
      <address>
        <city>Torino</city>
        <zip>10125</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Italy</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 2, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 10, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 11, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 10, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 10, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 11, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Multiple Myeloma</keyword>
  <keyword>Monoclonal antibody</keyword>
  <keyword>Immunomodulating agents</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Multiple Myeloma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms, Plasma Cell</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Dexamethasone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pomalidomide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Daratumumab</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

