<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03793829</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>16-010561</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>W81XWH-16-1-0266</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>W81XWH-16-1-0265</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03793829</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Neoadjuvant Multi-epitope HER2 Peptide Vaccine in Patients With HER2-expressing DCIS</brief_title>
  <acronym>HER2Vaccine</acronym>
  <official_title>A Phase IB Trial of Neoadjuvant Multi-epitope HER2 Peptide Vaccine in Patients With HER2-expressing DCIS</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Mayo Clinic</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Mayo Clinic</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This interventional clinical study will examine the safety and efficacy of a degenerate
      subdominant HER2 specific helper T cell epitope vaccine (H2NVAC) in patients with
      HER2-expressing ductal carcinoma in situ (DCIS). The ultimate goal of this vaccine is to
      prevent future invasive breast cancer among patients who are diagnosed with DCIS. However,
      the focus of this study is safety and efficacy.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is an interventional clinical study examining the safety and efficacy of a degenerate
      subdominant HER2 specific helper T cell epitope vaccine (H2NVAC) in patients with
      HER2-expressing ductal carcinoma in situ (DCIS). The ultimate goal of this vaccine is to
      prevent future invasive breast cancer among patients who are diagnosed with DCIS. However,
      the focus of this study is safety and efficacy. The vaccine consists of 4 peptide epitopes
      (15-18 amino acids in length) derived from the HER2 protein. These peptides are derived from
      HER2 and were selected based upon their recognition by lymphocytes from women with prior
      HER-2 positive breast cancer. To enhance immunity, the peptides are admixed with the adjuvant
      GM-CSF. Patients will receive four bi-monthly vaccinations followed by surgery as diagrammed
      below; observation includes periodic blood draws to assess toxicity and immune responses, as
      well as periodic echocardiography to assess left ventricular ejection fraction.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Biological/Vaccine</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse Events</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Number of adverse events reported</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Dose limiting toxicities</measure>
    <time_frame>14 days post vaccination, 2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Measured using criteria from the National Cancer Institute's Cancer Therapy Evaluation Program (CTEP) Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events, version 4.0 with Grade ≥ 2 allergic reaction, Grade ≥ 2 autoimmune reaction, Grade ≥ 2 injection site reaction manifesting as an ulceration, Grade ≥ 2 neurologic problem, Grade 3+ toxicity, or any one of following changes in LVEF</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">43</enrollment>
  <condition>DCIS</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>GM-CSF and H2NVAC vaccine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>GM-CSF Dose and route: 125 mcg admixed with vaccine; intradermal injection Every 14 days ± 2 days for a maximum of 4 cycles H2NVAC vaccine 4 peptides, at dose level as shown below, admixed with GM-CSF; intradermal injection. Every 14 days ± 2 days for a maximum of 4 cycles</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>(H2NVAC)</intervention_name>
    <description>Intervention: Biological/Vaccine: (H2NVAC) Dose levels: In phase I, there are 3 dose levels of H2NVAC Nine patients will be treated in each dose level starting dose level 1. a total of 27 patients will be enrolled in this phase.
Dose Levels H2NVAC Dose 1.500 µg/peptide 2.1000 µg/peptide 3.1500 µg/peptide
The dose with acceptable safety and tolerability &amp; maximum immune response will be used in the expansion cohort of this trial. A total of 16 additional patients will be enrolled in this portion of this trial.
Dose limiting toxicities (DLT) are defined to be any of the following criteria using the National Cancer Institute's Cancer Therapy Evaluation Program (CTEP) Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events, version 4.0</description>
    <arm_group_label>GM-CSF and H2NVAC vaccine</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Dose levels</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Eligibility

        Criteria:

        Inclusion Criteria

          -  Female age ≥ 18 years.

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status ≤ 2

          -  Patients must not have received any prior therapy for current DCIS.

          -  Note: Patients who received tamoxifen or raloxifene or another agent for prevention of
             breast cancer may be included as long as the patient has discontinued the treatment at
             least 2 months prior to baseline study biopsy.

          -  Note: Concurrent use of endocrine therapy during the vaccination/preoperative period
             is not allowed. However, standard adjuvant endocrine therapy with tamoxifen or
             aromatase inhibitor after completion of vaccination and surgery is allowed.

          -  Patients must be agreeable to have an additional research biopsy prior to the first
             vaccination.

          -  Patients must have evidence of at least 1.0 cm of disease extent based on mammogram or
             ultrasound imaging.

          -  Patients must have adequate organ and marrow function less than or equal to 28 days
             prior to Pre-Registrationas defined below:

          -  Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) ≥ 1500/mm3

          -  Platelet count ≥ 75,000/mm3

          -  Hemoglobin ≥ 9.0 g/dL

          -  Creatinine ≤2 x ULN

          -  SGOT (AST) ≤ 2 x ULN

          -  Albumin ≥ 3 g/dL

          -  Negative serum pregnancy test done ≤ 7 days prior to Pre-registration, for women of
             childbearing potential only.

          -  Willing to employ adequate contraception from the time of Pre-registration through 6
             months after the final vaccine cycle.

          -  Note: Adequate contraception methods include birth control pills, barrier device,
             intrauterine device.

          -  Capable of understanding the investigative nature, potential risks, and benefits of
             the study.

          -  Capable of providing valid informed consent.

          -  Willing to return to enrolling institution for all study visits (immunizations, blood
             draws, etc).

          -  Willing to provide blood samples for correlative research purposes

          -  Willing to receive a tetanus vaccination if subject has not had one within the past
             year.

        Exclusion Criteria

          -  Any of the following because this study involves an investigational agent whose
             genotoxic, mutagenic and teratogenic effects on the developing fetus and newborn are
             unknown:

          -  Pregnant women

          -  Nursing women unwilling to stop breast feeding

          -  Women of child bearing potential who are unwilling to employ adequate contraception
             from the time of registration through 6 months after the final vaccine cycle.

          -  Co-morbid systemic illnesses or other severe concurrent disease which, in the judgment
             of the investigator, would make the patient inappropriate for entry into this study or
             interfere significantly with the proper assessment of safety and toxicity of the
             prescribed regimens.

          -  Immunocompromised patients including patients known to be HIV positive or those on
             chronic steroids.

          -  Note: Must be off systemic steroids greater than or equal to 90 days prior to
             Pre-registration. However, topical steroids, inhalants or steroid eye drops are
             permitted.

          -  Uncontrolled intercurrent illness including, but not limited to, ongoing or active
             infection, symptomatic congestive heart failure, unstable angina pectoris, cardiac
             arrhythmia, or psychiatric illness/social situations that would limit compliance with
             study requirements.

          -  Uncontrolled acute or chronic medical conditions including, but not limited to the
             following:

          -  Active infection requiring antibiotics

          -  Congestive heart failure with New York Heart Association class III or IV; moderate to
             severe objective evidence of cardiovascular disease

          -  Myocardial infarction or stroke less than or equal to 6 months prior to
             Pre-Registration

          -  Receiving any other investigational agent.

          -  Other active malignancy at time of Pre-registration or less than or equal to the last
             three years prior to Pre-registration. EXCEPTIONS: Non-melanoma skin cancer or
             carcinoma-in-situ (e.g. of cervix, prostate). NOTE: If there is a history of prior
             malignancy, they must not be receiving other specific treatment (cytotoxics,
             monoclonal antibodies, small molecule inhibitors) for their cancer.

          -  Known history of autoimmune disease, including Type I diabetes.

          -  Any prior hypersensitivity or adverse reaction to GM-CSF.

          -  History of trastuzumab-related cardiac toxicity requiring interruption or
             discontinuation of therapy, even if LVEF fully recovered.

          -  Baseline LVEF with a value below 55%.

          -  Failure to fully recover from acute, reversible effects of prior chemotherapy
             regardless of interval since last treatment.

          -  History of myocardial infarction ≤ 168 days (6 months) prior to Pre-registration, or
             congestive heart failure requiring use of ongoing maintenance therapy for life
             threatening ventricular arrhythmias.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <gender_based>Yes</gender_based>
    <gender_description>Any degree of HER2 expression as performed on the diagnostic clinical biopsy defined by immunohistochemistry +1, +2, or +3.</gender_description>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Amy C Degnim</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Mayo Clinic</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Lisa R Seymour, BA</last_name>
    <phone>507-293-7698</phone>
    <email>seymour.lisa@mayo.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Gen A Smith, RN</last_name>
    <phone>507-284-0602</phone>
    <email>Smith.Gen@mayo.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mayo Clinic in Florida</name>
      <address>
        <city>Jacksonville</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>32224</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mayo Clinic in Rochester</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rochester</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55905</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Amy C Degnim</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://www.mayo.edu/research/clinical-trials</url>
    <description>Mayo Clinic Clinical Trials</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>June 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>December 19, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 2, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 4, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 5, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 5, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 7, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Mayo Clinic</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Amy C. Degnim</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>HER2-expressing ductal carcinoma in situ (DCIS).</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

