<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03791658</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PNE 2018-386</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03791658</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Assessment of Adherence to Controller Inhalation Medication in Asthma- and COPD Patients.</brief_title>
  <official_title>Assessment of Adherence to Controller Inhalation Medication in Asthma- and COPD Patients.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Universitair Ziekenhuis Brussel</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Universitair Ziekenhuis Brussel</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The main aim of the study is to evaluate the adherence to controller inhalation medication in
      asthma and Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease (COPD) in Universitair Ziekenhuis Brussel.
      Adherence will be assessed using the 12-question Test for the Adherence to Inhalers (TAI)
      yielding a score indicating level of adherence (high, intermediate or poor). The TAI also
      provides some indication about the possible mechanisms of non-adherence (sporadic, deliberate
      or unconscious). The aim of the study is also to compare the adherence between the 2 study
      subgroups (asthma and COPD patients). Several other factors which could influence the
      compliance of the patients will also be evaluated: age, sex, pack years, FEV1 (Forced
      Expiratory Volume 1), exacerbation history, symptom control, type of inhaler and number of
      inhalers. By identifying different patient and treatment characteristics that lead to
      non-adherence, future education efforts could be better targeted to these patients presenting
      the most important unmet need in terms of adherence.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Adherence to the controller inhalation medication is an important component of asthma and
      COPD care. Good adherence to the prescribed medication is asthma patients is associated with
      better symptom control and improved lung function. Also, lower exacerbation rate and
      mortality risk, less healthcare utilisation, lower healthcare-associated costs and a better
      quality of life are linked with better adherence in asthma and COPD patients.

      However, studies have shown that the adherence to therapy in chronically ill patients
      averages around 50%. In asthma patients the level of adherence varies between 30-70%, while
      compliance rate in COPD patients is around 20-60% (though the numbers vary). Adherence in
      asthma and COPD patients is thus generally low.

      Adherence in these patients is measured in studies in different ways: electronic device
      monitoring, dispensing data, drug levels or several self-administered questionnaires, among
      others. Each technique has its own benefits and drawbacks. However, the easiest to use are
      the self-administered questionnaires. Although many of these exist, a particularly
      interesting questionnaire is the TAI (Test for the Adherence to Inhalers). It exists in 2
      versions: a 10-question and a longer 12-question test. The 12 question TAI has 2 added
      questions, in which a healthcare professional evaluates the use of the inhaler by the
      patient. All 12 questions can then be used to identify different non-compliance behavioural
      patterns. The advantages of this questionnaire are therefore that it can be used for both
      asthma and COPD patients, that it is designed specifically for inhalation medication and that
      it not only measures adherence but also the type of non-compliance .

      The main aim of the study is thus to evaluate the adherence to controller inhalation
      medication in asthma and COPD in Universitair Ziekenhuis Brussel. Adherence will be assessed
      using the 12-question TAI (Test for the Adherence to Inhalers). The aim of the study is also
      to compare the adherence between the 2 study subgroups (asthma and COPD patients). Several
      other factors which could influence the compliance of the patients will also be evaluated:
      age, sex, pack years, FEV1, exacerbation history, symptom control, type of inhaler and number
      of inhalers. By identifying different patient and treatment characteristics that lead to
      non-adherence, future education efforts could be better targeted to these patients presenting
      the most important unmet need in terms of adherence.

      Patient recruitment will take place at the Universitair Ziekenhuis Brussel respiratory
      outpatient clinic. Before their scheduled appointment, patients they will be screened to
      participate in the study. Recruitment will start January 2019 until March 2019, or until the
      target number of patients is reached. On the day of their appointment, the participants will
      receive all necessary information about the study and the informed consent process from the
      principal investigator.

      Patients will have sufficient time to reflect on their participation in this study and to ask
      questions. After obtaining the written informed consent from the patients, the necessary
      interventions (filling in questionnaires and gathering information from the patients files)
      will take place.

      It will be allowed for the patients to provide informed consent and to participate in the
      study on a later date.

      Statistical analysis:

      The statistical analysis will be conducted in 3 steps :

        1. Preliminary one-way ANOVA to evaluate the dependent variable (TAI level of adherence)
           for each independent variable.

        2. A multi-way ANOVA model will be constructed to include the relevant independent
           variables and potential two-way interactions, by maximization of adjusted R2 obtained
           through a backward elimination in order to correct for multicollinearity.

        3. In a final step, the model residuals will be checked to satisfy the normality condition
           through application of the Kolmogorov-Smirnov and Shapiro-Wilk tests, also exploring the
           influence of potential heteroscedasticity.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 2, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 2, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">April 17, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Cross-sectional, single center, single visit study.
1 group of 70 asthmatics, 1 group of 70 COPD-patients</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Adherence to inhalation medication evaluated using the Test for the Adherence to Inhalers</measure>
    <time_frame>15 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>Level of adherence: high (=50 points), intermediate (between 46 and 49 points) or poor (&lt; or = 45 points) .</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Type of non-adherence/ Behavioural pattern (using TAI)</measure>
    <time_frame>15 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>Sporadic non-adherence: items 1 to 5 &lt;25points Deliberate non-adherence: items 6 to 10 &lt; 25 points Unconscious non-adherence: items 11 and 12 &lt; 4 points</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adherence in correlation to specific factors</measure>
    <time_frame>15 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>Asthma patients: Age, sex, FEV1 derived from the last spirometry (including spirometry performed on day of study visit), GINA step, number of exacerbations in the year prior to the study, the prescribed medication: type of inhaler, number of inhalers for maintenance treatment, number of inhalations a day, number of different medications taken by the patient on a daily basis (excluding the inhalers for maintenance treatment of asthma), FENO from the day of the study visit (if available), result of ACT. COPD-patients: Age, sex, Pack Years, GOLD stage and GOLD group, the prescribed medication: type of inhaler, number of inhalers for maintenance treatment, number of inhalations a day, number of different medications taken by the patient on a daily basis (excluding the inhalers for maintenance treatment of COPD).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">141</enrollment>
  <condition>Asthma</condition>
  <condition>COPD</condition>
  <condition>Adherence, Medication</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Asthmatics</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>From the patients file the following information will be collected by the investigators:
Age
Sex
FEV1 derived from the last spirometry (including spirometry performed on day of study visit).
GINA step (Global Initiative for Asthma).
Number of exacerbations in the year prior to the study.
The prescribed medication: type of inhaler, number of inhalers for maintenance treatment, number of inhalations a day.
Number of different medications taken by the patient on a daily basis, excluding the inhalers for maintenance treatment of asthma.
FENO (Fraction Exhaled Nitric Oxide) from the day of the study visit (if available).
Patients will fill out:
The 12-question TAI-questionnaire (test for the adherence to inhalers)
The Asthma Control Test (ACT)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>COPD-patients</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>From the patients file the following information will be collected by the investigators:
Age
Sex
Pack Years
GOLD stage (Global Initiative for Chronic Obstructive Lung Disease)(post-bronchodilator FEV1)
Number of exacerbations in the year prior to the study.
The prescribed medication: type of inhaler, number of inhalers for maintenance treatment, number of inhalations a day.
Number of different medications taken by the patient on a daily basis, excluding the inhalers for maintenance treatment of COPD.
Patients will fill out:
The 12-question TAI-questionnaire (test for the adherence to inhalers)
The COPD Assessment Test (CAT)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>The 12-question TAI</intervention_name>
    <description>The 12-question TAI (Test for the Adherence to Inhalers) yields a score indicating level of adherence (high, intermediate or poor). The TAI also provides some indication about the possible mechanisms of non-adherence (sporadic, deliberate or unconscious).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Asthmatics</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>COPD-patients</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Information from patients file</intervention_name>
    <description>Depending on which arm or group specific information will be gathered from the patients file after informed consent.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Asthmatics</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>COPD-patients</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>The Asthma Control Test (ACT)</intervention_name>
    <description>An international validated questionnaire on the symptoms an asthmatic experiences and the disease control in the patient. Only for the Asthmatics arm of the study</description>
    <arm_group_label>Asthmatics</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>The COPD Assessment Test (CAT)</intervention_name>
    <description>An international validated questionnaire on the symptoms a COPD-patient experiences and the disease control in the patient. Only for the COPD arm of the study</description>
    <arm_group_label>COPD-patients</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Asthmatics with treatment ≥ GINA step 2.

          -  COPD-patients , GOLD stage II-IV.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  No spirometry results available.

          -  COPD patients not on long-acting bronchodilators.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Lisa N Vancampenhout</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Master student in Medicine at Vrije Universiteit Brussel</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Universitair Ziekenhuis Brussel</name>
      <address>
        <city>Brussel</city>
        <state>Brussels</state>
        <zip>1090</zip>
        <country>Belgium</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Belgium</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.asthmacontroltest.com/</url>
    <description>The Asthma Control Test used in this study</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.catestonline.org/</url>
    <description>The COPD Assessment Test used in this study</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Plaza V, Fernández-Rodríguez C, Melero C, Cosío BG, Entrenas LM, de Llano LP, Gutiérrez-Pereyra F, Tarragona E, Palomino R, López-Viña A; TAI Study Group. Validation of the 'Test of the Adherence to Inhalers' (TAI) for Asthma and COPD Patients. J Aerosol Med Pulm Drug Deliv. 2016 Apr;29(2):142-52. doi: 10.1089/jamp.2015.1212. Epub 2015 Jul 31.</citation>
    <PMID>26230150</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>December 31, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 31, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 2, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 25, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 25, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 29, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Universitair Ziekenhuis Brussel</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Lisa Nicky Vancampenhout</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Medical student</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>TAI</keyword>
  <keyword>Test for the Adherence to Inhalers</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Asthma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Choice made with regards to the current General Data Protection Regulation in Europe.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

