<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03792074</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>SCT510-A301</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03792074</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>To Evaluate the Efficacy and Safety of SCT510 in the Treatment of Non-small Cell Lung Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>to Evaluate SCT510 Compared to Avasitin Respectively Combined Paclitaxel and Carboplatin First-line Treatment of Locally Advanced and Metastatic or Recurrent Squamous Cell Non-small Cell Lung Cancer Efficacy and Safety</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Sinocelltech Ltd.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Sinocelltech Ltd.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To evaluate the safety, efficacy and immunogenicity of SCT510 combined with paclitaxel and
      carboplatin compared with bevacizumab combined with paclitaxel and carboplatin in the
      first-line treatment of locally advanced metastatic or recurrent squamous cell non-small cell
      lung cancer.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      A randomized, double-blind, parallel-controlled, multicenter phase 3 clinical trial.

      560 patients with non-resectable locally advanced, metastatic or recurrent non-squamous cell
      non-small cell lung cancer (NSCLC) were randomly divided into two groups (SCT510 group and
      bevacizumab group) at a 1:1 ratio, and the treatment included combination chemotherapy and
      maintenance treatment, followed by follow-up.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">February 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Objective response rate</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>the proportion of subjects whose CR（complete response） and PR（partial response）combined , according to RECIST 1.1 criteria</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Objective response rate</measure>
    <time_frame>18 week</time_frame>
    <description>the proportion of subjects whose CR（complete response） and PR（partial response）combined , according to RECIST 1.1 criteria</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Disease control rate</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks and 18 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>the proportion of subjects with CR（complete response）, PR（partial response） and SD（Stable disease） combined，according to RECIST 1.1 criteria</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of Response</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>The time from the first assessment of CR（complete response） or PR（partial response） to the first assessment of PD（progressive disease） or any cause of death，according to RECIST 1.1 criteria</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression free survival</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>The time from randomization to PD（progressive disease） or any cause of death，according to RECIST 1.1 criteria</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>1-year overall survival rate</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>The proportion of subjects who survived longer than 1 year after randomization</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Defined as the time from randomization of subjects to death from any cause</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">560</enrollment>
  <condition>Non-squamous Cell Non-small Cell Lung Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>SCT510 combined paclitaxel and carboplatin</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>SCT510 15mg/kg+ paclitaxel 175mg+ carboplatin (AUC=5), intravenous infusion，on day 1，Once every 3 weeks;Four to six cycles in a row</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Bevacizumab combined paclitaxel and carboplatin</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Bevacizumab 15mg/kg+ paclitaxel 175mg+ carboplatin (AUC=5), intravenous infusion，on day 1，Once every 3 weeks;Four to six cycles in a row</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>SCT510</intervention_name>
    <description>SCT510 Injection</description>
    <arm_group_label>SCT510 combined paclitaxel and carboplatin</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Bevacizumab</intervention_name>
    <description>Bevacizumab Injection</description>
    <arm_group_label>Bevacizumab combined paclitaxel and carboplatin</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Avastin</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Paclitaxel</intervention_name>
    <description>Paclitaxel Injection</description>
    <arm_group_label>Bevacizumab combined paclitaxel and carboplatin</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>SCT510 combined paclitaxel and carboplatin</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>PTX;TAX</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Carboplatin</intervention_name>
    <description>Carboplatin injection</description>
    <arm_group_label>Bevacizumab combined paclitaxel and carboplatin</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>SCT510 combined paclitaxel and carboplatin</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Volunteer to participate in this study and sign the informed consent;

          2. age is ≤ 18 years old and ≥ 80 years old, regardless of gender;

          3. Subjects with unresectable locally advanced metastatic（Not suitable for the
             multidisciplinary treatment Ⅲ B - Ⅳ period of subjects, according to the international
             association for the study of lung cancer (IASLC) lung cancer staging manual version 8
             standard judgment） or recurrent non-squamous cell non-small cell lung cancer diagnosed
             by histological and/or cytological examination.The diagnosis of non-squamous cell
             non-small cell lung cancer based on sputum cytology requires immunohistochemical
             confirmation.If multiple tumor components are mixed, the main cell types are
             classified.

          4. It is able to provide relevant documents about EGFR mutation and ALK fusion gene
             status, and there is no EGFR sensitive mutation (including exon mutation no. 18
             (G719X), exon deletion no. 19 and exon mutation no. 21 (L858R, L861Q)) and ALK
             fusion.Subjects who have not previously undergone EGFR and ALK gene testing will need
             to undergo genetic testing during the screening period.Among them, subjects whose EGFR
             or ALK gene status cannot be determined for various reasons can be enrolled;Subjects
             who are known to have EGFR sensitive mutations and/or ALK fusion may also be enrolled
             if they are currently unable to obtain the corresponding targeted drugs (including the
             rejection of the subjects) and chemotherapy is standard treatment at the research
             center;

          5. According to RECIST v1.1 criteria, at least one measurable lesion was ensured;The
             lesions that had received radiotherapy before could only be selected as target lesions
             if there was clear disease progression 3 months after the end of radiotherapy.

          6. Systemic antitumor therapy for locally advanced metastatic or recurrent non-squamous
             non-small cell lung cancer has not been accepted.If the subjects in the complete early
             non-small cell lung cancer after radical treatment received adjuvant therapy, and
             disease relapse, participants need to ensure that adjuvant therapy over time from this
             study first dosing interval more than 6 months, and auxiliary treatment led to a
             variety of toxic effects have been restored (according to the CTCAE v4.03 standard
             judgment level 1 or less, except for hair loss).

          7. Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group （ECOG） physical condition score 0 or 1

          8. the expected survival time is more than 6 months;

          9. Laboratory inspection meets the following requirements:

               -  absolute neutrophil value (ANC) is greater than 1.5 x 109/L, platelet count (PLT)
                  is greater than 100 x 109/L, hemoglobin (HGB) is greater than 90 g/L, and white
                  blood cell (WBC) is greater than 3.0 x 109/L;

               -  liver function: total bilirubin (TBil) &lt; 1.5 times the normal upper limit;
                  Aspartate aminotransferase(AST/SGOT),Alanine aminotransferase
                  (ALT/SGPT),andalkaline phosphatase(ALP) &lt; 2.5 times the normal upper limit;In the
                  case of liver metastasis, AST and ALT were less than or equal to 5.0 times the
                  upper limit of normal values.In the case of liver metastasis and/or bone
                  metastasis, ALP is less than or equal to 5.0 times the normal upper limit.

               -  renal function: upper limit of normal serum creatinine (Scr) less than 1.5 times;

               -  urine protein &lt; 2 (+) detected by routine urine test;If the urine protein at
                  baseline is greater than or equal to 2 (+), the 24-hour urine protein
                  quantification must be less than or equal to 1.0 g.

               -  coagulation function: the international standardized ratio (INR) is no more than
                  1.5, and the activation time of partial thrombin (APTT) is no more than 1.5 times
                  the upper limit of normal value;

         10. Heart function: left ventricular ejection fraction (LVEF) 50% or higher;

         11. able to communicate well with researchers and follow the visit, treatment, laboratory
             examination and other relevant regulations stipulated in the study.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. subjects with mixed non-small cell and small cell carcinoma, squamous cell carcinoma
             or mixed adenosquamous carcinoma with squamous cell as the main component

          2. patients with a history of tracheoesophageal fistula, gastrointestinal perforation or
             gastrointestinal fistula and intraperitoneal abscess within 6 months before
             randomization;

          3. patients with malignant tumors other than lung cancer within the first 5 years were
             randomized, excluding cured carcinoma in situ of the cervix, skin basal cells cancer
             or squamous epithelial cells skin cancer, local prostate cancer after radical
             resection and ductal carcinoma in situ of the breast after radical resection;

          4. severe cardiovascular and cerebrovascular diseases, including cerebrovascular
             accidents (CVA), transient ischemic attack (TIA), myocardial infarction and
             significant vascular diseases (including but not limited to aortic aneurysms requiring
             surgical repair or recent arterial thrombosis) within the first 6 months
             randomly;Patients with unstable angina, New York heart association (NYHA)
             classification ≥ Ⅱ heart failure and arrhythmia drugs can't control;

          5. Subjects who received lung radiotherapy within the first 4 weeks or who had not
             recovered from radiation-related toxicity were randomized.For all other anatomical
             sites, subjects received radiotherapy within the first 2 weeks of randomization or did
             not recover from radiation-related toxicity;

          6. Major surgery was performed within the first 4 weeks of randomization or major
             surgical treatment was planned during the trial period (the researchers determined
             that there was a risk of bleeding or wound healing complications);

          7. Have bleeding tendency, high bleeding risk or coagulation dysfunction, including
             thrombotic disease within 6 months prior to randomization and/or hemoptysis history
             within 3 months prior to randomization (single hemoptysis is more than 2.5mL);Or
             recently (less than 10 days after the first study drug treatment) using a full dose
             oral or extralimental anticoagulant or thrombolytic agent or aspirin (&gt; 325 mg/ day)
             or other nsaids that inhibit platelet function;Or prior to surgery, the researchers
             determined that there was a tendency to bleed;

          8. subjects with high suspicion of idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis, organic pneumonia,
             drug-related pneumonia, idiopathic pneumonia or active pneumonia in chest CT scan
             during the screening period;

          9. subjects with known central nervous system metastasis (except asymptomatic brain
             metastasis and subjects with treated symptoms controlled and stable symptoms within 1
             month prior to randomization).Patients with clinical suspected central nervous system
             metastasis must undergo enhanced CT or MRI within the first 28 days randomly to
             exclude central nervous system metastasis.

         10. imaging examination showed signs of tumor invasion into the large blood vessel, and
             the tumor had completely approached, wrapped or invaded the large blood vessel cavity
             (such as pulmonary artery or superior vena cava);

         11. patients with hypertension (systolic blood pressure &gt; 150 mmHg or diastolic blood
             pressure &gt; 100 mmHg) who are still under poor control after combined treatment with
             two or more antihypertensive drugs in the screening period, as well as those who have
             a history of hypertension crisis or hypertensive encephalosis;

         12. The presence of unhealed wounds, active peptic ulcers and fractures (excluding healed
             old fractures);

         13. There is a large amount of pericardial effusion, peritoneal or pleural effusion that
             cannot be controlled by drainage or other symptomatic treatment (symptomatic treatment
             is allowed before enrollment, but drugs with anti-tumor indications, such as
             chemotherapy drugs, anti-angiogenic drugs and molecular targeted drugs, cannot be
             given);

         14. HBsAg is positive, and the titer detection of HBV-DNA in peripheral blood ≥ 1x103 copy
             number /mL (or the quantitative determination of HBV-DNA ≥200 units /mL); HCV or HIV
             or syphilis positive subjects;At present, there are other active infectious diseases,
             which are not suitable for inclusion in this study.

         15. known for SCT510, bevacizumab, paclitaxel and carboplatin injection and its material
             composition allergies;

         16. women who are pregnant or breast-feeding;

         17. women of child-bearing age or male subjects who are unwilling to take effective
             contraceptive measures during the study period or within 6 months after the last
             administration of the study drugs;

         18. subjects who have participated in other clinical studies in the first 4 weeks of
             randomization or who are receiving treatment in other clinical trials (except those
             who participated in the overall survival follow-up of one study);

         19. previous history of alcoholism or drug abuse;

         20. in addition to the above circumstances, the researcher believes that there are other
             circumstances that are not suitable for inclusion.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>ming gao</last_name>
    <phone>8618610163675</phone>
    <email>ming_gao@sinocelltech.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <verification_date>December 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>December 26, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 1, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 3, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 1, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 1, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 3, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lung Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Non-Small-Cell Lung</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Paclitaxel</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Bevacizumab</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carboplatin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

