<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03792737</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ESC-201702</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03792737</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study of Two Types of Absorbable Surgical Sutures in the Suturing of Thyroid Surgery Incision</brief_title>
  <acronym>Nautilus</acronym>
  <official_title>A Prospective, Multi-center, Randomized Controlled Study Evaluating the Efficacy and Safety of Two Types of Absorbable Surgical Sutures in the Suturing of Thyroid Surgery Incision</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Ethicon, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Ethicon, Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The primary objective of this study is to evaluate the efficacy and safety of two types of
      absorbable surgical sutures -- STRATAFIX Spiral PDS Knotless Plus Tissue Control Device and
      STRATAFIX Spiral MONOCRYL Plus Knotless Tissue Control Device (hereinafter referred to as
      Spiral PDS Plus and Spiral MONOCRYL Plus) used in thyroid surgery to suture surgical
      incision.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study adopts a multicenter, prospective, randomized controlled design. The study
      population are subjects who undergo thyroid surgery.

      Before the surgery, subjects are randomized in 1:1:1 ratio to the investigational group 1
      (using Spiral PDS Plus), investigational group 2 (using Spiral MONOCRYL Plus) and control
      group. See the table below for the specific suture levels, materials and techniques of each
      group.

      A blinded central imaging evaluation will be performed on the healing condition of surgical
      incision on Day 5-7 post-surgery. The subjects will be blinded to the type of suture used for
      wound closure.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">April 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">January 6, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 12, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of subjects achieving Grade A healing of surgical incision(success) in each group.</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 5-7 post-surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Wound healing grade will be assessed by independent, blinded Central Imaging evaluators using (a picture of complete neck anterior view, containing full length of the incision) on Day 5-7 post-surgery.
Wound healing status is classified into three grades:
Grade A healing: Good healing with no adverse reaction;
Grade B healing: Inflammatory reaction(s) at the healing, such as red swelling, induration, hematoma, effusion, etc., but without suppuration;
Grade C healing: Suppuration of incision, requiring incision and drainage and other treatments.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incision suturing time</measure>
    <time_frame>Surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Incision suturing time, defined as the time required from the first needle insertion for stitching ribbon muscles to the completion of intradermal suture (min)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Modified Hollander Wound Evaluation Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>28-35 days after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Modified Hollander Wound Evaluation Scale [assessed by Central Imaging evaluators using pictures, including a picture of complete neck anterior view containing full length of the incision, a picture taken parallel to the incision plane, a picture taken at a 45° angle to the incision plane, and incision lateral view pictures of both sides (one for each)]</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Postoperative incision pain score (Visual Analogue Scale, VAS)</measure>
    <time_frame>5-7 days after surgery, 28-35 days after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Postoperative incision pain score (Visual Analogue Scale, VAS).Score range is from 0 to 10, Score 0 means no pain, for the best outcome, and score 10 means unbearable: severely affects sleep with other symptoms, or passive position, for the worst outcome.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Health related quality of life scale (EQ-5D-5L).</measure>
    <time_frame>5-7 days after surgery, 28-35 days after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>The EQ-5D-5L essentially consists of 2 pages: the EQ-5D descriptive system and the EQ visual analogue scale (EQ VAS).
The descriptive system comprises five dimensions: mobility, self-care, usual activities, pain/discomfort and anxiety/depression. Each dimension has 5 levels: no problems, slight problems, moderate problems, severe problems and extreme problems. The digits for the five dimensions can be combined into a 5-digit number that describes the patient's health state.
The EQ VAS records the patient's self-rated health on a vertical visual analogue scale, where the endpoints are labelled, score 100 means the best health you can imagine, score 0 means the worst health you can imagine.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">501</enrollment>
  <condition>Sutures</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Investigational group 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Investigational group 1: Use the study device Spiral PDS Plus for continuous suture of the ribbon muscles, VICRYL Plus for interrupted suture of the platysma, and MONOCRYL Plus for continuous subcuticular suture.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Investigational group 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Investigational group 2: Use PDS Plus for continuous suture of the ribbon muscles, VICRYL Plus for interrupted suture of the platysma, and the study device Spiral MONOCRYL Plus for continuous subcuticular suture.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Control group: Use the control device PDS Plus for continuous suture of the ribbon muscles, VICRYL Plus for interrupted suture of the platysma, and the control device MONOCRYL Plus continuous subcuticular suture.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Spiral PDS Plus</intervention_name>
    <description>The Spiral PDS Plus is an antibacterial monofilament, synthetic absorbable device. It contains triclosan, a broad spectrum antibacterial agent. The device consists of barbed suture material, armed with a surgical needle on one end and a fixation loop at the opposite end. The device is designed to anchor with a closed loop at one end and a unidirectional barbed section on the other end. Spiral PDS Plus barbs are oriented in one direction to allow tissue approximation without the need to tie surgical knots.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Investigational group 1</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Spiral MONOCRYL Plus</intervention_name>
    <description>The Spiral MONOCRYL Plus is an antibacterial monofilament, synthetic absorbable device. It contains triclosan, a broad spectrum antibacterial agent. The device consists of barbed suture material, armed with a surgical needle on one end and a fixation loop at the opposite end. The device is designed to anchor with a closed loop at one end and a unidirectional barbed section on the other end. Spiral MONOCRYL Plus barbs are oriented in one direction to allow tissue approximation without the need to tie surgical knots.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Investigational group 2</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>PDS Plus</intervention_name>
    <description>PDS Plus is a non-barbed antibacterial monofilament, synthetic absorbable suture. The suture contains triclosan, a broad spectrum antibacterial agent.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Investigational group 2</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>MONOCRYL Plus</intervention_name>
    <description>MONOCRYL Plus is a non-barbed antibacterial monofilament, synthetic absorbable suture. The suture contains triclosan, a broad spectrum antibacterial agent.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Investigational group 1</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>VICRYL Plus</intervention_name>
    <description>VICRYL Plus antibacterial suture is a non-barbed synthetic absorbable sterile, surgical suture. The suture contains triclosan, a broad spectrum antibacterial agent.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Investigational group 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Investigational group 2</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. The subject is ≥18, and &lt;70 years old

          2. Planned open thyroid surgery, adopting an anterior cervical curved incision (Kocher's
             incision);

          3. Subject who volunteers to participate in this study, follows the study requirements
             and follow-up visit and signs the written Informed Consent Form voluntarily;

          4. Subject who agrees to not schedule any elective surgical operation except the study
             surgery before the study is completed;

          5. The investigator considers the subject's expected postoperative survival time is not
             less than 3 months.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Female subjects who are pregnant or lactation at screening;

          2. Preoperative clinical staging shows stage IV thyroid cancer, or cervical lymph nodes
             dissection is planned;

          3. Suspected or confirmed anaplastic thyroid cancer;

          4. Peripheral vascular disease affecting blood supply of the neck;

          5. Active infectious collagenosis (e.g. scleroderma), or any other disease that would
             interfere with wound healing;

          6. Fasting plasma glucose ≥7.7 mmol/L;

          7. History of coagulation diseases;

          8. Current oral or intravenous antibiotic therapy for existing disease or infection;

          9. History of immunosuppressant use (e.g. steroids) within the last 6 months;

         10. Chemotherapy or radiotherapy within the last 6 months, or planned chemotherapy or
             radiotherapy during the study;

         11. Personal or family history of keloid formation or hyperplasia;

         12. Current participation in any other drug (within 30 days or within 5 half-lives of the
             investigational drug) or device clinical study;

         13. History of any thyroid surgery, except thyroid fine-needle aspiration biopsy;

         14. Planned use of skin adhesive at the incision site;

         15. The subject is not suitable for participating in this study for any other reasons, as
             judged by the investigator.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>69 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Hao Zhang</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>First Hospital of China Medical University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Fujian Medical University Union Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Fuzhou</city>
        <state>Fujian</state>
        <zip>350001</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Peking University Shenzhen Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Shenzhen</city>
        <state>Guangdong</state>
        <zip>518035</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The First Affiliated Hospital of Zhengzhou University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Zhengzhou</city>
        <state>Henan</state>
        <zip>450052</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Union Hospital Tongji Medical college Huazhong University of science and technologyUnion Hospital Tongji Medical college Huazhong University of science and technology</name>
      <address>
        <city>Wuhan</city>
        <state>Hubei</state>
        <zip>430022</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Jiangsu Province Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nanjing</city>
        <state>Jiangsu</state>
        <zip>210029</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The First Hospital of China Medical University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Shenyang</city>
        <state>Liaoning</state>
        <zip>110001</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The First Affiliated Hospital of Xi'An Jiaotong University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Xi'an</city>
        <state>Shanxi</state>
        <zip>710061</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>West China Hospital, Sichuan University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chengdu</city>
        <state>Sicuan Province</state>
        <zip>610041</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The First Affiliated Hospital, Zhejiang University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hangzhou</city>
        <state>Zhejiang</state>
        <zip>310006</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Beijing Friendship Hospital, Capital Medical University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Beijing</city>
        <zip>100050</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 29, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 2, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 3, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 25, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 25, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 27, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Surgical Wound</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

