<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03796689</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>18-254-53</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03796689</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The PCORnet Blood Pressure Home Monitoring Study</brief_title>
  <acronym>BP Home</acronym>
  <official_title>The PCORnet Blood Pressure Home Monitoring Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of California, San Francisco</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Patient-Centered Outcomes Research Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of California, San Francisco</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>Yes</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The PCORnet Blood Pressure Home Monitoring (BP HOME) Study is a patient-level randomized
      controlled trial that will compare the effectiveness of home blood pressure monitoring (HPBM)
      with versus without a linked Smartphone application (&quot;app&quot;) for helping patients with
      uncontrolled hypertension achieve a reduction in systolic blood pressure. The trial will be
      conducted within the National Patient-Centered Clinical Research Network (PCORnet), which
      supports a research network that enables distributed querying of EHR data in a common data
      model. It will also use the Eureka Research Platform, an online research platform hosted by
      UCSF that supports eConsent, online surveys, and data collection from devices such as HBPMs.
      Data from these two data sources will be used together to accomplish the study aims. Given
      that HBPM is the guideline-recommended standard of care (without specification of Smartphone
      linkage), the HPBM devices and the app are all commercially available and currently in use,
      and that clinicians, with input from patients, will maintain full control of how BP is
      clinically managed, we believe participation in the project poses minimal risk to
      participants.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      We have designed a patient-level randomized controlled trial that will compare the
      effectiveness of Smartphone-linked versus standard HBPM for helping patients with
      uncontrolled hypertension achieve a reduction in their Systolic Blood Pressure (SBP), and
      patient satisfaction with the device. We aim to enroll 2000 patients who will be randomized
      in a 1:1 ratio to receive a Smartphone-linked or standard HBPM. We will use data from the
      electronic health record (EHR), an online patient portal, and the home BP monitor (in the
      Smartphone-linked arm) to collect outcome data for a period of at least 6 months (for the
      primary outcome), and up to 18 months (for secondary outcomes, depending on enrollment date).
      The primary BP control outcome will be reduction in SBP, by clinic measurements, at 6 months.
      The primary patient satisfaction outcome will be the Net Promoter Score derived from
      self-reported likelihood of recommending the device to a friend, at 6 months.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">August 15, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 30, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 28, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Reduction in Systolic Blood Pressure (SBP)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Reduction is defined by the absolute difference between the SBP measured at the most recent outpatient clinical encounter at the time of enrollment, and the SBP measured at the most recent outpatient clinical encounter 6 months after enrollment. If more than 1 measurement is recorded during a single clinical encounter, the lower/lowest will be used.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Net Promoter Score</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>This score is assessed by asking a single question about likelihood of recommending the device to a friend, with options from 1-10 (10 being extremely likely). As per published methods, persons indicating 9 or 10 are considered &quot;Promoters&quot;; persons indicating 7 or 8 are &quot;Passives&quot;; and persons indicating 1-6 are &quot;Detractors&quot;. The score is calculated by taking the percent of Promoters and subtracting the percent of Detractors, yielding a score for each group ranging from -100 to 100.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">2000</enrollment>
  <condition>Hypertension</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Smartphone-linked</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Standard</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Smartphone-linked HBPM and associated app</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants in the Smartphone-linked arm of the study will receive an Omron 786N Home Blood Pressure Monitor (HBPM) that can be linked to the Omron Connect app via Bluetooth. They will also receive instructions about how to use their device and download the app and will be provided with publically available guidelines for HBPM. Participants will be instructed to use their device and app to take readings which they can track over time and share with their provider using the app.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Smartphone-linked</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Standard HBPM</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants in the Standard arm of the study will receive an Omron 785N Home Blood Pressure Monitor (HBPM), instructions about how to use their device and publically available guidelines for HBPM. They will be instructed to use their device to take readings which they can track over time and share with their provider.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Standard</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age ≥ 18 years

          -  At least one ambulatory visit in one of the participating study sites during the past
             year

          -  SBP &gt; 145 mmHg at most recent clinic visit (may be treated with BP meds already or
             not)

          -  A self-reported commitment to &quot;work on lowering your blood pressure by 10 points or
             more to reduce your risk of heart attack and stroke&quot;

          -  Owns a Smartphone (Android or iOS)

          -  Nobody in household currently owns a HBPM

          -  Willing to receive text messages from the study

          -  Can read/write English well enough to use English-based Smartphone apps and fill out
             online surveys in English

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Has an arm circumference &lt;22 cm or &gt;42 cm
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mark Pletcher, MD MPH</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of California, San Francisco</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Madelaine Faulkner, MPH</last_name>
    <phone>415-476-3393</phone>
    <email>Madelaine.Faulkner@ucsf.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Mark Pletcher, MD MPH</last_name>
    <phone>415-514-8008</phone>
    <email>Mark.Pletcher@ucsf.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Florida Health</name>
      <address>
        <city>Gainesville</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>32610</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Rhonda Cooper-Dehoff, PharmD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>New Orleans</city>
        <state>Louisiana</state>
        <zip>70112</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Tom Carton, Ph.D</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mayo Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rochester</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55902</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Alanna Chamberlain, Ph.D</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 4, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 4, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 8, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 4, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 4, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 8, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hypertension</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

