<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03795493</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HREBA.CC-18-0657</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03795493</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Diet Restriction and Exercise-induced Adaptations in Metastatic Breast Cancer</brief_title>
  <acronym>DREAM</acronym>
  <official_title>Diet Restriction and Exercise-induced Adaptations in Metastatic Breast Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Alberta</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Canadian Cancer Society Research Institute (CCSRI)</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Canadian Institutes of Health Research (CIHR)</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Alberta</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Fifty patients with metastatic breast cancer will be randomly assigned to an acute
      intervention consisting of both aerobic exercise and caloric restriction administered acutely
      prior to each of six chemotherapy cycles, or to usual care. The aerobic exercise intervention
      will consist of a single supervised recumbent cycle ergometer session performed concurrent to
      each chemotherapy infusion. The diet intervention consists of provision of meals freshly
      prepared in a metabolic kitchen under the supervision of a dietitian with caloric content
      equivalent to 50% of measured energy requirements and low carbohydrate content for the 72
      hours prior to each chemotherapy infusion. Tumor outcomes will be assessed via CT scan (tumor
      size)and MRI (novel marker of tumor regression), while treatment side effects will be
      assessed by MRI and treatment symptoms and quality of life will be assessed via questionnaire
      before, during and after up to six chemotherapy cycles of a consistent treatment protocol.
      Progression-free and overall survival will be tracked for two years after diagnosis.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Despite major advances in recent decades in treatment for early stage breast cancer leading
      to an 89% 5-year survival rate, metastatic breast cancer is still considered incurable due to
      resistance to most available treatments. As such, 5-year survival rate for metastatic breast
      cancer is only 22%. One mechanism for resistance to cancer therapies and promotion of
      metastasis in solid tumors is that their vascular system is impaired causing diminished
      delivery of systemic therapy and oxygen. Furthermore, toxicity can be quite high with
      metastatic regimens, which can limit the dose received. Both diet and exercise have been used
      to attenuate treatment toxicity, but the promising preclinical evidence showing their
      potential to enhance chemotherapy efficacy and survival has not been studied in humans. For
      example, a single bout of aerobic exercise substantially increased tumor blood flow and
      oxygen delivery, suggesting that chemotherapy delivery to the tumor would be enhanced. Short
      periods of fasting or caloric restriction also appear to be safe and effective strategies to
      inhibit tumor growth, enhance chemotherapy efficacy, while also promoting resistance to
      chemotherapy in healthy cells. Furthermore, combining aerobic exercise and caloric
      restriction can elicit synergistic effects on outcomes relevant to cancer, including body
      composition, aerobic fitness, fasting insulin and glucose, insulin-like growth factor, and
      tumor promoter pathways.

      Study Design: With preclinical proof-of-principle and clinical safety and feasibility of each
      intervention independently established, this study will be a phase II, two-arm, single blind,
      randomized controlled trial. Fifty patients will be randomly assigned to an acute
      intervention consisting of both aerobic exercise and caloric restriction administered acutely
      prior to each of six chemotherapy cycles, or to usual care.

      Approach: Participants will include adults with metastatic breast cancer with measurable
      metastases that will receive intravenous chemotherapy. The aerobic exercise intervention will
      consist of a single supervised recumbent cycle ergometer session performed concurrent to each
      chemotherapy infusion. The diet intervention consists of provision of meals freshly prepared
      in a metabolic kitchen under the supervision of a dietitian with caloric content equivalent
      to 50% of measured energy requirements and low carbohydrate content for the 72 hours prior to
      each chemotherapy infusion. This acute intervention does not lead to long-term nutritional
      imbalances or weight loss. Exercise intensity and meals will be individualized to participant
      abilities and preferences. Tumor outcomes will be assessed via CT scan (tumor size) and MRI
      (novel marker of tumor regression), while symptoms and quality of life will be assessed via
      questionnaire before, during and after up to six chemotherapy cycles of a consistent
      treatment protocol. Progression-free and overall survival will be tracked for two years after
      diagnosis.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Enrolling by invitation</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">April 23, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Tumor size</measure>
    <time_frame>0-6 weeks before the first chemotherapy treatment and 1-4 weeks after the last chemotherapy treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Percent change in tumor size measured by computerized tomography.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Tumor response to therapy by magnetic resonance imaging</measure>
    <time_frame>0-6 weeks before the first chemotherapy treatment and 1-4 weeks after the last chemotherapy treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) derived water apparent diffusion coefficient within the tumor</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Patient-reported treatment symptoms</measure>
    <time_frame>0-6 weeks before the first chemotherapy treatment, 2-4 weeks after the third chemotherapy, and 2-4 weeks after six chemotherapy treatments</time_frame>
    <description>Patient-reported treatment symptoms assessed using the Rotterdam Symptom Checklist</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Self reported quality of life</measure>
    <time_frame>0-6 weeks before the first chemotherapy treatment, 2-4 weeks after the third chemotherapy, and 2-4 weeks after six chemotherapy treatments</time_frame>
    <description>Quality of life assessed using the total score from the Functional Assessment of Cancer Therapy - Fatigue Questionnaire. Scores can range from 0 - 52 where a high score represents a better quality of life.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Progression-free survival</measure>
    <time_frame>Two years after study enrollment</time_frame>
    <description>Average survival time extracted from Cancer Control Alberta's electronic database</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival</measure>
    <time_frame>Two years after study enrollment</time_frame>
    <description>Average survival time extracted from Cancer Control Alberta's electronic database</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Liver T1 relaxation time</measure>
    <time_frame>0-6 weeks before the first chemotherapy treatment and 1-4 weeks after the last chemotherapy treatment</time_frame>
    <description>MRI-derived relaxation time from healthy liver</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Left ventricular ejection fraction</measure>
    <time_frame>0-6 weeks before the first chemotherapy treatment and 1-4 weeks after the last chemotherapy treatment</time_frame>
    <description>MRI-derived left ventricular ejection fraction</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Thigh muscle mass</measure>
    <time_frame>0-6 weeks before the first chemotherapy treatment and 1-4 weeks after the last chemotherapy treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Dixon fat water separation by MRI of the mid-thigh</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Thigh muscle quality</measure>
    <time_frame>0-6 weeks before the first chemotherapy treatment and 1-4 weeks after the last chemotherapy treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Percent of intermuscular fat in thigh muscle derived by Dixon fat water separation imaging</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Thigh skeletal muscle T1 relaxation time</measure>
    <time_frame>0-6 weeks before the first chemotherapy treatment and 1-4 weeks after the last chemotherapy treatment</time_frame>
    <description>MRI-derived skeletal muscle T1 relaxation time at mid-thigh</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Breast Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Standard chemotherapy treatment and oncology care plus short-term diet and exercise intervention.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Standard chemotherapy treatment and oncology care.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Short-term diet and exercise intervention</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants assigned to the intervention group will perform both the diet and acute exercise interventions. The interventions will be applied prior to up to six chemotherapy treatments of a consistent protocol. The total number of treatments of a given protocol received prior to treatment conclusion is dependent on patient condition and oncologic care preferences.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Diagnosis of stage IV or metastatic breast cancer;

          -  Measurable metastases.

          -  Age &gt;18

          -  Starting (or having only received one treatment of) any type of intravenously
             administered chemotherapy;

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) Score &lt; 3

          -  Oncologist approval to participate

          -  Able to communicate and read and understand English;

          -  Willing and able to adhere to the study interventions and assessments;

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Limitations to sustained exercise (including bone metastases in the femur neck);

          -  Clinical evidence of cachexia (oncologist's discretion, study team will use body mass
             index &lt;18.5kg/m² as a flag to highlight concern to treating oncologist);

          -  Body mass &gt;109 kg at time of enrollment;

          -  Diabetes;

          -  Severe food allergies;

          -  History of eating disorder (diagnosed or self-reported);

          -  Unable to provide informed consent (i.e. cognitive impairment);

          -  Supplemental oxygen requirement;

          -  Uncontrolled pleural effusions (oncologists approval if pleural effusions exists and
             are controlled);

          -  Bilirubin &gt;30 umol/L;

          -  Creatinine &gt;120 umol/L;

          -  Pregnant;

          -  Contraindications to 3T MRI for research purposes
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Carla Prado, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Alberta</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Richard Thompson, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Alberta</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Alberta</name>
      <address>
        <city>Edmonton</city>
        <state>Alberta</state>
        <zip>T6G 2E1</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 26, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 4, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 7, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 12, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 12, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">December 16, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Alberta</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Carla Prado</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Exercise</keyword>
  <keyword>Nutrition</keyword>
  <keyword>Caloric Restriction</keyword>
  <keyword>Chemotherapy</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

