<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04389814</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>0012018</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04389814</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>New Time Clock for ST-elevation MI Based on Biochemical Myocardial Infarction Onset Time</brief_title>
  <acronym>BIT-STEMI</acronym>
  <official_title>Determination of Biochemical Onset Time for ST-Segment Elevation Myocardial Infarction and Comparison With Patient-Reported Symptom Onset Time</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Tabba Heart Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Tabba Heart Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      ST segment elevation myocardial infarction (STEMI) is one of the leading causes of death
      across the world and immediate treatment with either thrombolytics or percutaneous coronary
      intervention (PCI) results in lower mortality. It is essential to accurately determine the
      time of onset of myocardial infarction. Standard practice is to take the time of symptom
      onset as a surrogate for artery occlusion time. However symptom onset is a subjective
      parameter and affected by multiple factors such as recall issues in elderly patients and
      preceding unstable angina symptoms before artery occlusion.

      In a recent study by Mahmoud et al. an objective method, biochemical onset time is proposed
      for estimation of artery occlusion time using serial cardiac troponin T (cTnT) levels in
      patients with STEMI. However, this study was retrospective, had an average of two
      measurements of cTnT for each patient, peak troponin level was frequently missing and newer
      earlier detectable biomarkers such as high sensitive Troponin I (hsTnI) were not used.

      We plan to use multiple samples of hsTnI for each patient using the same method as above and
      we will compare the biochemical ischemic time with the patient reported symptom onset time.
      Secondarily, we will try to determine whether a single sample of multiple cardiac biomarkers
      with different release kinetics drawn at time of patient presentation in emergency room (ER)
      could predict precise time of onset of myocardial infarction.

      OBJECTIVES

        1. To determine the biochemical onset time using multiple hsTnI measurements from each
           patient (zero, 03, 08, 24 hrs), and compare this biochemical time to the
           patient-reported symptoms onset time as an indicator of coronary artery occlusion.

        2. To predict biochemical occlusion at the time of presentation with the use of single
           sample of six different markers of myocardial injury.

        3. To assess the association of conventional ischemic time and biochemical ischemic time
           with infarct size; using peak hsTnI, percent ejection fraction by Echocardiography and
           Cardiac Magnetic Resonance imaging (CMR) based infarct volume in grams.

        4. To assess the association of conventional ischemic time and biochemical ischemic time
           with in-hospital and 30-days major adverse cardiac events, MACE; a composite of heart
           failure, shock, re MI or death.

      A prospective nonintervention pilot study will include 100 consecutive patients coming with
      acute STEMI. Patients' recruitment will be done in ER of Tabba Heart Institute, Karachi
      Pakistan.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      ST segment elevation myocardial infarction (STEMI) is one of the leading causes of death
      across the world (1) and immediate treatment with either thrombolytics or percutaneous
      coronary intervention (PCI) results in lower mortality (2,3,4). Prior studies have
      demonstrated that in patients with STEMI approximately 50% of jeopardized myocardium
      undergoes necrosis in the first hour, and after 6 hours, myocardial salvage is minimal or
      absent (5,6). Among such patients each minute of delay in reperfusion treatment raises 1-year
      mortality; in fact, the risk of 1-year mortality increases by 7.5% for each 30-minute delay
      (7).

      As the outcome of reperfusion treatment in STEMI is time dependent, it is essential to
      accurately determine the time of onset of myocardial infarction. It is standard clinical
      practice to take the time of symptom onset as a surrogate for artery occlusion time, and this
      helps in decision making about mode of reperfusion in STEMI-patients. However symptom onset
      is a subjective parameter and affected by multiple factors such as recall issues in elderly
      patients and preceding unstable angina symptoms before artery occlusion. This mandates need
      for an objective method to know the artery occlusion time. Different time intervals are
      defined for STEMI patients that include, &quot;artery occlusion to symptom onset time&quot;, &quot;symptom
      onset to first medical contact time&quot; and &quot;door to balloon time&quot; and combination of all these
      intervals is &quot;Total Ischemic time&quot; i.e. the time between artery occlusion and re-opening,
      which is strongly correlated with 1-year mortality (8).

      In a recent study by Mahmoud et al. (9) an objective method, biochemical onset time is
      proposed for estimation of artery occlusion time using serial cardiac troponin T (cTnT)
      levels in patients with STEMI. However, this study was retrospective, had an average of two
      measurements of cTnT for each patient, peak troponin level was frequently missing and newer
      earlier detectable biomarkers such as high sensitive Troponin I (hsTnI) were not used.

      The objective of this pilot study is to observe if there is any role of multiple samples of
      markers of myocardial injury in prediction of the biochemical onset time. We plan to use
      multiple samples (four) of hsTnI for each patient using the same method as above (9); and we
      will compare the biochemical ischemic time with the patient reported symptom onset time.
      Secondarily, we will try to determine whether a single sample of multiple cardiac biomarkers
      with different release kinetics drawn at time of patient presentation in emergency room (ER)
      can also predict precise time of onset of myocardial infarction, which would be a
      revolutionary finding in STEMI patients' early management. For this purpose we will use three
      markers including cardiac specific myoglobin (CS-Mb) and Creatinine kinase-Mb (CK-Mb) (10).
      We also plan to test three other novel markers which has previously shown to have some role
      in post MI prognosis and cardiac event risk prediction in general population {(Mean
      neutrophil volume (MNV), Gamma Prime fibrinogen (γ' Fibrinogen) and heart type fatty acid
      binding protein (h-FABP)} to assess whether it has a possible predictive value to assess time
      of onset of MI. Lastly, we plan to assess the prognostic value of biochemical ischemic time
      versus conventional ischemic time for the outcomes of major adverse cardiovascular events
      (MACE) at hospital discharge and 30 days post MI, infarct size using CMR and echo based
      parameters.

      OBJECTIVES

        1. To determine the biochemical onset time using multiple measurements of hsTnI from each
           patient (zero, 03, 08, 24hrs), and compare this biochemical time to the patient-reported
           symptoms onset time as an indicator of coronary artery occlusion.

        2. To predict Biochemical occlusion at the time of presentation with the use of single
           sample of six different markers of myocardial injury.

        3. To assess the association of conventional ischemic time and biochemical ischemic time
           with infarct size; using peak hsTnI, percent ejection fraction by Echocardiography and
           Cardiac Magnetic Resonance imaging (CMR) based infarct volume in grams.

        4. To assess the association of conventional ischemic time and biochemical ischemic time
           with in-hospital and 30-days major adverse cardiac events, MACE; a composite of heart
           failure, shock, re MI or death.

      METHODS This will be a single center nonintervention pilot study on 100 patients on
      consecutive patients coming to ER Tabba Heart Institute Karachi, Pakistan, (THI) with acute
      STEMI. Data will be collected prospectively.

      Sampling technique:

      Non probability consecutive sampling will be done to enroll patients from the ER of the
      hospital. Consecutive patients presenting at emergency of THI with diagnosis of STEMI within
      24 hours of symptom onset will be assessed for eligibility.

      Questionnaire and interview:

      Research Officer (RO): three data collectors and one research officer will be employed full
      time for the duration of the study. Their job description will include to make sure consent
      forms and questionnaires are completed and to fill out the deficiencies from patients'
      medical record files, to keep log of the patient forms and to arrange team meetings every
      fortnight. Also they will follow the patients throughout the hospital stay to record relevant
      events. Also he or she will be responsible to call and coordinate the patients for follow up
      echo and CMR at 30 day post MI. This person will also be trained by the PI prior to the start
      of enrollment.

      Ethical approval: Ethical approval has been taken from ethical review committee in THI.

      Informed consent: Before enrollment, patient or the designated attendant will be asked to
      sign an informed consent form, provided both in Urdu and English as applicable to the
      patients and attendants. The patient will be explained about their rights during the study,
      regarding withdrawal and refusal anytime during the study. If the potential participant
      disagrees to consent then the staff will politely inquire about the possible reasons behind
      it and will offer reconsideration on next visit if possible. There will be no coercion,
      persuasion or resentment from the study staff on refusal to consent. One copy of the consent
      form will be handed to the patient along with important contact numbers.

      Questionnaire: research officer will fill the questionnaire with the help of patient and the
      attendants. The information which is not supplied by the participant will be attempted to
      retrieve from the medical records and hospital data registry.

      Assessment of outcomes Blood sampling Four trained phlebotomists will be utilized for blood
      sampling. The study staff will take the samples; label them with patients' study ID and
      medical record (MR) numbers, time and number of sample, and the biomarker being assessed.
      Separate tubes will be used for each biomarker. To ensure timely sampling for each patient a
      sheet with timed slots will be added to the patient's file to mark number of samples and
      their timings. The test tubes will be promptly delivered to the lab by the phlebotomist. Cost
      of blood testing of routine and additional cardiac biomarkers will be borne by the
      investigating team.

      Assessment of Infarct size 24hrs hsTnI: Blood sample will be drawn at 24hours of admission
      for peak HsTnI as surrogate for the infarct size.

      Transthoracic Echocardiogram: A post STEMI standard transthoracic echo will be performed on
      all patients during index hospitalization which included detailed assessment of ejection
      fraction and wall motion abnormality. At 30-days, re assessment of left ventricular (LV)
      function will be performed via 2D Echo.

      Cardiac MRI: Myocardial infarction can be visualized and quantified using inversion recovery
      imaging 10 to 15 minutes after intravenous administration of gadolinium contrast (late
      enhancement imaging). Infarct size is expressed as absolute mass or percent of left
      ventricular mass (mass [grams] = volume [mL] × myocardial density [1.05 grams/mL]). Other
      additional parameters such as left ventricular volumes, ejection fraction, micro vascular
      obstruction (MO) and myocardial salvage index (MSI) will also be obtained. Infarct size and
      late MO will be assessed in late gadolinium enhancement (LGE) short-axis images covering the
      whole left ventricle (LV) approximately 15 min after injection of gadolinium chelate.

      Assessment of Major adverse cardiovascular events (MACE):

      Patients will continue to get their routine standard care in the inpatient areas. After the
      discharge in cardiology clinics, they will continue to receive standard medical care
      including adjustments in drug regimens according to primary physician's opinion. For in
      hospital MACE, data regarding heart failure (HF), cardiogenic shock, re-MI and in hospital
      death will be calculated. At 30 day, data on re MI and death will be collected.

      Sample size Sample size is not determined using statistical power calculations. Sample size
      is determined by the number of available specimens of each cohort.

      STATISTICAL ANALYSIS Means ± SD will be reported for continuous variables if normally
      distributed or median ± IQR if not normally distributed. Percentages will be used for
      categorical variables. Boxplot will be to show the data range for each biomarkers.

      Scatter plots will be generated using the time between symptom onset time and sample
      collection time vs. biomarker values for each biomarker. PROC TRANSREG will be used to fit a
      curve to the data if applicable. Scatter plots will be generated using time between symptom
      onset time and sample collection time vs. change of biomarker values from previous time point
      for each biomarker. PROC TRANSREG will be used to fit a curve to the data if applicable.

      Scatter plots will also be generated using time between symptom onset time and sample
      collection time vs. percent change of biomarker values from previous time point for each
      biomarker. PROC TRANSREG will be used to fit a curve to the data if applicable.

      Regression Analysis Based on the above scatter plots, for each biomarker, a linear/nonlinear
      regression will be run using time between symptom onset time and collection time as dependent
      variable and using initial biomarker value, change of the biomarker value, age (in deciles),
      gender and any interaction terms of these variables as independent variables. Backward
      selection will be used to choose the best model for each biomarker.

      Multiple Biomarkers Analysis Change for each biomarker will be calculated at the presentation
      using biomarker value at presentation against corresponding limit of detection (LOD).

        1. Regressions will be run using time between symptom onset time and collection time as
           dependent variable and using initial biomarker value, change of the biomarker value, age
           (in deciles), gender and any interaction terms of these variables as independent
           variables. The best regression model selection based on the minimum of Akaike
           Information Criterion (AIC) will be chosen.

        2. Principle component analysis (11) will be used to determine all the principal components
           with Eigen values greater than 1 using the following variables: change of each the six
           biomarkers, age, gender.

      Regression using time between symptom onset time and collection time as dependent variable
      and principal components as independent variables will be run.

      A P-value &lt;0.05 will be taken as statistically significant. SAS version, 9.2 will be used for
      analysis.

      Sensitivity analysis: In the sensitivity analyses, we will use mixed effects Tobit model with
      random effects that will account for repeated measures of biomarker within the same subject,
      and compare the results with the main fixed-effects analysis. We will also conduct sub-group
      analyses according to type of treatment i.e. thrombolytic therapy vs. PCI.

      Secondary analysis: Estimates of first samples of the biomarkers (hsTnI, CS myoglobin, CK-Mb,
      MNV and gamma' fibrinogen) at the time of ER presentation will be used to calculate the
      biochemical onset time of MI using the same model. We will derive an equation using the
      regression coefficients of the biomarkers against their respective times of measurements. We
      will determine the discrimination and calibration (best fit) of the model with all these
      biomarkers combined or any of their combination compared to hsTnI only. If feasible, a
      nomogram will be developed using these regression coefficients to predict the biochemical MI
      onset time.

      Additional analysis: To analyze the associations of patient-reported symptom onset time and
      biochemical onset time separately with infarct size using HsTnI, 2D echo derived EF and CMR
      derived infarct size, in-hospital and 30-day MACE, we will use Cox proportional hazards
      models.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 15, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 30, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Biochemical myocardial infarction onset time comparison to patient reported symptom onset time</measure>
    <time_frame>24 hours</time_frame>
    <description>biochemical onset time using multiple measurements of hsTnI from each patient within 24 hours of presentation and compare this biochemical time to the patient-reported symptoms onset time as an indicator of coronary artery occlusion.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Prediction of time onset of myocaridal infarction</measure>
    <time_frame>24 hours</time_frame>
    <description>predict Biochemical occlusion at the time of presentation with the use of single sample of six different markers of myocardial injury i.e. hsTnI, h-FABP, γ' Fibrinogen, MNV, CS-Mb and CK-Mb.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Correlation of biologic ischemia onset time with infarct size</measure>
    <time_frame>7 days</time_frame>
    <description>Correlation of conventional ischemic time and biochemical ischemic time with infarct size using peak hsTnI value and CMR based infarct volume in grams</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Correlation of biologic ischemia onset time with adverse outcomes</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days</time_frame>
    <description>Correlation of conventional ischemic time and biochemical ischemic time with in-hospital and 30-days major adverse cardiac events ,MACE (latter defined as composite of heart failure, shock, re MI or death)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Mi Q Wave</condition>
  <condition>Coronary Artery Disease</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Biochemical markers</intervention_name>
    <description>Multiple biomarkers of myocaridial ishemia will be obtained serially to calculate thier time of their release according to their release kinetics</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Consecutive patients presenting at emergency of THI with diagnosis of STEMI within 24 hours
        of symptom onset will be assessed for eligibility.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  All adult males and females coming to the ER of the hospital with acute STEMI

          -  Both initial and follow up patients will be included

          -  Patients coming within the time frame of reperfusion therapy with primary PCI i.e.
             within 24 hours of patient reported onset of symptoms.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients receiving thrombolytic therapy as first mode of therapy outside hospital or
             inside the ER.

          -  Moderate to severe renal disease (Creatinine clearance&lt;40)

          -  Recent acute coronary syndrome (ACS) within last 14 days with troponin rise

          -  Post-CABG or PCI patients within 14 days of procedure

          -  Patients with cardiogenic shock and cardiac arrest, due to expected high mortality
             since these patients will not be available for follow up

          -  Patients incapable of providing reliable history due to impaired memory or other
             reasons
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Asad Z Pathan</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Tabba Heart Institute</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Asad Z Pathan, MD</last_name>
    <phone>00922136811841</phone>
    <phone_ext>1342</phone_ext>
    <email>asadzpathan@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Asadullah Bugti, MBBS</last_name>
    <phone>00923343667741</phone>
    <email>drasadullahbugti@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Tabba Heart Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Karachi</city>
        <state>Sind</state>
        <zip>75950</zip>
        <country>Pakistan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Saba Aijaz, MD</last_name>
      <phone>02136811863</phone>
      <phone_ext>1371</phone_ext>
      <email>Sabaxlent@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Asad Z Pathan, MD</last_name>
      <phone>02136811863</phone>
      <phone_ext>1343</phone_ext>
      <email>Asadzpathan@gmail.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Pakistan</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 5, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 11, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 15, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 15, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 15, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 19, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>MI</keyword>
  <keyword>CAD</keyword>
  <keyword>Biomarkers</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Coronary Artery Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myocardial Infarction</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Infarction</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

