<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04388488</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CIP2020021338</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04388488</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Connect TF - An Investigation of Function and Usability of a New Adaptable Socket System</brief_title>
  <official_title>Connect TF - An Investigation of Function and Usability of a New Adaptable Socket System for</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Össur Ehf</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Indiana University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Össur Ehf</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The primary objective of this investigation is to evaluate how the CONNECT TF compares to
      traditional handmade sockets, specifically that it provides reliable suspension and improved
      usability and comfort for the amputee, and that it enables single clinical visit for fitting.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Design:

      This clinical investigation will be of a single group non-randomized open label prospective
      repeated measures (ABBA) design comparing subject´s current conventional socket and the
      CONNECT TF. The subjects will be asked to use the CONNECT TF as their primary prosthesis for
      up to six weeks. Subject will be fitted with the same foot-pylon-knee prosthetic system as
      used with their current conventional socket, with the CONNECT TF socket.

      Procedures:

      There are four scheduled study events. At the initial visit, the first study event, for each
      subject a qualified researcher will obtain an informed consent. Prior to fitting the patient
      subject to CONNECT TF he/she will be asked to provide feedback and perform tasks on/using
      their current conventional prosthetic socket. The patient subjects will be fitted with the
      CONNECT TF within the standard methods of prosthetic fitting, alignment, introduction,
      training and walking on various terrain.

      The CPO (Certified Prosthetis/Orthotist) will conduct the fitting and aligning of the CONNECT
      TF.

      A Co-Investigator will time the fitting procedure; from unpacking the device until it is
      correctly adjusted and properly fit to the subject.

      Data on initial feedback on the device will be collected from the subjects using the
      instruments specified above. Afterwards an appointment at 2 weeks is made and the subjects
      leave the clinic on the device.

      If the fitting of CONNECT TF fails, i.e. the PI/CPO does not manage to fit the device
      properly or the subject cannot use the device as intended during training at the clinic, a
      new appointment is made, if the subject is willing to continue participation.

      The second event will be according to the appointment scheduled 2 weeks earlier. During this
      visit the same set of information will be gathered from/on the subjects as at the initial
      visit using the conventional socket. A 6 week follow up (6WFU) visit is scheduled and the
      subject leaves on the CONNECT TF socket.

      The third event will be according to the appointment scheduled at the previous visit. During
      this visit set of information will be gathered from/on the subjects as at the initial visit
      using the conventional socket. A final 6WFU visit is scheduled and the subjects are fitted
      back to and leave on their current conventional socket.

      The fourth event will be according to the appointment scheduled at the previous visit. During
      this visit set of information will be gathered from/on the subjects as at the initial visit
      using the conventional socket. End of study.

      Data analysis:

      The dataset will be assessed with inferential statistics based on the acceptance criteria for
      the data, as applicable.

      Outcomes at each time point will be visually inspected for normality using histograms and
      qq-plots. If the data are deemed to be normal the hypothesis will be tested using a
      two-tailed, paired, student's t-test for 2WFU evaluation and mixed models for the 6WFU
      evaluation. Non-normal data will be tested using the Wilcoxon signed-rank test.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">June 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>This clinical investigation will be of a single group non-randomized open label prospective repeated measures (ABBA) design.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Comprehensive Lower-limb Amputee Socket Survey (CLASS)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>CLASS is a self-report measure of prosthetic socket satisfaction for lower limb amputees, designed to provide an effective means of communication for the patient to describe with clarity, the quality of their socket fit during common activities. CLASS evaluates static and dynamic features of socket stability, suspension, comfort and appearance and has been reported to be a reliable, quick and easy report measure.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Prosthesis evaluation questionnaire - Residual limb health (PEQ- RLH)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>average of 6 item subscale from the PEQ</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Prosthesis evaluation questionnaire - Sounds (PEQ-Sounds)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>average of 2 item subscale from the PEQ</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mobility (2MWT)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>2 minute walking test</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Balance during ambulation (TUG)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Times up and go test</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Prosthesis User</condition>
  <condition>Amputation</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>CONNECT TF</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Trans-femoral amputees currently using a conventional handmade socket will be fitted with the CONNECT TF adaptable socket system for 6 weeks and their current existing conventional socket for 6 weeks, data collection on both sockets will be performed and outcomes compared.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>CONNECT TF adaptable socket system</intervention_name>
    <description>Prefabricated, adaptable socket system</description>
    <arm_group_label>CONNECT TF</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Any conventional handmade socket</intervention_name>
    <description>Subjects current socket</description>
    <arm_group_label>CONNECT TF</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Lower limb amputees

          -  Uni- or bilateral TF amputees

          -  40 &lt; body weight &lt; 125Kg

          -  Activity level: K1-K2;

          -  Liner size: 28-45;

          -  Max 1 user in sizes 28 and 45, respectively

          -  Residual limb parameters; perineum to distal end: 205 to 280 mm

          -  Older than 18 years

          -  Prosthetic users for more than 3 months

          -  Components of conventional socket functionally compatible to Össur components
             (foot-pylon-knee combination)

          -  Users understanding the function of the device

          -  Willing and able to participate in the study and follow the protocol

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Other amputees

          -  40&gt; body weight &gt; 125Kg

          -  Amputees with broken skin on the residual limb

          -  Younger than 18 years

          -  Prosthetic users for less than 3 months

          -  Using no liner

          -  Using a microprocessor controlled prosthetic knee not manufactured by Össur

          -  Users not understanding the function of the device
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Sashwati Roy, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Indiana University School of Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Steinþóra Jónsdóttir, MPH</last_name>
    <phone>003548665707</phone>
    <email>stjonsdottir@ossur.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Benedikt Þ Sigurjónsson, M.Sc.</last_name>
    <phone>00354 425 2314</phone>
    <email>bsigurjonsson@ossur.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Eskenazi Health</name>
      <address>
        <city>Indianapolis</city>
        <state>Indiana</state>
        <zip>46202</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jennifer L Mohnacky, MS</last_name>
      <phone>317-278-2720</phone>
      <email>jmohnack@iu.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>IU Health Comprehensive Wound Center at Methodist Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Indianapolis</city>
        <state>Indiana</state>
        <zip>46206-1367</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jennifer L Mohnacky, MS</last_name>
      <phone>317-278-2720</phone>
      <email>jmohnack@iu.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>April 30, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 11, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 14, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 11, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 11, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 14, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

