<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04380259</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MBTR-R Tel Aviv</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04380259</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Mindfulness-Based Trauma Recovery for Refugees (MBTR-R)</brief_title>
  <official_title>Mindfulness-Based Trauma Recovery for Refugees (MBTR-R): Efficacy, Safety and Mechanisms</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Haifa</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Haifa</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Worldwide, refugees and asylum seekers suffer at high rates from trauma- and stress-related
      mental health problems. The investigators thus developed Mindfulness-Based Trauma Recovery
      for Refugees (MBTR-R) - a 9-week, mindfulness- and compassion-based, trauma-sensitive and
      socio-culturally adapted, group intervention for refugees and asylum seekers. The overarching
      aims of the study were to, first, test whether MBTR-R is an efficacious and safe mental
      health intervention for traumatized refugees and asylum seekers with respect to stress- and
      trauma-related mental health outcomes; and, second, to test theorized mechanisms of action of
      MBTR-R. Accordingly, the investigators conducted a randomized waitlist-controlled trial among
      a community sample of female and male Eritrean asylum seekers in an urban post-displacement
      setting in the Middle East (Israel).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Broadly, the investigators aimed to assess whether MBTR-R is an efficacious and safe mental
      health intervention for traumatized asylum seekers. Aim I: The investigators predicted that,
      relative to a waitlist control condition, MBTR-R will lead to improved stress-and
      trauma-related mental health outcomes, including lower levels and rates of posttraumatic
      stress, depression, anxiety, and improved subjective well-being at post-intervention and
      5-week follow-up. Aim II: The investigators aimed to test, whether relative to the
      waitlist-control condition, MBTR-R was safe and thus not associated with participant-level
      clinically significant deterioration in any of the monitored primary mental health outcomes
      at post-intervention or at follow-up. In the event of adverse responding, the investigators
      planned to test whether key demographic factors or pre-existing vulnerability factors at
      pre-intervention that may predict participant-level deterioration or adverse responding to
      the intervention - so as to identify candidate contraindications for MBTR-R. Aim III: The
      investigators predicted that, relative to a waitlist control condition, MBTR-R will lead to
      changes in psycho-behavioral processes targeted by the intervention and implicated in
      vulnerability at pre-intervention, from pre-to-post intervention, measured in controlled
      behavioral and cognitive-experimental lab tasks or experience sampling measures, including
      measures of (a) self-compassion and self-criticism, (b) self-referential processing of fear,
      (c) avoidance, (d) emotional reactivity to trauma-related information and autobiographical
      memory, (e) impaired executive functions of trauma-related information processing in working
      memory. Aim IV: The investigators aimed to test whether, among the MBTR-R group,
      pre-to-post-intervention change and pre-intervention to follow-up change in mental health
      outcomes (Aim I) will be predicted or mediated by pre-to-post intervention change in the
      targeted psycho-behavioral processes.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 10, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 18, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 18, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Harvard Trauma Questionnaire (HTQ)</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from 1-week pre-intervention to 1-week post-intervention and change from 1-week pre-intervention to 5-weeks post-intervention</time_frame>
    <description>The Harvard Trauma Questionnaire (HTQ) is a 16-item self-report questionnaire to assess post-traumatic stress symptom severity (5-point Likert scale) with higher scores indicating greater post-traumatic stress severity (minimum scale score 1 and maximum scale score 5), HTQ mean cut-off score ≥ 2 is commonly used to identify categorical (diagnostic) symptom status of post-traumatic stress disorder</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Brief Patient Health Questionnaire (PHQ-9)</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from 1-week pre-intervention to 1-week post-intervention and change from 1-week pre-intervention to 5-weeks post-intervention</time_frame>
    <description>The brief Patient Health Questionnaire (PHQ-9) is a 9-item self-report questionnaire to assess depression symptom severity (5-point Likert scale) with higher scores indicating greater depression symptom severity (minimum scale score 0 and maximum scale score 36), PHQ-9 mean cut-off score ≥10 is commonly used to identify categorical (diagnostic) symptom status of depression</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Beck's Anxiety Inventory (BAI)</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from 1-week pre-intervention to 1-week post-intervention and change from 1-week pre-intervention to 5-weeks post-intervention</time_frame>
    <description>The Beck's Anxiety Inventory (BAI) is a 21-item self-report questionnaire to assess anxiety symptom severity (4-point Likert scale) with higher scores indicating greater anxiety symptom severity (minimum scale score 0 and maximum scale score 63), BAI total cut-off score ≥ 16 is commonly used to identify categorical (diagnostic) symptom status of anxiety disorder</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Brief Inventory of Thriving (BIT)</measure>
    <time_frame>1-week pre-intervention, 1-week post-intervention and 5-weeks post-intervention</time_frame>
    <description>One item of the 9-item self-report questionnaire Brief Inventory of Thriving (BIT) was used to assess subjective well-being (5-point Likert scale) with higher scores indicating greater subjective well-being (minimum score 1 and maximum score 5)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Post-Migration Living Difficulties Checklist (PMLD)</measure>
    <time_frame>1-week pre-intervention</time_frame>
    <description>The Post-Migration-Living-Difficulties Checklist (PMLD) is a 9-item self-report questionnaire to assess post-migration stress (5-point Likert scale) with higher scores indicating greater post-migration stress (minimum scale score 1 and maximum scale score 5)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The State Shame and Guilt Scale (SSGS)</measure>
    <time_frame>1-week pre-intervention, 1-week post-intervention and 5-weeks post-intervention</time_frame>
    <description>The State Shame and Guilt Scale (SSGS) is a 15-item self-report questionnaire to assess state shame and guilt (5-point Likert scale) with higher scores indicating greater levels of state shame, guilt and pride (minimum scale score 15 and maximum scale score 75)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The Short Self Compassion Scale (SSCS)</measure>
    <time_frame>1-week pre-intervention, 1-week post-intervention and 5-weeks post-intervention</time_frame>
    <description>The Short Self-Compassion Scale SSCS is a 12-item self-report questionnaire to assess different facets of self-compassion (5-point Likert scale) with higher scores indicating greater levels of self-compassion (minimum scale score 1 and maximum scale score 5)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The Five Facets Mindfulness Questionnaire (FFMQ)</measure>
    <time_frame>1-week pre-intervention, 1-week post-intervention and 5-weeks post-intervention</time_frame>
    <description>The Five Facets of Mindfulness Questionnaire (FFMQ) is a self-report questionnaire to assess different facets of trait mindfulness (5-point Likert scale) with higher scores indicating greater levels of trait mindfulness (minimum scale score 1 and maximum scale score 5)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Moral Injury Event Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>1-week pre-intervention, 1-week post-intervention and 5-weeks post-intervention</time_frame>
    <description>The Moral Injury Event Scale is a self-report questionnaire to assess moral injury (6-point Likert scale) with higher scores indicating greater levels of moral injury (minimum scale score 1 and maximum scale score 6)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Trauma Cue Exposure Task</measure>
    <time_frame>1-week pre-intervention, 1-week post-intervention</time_frame>
    <description>The Trauma Cue Exposure Task measures behavioral avoidance in response to trauma cues</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Autobiographical Memory Recall Task</measure>
    <time_frame>1-week pre-intervention, 1-week post-intervention</time_frame>
    <description>The Autobiographical Memory Recall Task measures avoidance in response to recalling a traumatic autobiographical memory</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adapted Sternberg Working Memory Task</measure>
    <time_frame>1-week pre-intervention, 1-week post-intervention</time_frame>
    <description>The Adapted Sternberg Working Memory Task measures working memory processing of trauma- and stress-related words versus positive words</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Self-Referential Encoding Task (SRET) of Self-Compassion and Self-Criticism</measure>
    <time_frame>1-week pre-intervention, 1-week post-intervention</time_frame>
    <description>The SRET measures self-referential processing of self-criticism and self-compassion</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Single Experience and Self-Implicit Association Task (SES-IAT)</measure>
    <time_frame>1-week pre-intervention, 1-week post-intervention</time_frame>
    <description>The SES-IAT measures self-referential processing of fear</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Experience Sampling of State Mindfulness</measure>
    <time_frame>15-minutes pre-intervention session and 15-minutes post-intervention session</time_frame>
    <description>3-item experience sample (5-point Likert scale) of state mindfulness (minimum score 3 maximum score 15), higher scores indicate greater levels of state mindfulness</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Experience Sampling of Cognitive Avoidance</measure>
    <time_frame>15-minutes pre-intervention session</time_frame>
    <description>1-item experience sample (5-point Likert scale) of cognitive avoidance (minimum score 1 maximum score 5), higher scores indicate greater levels of cognitive avoidance</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Experience Sampling of Negative Repetitive Thinking</measure>
    <time_frame>15-minutes pre-intervention session</time_frame>
    <description>1-item experience sample (5-point Likert scale) of negative repetitive thinking (minimum score 1 maximum score 5), higher scores indicate greater levels of negative repetitive thinking</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Experience Sampling of Emotion</measure>
    <time_frame>15-minutes pre-intervention session and 15-minutes post-intervention session</time_frame>
    <description>4-item experience sample (5-point Likert scale) of the emotions happy, calm, sad and nervous/tense (minimum score 4 maximum score 20), higher scores indicate greater levels of the emotions happy, calm, sad and nervous/tense</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Experience Sampling of Formal and Informal Mindfulness Practice</measure>
    <time_frame>15-minutes pre-intervention session</time_frame>
    <description>2-item experience sample number of formal and informal mindfulness practice during the past week, higher scores indicate greater number of mindfulness practices during the past week</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Experience Sampling of Self-Compassion</measure>
    <time_frame>15-minutes pre-intervention session</time_frame>
    <description>1-item experience sample (5-point Likert scale) of negative self-compassion (minimum score 1 maximum score 5), higher scores indicate greater levels of self-compassion</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Experience Sampling of Depression</measure>
    <time_frame>15-minutes pre-intervention session</time_frame>
    <description>1-item experience sample (5-point Likert scale) of depression (minimum score 1 maximum score 5), higher scores indicate greater levels of depression</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Experience Sampling of Anxiety</measure>
    <time_frame>15-minutes pre-intervention session</time_frame>
    <description>1-item experience sample (5-point Likert scale) of anxiety (minimum score 1 maximum score 5), higher scores indicate greater levels of anxiety</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">158</enrollment>
  <condition>Stress Disorders, Post-Traumatic</condition>
  <condition>Stress Related Disorder</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>MBTR-R (Mindfulness-Based Trauma Recovery for Refugees)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Mindfulness-based group intervention consisting of nine 2.5-hour weekly sessions.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Waitlist-Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Following the 9-week waitlist period and 1-week post-intervention assessment, participants randomized to waitlist-control were offered an equivalent group intervention (i.e., 22.5 total hours, group instructor and cultural mediator, psychoeducation and low-intensity cognitive behavior therapy skill training, relaxation techniques).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Mindfulness-Based Trauma Recovery for Refugees (MBTR-R)</intervention_name>
    <description>MBTR-R is a mindfulness-based group intervention of nine 2.5-hour weekly sessions. MBTR-R format and structure parallel MBSR (mindfulness-based stress reduction) and MBCT (mindfulness-based cognitive therapy). MBTR-R includes systematic training in formal and informal mindfulness practices with trauma-sensitive adaptations and home practice. Trauma-sensitive adaptations include a &quot;safe place&quot; practice, psychoeducation about posttraumatic stress, stress reactivity, as well as self-compassion practices to cope with fear, self-judgement, guilt and shame. Socio-cultural adaptations include real-time linguistic translation of each session by a cultural mediator from the refugee community and use of socio-culturally specific metaphors. MBTR-R groups were conducted for men and women separately and delivered in an accessible, &quot;safe space&quot; in the local refugee community. Group meetings included a shared meal of traditional Eritrean food and female participants were offered free child care.</description>
    <arm_group_label>MBTR-R (Mindfulness-Based Trauma Recovery for Refugees)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Eritrean refugee or asylum seeker living in Israel

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  active suicidality

          -  current psychotic symptoms

          -  current mental health treatment (e.g. psychotherapy, participation in psycho-social
             support group)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Amit Bernstein</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Haifa</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Kuchinate</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tel Aviv</city>
        <state>Merkaz</state>
        <zip>637909</zip>
        <country>Israel</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Israel</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>April 26, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 5, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 8, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 5, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 5, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 8, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Asylum Seekers, Anxiety, Compassion, Depression, Mindfulness, PTSD, Post-Migration Stress, Refugees, Trauma</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Stress Disorders, Post-Traumatic</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

