<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04384120</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>13130</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04384120</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>BFR Therapy in Patients With Rotator Cuff Tears</brief_title>
  <official_title>Use of Blood Flow Restriction (BFR) Therapy in Patients With Rotator Cuff Tears Treated Nonoperatively or Operatively: a Randomized Controlled Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Henry Ford Health System</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Henry Ford Health System</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to examine the effect of utilizing blood flow restriction (BFR)
      therapy in patients treated both non operatively and operatively for rotator cuff tears
      (RCT). BFR has been proposed to work by restricting arterial inflow leading to an oxygen
      depleted environment and the ability to induce muscle adaption at lower maximum repetition
      via reactive hyperemia. Muscle atrophy occurs following rotator cuff tear. Thus, physical
      therapy is used to regain strength with the ultimate goal of returning to activity.

      The goal of this investigation is to determine if using BFR during therapy for
      non-operatively managed and operatively managed rotator cuff tears would lead to increased
      and expedited strength gains. Additionally the investigators would like to determine if BFR
      is beneficial in preventing muscle atrophy and fatty infiltration often seen in the setting
      of rotator cuff tear, as it is known that cuff tears can subject the muscles to degenerative
      changes and these patients are at risk for poorer clinical outcomes. The investigators will
      also look at patient reported outcomes metrics and pain scores to determine if BFR has a
      significant impact on the patient experience surrounding rotator cuff tear after both
      nonoperative treatment with therapy and operative treatment with surgical repair and
      peri-operative rehabilitation.

      The investigators hypothesize that the BFR group will have significantly greater strength
      gains at all time points. Previous studies have shown that BFR has potential in increasing
      muscle torque generation and cross sectional area in the first six months following anterior
      cruciate ligament (ACL) reconstruction. While there have not been as many studies
      investigating the use of BFR following upper extremity surgery, previous research has
      demonstrate that BFR can be useful both proximal and distal to the targeted muscle groups in
      the upper extremity. In addition to the paucity of research on post-operative BFR following
      rotator cuff repair (RCR), there is no evidence on pre-operative use as well. The
      investigators believe that the use of BFR in the perioperative period surrounding rotator
      cuff tear and repair has the potential to significantly decrease muscle atrophy and lead to
      faster, more substantial strength gains and less muscle atrophy and fatty infiltration.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Patients who are seen in clinic for rotator cuff pathology will undergo treatment for their
      rotator cuff based on a shared-decision making process with the orthopedic surgeon,
      irrespective of this study. Once a treatment plan is in place, the patient will be introduced
      to this study and presented with the opportunity to participate. If the patient agrees, a
      formal consent process will take place in clinic and the patient will undergo initial,
      baseline testing of strength, range of motion, pain scores, and patient reported outcome
      scores.

      Therefore patients will be either in the nonoperative arm or the operative arm of this study.
      Within each arm, patients will be randomized via computer to be placed in either the blood
      flow restriction (BFR) cohort or the traditional (non-BFR cohort). Patients will
      prospectively undergo rotator cuff rehabilitation using BFR or conventional therapy by
      physical therapists with extensive experience in rotator cuff rehabilitation who will undergo
      training on use of BFR.

      The nonoperative group will be given identical rehabilitation protocols, with the only
      difference being the use of a BFR cuff during rehabilitation for the BFR cohort. Similarly,
      the operative group will be given identical rehabilitation protocols, with the only
      difference being the use of a BFR cuff during rehabilitation for the BFR cohort.

      Patients undergoing operative rotator cuff repair (RCR) will undergo preoperative
      rehabilitation prior to surgery for two weeks. Due to limitations of health insurance
      coverage of physical therapy sessions, the two weeks of preoperative &quot;prehab&quot; will consist of
      a structured home exercise program that is taught to the patient by a physical therapist
      during one session and recorded on a physical therapy (PT) diary by the patient during the
      two weeks leading up to surgery. Patients will be provided video instruction and training on
      how to conduct the exercises and this will also be done with and without the use of BFR
      depending on group allocation (via randomization). Additionally, warning signs for BFR cuff
      intolerance such as increased pain, swelling, numbness/tingling of the arm will be
      communicated to the patient. Following surgery patients will immediately be started in a
      formal physical therapy regimen as an outpatient. Therapy will consist of a structured
      program progressing from range of motion, to strength training and then functional tests.
      Patients will remain in their allocated BFR or non-BFR group.

      Protocol as follows, both groups will use the same protocol with the only difference being
      use of BFR:

      For surgical patients:

      • Preop: Patients will undergo a home program consisting of isometric exercises including
      shoulder extension, abduction, external rotation and internal rotation pushing against a
      wall.

      For both surgical and non-surgical patients:

        -  Post-op weeks 0-8: Passive shoulder range of motion (ROM) only

             -  Sling immobilization with active elbow, wrist and hand ROM

             -  Passive ROM only of shoulder including pendulums, supine elevation in scapular
                plane, external rotation with arm at side.

        -  8-12 weeks being more active range of motion

             -  Discontinue sling

             -  Being active exercises including prone row, standing internal/external rotation
                with bands, wall slides into shoulder flexion

        -  Weeks 12-20: Strength and function o Sidelying shoulder external rotation, increase
           resistance band exercises

      Throughout this protocol patients will have a pre-operative visit, an early 2 week post
      operative visit to check range of motion and wound healing, a six week visit to monitor range
      of motion and potentially clear for active ROM and sling discontinuation, and a three month
      visit prior to clearance to being return to more aggressive activity. Strength and range of
      motion will be recorded at each of these visits in order to assess the primary endpoint.

      Outcomes:

        -  Primary Outcome:

           o Strength to be measured via dynamometer at each clinic visit

        -  Secondary Outcomes:

             -  Range of motion via goniometer

             -  Pain via visual analogue scale (VAS) pain scale at each visit

             -  Patient reported outcomes scores at each visit

             -  Fatty infiltration and muscle atrophy measured via ultrasound and compared to
                pre-operative imaging

      Plan to recruit patients starting in June 2020. Will enroll patients and collect data from
      June-2020 to May 2021. Manuscript writing and submission to occur in June 2021.

        -  Data analysis: The primary endpoint of this study was a maximum repetition total work
           deficit of 15% between the BFR and control group as measured by dynamometer. This was
           based on previous data showing that a strength deficit of 15% represents a clinically
           significant difference that is not likely attributable to limb dominance. Work deficit
           was calculated in each group by comparing the operative leg with the nonoperative leg to
           obtain a deficit percent. A power analysis was performed before the study to assess the
           number of patients needed to detect a 15% total work deficit between the BFR and control
           groups. With a power of 80% (beta level ¼ 0.80, alpha level ¼ 0.05), a sample size of 34
           (17 patients per group) was obtained. Data will be provided to and analyzed by trained
           statisticians to determine differences in primary and secondary outcomes.

        -  All continuous data will be analyzed using independent 2-group t tests and reported as
           means ± standard deviations. Categorical data will be compared between the 2 groups
           using chi-square tests and reported as counts and percentages. A preliminary test to
           confirm the quality of variances will be conducted prior to utilizing the t test to
           confirm the appropriate statistical analysis. Nonparametric equivalents Wilcoxon
           rank-sum and Fisher exact tests will be used as needed for nonnormal distributions and
           low variable numbers, respectively. A multivariable regression analysis was performed to
           assess for potential confounding demographic variables.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">June 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Care Provider, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Strength</measure>
    <time_frame>through study completion, an average of 12 months post-operative follow-up</time_frame>
    <description>Strength will be quantified through dynamometers</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Range of Motion</measure>
    <time_frame>through study completion, an average of 12 months post-operative follow-up</time_frame>
    <description>Range of motion of the shoulder will be assessed using a goniometer</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pain Score</measure>
    <time_frame>through study completion, an average of 12 months post-operative follow-up</time_frame>
    <description>Pain will be assessed using a visual analogue scale (VAS), a pain scale from 0-10 where higher numbers indicate worse pain</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient reported outcomes measurement information system</measure>
    <time_frame>through study completion, an average of 12 months post-operative follow-up</time_frame>
    <description>Patient reported outcome measurement information system (PROMIS) scores will be collected through a series of questionnaires from the PROMIS domain of physical function, upper extremity, and depression. These scores are standardized T-scores with the mean set at 50 and the standard deviation set at 10.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Rotator Cuff Integrity</measure>
    <time_frame>through study completion, an average of 12 months post-operative follow-up</time_frame>
    <description>Fatty infiltration and muscle atrophy of the rotator cuff will be measured by ultrasound and compared to preoperative imaging</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>ASES Outcome Score</measure>
    <time_frame>through study completion, an average of 12 months post-operative follow-up</time_frame>
    <description>American shoulder and elbow surgeons standardized shoulder assessment form is a 100-point scale that consists of a pain scale worth 50 points and ten activities of daily living worth 50 points.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Blood Flow Restriction</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Rotator Cuff Rehabilitation Using BFR</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients with rotator cuff tears who plan for either nonoperative treatment with physical therapy or operative treatment with arthroscopic rotator cuff repair (RCR) surgery will be randomized to undergo rehabilitation using blood flow restriction cuffs.
Patients who elect for nonoperative treatment of their rotator cuff tear will undergo traditional therapy using blood flow restriction cuffs.
Patients who elect for RCR will undergo preoperative and postoperative traditional therapy using blood flow restriction cuffs.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Rotator Cuff Rehabilitation Without BFR</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients with rotator cuff tears who plan for either nonoperative treatment with physical therapy or operative treatment with arthroscopic rotator cuff repair (RCR) surgery will be randomized to undergo rehabilitation without using blood flow restriction cuffs.
Patients who elect for nonoperative treatment of their rotator cuff tear will undergo traditional therapy without using blood flow restriction cuffs.
Patients who elect for RCR will undergo preoperative and postoperative traditional therapy without using blood flow restriction cuffs.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Blood Flow Restriction Therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>Blood flow restriction cuffs which are FDA approved will be provided to patients randomized into the BFR group. Patients will be provided video instruction and training on how to conduct the traditional therapy exercises with the use of BFR.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Rotator Cuff Rehabilitation Using BFR</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Traditional Therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients will be provided video instruction and training on how to conduct the traditional therapy exercises.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Rotator Cuff Rehabilitation Without BFR</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  patients aged 18-80 who suffered a rotator cuff tear

          -  Patients undergoing arthroscopic rotator cuff repair

          -  Patients undergoing nonoperative treatment with physical therapy

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  o Subjects will be excluded if they are undergoing revision rotator cuff repair,
             history of DVT, neurovascular injury, unable to tolerate BFR treatment, unable to
             complete physical therapy, peripheral vascular disease
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Lafi S Khalil, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Henry Ford Health System</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Lafi S Khalil, MD</last_name>
    <phone>313-932-5657</phone>
    <email>lkhalil2@hfhs.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Joseph S Tramer, MD</last_name>
    <phone>216-536-2904</phone>
    <email>jtramer1@hfhs.org</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Henry Ford Health Systems</name>
      <address>
        <city>Detroit</city>
        <state>Michigan</state>
        <zip>48202</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Clark BC, Manini TM, Hoffman RL, Williams PS, Guiler MK, Knutson MJ, McGlynn ML, Kushnick MR. Relative safety of 4 weeks of blood flow-restricted resistance exercise in young, healthy adults. Scand J Med Sci Sports. 2011 Oct;21(5):653-62. doi: 10.1111/j.1600-0838.2010.01100.x. Epub 2010 Mar 11.</citation>
    <PMID>21917016</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dankel SJ, Jessee MB, Abe T, Loenneke JP. The Effects of Blood Flow Restriction on Upper-Body Musculature Located Distal and Proximal to Applied Pressure. Sports Med. 2016 Jan;46(1):23-33. doi: 10.1007/s40279-015-0407-7. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26446893</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hamano N, Yamamoto A, Shitara H, Ichinose T, Shimoyama D, Sasaki T, Kobayashi T, Kakuta Y, Osawa T, Takagishi K. Does successful rotator cuff repair improve muscle atrophy and fatty infiltration of the rotator cuff? A retrospective magnetic resonance imaging study performed shortly after surgery as a reference. J Shoulder Elbow Surg. 2017 Jun;26(6):967-974. doi: 10.1016/j.jse.2016.10.016. Epub 2017 Feb 15.</citation>
    <PMID>28214172</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kuzel BR, Grindel S, Papandrea R, Ziegler D. Fatty infiltration and rotator cuff atrophy. J Am Acad Orthop Surg. 2013 Oct;21(10):613-23. doi: 10.5435/JAAOS-21-10-613. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24084435</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Madarame H, Sasaki K, Ishii N. Endocrine responses to upper- and lower-limb resistance exercises with blood flow restriction. Acta Physiol Hung. 2010 Jun;97(2):192-200. doi: 10.1556/APhysiol.97.2010.2.5.</citation>
    <PMID>20511128</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Melis B, DeFranco MJ, Chuinard C, Walch G. Natural history of fatty infiltration and atrophy of the supraspinatus muscle in rotator cuff tears. Clin Orthop Relat Res. 2010 Jun;468(6):1498-505. doi: 10.1007/s11999-009-1207-x.</citation>
    <PMID>20094853</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Noordin S, McEwen JA, Kragh JF Jr, Eisen A, Masri BA. Surgical tourniquets in orthopaedics. J Bone Joint Surg Am. 2009 Dec;91(12):2958-67. doi: 10.2106/JBJS.I.00634. Review. Erratum in: J Bone Joint Surg Am. 2010 Feb;92(2):442.</citation>
    <PMID>19952261</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ohta H, Kurosawa H, Ikeda H, Iwase Y, Satou N, Nakamura S. Low-load resistance muscular training with moderate restriction of blood flow after anterior cruciate ligament reconstruction. Acta Orthop Scand. 2003 Feb;74(1):62-8.</citation>
    <PMID>12635796</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Takarada Y, Takazawa H, Ishii N. Applications of vascular occlusion diminish disuse atrophy of knee extensor muscles. Med Sci Sports Exerc. 2000 Dec;32(12):2035-9.</citation>
    <PMID>11128848</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wernbom M, Augustsson J, Raastad T. Ischemic strength training: a low-load alternative to heavy resistance exercise? Scand J Med Sci Sports. 2008 Aug;18(4):401-16. doi: 10.1111/j.1600-0838.2008.00788.x. Epub 2008 May 3. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18466185</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 1, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 11, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 12, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 11, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 11, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 13, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Henry Ford Health System</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Lafi Khalil</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Rotator Cuff Injuries</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>per request</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

