<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04388124</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2018/350/HP</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04388124</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>VASCULAR AND RENAL IMPACT OF ENDOTHELIN-1 RECEPTOR BLOCKADE IN PATIENTS WITH RESISTANT ARTERIAL HYPERTENSION</brief_title>
  <acronym>ENDOTHELIN-2</acronym>
  <official_title>VASCULAR AND RENAL IMPACT OF ENDOTHELIN-1 RECEPTOR BLOCKADE IN PATIENTS WITH RESISTANT ARTERIAL HYPERTENSION</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University Hospital, Rouen</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University Hospital, Rouen</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The management of patients with resistant arterial hypertension, who are characterized by a
      very high cardiovascular risk, remains a major therapeutic issue. The use of endothelin-1
      (ET-1) receptor antagonists, in addition to lowering blood pressure, may also improve
      endothelial function in these patients. The objective of this study is to assess the vascular
      impact of an ET-1 receptor antagonist on vascular function and systemic and central
      hemodynamics in patients with resistant arterial hypertension and ensure their good renal
      tolerance.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">September 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
    <masking_description>Modification of the pharmaceutical form, removal from the primary packaging and repackaging-&gt; tablet of Bosentan will be encapsuled. The pharmaceutical form of placebo and bosentant will be identical</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>assess the effect of ET-1 receptor antagonist administration during 8 weeks on endothelial function in patients with resistant hypertension.</measure>
    <time_frame>through study completion, an average of 22 months</time_frame>
    <description>8-week change in amplitude of endothelium-dependent radial artery dilatation with sustained increase in blood flow</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>assess the effect of the administration of an ET-1 receptor antagonist during 8 weeks on systemic and central hemodynamics</measure>
    <time_frame>through study completion, an average of 22 months</time_frame>
    <description>8 week change in peripheral and central arterial pressures and arterial stiffness</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>assess the effect of the administration of an ET-1 receptor antagonist during 8 weeks on local concentrations of endothelial factors during a sustained increase of the blood flow</measure>
    <time_frame>through study completion, an average of 22 months</time_frame>
    <description>8-week change in local concentrations of NO, EETs and ET-1 with sustained increase in blood flow</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>assess the effect of the administration of an ET-1 receptor antagonist during 8 weeks on the renal function of patients with resistant hypertension.</measure>
    <time_frame>through study completion, an average of 22 months</time_frame>
    <description>Variation in 8 weeks of natriuresis and measured glomerular filtration rate (DTPA labeled by the technetium 99m)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">24</enrollment>
  <condition>Resistant Hypertension</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patient will receive placebo for 56 days: 2 capsules of 62.5 mg per day for 27 days +/-1 day, 2 capsules of 125 mg per day for 27 days +/-1 day.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Bosentan</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patient will receive Bosentan for 56 days: 2 capsules of 62.5 mg per day for 27 days +/-1 day, 2 capsules of 125 mg per day for 27 days +/-1 day.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Bosentan</intervention_name>
    <description>vascular assesment Clinical exam urinary analysis blood results natriuresis and measured glomerular filtration rate</description>
    <arm_group_label>Bosentan</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Placebo</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  age between 30 and 80 years old

          -  Patients with resistant hypertension defined according to the criteria recognized by
             the French Society of Hypertension (SFHTA): arterial pressure greater than or equal to
             140 and / 90 mm Hg under triple antihypertensive therapy at optimal dose comprising at
             least one diuretic pendant at less than 4 weeks.

          -  Patients with resistant hypertension confirmed by self-measurement (≥135 / 85 mmHg on
             average) or by ambulatory blood pressure measurement (mean of 24h ≥130 / 80 mmHg).

          -  Hemoglobin level ≥ 12 g / dL

          -  For women of childbearing potential, reliable methods of contraception (as defined by
             the WHO-Pearl Index) should be used (hormonal contraception should not be the only
             contraceptive method used during bosentan treatment).

          -  For postmenopausal women: confirmatory diagnosis (non-medically induced amenorrhea for
             at least 12 months and age greater than 45, before the inclusion visit)

          -  Patient who read and understood the newsletter and signed the consent form

          -  Patient affiliated to a social security scheme

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with hypertension

          -  Patients with secondary arterial hypertension other than sleep apnea syndrome or
             chronic renal failure stage 2 or 3.

          -  Patients with hypertension greater than or equal to 180 and / or 110mmHg

          -  Chronic renal failure stage 4 and 5 (defined by DFG CKD-EPI &lt;30 ml / min / 1,73m²)

          -  Renal transplant patient XML File Identifier: CEyMau8sPo+QFyOLD1ZEY3ZGFow= Page 11/22

          -  Orthostatic hypotension (decreased SBP&gt; 20mmHg and / or DBP&gt; 10mmHg occurring within 3
             minutes of standing).

          -  Contra-indication to NATISPRAY 0.30 mg / dose, oral spray solution (including nitrate
             hypersensitivity) in accordance with the NATISPRAY

        SPC:

          -  shock, severe hypotension,

          -  in combination with sildenafil

          -  obstructive cardiomyopathy,

          -  inferior court inferior myocardial infarction with right ventricular extension, except
             in case of evidence of left ventricular failure,

          -  intracranial hypertension,

             • Contra-indication to BOSENTAN MYLAN 62.5 mg and 125 mg filmcoated tablets:

          -  Hypersensitivity to the active substance or to any of the excipients listed in the SPC
             Moderate to severe hepatic insufficiency corresponding to class B or C of the
             Child-Pugh classification

          -  Serum levels of liver aminotransferases, ASAT and / or ALAT&gt; 3 times the upper limit
             of normal at start of treatment (results less than 3 months old).

          -  Association with ciclosporin A

               -  Known allergy to cellulose

               -  Patients treated with: tacrolimus or sirolimus, fluconazole or other CYP2C9 or
                  CYP3A4 inhibitors, glibenclamide, rifampicin, antiretroviral drugs including
                  lopinavir + ritonavir, warfarin, simvastatin, ketoconazole, epoprostenol,
                  sildenafil and digoxin

               -  Pregnant, breastfeeding woman, or woman of childbearing potential not using
                  reliable methods of contraception (hormonal contraception should not be the only
                  contraceptive method used during bosentan treatment) or no proven reliable
                  effective contraception;

               -  Person deprived of liberty by an administrative or judicial decision or person
                  placed under the protection of justice, under tutorship or curatorship

               -  Patient participating or having participated in the 4 weeks prior to inclusion in
                  a clinical trial
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <verification_date>May 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 11, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 13, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 14, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 13, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 13, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 14, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>endothelin-1</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hypertension</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Bosentan</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

