<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04385355</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ECRMGTCP2020</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04385355</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Influence of the Design of the Transmucosal Abutment on the Periimplant Bone Level</brief_title>
  <official_title>Influence of the Design of the Transmucosal Abutment on the Marginal Periimplant Bone Loss. Randomized Clinical Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Santiago de Compostela</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Mozo Grau Ticare Implants</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Santiago de Compostela</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The objective of this study is to evaluate the radiographic changes on the marginal
      peri-implant bone level on bone level implants with a narrower transmucosal abutment, in
      comparison to the conventional abutment, both of 3mm height
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Patients will receive from one to eight bone-level implants according to their rehabilitation
      necessity and transmucosal abutments will be connected the day of the surgery. The control
      group will receive conventional transmucosal abutments while the test group will receive TCP
      abutments, with a narrower design.

      Results will be evaluated initially 6 and 12 months after the connection of the definitive
      prostheses, and finally 3 years later.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">September 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 1, 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 1, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>For each participant on the test group will be another participant on the control group</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>None of the participants or the outcomes assessor will know the device (transmucosal abutment) received. The care provider will connect the transmucosal abutment while the surgery, after opening the randomization envelope; and the investigator will identify the participant's group while analysing the radiographs.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Radiographic marginal periimplant bone level changes</measure>
    <time_frame>from baseline (connection of the definitive abutment) to 6 and 12 months after the definitive prostheses will be connected, and finally 3 years later</time_frame>
    <description>Measured as the distance from the bone crest to the first implant-to-bone contact. This will be assessed on parallelized periapical radiographies</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Probing pocket depth</measure>
    <time_frame>6 and 12 months after the definitive prostheses will be connected, and finally 3 years later</time_frame>
    <description>measured with a CP12 probe as the distance from the soft tissue margin to the bottom of the peri-implant pocket</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Papilla refill</measure>
    <time_frame>6 and 12 months after the definitive prostheses will be connected, and finally 3 years later</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluated according to the Jemt 1997 index</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Bleeding on probing</measure>
    <time_frame>6 and 12 months after the definitive prostheses will be connected, and finally 3 years later</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluated according to the Mombelli 1987 index, presence of bleeding after probing</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Plaque index</measure>
    <time_frame>6 and 12 months after the definitive prostheses will be connected, and finally 3 years later</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluated according to the Mombelli 1987 index, presence of plaque</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient Reported Outcomes Measurements</measure>
    <time_frame>6 and 12 months after the definitive prostheses will be connected, and finally 3 years later</time_frame>
    <description>Using a visual analoge scale from 1 to 10 to evaluate patient's satisfaction parameters related to the aesthetics, masticatory ability, confort, general satisfaction and phonetics</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse effects frequency</measure>
    <time_frame>6 and 12 months after the definitive prostheses will be connected, and finally 3 years later</time_frame>
    <description>Presence of adverse effects during the follow-up, such as fracture of the implant or the prosthetic unit or presence of periimplantitis or mucositis</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">36</enrollment>
  <condition>Peri-implant Marginal Bone Loss</condition>
  <condition>Peri-implant Bone Level</condition>
  <condition>Transmucosal Abutment Design</condition>
  <condition>Peri-implant Bone Loss</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Control group will receive an intermediate transmucosal abutment with conventional diameter and 3mm height, once the implants are placed.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Test Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Test group will receive an intermediate transmucosal abutment with a TCP design, narrower than the conventional one, of 3mm height, once the implants are placed</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Conventional transmucosal abutment design</intervention_name>
    <description>The macroscopic design of the intermediate transmucosal abutment will be evaluated on terms of the marginal peri-implant bone levels using two identical devices, if only being the test device narrower than the control one</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Narrow transmucosal abutment design</intervention_name>
    <description>The macroscopic design of the intermediate transmucosal abutment will be evaluated on terms of the marginal peri-implant bone levels using two identical devices, if only being the test device narrower than the control one</description>
    <arm_group_label>Test Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Absence of systemic and periodontal pathology, over 18 years of age, with a plaque
             index below 25%.

          -  Absence of at least one tooth, with natural adjacent teeth, allowing a prosthetic
             rehabilitation with an osseointegrated implant and a prosthetic unit.

          -  Adequate bone quality available, allowing placement of MOZO GRAU® implants InHex STD
             QUATTRO with diameters of 3.75 mm or 4.25 mm and lengths of 8, 10 and 11.5 mm.

          -  Natural teeth or implants with fixed restoration as antagonists.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Systemic factors:

               -  Continuous administration of systemic medication that can interfere with the bone
                  metabolism or medical conditions requiring prolonged use of steroids and / or
                  medications that can interfere with bone metabolism.

               -  History of leukocyte dysfunction and deficiency, immunodeficiency syndromes,
                  kidney failure or bone metabolic disorders, such as osteoporosis.

               -  Physical disability that may interfere with proper oral hygiene.

               -  Use of any investigational medication or device within the previous 30 days to
                  implant surgery in the study.

               -  Alcoholism or drug addiction

               -  Smoker of more than 10 cigarettes per day.

               -  Conditions or circumstances that could prevent compliance with participation in
                  study or interfere with the analysis of results, such as a history of breach or
                  unreliability.

        Local factors:

          -  History of local radiotherapy.

          -  Bruxism.

          -  Diseases that affect the oral mucosa, such as oral lichen planus.

          -  Untreated periodontitis.

          -  Persistent intraoral infection.

          -  Post-extraction alveoli not cured (less than 6 weeks after extraction).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Lucia Maceiras</last_name>
    <phone>+0034676780483</phone>
    <email>luciamaceiraspombo@outlook.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Santiago de Compostela</name>
      <address>
        <city>Santiago De Compostela</city>
        <state>La Coruña</state>
        <zip>15782</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Spain</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Alves CC, Muñoz F, Cantalapiedra A, Ramos I, Neves M, Blanco J. Marginal bone and soft tissue behavior following platform switching abutment connection/disconnection--a dog model study. Clin Oral Implants Res. 2015 Sep;26(9):983-91. doi: 10.1111/clr.12385. Epub 2014 Apr 16.</citation>
    <PMID>24735458</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Berglundh T, Lindhe J. Dimension of the periimplant mucosa. Biological width revisited. J Clin Periodontol. 1996 Oct;23(10):971-3.</citation>
    <PMID>8915028</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Blanco J, Pico A, Caneiro L, Nóvoa L, Batalla P, Martín-Lancharro P. Effect of abutment height on interproximal implant bone level in the early healing: A randomized clinical trial. Clin Oral Implants Res. 2018 Jan;29(1):108-117. doi: 10.1111/clr.13108. Epub 2017 Dec 8.</citation>
    <PMID>29222809</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ericsson I, Persson LG, Berglundh T, Marinello CP, Lindhe J, Klinge B. Different types of inflammatory reactions in peri-implant soft tissues. J Clin Periodontol. 1995 Mar;22(3):255-61.</citation>
    <PMID>7790533</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Koutouzis T, Adeinat B, Ali A. The influence of abutment macro-design on clinical and radiographic peri-implant tissue changes for guided, placed, and restored implants: A 1-year randomized controlled trial. Clin Oral Implants Res. 2019 Sep;30(9):882-891. doi: 10.1111/clr.13493. Epub 2019 Jun 24.</citation>
    <PMID>31180160</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nóvoa L, Batalla P, Caneiro L, Pico A, Liñares A, Blanco J. Influence of Abutment Height on Maintenance of Peri-implant Crestal Bone at Bone-Level Implants: A 3-Year Follow-up Study. Int J Periodontics Restorative Dent. 2017 Sep/Oct;37(5):721-727. doi: 10.11607/prd.2762.</citation>
    <PMID>28817138</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Souza AB, Alshihri A, Kämmerer PW, Araújo MG, Gallucci GO. Histological and micro-CT analysis of peri-implant soft and hard tissue healing on implants with different healing abutments configurations. Clin Oral Implants Res. 2018 Oct;29(10):1007-1015. doi: 10.1111/clr.13367. Epub 2018 Sep 23.</citation>
    <PMID>30246409</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 6, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 9, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 12, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 9, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 9, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 12, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Santiago de Compostela</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Juan Blanco Carrión</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>periimplant bone loss</keyword>
  <keyword>abutment design</keyword>
  <keyword>transmucosal abutment</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Bone Diseases, Metabolic</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

