<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04386772</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>EHBHKY2018-02-024</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04386772</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Portal Vein Embolization Using Coils Plus TAGM vs Multiple Coils for Patients With Perihilar Cholangiocarcinoma or Hepatocellular Carcinoma</brief_title>
  <official_title>Preoperative Portal Vein Embolization Using Coils Plus TAGM vs Multiple Coils for Patients With Perihilar Cholangiocarcinoma or Hepatocellular Carcinoma: a Randomized Controlled Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Eastern Hepatobiliary Surgery Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Eastern Hepatobiliary Surgery Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The aim of this study is to investigate the differences of safety and liver hypertrophy
      between portal vein embolization (PVE) using coils plus tris-acryl gelatin microspheres
      (TAGM) and multiple coils in patients with perihilar cholangiocarcinoma (pCCA) or with
      hepatocellular carcinoma (HCC).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Perihilar cholangiocarcinoma (pCCA) and hepatocellular carcinoma (HCC) both are common
      primary hepatobiliary tumors, which often require extensive hepatic resection and challenge
      perioperative management as surgery remains the only chance of long-term survival for such
      patients. PVE induces effective hypertrophy on one side of the liver parenchyma ahead of a
      planned liver resection of the other side which becomes atrophic.

      Technically, the percutaneous transhepatic approach becomes the standard of care for PVE.
      PVEs themselves with different embolization materials could vary in the degree of liver
      hypertrophy, though some techniques, such as TAE, HVE and stem cell, have been already used
      in combination with PVE and could promote the hypertrophy. Several aspects on the use of PVE
      are insufficiently studied and most recommendations are based on low-grade evidence. Large
      clinical studies that compare the effect of different embolic materials on the hypertrophy
      response are lacking. PVE using multiple coils to completely occlude all the target segmental
      and sectional branches is a conventional and fundamental approach in our center, which
      ensured a reliable hypertrophy response with a low PVE-related morbidity and post-hepatectomy
      liver failure rate in the past decades. PVE using with tris-acryl gelatin microspheres (TAGM)
      distally and coils proximally, which needs more interventional experience, has become one of
      standard approaches in our center. However, the study of high-grade evidence regarding the
      hypertrophy effect of PVE with TAGM and coils is still lacking.

      In this randomized study, the investigators aim to compare PVE using TAGM plus coils to PVE
      using coils alone, in term of PVE-related complications, hypertrophy degree, hepatectomy
      completion rate, post-hepatectomy liver failure rate, features of immunohistochemical
      examination on parenchyma, for patients stratified by either pCCA or HCC.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 27, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>PVE related morbidity</measure>
    <time_frame>During and 2 weeks after PVE procedure</time_frame>
    <description>The rate of major and minor PVE-related complications</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Hypertrophy degree of standardized FLR</measure>
    <time_frame>2 weeks after PVE procedure</time_frame>
    <description>The difference of standardized FLR ratios before and 2 weeks after PVE</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hepatectomy completion rate</measure>
    <time_frame>The end of hepatectomy procedure</time_frame>
    <description>The rate of completed major hepatectomy in each Arm group</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Liver failure rate after major hepatectomy</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months after hepatectomy</time_frame>
    <description>The rate of liver failure measured by 50-50, TB peak 7mg, and ISGLS criteria</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Immunohistochemical stainings of liver parenchyma</measure>
    <time_frame>During (sampling) and immediately after hepatectomy (IHC examination)</time_frame>
    <description>Immunohistochemical stainings of hypertrophic and atrophic parenchyma including anti-albumin, anti-PCNA, TUNEL staining, etc.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">56</enrollment>
  <condition>Portal Vein Occlusion</condition>
  <condition>Cholangiocarcinoma, Perihilar</condition>
  <condition>Hepatocellular Carcinoma</condition>
  <condition>Liver; Hypertrophy, Acute</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>PVE with coils plus TAGM</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>PVE with coils proximally plus TAGM distally and subsequent major hepatectomy</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>PVE with multiple coils</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>PVE with multiple coils and subsequent major hepatectomy</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>PVE with coils plus TAGM</intervention_name>
    <description>PVE with TAGM distally and coils proximally and subsequent scheduled major hepatectomy. Sequential transcatheter arterial chemoembolization and PVE for patients with HCC. Selective biliary drainage on future liver remnant (FLR) side for patients with pCCA when obstructive jaundice is present.</description>
    <arm_group_label>PVE with coils plus TAGM</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>PVE with multiple coils</intervention_name>
    <description>Procedure: PVE with multiple coils PVE with multiple coils proximally and distally and subsequent scheduled major hepatectomy. Sequential transcatheter arterial chemoembolization and PVE for patients with HCC. Selective biliary drainage on FLR side for patients with pCCA when obstructive jaundice is present.</description>
    <arm_group_label>PVE with multiple coils</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Male or female patients &gt; 18 years and ≤ 70 years of age.

          -  Diagnosis of pCCA or HCC (through imaging, serology, and/or histological biopsy)

          -  Performance status: Karnofsky score ≥ 70

          -  Candidates for right portal vein embolization for potential major hepatectomy with
             curative intent. Volumetric indication for PVE is less than 40% of standardized FLR.

          -  Selective biliary drainage on FLR side for patients with pCCA should be performed when
             total bilirubin level is above 85.5μmol/L or bile duct dilation of FLR presents.
             Transcatheter arterial chemoembolization should be performed between 1 and 4 weeks
             before PVE for patients with HCC.

          -  Criteria of liver function: Child-Pugh A-B7 level, serum total bilirubin &lt; 85.5μmol/L
             after biliary drainage in pCCA, alanine aminotransferase and aspartate
             aminotransferase ≤ 3 times the upper limit of normal value.

          -  Patients who can understand this trial and have signed the informed consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with apparent cardiac, pulmonary, cerebral and renal dysfunction, which may
             affect the treatment.

          -  Patients with a history of any other malignant tumor, or allergic to iodine or
             gelatin.

          -  Subjects participating in other clinical trials.

          -  Platelet count &lt; 80×109/L and/or moderate or severe esophageal varices.

          -  ICGR15 ≥ 15% for HCC patients

          -  Obstructive jaundice lasts for &gt;2 months before PVE for pCCA patients.

          -  Tumor becomes unresectable by local progression and/or distant metastasis presents
             before PVE.

          -  Right portal vein is occluded by tumor invasion or embolus before PVE.

          -  Free portal vein pressure &gt;20 mmHg or porto-hepatic vein fistula at the beginning of
             PVE procedure.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Feng SHEN, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>0086-21-81875005</phone>
    <email>shenfengehbh@sina.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Bin YI, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>0086-21-81887805</phone>
    <email>billyyi11@163.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Easter hepatobiliary surgery hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Shanghai</city>
        <state>Shanghai</state>
        <zip>200438</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Bin YI, MD</last_name>
      <phone>021-81887565</phone>
      <email>billyyi11@163.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 1, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 8, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 13, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 15, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 15, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 17, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Eastern Hepatobiliary Surgery Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Shen Feng</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor and Chief Surgeon, Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Portal vein embolization</keyword>
  <keyword>Trisacryl gelatin microspheres</keyword>
  <keyword>Coils</keyword>
  <keyword>Major hepatectomy</keyword>
  <keyword>Liver hypertrophy</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Hepatocellular</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cholangiocarcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Klatskin Tumor</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hypertrophy</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

