<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04384848</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>1R21CA230367-01A1</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04384848</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The EMPATHY Pilot Study</brief_title>
  <official_title>Evaluating Patient-Reported Outcomes Monitoring in Routine Care of Patients With Chronic Myeloid Leukemia for Increasing Adherence and Clinical Response to THerapY: The EMPATHY Pilot Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Northwestern University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Fondazione GIMEMA - Franco Mandelli Onlus</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Augusta University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Northwestern University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The proposed study, may significantly contribute to improve healthcare delivery in patients
      with Chronic Myeloid Leukemia (CML) treated with modern tyrosine kinase inhibitors (TKIs) in
      two ways. First, it may provide novel empirical data on the positive effects of
      systematically monitoring of patient-reported adverse events (AEs) in routine practice for
      improving symptom management and adherence to therapy. Second, it will inform the development
      of a large international randomized controlled trial (RCT) to test whether systematic
      collection of patient-reported AEs, could improve clinical response to TKI therapy.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The evolution in the understanding of the biology of Chronic Myeloid Leukemia (CML), that
      eventually translated into highly effective molecular targeted therapies, is unparalleled in
      cancer medicine. This knowledge led the development of a number of orally active molecule
      tyrosine kinase inhibitors (TKIs) that have dramatically improved clinical outcomes. In less
      than two decades, the 10-year survival probability increased from 20 to 53% with previous
      (IFN)-therapies to about 90% in the TKI era. Life expectancy of these patients now approaches
      that of the general population. While oral TKIs are now the standard of care for CML, it
      should be considered that therapy is lifelong and patients are requested to take medication
      on a daily basis. Importantly, there is convincing evidence that full adherence to therapy is
      a critical factor to obtain and maintain an optimal response to therapy. However,
      non-adherence is a major challenge in CML, since side effects induced by these drugs
      negatively impact on patient's quality of life (QoL), seriously undermine full adherence with
      treatment schedule and thereby often lead to sub-optimal clinical responses to drugs. From
      previous Preliminary Data we extrapolated the following evidences: Systematic monitoring of
      Patient-Reported Outcomes (PRO) in routine care has several advantages, such as improved
      symptom control, enhanced patient-physician communication, as well as patient satisfaction
      and wellbeing. Furthermore, it was found that Adverse Events (AEs) are the most frequent
      cause for non-adherence to CML therapy and that even experienced physicians tend to
      underestimate burden of TKIs of their patients. This mismatch might have major clinical
      implications in disease management, as physicians might not be able to early identify those
      patients who might be at heightened risk of poor adherence behavior. Given these findings, we
      hypothesized that systematic electronic monitoring of Patient-Reported AEs in CML routine
      practice may improve adherence to therapy, quality of life, and clinical response to therapy.
      This hypothesis will be addressed in the experiments of the following Specific Aims: 1) To
      develop an online platform for systematic monitoring of patient-reported AE assessment that
      is tailored to the unique demands of TKI therapy for CML. 2) To assess patient and physician
      acceptability and satisfaction with use of this platform in CML routine practice and evaluate
      its value in improving symptom management, quality of life, adherence to therapy as well as
      preliminary efficacy. We anticipate this study will provide unprecedented information on the
      value of systematically collecting patient-reported AEs information in CML routine care. If
      positive, our results will inform the development of large international randomized
      controlled trial (RCT) to investigate whether this experimental approach can improve depth
      and rates of clinical responses to TKI therapies in CML patients.

      Dr. Fabio Efficace is also a Principal Investigator on this study. He is also a Professor in
      the Department of Medical Social Sciences at Northwestern University, Feinberg School of
      Medicine.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">June 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Medication Adherence</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Adherence to Refills and Medications Scale</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Medication Adherence</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Prescription refill data extracted from hospital pharmacy records. Prescription refill data will be evaluated over 6 months. Missed refills, for reasons other than mortality or physician change of medication, will count as non-adherence</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Health-Related Quality of Life</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Functional Assessment of Cancer Therapy-General</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Fatigue</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Functional Assessment of Chronic Illness Therapy-Fatigue</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient Satisfaction</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Patient satisfaction with the study platform. Author-constructed items include questions on overall satisfaction and acceptability with the study website.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cytogenetic response</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Cytogenetic response (CyR) is defined based on the percentage of Ph pos metaphases, as evaluated by chromosome banding analysis of at least 20 marrow cell metaphases (cytogenetics). Complete CyR is when the percentage of Ph pos metaphases is 0; Partial CyR is when the percentage of Ph pos metaphases ranges from 1 to 35, Minor CyR if the percentage of Ph pos metaphases ranges from 36 to 65, minimal CyR if the percentage of Ph pos metaphases ranges from 66 to 95, No CyR if the percentage of Ph pos metaphases is higher than 95.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Physician acceptability</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>physician acceptability of study platform. Author-constructed questionnaire includes items assessing physician satisfaction and acceptability of the study website.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">94</enrollment>
  <condition>Leukemia, Chronic Myeloid</condition>
  <condition>Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Chronic myeloid leukemia (CML) patients</arm_group_label>
    <description>CML patients undergoing first-line tyrosine kinase inhibitor (TKI) therapy</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>EMPATHY Pilot</intervention_name>
    <description>The goal of this pilot is to develop and pilot a tailored monitoring intervention targeting symptomatic, Patient-reported adverse events (AEs) in chronic myeloid leukemia (CML) Patients undergoing first-line tyrosine kinase inhibitor (TKI) therapy. The tailored monitoring intervention will draw primarily from the PRO-CTCAE Item Library, with additional items drawn from the FACIT and EORTC Item libraries as necessary. After identifying the full set of AEs to be monitored, we will load the Patient assessment and report program into tablets for electronic administration in the busy clinic setting. We will then pilot a six-month intervention aimed to monitor and manage emerging AEs, coupled with assessment of intervention feasibility, Patient acceptability and satisfaction, provider acceptability and clinical management utility, adherence to TKI therapy, and HRQoL. We expect that adherence to therapy, clinical response, and HRQoL will be enhanced by such an intervention.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Chronic myeloid leukemia (CML) patients</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        For Northwestern University in Chicago, Illinois, CML patients will be recruited from the
        outpatient clinical cancer center in Northwestern's Galter Pavilion in collaboration with
        the Robert H. Lurie Comprehensive Cancer Center of Northwestern University.

        For Augusta University in Augusta, Georgia, CML patients will be recruited from the
        Division of Hematology/Medical Oncology at the Medical College of Georgia at Augusta.

        For the GIMEMA Foundation (Italian Group for Adult Hematologic Diseases) in Italy, CML
        patients will be recruited from the GIMEMA Foundation Research Network. For the purposes of
        the study, patients will be enrolled from thirteen Centers throughout Italy.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Diagnosis of Philadelphia chromosome positive and/or BCR-ABL positive CML confirmed by
             cytogenetic and/or molecular analysis;

          2. Newly diagnosed chronic phase (CP)-CML Patients planned to receive one of the
             following TKI approved as first line treatment: imatinib, dasatinib, nilotinib or
             bosutinib;

          3. Adult Patients (≥18 years) at the time of study entry; Children under the age of 18
             will be excluded from the study. The exclusion of children is justified by the
             following circumstances: a) The condition is relatively rare in children, as compared
             to adults; b) Issues of study preclude direct applicability of hypotheses and/or
             interventions to both adults and children.

          4. Written informed consent.

          5. Written informed consent from Patient's physician as a participant.

          6. Newly diagnosed Chronic Phase (CP)-CML Patients who are within 4 weeks of first line
             TKI therapy (anyone of the TKI approved in the USA and Europe, that is: imatinib,
             dasatinib, nilotinib or bosutinib).

          7. Ability to read/converse in English (Northwestern University and Augusta University
             Sites). Ability to read/converse in Italian (GIMEMA Centers).

        Patient exclusion criteria will include:

          1. Major cognitive deficits or psychiatric problems hampering a self-reported evaluation;

          2. Having received any CML treatment - other than TKI - for more than 3 months prior to
             receiving current TKI therapy.

        This project will focus on CML, which affect both men and women. Therefore, there are no
        exclusion/inclusion criteria based on sex/gender. In addition, there are no
        exclusion/inclusion criteria based on race and ethnicity.

        Physician inclusion criteria will include:

        1)Provider of clinical care for Patient who meets inclusion criteria for the study

        Please note that Physician consent is requisite for the Patient to be enrolled as a
        participant in the study.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Major cognitive deficits or psychiatric problems hampering a self-reported evaluation

          2. Having received any CML treatment prior to therapy with imatinib, dasatinib, bosutinib
             or nilotinib for more than three months
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>David Cella, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Northwestern University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Fabio Efficace, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Fondazione GIMEMA - Franco Mandelli Onlus</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Leilani Lacson, MPH</last_name>
    <phone>3125033463</phone>
    <email>l-lacson@northwestern.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Betina Yanez, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>3125035341</phone>
    <email>betina.yanez@northwestern.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Augusta University, Hematology and Oncology</name>
      <address>
        <city>Augusta</city>
        <state>Georgia</state>
        <zip>30912</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Manickam Alagar, PhD</last_name>
      <email>MALAGAR@augusta.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Vamsi Kota, MD</last_name>
      <email>VKOTA@augusta.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Vamsi Kota, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Northwestern University, Robert H. Lurie Comprehensive Cancer Center Comprehensive Cancer Center (RHLCCC)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chicago</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60611</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Leilani Lacson, MPH</last_name>
      <email>l-lacson@northwestern.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Betina Yanez, PhD</last_name>
      <email>betina.yanez@northwestern.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>David Cella, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Policlinico Sant'Orsola Malpighi - UOC Ematologia - Azienda Ospedaliero-Universitaria di Bologna</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bologna</city>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Gianantonio Rosti</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Gianantonio Rosti</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ospedale &quot;A. Businco&quot; - Struttura Complessa di Ematologia e CTMO - Azienda Ospedaliera G. Brotzu</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cagliari</city>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Giovanni Caocci</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Giovanni Caocci</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Milano Fondazione IRCCS Ca' Granda Ospedale Maggiore Policlinico - UOC Oncoematologia - Padiglione Marcora</name>
      <address>
        <city>Milano</city>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Alessandra Iurlo</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Alessandra Iurlo</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Azienda Ospedaliera Universitaria - Università degli Studi di Napoli &quot;Federico II&quot; - UOC Ematologia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Napoli</city>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Luigia Luciano</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Luigia Luciano</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Azienda Ospedaliera Universitaria Maggiore della Carità di Novara - SCDU Ematologia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Novara</city>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Andrea Patriarca</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Andrea Patriarca</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>AUSL Reggio Emilia - Arcispedale S. Maria Nuova, IRCSS - SC Ematologia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Reggio Emilia</city>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Isabella Capodanno</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Isabella Capodanno</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Azienda Ospedaliera Universitaria Policlinico Umberto I - Università degli Studi &quot;Sapienza&quot; - UOC Ematologia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Roma</city>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Maurizio Martelli</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Maurizio Martelli</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ospedale Sant'Eugenio</name>
      <address>
        <city>Roma</city>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Elisabetta Abruzzese</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Elisabetta Abruzzese</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The GIMEMA Foundation (Italian Group for Adult Hematologic Diseases)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rome</city>
        <zip>00161</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Giulia Sagrestani, PhD</last_name>
      <email>g.sagrestani@gimema.it</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Fabio Efficace, PhD</last_name>
      <email>f.efficace@gimema.it</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Fabio Efficace</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Azienda Ospedaliero-Universitario Città della Salute e della Scienza di Torino - Ospedale S. Giovanni Battista Molinette - SC Ematologia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Torino</city>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Patrizia Pregno</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Patrizia Pregno</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ospedale Mauriziano Umberto I - Torino - SCDU Ematologia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Torino</city>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Carmen Fava</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Carmen Fava</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>ASUI di Udine - Presidio Ospedaliero &quot;Santa Maria della Misericordia&quot; - Clinica Ematologica</name>
      <address>
        <city>Udine</city>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Mario Tiribelli</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Mario Tiribelli</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Azienda Ospedaliera Universitario Integrata di Verona, Policlinico G.B. Rossi - UOC Ematologia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Verona</city>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Massimiliano Bonifacio</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Massimiliano Bonifacio</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>USL 6 - Ospedale San Bortolo - Vicenza</name>
      <address>
        <city>Vicenza</city>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Maria Cristina Miggiano</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Maria Cristina Miggiano</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Italy</country>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://wizard.facit.org</url>
    <description>FACIT Searchable Library and Custom Form Developer (Build-a-PRO)</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>https://www.eortc.be/itemlibrary/</url>
    <description>EORTC Quality of Life Group Item Library</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Druker BJ, Sawyers CL, Kantarjian H, Resta DJ, Reese SF, Ford JM, Capdeville R, Talpaz M. Activity of a specific inhibitor of the BCR-ABL tyrosine kinase in the blast crisis of chronic myeloid leukemia and acute lymphoblastic leukemia with the Philadelphia chromosome. N Engl J Med. 2001 Apr 5;344(14):1038-42. Erratum in: N Engl J Med 2001 Jul 19;345(3):232.</citation>
    <PMID>11287973</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Druker BJ, Talpaz M, Resta DJ, Peng B, Buchdunger E, Ford JM, Lydon NB, Kantarjian H, Capdeville R, Ohno-Jones S, Sawyers CL. Efficacy and safety of a specific inhibitor of the BCR-ABL tyrosine kinase in chronic myeloid leukemia. N Engl J Med. 2001 Apr 5;344(14):1031-7.</citation>
    <PMID>11287972</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rosti G, Castagnetti F, Gugliotta G, Baccarani M. Tyrosine kinase inhibitors in chronic myeloid leukaemia: which, when, for whom? Nat Rev Clin Oncol. 2017 Mar;14(3):141-154. doi: 10.1038/nrclinonc.2016.139. Epub 2016 Oct 18. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>27752053</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cella D, Nowinski CJ, Frankfurt O. The impact of symptom burden on patient quality of life in chronic myeloid leukemia. Oncology. 2014;87(3):133-47. doi: 10.1159/000362816. Epub 2014 Jul 8. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25012261</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bower H, Björkholm M, Dickman PW, Höglund M, Lambert PC, Andersson TM. Life Expectancy of Patients With Chronic Myeloid Leukemia Approaches the Life Expectancy of the General Population. J Clin Oncol. 2016 Aug 20;34(24):2851-7. doi: 10.1200/JCO.2015.66.2866. Epub 2016 Jun 20.</citation>
    <PMID>27325849</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Efficace F, Baccarani M, Breccia M, Cottone F, Alimena G, Deliliers GL, Baratè C, Specchia G, Di Lorenzo R, Luciano L, Turri D, Martino B, Stagno F, Dabusti M, Bergamaschi M, Leoni P, Simula MP, Levato L, Fava C, Veneri D, Sica S, Rambaldi A, Rosti G, Vignetti M, Mandelli F. Chronic fatigue is the most important factor limiting health-related quality of life of chronic myeloid leukemia patients treated with imatinib. Leukemia. 2013 Jul;27(7):1511-9. doi: 10.1038/leu.2013.51. Epub 2013 Feb 18.</citation>
    <PMID>23417029</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Guérin A, Chen L, Ionescu-Ittu R, Marynchenko M, Nitulescu R, Hiscock R, Keir C, Wu EQ. Impact of low-grade adverse events on health-related quality of life in adult patients receiving imatinib or nilotinib for newly diagnosed Philadelphia chromosome positive chronic myelogenous leukemia in chronic phase. Curr Med Res Opin. 2014 Nov;30(11):2317-28. doi: 10.1185/03007995.2014.944973. Epub 2014 Aug 5.</citation>
    <PMID>25025755</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Williams LA, Garcia Gonzalez AG, Ault P, Mendoza TR, Sailors ML, Williams JL, Huang F, Nazha A, Kantarjian HM, Cleeland CS, Cortes JE. Measuring the symptom burden associated with the treatment of chronic myeloid leukemia. Blood. 2013 Aug 1;122(5):641-7. doi: 10.1182/blood-2013-01-477687. Epub 2013 Jun 18.</citation>
    <PMID>23777764</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Noens L, Hensen M, Kucmin-Bemelmans I, Lofgren C, Gilloteau I, Vrijens B. Measurement of adherence to BCR-ABL inhibitor therapy in chronic myeloid leukemia: current situation and future challenges. Haematologica. 2014 Mar;99(3):437-47. doi: 10.3324/haematol.2012.082511. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24598855</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Marin D, Bazeos A, Mahon FX, Eliasson L, Milojkovic D, Bua M, Apperley JF, Szydlo R, Desai R, Kozlowski K, Paliompeis C, Latham V, Foroni L, Molimard M, Reid A, Rezvani K, de Lavallade H, Guallar C, Goldman J, Khorashad JS. Adherence is the critical factor for achieving molecular responses in patients with chronic myeloid leukemia who achieve complete cytogenetic responses on imatinib. J Clin Oncol. 2010 May 10;28(14):2381-8. doi: 10.1200/JCO.2009.26.3087. Epub 2010 Apr 12.</citation>
    <PMID>20385986</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Noens L, van Lierde MA, De Bock R, Verhoef G, Zachée P, Berneman Z, Martiat P, Mineur P, Van Eygen K, MacDonald K, De Geest S, Albrecht T, Abraham I. Prevalence, determinants, and outcomes of nonadherence to imatinib therapy in patients with chronic myeloid leukemia: the ADAGIO study. Blood. 2009 May 28;113(22):5401-11. doi: 10.1182/blood-2008-12-196543. Epub 2009 Apr 6.</citation>
    <PMID>19349618</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ibrahim AR, Eliasson L, Apperley JF, Milojkovic D, Bua M, Szydlo R, Mahon FX, Kozlowski K, Paliompeis C, Foroni L, Khorashad JS, Bazeos A, Molimard M, Reid A, Rezvani K, Gerrard G, Goldman J, Marin D. Poor adherence is the main reason for loss of CCyR and imatinib failure for chronic myeloid leukemia patients on long-term therapy. Blood. 2011 Apr 7;117(14):3733-6. doi: 10.1182/blood-2010-10-309807. Epub 2011 Feb 23.</citation>
    <PMID>21346253</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Efficace F, Cannella L. The value of quality of life assessment in chronic myeloid leukemia patients receiving tyrosine kinase inhibitors. Hematology Am Soc Hematol Educ Program. 2016 Dec 2;2016(1):170-179. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>27913477</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Experts in Chronic Myeloid Leukemia. The price of drugs for chronic myeloid leukemia (CML) is a reflection of the unsustainable prices of cancer drugs: from the perspective of a large group of CML experts. Blood. 2013 May 30;121(22):4439-42. doi: 10.1182/blood-2013-03-490003. Epub 2013 Apr 25.</citation>
    <PMID>23620577</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kotronoulas G, Kearney N, Maguire R, Harrow A, Di Domenico D, Croy S, MacGillivray S. What is the value of the routine use of patient-reported outcome measures toward improvement of patient outcomes, processes of care, and health service outcomes in cancer care? A systematic review of controlled trials. J Clin Oncol. 2014 May 10;32(14):1480-501. doi: 10.1200/JCO.2013.53.5948. Epub 2014 Apr 7. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24711559</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Velikova G, Booth L, Smith AB, Brown PM, Lynch P, Brown JM, Selby PJ. Measuring quality of life in routine oncology practice improves communication and patient well-being: a randomized controlled trial. J Clin Oncol. 2004 Feb 15;22(4):714-24.</citation>
    <PMID>14966096</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Efficace F, Gaidano G, Lo-Coco F. Patient-reported outcomes in hematology: is it time to focus more on them in clinical trials and hematology practice? Blood. 2017 Aug 17;130(7):859-866. doi: 10.1182/blood-2017-03-737403. Epub 2017 Jul 10. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>28694324</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Efficace F, Baccarani M, Rosti G, Cottone F, Castagnetti F, Breccia M, Alimena G, Iurlo A, Rossi AR, Pardini S, Gherlinzoni F, Salvucci M, Tiribelli M, Vignetti M, Mandelli F. Investigating factors associated with adherence behaviour in patients with chronic myeloid leukemia: an observational patient-centered outcome study. Br J Cancer. 2012 Sep 4;107(6):904-9. doi: 10.1038/bjc.2012.348. Epub 2012 Aug 7.</citation>
    <PMID>22871884</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dueck AC, Mendoza TR, Mitchell SA, Reeve BB, Castro KM, Rogak LJ, Atkinson TM, Bennett AV, Denicoff AM, O'Mara AM, Li Y, Clauser SB, Bryant DM, Bearden JD 3rd, Gillis TA, Harness JK, Siegel RD, Paul DB, Cleeland CS, Schrag D, Sloan JA, Abernethy AP, Bruner DW, Minasian LM, Basch E; National Cancer Institute PRO-CTCAE Study Group. Validity and Reliability of the US National Cancer Institute's Patient-Reported Outcomes Version of the Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (PRO-CTCAE). JAMA Oncol. 2015 Nov;1(8):1051-9. doi: 10.1001/jamaoncol.2015.2639. Erratum in: JAMA Oncol. 2016 Jan;2(1):146.</citation>
    <PMID>26270597</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Basch E, Deal AM, Kris MG, Scher HI, Hudis CA, Sabbatini P, Rogak L, Bennett AV, Dueck AC, Atkinson TM, Chou JF, Dulko D, Sit L, Barz A, Novotny P, Fruscione M, Sloan JA, Schrag D. Symptom Monitoring With Patient-Reported Outcomes During Routine Cancer Treatment: A Randomized Controlled Trial. J Clin Oncol. 2016 Feb 20;34(6):557-65. doi: 10.1200/JCO.2015.63.0830. Epub 2015 Dec 7. Erratum in: J Clin Oncol. 2016 Jun 20;34(18):2198. Erratum in: J Clin Oncol. 2019 Feb 20;37(6):528.</citation>
    <PMID>26644527</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Osterberg L, Blaschke T. Adherence to medication. N Engl J Med. 2005 Aug 4;353(5):487-97. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>16079372</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Weidle PJ, Wamai N, Solberg P, Liechty C, Sendagala S, Were W, Mermin J, Buchacz K, Behumbiize P, Ransom RL, Bunnell R. Adherence to antiretroviral therapy in a home-based AIDS care programme in rural Uganda. Lancet. 2006 Nov 4;368(9547):1587-94.</citation>
    <PMID>17084759</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kripalani S, Risser J, Gatti ME, Jacobson TA. Development and evaluation of the Adherence to Refills and Medications Scale (ARMS) among low-literacy patients with chronic disease. Value Health. 2009 Jan-Feb;12(1):118-23. doi: 10.1111/j.1524-4733.2008.00400.x.</citation>
    <PMID>19911444</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cella DF, Tulsky DS, Gray G, Sarafian B, Linn E, Bonomi A, Silberman M, Yellen SB, Winicour P, Brannon J, et al. The Functional Assessment of Cancer Therapy scale: development and validation of the general measure. J Clin Oncol. 1993 Mar;11(3):570-9.</citation>
    <PMID>8445433</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Phillips KM, Pinilla-Ibarz J, Sotomayor E, Lee MR, Jim HS, Small BJ, Sokol L, Lancet J, Tinsley S, Sweet K, Komrokji R, Jacobsen PB. Quality of life outcomes in patients with chronic myeloid leukemia treated with tyrosine kinase inhibitors: a controlled comparison. Support Care Cancer. 2013 Apr;21(4):1097-103. doi: 10.1007/s00520-012-1630-5. Epub 2012 Nov 20.</citation>
    <PMID>23179489</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yellen SB, Cella DF, Webster K, Blendowski C, Kaplan E. Measuring fatigue and other anemia-related symptoms with the Functional Assessment of Cancer Therapy (FACT) measurement system. J Pain Symptom Manage. 1997 Feb;13(2):63-74.</citation>
    <PMID>9095563</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Basch E, Iasonos A, Barz A, Culkin A, Kris MG, Artz D, Fearn P, Speakman J, Farquhar R, Scher HI, McCabe M, Schrag D. Long-term toxicity monitoring via electronic patient-reported outcomes in patients receiving chemotherapy. J Clin Oncol. 2007 Dec 1;25(34):5374-80.</citation>
    <PMID>18048818</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Baccarani M, Deininger MW, Rosti G, Hochhaus A, Soverini S, Apperley JF, Cervantes F, Clark RE, Cortes JE, Guilhot F, Hjorth-Hansen H, Hughes TP, Kantarjian HM, Kim DW, Larson RA, Lipton JH, Mahon FX, Martinelli G, Mayer J, Müller MC, Niederwieser D, Pane F, Radich JP, Rousselot P, Saglio G, Saußele S, Schiffer C, Silver R, Simonsson B, Steegmann JL, Goldman JM, Hehlmann R. European LeukemiaNet recommendations for the management of chronic myeloid leukemia: 2013. Blood. 2013 Aug 8;122(6):872-84. doi: 10.1182/blood-2013-05-501569. Epub 2013 Jun 26. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23803709</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Charlson ME, Pompei P, Ales KL, MacKenzie CR. A new method of classifying prognostic comorbidity in longitudinal studies: development and validation. J Chronic Dis. 1987;40(5):373-83.</citation>
    <PMID>3558716</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>O'Brien S, Berman E, Borghaei H, Deangelo DJ, Devetten MP, Devine S, Erba HP, Gotlib J, Jagasia M, Moore JO, Mughal T, Pinilla-Ibarz J, Radich JP, Shah Md NP, Shami PJ, Smith BD, Snyder DS, Tallman MS, Talpaz M, Wetzler M; National Comprehensive Cancer Network. NCCN clinical practice guidelines in oncology: chronic myelogenous leukemia. J Natl Compr Canc Netw. 2009 Oct;7(9):984-1023.</citation>
    <PMID>19878641</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sokal JE, Cox EB, Baccarani M, Tura S, Gomez GA, Robertson JE, Tso CY, Braun TJ, Clarkson BD, Cervantes F, et al. Prognostic discrimination in &quot;good-risk&quot; chronic granulocytic leukemia. Blood. 1984 Apr;63(4):789-99.</citation>
    <PMID>6584184</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Alonso J, Bartlett SJ, Rose M, Aaronson NK, Chaplin JE, Efficace F, Leplège A, Lu A, Tulsky DS, Raat H, Ravens-Sieberer U, Revicki D, Terwee CB, Valderas JM, Cella D, Forrest CB; PROMIS International Group. The case for an international patient-reported outcomes measurement information system (PROMIS®) initiative. Health Qual Life Outcomes. 2013 Dec 20;11:210. doi: 10.1186/1477-7525-11-210.</citation>
    <PMID>24359143</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cottone F, Deliu N, Collins GS, Anota A, Bonnetain F, Van Steen K, Cella D, Efficace F. Modeling strategies to improve parameter estimates in prognostic factors analyses with patient-reported outcomes in oncology. Qual Life Res. 2019 May;28(5):1315-1325. doi: 10.1007/s11136-018-02097-2. Epub 2019 Jan 18.</citation>
    <PMID>30659449</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Efficace F, Baccarani M, Breccia M, Saussele S, Abel G, Caocci G, Guilhot F, Cocks K, Naeem A, Sprangers M, Oerlemans S, Chie W, Castagnetti F, Bombaci F, Sharf G, Cardoni A, Noens L, Pallua S, Salvucci M, Nicolatou-Galitis O, Rosti G, Mandelli F. International development of an EORTC questionnaire for assessing health-related quality of life in chronic myeloid leukemia patients: the EORTC QLQ-CML24. Qual Life Res. 2014 Apr;23(3):825-36. doi: 10.1007/s11136-013-0523-5. Epub 2013 Sep 13.</citation>
    <PMID>24026634</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>April 17, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 7, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 12, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 18, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 18, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 20, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Northwestern University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>David Cella</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor, Medical Social Sciences; Feinberg School of Medicine</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Leukemia, Chronic Myeloid</keyword>
  <keyword>Health-Related Quality Of Life</keyword>
  <keyword>Patient Reported Outcome</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Leukemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Myelogenous, Chronic, BCR-ABL Positive</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

