<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04385056</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IMAC-001</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04385056</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluate Umbilical Cord-derived Allogeneic Mesenchymal Stem Cells for the Treatment of Bradykinesia</brief_title>
  <official_title>An Open-label, Dose-escalation Study to Evaluate the Use of Umbilical Cord-derived Allogeneic Mesenchymal Stem Cells (UC-MSCs) for the Treatment of Bradykinesia</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>IMAC Holdings, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>IMAC Holdings, Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Investigate the safety and tolerability of umbilical cord-derived allogeneic mesenchymal stem
      cells to treat patients with Bradykinesia.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      While the pathophysiological changes that result in the symptoms of bradykinesia are poorly
      understood, an inflammatory component appears to be involved. Human umbilical cord-derived
      allogeneic mesenchymal stem cells have documented anti-inflammatory properties, which suggest
      these cells may be effective at treating Bradykinesia. It is understood that perinatal
      products are potent immune modulators. It is believed that the positive symptomatic effects
      are secondary to the modulation of the immune system, and specifically the reduction in
      pathological inflammation. The study is designed to evaluate the safety and tolerability of
      umbilical cord-derived allogeneic mesenchymal stem cells to treat patients with Bradykinesia.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">July 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 1, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 1, 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of Serious Adverse Events and Adverse Events</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Number of serious adverse events and adverse events for the duration of the study.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">15</enrollment>
  <condition>Bradykinesia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Low Dose MSCTC-0010</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will receive low-dose cell administration</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Medium Dose MSCTC-0010</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will receive medium-dose cell administration</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>High Dose MSCTC-0010</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will receive high-dose cell administration</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>MSCTC-0010</intervention_name>
    <description>MSCTC-0010 is a suspension product for infusion. The active ingredient is the umbilical cord-derived allogeneic mesenchymal stem cells (US-MSCs).</description>
    <arm_group_label>High Dose MSCTC-0010</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Low Dose MSCTC-0010</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Medium Dose MSCTC-0010</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age of 55 years or older

          -  Clinically diagnosed with Parkinsonism

          -  All subjects, or their authorized representatives, must be adequately informed and
             understand the nature and risks of the study and must be able to provide a signature
             and date in the Informed Consent Form (ICF).

          -  Clinically diagnosed bradykinesia for at least 3 months prior to baseline visit.

          -  On stable treatment regimen with L-dopa and other anti-parkinsonian treatment for 4
             weeks prior to baseline.

          -  Women of child-bearing potential must undergo a negative serum pregnancy test at the
             screening assessment.

          -  Subjects, or their representatives, must be able to communicate effectively with the
             study staff.

          -  Subjects, or their authorized representatives, must certify that they are able and
             willing to follow all protocol requirements and study restrictions.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects who are intolerant of, or unwilling to, participate in all procedures
             required of this protocol.

          -  Subjects who cannot tolerate a venipuncture and/or have adequate venous access.

          -  Inability to ambulate 100 feet independently with or without an assistive device.

          -  Subjects who have a history of allergy, hypersensitivity, or intolerance to any
             medications, components, or excipients of the investigational product or procedures,
             and which cannot be resolved by the staff conducting the study.

          -  Subjects with a known diagnosis of Atypical Parkinsonian Syndrome e.g.:

               1. Dementia with Lewy Bodies;

               2. Progressive Supranuclear Palsy;

               3. Corticobasal Degeneration;

               4. Multiple System Atrophy;

               5. Other Neurodengerative Conditions.

          -  Head trauma related to the onset of bradykinesia symptoms.

          -  History of repeated head injury, hydrocephalus, encephalitis, or cerebral tumors.

          -  Choreoathetosis

          -  Any documented abnormality in the brain by CT or MRI, which might contribute to the
             motor function, e.g., stroke, tumor, or other space-occupying lesions, hydrocephalus,
             or encephalomalacia.

          -  Known history of serum or plasma progranulin level &lt; 110.9 ng/mL.

          -  Disease associated mutation in TDP-34, PGRN, CHMPB2, or VCP genes or any other FTLD
             Causative genes.

          -  Intracranial operation, e.g., pallidotomy, thalamotomy, and/or deep brain stiumulation
             surgery.

          -  Other known neurodegenerative diseases not underlying the bradykinesia, e.g.,
             Spinocerellar Atropy (SCA), Wilson's Disease, or Amyotrphic Lateral Sclerosis (ALS).

          -  History of other significant neurological or physciatric disorders including, but not
             limited to, Alzheimer's disease, Lewy Body Dementia, Prior Disease, stroke, or seizure
             disorder.

          -  Psychiatric illness that is unrelated to the Bradykinesia, e.g., severe bipolar or
             unipolar depression.

          -  History of neurotoxin exposure.

          -  History of REM behavior disorder.

          -  Patients with Hepatocellular Carcinoma (HCC).

          -  Acute liver failure or episode of hepatic encephalopthy.

          -  Systolic blood pressure greater than 180 or less than 90 mmHg.

          -  Diastolic blood pressure greater than 105 or less than 50 mmHg.

          -  Presence of QTcprolongation or ECG abnormal at screening and judged to be clinically
             significate by the site investigator.

          -  Clinically significant cardiovascular disease, e.g., cardiac surgery or myocardial
             infarction within the last 6 months, unstable angina, congestive heart failure,
             significant cardaic arrthymia; or cogenitial heart disease.

          -  Early, symptomatic autonomic dysfunction.

          -  Any malignancy (other than non-metasticic basal cell carcinoma of the skin) with 5
             years of screening.

          -  Clinically significant lab abnormalities at screening, including creatinine ≥ 2.5
             mg/dL, vitam B12 below laboratory normal reference range, or TSH above laboratory
             normal reference range.

          -  Current clinically significant hematological, endocrine, cardiovascular, renal,
             heapatic, gastrointestinal, or neurological disease. For the non-cancerconditions, if
             the condition has been stable for at least the past year and is judged by the site
             investigator not to interfere with the patient's participation in the study, the
             patient may be included.

          -  A history of alcohol or substance abuse within 1 year prior to screening and deemed to
             be clinically significant by the site investigator.

          -  An employee or relative of an employee.

          -  Subjects who have donated plasma or platelets or had a significant loss of whole blood
             (480 ml or more) within 30 days.

          -  Subjects who have received blood or blood products within 30 days prior to screening.

          -  Treatment with any investigational drugs or device or participation in an
             investigational drug study within 60 days of screening.

          -  Women of childbearing potential who are not using at least two forms of medically
             recognized contraception.

          -  Female subjects who are pregnant, expecting to become pregnant, or lactating/nursing.

          -  Any subjects who have a clinically significant abnormal laboratory value.

          -  Subjects who have been treated with another research product 30 days prior to the
             screening assessment, or plant to participate in another clinical trial, while in this
             study. If more than 30 days have passed since participation in another clinical trial,
             the study staff must ensure that the subject has recovered from any adverse events
             associated with the research product used.

          -  Subjects who have a history of any other clinically significant disease or disorder
             that in the opinion of the Principal Investigator, may place the subject at risk due
             to participation in the study, or may influence the results of the study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>55 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <verification_date>May 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 5, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 11, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 12, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 11, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 11, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 12, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hypokinesia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

