<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04387851</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>META-BLOM-DD-2022</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04387851</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Learning Mechanisms for Placebo and Nocebo Studies on Somatosensory Sensations: a Systematic Review and Meta-analysis.</brief_title>
  <official_title>Learning Mechanisms for Placebo and Nocebo Studies on Somatosensory Sensations: a Systematic Review and Meta-analysis.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Leiden University Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Universiteit Leiden</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Leiden University Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Placebo and nocebo effects are defined as the positive and negative effects occurring after
      the (supposed) administration of an inert treatment, which, through a given learning process,
      is believed to have positive or negative effects. The objective of this study is to summarize
      the available knowledge on experimental inductions of placebo and nocebo effects on
      somatosensory sensations, specifically pain and itch. The aim isto investigate the extent to
      which learning processes (such as conditioning and verbal suggestions) induce placebo and
      nocebo effects on pain and itch in healthy humans. The researchers intent to examine
      expectancy induction methods for placebo and nocebo effects on somatosensory sensations,
      describe methodological attributes of the research and propose practical and theoretical
      implications as well as future directions for research investigating placebo and nocebo
      effects on somatosensory sensations.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Research questions include:

        1. What is the average magnitude of placebo or nocebo effects on pain and on itch, across
           included studies?

        2. Across studies that tested multiple learning processes for placebo and nocebo effects on
           pain, is the magnitude of a placebo or nocebo effect on pain different based on the
           learning process used to induce the effect?

        3. Does the magnitude of placebo or nocebo effects differ between the sensations of pain
           and itch?

        4. Are nocebo effects on pain and itch stronger than placebo effects on pain and itch, as
           measured by their relative magnitude?

      Dependent upon search results, the researchers intend to answer questions 1 and 2 with
      meta-analysis, and questions 3 and 4 with systematic review.

      Search Strategy:

      PubMed, PsycINFO, EMBASE, and the Cochrane CENTRAL Methodology Library will be searched.
      Languages are restricted to English, Dutch, and German. Publication period is not restricted.
      Searches were initially conducted on March 18th, 2019. The detailed key-worded search
      strategy will not be made publicly available until this review is complete.

      Condition or domain being studied:

      Experimental induction of placebo or nocebo effects on somatosensory sensations (i.e., pain
      and/or itch). For the purposes of in- and exclusion, studies are considered to have induced a
      placebo or nocebo effect if the (supposed) administration of an inert treatment, is paired
      with a given learning process attempt to induce positive or negative outcome-effects

      Participants/population:

      Healthy, adult human volunteers. Patient samples will not be included to improve homogeneity
      of the results.

      Data extraction:

      Titles and abstracts of articles retrieved using the search strategy and those from
      additional sources will be screened by two independent reviewers to identify studies that
      potentially meet the inclusion criteria outlined above. The full text of these articles and
      articles about which doubts exist based on the title and/or abstract will be retrieved and
      assessed for eligibility by two independent reviewers. Full texts that are considered to be
      possibly eligible for inclusion or about which doubts exist will also be assessed for
      eligibility by a third reviewer. Two independent reviewers will use a standardized form to
      extract data from the included studies to derive study characteristics, assess study quality,
      and for data analysis. Extracted information will include details of the intervention,
      control condition, study population, sensation type and how sensations were measured (e.g.
      self-report), type of experimental induction (i.e., learning method used), type of expectancy
      (i.e., placebo or nocebo), information for quality assessment, and outcome data for
      meta-analysis (e.g., sample size, mean, and standard deviation). Doubts regarding
      data-extraction will be resolved through discussion with a second review author. Missing data
      will be requested from the study authors.

      Risk of bias assessment:

      Risk of bias will be assessed using the method developed by Marcuzzi and colleagues in 2013
      specifically for quantitative sensory testing studies. This method assesses 1) whether the
      sample was clearly described, 2) whether the sample is representative of the population, 3)
      whether the somatosensory assessment methods are standardized, validated, and well described,
      4) adequate blinding if relevant, and 5) whether potential confounders were taken into
      account.

      Strategy for data synthesis:

      A quantitative synthesis, using aggregate data, of the data is planned. The (standardized)
      mean difference (with a 95% confidence interval) will be calculated for all included studies
      for which sufficient data are available. Both between and within subject designs will be
      included; sensitivity analyses will be conducted to test for a difference in design type
      (within/between). If significant differences are detected, design type will be included in
      the analyses as a moderator variable). Subsequently, the pooled effects for each of the
      experimental induction will be analyzed using a random-effects model. The effects of
      experimental inductions will also be compared between placebo and nocebo effects. If
      sufficient data are available, the effects of the experimental inductions will be compared
      between different somatosensory sensations (see below). Where statistical pooling is not
      possible, the findings of the systematic review will be presented in narrative form.
      Heterogeneity will be assessed with the I2 statistic, by visual inspection of the forest
      plot(s), and by subset analyses (see below). The presence of publication bias will also be
      assessed (e.g., via inspection of a funnel plot).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 1, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 1, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Other</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Retrospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Placebo magnitude</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion, an average of 1 month</time_frame>
    <description>The magnitude of induced placebo effects, by measures including, but not limited to, self-report measures of perceived sensation intensity or unpleasantness (e.g., as rated on a visual analogue scale or numerical rating scale).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Nocebo magnitude</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion, an average of 1 month</time_frame>
    <description>The magnitude of induced nocebo effects, by measures including, but not limited to, self-report measures of perceived sensation intensity or unpleasantness (e.g., as rated on a visual analogue scale or numerical rating scale).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">90</enrollment>
  <condition>Pain</condition>
  <condition>Itch</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <description>Placebo effects are defined as the positive effects occurring after the (supposed) administration of an inert treatment, which, through a given learning process, is believed to have positive effects.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Nocebo</arm_group_label>
    <description>Nocebo effects are defined as the negative effects occurring after the (supposed) administration of an inert treatment, which, through a given learning process, is believed to have negative effects.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo induction</intervention_name>
    <description>The placebo interventions of interest are experimental learning methods (e.g. verbal suggestion, conditioning), used to induce placebo effects on somatosensory sensations.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Control</intervention_name>
    <description>Placebo and nocebo effects should be measured relative to a control group (between-subjects design). In the case of within-subjects designs, these will be included to the extent possible (in a separate analysis or descriptively depending on the number of results).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Nocebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Nocebo</intervention_name>
    <description>The nocebo interventions of interest are experimental learning methods (e.g. verbal suggestion, conditioning), used to induce nocebo effects on somatosensory sensations.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Nocebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Healthy, adult human volunteers. Patient samples will not be included to improve
        homogeneity of the results.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Studies using experimental induction of placebo and/or nocebo effects on somatosensory
             sensations (i.e., pain and/or itch), which necessitates the (supposed) administration
             of an inert treatment, which, through a given learning process, is believed to have
             positive or negative effects.

          -  This review will include original, controlled experimental studies on healthy
             participants that employed learning-based inductions of placebo and/or nocebo effects
             on somatosensory sensations. The studies should be written in English, German or
             Dutch, available full-text, and published in a peer-reviewed journal. No year
             restrictions on publication date will be imposed.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Andrea WM Evers, Prof. Dr.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Leiden University Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Joe S Blythe, MSc</last_name>
    <phone>0715273008</phone>
    <email>j.s.blythe@fsw.leidenuniv.nl</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Mia A Thomaidou, MSc</last_name>
    <phone>0715273008</phone>
    <email>a.m.thomaidou@fsw.leidenuniv.nl</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Leiden University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Leiden</city>
        <state>South Holland</state>
        <zip>2333 AK</zip>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Mia A Thomaidou, MSc</last_name>
      <phone>0715273008</phone>
      <email>a.m.thomaidou@fsw.leidenuniv.nl</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Netherlands</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 11, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 11, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 14, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 13, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 13, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 15, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Leiden University Medical Center</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>AWMEvers</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Placebo</keyword>
  <keyword>Nocebo</keyword>
  <keyword>Pain</keyword>
  <keyword>Itch</keyword>
  <keyword>Somatosensory</keyword>
  <keyword>Learning</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>No personal data are collected, stored, or shared. Data collection is monitored by the department's Data Monitor.</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Statistical Analysis Plan (SAP)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>Immediately after publication of the study. Data will be retained for 15 years.</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>Data can be shared with scientists in relevant fields for the purpose of future studies such as replication or meta-analysis (or with designated persons for monitoring purposes).</ipd_access_criteria>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

