<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04382313</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>sf2020-2-5012</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04382313</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effect of Hydration Guided by Vigileo on the Prevention of CIN After Direct PCI for Patients With AMI</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effect of Hydration Guided by Vigileo on the Prevention of Contrast Induced Nephropathy After Direct PCI for Patients With Acute Myocardial Infarction</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Chinese PLA General Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Chinese PLA General Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      In this study, Vigileo is used to guide hydration adjustment, and SCr is used to estimate
      renal function. The aim of the study is to investigate the preventive effect of adequate
      hydration guided by Vigileo on contrast induced nephropathy in patients with acute myocardial
      infarction who undergo direct PCI.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study was conducted in patients with acute myocardial infarction who undergo direct PCI
      in Chinese PLA General Hospital. The patients were randomly divided into two groups: the
      adequate hydration group guided by Vigileo and control group. For the adequate hydration
      group guided by Vigileo, Vigileo equipment is used to perform hemodynamic monitoring through
      the femoral or radial arteries to obtain relevant hemodynamic parameters (CO, SV, SVV), and
      the fluid-rehydration velocity of normal saline is adjusted according to the flow parameters
      of blood flow. The specific scheme is: if the patient is mechanically ventilated, the
      following scheme is adopted: if SVV≤10%, then adjust the rehydration speed to 1 ml/kg/h; if
      10%＜SVV＜15%, then adjust the rehydration speed to 2 ml/kg/h; if SVV≥15%, then adjust the
      rehydration speed to 5 ml/kg/h. The hydration lasts 24 hours after operation, and the
      rehydration speed is changed according to the SVV. If the patient does not use mechanical
      ventilation, the following scheme is adopted: 250ml normal saline is administered within 10
      minutes after direct PCI, and the rehydration volume changes to 125ml in patients with
      mild-to-moderate congestive heart failure. If the increment of SV≥15%, then adjust the
      rehydration speed to 5 ml/kg/h; if 10%≤the increment of SV＜15%, then adjust the rehydration
      speed to 2 ml/kg/h; if the increment of SV＜10%, then adjust the rehydration speed to 1
      ml/kg/h. Reassessed every 1 hour until SV is stable，and the hydration also lasts 24 hours
      after operation. For the control group, the routine hydration regimen is adopted,
      perioperative saline ≤500 ml hydration. The changes of renal function (serum creatinine,
      serum cystatin), symptoms and signs of cardiac insufficiency during perioperative period and
      cardiac objective indexes (left ventricular ejection fraction, left ventricular end-diastolic
      diameter, brain natriuretic peptide) are observed. The incidence of postoperative acute
      pulmonary edema is recorded, and the major cardiovascular events and hemodialysis events are
      followed up for 6 months. By comparing the perioperative indexes of heart and kidney function
      between the intervention group and the control group, the preventive effect of adequate
      hydration guided by Vigileo on contrast induced nephropathy after direct PCI was clarified.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">June 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Contrast induced nephropathy</measure>
    <time_frame>48-72 hours after direct PCI</time_frame>
    <description>Contrast induced nephropathy is defined as serum creatinine values increased by 0.5 mg/dl or 25% relative to baseline absolute values after direct PCI within 48-72 hours.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The acute renal injury caused by contrast agent</measure>
    <time_frame>48 hours after direct PCI</time_frame>
    <description>The acute renal injury caused by contrast agent is defined as the serum creatinine value increased by 0.3 mg/dl than the baseline absolute value after direct PCI within 48 hours.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Persistent renal insufficiency</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months after direct PCI</time_frame>
    <description>Persistent renal insufficiency is defined as at least 25% decrease compared with baseline in creatinine clearance 3 months after direct PCI.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>renal replacement therapy and/or death from acute renal failure</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months after direct PCI</time_frame>
    <description>renal replacement therapy and/or death from acute renal failure</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Major adverse cardiac events</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months after direct PCI</time_frame>
    <description>all-cause death, non-lethal acute myocardial infarction, revascularization</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">440</enrollment>
  <condition>Acute Myocardial Infarction</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>the adequate hydration group guided by Vigileo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The rehydration speed is adjusted according to SVV.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>the control group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The hydration method is perioperative saline ≤500 ml.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>the adequate hydration group guided by Vigileo</intervention_name>
    <description>If the patient is mechanically ventilated, the following scheme is adopted: if SVV≤10%, then adjust the rehydration speed to 1 ml/kg/h; if 10%＜SVV＜15%, then adjust the rehydration speed to 2 ml/kg/h; if SVV≥15%, then adjust the rehydration speed to 3 ml/kg/h. The hydration lasts 24 hours after operation, and the rehydration speed is changed according to the SVV. If the patient does not use mechanical ventilation, the following scheme is adopted: 250ml normal saline is administered within 10 minutes after direct PCI, and the rehydration volume changes to 125ml in patients with mild-to-moderate congestive heart failure. If the increment of SV≥15%, then adjust the rehydration speed to 3 ml/kg/h; if 10%≤the increment of SV＜15%, then adjust the rehydration speed to 2 ml/kg/h; if the increment of SV＜10%, then adjust the rehydration speed to 1 ml/kg/h. Reassessed every 1 hour until SV is stable，and the hydration also lasts 24 hours after operation.</description>
    <arm_group_label>the adequate hydration group guided by Vigileo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Saline</intervention_name>
    <description>The routine hydration regimen is adopted, perioperative saline ≤500 ml hydration.</description>
    <arm_group_label>the control group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Clearly diagnosed STEMI patients: ischemic chest pain lasting more than 30 minutes and
             adjacent 2 or more leads ST elevation (limb lead ≥0.1Mv, thoracic lead ≥0.2 mV) with
             or without myocardial enzymatic elevation

          -  Chest pain time less than 12 hours

          -  Patients aged 18-75 years

          -  Patients are scheduled to undergo direct percutaneous coronary interventions

          -  Estimated glomerular filtration rate eGFR &lt;100ml / min (according to MDRD formula)

          -  Sign the informed consent to join the group.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with mechanical complications

          -  Patients with cardiogenic shock who requiring IABP

          -  Patients with aortic dissection

          -  Patients who have malignant tumors or short-term progressive diseases that researchers
             believe improper to be included in the group

          -  Hemodialysis-dependent patients with end-stage renal failure

          -  Patients who had a history of exposure to radioactive contrast media within 1 week
             before or 72 hours after direct PCI

          -  Patients who are allergic to radioactive contrast agents

          -  Patients diagnosed with right ventricular myocardial infarction with hypotension
             (defined as systolic blood pressure ≤90 mmHg) on admission.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Geng Qian, MD</last_name>
    <phone>13810914587</phone>
    <email>qiangeng9396@263.net</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Chinese People's Liberation Army General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Peking</city>
        <state>Beijing</state>
        <zip>100853</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Geng Qian, MD</last_name>
      <phone>086-01055499312</phone>
      <email>qiangeng9396@263.net</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mehran R, Aymong ED, Nikolsky E, Lasic Z, Iakovou I, Fahy M, Mintz GS, Lansky AJ, Moses JW, Stone GW, Leon MB, Dangas G. A simple risk score for prediction of contrast-induced nephropathy after percutaneous coronary intervention: development and initial validation. J Am Coll Cardiol. 2004 Oct 6;44(7):1393-9.</citation>
    <PMID>15464318</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>From AM, Bartholmai BJ, Williams AW, Cha SS, McDonald FS. Mortality associated with nephropathy after radiographic contrast exposure. Mayo Clin Proc. 2008 Oct;83(10):1095-100. doi: 10.4065/83.10.1095.</citation>
    <PMID>18828968</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sadeghi HM, Stone GW, Grines CL, Mehran R, Dixon SR, Lansky AJ, Fahy M, Cox DA, Garcia E, Tcheng JE, Griffin JJ, Stuckey TD, Turco M, Carroll JD. Impact of renal insufficiency in patients undergoing primary angioplasty for acute myocardial infarction. Circulation. 2003 Dec 2;108(22):2769-75. Epub 2003 Nov 24.</citation>
    <PMID>14638545</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Marenzi G, Lauri G, Assanelli E, Campodonico J, De Metrio M, Marana I, Grazi M, Veglia F, Bartorelli AL. Contrast-induced nephropathy in patients undergoing primary angioplasty for acute myocardial infarction. J Am Coll Cardiol. 2004 Nov 2;44(9):1780-5.</citation>
    <PMID>15519007</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Caspi O, Habib M, Cohen Y, Kerner A, Roguin A, Abergel E, Boulos M, Kapeliovich MR, Beyar R, Nikolsky E, Aronson D. Acute Kidney Injury After Primary Angioplasty: Is Contrast-Induced Nephropathy the Culprit? J Am Heart Assoc. 2017 Jun 24;6(6). pii: e005715. doi: 10.1161/JAHA.117.005715.</citation>
    <PMID>28647690</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pyxaras SA, Sinagra G, Mangiacapra F, Perkan A, Di Serafino L, Vitrella G, Rakar S, De Vroey F, Santangelo S, Salvi A, Toth G, Bartunek J, De Bruyne B, Wijns W, Barbato E. Contrast-induced nephropathy in patients undergoing primary percutaneous coronary intervention without acute left ventricular ejection fraction impairment. Am J Cardiol. 2013 Mar 1;111(5):684-8. doi: 10.1016/j.amjcard.2012.11.018. Epub 2012 Dec 19.</citation>
    <PMID>23261003</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Brar SS, Aharonian V, Mansukhani P, Moore N, Shen AY, Jorgensen M, Dua A, Short L, Kane K. Haemodynamic-guided fluid administration for the prevention of contrast-induced acute kidney injury: the POSEIDON randomised controlled trial. Lancet. 2014 May 24;383(9931):1814-23. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(14)60689-9.</citation>
    <PMID>24856027</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pannu N, Wiebe N, Tonelli M; Alberta Kidney Disease Network. Prophylaxis strategies for contrast-induced nephropathy. JAMA. 2006 Jun 21;295(23):2765-79. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>16788132</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Task Force on Myocardial Revascularization of the European Society of Cardiology (ESC) and the European Association for Cardio-Thoracic Surgery (EACTS); European Association for Percutaneous Cardiovascular Interventions (EAPCI), Wijns W, Kolh P, Danchin N, Di Mario C, Falk V, Folliguet T, Garg S, Huber K, James S, Knuuti J, Lopez-Sendon J, Marco J, Menicanti L, Ostojic M, Piepoli MF, Pirlet C, Pomar JL, Reifart N, Ribichini FL, Schalij MJ, Sergeant P, Serruys PW, Silber S, Sousa Uva M, Taggart D. Guidelines on myocardial revascularization. Eur Heart J. 2010 Oct;31(20):2501-55. doi: 10.1093/eurheartj/ehq277. Epub 2010 Aug 29.</citation>
    <PMID>20802248</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tumkur SM, Vu AT, Li LP, Pierchala L, Prasad PV. Evaluation of intra-renal oxygenation during water diuresis: a time-resolved study using BOLD MRI. Kidney Int. 2006 Jul;70(1):139-43. Epub 2006 Mar 29.</citation>
    <PMID>16572109</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Epstein FH, Veves A, Prasad PV. Effect of diabetes on renal medullary oxygenation during water diuresis. Diabetes Care. 2002 Mar;25(3):575-8.</citation>
    <PMID>11874950</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Briguori C, Condorelli G. Hydration in contrast-induced acute kidney injury. Lancet. 2014 May 24;383(9931):1786-8. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(14)60753-4.</citation>
    <PMID>24856014</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bagai A, Armstrong PW, Stebbins A, Mahaffey KW, Hochman JS, Weaver WD, Patel MR, Granger CB, Lopes RD. Prognostic implications of left ventricular end-diastolic pressure during primary percutaneous coronary intervention for ST-segment elevation myocardial infarction: Findings from the Assessment of Pexelizumab in Acute Myocardial Infarction study. Am Heart J. 2013 Nov;166(5):913-9. doi: 10.1016/j.ahj.2013.08.006. Epub 2013 Sep 24.</citation>
    <PMID>24176448</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Remmelink M, Sjauw KD, Henriques JP, Vis MM, van der Schaaf RJ, Koch KT, Tijssen JG, de Winter RJ, Piek JJ, Baan J Jr. Acute left ventricular dynamic effects of primary percutaneous coronary intervention from occlusion to reperfusion. J Am Coll Cardiol. 2009 Apr 28;53(17):1498-502. doi: 10.1016/j.jacc.2008.12.058.</citation>
    <PMID>19389559</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Satıroğlu O, Ciçek Y, Bostan M, Cetin M, Bozkurt E. Acute change in left ventricle end-diastolic pressure after primary percutaneous coronary intervention in patients with ST segment elevation myocardial infarction. Am Heart Hosp J. 2010 Winter;8(2):E86-90.</citation>
    <PMID>21928186</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Marenzi G, Ferrari C, Marana I, Assanelli E, De Metrio M, Teruzzi G, Veglia F, Fabbiocchi F, Montorsi P, Bartorelli AL. Prevention of contrast nephropathy by furosemide with matched hydration: the MYTHOS (Induced Diuresis With Matched Hydration Compared to Standard Hydration for Contrast Induced Nephropathy Prevention) trial. JACC Cardiovasc Interv. 2012 Jan;5(1):90-7. doi: 10.1016/j.jcin.2011.08.017.</citation>
    <PMID>22230154</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Maioli M, Toso A, Leoncini M, Micheletti C, Bellandi F. Effects of hydration in contrast-induced acute kidney injury after primary angioplasty: a randomized, controlled trial. Circ Cardiovasc Interv. 2011 Oct 1;4(5):456-62. doi: 10.1161/CIRCINTERVENTIONS.111.961391. Epub 2011 Oct 4.</citation>
    <PMID>21972403</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Qian G, Fu Z, Guo J, Cao F, Chen Y. Prevention of Contrast-Induced Nephropathy by Central Venous Pressure-Guided Fluid Administration in Chronic Kidney Disease and Congestive Heart Failure Patients. JACC Cardiovasc Interv. 2016 Jan 11;9(1):89-96. doi: 10.1016/j.jcin.2015.09.026. Epub 2015 Dec 9.</citation>
    <PMID>26685074</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sugasawa Y, Hayashida M, Yamaguchi K, Kajiyama Y, Inada E. Usefulness of stroke volume index obtained with the FloTrac/ Vigileo system for the prediction of acute kidney injury after radical esophagectomy. Ann Surg Oncol. 2013 Nov;20(12):3992-8.</citation>
    <PMID>23797754</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hofer CK, Senn A, Weibel L, Zollinger A. Assessment of stroke volume variation for prediction of fluid responsiveness using the modified FloTrac and PiCCOplus system. Crit Care. 2008;12(3):R82. doi: 10.1186/cc6933. Epub 2008 Jun 20.</citation>
    <PMID>18570641</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hofer CK, Müller SM, Furrer L, Klaghofer R, Genoni M, Zollinger A. Stroke volume and pulse pressure variation for prediction of fluid responsiveness in patients undergoing off-pump coronary artery bypass grafting. Chest. 2005 Aug;128(2):848-54.</citation>
    <PMID>16100177</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sander M, Spies CD, Berger K, Grubitzsch H, Foer A, Krämer M, Carl M, von Heymann C. Prediction of volume response under open-chest conditions during coronary artery bypass surgery. Crit Care. 2007;11(6):R121.</citation>
    <PMID>18034888</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 7, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 8, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 11, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 8, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 8, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 11, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Chinese PLA General Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Qian geng</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Chinese People's Liberation Army General Hospital</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Myocardial Infarction</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Infarction</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

