<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04382443</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CECI-03</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04382443</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Oral Colchicine in Argentina to Prevent Restenosis</brief_title>
  <acronym>ORCA</acronym>
  <official_title>Oral Colchicine in Argentina (ORCA Trial) for the Prevention of Adverse Events After Percutaneous Coronary Interventions</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Centro de estudios en Cardiologia Intervencionista</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Centro de estudios en Cardiologia Intervencionista</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The Oral treatment of Colchicine in Argentina (ORCA) trial is a prospective, randomized,
      multicenter trial to included 450 patients with indication for myocardial revascularization
      with PCI between a group to be treated with BMS plus oral colchicine (OC) for three months,
      which should be administered at the time of PCI, these patients they would receive 0.5 mg
      twice a day per 3 months compared to the other group of patients who will be treated
      exclusively with last generation of DES.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      In a previous randomized comparison oral colchicine plus bare metal stent (BMS) compared to
      BMS plus placebo in a diabetic High risk for re-stenosis population, OC demonstrate a
      significant reduction of angiographic and intravascular ultrasound parameters of in-stent
      restenosis (ISR) after BMS implantation at one year of follow up (Journal of the American
      College of Cardiology,2013,61,1678-1685), with a clinical indication of target lesion
      revascularization in 3.6%. In addition previous reported registries from our group with Drug
      Eluting Stents showed similar amount of reduction in clinical parameters (not angiographic)
      of restenosis (ERACI III trial, one year TVR in 8.8% with 1st DES design, Rodriguez A et al
      EuroIntervention 2006,2:53-60 and 4.0% with 2nd generation DES design ERACI IV Cardiac and
      cardiovascular interventions Journal, 2014 ). Taking in account those numbers the
      investigators sought to compare differences in overall cost with both revascularization
      strategies at 1, 2, 3 and 5 years of follow up assuming that safety and efficacy clinical end
      points would be similar. Cost included in hospital, procedural and resources fees, follow up
      cost including re-hospitalization driving by target vessel revascularization (TVR) and both
      spontaneous and TVR myocardial infarction (MI) and medication cost for each revascularization
      strategies Safety end point will be incidence of major adverse cardiac events (MACE) defined
      as the composite of death from any cause, MI (peri-procedural and spontaneous at follow up)
      and ischemic driving TVR.

      The study will be considered complete after all subjects have completed the 12-month Primary
      safety and efficacy endpoint was incidence of target vessel failure (TVF) plus one year
      overall cost with both strategies.. Additional end points are clinical endpoints measured
      in-hospital at at follow up period. cardiac death, cardiac death plus MI. spontaneous MI
      beyond 30 day to 5 years, and stent thrombosis rate (ST) (definite or probable by Academic
      Research Consortium definitions).

      A sub-study of changes in biological markers of inflammation in patients with acute coronary
      syndrome (ACS) including MI will be analyzed in both groups. For this reason, a measurement
      of interleukin 6, metalloproteases, adiponectin and Protein C reactive (PCR) will be
      performed at the time of enrolment and 4 days and a month after inclusion.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 12, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>MACE</measure>
    <time_frame>365 days</time_frame>
    <description>MACE: Was defined as a composite of death, Myocardial infarction (MI) and ischemic target vessel revascularization (TVR) Death included cardiac, non- cardiac and non- determined. MI included STEMI with new q waves at the EKG and /or 5 times increase cardiac enzymes elevation for baseline levels. NSTEMI included 5 times enzymes elevation with non- new Q waves.
TVR included repeat revascularization in the target vessel initially treated driving by new chest pain and / or perfusion ischemic changes at ergometric or perfusion test.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Target lesion failure</measure>
    <time_frame>365 days</time_frame>
    <description>Target lesion failure (TLF): TLF was defined as cardiac death, MI and ischemic driving revascularization (TLR) of initially treated lesion.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Changes C-Reactive Protein (CRP) values</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 4 and 30 days</time_frame>
    <description>Normal values: 0 to 5 mg/L</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in Adinopectine values μU/mL</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and 30 days</time_frame>
    <description>Normal values in women 4,62±1,57 vs In men 3,93±1,86 μU/mL</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in Interleukin 6 values (pg/m)</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and 30 days</time_frame>
    <description>Normal values IL-6 (5-15 pg/ml)</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">450</enrollment>
  <condition>Coronary Artery Disease</condition>
  <condition>Restenosis of Coronary Artery Stent</condition>
  <condition>Atherosclerosis</condition>
  <condition>Acute Coronary Syndrome</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Oral Colchicine +BMS implantation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>This group will receive after BMS and Colchicine, at the time of PCI, 0,5 mg twice a day during the first three months after stent implantation</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Second generation Drug eluting stent (DES)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>This group will receive DES at the moment of randomization and will be treated as standard of care.
All second generation DES should be approved by ANMAT for clinical use.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Colchicine</intervention_name>
    <description>At the moment of BMS implantation intervention will mean that this group will receive colchicine as described.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Oral Colchicine +BMS implantation</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>BMS+Colchicine</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Clinical and angiographic

               1. Subject must be at least 18 to 80 years of age.

               2. Subject (or legal guardian) indicates understanding of the trial requirements and
                  the treatment procedures and provides written informed consent before procedures
                  are performed.

               3. Subject is eligible for PCI

               4. Subject has symptomatic coronary artery disease or silent ischemia with objective
                  evidence of ischemia, or acute coronary syndromes, and qualifies for PCI

             6. Subject has a left ventricular ejection fraction (LVEF) &gt; 40 % as measured within
             60 days prior to enrollment.

             7. Subject is willing to comply with all protocol-required follow-up evaluations.

             8. Subject has one or more coronary artery stenosis of ≥ 70 % in a coronary artery
             with visually estimated reference vessel diameter (RVD) ≥2.50 mm.

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Clinical and angiographic

          1. Subject has a known allergy to contrast (that cannot be adequately pre-medicated)
             and/or the stent system or Colchicine. (e.g., cobalt chromium alloy, stainless steel,
             all P2Y12 inhibitors, or aspirin)

          2. Planned surgery within 30 days after the index procedure

          3. Other serious medical illness (e.g., cancer, congestive heart failure) with estimated
             life expectancy of less than 36 months.

          4. Current problems with substance abuse (e.g., alcohol, cocaine, heroin, etc.)

          5. Planned procedure that may cause non-compliance with the protocol or confound data
             interpretation.

          6. Subject has a history of bleeding diathesis or coagulopathy or will refuse blood
             transfusions

        5. Subject is participating in another investigational drug or device clinical trial that
        has not reached its primary endpoint, or that, in the opinion of the investigator, may
        cause non-compliance with the protocol or confound data interpretation.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>110 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sanatorio Otamendi</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ciudad de Buenos Aires</city>
        <state>Buenos Aires</state>
        <zip>1126</zip>
        <country>Argentina</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sanatorio Las Lomas</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Isidro</city>
        <state>Buenos Aires</state>
        <zip>1111</zip>
        <country>Argentina</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Argentina</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 31, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 8, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 11, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 8, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 8, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 11, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Centro de estudios en Cardiologia Intervencionista</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Alfredo E Rodriguez</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>MD, PhD</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>restenosis</keyword>
  <keyword>atherosclerosis</keyword>
  <keyword>acute coronary syndrome</keyword>
  <keyword>percutaneous coronary intervention</keyword>
  <keyword>colchicine</keyword>
  <keyword>inflammation</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Coronary Artery Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Acute Coronary Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Atherosclerosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Colchicine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

