<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04389749</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>OS19088 IRB 2019-0541</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04389749</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Continuous Passive Motion Following Fixation of Pelvic and Knee Fractures</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Role of Continuous Passive Motion in Pain Control of Patients Undergoing Operative Management of Isolated Acetabular Fractures, Supracondylar Femur Fractures, or Tibial Plateau Fracture: A Comparative Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Cincinnati</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Cincinnati</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>Yes</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The investigators will directly compare the visual analog scale scores and narcotic pain
      medication requirements in the patients who have continuous passive motion (CPM) versus those
      who do not during the course of the hospital admission following an open reduction internal
      fixation surgery for acetabular fracture, supracondylar femur fracture, or a tibial plateau
      fracture.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This will be a prospective comparative cohort study analyzing the practices of three
      surgeons, one of whom routinely uses CPM following fixation of pelvic and acetabular
      fractures, and two surgeons who do not.

      All patients, over the age of 18 years who have undergone open reduction and internal
      fixation (ORIF) of isolated acetabular fractures, supracondylar femur fractures, or tibial
      plateau fracture will be asked to participate. Those who consent will be randomized into two
      groups. The experimental group will have a CPM applied in the PACU immediately post-op and it
      will be utilized while the patient is awake in bed for 2 hours on and 2 hours off, when not
      mobilizing with Physical Therapy (PT). The experimental group will also have traditional PT,
      including sessions 1 to 3 times a week. The control group will have typical care, including
      working with physical therapy 1 to 3 times a week. The investigators will directly compare
      the VAS scores and narcotic pain medication requirements in the patients who have CPM versus
      those who do not during the course of the hospital admission. VAS scores will be assessed
      throughout the day by RN and/or PT. Functional outcomes will be assessed at the one-year mark
      using the Iowa and Majeed pelvic functional outcome tools along with the SF-12. Orthopedic
      Resident or Nurse Clinical will check the patient for incision integrity each day and each
      session of using the CPM, the patient will be monitored for adverse events. Data will be
      collected using Epic.

      The investigators will record patient demographics including age, sex, and pre-existing
      narcotic usage. Fracture type according to the Orthopaedic Trauma Association will be
      recorded. VAS scores and pain medication requirements will be recorded from the first 48
      hours during the patient's stay. Pain scores and CPM use will be obtained from Epic using the
      flowsheet.

      Functional outcomes will be assessed at the one-year mark using the Iowa and Majeed pelvic
      functional outcome tools along with the SF-12.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">June 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2026</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2025</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>prospective comparative cohort study</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>VAS Pain Score</measure>
    <time_frame>Visual Analog Score for pain will be recorded daily after the surgery each day until the patient is discharged or up to 365 days..</time_frame>
    <description>Pain will be assessed by the patient on a scale of 1-10 during hospitalization</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>SF-12</measure>
    <time_frame>This score will be completed at the one-year post-operative visit.</time_frame>
    <description>The Short Form 12 (SF-12) uses just 12 questions to measure functional health and well-being from the patient's point of view.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Fractures, Bone</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>CPM</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The experimental group will have a CPM applied in the PACU immediately post-op and it will be utilized while the patient is awake in bed for 2 hours on and 2 hours off, when not mobilizing with Physical Therapy (PT). The experimental group will also have traditional PT, including sessions 1 to 3 times a week.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>No CPM</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>The control group will have typical care, including working with physical therapy 1 to 3 times a week.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>CPM</intervention_name>
    <description>CPM-continuous passive motion device.</description>
    <arm_group_label>CPM</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age 18 or greater

          -  Isolated acetabular fractures, supracondylar femur fractures, or tibial plateau
             fracture

          -  Have undergone operative intervention for fracture

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Injury to either lower extremity that affects the patient's ability to weight bear

          -  Under the age of 18

          -  Pregnant

          -  A prisoner
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Henry C Sagi, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Cincinnati</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Kimberly A Hasselfeld, MS</last_name>
    <phone>513-558-1933</phone>
    <email>hasselky@uc.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <verification_date>May 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>April 26, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 11, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 15, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 11, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 11, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 15, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Cincinnati</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>H. Claude Sagi, MD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Fractures, Bone</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

