<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04383015</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>e2018-306</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04383015</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Carbohydrate and Insulin Requirements During Prolonged Fasted Exercise</brief_title>
  <official_title>Carbohydrate Requirements for Prolonged, Fasted Exercise With and Without Basal Rate Reductions in Individuals With Type 1 Diabetes on Continuous Subcutaneous Insulin Infusion</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>York University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Insulet Corporation</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>York University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to compare the time spent in glucose target range (4.0-10.0
      mmol/L) during exercise and in recovery using three different management strategies for
      prolonged aerobic exercise: A) carbohydrate dose of 0.3g/kg/hr; B) A 50 percent basal rate
      reduction, performed 90-minutes in advance of exercise for the duration of the activity; and
      C) A 50 percent basal rate reduction, performed at exercise onset, with carbohydrate dose of
      0.3g/kg/hr
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This project focuses on the effectiveness of various exercise strategies on the time spent in
      target range during and after aerobic exercise in adults with type 1 diabetes (T1D) on
      continuous subcutaneous insulin infusion (CSII).

      The primary objective of the protocol is to determine if a moderate basal insulin reduction
      (-50 percent of basal), performed 90-minutes before a 120-minute aerobic exercise session
      (with 5-minute breaks every 30 minutes of exercise, and a ten minute break mid-exercise),
      improves the time in target range compared to either a carbohydrate consumption only strategy
      or insulin reduction (-50 percent) and carbohydrate consumption strategy both performed at
      the onset of exercise in patients with T1D on CSII therapy. The time in target will be
      determined for both the exercise period and during a 24-hour window after the end of
      exercise.

      In all three sessions, aerobic exercise (brisk walking) will be performed in the fasted state
      (minimum 8 hours after the last meal) in the early-morning. The exercise will consist of four
      30-minute bouts of walking at 40-50 percent of the participant's pre-determined aerobic
      capacity, separated by 5-10 minute breaks. The participants exercise intensity will be
      monitored continuously using heart rate and activity monitors. Blood glucose and blood ketone
      levels will be monitored throughout exercise.

      Each participant will be assigned to a sequence of the three experimental visits through a
      randomization process. Each exercise session will be separated by at least two days and
      participants will be expected to complete all sessions within ~ 12 weeks from the time of the
      baseline/screening visit. Participants will be instructed to apply a new continuous glucose
      monitor (CGM) sensor between 1-5 days prior, not to perform moderate-to-vigorous exercise 24
      hours prior and refrain from caffeine and alcohol 12 hours prior to each study visit.
      Participants are also instructed not to eat after 2330h the night before arriving to the
      laboratory and not to give bolus insulin or perform temporary basal rate changes after 0200h
      on the morning of the exercise visit. Participants are instructed to try to arrive at the
      laboratory with their blood glucose between 72-270 mg/dL, with no active bolus insulin
      according to personal CSII device, in the fasted state. If a bolus of insulin was given prior
      to the exercise session, the session was rescheduled. Females of reproductive capacity
      performed all three visits in the early follicular phase (days 1-6 of cycle). Participants
      arrived at the laboratory between 0600h and 1000h. Exercise start time was between 0700h and
      1045h, based on participants' choice, and the timing of exercise was kept consistent within
      participants.

      Following each exercise session, the participant will rest for 20-minutes and then leave the
      laboratory. The participants glucose will be monitored for 24-hours after the standardized
      exercise. They will also be instructed to perform a standardized basal insulin reduction
      overnight to help reduce the risk of post-exercise nocturnal hypoglycemia (-20 percent from
      bedtime for 6 hours).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 31, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">October 17, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">October 16, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Patients with type 1 diabetes on insulin pump therapy will remain on their usual insulin regimen. However, we are testing percent basal rate reductions during exercise (50 percent reduction) with or without carbohydrate feeding.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Time in glucose target range during exercise intervention</measure>
    <time_frame>140 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>The primary outcome measurement is to determine which strategy had the best time in blood glucose target range (4.0-10.0 mmol/L) during the prolonged exercise</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Recovery Interstitial Glucose</measure>
    <time_frame>24 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Using CGM to measure recovery glucose levels post-exercise to analyze time in target range, time in hypoglycemia (&lt; 4.0 mmol/L) and time in hyperglycemia (&gt; 10.0 mmol/L).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">15</enrollment>
  <condition>Type 1 Diabetes</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Carbohydrate (CHO)-only</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Carbohydrate dose of 0.3g/kg/hr given every 30 minutes of exercise if blood glucose is in range with usual basal insulin infusion</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>50 Percent Basal Rate Reduction (BRR)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>A 50 percent basal rate reduction set 90-minutes pre-exercise and throughout exercise</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Combo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>The combination of a 50 percent basal rate reduction and carbohydrate dose of 0.3g/kg/hr (given every 30 minutes) both at exercise onset</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Exercise strategies</intervention_name>
    <description>Strategies for exercise in type 1 diabetes to maintain glucose control</description>
    <arm_group_label>50 Percent Basal Rate Reduction (BRR)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Carbohydrate (CHO)-only</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Combo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Clinical diagnosis of presumed autoimmune type 1 diabetes

          -  Last HbA1c ≤ 9.9 percent

          -  Age: 17+ years

          -  Duration of T1D: ≥ 1.5 years

          -  Using insulin pump therapy: ≥3 months (at least 0.25 units of insulin per kilogram of
             body mass)

          -  In good general health with no conditions that could impact the outcome of the trial

          -  Willing to adhere to the protocol requirements for the duration of the study

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Physician diagnosis of active diabetic retinopathy that could be worsened by exercise

          -  Physician diagnosis of peripheral neuropathy or autonomic neuropathy

          -  Medications:

               1. Beta-blockers

               2. Agents that affect hepatic glucose production (xanthine derivatives)

               3. Pramlintide

               4. Any other hypoglycemic agent

          -  Participation in other studies involving the administration of an investigational drug
             or device during the duration of the current study

          -  Severe hypoglycemia in the last 3 months, defined as the individual requiring third
             party assistance or hospitalization
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Michael Riddell, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>York University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>York University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toronto</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>M3J1P3</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 6, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 6, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 11, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 6, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 6, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 11, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>York University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Michael Riddell</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Physical Activity</keyword>
  <keyword>Exercise</keyword>
  <keyword>Carbohydrates</keyword>
  <keyword>Hypoglycemia</keyword>
  <keyword>Continuous Glucose Monitoring</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus, Type 1</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

