<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04380623</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>18-12-890</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04380623</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Tailored, Health Communication Intervention for HPV Vaccine Hesitant Families</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Tailored, Health Communication Intervention for HPV Vaccine Hesitant Families</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Meharry Medical College</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Meharry Medical College</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The human papillomavirus (HPV) causes 90% of cervical cancers and is implicated in multiple
      other cancers. The HPV vaccine can prevent the vast majority of these cancers, but it is
      underused in adolescents, especially among those within vaccine hesitant (VH) parents. The
      proposed research is to develop and pilot test a tailored, health communication intervention
      aimed to increase HPV vaccination among VH parents. The proposed research is innovative
      because no evidence-based health communication interventions target HPV VH parents, and we
      will use stakeholder engagement throughout this study. The research will add knowledge on how
      tailored education provided before a doctor's visit can play a role in improving HPV
      vaccination rates among underserved, VH parents.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The goal of this K01 application is to develop and pilot test an individually tailored,
      pre-visit health communication intervention targeting HPV-VH parents. We will partner with
      the Meharry Medical College Pediatric Group (MMC Pediatrics), a safety-net clinic serving
      primarily publicly-insured and uninsured patients. The study has three specific aims.

      Aim 1. To develop a tailored, health communication intervention targeting HPV-VH parents
      prior to clinic visits. The tailored intervention will be delivered to VH parents via mobile
      phones. We will draft initial content based on the Theory of Reasoned Action and Health
      Belief Model, previous VH research,14 and my preliminary data. We will then conduct
      semi-structured interviews with 25-30 VH parents who previously declined the HPV vaccine and
      10 physicians to elicit feedback on draft content. Qualitative data will be collected and
      analyzed iteratively, informing successive modifications to the intervention to cover a range
      of potential concerns for VH parents, enhance message relevance, and refine the intervention
      delivery process. Next, we will work with MMC Pediatrics to develop and refine the study
      protocol. We will pre-test and get feedback on the protocol from 16 VH parents and 3
      physicians to maximize acceptance and feasibility.

      Aim 2. Conduct a pilot study of the intervention and study protocol to demonstrate
      feasibility for the future full-scale randomized control trial (RCT). Based on Aim 1, we
      conduct a small, pilot RCT with 70 VH parents with scheduled clinic visits. Feasibility
      indicators are recruitment rates, retention rates, and ability to ascertain patients'
      post-visit HPV vaccine status in the clinical record. VHealth software will be used to
      extract information from the EHR to identify potentially eligible patients with a previous
      HPV vaccine refusal and to determine the whether an HPV vaccine dose was received during the
      scheduled visit.

      Aim 3. Examine acceptability of the intervention and protocol among parents and providers.
      Parents participating in the pilot study will complete a post-visit survey to measure
      acceptability of the intervention and protocol, provider trust/rapport, and satisfaction with
      provider-patient communication. In addition, we will conduct semi-structured debriefing
      interviews with a subset of 20-30 parents and 3 providers to gather qualitative data about
      their experiences (e.g., unforeseen problems and barriers) and their perceptions of
      acceptability of the intervention and protocol (e.g., ease of use, content, graphics). The
      findings will be used identify needs for any additional modifications to the intervention and
      protocol prior to the RCT.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">June 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 30, 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 30, 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Care Provider)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Recruitment Rates</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>pre-screened, % contacted, % unable to contact, % screened, % enrolled, # enrolled per month</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Retention Rates</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>% completed baseline survey, % came to clinic visit (primary retention endpoint), % completed post-visit survey</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Data collection processes</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>% ascertained post-visit HPV vaccine status, # minutes to complete surveys</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>HPV vaccine rates</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description># vaccinated post-intervention</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">244</enrollment>
  <condition>Human Papilloma Virus</condition>
  <condition>HPV-Related Carcinoma</condition>
  <condition>Vaccine Refusal</condition>
  <condition>Parents</condition>
  <condition>Program, Communication</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Mobile Phone-Based Web-Page: HPV vaccine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Parents who have already declined the HPV vaccine for their adolescent will receive pre-visit, tailored education information on the HPV vaccine via a text message with a website link.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Mobile Phone-Based Web-Page: Healthy Lifestyles</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Parents who have already declined the HPV vaccine for their adolescent will receive pre-visit education information on an unrelated topic (e.g., healthy eating and physical activity) via a text message with a website link.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Mobile Phone-Based Web-Page: HPV vaccine</intervention_name>
    <description>Website to be accessed via mobile phone to deliver tailored educational material</description>
    <arm_group_label>Mobile Phone-Based Web-Page: HPV vaccine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Mobile Phone-Based Web-Page: Healthy Lifestyles</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Aim 1 Stage 1: (A) VH parents: Parents with unvaccinated children who are patients in MMC
        Pediatrics aged 11-18, refused HPV vaccine in past two years, speak English, own
        smartphone; (B) Providers: physicians, physician assistants, and nurse practitioners who
        deliver primary care to patients aged 11-18.

        Aim 1 Stage 2: (A) Parents of patients of MMC Pediatrics aged 11-18, refused HPV
        vaccination in the past two years, have not received any doses of HPV vaccine, have a
        clinic appointment scheduled within the coming month, speak English, own smartphone, and
        did not participate in Aim 1 Stage 1.

        Aim 2: (A) Parents/guardians of adolescent patients of MMC Pediatrics aged 11-18, refused
        HPV vaccination in the past two years, have not received any doses of HPV vaccine, have a
        clinic appointment scheduled in coming month, speak English, own smartphone, and did not
        participate in Aim 1; and (B) MMC pediatric providers participating in the pilot.

        Aim 3: We will not be recruiting in Aim 3.

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Aim 1 Stage 1: (A) Parents with vaccinated patients or never been offered the vaccine in
        MMC pediatrics aged 11-18, unvaccinated yet never refused the vaccine, do not speak
        English, and do not own a smart phone; (B) Providers who do not deliver primary care to
        patients aged 11-18.

        Aim 1 Stage 2: Parents with vaccinated patients or who have never been offered the vaccine
        in MMC pediatrics aged 11-18, unvaccinated yet never refused the vaccine, do not speak
        English, participated in Aim 1 Stage 1; do not own a smart phone; does not have upcoming
        monthly clinic appointment for child.

        Aim 2: (A) Parents/guardians of adolescent patients of MMC Pediatrics aged 11-18 who have
        vaccinated or not been offered the vaccine, do not have a clinic appointment scheduled in
        coming month, does not speak English, does not own smartphone, and participated in Aim 1;
        and (B) providers not participating in pilot study

        Aim 3: N/A
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Meharry Medical College</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nashville</city>
        <state>Tennessee</state>
        <zip>37208</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jennifer C Erves, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>615-327-5692</phone>
      <email>jerves@mmc.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Desiree Johnson, MHA</last_name>
      <phone>615-327-5654</phone>
      <email>djohnson@mmc.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 5, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 5, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 8, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 5, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 5, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 8, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Papilloma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

