<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04384796</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>KAEK:899</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04384796</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Turkish Version of Infant Movement Motivation Questionnaire</brief_title>
  <official_title>Turkish Validity and Reliability Study of Infant Movement Motivation Questionnaire</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Yeditepe University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Yeditepe University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Purpose: It is the examination of the Infant Movement Motivation Questionnaire of the
      validity and reliability of Turkish.

      Pretest: Participants were informed about the aims of the study and fill in a consent form.
      They filled in a paper version of the Turkish translation of the Infant Movement Motivation
      Questionnaire. The parents had to answer questions about the content and meaning of the IMMQ
      items and sociodemographic.

      Validation Study: Participants were informed about the aims of the study and filled in a
      consent form. The questionnaires of the survey filled in at the early intervention center.
      About 30 minutes were needed to answer the 27 questions of the IMMQ, Ages and Stages
      Questionnaire, and sociodemographic.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The period when human life activity most intense is the first years of life. Different
      practices such as voicing, speaking, sitting, walking, mental skills, communication,
      socializing acquire new skills. Infant Movement Motivation Questionnaire(IMMQ) 27-item scale
      that questions babies' discovery, activity, motivation, and adaptation skills in daily life
      activities through the parent. The scale was developed in 2012 by Samantha Doralp. As the
      scale provides information about how babies spend their time in their natural environment and
      the personal characteristics of babies, it was decided to carry out a validity and
      reliability study in the Turkish language, considering the early use of support programs in
      clinical use. The development of this scale shows the first step in understanding the role of
      baby characteristics in the movement development of babies in the first year of life. A good
      understanding of the link between baby characteristics and motor development can have a
      significant impact on planning interventions and can have a significant impact in ensuring
      that a particular environment is optimally tailored to the child's use and needs.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 1, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 15, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">January 1, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational [Patient Registry]</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Other</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Other</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <target_duration>1 Day</target_duration>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Infant Movement Motivation Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>The survey assesses the willingness of the movement of babies between 0 and 12 months. The questionnaire includes 27 questions in 4 areas: &quot;activity, exploratory behavior, motivation, adaptation&quot;. The questionnaire is answered on a five-point Likert scale by caregivers.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Ages and Stages Questionnaire-2, (ASQ 2)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>It is used to evaluate the development of babies from 3 months 0 days to 60 months with 19 different questionnaires customized by age. It evaluates five different areas: communication, gross motor, fine motor, problem-solving, personal-social.
Each question is answered by the parent as Yes, Sometimes and No. In the calculation of the points, Yes is recorded as 10 points, Sometimes 5 points, and No, 0 points.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">164</enrollment>
  <condition>Infant Development</condition>
  <condition>Temperament</condition>
  <condition>Early Intervention</condition>
  <condition>Infant Behavior</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Babies between 0-12 months who meet the working criteria.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        • Volunteers who have babies with typical development between 0-12 months

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Parents of babies with a neurological diagnosis

          -  Parents of babies with vision, hearing loss

          -  Parents of babies with a genetic and metabolic diagnosis
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>12 Months</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ebru Altunalan</name>
      <address>
        <city>Istanbul</city>
        <zip>34750</zip>
        <country>Turkey</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Turkey</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Doralp S, Bartlett D. Infant Movement Motivation Questionnaire: development of a measure evaluating infant characteristics relating to motor development in the first year of life. Infant Behav Dev. 2014 Aug;37(3):326-33. doi: 10.1016/j.infbeh.2014.04.002. Epub 2014 May 28.</citation>
    <PMID>24861943</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Doralp S, Bartlett DJ. Environmental opportunities questionnaire: development of a measure of the environment supporting early motor development in the first year of life. Disabil Rehabil. 2013 Sep;35(20):1692-7. doi: 10.3109/09638288.2012.751133. Epub 2013 Jan 25.</citation>
    <PMID>23350756</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Caçola PM, Gabbard C, Montebelo MI, Santos DC. Further Development and Validation of the Affordances in the Home Environment for Motor Development-Infant Scale (AHEMD-IS). Phys Ther. 2015 Jun;95(6):901-23. doi: 10.2522/ptj.20140011. Epub 2014 Dec 18.</citation>
    <PMID>25524875</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 8, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 8, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 12, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 30, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 30, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 1, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

