<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00954226</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2008-0137</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2012-01639</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2010-01142</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>2008-0137</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>P30CA016672</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00954226</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Standard-Dose or High-Dose Erlotinib Hydrochloride Before Surgery in Treating Patients With Head and Neck Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase Ib Study of Erlotinib Prior to Surgery in Patients With Head and Neck Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This randomized phase Ib trial studies standard-dose or high-dose erlotinib hydrochloride
      before surgery in treating patients with head and neck cancer. Erlotinib hydrochloride may
      stop the growth of tumor cells by blocking some of the enzymes needed for cell growth.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PRIMARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To determine the effects of erlotinib (erlotinib hydrochloride) 150 mg/day (standard dose)
      and 200 mg/day or 300 mg/day (high-dose) on the phosphorylation of AKT protein downstream
      from epidermal growth factor receptor (EGFR).

      SECONDARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To assess the safety and tolerability of erlotinib 150 mg/day (standard dose) and 200
      mg/day or 300 mg/day (high-dose).

      II. To correlate the effects of erlotinib on the phosphorylation of AKT with the
      immunohistochemical expression level of EGFR and the level of amplification of the EGFR gene
      as determined by fluorescent in situ hybridization (FISH).

      III. To evaluate the preliminary response rate with a short course of erlotinib.

      IV. To evaluate changes in the activation status of proteins downstream from EGFR and other
      receptor tyrosine kinases and in markers of epithelial to mesenchymal transition.

      V. To evaluate changes in blood-based biomarkers. VI. To evaluate the effects of a higher
      dose of erlotinib (300 mg/day) in current smokers.

      TERTIARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To evaluate EGFR gene copy number by fluorescent in situ hybridization. II. To evaluate
      immunohistochemistry, western blotting and reverse phase protein lysate arrays to assess the
      activation (usually phosphorylation) status of other downstream proteins from EGFR and other
      receptor tyrosine kinases (these will include, but are not restricted to: EGFR itself,
      phosphatidylinositol 3 Kinase [PI3K], AKT, mammalian target of rapamycin [mTOR], glycogen
      synthase kinase 3 [GSK3], p70 ribosomal S6 kinase [p70S6K], S6, 4E-binding protein 1[4E-BP1],
      MEK1/2, mitogen-activated protein kinase [MAPK], p38, -c-Jun N-terminal kinase [JNK],
      insulin-like growth factor 1 receptor [IGF-1R], IGF-2R, mesenchymal epithelial transition
      [MET], hypoxia-inducible factor [HIF]) both before and after treatment with erlotinib.

      III. To evaluate immunohistochemical expression levels of markers of epithelial to
      mesenchymal transition (these will include, but are not restricted to: e-cadherin and
      vimentin).

      IV. To study blood-based biomarkers of interest, which will include (but are not restricted
      to): trough levels of erlotinib and its metabolites, a panel of 59 cytokine and angiogenic
      factors measured by available Luminex multiplex beads kits (Bio-Plex 27-Plex &amp; 23-Plex Kits
      [Bio-Rad, Hercules, CA] and Human cardiovascular disease [CVD] Biomarker Panel 1 kit [Linco
      Research, Inc., St, Charles, MO]) as well as validated enzyme-linked immunosorbent assays for
      soluble vascular endothelial growth factor receptor 1(VEGFR1), VEGFR2 (Invitrogen, Carlsbad,
      CA), total IGF-1, IGF-2, insulin-like growth factor-binding protein (IGFBP3) (DSL, Webster,
      TX), and osteopontin (R&amp;D Systems, Minneapolis, MN).

      V. To evaluate whole genome sequencing and/or sequencing of specific genes of interest,
      analysis of gene copy number, messenger ribonucleic acid (mRNA) expression profiles,
      non-coding RNA expression profiles, single nucleotide polymorphisms, deoxyribonucleic acid
      (DNA) methylation profiles, immunohistochemistry of proteins of interest to head and neck
      cancer biology, and proteomics in tumor tissue and/or normal tissue (including blood) before
      and after treatment with erlotinib.

      OUTLINE: Patients are randomized to 1 of 2 treatment arms.

      ARM I: Patients receive standard-dose erlotinib hydrochloride orally (PO) once daily (QD) for
      2-3 weeks (up to 8 weeks if surgery is delayed).

      ARM II: Patients receive high-dose erlotinib hydrochloride PO QD for 2-3 weeks (2-8 weeks for
      current smokers or up to 8 weeks if surgery is delayed).

      After completion of study treatment, patients are followed up within 30 days.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">August 5, 2009</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 31, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 31, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in modulation of the biomarker phospho-Akt in tumor specimens</measure>
    <time_frame>From baseline to surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Modulation of phospho-Akt (difference in immunohistochemistry [IHC] score between the surgical specimen and the baseline biopsy) will be compared between the two treatment arms (i.e., standard-dose and high-dose) with the use of Wilcoxon rank sum test.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">55</enrollment>
  <condition>Recurrent Head and Neck Carcinoma</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Salivary Gland Carcinoma</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Skin Carcinoma</condition>
  <condition>Skin Squamous Cell Carcinoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm I (standard-dose erlotinib hydrochloride)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive standard-dose erlotinib hydrochloride PO QD for 2-3 weeks (up to 8 weeks if surgery is delayed).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm II (high-dose erlotinib hydrochloride)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive high-dose erlotinib hydrochloride PO QD for 2-3 weeks (2-8 weeks for current smokers or up to 8 weeks if surgery is delayed).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Erlotinib Hydrochloride</intervention_name>
    <description>Given PO</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm I (standard-dose erlotinib hydrochloride)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm II (high-dose erlotinib hydrochloride)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Cp-358,774</other_name>
    <other_name>OSI-774</other_name>
    <other_name>Tarceva</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Laboratory Biomarker Analysis</intervention_name>
    <description>Correlative studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm I (standard-dose erlotinib hydrochloride)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm II (high-dose erlotinib hydrochloride)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with histologically confirmed cancer of the head and neck. Patients with
             salivary gland tumors and squamous cell carcinomas of the skin are also eligible.
             (Note: Any patient with a diagnosis of aggressive squamous cell carcinoma of the skin
             and determined to be surgically resectable will be considered for eligibility. These
             patients are typically seen in the Head &amp; Neck surgery clinic and decisions for study
             consideration will be based on consultations with the department of Head &amp; Neck
             surgery.)

          -  The patient must have biopsy-accessible disease.

          -  Patients must be surgical candidates (either definitive or palliative setting).

          -  Patients may have received prior therapy including cytotoxic chemotherapy (e.g.
             platinum drugs and taxanes) and radiation therapy.

          -  Patients must have a performance score (ECOG) of 0-2.

          -  Patients should have adequate bone marrow function, as defined by peripheral
             granulocyte count of &gt;/= 1,000/mm³, and a platelet count of &gt;/= 50,000/mm³.Patients
             must have adequate liver function with a bilirubin &lt;/= 1.5 times the upper limit of
             normal (ULN). Aspartate aminotransferase (AST) and alanine aminotransferase (ALT) must
             be &lt;/= 2 x the ULN and alkaline phosphatase must be &lt;/= 2 x ULN.

          -  Patients should have adequate renal function (serum creatinine &lt;/= 1.5 x ULN).

          -  Age &gt;/= 18 years

          -  Ability to understand and the willingness to sign a written informed consent document
             indicating that they are aware of the investigational nature of the study, in keeping
             with institutional policy

          -  Women of childbearing potential must agree to use adequate contraception (hormonal or
             barrier method of birth control; abstinence) prior to study entry and for the duration
             of study participation. Childbearing potential will be defined as women who have had
             menses within the past 12 months,who have not had tubal ligation or bilateral
             oophorectomy. Should a woman become pregnant or suspect that she is pregnant while
             participating in this study,she should inform her treating physician immediately.The
             patient,if a man,agrees to use effective contraception or abstinence.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with prior exposure to small molecule tyrosine kinase inhibitors or
             EGFR-targeted antibodies within the past 6 months.

          -  Patients for whom, in the opinion of the treating surgeon, the administration of
             erlotinib would cause a deleterious delay in surgical treatment.

          -  Patients with uncompensated congestive cardiac failure.

          -  Patients with an organ allograft.

          -  Patients with a serious concurrent infection or illness including, but not limited to,
             unstable angina pectoris, cardiac arrhythmia, or psychiatric illness that could limit
             compliance with study requirements.

          -  Female patients who are pregnant or breastfeeding

          -  Patients currently on chemotherapy, immunotherapy, or therapy with monoclonal
             antibodies or other investigational agents with anti-tumor activity
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Xiuning Le</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>M D Anderson Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.mdanderson.org</url>
    <description>MD Anderson Cancer Center Website</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>December 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 6, 2009</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 6, 2009</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 7, 2009</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 28, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 28, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 2, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Head and Neck Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Erlotinib Hydrochloride</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

