<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04283500</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>19-01700</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04283500</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Buprenorphine Loading in the Emergency Department</brief_title>
  <official_title>Buprenorphine Loading in the Emergency Department</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>NYU Langone Health</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Emergency Medicine Foundation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>NYU Langone Health</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Buprenorphine (BUP) is FDA-approved for the treatment of opioid withdrawal and opioid use
      disorder. Few ED providers have received the necessary DEA registration (aka X waiver)
      required to prescribe BUP, and urgent appointments to continue ongoing BUP treatment may not
      be readily available, thus leading to medication discontinuity. A loading dose induction
      strategy with 32mg of BUP may help effectively link ED patients to outpatient treatment while
      minimizing known barriers to ED uptake. Administering a &quot;loading dose&quot; of BUP to saturate
      mu-opioid receptors would extend the duration of action and provide additional time to secure
      ongoing treatment. Further, BUP's ceiling effect on respiratory depression makes it a
      remarkably safe drug even at high doses. In recent years, ED providers have begun to
      incorporate this approach into clinical protocols, however, it has not been formally studied
      in this clinical setting. The investigator's study represents the necessary step of studying
      this novel approach in the ED setting to define the parameters for clinical protocols and
      large-scale studies.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      A novel induction strategy, in which a loading dose of Buprenorphine (BUP) 32mg is
      administered, has the potential to mitigate barriers to treatment initiation. ED providers
      can treat patients with BUP for opioid withdrawal since DEA registration (X-waiver) is not
      required unless they wish to issue a prescription. Current BUP induction protocols, developed
      for inpatient and ambulatory care settings as well as for unobserved self- administration via
      prescription, usually recommend a first day dose of 8mg given in divided doses of 2- 4mg.
      However, patients discharged with ≤ 8mg SL total dose may experience return of withdrawal
      symptoms and/or opioid craving within only 4 hours.Treatment with a loading dose of 32mg in
      the ED may provide the necessary bridge treatment, relieving symptoms of withdrawal until a
      patient is able to attend a follow up appointment for further treatment.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">March 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of participants with successful rapid induction</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 0</time_frame>
    <description>This will be measured by the proportion of participants who report Successful Rapid Induction. Participants will receive a loading dose of BUP SL 32mg in the ED without experiencing a clinically significant serious and/or severe adverse event (AE) related to the intervention - specifically, the receipt of a dose of BUP SL greater than 8mg during the Index ED visit. Successful rapid induction is defined only by the outcome of the participant's visit, and not by any following research visits.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in opioid withdrawal and craving using COWS</measure>
    <time_frame>Index ED Visit 1(Day 0), Research Visit 2 ( Day 1), Research Visit 3 (Day 2), Research Visit 4 (Day 3)]</time_frame>
    <description>The Clinical Opiate Withdrawal Scale (COWS) is an 11-item scale designed to be administered by a clinician. The tool can be used in both inpatient and outpatient settings to reproducibly rate common signs and symptoms of withdrawal and monitor these symptoms over time. The summed score can be used to help clinicians determine the stage or severity of withdrawal and assess the level of physical dependence on opioids. The change in withdrawal and craving symptoms will be measured using COWS during the index visit, as well as during the research visits on days 1, 2, and 3.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Opioid withdrawal and craving scores using SOWS during the index ED visit</measure>
    <time_frame>Index ED Visit 1(Day 0), Research Visit 2 ( Day 1), Research Visit 3 (Day 2), Research Visit 4 (Day 3)]</time_frame>
    <description>The Subjective Opiate Withdrawal Scale (SOWS) is a self-administered scale for grading opioid withdrawal symptoms. It contains 16 symptoms whose intensity the patient rates on a scale of 0 (not at all) to 4 (extremely). Similar to COWS, the score is used to assess stage and severity of withdrawal and level of physical dependence on opioids. SOWS will be assessed during the index visit, as well as research visits on days 1, 2, and 3.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Time to next BUP dose (length of withdrawal suppression)</measure>
    <time_frame>Research Visit 2 ( Day 1), Research Visit 3 (Day 2), Research Visit 4 (Day 3), Research phone call (Day 30)</time_frame>
    <description>Participants will asked to report the date and time of the next dose of BUP following the loading dose given during their index visit. If needed for treatment of withdrawal, this dose may be administered or prescribed by the study team during a research visit.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in the Opioid and other illicit drug use</measure>
    <time_frame>Research Visit 2 ( Day 1), Research Visit 3 (Day 2), Research Visit 4 (Day 3), Research phone call (Day 30)</time_frame>
    <description>Participants will be asked to report any use of opioids as well as other illicit drugs during the study period. Usage patterns of opioids and other substances will be compared from before and after administration of the 32 mg loading dose of BUP. Substance use will be reported at each research visit, as well as during the 30 day follow up phone call. During the phone call, the Timeline Follow-Back method (TLFB) will be used to report usage during the past 30 days.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in healthcare utilization</measure>
    <time_frame>Research Visit 2 ( Day 1), Research Visit 3 (Day 2), Research Visit 4 (Day 3), Research phone call (Day 30)</time_frame>
    <description>Change in healthcare utilization using the non-study treatment service use form, participant satisfaction and perceived utility of ED-initiated intervention. Engagement in treatment will be assessed by self-report and/or confirmed by treatment provider.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">35</enrollment>
  <condition>Opioid-use Disorder</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>BUP treatment arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects will be given BUP 32mg in 2 doses, and observed for at least 90 minutes after the 2nd dose. The whole process will take a total of about 3-4 hours including the consenting process. Subjects will be asked questions and be examined repeatedly. Subjects will have 4 in-person visits and a phone call in addition to review of medical records.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Buprenorphine Naloxone</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will receive the BUP SL 32mg in divided doses rather than all at once. If after the initial 8mg dose a participant experiences over-sedation or another adverse event that would preclude further dosing, such as an allergic reaction, the subsequent dose will not be administered and the patient will be withdrawn from the study. The participant will be reassessed for other possible etiologies for these symptoms.</description>
    <arm_group_label>BUP treatment arm</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Suboxone</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Is able to speak English sufficiently to understand the study procedures and provide
             written informed consent to participate in the study.

          -  Meets DSM-5 criteria for moderate to severe OUD

          -  Has a positive urine screen for opioids and a negative urine screen for methadone

          -  Must be experiencing opioid withdrawal with a COWS score ≥8

          -  Is willing and able to participate in the study and follow study procedures

          -  Is able to provide adequate and reliable locator information for follow-up

          -  Has reliable access to a phone

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Is currently engaged in medication treatment for OUD with methadone, BUP, or
             naltrexone

          -  Has a urine toxicology test that is positive for methadone or buprenorphine

          -  Currently requires prescribed opioids for treatment of an ongoing pain condition

          -  Has a known allergy to BUP

          -  Is pregnant as determined by urine hCG testing at the index ED visit

          -  Is breastfeeding as determined by self-report

          -  Has medical, psychiatric, or concurrent substance use conditions or severe cognitive
             impairment which might prelude safe participation

          -  Is a prisoner or in police custody at the time of the index ED visit

          -  Has previously enrolled in the current study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ryan McCormack, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>NYU Langone</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Ryan McCormack</last_name>
    <phone>2122632862</phone>
    <email>Ryan.McCormack@nyulangone.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Zelda Moran</last_name>
    <phone>6465010125</phone>
    <email>Zelda.Moran@nyulangone.org</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <verification_date>February 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 21, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 24, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 25, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 24, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 24, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 25, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Emergencies</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Buprenorphine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Buprenorphine, Naloxone Drug Combination</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Naloxone</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Individual participant data that underlie the results reported in this article, after deidentification (text, tables, figures, and appendices).</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Statistical Analysis Plan (SAP)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>Beginning 9 months and ending 36 months following article publication or as required by a condition of awards and agreements supporting the research.</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>The investigator who proposed to use the data. Upon reasonable request. Requests should be directed to Ryan.McCormack@nyulangone.org. To gain access, data requestors will need to sign a data access agreement.</ipd_access_criteria>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

