<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04281901</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>0120-146/2019/5</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04281901</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Efficacy of Platelet- and Extracellular Vesicle-rich Plasma in Chronic Postsurgical Temporal Bone Inflammations</brief_title>
  <acronym>PvRP-ear</acronym>
  <official_title>Efficacy of Platelet- and Extracellular Vesicle-rich Plasma for the Treatment of Chronically Inflamed Post-surgical Temporal Bone Cavities: a Randomised Controlled Clinical Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University Medical Centre Ljubljana</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Ljubljana</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Ljubljana, Faculty of Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University Medical Centre Ljubljana</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This clinical study evaluates the efficacy of the autologous blood-derived product called
      platelet- and extracellular vesicle-rich plasma (PVRP) for the treatment of chronically
      inflamed post-surgical temporal bone cavities. Half of the participants will be treated with
      platelet- and extracellular vesicle-rich plasma and another half with standard nonsurgical
      measures.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The hypothesis of this study is that platelet- and extracellular vesicle-rich plasma (PVRP)
      may be efficient in the treatment of chronically inflamed post-surgical temporal bone
      cavities.

      Platelet-rich plasma (PRP) is a well-known autologous blood-derived product with favourable
      immune, haemostatic and regenerative effects. It has been used in various medical fields
      including otorhinolaryngology.

      In fact, PRP contains important concentrations of extracellular vesicles (EV) which are the
      main contributors to PRP effects. For that reason, PRP can be identified as platelet- and
      extracellular vesicle-rich plasma (PVRP). In this study, PVRP will be prepared by a unique
      non-commercial 2-step centrifugation protocol developed by this study researchers.

      A radical cavity is a large post-surgical temporal bone cavity due to removal of the
      posterior external ear canal wall in open-technique cholesteatoma surgery. This technique is
      performed in approximately 40 per cent of cholesteatoma surgery.

      Radical cavities become inflamed in 3-20 per cent, which leads to the formation of
      granulation tissue and multiple suppurative periods. The large spectrum of surgical and
      nonsurgical treatment options have been applied to reduce patient discomfort. This
      significantly worsens the patients' quality of life and puts a significant burden on health
      care.

      Due to the knowledge of local immune response mechanisms in moist radical cavities and
      exhausted treatment options, new conservative treatment options have been researched. PVRP
      could present a promising treatment option for chronically inflamed radical cavities based on
      published preclinical and clinical studies.

      PVRP will be administered to chronically inflamed radical cavities via PVRP-soaked ear wicks.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 24, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Participants treated with PVRP will receive PVRP-soaked ear wicks at the day of recruitment, additionally 1 month later and then followed-up twice in 1-month intervals. Participants not treated with PVRP will be treated with standard conservative nonsurgical measures with the same follow-up time.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>A person unaware of the participants and their random allocation will measure inflammation area with computer software provided by ZEN Lite, Zeiss.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in inflammation surface area</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 1 month, 2 months and 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Surface of inflamed radical cavity tissue observed by otomicroscopic examination</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Chronic Otitis Media Questionnaire 12 score</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 1 month, 2 months and 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Sum score of Chronic Otitis Media Questionnaire 12 (COMQ-12), patient-reported health-related quality of life measure.
Each question is scored from 0 to 5 points, therefore the minimum score value is 0 and the maximum 60.
A higher score means worse chronic otitis media-related quality of life. A higher change in COMQ-12 score means a better treatment outcome.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in microbial presence</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 2 months</time_frame>
    <description>Change in microbial presence based on microbiological analysis of ear swabs</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">25</enrollment>
  <condition>Otitis Media Chronic</condition>
  <condition>Temporal Bone</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>PVRP treated participants</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will receive PVRP in the chronically inflamed radical cavity at the baseline evaluation (day 0) and 1 month later (1. follow-up). There will be 2 additional follow-ups with a 1-month interval.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Standardly treated participants</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will receive standard conservative measures for the chronically inflamed radical cavity at the baseline evaluation (day 0), 1 month later (1. follow-up), 2 months later (2. follow-up) and 3 months later (3. follow-up).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Platelet- and extracellular vesicle-rich plasma</intervention_name>
    <description>ear wick soaked in platelet- and extracellular vesicle-rich plasma</description>
    <arm_group_label>PVRP treated participants</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Standard conservative treatment</intervention_name>
    <description>standard conservative measures, including antimicrobials, antiseptics and aural toilette for treating a chronically inflamed radical cavity.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Standardly treated participants</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  chronic otitis media, defined as a presence of at least 1 of the following: visible
             ear discharge, indirect signs of ear discharge (e.g. on a pillow, clothes), ear
             itching, the sensation of ear fullness, clinical signs of acute exacerbation of
             chronic otitis media during an otomicroscopic examination.

          -  non-cholesteatomatous chronic otitis media despite prior standard conservative
             treatment

          -  non-cholesteatomatous chronic otitis media despite prior surgical treatment

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  the presence or suspicion of cholesteatoma

          -  infection of venepuncture site

          -  pregnancy

          -  breastfeeding

          -  long-term treatment with antimicrobial drugs

          -  long-term treatment with immunosuppressant drugs

          -  the presence of systemic infectious disease

          -  the presence of an autoimmune disease

          -  the presence of cancer

          -  receiving other types of experimental treatment for chronic otitis media
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Saba Battelino, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Department of Otorhinolaryngology and Cervicofacial Surgery, UMC Ljubljana</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Medical Centre Ljubljana</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ljubljana</city>
        <zip>1000</zip>
        <country>Slovenia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Slovenia</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Vozel D, Uršič B, Krek JL, Štukelj R, Kralj-Iglič V. Applicability of extracellular vesicles in clinical studies. Eur J Clin Invest. 2017 Apr;47(4):305-313. doi: 10.1111/eci.12733. Epub 2017 Feb 28. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>28156006</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Uršič B, Vozel D, Šuštar V, Kocjančič B, Dolinar D, Kralj-Iglič V. Extracellular Vesicles from Platelet-Rich Plasma as Conveyors of Regeneration Potential in Orthopedics. J Hematol Thromboembolic Dis 2(5), 2014.</citation>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 20, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 20, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 24, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 5, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 5, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 9, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University Medical Centre Ljubljana</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Domen Vozel, MD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>MD</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Otitis Media</keyword>
  <keyword>Mastoidectomy</keyword>
  <keyword>Wound Healing</keyword>
  <keyword>Platelet-Rich Plasma</keyword>
  <keyword>Extracellular Vesicles</keyword>
  <keyword>Cholesteatoma</keyword>
  <keyword>Regenerative Medicine</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Otitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Otitis Media</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Blister</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>IPD relevant for the results will be shared</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Statistical Analysis Plan (SAP)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Informed Consent Form (ICF)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>Data will be available from the beginning of the study until the conclusion.</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>Access for the data affecting results will be provided. Access to this data will be provided by the central contact person or central contact backup. No personal identification information will be provided.</ipd_access_criteria>
  </patient_data>
  <pending_results>
    <submitted>June 16, 2020</submitted>
    <returned>July 2, 2020</returned>
    <submitted>July 6, 2020</submitted>
    <returned>July 17, 2020</returned>
    <submitted>July 17, 2020</submitted>
  </pending_results>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

