<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04284618</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>1100/2019</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04284618</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Off Axis View Radiographs Assessing Hallux Valgus Interphalangeus in Hallux Valgus Deformity</brief_title>
  <official_title>Off Axis View Radiographs Assessing Hallux Valgus Interphalangeus in Hallux Valgus Deformity: A Comparison With the Traditional Anteroposterior Standing Radiographs</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Dr.Gerhard Kaufmann</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Medical University Innsbruck</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>OFZ Innsbruck</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      In hallux valgus deformity an additional deformity of the proximal phalangeal bone can be
      observed frequently as well. Due to a hyperpronation of the greater toe on standardized
      radiographs the deformity defining angles are likely to be underestimated. Therefore the
      investigators developed an off axis view radiograph for determining the real deformity. This
      study compares the standardized and the off axis view radiographs.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Hallux valgus is a frequent deformity of the first ray of the foot with adduction and
      pronation of the greater toe at the first metatarsophalangeal joint and abduction of the
      first metatarsal at the first tarsometatarsal joint. Valgus deformity of the greater toe
      itself - so called &quot;Hallux valgus interphalangeus (HVI)&quot; - can be found regularly in hallux
      valgus deformities as well. Various osteotomies and soft tissue procedures to correct hallux
      valgus deformity have been proposed so far. While corrective osteotomies of the first
      metatarsal bone represent the main therapeutical option in hallux valgus correction, the need
      for additional phalangeal osteotomy of the greater toe (e.g., Akin osteotomy) is discussed
      controversial and remains a surgeon's decision to date. In this context, the decision to
      perform an additional Akin osteotomy depends on the radiographic measurement of the hallux
      valgus interphalangeus deformity.

      The following radiographic angles to define HVI have been used most consistently in the
      literature so far: The hallux interphalangeal angle (HIA), the proximal to distal phalangeal
      articular angle (PDPAA), the proximal phalangeal articular angle (PPAA) or distal articular
      set angle (DASA), and the distal phalangeal articular angle (DPAA). To date, a hallux valgus
      interphalangeal angle of greater than 10 degrees serves as the most frequently used
      definition of HVI. However, the measurement of HIA is prone to error due to the irregular
      geometry of the distal phalanx. Therefore, the proximal to distal phalangeal articular angle
      might describe hallux valgus interphalangeus deformity more precisely and reliably.
      Furthermore, a significant hyperpronation of the phalangeal bone can be observed frequently
      in hallux valgus deformity. This phalangeal hyperpronation results in a non-orthogonal
      projection of the greater toe on preoperative films, which might be the cause for
      underestimation of HVI on standardized weightbearing radiographs.

      The aim of this study is to investigate the reliability of radiological assessment of hallux
      valgus interphalangeus and to evaluate, if HVI can be defined more precisely using
      intraoperative anteroposterior &quot;off axis view&quot; radiographs additionally. The investigators
      hypothesize that (1) HVI is underestimated on pre-operative standardized anteroposterior
      radiographs compared to anteroposterior off axis views; (2) the Investigators hypothesize
      that PDPAA shows significantly less intra- and interobserver variance and is therefore more
      reliable than other angles (HIA, PPAA, DPAA) for measuring HVI; and (3) the investigators
      hypothesize, that the detected differences between weightbearing and off axis radiographs are
      a function of the severity of the deformity
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 10, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">August 30, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 31, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Retrospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>reliability of standardized Standing radiographs for defining hallux valugs interphalangeus</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Analysis of the reliability of radiological angles hallux valgus interphalangeus and evaluation, if Hallux valgus interphalangeus can be determined more precisely on off axis view radiographs. Evaluation is made with specific radiographic angles. The used angles are the following: hallux interphalangeal angle (HIA), the proximal to distal phalangeal articular angle (PDPAA), the proximal phalangeal articular angle (PPAA) or distal articular set angle (DASA), and the distal phalangeal articular angle (DPAA).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>correlation of hallux valgus interphalangeus angles with the severity of hallux valgus deformity</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>analysis of hallux valgus severity and ist influence on weightbearing and off axis radiographs by the use of radiographic angles. The used angles are the following: hallux interphalangeal angle (HIA), the proximal to distal phalangeal articular angle (PDPAA), the proximal phalangeal articular angle (PPAA) or distal articular set angle (DASA), and the distal phalangeal articular angle (DPAA).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Hallux Valgus Interphalangeus</condition>
  <condition>Hallux Valgus</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>assessment of radiographic angles on standardized films</arm_group_label>
    <description>On Standing standardized radiographs of the foot the most common angles for describing a hallux valgus interphalangeus deformity are measured. The measured angles are the following: The hallux interphalangeal angle (HIA), the proximal to distal phalangeal articular angle (PDPAA), the proximal phalangeal articular angle (PPAA) or distal articular set angle (DASA), and the distal phalangeal articular angle (DPAA).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>assessment of radiographic angles on off axis view films</arm_group_label>
    <description>On off axis view radiographs of the foot the most common angles for describing a hallux valgus interphalangeus deformity are measured. The measured angles are the following: The hallux interphalangeal angle (HIA), the proximal to distal phalangeal articular angle (PDPAA), the proximal phalangeal articular angle (PPAA) or distal articular set angle (DASA), and the distal phalangeal articular angle (DPAA).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>assessment of standardized and off axis view radiographs</intervention_name>
    <description>Radiographic assessment of hallux valgus interphalangeus angles is performed on preoperative standing anteroposterior and on off axis view radiographs. These radiographs are taken by equalizing the hyperpronation of the greater toe.</description>
    <arm_group_label>assessment of radiographic angles on off axis view films</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>assessment of radiographic angles on standardized films</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        a retrospective cohort of 60 patients is assessed
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  All patients who have undergone surgery for hallux valgus deformity by open or
             minimally invasive percutaneous hallux valgus correction at the Orthopedic and Foot
             Center Innsbruck between November 2018 and May 2019.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Incomplete radiological data (preoperative and intraoperative radio-graphs)

          -  Pregnancy

          -  missing of written informed consent
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Gerhard Kaufmann</name>
      <address>
        <city>Innsbruck</city>
        <state>Tirol</state>
        <zip>6020</zip>
        <country>Austria</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Austria</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kaufmann G, Sinz S, Giesinger JM, Braito M, Biedermann R, Dammerer D. Loss of Correction After Chevron Osteotomy for Hallux Valgus as a Function of Preoperative Deformity. Foot Ankle Int. 2019 Mar;40(3):287-296. doi: 10.1177/1071100718807699. Epub 2018 Oct 31.</citation>
    <PMID>30379084</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Partio N, Mäenpää H, Huttunen T, Haapasalo H, Laine HJ, Mattila VM. Incidence of hallux valgus primary surgical treatment. Finnish nationwide data from 1997 to 2014. Foot Ankle Surg. 2019 Dec;25(6):761-765. doi: 10.1016/j.fas.2018.10.001. Epub 2018 Oct 17.</citation>
    <PMID>31796164</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Deenik A, van Mameren H, de Visser E, de Waal Malefijt M, Draijer F, de Bie R. Equivalent correction in scarf and chevron osteotomy in moderate and severe hallux valgus: a randomized controlled trial. Foot Ankle Int. 2008 Dec;29(12):1209-15. doi: 10.3113/FAI.2008.1209.</citation>
    <PMID>19138485</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Klugarova J, Hood V, Bath-Hextall F, Klugar M, Mareckova J, Kelnarova Z. Effectiveness of surgery for adults with hallux valgus deformity: a systematic review. JBI Database System Rev Implement Rep. 2017 Jun;15(6):1671-1710. doi: 10.11124/JBISRIR-2017-003422. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>28628523</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Thordarson DB, Rudicel SA, Ebramzadeh E, Gill LH. Outcome study of hallux valgus surgery--an AOFAS multi-center study. Foot Ankle Int. 2001 Dec;22(12):956-9. Erratum in: Foot Ankle Int 2002 Feb;23(2):96.</citation>
    <PMID>11783920</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kaufmann G, Hofmann M, Braito M, Ulmer H, Brunner A, Dammerer D. Need for concomitant Akin osteotomy in patients undergoing Chevron osteotomy can be determined preoperatively: a retrospective comparative study of 859 cases. J Orthop Surg Res. 2019 Aug 28;14(1):277. doi: 10.1186/s13018-019-1319-2.</citation>
    <PMID>31455364</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kaufmann G, Hofmann M, Ulmer H, Putzer D, Hofer P, Dammerer D. Outcomes after scarf osteotomy with and without Akin osteotomy a retrospective comparative study. J Orthop Surg Res. 2019 Jun 26;14(1):193. doi: 10.1186/s13018-019-1241-7.</citation>
    <PMID>31242910</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 19, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 22, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 26, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 22, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 22, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 26, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>OFZ Innsbruck</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Dr.Gerhard Kaufmann</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Dr. Gerhard Kaufmann, Principal investigator and Head of the Orthopaedic and Foot Center Innsbruck</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hallux Valgus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Bunion</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

