<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04286802</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>04-60-21</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04286802</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Impact of Self-monitoring of Salt Intake by Salt Meter in Hypertensive Patients</brief_title>
  <acronym>SMAL-SALT</acronym>
  <official_title>Impact of Self-monitoring of Salt Intake by Salt Meter in Hypertensive Patients</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Mahidol University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Mahidol University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Hypertension is one of the most common chronic medical conditions. The concerned sequelae are
      the cardiovascular complications, especially acute myocardial infarction and stroke. In
      Thailand, the incidence of hypertension is increasing each year. Many clinical studies found
      that salt intake over the reference level (&gt;5 g/day) would result in elevated blood pressure
      (BP) and long-term morbidity. Dietary salt reduction campaigns were unsuccessful, in part,
      due to time limitation in the clinic, lacking of awareness, and the higher threshold to
      detect salt taste in chronic high salt ingestion. Salt meter is a device used to detect
      sodium content in daily food. It will facilitate monitoring and control of salt intake. The
      24-hour urinary sodium excretion is an acceptable method to reflect the quantity of sodium
      intake. This study aimed to compare the efficacy of salt meter plus dietary education
      compared with education alone in terms of salt intake reduction, blood pressure, salt taste
      sensitivity, and vascular consequence.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      A randomized-controlled trial was conducted in hypertensive patients whose BP was
      uncontrolled (systolic BP ≥140 mmHg or diastolic BP ≥90 mmHg) despite therapy or
      antihypertensive-naïve. Patients were randomized to receive salt meter to use in conjunction
      with dietary education (group A) or receive education only (group B), and were followed up
      for 8 weeks. Dietary education was provided by certified dietician without awareness of
      patients' allocation. The primary endpoint was change in 24-hour urinary sodium excretion.
      Changes in BP, salt taste sensitivity threshold, cardio-ankle vascular index (CAVI), as well
      as motivation to maintain low salt diet were also analyzed.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 11, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 28, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 21, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>24-hour urinary sodium excretion</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Change in 24-hour urinary sodium excretion from baseline</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in systolic and diastolic blood pressure</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Changes in systolic and diastolic blood pressure from baseline</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Improvement in salt taste sensitivity by evaluating the salt detection or recognition thresholds</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Using the different saline concentration in solution. Starting from the lowest to higher concentration, the point when the patient can differentiate from distilled water is called &quot;detection threshold&quot;, and the point that patient can identify salty taste is called &quot;recognition&quot; threshold.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in cardio-ankle vascular index (CAVI)</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Change in cardio-ankle vascular index (CAVI) from baseline</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Number of patients with hypertensive emergency</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Number of patients documented to have hospitalisation for hypertension treatment including hypertensive emergency requiring intravenous antihypertensive agents.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Questionnaire about motivation to maintain low salt diet</measure>
    <time_frame>after 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Scale from 0 to 10 to estimate self motivation for taking low salt strategy at baseline and at 8 weeks</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Hypertension</condition>
  <condition>Salt; Excess</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Salt-meter</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients received salt-meter in conjunction with dietary education by trained dietician to help monitoring the salt content in food, as well as usual care by their primary physicians.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients received dietary education by trained dietician and usual care by their primary physicians.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Salt-meter</intervention_name>
    <description>Salt-meter, developed by Faculty of Engineering at Mahidol University, is a device to measure sodium chloride content in the food and reflects to user with number and symbols for easy-understanding.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Salt-meter</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Education</intervention_name>
    <description>Program dietary education by certified dietician who did not know the patients arm allocation.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Salt-meter</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Mean SBP 140-179 mmHg or mean DBP 90-109 mmHg (average 3 times)

          -  Diagnosed of hypertension for at least 3 months

          -  No adjustment of antihypertensive agents for at least 1 month

          -  24h Urine sodium ≥ 90 mmol/day

          -  eGFR ≥ 45 ml/min/1.73 sq.m.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  eGFR &lt; 45 ml/min/1.73 sq.m.

          -  UACR &gt; 300 mg/g

          -  Serum potassium &gt; 6.0 mmol/l

          -  Serum sodium &lt; 135 mmol/l

          -  Unable to collect 24-hour urine
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Faculty of Medicine, Ramathibodi Hospital, Mahidol University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bangkok</city>
        <zip>10400</zip>
        <country>Thailand</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Thailand</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mente A, O'Donnell MJ, Rangarajan S, McQueen MJ, Poirier P, Wielgosz A, Morrison H, Li W, Wang X, Di C, Mony P, Devanath A, Rosengren A, Oguz A, Zatonska K, Yusufali AH, Lopez-Jaramillo P, Avezum A, Ismail N, Lanas F, Puoane T, Diaz R, Kelishadi R, Iqbal R, Yusuf R, Chifamba J, Khatib R, Teo K, Yusuf S; PURE Investigators. Association of urinary sodium and potassium excretion with blood pressure. N Engl J Med. 2014 Aug 14;371(7):601-11. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa1311989.</citation>
    <PMID>25119606</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cook NR, Kumanyika SK, Cutler JA, Whelton PK; Trials of Hypertension Prevention Collaborative Research Group. Dose-response of sodium excretion and blood pressure change among overweight, nonhypertensive adults in a 3-year dietary intervention study. J Hum Hypertens. 2005 Jan;19(1):47-54.</citation>
    <PMID>15343354</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>MacGregor GA, Markandu ND, Sagnella GA, Singer DR, Cappuccio FP. Double-blind study of three sodium intakes and long-term effects of sodium restriction in essential hypertension. Lancet. 1989 Nov 25;2(8674):1244-7.</citation>
    <PMID>2573761</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Piovesana Pde M, Sampaio Kde L, Gallani MC. Association between Taste Sensitivity and Self-Reported and Objective Measures of Salt Intake among Hypertensive and Normotensive Individuals. ISRN Nutr. 2012 Oct 24;2013:301213. doi: 10.5402/2013/301213. eCollection 2013.</citation>
    <PMID>24967247</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kusaba T, Mori Y, Masami O, Hiroko N, Adachi T, Sugishita C, Sonomura K, Kimura T, Kishimoto N, Nakagawa H, Okigaki M, Hatta T, Matsubara H. Sodium restriction improves the gustatory threshold for salty taste in patients with chronic kidney disease. Kidney Int. 2009 Sep;76(6):638-43. doi: 10.1038/ki.2009.214. Epub 2009 Jun 10.</citation>
    <PMID>19516246</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 11, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 25, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 27, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 25, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 25, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 27, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>hypertension</keyword>
  <keyword>uncontrolled</keyword>
  <keyword>salt, excess</keyword>
  <keyword>salt meter</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hypertension</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

