<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04287699</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Labor Dance</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04287699</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Effect of Labor Dance on Traumatic Birth Perception and Comfort</brief_title>
  <acronym>labordance</acronym>
  <official_title>The Effect of Labor Dance on Traumatic Birth Perception and Comfort</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Selcuk University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Selcuk University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      ne of the non-pharmacological methods that provide opportunities such as massage and freedom
      of movement with the support of the spouse / partner is the birth dance.

      In order to reduce the pain perceived by the woman and provide emotional support, the birth
      dance is started in the active phase of the first phase of the labor and continues until the
      end of the first phase. The woman is given the opportunity to act rhythmically with a
      relaxing light music with someone she prefers (spouse / partner, mother, midwife, etc.). The
      hands of the pregnant woman dance in the form of swinging from left to right, on the shoulder
      of his wife, with music; The partner is massaged by the sacrum area. It is aimed to increase
      the effectiveness of the method applied by adding spouse / partner support, upright posture
      and massage in addition to the music and body movements that dance includes, and also to
      provide emotional support to the woman. In this study, it was aimed to evaluate the effect of
      birth dance on traumatic birth perception and comfort.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The study was planned as randomized controlled. Pregnant women and their accompanying persons
      assigned to the study group will be informed about working in the tram room where the
      pregnant woman is before the active phase begins 'Using the Labor Dance Practice Guide (Annex
      3) and cervical dilatation 4 cm. they will be asked to practice in accordance with this
      guide. Details of the application (such as dance time, rest time) will be recorded in the
      'Labor Dance Control Guide' (Annex 4) by the researcher. Pregnant women will be followed by
      the doctor and midwife responsible for the pregnancy during the tram, and the researcher will
      not be involved in tram follow-up of the pregnant woman (cervical dilation, pediatric heart
      sound, contraction follow-up, vital signs of the pregnant woman).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 15, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 15, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 15, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>The study was planned as randomized controlled. Pregnant women and their accompanying persons assigned to the study group will be informed about working in the tram room where the pregnant woman is before the active phase begins 'Using the Birth Dance Practice Guide (Annex 3) and cervical dilatation 4 cm. they will be asked to practice in accordance with this guide. Details of the application (such as dance time, rest time) will be recorded in the 'Birth Dance Control Guide' (Annex 4) by the researcher. Pregnant women will be followed by the doctor and midwife responsible for the pregnancy during the tram, and the researcher will not be involved in tram follow-up of the pregnant woman (cervical dilation, pediatric heart sound, contraction follow-up, vital signs of the pregnant woman).</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Childbirth Comfort Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>ten minute after labor dance</time_frame>
    <description>The scale is a five-point Likert type scale with 14 items. In the original of the scale, it is stated that each item can be scored between 1-5 (1 = Strongly disagree, 2 = Mostly disagree, 3 = Partially agree, 4 = Mostly agree, 5 = I totally agree). The minimum score that can be obtained from the scale is 14 and the highest score is 70. The higher the score, the higher the comfort, the lower the lower comfort.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">160</enrollment>
  <condition>Labor Pain</condition>
  <condition>Fear of Childbirth</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>labor dance group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The pregnant women and their spouses/partners who wanted to perform the practice were asked to inform the researcher when the labor started. The researcher stayed with the pregnant women and their spouses during the practice and labor process. The pregnant women started to dance with their spouses during the active phase of the labor process accompanied by meditation music in a dim, silent environment.The pregnant women started to dance with their spouses during the active phase of the labor process accompanied by meditation music in a dim, silent environment. The spouse or partner massaged the pregnant woman's sacral area while dancing.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Only routine practices were performed with the control group, and data were recorded as in the experimental groups.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>labor dance</intervention_name>
    <description>The pregnant women and their spouses/partners who wanted to perform the practice were asked to inform the researcher when the labor started. The researcher stayed with the pregnant women and their spouses during the practice and labor process. The pregnant women started to dance with their spouses during the active phase of the labor process accompanied by meditation music in a dim, silent environment. The spouse or partner massaged the pregnant woman's sacral area while dancing.</description>
    <arm_group_label>labor dance group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Those who were admitted to Hospital for labor

          -  Those whose cervical dilatation between 4 and 8 cm.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  When delivered by cesarean sectio,

          -  Labor was inducted

          -  Narcotic analgesics used
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>40 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Selcuk University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Konya</city>
        <zip>42100</zip>
        <country>Turkey</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Turkey</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 25, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 25, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 27, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 25, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 25, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 27, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Selcuk University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Bihter Akın</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Asisstant Prof. Dr.</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Labor Pain</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

