<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04286919</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>H18-266</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04286919</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Comparing Two Different Methods to Prescribe Exercise</brief_title>
  <acronym>HEAT</acronym>
  <official_title>The Heat Is On To Increase Physical Activity: Comparing Two Different Methods To Prescribe Exercise</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Connecticut</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Connecticut</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Practical interventions are needed to increase physical activity (PA) levels in
      insufficiently active individuals. HEAT is a randomized controlled trial comparing two
      different exercise prescription (ExRx) methods to increase PA volume among insufficiently
      active UConn students. Students will be randomized to two groups: (1) ExRx#1 will emphasize
      meeting the Physical Activity Guidelines for Americans via the Frequency, Intensity, Time,
      and Type or FITT principle of ExRx; and (2) ExRx#2 will be founded in the Integrated Behavior
      Change Theory and based on the 2018 Physical Activity Guidelines Review Committee Scientific
      Report heat map which emphasizes that all PA counts. HEAT aims to assess the effectiveness of
      each ExRx individually and comparatively to one another for each outcome measure. We
      hypothesize that UConn students in ExRx#2 will increase PA volume more than ExRx#1 in
      response to the 12wk ExRx due to its foundation in the IBC. If our hypothesis proves correct
      we aim to inform healthcare providers on university campuses on which method of ExRx is more
      effective at increasing PA participation among their insufficiently active students.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Being regularly physically active, defined as exercising at least 3-days/wk for 30-min
      provides essential and seemingly unlimited health benefits. To emphasize the importance of
      the health benefits of physical activity (PA), the United States government recently provided
      us with The Physical Activity Guidelines for Americans (PAG) 2nd edition. This recommended PA
      prescription for improving and maintaining health includes 150-min/wk of moderate intensity
      aerobic PA plus 2-days of muscle-strengthening PA. Yet, an estimated 26% of American adults
      and 36% of college students do not perform any leisure-time PA. A novelty of the PAG 2nd
      edition is the updated research acknowledging that PA exists on a spectrum where any and all
      movement is beneficial to health. This update emphasizes that the steepest decrease in
      relative risk of all-cause mortality among physically inactive individuals occurs with the
      substitution of sedentary behavior for light intensity movement, inherently encompassing
      lifestyle activities as healthy, meaningful PA. The 2018 Physical Activity Guidelines
      Advisory Committee Scientific Report (PAGACSR) conceptualizes this important public health
      message with the creation of a heat map relating PA with all-cause mortality, creatively
      depicting the dose-response effect of increased PA on health. The Office of Disease
      Prevention and Health Promotion contends that this new emphasis on all PA counting towards
      health can serve as a method of increasing PA in physically inactive individuals as
      demonstrated by the launch of the Move Your Way initiative. The all movement counts message
      can encompass the Integrated Behavior Change Theory (IBC) which attributes increased PA to
      perceived behavioral control due to higher autonomy.

      HEAT is a Randomized Controlled Trial (RCT) comparing the PAG exercise prescription (ExRx#1)
      of 150-min/wk of moderate intensity aerobic PA plus 2-days of muscle-strengthening PA to a
      new method of exercise prescription (ExRx) using the everything counts message depicted by
      the heat map (ExRx#2) to prescribe exercise to physically inactive individuals. ExRx#1 uses
      the Frequency, Intensity, Time, and Type or FITT principle of ExRx to relay the PAG; and
      ExRx#2 will be founded in the Integrated Behavior Change Theory (IBC) and emphasize that all
      PA counts to relay the message of the heat map. ExRx#1 communicates the PAG ultimate weekly
      goal ExRx using an image adopted from the PAG website that depicts the 150-minutes of aerobic
      and 2 days of muscle strengthening exercise and provides a weekly prescription on the FITT of
      how to accomplish this weekly goal. ExRx#2 uses the heat map image to communicate the ExRx of
      all movement counts and that exercise can be done along any FITT.

      Both ExRx were created by an expert panel of exercise professionals including the principal
      investigator Linda S Pescatello, PhD, who was senior editor of the American College of Sports
      Medicine Guidelines for Exercise Testing and Prescription 9th edition and one of the 17
      Advisory Committee members of the PAGACSR which provided the scientific foundation for the
      PAG 2nd edition.

        1. ExRx #1: The ExRx given to participants each week represents the ultimate weekly goal of
           150-min of aerobic PA plus 2-days of muscle-strengthening PA to support optimal health.
           For example, the ExRx on week 6 suggests 3-days/wk of 50-min of aerobic PA plus 2-days
           of 30-min of muscle-strengthening PA in the form of resistance or neuromotor exercise.
           The ExRx then gives examples of taking a 50-min moderate intensity Zumba class on one
           day to fulfill part of the weekly aerobic PA guideline and 2-3 sets of 8-12 reps of
           resistance exercises for 30-min of muscle-strengthening PA on another day.

        2. ExRx #2: The ExRx given to participants each week represents the ultimate weekly goal of
           moving more throughout the day across all intensities in order to achieve optimal health
           as represented by the deep green color on the bottom right of the heat map image that
           represented high amounts of activity and good health. For example, the ExRx on week 6
           suggests including a variety of moderate intensity physical activities and light
           intensity physical activities to achieve the deep green color on the bottom right of the
           heat map. The ExRx then gives the examples of taking a Zumba class and weight training.

      Subjects will be randomly assigned to receiving either ExRx#1 (n=30), or ExRx#2 (n=30). All
      subjects will participate in a 12-week unsupervised ExRx program that will safely progress
      them from being physically inactive to becoming physically active. Each week subjects of both
      groups will be sent an ExRx in the form of PA recommendations for the week that will be
      matched in terms of intervention setting, behavior change strategies, mode of intervention
      delivery, suggestions for types of PA to do, action planning, goal timeframe, and feedback.
      The difference between the two ExRx methods is the messaging of the specific frequency,
      intensity time, and type to follow in ExRx#1 versus giving only suggestions of exercises to
      do and no frequency, intensity, time or type restriction as &quot;all movement counts&quot; is
      emphasized in ExRx#2. Both groups will be given the main goal of the guidelines they are
      randomized to along with the same information on the definitions of aerobic, resistance,
      neuromotor, flexibility and concurrent exercise along with how to measure intensity of PA
      using the talk test and the Borg Ratings of Perceived Exertion 6-20 scale. Each participant
      will be verbally explained the overall goal of the ExRx and walked through the definitions to
      ensure complete understanding of each mode of PA and how to monitor intensity of activity.
      Both groups will be instructed that the guidelines will progress them from being physically
      inactive to meeting the overall goal of the ExRx from weeks 1-6; then the guidelines will
      stay consistent in prescribing the overall goal of the ExRx from weeks 6-12. In both groups,
      the ExRx is described as effective for improving and maintaining health and that all PA
      participation is at their own discretion and they can do whatever PA type they would like.
      Participants in both groups will be given the same exercise compendium of aerobic and
      resistance exercises to choose from in case they are unsatisfied with the example types of PA
      recommended in the weekly guidelines. Researchers will stress the goal of accurately
      recording PA and exercise regardless of if the recommendations given to them are met or not.

      Currently 36% of University students are physically inactive. Due to barriers such as lack of
      time, exercising 150-min/wk+ and accomplishing a specific FITT such as the ExRx#1 provides
      may seem unattainable. In contrast, the ExRx#2 demonstrates a simple message to move more
      however you can, allowing for practical uptake of increased PA and using the IBC to connect
      the intention to exercise with the behavior through increased self-efficacy and autonomy. We
      hypothesize that ExRx #2 will elicit greater increases in PA volume from baseline (BL) to
      post-test at the end of the 12 weeks of guidelines (12W) compared to ExRx#1. We hypothesize
      that ExRx#2 will produce greater improvement in autonomy and self-efficacy compared to ExRx#1
      at 12W.

      Anthropometrics, health-fitness assessments, PA tracking and questionnaires will be
      administered at BL, 6W and 12W. All questionnaires will be administered in person using
      Qualtrics Secure encrypted database and will be compared between groups at BL, 6W and 12W to
      measure changes over time. Age will be assessed in years. Height (cm) and weight (kg) will be
      measured and used to calculate body mass index in m2/kg. Waist circumference will be measured
      at the height of the iliac crest with a Gulick tape measure in cm. Cardiorespiratory fitness
      will be assessed using a modified and validated Harvard Step Test protocol where participants
      step up and down on a 30cm box at a rate of 30 steps/min for 3-min and recovery heart rate
      (HR) is recorded. Muscular endurance will be measured via the push-up test with males
      performing repetitions until failure in the standard position and females in the modified
      kneeling position. Handgrip strength is a validated measure of overall muscular strength and
      will be measured using a validated protocol in the dominant hand with the Jamar Hydraulic
      Handgrip Dynamometer. Flexibility will be measured in cm using a Sit and Reach Flexibility
      Box. Timeline Follow-Back for Exercise (TLFB-E) is a self-report calendar diary method for
      logging daily exercise and PA, and sitting and sleeping time. Participants will record daily
      PA frequency, type, duration (min) and intensity using the Borg 6-20 scale. Researchers will
      assess the TLFB-E weekly to ensure students are actively participating in reading the ExRx
      guidelines and logging activity. Paffenbarger Physical Activity Questionnaire Question 8 will
      measure duration (min) in each intensity of PA plus time spent sleeping and sitting for a
      typical weekday and weekend day. PA volume will be calculated in MET.min/wk. Actical®
      accelerometers will be given to participants to wear on their hip for 4 consecutive days
      including 2 weekdays and 2 weekend days as an objective measure of PA volume in MET.min/day,
      steps/day and time spent in light, moderate and vigorous intensities. Transtheoretical Model
      Stage of Change will assess readiness to take action to exercise regularly and measures
      transitions in this readiness. Motivation for Physical Activity will determine type of
      motivation for PA (e.g., intrinsic vs external) and self-perceived autonomy. Marcus
      Self-Efficacy questionnaire will measure confidence for exercising when 5 different perceived
      barriers present. Task Self-Efficacy will measure confidence for exercising 3 times/wk at
      increasing durations. Barriers to Self-Efficacy will assess confidence in exercising 3days/wk
      for the next 3 months in the presence of possible barriers to exercise.

      Group descriptive statistics will be presented as mean±standard deviation and ANOVA will be
      performed to determine if there are BL differences between the groups. All BL, 6W and 12W
      measures of PA and the psychosocial questionnaires will be analyzed with repeated measures
      ANCOVA using gender as a fixed factor and age, BMI, WC and other baseline descriptive
      characteristics as possible covariates. Post-hoc analyses will be used to test differences in
      groups and for 3 time points if there are significant time, group or time*group interactions.
      Methods such as multiple imputation and estimated means algorithm will be used to carry out
      statistical inferences in the presence of missing data. All analyses will be set at the alpha
      level of .05 and will be carried out using SPSS Version 25.

      ExRx #1 utilizes the widely-used gold standard FITT principle of ExRx to promote achieving
      the PAG. ExRx #2 uses updated research on the benefits of light intensity movement and the
      all movement counts message founded in the IBC to inherently support autonomy and higher
      self-efficacy to connect the intention to exercise with the behavior. This RCT will inform
      practitioners about which message resonates more with physically inactive students so we can
      more effectively promote healthy, active lifestyles.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 22, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Randomized Controlled Trial with 1 control group and 1 intervention group. The control group is getting the standard of care exercise prescription based on the 2018 physical activity guidelines for Americans and the intervention group is getting a new method of prescribing exercise based on new research informing the 2018 Move Your Way initiative where all physical activity across all types and intensities is advised.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Health Services Research</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
    <masking_description>Participants do not know that there is another group getting a different exercise prescription. At the end of their participation, all participants will be offered the other exercise prescription.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Physical Activity Volume change from Baseline to 12 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Actical® (Mini Meter, Respironics Inc.) accelerometers will be given to participants to wear on their hip for 4 consecutive days including 2 weekdays and 2 weekend days as an objective measure of PA volume in MET-hours/day. This data will be collected at baseline before the exercise guidelines start and at week 12 of the exercise guidelines to measure change from baseline to 12 weeks.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Autonomy Score Change from Baseline to 12 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Motivation for Physical Activity will be assessed by a questionnaire developed using the Self-Determination theory which is found to be valid and reliable in assessing type of motivation for PA in adults. This instrument has 16 items that will allow researchers to determine type of motivation (e.g., intrinsic versus external) and create a relative autonomy index for each subject as a direct result of the scoring of this questionnaire. This score is used to detect level of autonomy in exercise. This measure will be administered at baseline and 12 weeks to measure change from baseline over 12 weeks.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">46</enrollment>
  <condition>Physical Activity</condition>
  <condition>Health Behavior</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>ExRx#1: Physical Activity Guidelines</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>ExRx#1 uses the Frequency, Intensity, Time, and Type or FITT principle of exercise prescription to prescribe the Physical Activity Guidelines for Americans which is a weekly goal of 150-minutes of moderate intensity aerobic physical activity plus 2 days of muscle strengthening physical activity. ExRx#1 communicates the ultimate goal of the physical activity guidelines for Americans using an image adopted from the physical activity guidelines website that depicts the weekly goal. There are 12 weeks of exercise guidelines that will progress participants from being physically inactive to meeting the physical activity guidelines ultimate weekly goal by providing a weekly prescription of Frequency, Intensity, Time, and Type of physical activity that accomplishes meeting the physical activity guidelines weekly goal.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>ExRx#2: Heat Map</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>ExRx#2 uses the heat map image published in the 2018 Physical Activity Guidelines Advisory Committee Scientific Report that communicates the dose-response relationship between increased physical activity and improved health to prescribe the message that all physical activity across all Frequencies, Intensities, Time bouts and Types (FITT) counts towards health. ExRx#2 is founded in the Integrated Behavior Change Theory and emphasizes that all physical activity matters regardless of FITT as depicted by the heat map image. There are 12 weeks of exercise guidelines that will progress participants from being physically inactive to meeting the ExRx#2 heat map ultimate weekly goal of moving more throughout the day across all intensities in order to achieve optimal health as represented by the deep green color on the bottom right of the heat map image.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>A Randomized Controlled Trial Comparing the Physical Activity Guidelines for Americans to a New Method of Exercise Prescription Among College Students</intervention_name>
    <description>A randomized controlled trial comparing the 2018 Physical Activity Guidelines for Americans weekly recommendations of 150-minutes of moderate intensity physical activity plus 2 days of muscle-strengthening physical activity to the Move Your Way Campaign message of increasing any and all physical activity to accumulate more movement throughout the week across all types and intensities.</description>
    <arm_group_label>ExRx#1: Physical Activity Guidelines</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>ExRx#2: Heat Map</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Comparing the Physical Activity Guidelines for Americans to The Move Your Way Campaign Methods of Exercise Prescription Among College Students</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  &gt;18 years old.

          -  Participants will attend UConn Storrs campus as an undergraduate or graduate student
             during the study.

          -  Participants must be physically inactive as defined by participating in less than or
             equal to 2 days of planned, structured physical activity over the past 12 weeks.

          -  Any and all races may be included.

          -  Participants will be healthy with no diagnosed cardiovascular, pulmonary, metabolic,
             or other chronic diseases or depression and not taking medication for any of these
             chronic diseases or health conditions as defined by answering &quot;no&quot; to all General
             Health Questions listed in the Physical Activity Readiness Questionnaire for Everyone
             (PAR-Q+).

          -  Anyone scoring less than a 19 on the Beck Depression Inventory.

          -  Those who answer &quot;yes&quot; to 3 or less on the eating questionnaire will be included.

          -  Between 18-35 m2/kg.

          -  Participants should be non-smokers for at least 6 months prior to entry.

          -  Participants should drink &lt;2 alcoholic drinks daily.

          -  Women who are not pregnant or lactating and do not plan on becoming pregnant.

          -  Participants with no arthritis or orthopedic problems inhibiting their ability to
             exercise across all intensities without exacerbating the problem.

          -  Participants willing to maintain their habitual diet throughout the study.

          -  Participants wanting to enter the study for reasons that do not include weight loss.

          -  Participants should be willing and able to consent to all data collection processes
             including the intended timeline of the study procedures as well as all questionnaires,
             fitness assessments, and physical activity monitor usage.

          -  Participants who are willing to use only the physical activity program given to them
             by researchers and are willing to refrain from obtaining and using another program
             given to them by anyone else besides study researchers. Participants must also agree
             to not look at the physical activity guidelines being administered to the other
             intervention group that they are not assigned to.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  &lt;18 years old

          -  Not attending UConn Storrs campus during the duration of their enrollment.

          -  Answering &quot;no&quot; to any question on the 12-item checklist of inclusion criteria

          -  Participating in more than 2 days of planned, structured physical activity over the
             past 12 weeks.

          -  Unhealthy students as determined by answering &quot;yes&quot; to any question listed on the
             PAR-Q+.

          -  Scoring a 19 or higher on the Beck Depression Inventory.

          -  Those who answer &quot;yes&quot; to more than 3 statements on the SCOFF eating disorder
             questionnaire will be excluded.

          -  BMI &lt;18 or &gt;35 m2/kg.

          -  People who currently smoke, plan on smoking or have smoked tobacco within the last 6
             months.

          -  People drinking 2 or more alcoholic drinks daily.

          -  Women who are pregnant or lactating.

          -  People with arthritis or orthopedic problems will not be enrolled if these conditions
             compromise their completion of the exercise protocols or ability to exercise across
             all intensities.

          -  People unwilling to maintain their habitual diet as we request throughout study
             participation.

          -  We will not recruit subjects whose primary motivation for enrolling is to lose weight.

          -  People who do not think they will be able to complete all study protocols at the times
             they are scheduled to complete them. This includes the completion of study time logs
             and all study visits.

          -  Anyone not willing to confirm that they will refrain from obtaining another exercise
             program or viewing that of the other group.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Linda S Pescatello, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Connecticut</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Connecticut</name>
      <address>
        <city>Storrs</city>
        <state>Connecticut</state>
        <zip>06268</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://health.gov/news-archive/blog-bayw/2018/03/2018-physical-activity-guidelines-advisory-committee-submits-scientific-report/index.html</url>
    <description>2018 Physical Activity Guidelines Advisory Committee Scientific Report</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>https://health.gov/our-work/physical-activity/move-your-way-campaign</url>
    <description>Move Your Way Campaign</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>https://health.gov/moveyourway</url>
    <description>Physical Activity Guidelines Figure depicting 150-minutes per week of moderate intensity aerobic physical activity plus two days of muscle strengthening activity</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>https://www.healthypeople.gov/2020/topics-objectives/topic/physical-activity/objectives</url>
    <description>Healthy People 2020 Topics and Objectives: Physical Activity</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Powell KE, King AC, Buchner DM, Campbell WW, DiPietro L, Erickson KI, Hillman CH, Jakicic JM, Janz KF, Katzmarzyk PT, Kraus WE, Macko RF, Marquez DX, McTiernan A, Pate RR, Pescatello LS, Whitt-Glover MC. The Scientific Foundation for the Physical Activity Guidelines for Americans, 2nd Edition. J Phys Act Health. 2018 Dec 17:1-11. doi: 10.1123/jpah.2018-0618. [Epub ahead of print]</citation>
    <PMID>30558473</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lee IM, Shiroma EJ, Lobelo F, Puska P, Blair SN, Katzmarzyk PT; Lancet Physical Activity Series Working Group. Effect of physical inactivity on major non-communicable diseases worldwide: an analysis of burden of disease and life expectancy. Lancet. 2012 Jul 21;380(9838):219-29. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(12)61031-9.</citation>
    <PMID>22818936</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Riebe D, Ehrman J, Liquori G, Magal M. ACSM's Guidelines for Exercise Testing and Prescription tenth edition. 10th ed. Wolters Kluwer: Katie Feltman; 2018.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hagger MS, Chatzisarantis NL. An integrated behavior change model for physical activity. Exerc Sport Sci Rev. 2014 Apr;42(2):62-9. doi: 10.1249/JES.0000000000000008. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24508739</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Williams SL, French DP. What are the most effective intervention techniques for changing physical activity self-efficacy and physical activity behaviour--and are they the same? Health Educ Res. 2011 Apr;26(2):308-22. doi: 10.1093/her/cyr005. Epub 2011 Feb 14.</citation>
    <PMID>21321008</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Samdal GB, Eide GE, Barth T, Williams G, Meland E. Effective behaviour change techniques for physical activity and healthy eating in overweight and obese adults; systematic review and meta-regression analyses. Int J Behav Nutr Phys Act. 2017 Mar 28;14(1):42. doi: 10.1186/s12966-017-0494-y. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>28351367</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chatzisarantis NL, Hagger MS, Smith B. Influences of perceived autonomy support on physical activity within the theory of planned behavior. European Journal of Social Psychology 2007;37(5):934-954.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Keating XD, Guan J, Piñero JC, Bridges DM. A meta-analysis of college students' physical activity behaviors. J Am Coll Health. 2005 Sep-Oct;54(2):116-25. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>16255324</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Trost SG, Owen N, Bauman AE, Sallis JF, Brown W. Correlates of adults' participation in physical activity: review and update. Med Sci Sports Exerc. 2002 Dec;34(12):1996-2001. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>12471307</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hill LS, Reid F, Morgan JF, Lacey JH. SCOFF, the development of an eating disorder screening questionnaire. Int J Eat Disord. 2010 May;43(4):344-51. doi: 10.1002/eat.20679.</citation>
    <PMID>19343793</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Simpson K, Parker B, Capizzi J, Thompson P, Clarkson P, Freedson P, Pescatello LS. Validity and reliability question 8 of the Paffenbarger Physical Activity Questionnaire among healthy adults. J Phys Act Health. 2015 Jan;12(1):116-23. doi: 10.1123/jpah.2013-0013. Epub 2014 Apr 11.</citation>
    <PMID>24733349</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Thompson PD, Arena R, Riebe D, Pescatello LS; American College of Sports Medicine. ACSM's new preparticipation health screening recommendations from ACSM's guidelines for exercise testing and prescription, ninth edition. Curr Sports Med Rep. 2013 Jul-Aug;12(4):215-7. doi: 10.1249/JSR.0b013e31829a68cf.</citation>
    <PMID>23851406</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ibrahim JG, Chen M, Lipsitz SR, Herring AH. Missing-data methods for generalized linear models: A comparative review. Journal of the American Statistical Association 2005;100(469):332-346.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rubin DB. Inference and missing data. Biometrika 1976;63(3):581-592.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>American Society of, Hand Therapists. Clinical assessment recommendations. 1992.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>KEEN EN, SLOAN AW. Observations on the Harvard step test. J Appl Physiol. 1958 Sep;13(2):241-3.</citation>
    <PMID>13575336</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Panza GA, Weinstock J, Ash GI, Pescatello LS. Psychometric Evaluation of the Timeline Followback for Exercise among College Students. Psychol Sport Exerc. 2012 Nov;13(6):779-788. Epub 2012 Jun 20.</citation>
    <PMID>22844226</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Matthews CE, Ainsworth BE, Thompson RW, Bassett DR Jr. Sources of variance in daily physical activity levels as measured by an accelerometer. Med Sci Sports Exerc. 2002 Aug;34(8):1376-81.</citation>
    <PMID>12165695</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Freedson PS, Melanson E, Sirard J. Calibration of the Computer Science and Applications, Inc. accelerometer. Med Sci Sports Exerc. 1998 May;30(5):777-81.</citation>
    <PMID>9588623</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>McAuley E, Courneya KS. The subjective exercise experiences scale (SEES): Development and preliminary validation. Journal of Sport and Exercise Psychology 1994;16(2):163-177..</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Resnick B, Zimmerman SI, Orwig D, Furstenberg AL, Magaziner J. Outcome expectations for exercise scale: utility and psychometrics. J Gerontol B Psychol Sci Soc Sci. 2000 Nov;55(6):S352-6.</citation>
    <PMID>11078112</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Deci E. Exercise Self-Regulation Questionnaires. Self-Determination Theory: An Approach to Human Motivation and Personality- The Self-Regulation Questionnaires 2004.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>McAuley E. The role of efficacy cognitions in the prediction of exercise behavior in middle-aged adults. J Behav Med. 1992 Feb;15(1):65-88.</citation>
    <PMID>1583674</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>McAuley E, Blissmer B. Self-efficacy determinants and consequences of physical activity. Exerc Sport Sci Rev. 2000 Apr;28(2):85-8. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>10902091</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Marcus BH, Selby VC, Niaura RS, Rossi JS. Self-efficacy and the stages of exercise behavior change. Res Q Exerc Sport. 1992 Mar;63(1):60-6.</citation>
    <PMID>1574662</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Marcus, B H and Forsyth L H. Motivating People to Be Physically Active. : Human Kinetics; 2003. p. 21.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>O'Brien E, Beevers G, Lip GY. ABC of hypertension: Blood pressure measurement. Part IV-automated sphygmomanometry: self blood pressure measurement. BMJ. 2001 May 12;322(7295):1167-70. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>11348915</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pickering TG, Hall JE, Appel LJ, Falkner BE, Graves JW, Hill MN, Jones DH, Kurtz T, Sheps SG, Roccella EJ; Council on High Blood Pressure Research Professional and Public Education Subcommittee, American Heart Association. Recommendations for blood pressure measurement in humans: an AHA scientific statement from the Council on High Blood Pressure Research Professional and Public Education Subcommittee. J Clin Hypertens (Greenwich). 2005 Feb;7(2):102-9.</citation>
    <PMID>15722655</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Roshanaei-Moghaddam B, Katon WJ, Russo J. The longitudinal effects of depression on physical activity. Gen Hosp Psychiatry. 2009 Jul-Aug;31(4):306-15. doi: 10.1016/j.genhosppsych.2009.04.002. Epub 2009 May 13. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19555789</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Beck AT, Steer RA, Carbin MG. Psychometric properties of the Beck Depression Inventory: Twenty-five years of evaluation. Clin Psychol Rev 1988;8(1):77-100.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Morgan JF, Reid F, Lacey JH. The SCOFF questionnaire: assessment of a new screening tool for eating disorders. BMJ. 1999 Dec 4;319(7223):1467-8.</citation>
    <PMID>10582927</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bravata DM, Smith-Spangler C, Sundaram V, Gienger AL, Lin N, Lewis R, Stave CD, Olkin I, Sirard JR. Using pedometers to increase physical activity and improve health: a systematic review. JAMA. 2007 Nov 21;298(19):2296-304. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18029834</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>McEwan D, Harden SM, Zumbo BD, Sylvester BD, Kaulius M, Ruissen GR, Dowd AJ, Beauchamp MR. The effectiveness of multi-component goal setting interventions for changing physical activity behaviour: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Health Psychol Rev. 2016;10(1):67-88. doi: 10.1080/17437199.2015.1104258. Epub 2015 Nov 13. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26445201</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Napolitano MA, Fotheringham M, Tate D, Sciamanna C, Leslie E, Owen N, Bauman A, Marcus B. Evaluation of an internet-based physical activity intervention: a preliminary investigation. Ann Behav Med. 2003 Spring;25(2):92-9.</citation>
    <PMID>12704010</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Greene GW, White AA, Hoerr SL, Lohse B, Schembre SM, Riebe D, Patterson J, Kattelmann KK, Shoff S, Horacek T, Blissmer B, Phillips BW. Impact of an online healthful eating and physical activity program for college students. Am J Health Promot. 2012 Nov-Dec;27(2):e47-58. doi: 10.4278/ajhp.110606-QUAN-239.</citation>
    <PMID>23113786</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rovniak LS, Hovell MF, Wojcik JR, Winett RA, Martinez-Donate AP. Enhancing theoretical fidelity: an e-mail-based walking program demonstration. Am J Health Promot. 2005 Nov-Dec;20(2):85-95.</citation>
    <PMID>16295700</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Joseph RP, Keller C, Adams MA, Ainsworth BE. Print versus a culturally-relevant Facebook and text message delivered intervention to promote physical activity in African American women: a randomized pilot trial. BMC Womens Health. 2015 Mar 27;15:30. doi: 10.1186/s12905-015-0186-1.</citation>
    <PMID>25886945</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Taylor WC, Paxton RJ, Shegog R, Coan SP, Dubin A, Page TF, Rempel DM. Impact of Booster Breaks and Computer Prompts on Physical Activity and Sedentary Behavior Among Desk-Based Workers: A Cluster-Randomized Controlled Trial. Prev Chronic Dis. 2016 Nov 17;13:E155. doi: 10.5888/pcd13.160231.</citation>
    <PMID>27854422</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Piercy KL, Troiano RP, Ballard RM, Carlson SA, Fulton JE, Galuska DA, George SM, Olson RD. The Physical Activity Guidelines for Americans. JAMA. 2018 Nov 20;320(19):2020-2028. doi: 10.1001/jama.2018.14854.</citation>
    <PMID>30418471</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 20, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 25, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 27, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 13, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 13, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 15, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Connecticut</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Linda Pescatello</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Exercise</keyword>
  <keyword>Adherence</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>No individual participant data will be shared. All data will be analyzed and presented in aggregate as accepted by the University of Connecticut IRB.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

