<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04285567</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CO41685</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2019-003327-37</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04285567</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study to Compare the Efficacy and Safety of a Combined Regimen of Venetoclax and Obinutuzumab Versus Fludarabine, Cyclophosphamide, and Rituximab (FCR)/ Bendamustine And Rituximab (BR) in FIT Patients With Previously Untreated Chronic Lymphocytic Leukemia (CLL) Without DEL (17P) or TP53 Mutation</brief_title>
  <acronym>CRISTALLO</acronym>
  <official_title>A Prospective, Open-Label, Multicenter Randomized Phase III Study to Compare The Efficacy and Safety of A Combined Regimen of Venetoclax and Obinutuzumab Versus Fludarabine, Cyclophosphamide, and Rituximab (FCR)/Bendamustine and Rituximab (BR) in FIT Patients With Previously Untreated Chronic Lymphocytic Leukemia (CLL) Without DEL(17P) or TP53 Mutation</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Hoffmann-La Roche</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Hoffmann-La Roche</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will evaluate the efficacy and safety of venetoclax and obinutuzumab (VEN + G)
      compared with fludarabine + cyclophosphamide + rituximab or bendamustine + rituximab (FCR/BR)
      in FIT participants (FIT is defined by a cumulative illness rating scale [CIRS]/score of ≤6
      and a normal creatinine clearance of ≥70 mL/min) with previously untreated CLL without
      DEL(17P) or TP53 mutation requiring treatment. Eligible participants will be randomly
      assigned in a 1:1 ratio to receive either VEN + G (Arm A) or FCR/BR (Arm B).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 28, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 28, 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 8, 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Minimal Residual Disease (MRD) Response Rate in the First 140 Participants Recruited</measure>
    <time_frame>At Month 15</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression-free Survival (PFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Every year after disease progression until end of study (up to 46 months)</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>MRD Response Rate in Peripheral Blood (PB) at the End of Treatment Response Visit</measure>
    <time_frame>At end of treatment response visit (up to approximately 15 months in Arm VEN + G and 9 months in Arm FCR/BR</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>MRD Response Rate in Bone Marrow (BM) at the End of Treatment Response Visit</measure>
    <time_frame>At end of treatment response visit (up to approximately 15 months in Arm VEN + G and 9 months in Arm FCR/BR</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Objective Response Rate (ORR)</measure>
    <time_frame>At Month 15</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Complete Response (CR) Rate</measure>
    <time_frame>At Month 15</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>MRD Response Rate in PB of Participant With a CR/CR With Incomplete Blood Count (CRi) at Month 15</measure>
    <time_frame>At Month 15</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>MRD Response Rate in the BM of Participants With a CR/CRi at the End of Treatment Visit</measure>
    <time_frame>At end of treatment response visit (up to approximately 15 months in Arm VEN + G and 9 months in Arm FCR/BR</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of Objective Response (DOR)</measure>
    <time_frame>Every year after disease progression until end of study (up to 46 months)</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Best Overall Response</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to and including the assessment at Month 15</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Event-free Survival (EFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Every year after disease progression until end of study (up to 46 months)</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival (OS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Every year after disease progression until end of study (up to 46 months)</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change From Baseline in M.D. Anderson Symptom Inventory-CLL (MDASI-CLL) Score</measure>
    <time_frame>Arm VEN + G: Day 1 of Cycle 1-12, Day 28 after treatment completion/early termination (TC/ET), follow up (FU) visits; Arm FCR/BR: Day 1 of Cycle 1-6, Day 28 after TC/ET, end of combination treatment response visit and FU visit (up to 46 months)</time_frame>
    <description>The MDASI-CLL is a questionnaire of 25 items related to CLL specific symptoms that a participant may have experienced in the past 24 hours. Participants were asked to rate the severity of 13 symptoms called mean core symptom severity (i.e., pain, fatigue, nausea, disturbed sleep, distressed, shortness of breath, remembering things, lack of appetite, drowsy, dry mouth, sadness, vomiting, and numbness or tingling), 6 disease-specific symptoms called mean module symptom severity (night sweats, fevers and chills, lymph node swelling, diarrhea, easy bruising or bleeding, and constipation) and 6 mean interference on life questions (i.e., general activity, walking, work, mood, relations with other people, and enjoyment of life) on a scale from 0 to 10 with 0 indicating that the symptom is &quot;not present&quot; or &quot;did not interfere&quot; with the participant's activities and 10 indicating &quot;as bad as you can imagine&quot; or &quot;interfered completely&quot;.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change From Baseline in European Organization for Research and Treatment of Cancer Quality of Life Questionnaire Core-30 (EORTC QLQC-30)</measure>
    <time_frame>Arm VEN + G: Day 1 of Cycle 1-12, Day 28 after treatment completion/early termination (TC/ET), follow up (FU) visits; Arm FCR/BR: Day 1 of Cycle 1-6, Day 28 after TC/ET, end of combination treatment response visit and FU visit (up to 46 months)</time_frame>
    <description>The EORTC QLQ-C30 is a validated and reliable self-report measure consisting of 30 questions incorporated into five functional scales (physical, role, cognitive, emotional, and social scales), three symptom scales (fatigue, pain, nausea, and vomiting scales), and a global health status/global quality−of−life scale. The remaining single items (dyspnea, appetite loss, sleep disturbance, constipation, and diarrhea) assess the additional symptoms experienced by patients with cancer and the perceived financial burden of treatment. The 28 function and symptom items were scored on a 4-point scale that ranged from &quot;not at all&quot; to &quot;very much,&quot; and the 2 global health status/global quality-of-life items were scored on a 7-point scale that ranged from &quot;very poor&quot; to &quot;excellent.&quot; Raw average scale scores were linearly transformed to range 0-100 with higher scores indicating higher response levels (i.e., higher functioning, higher symptom severity).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants With Adverse Events (AEs)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 28 days after last dose of study drug or until initiation of another anti-cancer therapy (up to 46 months)</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">165</enrollment>
  <condition>Chronic Lymphocytic Leukemia (CLL)</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>VEN + G</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will receive 12 cycles of treatment (each cycle is 28 days). Venetoclax (VEN) will be administered orally, daily, with a 5-week ramp-up period, starting on Cycle 1, Day 22 and administration will continue until the end of Cycle 12. Obinutuzumab (G) will be administered intravenously (IV) on Days 1 (and 2), 8, and 15 of Cycle 1 and on Day 1 of Cycles 2-6.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>FCR/BR</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will receive 6 cycles of Fludarabine + Cyclophosphamide + Rituximab (FCR) consisting of a single cycle of a single infusion of rituximab on Day 1 and fludarabine and cyclophosphamide infusions on Days 1-3 of each 28-day cycle or bendamustine (B) as infusions on Days 1 and 2 and a single cycle of rituximab on Day 1 of each 28-day cycle.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Obinutuzumab</intervention_name>
    <description>Obinutuzumab 1000 mg will be administered IV on Days 1 (and 2), 8, and 15 of Cycle 1 and on Day 1 of Cycles 2-6.</description>
    <arm_group_label>VEN + G</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Gazyva</other_name>
    <other_name>RO5072759</other_name>
    <other_name>GA101</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Venetoclax</intervention_name>
    <description>Venetoclax 20 mg will be administered orally, once daily starting on Day 22 of Cycle 1 for 7 days, then ramp up from 50 to 400 mg/day during Cycle 2 and continue at 400 mg/day from Day 1 of Cycle 3 till end of Cycle 12.</description>
    <arm_group_label>VEN + G</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Venclexta</other_name>
    <other_name>RO5537382</other_name>
    <other_name>GDC-0199</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Fludarabine</intervention_name>
    <description>Fludarabine will be administered in a dosage of 25 mg/m^2 IV on days 1, 2, and 3 of Cycles 1-6.</description>
    <arm_group_label>FCR/BR</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cyclophosphamide</intervention_name>
    <description>Cyclophosphamide will be administered in a dosage of 250 mg/m^2 IV on Days 1, 2, and 3 Cycles 1-6.</description>
    <arm_group_label>FCR/BR</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Rituximab</intervention_name>
    <description>Rituximab will be administered at a dose of 375 mg/m^2 IV on Cycle 1, Day 1 followed by 500 mg/m^2 on Day 1 of Cycles 2-6.</description>
    <arm_group_label>FCR/BR</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Bendamustine</intervention_name>
    <description>Bendamustine will be administered at a dose of 90 mg/m^2 IV on 2 consecutive days of Cycles 1-6.</description>
    <arm_group_label>FCR/BR</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Ability to comply with the study protocol, in the investigator's judgment

          -  Aged 18 years or older

          -  Have previously untreated documented Chronic Lymphocytic Leukemia (CLL) according to
             the International Workshop on Chronic Lymphocytic Leukemia (iwCLL) criteria

          -  CLL requiring treatment according to the iwCLL criteria

          -  Cumulative Illness Rating Scale (CIRS) score ≤ 6 and creatinine clearance (CrCl) ≥ 70
             mL/min

          -  Hematology values within the following limits, unless cytopenia is caused by the
             underlying disease (i.e., no evidence of additional bone marrow (BM) dysfunction;
             e.g., myelodysplastic syndrome, hypoplastic BM):

               -  Absolute neutrophil count ≥ 1.0 x 109/L, unless there is BM involvement

               -  Platelet count ≥ 75 x 109/L and more than 7 days since last transfusion, or ≥ 30
                  x 109/L if there is BM involvement

          -  Adequate liver function as indicated by a total bilirubin, aspartate aminotransferase,
             and Alanine transaminase ≤ 2 times the institutional upper limit of normal (ULN)
             value, unless directly attributable to the participant's CLL

          -  Life expectancy &gt;6 months

          -  For women of childbearing potential: agreement to remain abstinent (refrain from
             heterosexual intercourse) or use contraception and agreement to refrain from donating
             eggs

          -  For men: agreement to remain abstinent (refrain from heterosexual intercourse) or use
             contraceptive methods, and agreement to refrain from donating sperm

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Transformation of CLL to aggressive Non-Hodgkin's Lymphoma (NHL)

          -  Participants with Small Lymphocyclic Lymphoma (SLL)

          -  Known central nervous system involvement

          -  Participants with a history of confirmed progressive multifocal leukoencephalopathy
             (PML)

          -  Detected del (17p) or TP53 mutation

          -  An individual organ/system impairment score of 4 as assessed by the Cumulative Illness
             Rating Scale (CIRS) definition limiting the ability to receive the treatment regimen
             of this trial with the exception of eyes, ears, nose, throat organ system

          -  Participants with uncontrolled autoimmune hemolytic anemia or immune thrombocytopenia

          -  History of prior malignancy

          -  Participants with infections requiring IV treatment (Grade 3 or 4) within the last 8
             weeks prior to enrollment

          -  Evidence of other clinically significant uncontrolled conditions including but not
             limited to active or uncontrolled systemic infection (e.g., viral, bacterial, or
             fungal)

          -  History of severe allergic or anaphylactic reactions to humanized or murine monoclonal
             antibodies or known sensitivity or allergy to murine products

          -  Hypersensitivity to fludarabine, bendamustine, cyclophosphamide, rituximab,
             obinutuzumab, or venetoclax or to any of the excipients (e.g., trehalose)

          -  Pregnant women and nursing mothers

          -  Vaccination with a live vaccine ≤ 28 days prior to randomization

          -  Prisoners or participants who are institutionalized by regulatory or court order or
             persons who are in dependence to the Sponsor or an investigator

          -  History of illicit drug or alcohol abuse within 12 months prior to screening, in the
             investigator's judgment

          -  Positive test results for chronic hepatitis B virus (HBV) infection (defined as
             positive hepatitis B surface antigen [HBsAg] serology)

          -  Positive test result for hepatitis C (hepatitis C virus [HCV] antibody serology
             testing)

          -  Participants with known infection with HIV or Human T-Cell Leukemia Virus 1 (HTLV-1)

          -  Any serious medical condition or abnormality in clinical laboratory tests that, in the
             investigator's judgment, precludes the participant's safe participation in and
             completion of the study

          -  Received any of the following agents within 28 days prior to the first dose of study
             treatment:

               -  Immunotherapy

               -  Radiotherapy

               -  Hormone therapy

               -  Any therapies intended for the treatment of lymphoma/leukemia whether approved or
                  experimental

          -  Participants who have received the following agents:

               -  Strong and moderate CYP3A inhibitors/inducers within 7 days prior to the
                  initiation of study treatment

               -  Steroid therapy for anti-neoplastic intent with the exception of inhaled steroids
                  for asthma, topical steroids, or replacement/stress corticosteroids within 7 days
                  prior to the first dose of study drug administration

               -  Consumed grapefruit, grapefruit products, Seville oranges(including marmalade
                  containing Seville oranges), or star fruit within 3 days prior to the first dose
                  of study drug and throughout venetoclax administration

          -  Inability to swallow a large number of tablets.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Clinical trial</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Hoffmann-La Roche</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Reference Study ID Number: CO41685 www.roche.com/about_roche/roche_worldwide.htm</last_name>
    <phone>888-662-6728 (U.S. Only)</phone>
    <email>global-roche-genentech-trials@gene.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Medical Center of Aurora; Rocky Mountain Cancer Centers</name>
      <address>
        <city>Aurora</city>
        <state>Colorado</state>
        <zip>80012</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Center For Cancer and Blood Disorders</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20817</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Maryland Oncology Hematology, P.A.</name>
      <address>
        <city>Columbia</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21044</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>St. Vincent Frontier Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Billings</city>
        <state>Montana</state>
        <zip>59101</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Regional Cancer Care Associates</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hackensack</city>
        <state>New Jersey</state>
        <zip>07601-2191</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>New York Oncology Hematology, P.C.</name>
      <address>
        <city>Albany</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>12206</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Oncology Assoc of Oregon, PC</name>
      <address>
        <city>Eugene</city>
        <state>Oregon</state>
        <zip>97401-8122</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>VA Portland Healthcare System</name>
      <address>
        <city>Portland</city>
        <state>Oregon</state>
        <zip>97239</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Consultants in Medical Oncology and Hematology, P.C.</name>
      <address>
        <city>Horsham</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19044</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Tennessee Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Knoxville</city>
        <state>Tennessee</state>
        <zip>37920</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Southwest Regional Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Austin</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>78705</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Texas Oncology-Denton South</name>
      <address>
        <city>Denton</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>76210</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>South Texas Cancer Center - McAllen</name>
      <address>
        <city>McAllen</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>78503</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Tyler Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tyler</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>75702</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Community Cancer Trials of Utah</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ogden</city>
        <state>Utah</state>
        <zip>84405</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Oncology &amp; Hematolgy Associates of SW Va Inc. - Roanoke</name>
      <address>
        <city>Roanoke</city>
        <state>Virginia</state>
        <zip>24014</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Canberra Hospital; Haematology Department</name>
      <address>
        <city>Canberra</city>
        <state>Australian Capital Territory</state>
        <zip>2605</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The Northern Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Epping</city>
        <state>New South Wales</state>
        <zip>3076</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Liverpool Hospital; Haematology</name>
      <address>
        <city>Liverpool</city>
        <state>New South Wales</state>
        <zip>2170</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Port Macquarie Base Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Port Macquarie</city>
        <state>New South Wales</state>
        <zip>2444</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Royal North Shore Hospital; Haematology Department</name>
      <address>
        <city>St. Leonards</city>
        <state>New South Wales</state>
        <zip>2065</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Royal Hobart Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hobart</city>
        <state>Tasmania</state>
        <zip>7000</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Peter MacCallum Cancer Centre; Department of Haematology</name>
      <address>
        <city>Melbourne</city>
        <state>Victoria</state>
        <zip>3002</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Monash Medical Centre; Haematology</name>
      <address>
        <city>Melbourne</city>
        <state>Victoria</state>
        <zip>3168</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CHU de Caen, Institut d'Hématologie de Basse-Normandie</name>
      <address>
        <city>Caen</city>
        <zip>14003</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hopital Henri Mondor; Hematologie Clinique</name>
      <address>
        <city>Creteil</city>
        <zip>94010</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Clinique Victor Hugo - Centre Jean Bernard</name>
      <address>
        <city>Le Mans Cedex 02</city>
        <zip>72015</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hopital Saint Jean; Centre Henri Pujol</name>
      <address>
        <city>Perpignan</city>
        <zip>66046</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hopital De Haut Leveque; Hematologie Clinique</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pessac</city>
        <zip>33604</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ch Lyon Sud; Hemato Secteur Jules Courmont</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pierre Benite</city>
        <zip>69495</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hopital De La Miletrie; Hematologie Et Oncologie Medicale</name>
      <address>
        <city>Poitiers</city>
        <zip>86021</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hopital Robert Debre; Hematologie Clinique</name>
      <address>
        <city>Reims</city>
        <zip>51092</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CHI de Toulon - Hôpital Sainte Musse</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toulon</city>
        <zip>83056</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hopital Bretonneau; Hematologie Therapie Cellulaire</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tours</city>
        <zip>37044</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Azienda Ospedaliero-Universitaria Policlinico di Modena Ematologia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Modena</city>
        <state>Emilia-Romagna</state>
        <zip>41123</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Universita' Degli Studi La Sapienza-Ist.Di Ematologia; Dip Biot Cel e Ematol</name>
      <address>
        <city>Roma</city>
        <state>Lazio</state>
        <zip>00161</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Uni Cattolica; Divisione Di Ematologia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Roma</city>
        <state>Lazio</state>
        <zip>00168</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ospedale Maggiore Di Milano; U.O. Ematologia I - Padiglione Marcora</name>
      <address>
        <city>Milano</city>
        <state>Lombardia</state>
        <zip>20122</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>ASST GRANDE OSPEDALE METROPOLITANO NIGUARDA; Struttura Complessa di Ematologia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Milano</city>
        <state>Lombardia</state>
        <zip>20162</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>SCDU Ematologia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Novara</city>
        <state>Piemonte</state>
        <zip>28100</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Irccs Ist. Tumori Giovanni Paolo Ii; Dipartimento Oncologia Medica</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bari</city>
        <state>Puglia</state>
        <zip>70124</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Asl Le-Ospedale &quot;Vito Fazzi&quot;;U.O. Ematologia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lecce</city>
        <state>Puglia</state>
        <zip>73100</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Azienda Ospedaliera Di Perugia Ospedale s. Maria Della Misericordia; Oncologia Medica</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sant'Andrea Delle Fratte (PG)</city>
        <state>Umbria</state>
        <zip>06132</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital de Navarra, Servicio de Hematología</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pamplona</city>
        <state>Navarra</state>
        <zip>31008</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Universitario de Canarias;servicio de Hematologia</name>
      <address>
        <city>La Laguna</city>
        <state>Tenerife</state>
        <zip>38320</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Universitari Vall d'Hebron; Servicio de Hematologia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Barcelona</city>
        <zip>08035</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Universitario la Paz; Servicio de Hematologia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Madrid</city>
        <zip>28046</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital General Universitario J.M Morales Meseguer; Servicio de Hematología</name>
      <address>
        <city>Murcia</city>
        <zip>30008</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Clinico Universitario de Salamanca;Servicio de Hematologia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Salamanca</city>
        <zip>37007</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Universitario Virgen del Rocio; Servicio de Hematologia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sevilla</city>
        <zip>41013</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Complejo Hospitalario de Toledo- H. Virgen de la Salud; Servicio de Hematología</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toledo</city>
        <zip>45004</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Australia</country>
    <country>France</country>
    <country>Italy</country>
    <country>Spain</country>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 25, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 25, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 26, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 13, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 13, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 14, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Leukemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Lymphoid</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Lymphocytic, Chronic, B-Cell</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cyclophosphamide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Bendamustine Hydrochloride</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Rituximab</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fludarabine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Venetoclax</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Obinutuzumab</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Qualified researchers may request access to individual patient level data through the clinical study data request platform(www.clinicalstudydatarequest.com). Further details on Roche's criteria for eligible studies are available here (https://clinicalstudydatarequest.com/Study-Sponsors/Study-Sponsors-Roche.aspx). For further details on Roche's Global Policy on the Sharing of Clinical Information and how to request access to related clinical study documents, see here (https://www.roche.com/research_and_development/who_we_are_how_we_work/clinical_trials/our_commitment_to_data_sharing.htm).</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

