<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04285606</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2019684MU</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04285606</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effect of Postop Rehab Methods on Outcomes Following Reverse Shoulder Arthroplasty</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effect of Different Postoperative Rehab Methods on Clinical Outcomes Following Reverse Shoulder Arthroplasty: A Prospective Randomized Clinical Trial Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Missouri-Columbia</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Harry S. Truman Memorial Veterans Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Missouri-Columbia</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Notwithstanding the rapid increase in utilization of reverse total shoulder arthroplasty
      (RTSA), little consensus or high-quality evidence exists regarding optimal rehab methods
      following the procedure. Our research question is how different rehab methods influence the
      clinical outcomes following RTSA. This proposal presents a prospective randomized clinical
      trial where 100 eligible RTSA patients will be randomly assigned to two rehab groups (Short
      immobilization with patient-directed therapy vs Long immobilization with supervised therapy)
      at a single institution. Patient-reported outcomes, objective clinical data, and
      complications will be compared between the groups over a period of 2 years.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The investigators will perform a prospective randomized non-blinded clinical study where the
      investigators will recruit a total of 100 patients undergoing RTSA at our institution
      according to the inclusion and exclusion criteria. Participants will be randomly assigned to
      one of two rehab groups (50 in each group) - short immobilization combined with
      patient-directed home therapy (Patient-led rehab) vs long immobilization combined with
      supervised physical therapy (Supervised rehab) - using a randomization protocol developed by
      our biostatistics department. The group assignment will be kept sealed in an envelope until
      the day of surgery to blind both the patients and surgeons.

      Surgical procedure and postoperative rehabilitation Enrolled patients will undergo RTSA with
      one of the two shoulder and elbow surgeons under general anesthesia combined with
      interscalene block. A standard deltopectoral approach will be used, and the subscapularis
      tendon will be repaired using transosseous sutures if it is reparable. Tornier reverse
      shoulder arthroplasty system (Ascent Flex humeral stem with 132.5°inclincation angle,
      standard Perform Reversed glenoid components, and standard polyethylene liner) will be used
      in all patients. The size of the humeral stem, baseplate, glenosphere, and polyethylene liner
      will be chosen on the basis of the patient's anatomy. A sling with an abduction pillow will
      be used for postoperative immobilization in 30° abduction and 45° internal rotation in all
      patients. The patient-led rehab group will be educated on their postoperative rehab in detail
      prior to surgery. The detailed rehab methods for each group are as follows.

        1. Patient-led rehab group Duration of the sling: 1 week in sling with abduction pillow for
           immobilization; then optional for comfort only Start of shoulder exercise: Within 1 week
           of surgery once pain subsides Mode of rehab: Patients performing exercises on their own
           following instructions Phase 1 (3-5 days to 2 weeks): Pendulum, deltoid and periscapular
           muscle isometric strengthening Phase 2 (2-4 weeks): passive, active assisted motion
           Phase 3 (4-8 weeks): Active motion Phase 4 (8-12 weeks): Strengthening

        2. Supervised rehab group Duration of the sling: 4 weeks in sling with abduction pillow for
           immobilization; then optional for comfort only Start of shoulder exercise: At 4 weeks
           after surgery Mode of rehab: Patients attending outpatient physical therapy sessions led
           by therapists Phase 1 (0-4 weeks): Immobilization in sling Phase 2 (4-8 weeks): Passive,
           active assisted motion Phase 3 (8-12 weeks): Active motin Phase 4 (12-16 weeks):
           Strengthening

      Postoperative outcome evaluation Strict adherence to the rehab protocol will be encouraged
      and monitored during the rehab period. The research coordinator will contact patients twice a
      week for the first 2 weeks and then once a week for the following 2 weeks. Patients will be
      given a pain diary where they will record their pain levels daily along with their daily
      narcotic use for the first 2 weeks. Patients will return for follow-up, undergo x-rays, and
      will be evaluated at 2 weeks, 6 weeks, 12 weeks, 6 months, 1 year, and 2 years. The following
      data will be obtained during the study period.

        1. Pain measured using a visual analog scale daily for the first 2 weeks; then at each
           follow-up visit

        2. Patient-reported outcomes: ASES, QuickDASH, SANE, and PROMIS at each visit except at 2
           weeks.

        3. Range of motion: forward elevation, external rotation, internal rotation at each visit
           except at 2 weeks

        4. Radiographic findings of failure such as dislocation, implant dislodgement, migration,
           or loosening, scapular notching, periprosthetic humuerus fracture, or scapular fracture
           at any time: Will be included as complications

        5. Complications such as instability, hematoma, wound healing issue, abnormal level of pain
           due to rehab method at any time, or reoperation

        6. Overall patient satisfaction with their rehab method using a 5-point Likert-type scale
           at 6 months (Question: Were you satisfied with your rehab method? Very unsatisfied,
           slightly unsatisfied, neutral, somewhat satisfied, very satisfied)

      Statistical analysis Sample size calculation: Sample size was calculated to examine the
      superiority of patient-led rehab over supervised rehab. The null hypothesis is that there is
      no difference in the primary outcome measure (ASES score at 6 months) between the two rehab
      methods. Considering similar protocols in the literature12-14 and a mean difference in ASES
      scores of 11 points with corresponding standard deviation of 18 points, a minimum of 100
      patients (50 for each group) are needed to achieve at least 80% power using a two-sided type
      I error of 0.05. These numbers account for a 10% patient attrition.

      Statistical methods: Intention-to-treat analysis will be used for this randomized clinical
      trial study. Patients who are lost to follow up (dropout), do not comply with their assigned
      rehab method based on criteria (noncompliance), or change to the other rehab method
      (cross-over) will be analyzed according to their original group assignment. If there is
      greater than 10% of data is missing, the group data will be treated according to a missing
      data protocol - multiple imputation method under a missing at random (MAR) assumption.
      Patient-reported and objective clinical outcomes will be compared between the two rehab
      groups using two sample t-test or Mann-Whitney U-test if assumptions are not met. Differences
      between rehab groups across the follow-up period will be identified using a repeated measures
      ANOVA, and the appropriate covariance structure will be determined using BIC, a measure of
      overall model fit. Categorical data including the proportions of complications will be
      compared between the two rehab groups using Chi-square or Fisher's Exact tests; odds ratios
      and 95% confidence limits will be calculated where appropriate.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 8, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 1, 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 1, 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>American shoulder and elbow surgeons score at 6 months following surgery</measure>
    <time_frame>At 6 months following surgery</time_frame>
    <description>American shoulder and elbow surgeons score at 6 months; lowest 0 point and highest 100 points; higher scores mean a better outcome</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Complications</measure>
    <time_frame>During the first 2 years following surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Proportions of patients who develop any kinds of postoperative complications</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Rotator Cuff Tear Arthropathy</condition>
  <condition>Shoulder Osteoarthritis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Patient-led rehab group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Immobilization in arm sling for a short period time followed by patient-led shoulder exercises for rehab following reverse shoulder arthroplasty</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Supervised rehab group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Prolonged immobilization in arm sling followed by supervised physical therapy by therapists for rehab following reverse shoulder arthroplasty</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Patient-led rehab with short immobilization</intervention_name>
    <description>Short immobilization followed by patient-led shoulder rehab</description>
    <arm_group_label>Patient-led rehab group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Aged 18 years or older

          2. Diagnosed with rotator cuff arthropathy, glenohumeral osteoarthritis with a &gt; 1.5-cm
             rotator cuff tear, or massive irreparable rotator cuff tear

          3. Have a normal functioning deltoid

          4. Have preserved teres minor function (a negative Hornblower's sign)

          5. Have failed conservative management for &gt;3 months

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. younger than 18 years

          2. chronic opiate use history

          3. fibromyalgia or other conditions that increase susceptibility to pain

          4. preoperative stiffness (definition: &lt; 30 degree passive external rotation, &lt; 90 degree
             passive forward elevation), neurologic disorder affecting the ipsilateral upper
             extremity,

          5. RTSA for acute proximal humerus fracture or fracture sequelae (nonunion, malunion)

          6. previous arthroplasty, fracture fixation, or open rotator cuff procedures in the same
             shoulder

          7. deltoid dysfunction

          8. inflammatory glenohumeral arthritis

          9. non-English speaking or unable to understand English for consent.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Hyunmin M Kim, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Missouri-Columbia</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Hyunmin M Kim, MD</last_name>
    <phone>314-920-3263</phone>
    <email>kimhm@health.missouri.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Stacee W Clawson, RN</last_name>
    <phone>573-884-9017</phone>
    <email>clawsons@health.missouri.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Missouri</name>
      <address>
        <city>Columbia</city>
        <state>Missouri</state>
        <zip>65212</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Susan Kady, BSN, RN</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Westermann RW, Pugely AJ, Martin CT, Gao Y, Wolf BR, Hettrich CM. Reverse Shoulder Arthroplasty in the United States: A Comparison of National Volume, Patient Demographics, Complications, and Surgical Indications. Iowa Orthop J. 2015;35:1-7.</citation>
    <PMID>26361437</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jain NB, Yamaguchi K. The contribution of reverse shoulder arthroplasty to utilization of primary shoulder arthroplasty. J Shoulder Elbow Surg. 2014 Dec;23(12):1905-1912. doi: 10.1016/j.jse.2014.06.055. Epub 2014 Oct 7.</citation>
    <PMID>25304043</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schairer WW, Nwachukwu BU, Lyman S, Craig EV, Gulotta LV. National utilization of reverse total shoulder arthroplasty in the United States. J Shoulder Elbow Surg. 2015 Jan;24(1):91-7. doi: 10.1016/j.jse.2014.08.026. Epub 2014 Oct 29.</citation>
    <PMID>25440519</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Palsis JA, Simpson KN, Matthews JH, Traven S, Eichinger JK, Friedman RJ. Current Trends in the Use of Shoulder Arthroplasty in the United States. Orthopedics. 2018 May 1;41(3):e416-e423. doi: 10.3928/01477447-20180409-05. Epub 2018 Apr 16.</citation>
    <PMID>29658976</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Boudreau S, Boudreau ED, Higgins LD, Wilcox RB 3rd. Rehabilitation following reverse total shoulder arthroplasty. J Orthop Sports Phys Ther. 2007 Dec;37(12):734-43. doi: 10.2519/jospt.2007.2562. Epub 2007 Aug 28. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18560182</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bullock GS, Garrigues GE, Ledbetter L, Kennedy J. A Systematic Review of Proposed Rehabilitation Guidelines Following Anatomic and Reverse Shoulder Arthroplasty. J Orthop Sports Phys Ther. 2019 May;49(5):337-346. doi: 10.2519/jospt.2019.8616. Epub 2019 Apr 25.</citation>
    <PMID>31021690</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Romano AM, Oliva F, Nastrucci G, Casillo P, Di Giunta A, Susanna M, Ascione F. Reverse shoulder arthroplasty patient personalized rehabilitation protocol. Preliminary results according to prognostic groups. Muscles Ligaments Tendons J. 2017 Sep 18;7(2):263-270. doi: 10.11138/mltj/2017.7.2.263. eCollection 2017 Apr-Jun.</citation>
    <PMID>29264337</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wolff AL, Rosenzweig L. Anatomical and biomechanical framework for shoulder arthroplasty rehabilitation. J Hand Ther. 2017 Apr - Jun;30(2):167-174. doi: 10.1016/j.jht.2017.05.009. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>28641735</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kwaees TA, Charalambous CP. Reverse shoulder arthroplasty--minimum age for surgery, postoperative rehabilitation and long term restrictions. A delphi consensus study. Ortop Traumatol Rehabil. 2014 Jul-Aug;16(4):435-9. doi: 10.5604/15093492.1119621.</citation>
    <PMID>25404633</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Flurin PH, Marczuk Y, Janout M, Wright TW, Zuckerman J, Roche CP. Comparison of outcomes using anatomic and reverse total shoulder arthroplasty. Bull Hosp Jt Dis (2013). 2013;71 Suppl 2:101-7.</citation>
    <PMID>24328590</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mulieri PJ, Holcomb JO, Dunning P, Pliner M, Bogle RK, Pupello D, Frankle MA. Is a formal physical therapy program necessary after total shoulder arthroplasty for osteoarthritis? J Shoulder Elbow Surg. 2010 Jun;19(4):570-9. doi: 10.1016/j.jse.2009.07.012. Epub 2009 Oct 2.</citation>
    <PMID>19800258</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sershon RA, Van Thiel GS, Lin EC, McGill KC, Cole BJ, Verma NN, Romeo AA, Nicholson GP. Clinical outcomes of reverse total shoulder arthroplasty in patients aged younger than 60 years. J Shoulder Elbow Surg. 2014 Mar;23(3):395-400. doi: 10.1016/j.jse.2013.07.047. Epub 2013 Oct 12.</citation>
    <PMID>24129052</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 23, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 23, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 26, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 8, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 8, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 10, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Missouri-Columbia</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>H. Mike Kim</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Reverse shoulder arthroplasty</keyword>
  <keyword>Rehabilitation</keyword>
  <keyword>Shoulder arthritis</keyword>
  <keyword>Rotator cuff tear arthropathy</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Joint Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Rotator Cuff Tear Arthropathy</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Rotator Cuff Injuries</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>No plan to share IPD</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

