<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04285281</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CE0072015-02-03</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04285281</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Oral Gabapentin in the Treatment of Carpal Tunnel Syndrome</brief_title>
  <official_title>Oral Gabapentin Versus Control in the Treatment of Carpal Tunnel Syndrome</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Universidad Europea de Madrid</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Universidad Europea de Madrid</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      In the present investigation the pain reduction effects of Gabapentin will be compared to
      those produced by the absence of treatment, in subjects who suffer the signs and symptoms of
      carpal tunnel syndrome.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The present randomized clinical trial will perform a comparison of the pain reduction effect
      produced by the application of an oral gabapentin (pharmaceutical) treatment, to the pain
      reduction effect produced by the lack of treatment in subjects diagnosed with carpal tunnel
      syndrome. Additionally, effects over the functionality of the affected upper limb will be
      evaluated and compared. Subjects will be invited to participate and randomly allocated to 2
      different groups.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">March 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Distal upper limb pain</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes from baseline (measured immediately before the application of each treatment) at 40 minutes after the application of treatment. Measures at baseline and after treatment will be performed 1 day a week during 4 weeks.</time_frame>
    <description>Assessed through the visual analog scale (VAS). The VAS is a psychometric response scale. It is a measurement instrument for subjective characteristics or attitudes that cannot be directly measured.The VAS is the most frequently used method to assess pain intensity. The scale will be displayed as a horizontal 10-cm line labelled at each end by descriptors such as 'no pain' (the minimum and best outcome possible) and 'worse pain ever' (maximum and worst outcome possible). The participant will mark the line to indicate pain severity and it is simply quantified by measuring the distance in centimeters from 0 (no pain) to the patient's marked rating.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Upper limb function</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes from baseline (measured immediately before the application of the first treatment), and at 40 minutes after the application of the last treatment.</time_frame>
    <description>Assessed through the quick Quick Disabilities of the Arm, Shoulder and Hand questionary (QuickDASH), which is a shortened version of the 30-item Disabilities of the Arm, Shoulder and Hand (DASH) instrument.The instrument administered to the participants will be a self-report questionnaire, that will rate the difficulty and interference of daily life on a 5 point Likert scale. At least 10 of the 11 items must be completed for a score to be calculated and the scores range from 0 (no disability) to 100 (most severe disability).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Carpal Tunnel Syndrome</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Gabapentin</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will be treated with a maximum of 1800 mg per day, subdivided in 3 intakes of 600 mg each 8 hours during a time lapse of 4 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants that belong to the no intervention arm will be assigned to a waiting list to receive treatment. The participants will not receive treatment for carpal tunnel syndrome during a time lapse of 4 weeks. After this period of time, participants will begin the best treatment available.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Gabapentin oral capsules</intervention_name>
    <description>Oral capsule pharmaceutical treatment.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Gabapentin</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Neurontin</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Participants must be medically diagnosed with unilateral carpal tunnel syndrome (with
             confirmative electrodiagnostic findings).

          -  Full understanding of written and spoken Spanish (language).

          -  Participants must freely consent to participate.

          -  The presence of positive Phalen an Tinel sings.

          -  The presence of carpal tunnel syndrome signs and symptoms

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  The lack to meet inclusion criterions, the presence of cognitive impairment, tumors,
             cancer, recent (affected) upper limb surgery or trauma, pregnancy, , deformities of
             the (affected) upper limb, recent skin injuries or infections (in the affected upper
             limb), autoimmune inflammatory conditions or flu type symptoms, allergy to gabapentin,
             and also: participants must not be (during the present investigation) under any type
             of pain reducing treatment (conservative, homeopathic, invasive or not invasive).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Francisco Unda, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Confederación Gallega de Discapacidad</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Francisco Unda, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>0034695634680</phone>
    <email>5299559@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>&quot;Centro Médico y de Especialidades Pediátricas Dr. José Gregorio Hernández &quot;</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Diego</city>
        <state>Carabobo</state>
        <zip>02006</zip>
        <country>Venezuela</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Venezuela</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hesami O, Haghighatzadeh M, Lima BS, Emadi N, Salehi S. The effectiveness of gabapentin and exercises in the treatment of carpal tunnel syndrome: a randomized clinical trial. J Exerc Rehabil. 2018 Dec 27;14(6):1067-1073. doi: 10.12965/jer.1836420.210. eCollection 2018 Dec.</citation>
    <PMID>30656171</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Taverner D, Lisbona MP, Segalés N, Docampo E, Calvet J, Castro S, Benito P. [Efficacy of gabapentin in the treatment of carpal tunnel syndrome]. Med Clin (Barc). 2008 Mar 22;130(10):371-3. Spanish.</citation>
    <PMID>18381028</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dosenovic S, Jelicic Kadic A, Miljanovic M, Biocic M, Boric K, Cavar M, Markovina N, Vucic K, Puljak L. Interventions for Neuropathic Pain: An Overview of Systematic Reviews. Anesth Analg. 2017 Aug;125(2):643-652. doi: 10.1213/ANE.0000000000001998. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>28731977</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Erdemoglu AK. The efficacy and safety of gabapentin in carpal tunnel patients: open label trial. Neurol India. 2009 May-Jun;57(3):300-3. doi: 10.4103/0028-3886.53287.</citation>
    <PMID>19587471</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sanz DR, Solano FU, López DL, Corbalan IS, Morales CR, Lobo CC. Effectiveness of median nerve neural mobilization versus oral ibuprofen treatment in subjects who suffer from cervicobrachial pain: a randomized clinical trial. Arch Med Sci. 2018 Jun;14(4):871-879. doi: 10.5114/aoms.2017.70328. Epub 2017 Sep 26.</citation>
    <PMID>30002707</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rodríguez-Sanz D, Calvo-Lobo C, Unda-Solano F, Sanz-Corbalán I, Romero-Morales C, López-López D. Cervical Lateral Glide Neural Mobilization Is Effective in Treating Cervicobrachial Pain: A Randomized Waiting List Controlled Clinical Trial. Pain Med. 2017 Dec 1;18(12):2492-2503. doi: 10.1093/pm/pnx011.</citation>
    <PMID>28340157</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Eren Y, Yavasoglu NG, Comoglu SS. The relationship between QDASH scale and clinical, electrophysiological findings in carpal tunnel syndrome. Adv Clin Exp Med. 2018 Jan;27(1):71-75. doi: 10.17219/acem/67947.</citation>
    <PMID>29521045</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yücel H, Seyithanoğlu H. Choosing the most efficacious scoring method for carpal tunnel syndrome. Acta Orthop Traumatol Turc. 2015;49(1):23-9. doi: 10.3944/AOTT.2015.13.0162.</citation>
    <PMID>25803249</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 23, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 23, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 26, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 23, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 23, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 26, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Universidad Europea de Madrid</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Francisco Unda Solano</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Biomedicine Doctorate Program Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Gabapentin</keyword>
  <keyword>Pain management</keyword>
  <keyword>Physiotherapy</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Carpal Tunnel Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Syndrome</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Gabapentin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

