<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04284319</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>19-01664</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04284319</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Heart Transplantation Using Normothermic Regional Perfusion Donation After Circulatory Death</brief_title>
  <official_title>Heart Transplantation Using Normothermic Regional Perfusion (NRP) Donation After Circulatory Death (DCD): A Pilot Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>NYU Langone Health</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>NYU Langone Health</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Normothermic regional perfusion (NRP) utilizes Extracorporeal Membrane Oxygenation (ECMO) or
      cardiopulmonary bypass to reperfuse the heart and other organs in situ after isolation and
      ligation of the cerebral vessels. In situ resuscitation of the heart has the added advantage
      of allowing full hemodynamic and echocardiographic assessment of the donor heart prior to
      final acceptance for transplantation without the imminent danger of ongoing warm ischemia.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The current procedure of DCD organ donation and procurement follows a well-established course
      for lung, liver, kidney and pancreas transplantation in the United States. After consent has
      been obtained, the organs are allocated through UNOS. When all parties are present and ready,
      the donor is withdrawn from life support (i.e., discontinuation of mechanical ventilation and
      any vasoactive medications). The surgical teams are generally present on the premises but not
      at the donor's bedside. After circulatory arrest occurs, which is determined by the absence
      of pulse and organized rhythmic cardiac activity, death is declared by a physician not
      associated with the transplant teams. Subsequently a period of stand-off is observed (5
      minutes for organs donated in New York) to ensure complete cessation of the circulation
      before organ procurement is commenced. If after withdrawal of life support the patient does
      not progress to circulatory death within the allotted time (variable among hospitals, but 180
      minutes in this study), the procurement is abandoned and the patient is transferred out of
      the operating room and placed on palliative measures.

      Given that DCD organ donation is already currently practiced in the US, the same standard
      approach defined by each state and locality can also be applied to DCD heart donation and
      will be followed for this protocol at NYULH. However, this protocol will utilize a
      normothermic regional perfusion (NRP) strategy that involves reestablishment of circulatory
      blood flow after the period of circulatory arrest has been established and the 5 minutes of
      standoff time has passed. The local Organ Procurement Organization (LiveOnNY) and NYULH
      Medical Leadership have reviewed and approved this approach to DCD heart donation.
      Specifically, normothermic regional perfusion involves the following steps:

        1. Opening the chest through a standard sternotomy used for heart and lung procurement.

        2. Ligation of the all the blood vessels that supply blood to the brain to ensure that
           blood flow to the brain is not reestablished once circulation is restarted as described
           below.

        3. Standard cannulation of the aorta and the right atrium as is done for cardiac surgical
           procedures.

        4. Initiation of cardiopulmonary bypass, which will re-establish the flow of blood to all
           organs of the body including the heart under normothermia. The initial step for ligation
           of the blood vessels to the head is necessary to ensure that blood flow to the brain
           does not occur.

      Once blood flow to the heart is established, the heart will start beating. At 30 minute
      intervals, the donor will be separated from cardiopulmonary bypass and the heart will be
      assessed for functionality. If accepted standard DBD procurement will commence. The heart
      transplantation surgery on the potential recipient will only begin once the heart has been
      accepted as suitable.

      If after assessment the heart is not suitable, cardiopulmonary bypass will be restarted. The
      donor heart will be reassessed at 30 minute intervals up to 180 minutes. If no significant
      acceptable recovery occurs and the heart is not deemed suitable for transplantation, then the
      study will be terminated, but the remaining organs can be recovered as standard practice.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 17, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 31, 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 31, 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Pilot Study</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Successful NRP-DCD Heart transplants</measure>
    <time_frame>One Year</time_frame>
    <description>The primary outcome is the rate of successful NRP-DCD heart transplants.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of living authorized representatives who authorize candidate's organs for donation and research</measure>
    <time_frame>One Year</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of candidates who are transferred to NYU Langone Health for donation after circulatory death (DCD)</measure>
    <time_frame>One Year</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of candidates who progress to death after withdrawal of care</measure>
    <time_frame>One Year</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Donors whose hearts are deemed suitable for donation following normothermic regional perfusion (NRP)</measure>
    <time_frame>One Year</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">10</enrollment>
  <condition>Heart Failure</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>DCD Heart Transplantation Using NRP</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Heart Transplantation Using Normothermic Regional Perfusion (NRP) Donation After Circulatory Death (DCD)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>DCD Heart Transplantation Using NRP</intervention_name>
    <description>Heart Transplantation Using Normothermic Regional Perfusion (NRP) Donation After Circulatory Death (DCD)</description>
    <arm_group_label>DCD Heart Transplantation Using NRP</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Recipient is ≥ 18 years old

          2. Recipient, or their designated healthcare proxy, is able and willing to sign informed
             consent

          3. Recipient meets standard listing criteria for heart transplantation at NYU Langone
             Health Transplant Institute

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Recipient is &lt; 18 years old

          2. Recipient, or their designated healthcare proxy, is unable to sign informed consent

          3. Recipient is participating in another interventional trial

          4. Recipient has a known history of HIV infection

          5. Recipient has any condition that, in the opinion of the Investigator, would make study
             participation unsafe or would interfere with the objectives of the study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Zachary Kon, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>NYU Langone Health-Transplant Institute</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Zachary Kon, MD</last_name>
    <phone>646-501-8290</phone>
    <email>Zachary.Kon@nyulangone.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>NYU Langone Health</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10016</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Zachary Kon, MD</last_name>
      <phone>646-501-8290</phone>
      <email>Zachary.Kon@nyulangone.org</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Elaina P Weldon, ACNP-BC</last_name>
      <phone>646-385-0920</phone>
      <email>Elaina.Weldon@nyumc.org</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 24, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 24, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 25, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 24, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 24, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 25, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>NYU Langone Health</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Zachary Kon</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Heart Transplantation</keyword>
  <keyword>Normothermic Regional Perfusion</keyword>
  <keyword>NRP</keyword>
  <keyword>Donation After Circulatory Death</keyword>
  <keyword>DCD</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Heart Failure</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Death</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

