<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04285086</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>P1101 ET</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04285086</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Ropeginterferon Alfa-2b (P1101) vs. Anagrelide in Essential Thrombocythemia Patients With Hydroxyurea Resistance or Intolerance</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase 3, Open-Label, Multicenter, Randomized, Active-controlled Study to Assess Pharmacokinetics and Compare the Efficacy, Safety, and Tolerability of P1101 vs Anagrelide as Second Line Therapy for Essential Thrombocythemia</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>PharmaEssentia</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Medpace, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>EPS International</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Brightech International</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>PharmaEssentia</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a Phase 3 open-label, multicenter, randomized, active-controlled study designed to
      compare the efficacy and safety and tolerability of P1101 compared with ANA after 12 months
      of treatment as second-line therapy for subjects with ET who have had a suboptimal or failed
      response to HU.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PharmaEssentia Corporation is developing a pegylated (PEG) IFN-α product, P1101, for the
      treatment of ET.

      Available clinical data and experience with P1101 in PV shows that the compound, with proper
      dose modifications, is effective in controlling disease in a significant proportion of
      subjects with ET. Further, its increased serum half-life presents distinct advantages for ET
      treatment over that of standard IFN-α and other available PEG IFN-α therapy. This pivotal
      Phase 3 study will establish the efficacy and safety of P1101 in ET subjects.

      The enrolled subjects will be randomized into two arms, the test arm is P1101, the control
      arm is ANA. The overall duration for each eligible patient is 14 months, including screening
      (1 month), treatment (12 months) and follow-up (1 month) period. Efficacy evaluations, safety
      assessments, and PK and immunogenicity evaluations of P1101 will be performed.

      Evaluation of efficacy will include clinical laboratory assessments, allelic burden
      measurements of CALR, JAK-2, and MPL, spleen size measurements, bone marrow sampling,
      EQ-5D-3L, and MPN-SAF TSS completion.

      Evaluation of safety will include assessing vital signs, clinical safety laboratory tests,
      physical examinations, ECG evaluation, heart ECHO, lung X-ray, ECOG performance status,
      ocular examination, and AEs.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">August 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Experimental Drug (Biological): Ropeginterferon alfa-2b (P1101), Q2W, SC injection Control Drug: Anagrelide, capsules, daily, p.o.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Peripheral blood count remission</measure>
    <time_frame>month 9 and month 12</time_frame>
    <description>platelets ≤400 x 109/L AND white blood cells (WBC) &lt;9.5 x 109/L</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Improvement or non-progression in disease-related signs</measure>
    <time_frame>month 9 and month 12</time_frame>
    <description>splenomegaly</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Large symptoms improvement</measure>
    <time_frame>month 9 and month 12</time_frame>
    <description>based on the Myeloproliferative Neoplasm Symptom Assessment Form Total Symptom Score (MPN-SAF TSS)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Absence of hemorrhagic or thrombotic events</measure>
    <time_frame>month 9 and month 12</time_frame>
    <description>absence of hemorrhagic or thrombotic events</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Durable response</measure>
    <time_frame>month 3 and month 6</time_frame>
    <description>measure durable response at month 3 and 6</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Longitudinal rate</measure>
    <time_frame>over the 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>measure longitudinal rate of change in the ELN response rates over the 12 months</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Response rates</measure>
    <time_frame>3, 6, 9, and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>measure response rate based on peripheral blood count remission, no signs of progressive disease, and absence of any hemorrhagic or thrombotic events</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Occurrence of thromboembolic events</measure>
    <time_frame>over the 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>measure occurrence of thromboembolic events over the 12 months</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to first peripheral blood count remission response</measure>
    <time_frame>over the 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>measure time to first peripheral blood count remission response over the 12 months</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of peripheral blood count remission response</measure>
    <time_frame>over the 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>measure duration of peripheral blood count remission response over the 12 months</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Symptomatic improvement assessed by the EuroQOL 5 dimensions 3 level version (EQ-5D-3L) questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>over the 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>measure symptomatic improvement assessed by the EuroQOL 5 dimensions 3 level version (EQ-5D-3L) questionnaire over the 12 months</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Symptomatic improvement assessed by the 10-item MPN-SAF TSS</measure>
    <time_frame>over the 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>measure symptomatic improvement assessed by the 10-item MPN-SAF TSS over the 12 months</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of CALR, MPL, and JAK-2 allelic burden over time</measure>
    <time_frame>over the 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>measure change of CALR, MPL, and JAK-2 allelic burden over time</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Spleen size assessment</measure>
    <time_frame>over the 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>measure spleen size over time</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Bone marrow histological remission</measure>
    <time_frame>over the 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>the disappearance of megakaryocyte hyperplasia and absence of &gt;grade 1 reticulin fibrosis</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">160</enrollment>
  <condition>Essential Thrombocythemia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Ropeginterferon alfa-2b (P1101)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Pre-filled Syringe, Q2W, SC injection</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Anagrelide</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Capsules, Daily, p.o.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ropeginterferon alfa-2b</intervention_name>
    <description>Ropeginterferon alfa-2b (P1101) dosage: from 250 mcg to 500 mcg Anagrelide dosage: 0.5 mg per capsule, according to label and physician's judgement</description>
    <arm_group_label>Anagrelide</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Ropeginterferon alfa-2b (P1101)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Anagrelide</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Male or female subjects ≥18 years old

          2. Subjects diagnosed with high-risk ET (either older than 60 years and JAK2V617-positive
             at screening, or having disease-related thrombosis or hemorrhage in the past),
             diagnosed according to the World Health Organization (WHO) 2016 criteria

          3. Subjects have received prior HU for ET, while the washout between the last dose of HU
             and the screening visit should not be shorter than 14 days

          4. Interferon treatment-naïve

          5. Documented resistance/intolerance to prior HU for ET, as defined by ELN criteria
             (Barosi, et al, 2007), whereby at least one of the following criteria is met:

             Platelet count &gt;600 x 109/L at ≥2 g/day (or ≥2.5 g/day if subject body weight &gt;80 kg)
             or maximally tolerated dose if &lt;2 g/day after at least 3 months of HU, or Platelet
             count &gt;400 x 109/L and WBC count &lt;2.5 x 109/L at any dose and any duration of HU, or
             Platelet count &gt;400 x 109/L and hemoglobin (HGB) &lt;10 g/dL at any dose and any duration
             of HU, or Presence of HU-related toxicities at any dose and any duration of therapy
             (e.g., leg ulcers, mucocutaneous manifestations, pneumonitis, or HU-related fever)

          6. Platelets &gt;450 x 109/L at screening

          7. WBC &gt;10 x 109/L at screening

          8. HGB ≥11 g/dL at screening for males and 10 g/dL at screening for females

          9. Neutrophil count ≥1.0 x 109/L at screening

         10. Adequate hepatic function defined as bilirubin ≤1.5 x upper limit normal (ULN),
             international normalized ratio ≤1.5 x ULN, albumin &gt;3.5 g/dL, alanine aminotransferase
             ≤2.0 x ULN, aspartate aminotransferase ≤2.0 x ULN at screening

         11. Creatinine clearance ≥40 mL/min (by Cockcroft-Gault equation)

         12. Males and females of childbearing potential, as well as all women &lt;2 years after the
             onset of menopause, must agree to use an acceptable form of birth control until 28
             days following the last dose of the study drug, and females must agree to not
             breastfeed during the study

         13. Written informed consent obtained from the subjectand ability for the subject to
             comply with the requirements of the study

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Any subject requiring a legally authorized representative

          2. Any contraindications or hypersensitivity to IFN-α or ANA and their excipients

          3. Known risk factors for QT-prolongation (e.g., congenital long QT, known history of
             acquired QT-prolongations)

          4. Co-morbidity with severe or serious condition that, in the Investigator's opinion,
             would jeopardize the safety of the subject or their compliance with the protocol,
             including significant cardiac disease (including New York Heart Association Class
             III-IV congestive heart failure and clinically significant arrhythmias) and pulmonary
             hypertension

          5. History of major organ transplantation

          6. Pregnant or lactating females

          7. Subjects with any other significant medical conditions that, in the opinion of the
             Investigator, would compromise the results of the study or may impair compliance with
             the requirements of the protocol, including but not limited to:

               1. Documented autoimmune disease at screening or in the history (e.g., thyroid
                  dysfunction, hepatitis, idiopathic thrombocytopenic purpura, scleroderma,
                  psoriasis, or any arthritis of autoimmune origin)

               2. Clinically relevant pulmonary infiltrates, pneumonia, and pneumonitis at
                  screening that, in the Investigator's opinion, would jeopardize the safety of the
                  subject or their compliance with the protocol

               3. Infections with systemic manifestations (e.g., bacterial, fungal, or human
                  immunodeficiency virus [HIV], except hepatitis B [HBV] and/or hepatitis C [HCV],
                  at screening)

               4. Evidence of severe retinopathy (e.g., cytomegalovirus retinitis, macular
                  degeneration) or clinically relevant ophthalmological disorder (due to diabetes
                  mellitus or hypertension)

               5. History or presence of clinically relevant depression, or previous suicide
                  attempts or at any risk of suicide at screening, in the judgement of the
                  Investigator

               6. History or presence of clinically significant neurologic diseases

               7. History of any malignancy within 5 years (except Stage 0 chronic lymphocytic
                  leukemia, basal cell, squamous cell, and superficial melanoma)

               8. History of alcohol or drug abuse within the last year

               9. History or evidence of any other (than ET) MPN

          8. Use of any investigational drug &lt;4 weeks prior to the first dose of study drug or not
             recovered from effects of prior administration of any investigational agent

          9. Subjects with documented ANA resistance or intolerance (see Appendix 8 for
             definition).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Toshiaki Sato, MD/PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>PharmaEssentia Corp.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Toshiaki Sato, MD/PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+81 3 68669531</phone>
    <email>toshiaki_sato@pharmaessentia.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>TingFang Wang, MS/MHA</last_name>
    <phone>+886 2 26557688</phone>
    <phone_ext>1306</phone_ext>
    <email>tingfang_wang@pharmaessentia.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <verification_date>June 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 23, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 23, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 26, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 30, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 30, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 2, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Essential Thrombocythemia</keyword>
  <keyword>Ropeginterferon</keyword>
  <keyword>P1101</keyword>
  <keyword>PharmaEssentia</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Thrombocytosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Thrombocythemia, Essential</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Anagrelide</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

