<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04281108</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>SP-1011-003</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04281108</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Efficacy and Safety APT-1011 in Subjects With Eosinophilic Esophagitis (EoE) (FLUTE-2)</brief_title>
  <acronym>FLUTE-2</acronym>
  <official_title>Fluticasone Propionate Oral Dispersible Tablet Formulation in Eosinophilic Esophagitis: A Two-Part, Randomized, Double-blind, Placebo-Controlled Study of APT-1011 in Adult and Adolescent Subjects With Eosinophilic Esophagitis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Adare Pharmaceuticals, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Adare Pharmaceuticals, Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a 2-part randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled study of APT-1011 in adults and
      adolescents (≥15 years) with EoE.

      Part A will evaluate the efficacy and safety of APT-1011 3 mg administered HS for the
      induction of response to treatment (histologic and symptomatic) over 12 weeks.

      Part B will evaluate histological relapse-free status in patients re-randomized to continue
      APT-1011 or placebo (active treatment withdrawal) until Week 52.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a 2-part randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled study of APT-1011 in adults and
      adolescents (≥15 years) with EoE.

      Part A will evaluate the efficacy and safety of APT-1011 3 mg administered HS for the
      induction of response to treatment (histologic and symptomatic) over 12 weeks.

      At Week 14, subjects will move into Part B. Subjects with histological response to APT-1011,
      defined as ≤6 peak eos/hpf, will be re-randomized to continue APT-1011 or receive placebo
      (active treatment withdrawal). APT-1011 histological non-responders will continue APT-1011,
      placebo histological non-responders will receive APT-1011 3mg HS. Placebo histological
      responders will continue placebo. Histological relapse-free status will be determined at the
      time of EGD in Part B (at or prior to Week 52, depending on unscheduled EGDs) and is defined
      as ≤15 peak eos/hpf.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 30, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 31, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Sequential Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Week 12 histologic responder rates</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 12</time_frame>
    <description>To compare the Week 12 histologic responder rates (≤ 6 peak eosinophils [eos]/high power field [HPF]) change from baseline for APT-1011 3 mg HS with that for placebo. HPF will be defined as a standard area of 235 square microns in a microscope with 40x lens and 22mm ocular</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean change in number of dysphagia episodes</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 12</time_frame>
    <description>To compare the mean change in number of dysphagia episodes from baseline to Week 12 for APT-1011 3 mg HS with that for placebo</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Week 52 histologic relapse-free rates</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 12 to Week 52</time_frame>
    <description>To compare the Week 52 histologic relapse-free rates (≤ 15 peak eos/HPF) for APT-1011 3 mg responders in Part A randomized to continue APT-1011 3 mg HS (maintenance) with that for placebo (withdrawal of APT-1011 3 mg HS)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean change in number of dysphagia episodes from Week 12 to Week 52</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 12 to Week 52</time_frame>
    <description>To compare mean change in number of dysphagia episodes from Week 12 to Week 52 for APT-1011 responders randomized to continue APT-1011 3 mg HS with those randomized to placebo (withdrawal of APT-1011 3 mg HS)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in EREFs from Week 0 to Week 12</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 0 to Week 12</time_frame>
    <description>To compare endoscopic appearance evaluated by the mean change from baseline to Week 12 in Eosinophilic Esophagitis Endoscopic Reference Score (EREFs) for APT-1011 3 mg HS with that for placebo. EREFs version 4-19 grades features of edema, rings, exudates, furrows, stricture, and crepe paper esophagus on a scale from 0 to up to 3, with 0 indicating absence of symptoms.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of subjects with &lt;1 peak eos)/HPF at Week 12</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 12</time_frame>
    <description>To compare the percentage of subjects with &lt;1 peak eosinophils/high power field (eosinophils (eos)/HPF) at Week 12 for APT-1011 3 mg HS with that for placebo.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean change in PROSE Symptom Burden Score</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 12</time_frame>
    <description>To compare the mean change from baseline to Week 12 in the episode-level symptom burden utilizing the Patient Reported Outcomes Symptoms of EoE (PROSE) for APT-1011 3 mg HS with that for placebo.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean change in PROSE Episode-level Severity Score</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 12</time_frame>
    <description>To compare the mean change from baseline to Week 12 in the episode-level severity utilizing the Patient Reported Outcomes Symptoms of EoE (PROSE) for APT-1011 3 mg HS with that for placebo.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Histological Change from Baseline to Week 12</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 12</time_frame>
    <description>To compare mean histologic change from baseline to Week 12 for APT-1011 3 mg HS with that for placebo.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Subjects with &lt;15 peak eos/HPF</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 12</time_frame>
    <description>To compare the percentage of subjects with &lt;15 peak eosinophils/high power field (eos/HPF) for APT-1011 3 mg HS with that for placebo.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean Number of Dysphagia-free Days</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 12</time_frame>
    <description>To compare the mean number of dysphagia-free days from baseline to Week 12 for APT-1011 3 mg HS with that for placebo</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean Change in Endoscopic Appearance</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 12 to Week 52</time_frame>
    <description>To compare endoscopic appearance evaluated by the mean change from Week 12 to the esophagogastroduodenoscopy (EGD) conducted in Part B (at or prior to Week 52) in EREFs for APT-1011 responders randomized to continue APT-1011 3 mg HS with responders randomized to placebo (withdrawal of APT-1011 3 mg HS).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean Histological Change in EDG</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 12 to Week 52</time_frame>
    <description>To compare the mean histologic change from Week 12 to EDG conducted in Part B (at or prior to Week 52) for APT-1011 responders randomized to continue APT-1011 3 mg HS with responders randomized to placebo (withdrawal of APT-1011 3 mg HS)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean Change in PROSE Symptom Burden Score</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 12 to Week 52</time_frame>
    <description>To compare mean change in the episode-level symptom burden using the Patient Reported Outcomes Symptoms of EoE (PROSE) instrument from Week 12 to EGD conducted in Part B (at or prior to Week 52) for APT-1011 responders randomized to continue APT-1011 3 mg HS with responders randomized to placebo (withdrawal of APT-1011 3 mg HS). PROSE is a patient diary instrument which includes measures of EoE symptoms scaled from 0-10, with 10 being most severe.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean change in PROSE Episode-level Severity Score</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 2 to Week 52</time_frame>
    <description>To compare mean change in the episode-level severity using the Patient Reported Outcomes Symptoms of EoE (PROSE) from Week 12 to EGD conducted in Part B (at or prior to Week 52) for APT-1011 responders. randomized to continue APT-1011 3 mg HS with responders randomized to placebo (withdrawal of APT-1011 3 mg HS). PROSE is a patient diary instrument which includes measures of EoE symptoms scaled from 0-10, with 10 being most severe.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean Number of Dysphagia-free Days</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 12 to Week 52</time_frame>
    <description>To compare the mean number of dysphagia-free days from Week 12 to EGD conducted in Part B (at or prior to Week 52) for APT-1011 responders randomized to continue APT-1011 3 mg HS with responders randomized to placebo (withdrawal of APT-1011 3 mg HS)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">120</enrollment>
  <condition>Eosinophilic Esophagitis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>APT-1011</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>APT-1011 3 mg HS</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>HS</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>APT-1011</intervention_name>
    <description>APT-1011 is an orally disintegrating tablet that includes fluticasone propionate as its active ingredient.</description>
    <arm_group_label>APT-1011</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>fluticasone propionate</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo oral tablet</intervention_name>
    <description>Placebo orally disintegrating tablet.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>PBO</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Adult male or female ≥15 years of age at the time of informed consent or assent

          2. Each subject and/or their parents or legal guardian (for adolescents), must read,
             understand and provide consent or assent together with their parent(s) or guardian
             signature (for adolescents) on the ICF for this study and be willing and able to
             adhere to study-related treatment regimens, procedures and visit schedule

          3. Diagnosis or presumptive diagnosis of EoE that is confirmed during the Screening
             period by histology that demonstrates ≥15 peak eos/HPF. In order to ensure that a
             diagnosis can be made, at least 5-6 biopsies should be taken including both proximal
             and distal specimens (~3 each). Mid-esophageal biopsies are optional

               1. Esophagogastroduodenoscopies and biopsies are to be obtained during the Screening
                  period

               2. Biopsies will be read by a central pathologist

               3. Esophagogastroduodenoscopies and biopsies performed outside the study will not be
                  accepted to meet eligibility criteria

               4. Optional biopsies may be taken and processed locally for local use, if specified
                  in the local ICF. If serious pathology is unexpectedly encountered biopsies of
                  such lesions must be processed locally

          4. Have a subject-reported history of ≥6 episodes of dysphagia in the 14 days prior to
             baseline

          5. Completion of the daily diary on at least 11 out of the 14 days during the 2-week
             Baseline Symptom Assessment

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Have known contraindication, hypersensitivity, or intolerance to corticosteroids

          2. Have a contraindication to, or factors that substantially increase the risk of, EGD
             procedure or esophageal biopsy or have narrowing of the esophagus that precludes EGD
             with a standard 9 mm endoscope

          3. Have history of an esophageal stricture requiring dilatation within the 12 weeks prior
             to Screening

          4. Bone age more than 12 months behind chronological age for adolescent subjects

          5. Have any physical, mental, or social condition or history of illness or laboratory
             abnormality that in the Investigator's judgment might interfere with study procedures
             or the ability of the subject to adhere to and complete the study or increase the
             safety risk to the subject such as uncontrolled diabetes or hypertension or may
             increase risk of corticosteroid toxicity (e.g. abnormal bone mineral density)

          6. History or presence of oral or esophageal mucosal infection whilst using inhaled or
             nasal corticosteroids

          7. Have any mouth or dental condition that prevents normal eating (excluding braces)

          8. Have any condition affecting the esophageal mucosa or altering esophageal motility
             other than EoE, including erosive esophagitis (grade B or higher as per the Los
             Angeles Classification of Gastroesophageal Reflux Disease;19, hiatus hernia longer
             than 3 cm, Barrett's esophagus, and achalasia)

          9. Use of systemic (oral or parenteral) corticosteroids within 60 days before Screening,
             use of swallowed corticosteroids within 30 days before Screening

         10. Initiation of either inhaled or nasal corticosteroids or high-potency dermal topical
             corticosteroids within 30 days before Screening

         11. Use of calcineurin inhibitors or purine analogues (azathioprine, 6-mercaptopurine) in
             the 12 weeks before Screening

         12. Use of potent cytochrome P450 (CYP) 3A4 inhibitors (eg, ritonavir and ketoconazole) in
             the 12 weeks before Screening

         13. Initiation of an elimination diet or elemental diet within 30 days before Screening
             (diet must remain stable after signing ICF)

         14. Morning (07:00 to 09:00, or as close to that window as possible) serum cortisol level
             ≤5 μg/dL (138 nmol/L) that is not responsive to ACTH stimulation: defined as a serum
             cortisol level &lt;16 μg/dL (440 nmol/L) at 60 minutes with ACTH stimulation test using
             250 μg cosyntropin administered intramuscularly (ie, an abnormal result on the ACTH
             stimulation test)

         15. Use of biologic immunomodulators in the 24 weeks before Screening (allergy
             desensitization injection or oral therapy is allowed as long as the course of therapy
             is not altered during the study period)

         16. Subjects who have initiated, discontinued, or changed dosage regimen of histamine H2
             receptor antagonists, antacids or antihistamines for any condition such as
             gastro-esophageal reflux disease within 4 weeks before qualifying endoscopy during
             Screening. If already receiving these drugs, the dosage must remain constant
             throughout the study

         17. Subjects who have changed dosage regimen of PPIs within 8 weeks before qualifying
             endoscopy. If already receiving PPIs, the dosage must remain constant throughout the
             study

         18. Infection with hepatitis B, hepatitis C, or human immunodeficiency virus

         19. Have gastrointestinal bleeding or documented active peptic ulcer within 4 weeks prior
             to Screening or entering a new study period

         20. Have chronic infection such as prior or active tuberculosis, active chicken pox or
             measles or absence of prior measles, mumps and rubella vaccine. Subjects with
             tuberculosis exposure or who live in, or travel to, high endemic areas should be
             assessed locally for tuberculosis before consideration for the study

         21. Have immunosuppression, immunodeficiency, malignancy (except treated non-melanoma skin
             cancer), or known severe bleeding disorder

         22. Have a history or presence of Crohn's disease, celiac disease, or other inflammatory
             disease of the gastrointestinal tract, including eosinophilic gastroenteritis

         23. Have current drug abuse in the opinion of the Investigator.

         24. Have current alcohol abuse in the opinion of the Investigator.

         25. Female subjects who are pregnant, breastfeeding, or planning to become pregnant during
             the study

         26. Sexually active females of childbearing potential who do not agree to follow highly
             effective contraceptive methods through the End of Study visit (see Section 8.6.4 and
             Appendix 1)

         27. Have received an investigational product, as part of a clinical trial within 30 days
             (or 5 half-lives, whichever is longest) of Screening. Subjects who are currently
             participating in observational studies or enrolled in patient registries are allowed
             in this study

         28. Have participated in a prior study with investigational product APT-1011
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>15 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Evan Dellon, MD, MPH</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>UNC Center for Eosphageal Diseases and Swallowing</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Karol Knoop, RN, BS, CCRA</last_name>
    <phone>(609) 450-1312</phone>
    <email>karol.knoop@adarepharma.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Gina Eagle Taran, MD</last_name>
    <phone>(609) 450-1312</phone>
    <email>gina.eagletaran@adarepharma.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Adare Pharmaceuticals</name>
      <address>
        <city>Montgomery</city>
        <state>Alabama</state>
        <zip>36013</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Adare Pharmaceuticals</name>
      <address>
        <city>Phoenix</city>
        <state>Arizona</state>
        <zip>85003</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Adare Pharmaceuticals</name>
      <address>
        <city>Little Rock</city>
        <state>Arkansas</state>
        <zip>72201</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Adare Pharmaceuticals</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sacramento</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94203</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Adare Pharmaceuticals</name>
      <address>
        <city>Denver</city>
        <state>Colorado</state>
        <zip>80012</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Adare Pharmaceuticals</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hartford</city>
        <state>Connecticut</state>
        <zip>06101</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Adare Pharmaceuticals</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tallahassee</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>32301</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Adare Pharmaceuticals</name>
      <address>
        <city>Atlanta</city>
        <state>Georgia</state>
        <zip>30301</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Adare Pharmaceuticals</name>
      <address>
        <city>Springfield</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>62701</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Adare Pharmaceuticals</name>
      <address>
        <city>Indianapolis</city>
        <state>Indiana</state>
        <zip>46201</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Withdrawn</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Adare Pharmaceuticals</name>
      <address>
        <city>Des Moines</city>
        <state>Iowa</state>
        <zip>50301</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Adare Pharmaceuticals</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baton Rouge</city>
        <state>Louisiana</state>
        <zip>70801</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Adare Pharmaceuticals</name>
      <address>
        <city>Annapolis</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21401</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Adare Pharmaceuticals</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02108</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Adare Pharmaceuticals</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lansing</city>
        <state>Michigan</state>
        <zip>48901</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Adare Pharmaceuticals</name>
      <address>
        <city>Saint Paul</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55101</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Adare Pharmaceuticals</name>
      <address>
        <city>Jefferson City</city>
        <state>Missouri</state>
        <zip>65101</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Adare Pharmaceuticals</name>
      <address>
        <city>Helena</city>
        <state>Montana</state>
        <zip>59601</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Adare Pharmaceuticals</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lincoln</city>
        <state>Nebraska</state>
        <zip>68501</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Adare Pharmaceuticals</name>
      <address>
        <city>Albany</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>12201</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Adare Pharmaceuticals</name>
      <address>
        <city>Raleigh</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27601</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Adare Pharmaceuticals</name>
      <address>
        <city>Columbus</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>43081</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Adare Pharmaceuticals</name>
      <address>
        <city>Oklahoma City</city>
        <state>Oklahoma</state>
        <zip>73101</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Adare Pharmaceuticals</name>
      <address>
        <city>Salem</city>
        <state>Oregon</state>
        <zip>97301</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Adare Pharmaceuticals</name>
      <address>
        <city>Harrisburg</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>17101</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Adare Pharmaceuticals</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pierre</city>
        <state>South Dakota</state>
        <zip>57501</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Adare Pharmaceuticals</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nashville</city>
        <state>Tennessee</state>
        <zip>37201</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Adare Pharmaceuticals</name>
      <address>
        <city>Austin</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>73301</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Adare Pharmaceuticals</name>
      <address>
        <city>Salt Lake City</city>
        <state>Utah</state>
        <zip>84101</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Adare Pharmaceuticals</name>
      <address>
        <city>Richmond</city>
        <state>Virginia</state>
        <zip>23173</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Adare Pharmaceuticals</name>
      <address>
        <city>Olympia</city>
        <state>Washington</state>
        <zip>98501</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 20, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 20, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 24, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 16, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 16, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 17, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>APT-1011</keyword>
  <keyword>Esophagitis</keyword>
  <keyword>Eosinophilic Esophagitis</keyword>
  <keyword>Esophageal Diseases</keyword>
  <keyword>Gastrointestinal Diseases</keyword>
  <keyword>Digestive System Diseases</keyword>
  <keyword>Gastroenteritis</keyword>
  <keyword>Eosinophilia</keyword>
  <keyword>Leukocyte Disorders</keyword>
  <keyword>Hematologic Diseases</keyword>
  <keyword>Hypersensitivity, Immediate</keyword>
  <keyword>Hypersensitivity</keyword>
  <keyword>Immune System Diseases</keyword>
  <keyword>Fluticasone</keyword>
  <keyword>Anti-Inflammatory Agents</keyword>
  <keyword>Bronchodilator Agents</keyword>
  <keyword>Autonomic Agents</keyword>
  <keyword>Peripheral Nervous System Agents</keyword>
  <keyword>Anti-Asthmatic Agents</keyword>
  <keyword>Respiratory System Agents</keyword>
  <keyword>Anti-Allergic Agents</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Esophagitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Eosinophilic Esophagitis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Fluticasone</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

