<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04287023</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>UniversitateaMFHCluj</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04287023</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effects of Physical Therapy on Gait Parameters in Patients With Parkinson Disease</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effects of Physical Therapy on Gait Parameters in Patients With Parkinson Disease</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Iuliu Hatieganu University of Medicine and Pharmacy</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Iuliu Hatieganu University of Medicine and Pharmacy</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Parkinson disease is a progressive neurologic disorder characterized by motor impairments
      which alter the walking capacity, and lead to reduced walking speed, decreased stride length
      and increased double support time. Physical therapy interventions are an important part of
      the non-pharmacological treatment for Parkinson disease. The purpose of this study is to
      assess whether there is a different outcome regarding improvement of gait parameters, when
      applying a physical therapy program in an individual or in a group manner.

      The study setting is the Clinical Rehabilitation Hospital in Cluj-Napoca, Cluj county,
      Romania. Patients will be randomly divided into 2 groups, and were prescribed either
      individual (1 patient and 1 physical therapist) or group physical therapy (6 patients and 1
      physical therapist). Treatment protocol includes 10 sessions of physical therapy, in the same
      room setting and performed the same routine of exercises, except for the 3 breaks during the
      sessions in the group therapy for informal socialization. Walking speed will be measured by
      two validated instruments, the 6-minute walk test and the 10-meter walk test, before and
      after treatment.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The rehabilitation protocol for the individual physical therapy will consist of
      cardiovascular warm-up activities, stretching exercises, strengthening exercises, functional,
      gait and balance training, recreational games and ended with relaxation exercises. In
      addition, the group protocol will follow the exact same pattern, except for 5-10 minute
      breaks for informal socialization between participants, at the beginning of the session,
      mid-session and at the end of the session.

      Also, both groups will have access to external cues, which will be applied during a variety
      of tasks and environmental situations, like gait initiation and termination, heel strike and
      push-off, sideways and backwards stepping, walking while dual tasking, and walking over
      various surfaces and long distances.

      All patients will be evaluated at the beginning and at the end of the physical therapy
      program. The evaluation includes the 6-minute walking test and the 10-meter walking test.
      Gait speed for each participant will be calculated as the ratio between the walked distance
      and the time unit, and it was measured in meters/seconds.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">March 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in walking speed</measure>
    <time_frame>at baseline and after 10 days</time_frame>
    <description>meters/seconds - the 6 minute walk test and 10 meter walk test</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Parkinson Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group Physical therapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>1 physical therapists and groups of 10 patients during the sessions</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Individual physical therapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>1 physical therapist and 1 patient during the sessions</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>individual physical therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>cardiovascular warm-up activities, stretching exercises, strengthening exercises, functional, gait and balance training, recreational games and ended with relaxation exercises - individual</description>
    <arm_group_label>Individual physical therapy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>group physical therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>cardiovascular warm-up activities, stretching exercises, strengthening exercises, functional, gait and balance training, recreational games and ended with relaxation exercises - groups of 10 patients</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group Physical therapy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  stable medication usage;

          -  Hoehn and Yahr stage 2, 3 or 4;

          -  ability to walk independently or by using an assistive walking device;

          -  no severe cognitive impairments (Mini-Mental State Examination - MMSE score, ≥24);

          -  no other severe neurologic, cardiopulmonary or orthopedic disorders;

          -  not having participated in a PT or rehabilitation program in the previous 2 months.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  not stable medication usage;

          -  Hoehn and Yahr stage 1;

          -  inability to walk independently or by using an assistive walking device;

          -  severe cognitive impairments (Mini-Mental State Examination - MMSE score, below 24);

          -  other severe neurologic, cardiopulmonary or orthopedic disorders;

          -  having participated in a PT or rehabilitation program in the previous 2 months.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Viorela Ciortea, MD,PhD</last_name>
    <email>viorela.ciortea@yahoo.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Laszlo Irsay, MD,PhD</last_name>
    <phone>004 0264 70 20 21</phone>
    <phone_ext>160</phone_ext>
    <email>irsaylaszlo@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <verification_date>February 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 25, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 25, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 27, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 25, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 25, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 27, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Iuliu Hatieganu University of Medicine and Pharmacy</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Viorela Mihaela Ciortea</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>MD, PhD</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Parkinson Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>upon request</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

