<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04281316</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>38R19.250</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04281316</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>High-Flow in Hypercapnic Stable COPD Patients</brief_title>
  <acronym>HIGH-FLOW</acronym>
  <official_title>Impact of Nasal High Flow (NHF) Versus Home Non-invasive Ventilation (NIV) on Nocturnal Transcutaneous PCO2 (PtCO2) in Stable COPD Patients: A Non-inferiority Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University Hospital, Grenoble</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Icadom</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Fisher and Paykel Healthcare</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University Hospital, Grenoble</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Monocentric, prospective, open, randomized 1:1, controlled study to evaluate the impact of
      nasal high-flow (NHF) on nocturnal transcutaneous PCO2 (PtCO2) compared to non-invasive
      ventilation ± Long-Term Oxygen Therapy (LTOT) in patients with a Chronic obstructive
      pulmonary disease (COPD)-related hypercapnic respiratory failure.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD) is a growing global health concern, causing
      considerable health-related costs and increased mortality. COPD is nowadays considered a
      complex, heterogeneous and systemic condition.

      In the late stage of the disease, non-invasive ventilation (NIV) is widely prescribed either
      to treat acute hypercapnic respiratory failure during COPD exacerbations or for long term
      home management.

      A meta-analysis has shown that higher daytime PaCO2 occurred in home NIV treated COPD
      patients when NIV compliance is less than 5 h/day. Thus, an optimal NIV adherence is a key
      target for controlling nocturnal and diurnal hypoventilation and improving prognosis.

      COPD is the clinical scenario during which a good NIV adherence is difficult to achieve.
      Particularly, in COPDs exhibiting hyperinflation, NIV can aggravate dynamic hyperinflation
      resulting in unrewarded inspiratory efforts, poor sleep and low NIV compliance. Alternatives
      to NIV are then desirable in this specific subgroup of hypercapnic COPD with poor adherence
      to NIV.

      During this trial, stable COPD patients treated by long term home Non-Invasive Ventilation
      (NIV) treatment following French national recommendations and exhibiting a NIV compliance of
      (less than 5 hours and more than 1 hour) per day in the last 3 months prior to inclusion will
      be randomized via a secure electronic website to either continue with their current NIV
      treatment or receive the nasal high flow (NHF) treatment delivered by myAirvo2 during 3
      months Nasal High-Flow (NHF) is a treatment delivering heated, humidified, and optionally
      oxygen-enriched air at high flow rates through a nasal cannula. The main physiologic effects
      of NHF are an improvement in gas exchanges including a reduction in hypercapnia, an
      optimization in breathing patterns with a reduction of work of breathing. Nasal High-Flow
      (NHF) is delivered via a comfortable nasal interface and has demonstrated good treatment
      adherence.

      The investigators hypothesize that in COPD-related hypercapnic chronic respiratory failure
      with limited compliance to NIV (less than 5 hours per night), nasal High-Flow (NHF) will be
      non-inferior for controlling nocturnal hypoventilation and might improve daytime subjective
      patients centered outcomes, physical activity and nocturnal adherence to treatment.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">April 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes on nocturnal parameters with the nasal high-flow (NHF) compared to non-invasive ventilation in patients with a COPD-related hypercapnic respiratory failure.</measure>
    <time_frame>between night at day 1 (baseline) and night at day 90 (3 months after)</time_frame>
    <description>Differences in mean overnight transcutaneous PtCO2 measurement</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluation the impact of nasal high-flow (NHF) on other nocturnal parameters compared to non-invasive ventilation ± LTOT compared to non-invasive ventilation in patients with a COPD-related hypercapnic respiratory failure.</measure>
    <time_frame>between night at day 1 (baseline) and night at day 90 (3 months after)</time_frame>
    <description>Maximum PtCO2</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Treatment adherence</measure>
    <time_frame>between night at day 1 (baseline) and night at day 90 (3 months after)</time_frame>
    <description>Treatment adherence measured objectively by download of NIV software data and for NHF (myAirvo2) by hour meter &amp; daily average of usage (screen display)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Daytime blood gas values in ambient air</measure>
    <time_frame>between day 0 (inclusion) and day 97 (end of the study)</time_frame>
    <description>PaCO2 &amp; PaO2 in ambient air will be measured by blood gas sample in NHF group compared de NIV group</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Other nocturnal parameter</measure>
    <time_frame>between night at day 1 (baseline) and night at day 90 (3 months after)</time_frame>
    <description>Overnight Sp02 will be evaluated by nocturnal oximetry at home in order to determine: mean nocturnal SaO2, nadir nocturnal SaO2, cumulative time spent below 90% of SaO2 (CT&lt;90%), Oxygen Desaturation Index.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Physical activity</measure>
    <time_frame>for 7 days from the day 1 and for 7 days from the day 90</time_frame>
    <description>An actimetry will allow evaluating physical activity (number of steps)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Sleep activity</measure>
    <time_frame>between night at day 1 (baseline) and night at day 90 (3 months after)</time_frame>
    <description>An actimetry will allow evaluating total sleep time in minutes</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Sleep activity</measure>
    <time_frame>between night at day 1 (baseline) and night at day 90 (3 months after)</time_frame>
    <description>An actimetry will allow evaluating sleep onset latency in minutes</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Sleep activity</measure>
    <time_frame>between night at day 1 (baseline) and night at day 90 (3 months after)</time_frame>
    <description>An actimetry will allow evaluating sleep efficiency</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pulmonary function tests</measure>
    <time_frame>between day 0 and day 97</time_frame>
    <description>Pulmonary function will be evaluated by routine patient care spirometry and will measure Vital capacity (VC) in liters</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pulmonary function tests</measure>
    <time_frame>between day 0 and day 97</time_frame>
    <description>Pulmonary function will be evaluated by routine patient care spirometry and will measure Forced vital capacity (FVC) in liters</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pulmonary function tests</measure>
    <time_frame>between day 0 and day 97</time_frame>
    <description>Pulmonary function will be evaluated by routine patient care spirometry and will measure Forced expiratory volume (FEV) in liters</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Health related quality of life</measure>
    <time_frame>between day 0 and day 97</time_frame>
    <description>Subjective functioning and quality of life will be measured by self-reporting questionnaire EQ-5D-5L</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Health related quality of life</measure>
    <time_frame>between day 0 and day 97</time_frame>
    <description>Subjective functioning and quality of life will be measured by self-reporting questionnaire SGRQ</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cardiovasculary function</measure>
    <time_frame>between day 0 and day 97</time_frame>
    <description>Blood pressure measurements will be done three times during rest at five minutes intervals to provide informations on systolic, diastolic and mean blood pressure</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with adverse events will be assessed in each group by interrogating patients in order to assess the safety of nasal high-flow (NHF) treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>between day 0 and day 97</time_frame>
    <description>All safety data will be recorded through an Electronic Medical Record as reported by the patient or recorded by the research nurse</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">36</enrollment>
  <condition>Adherence, Treatment</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Non Invasive Ventilation device group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The patients in the NIV arm will receive treatment as in their usual care with an additional educational session of one hour for improving compliance.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Nasal High Flow (MyAirvo) device group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The patients in the NHF arm will receive NHF treatment and two hours training adaptation session will be conducted in the hospital.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Nasal High Flow installation</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants randomized in NHF group will receive the nasal high flow (NHF) treatment delivered by myAirvo2.
Nasal High-Flow (NHF) is a treatment delivering heated, humidified, and optionally oxygen-enriched, air at high flow rates through a nasal cannula. The physiologic effects of NHF are an improvement in gas exchanges including a reduction in hypercarbia an optimization in breathing patterns with a reduction of work of breathing and high compliance as delivered via a comfortable nasal interface</description>
    <arm_group_label>Nasal High Flow (MyAirvo) device group</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>MyAirvo Device</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Non Invasive Ventilation</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants randomized in the Non Invasive Ventilation group will receive treatment as in their usual care.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Non Invasive Ventilation device group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Training session</intervention_name>
    <description>The patients in the Nasal High Flow (MyAirvo) arm will receive two hours training adaptation session in the hospital</description>
    <arm_group_label>Nasal High Flow (MyAirvo) device group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Education session</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants randomized in the Non Invasive Ventilation group will receive an additional educational session of one hour for improving compliance.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Non Invasive Ventilation device group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Diagnosed with COPD (FEV1/FVC &lt; 70%) and long term indication for home NIV for
             initiated at least 3 months prior the inclusion.

          -  Compliance with NIV (less than 5 hours and more than 1 hour) per night on average
             during the last 3 months prior to inclusion.

          -  Naïve to Nasal High Flow (NHF) therapy, i.e. having not used NHF in the last 6 months
             prior to inclusion.

          -  Able to understand, follow objectives and methods of protocol in French language.

          -  Patient affiliated to social security insurance or beneficiary of social health
             insurance.

          -  Willing and able to give written Informed Consent and to comply with the requirements
             of the study protocol.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Significant uncontrolled cardiac disease (investigator judgment), and/or Left
             Ventricular Ejection Fraction (LVEF) &lt; 45%.

          -  Known co-existing obstructive sleep apnea requiring expiratory pressure above 6 cmH20.

          -  Severe nasal obstruction, previous upper airway surgery preventing the usage of NHF,
             or, at the discretion of investigator, any other contraindication for using the NHF.

          -  Patients who are unable or unwilling to give informed consent.

          -  Participating in another research study.

          -  Patient protected by the Law, under guardianship or curators.

          -  Pregnancy and nursing mothers

          -  Patient not covered by a health insurance.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jean-Louis Pépin, MD PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Laboratoire EFCR, CHU de Grenoble</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Jean-Louis Pépin, MD PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+33 476 768 473</phone>
    <email>JPepin@chu-grenoble.fr</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Céline Barra</last_name>
    <phone>+33 476 76 82 50</phone>
    <email>CBarra@chu-grenoble.fr</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <reference>
    <citation>Biener AI, Decker SL, Rohde F. Prevalence and Treatment of Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease (COPD) in the United States. JAMA. 2019 Aug 20;322(7):602. doi: 10.1001/jama.2019.10241.</citation>
    <PMID>31429884</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Riley CM, Sciurba FC. Diagnosis and Outpatient Management of Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease: A Review. JAMA. 2019 Feb 26;321(8):786-797. doi: 10.1001/jama.2019.0131. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>30806700</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Houben-Wilke S, Augustin IM, Vercoulen JH, van Ranst D, Bij de Vaate E, Wempe JB, Spruit MA, Wouters EFM, Franssen FME. COPD stands for complex obstructive pulmonary disease. Eur Respir Rev. 2018 Jun 6;27(148). pii: 180027. doi: 10.1183/16000617.0027-2018. Print 2018 Jun 30. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>29875138</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Suh ES, Murphy PB, Hart N. Home mechanical ventilation for chronic obstructive pulmonary disease: What next after the HOT-HMV trial? Respirology. 2019 Aug;24(8):732-739. doi: 10.1111/resp.13484. Epub 2019 Feb 7. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>30729638</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Crimi C, Noto A, Princi P, Cuvelier A, Masa JF, Simonds A, Elliott MW, Wijkstra P, Windisch W, Nava S. Domiciliary Non-invasive Ventilation in COPD: An International Survey of Indications and Practices. COPD. 2016 Aug;13(4):483-90. doi: 10.3109/15412555.2015.1108960. Epub 2016 Jan 8.</citation>
    <PMID>26744042</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Köhnlein T, Windisch W, Wegscheider K, Welte T. Non-invasive positive pressure ventilation for severe COPD--Authors' reply. Lancet Respir Med. 2014 Oct;2(10):e19. doi: 10.1016/S2213-2600(14)70215-2.</citation>
    <PMID>25298063</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Murphy AM, Thomas A, Crinion SJ, Kent BD, Tambuwala MM, Fabre A, Pepin JL, Roche HM, Arnaud C, Ryan S. Intermittent hypoxia in obstructive sleep apnoea mediates insulin resistance through adipose tissue inflammation. Eur Respir J. 2017 Apr 19;49(4). pii: 1601731. doi: 10.1183/13993003.01731-2016. Print 2017 Apr.</citation>
    <PMID>28424360</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Vanfleteren LEGW, Spruit MA, Wouters EFM, Franssen FME. Management of chronic obstructive pulmonary disease beyond the lungs. Lancet Respir Med. 2016 Nov;4(11):911-924. doi: 10.1016/S2213-2600(16)00097-7. Epub 2016 Jun 2. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>27264777</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Borel JC, Pepin JL, Pison C, Vesin A, Gonzalez-Bermejo J, Court-Fortune I, Timsit JF. Long-term adherence with non-invasive ventilation improves prognosis in obese COPD patients. Respirology. 2014 Aug;19(6):857-65. doi: 10.1111/resp.12327. Epub 2014 Jun 9.</citation>
    <PMID>24912564</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Struik FM, Lacasse Y, Goldstein RS, Kerstjens HA, Wijkstra PJ. Nocturnal noninvasive positive pressure ventilation in stable COPD: a systematic review and individual patient data meta-analysis. Respir Med. 2014 Feb;108(2):329-37. doi: 10.1016/j.rmed.2013.10.007. Epub 2013 Oct 14. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24157199</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 11, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 19, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 24, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 19, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 19, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 24, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>non-compliance</keyword>
  <keyword>NIV</keyword>
  <keyword>NHF</keyword>
  <keyword>COPD</keyword>
  <keyword>hypercapnic respiratory failure</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

