<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04281966</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2019002851</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04281966</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Testing the Efficacy of the Ability School Engagement Partnership Program (ASEP)</brief_title>
  <acronym>ASEP</acronym>
  <official_title>Testing the Efficacy of the Ability School Engagement Partnership Program (ASEP)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>The University of Queensland</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Restorative Outcomes Australia</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Department of Education, Queensland</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Queensland Police Service</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Australian Department of Social Services</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>The University of Queensland</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This project is an up-scaled test of the Ability School Engagement Partnership (ASEP)
      Project. The ASEP is a partnership program that aims to increase school attendance and is
      grounded in the theory of Third-Party-Policing (TPP). In ASEP, school-based police officers
      partner with schools (i.e., the third-party) who have legal powers to control and prevent
      school absenteeism. The ASEP intervention includes an ASEP conference in which the legal
      requirements to attend school are explicitly communicated in a procedurally just way to young
      people missing school and their parents/guardians. Restorative Outcomes Australia (ROA) is a
      provide provider partner who will oversee the facilitation of the ASEP conferences. While the
      program is designed to re-engage these young people in school and/or facilitate transitions
      to work and reduce antisocial behavior (e.g., delinquency), this trial will also test the
      capacity of the program to improve collaboration between the schools and police and also
      monitor young participants' future life outcomes, such as future welfare dependence.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The ASEP is grounded in the theory of Third Party Policing (TPP). TPP interventions focus on
      controlling negative behavioral outcomes through partnerships that use a third party's legal
      powers. In ASEP, the police partner with the schools to work together to engage with young
      people, reduce their anti-social behavior and increase their school attendance. At the core
      of the partnership is communication of the legal lever: in ASEP, it is the Queensland
      Education (General Provisions) Act (2006) - requiring young people attend school up to age 16
      and holding parents legally responsible. The laws are communicated to parents and young
      people who are not regularly attending school in a procedurally fair way within the context
      of an ASEP conference. The ASEP conference is especially designed to incorporate fair
      communication of the laws and consequences and involves a purpose-built script that seeks to
      increase willingness of both parents and young people to comply with the law. The ASEP
      conference participants include a trained facilitator (from Restorative Outcomes Australia;
      ROA), the young person missing a lot of school, their parent or guardian, a uniformed
      school-based police officer, and a school representative (e.g., teacher). An individually
      tailored Action Plan is developed during the conference which stipulate the &quot;actions&quot; that
      all conference participants are to take over the subsequent two months in order to ensure
      that the young person increases their school attendance and re-engages with school and/or
      transitions into paid work.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 21, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 30, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 30, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>The current project utilizes a randomized controlled cluster trial to assess the efficacy of the ASEP intervention and thereby theoretically test the efficacy of third-party-policing. Data will be collected from high schools that are in either socially disadvantaged areas or have students who reside in socially disadvantaged areas. A total of 69 high schools were identified as eligible for the Trial based upon measures of social disadvantage. The 69 eligible high schools were randomly assigned to participate in the ASEP (experiment) or business-as-usual (control) conditions. Young people from schools who take part in the ASEP (experiment) will be recruited from the experimental schools. Official data will be obtained about the young people (identified for those in the experimental condition who consent; de-identified for the young people in the control schools).</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Official School Absences</measure>
    <time_frame>Six-Months Post-Intervention</time_frame>
    <description>A count of the number of school absences of young people.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Official Arrest Records</measure>
    <time_frame>Six-Months Post Intervention</time_frame>
    <description>A count of official arrest records of young people.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Perceptions of School Legitimacy</measure>
    <time_frame>Two-months post intervention</time_frame>
    <description>These measures are adapted from the original ASEP Project Trial (Mazerolle, 2014). The original ASEP researchers adapted these scales from Murphy and Mearns (2008), Sunshine and Tyler (2003), and Tankebe (2009). These indices include five items that address respondents' (young people and parents/guardians in the experimental group only) perceptions of legitimacy of school staff with higher values equating to better perceptions of school staff legitimacy.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Perceptions of School Procedural Justice</measure>
    <time_frame>Two-months post intervention</time_frame>
    <description>These measures are adapted from the original ASEP Project Trial (Mazerolle, 2014). The original ASEP researchers adapted these scales from Murphy and Mearns (2008), Sunshine and Tyler (2003), and Tankebe (2009). These indices include five items that address respondents' (young people and parents/guardians in the experimental group only) perceptions of procedural justice of school staff with higher values equating to better perceptions of school staff procedural justice.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Perceptions of Police Legitimacy</measure>
    <time_frame>Two-months post intervention</time_frame>
    <description>These measures are adapted from the original ASEP Project Trial (Mazerolle, 2014). The original ASEP researchers adapted these scales from Murphy and Mearns (2008), Sunshine and Tyler (2003), and Tankebe (2009). These indices include five items that address respondents' (young people and parents/guardians in the experimental group only) perceptions of legitimacy of police in general with higher values equating to better perceptions of police legitimacy.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Perceptions of Police Procedural Justice</measure>
    <time_frame>Two-months post intervention</time_frame>
    <description>These measures are adapted from the original ASEP Project Trial (Mazerolle, 2014). The original ASEP researchers adapted these scales from Murphy and Mearns (2008), Sunshine and Tyler (2003), and Tankebe (2009). These indices include five items that address respondents' (young people and parents/guardians in the experimental group only) perceptions of procedural justice of police in general.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Perceptions of Family Legitimacy</measure>
    <time_frame>Two-months post intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Adapted from the work of Trinkner, 2012; Trinkner et al., 2012; Trinker &amp; Cohn, 2014. Measures respondents' (young people and parents/guardians in the experimental group only) perceptions of family legitimacy with higher values equating to better perceptions of family legitimacy.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Perceptions of Family Procedural Justice</measure>
    <time_frame>Two-months post intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Adapted from the work of Trinkner, 2012; Trinkner et al., 2012; Trinker &amp; Cohn, 2014. Measures respondents' (young people and parents/guardians in the experimental group only) perceptions of family procedural justice with higher values equating to better perceptions of family legitimacy.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>General Well-being</measure>
    <time_frame>Two-months post intervention</time_frame>
    <description>The Short Warwick-Edinburgh Mental Well-being Scale (SWEMWBS; Haver et al., 2015; Stewart-Brown et al., 2009; Taggart et al., 2015; Tennant et al., 2007) to be administered to young people and parents in the experimental condition only. It includes 7 items, scores range from 7 to 35, and higher scores coincide with better well-being.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Self-efficacy</measure>
    <time_frame>Two-months post intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Includes 12 items from the Coping Orientation to Problems Experienced (COPE) Inventory (Carver et al., 1989; Carver, 1997) to be administered to young people and parents in the experimental condition only. Scores will range from 12 to 48 and coded so that higher values equate to better coping skills.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">753</enrollment>
  <condition>School Attendance</condition>
  <condition>Welfare Dependence</condition>
  <condition>Antisocial Behavior</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Experiment</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>For young people from schools randomly assigned to the experimental ASEP condition will participate in the ASEP intervention. The ASEP intervention is a Third-Party Policing partnership that involves a partnership between police and school, an ASEP conference and follow up which is organized and led by a conference facilitator with the young person, their parent (or guardian), a school representative (e.g., teacher), and a uniformed school-based police officer. The police and school representatives will be trained by the facilitator to utilize procedurally just dialogue during the entirety of the conference. The ASEP conference script will utilize a procedurally just dialogue to increase both the young person and their parents' perceptions and knowledge of the legitimacy of the truancy laws, police, and schools in order to gain willing compliance to follow the rules.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants allocated to the control condition will be given the &quot;business-as-usual' approach to handling school non-attendance. The control participants will be sanctioned in the usual manner for engaging in truancy through the requirements denoted in the Queensland Education (General Provisions) Act (2006).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ability School Engagement Program Conference</intervention_name>
    <description>The ASEP conference focuses on understanding the reasons behind why the young person is not attending school regularly, understand how the young person's non-attendance affects other conference participants, highlight the legal consequences of parents and/or guardians to ensure that their child attends school, and the development of a young person-centered Action Plan, which will specifically detail the &quot;actions&quot; that all parties are to take over the next three months to ensure that the young person re-engages with school and/or transitions into paid work.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Experiment</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  High school aged young people only, aged 12 to 16;

          -  Have 15% or more unexplained absences over each other previous two school terms;

          -  Have no known legitimate explanation for absences (e.g., ongoing medical issue); and

          -  Have at least one responsibly adult in their lives (e.g., parent, guardian, or carer)
             who provides social and/or financial support.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  None
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>12 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>16 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Lorraine Mazerolle, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>The University of Queensland</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Sarah Bennett, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>The University of Queensland</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Stephanie Cardwell, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>The University of Queensland</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Lorraine Mazerolle, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <phone>+61 7 334 67877</phone>
    <email>l.mazerolle@uq.edu.au</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The University of Queensland</name>
      <address>
        <city>Brisbane</city>
        <state>Queensland</state>
        <zip>4072</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Lorraine Mazerolle, Ph.D.</last_name>
      <phone>+61 7 334 67877</phone>
      <email>l.mazerolle@uq.edu.au</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Lorraine Mazerolle, Ph.D.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Sarah Bennett, Ph.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Stephanie M Cardwell, Ph.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Australia</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://www.crimesolutions.gov/ProgramDetails.aspx?ID=580</url>
    <description>Crime Solutions: Ability School Engagement Program</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Antrobus, E., Bennett, S., Mazerolle, L., &amp; Eggins, E. (2019). Parental and student perceptions of procedural justice and legitimacy in the context of truancy: Results from a randomized field trial. Australian &amp; New Zealand Journal of Criminology, 52(4), 534-557.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bennett, S., Mazerolle, L., Antrobus, E., Eggins, E., &amp; Piquero, A. R. (2018). Truancy intervention reduces crime: Results from a randomized field trial. Justice Quarterly, 35(2), 309-329.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cardwell, S. M., Mazerolle, L., &amp; Piquero, A. R. (2019). Parental attachment and truant rationalizations of antisocial behavior: findings from a randomized controlled trial. Journal of Crime and Justice, 1-19.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cardwell, S. M., Mazerolle, L., &amp; Piquero, A. R. (2019). Truancy intervention and violent offending: Evidence from a randomized controlled trial. Aggression and Violent Behavior, 49.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cardwell, S. M., Mazerolle, L., Bennett, S., &amp; Piquero, A. R. (2019). Changing the relationship between impulsivity and antisocial behavior: the impact of a school engagement program. Crime &amp; Delinquency, 65(8), 1076-1101.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Carver CS, Scheier MF, Weintraub JK. Assessing coping strategies: a theoretically based approach. J Pers Soc Psychol. 1989 Feb;56(2):267-83.</citation>
    <PMID>2926629</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cohn, E. S., Trinkner, R. J., Rebellon, C. J., Van Gundy, K. T., &amp; Cole, L. M. (2012). Legal attitudes and legitimacy: Extending the integrated legal socialization model. Victims &amp; Offenders, 7(4), 385-406.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mazerolle, L. (2014). The power of policing partnerships: Sustaining the gains. Journal of Experimental Criminology, 10(3), 341-365.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mazerolle L, Antrobus E, Bennett S, Eggins E. Reducing Truancy and Fostering a Willingness to Attend School: Results from a Randomized Trial of a Police-School Partnership Program. Prev Sci. 2017 May;18(4):469-480. doi: 10.1007/s11121-017-0771-7.</citation>
    <PMID>28317075</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mazerolle, L., Antrobus, E., Cardwell, S. M., Piquero, A. R., &amp; Bennett, S. (2019). Harmonizing legal socialization to reduce antisocial behavior: Results from a randomized field trial of truanting young people. Justice Quarterly, 1-28.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mazerolle, L., Bennett, S., Antrobus, E., Cardwell, S. M., Eggins, E., &amp; Piquero, A. R. (2019). Disrupting the pathway from truancy to delinquency: a randomized field trial test of the longitudinal impact of a school engagement program. Journal of Quantitative Criminology, 35(4), 663-689.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Murphy, K., &amp; Mearns, M. (2008). The Public Safety and Security in Australia Survey: Survey methodology and preliminary findings. ARC Centre for Excellence in Policing and Security (Working Paper, October 2008). The Australian National University.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sunshine, J., &amp; Tyler, T. R. (2003). The role of procedural justice and legitimacy in shaping public support for policing. Law &amp; Society Review, 37(3), 513-548.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tankebe, J. (2009). Public cooperation with the police in Ghana: Does procedural fairness matter? Criminology, 47(4), 1265-1293.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tennant R, Hiller L, Fishwick R, Platt S, Joseph S, Weich S, Parkinson J, Secker J, Stewart-Brown S. The Warwick-Edinburgh Mental Well-being Scale (WEMWBS): development and UK validation. Health Qual Life Outcomes. 2007 Nov 27;5:63.</citation>
    <PMID>18042300</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Trinkner, R. (2012). Testing the procedural justice model of legal socialization: Expanding beyond the legal world. (Doctoral dissertation). University of New Hampshire, Durham, New Hampshire.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Trinkner R, Cohn ES, Rebellon CJ, Van Gundy K. Don't trust anyone over 30: parental legitimacy as a mediator between parenting style and changes in delinquent behavior over time. J Adolesc. 2012 Feb;35(1):119-32. doi: 10.1016/j.adolescence.2011.05.003. Epub 2011 Jun 12.</citation>
    <PMID>21669454</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Trinkner R, Cohn ES. Putting the &quot;social&quot; back in legal socialization: procedural justice, legitimacy, and cynicism in legal and nonlegal authorities. Law Hum Behav. 2014 Dec;38(6):602-17. doi: 10.1037/lhb0000107. Epub 2014 Sep 22.</citation>
    <PMID>25243981</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Carver CS. You want to measure coping but your protocol's too long: consider the brief COPE. Int J Behav Med. 1997;4(1):92-100.</citation>
    <PMID>16250744</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Haver A, Akerjordet K, Caputi P, Furunes T, Magee C. Measuring mental well-being: A validation of the Short Warwick-Edinburgh Mental Well-Being Scale in Norwegian and Swedish. Scand J Public Health. 2015 Nov;43(7):721-7. doi: 10.1177/1403494815588862. Epub 2015 Jun 3.</citation>
    <PMID>26041133</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Stewart-Brown S, Tennant A, Tennant R, Platt S, Parkinson J, Weich S. Internal construct validity of the Warwick-Edinburgh Mental Well-being Scale (WEMWBS): a Rasch analysis using data from the Scottish Health Education Population Survey. Health Qual Life Outcomes. 2009 Feb 19;7:15. doi: 10.1186/1477-7525-7-15.</citation>
    <PMID>19228398</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Taggart, F., Stewart-Brown, S., &amp; Parkinson, J. (2015). Warwick-Edinburgh Mental Well-being Scale (WEMWBS) User Guide, Version 2. NHS Health Scotland.</citation>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 20, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 20, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 24, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 5, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 5, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 9, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>School Attendance</keyword>
  <keyword>Welfare Dependence</keyword>
  <keyword>Antisocial Behavior</keyword>
  <keyword>Third-Party Policing Partnerships</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Antisocial Personality Disorder</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

