<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04284462</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PEP-1908</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04284462</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Liking Adaptation to Beverages of Varying Sweetness Levels After Prolonged Exposure</brief_title>
  <official_title>Liking Adaptation to Beverages of Varying Sweetness Levels After Prolonged Exposure</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>PepsiCo Global R&amp;D</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>PepsiCo Global R&amp;D</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a double-blind, controlled, parallel, randomized sensory study. The study will
      consist of two cohorts; habitual regular full-calorie Carbonated Soft Drink (CSD) consumers
      and habitual low-calorie CSD consumers. Each cohort will be randomized to one of 3
      interventions for six months (24 weeks):

        -  Intervention 1: Control (full sweetness) beverage

        -  Intervention 2: Step-wise sweetness reduction series of beverages

        -  Intervention 3: Moderate sweetness (reduced sweetness) beverage

      The primary outcome is to assess the perception changes in sweetness (magnitude scale) and
      sweetness liking (Likert scale) of a test product and a control product over a period of six
      months. The study endeavors to explore whether consumers of sweetened carbonated beverages
      can adapt liking to lower sweetness beverages after prolonged exposure of daily consumption
      of beverages with step-wise reduction of sweetness, or maintenance at reduced (moderate)
      sweetness.

      The secondary outcome will be to assess dietary compensation for sweetness in the step-wise
      and moderate reduction arms compared to the control arms (the full calorie and low calorie
      control beverages). Dietary analysis of calories and intakes of total sugar, added sugar, and
      servings of low-/non-calorie sweeteners will be assessed using a 3-day diet record
      pre-intervention and monthly for 6 months.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Sponsor decision to stop study due to COVID-19 pandemic
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 14, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 11, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 11, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>Same packaging for all (cans). Color and flavor matched.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Sweetness liking</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes over a period of 6 months, measured at monthly intervals from month 0 (baseline) to month 6</time_frame>
    <description>Likert scale, 9 point scale from 1=Dislike extremely to 9=Like extremely</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Sweetness intensity perception</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes over a period of 6 months, measured at monthly intervals from month 0 (baseline) to month 6</time_frame>
    <description>Magnitude scale ranging from Barely perceptible to Strongest imaginable sweetness</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Dietary compensation for sweetness</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed pre-intervention, then monthly x 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>3-day diet record to assess calories and intake of total sugar, added sugar, low-/non-calorie sweeteners</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Aftertaste</measure>
    <time_frame>Monthly assessments x 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Scale 1-5, 1=Very unpleasant, 5=Very pleasant</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Aftertaste description</measure>
    <time_frame>Monthly assessments x 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>12 description options (ex., sweet, tart, bitter, etc.) or other, check all that apply</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Likely to buy</measure>
    <time_frame>One assessment at end of study, month 6</time_frame>
    <description>Scale from 1-5, 1= Definitely would not buy it, to 5 Definitely would buy it</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>6</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">170</enrollment>
  <condition>Sweetness Liking Adaptation</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control beverage for Habitual full-calorie CSD cohort, n=28</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Full sweetness (sugar) for 6 months</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control beverage for Habitual low-calorie CSD cohort, n=28</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Full sweetness low calorie sweetener (LCS) with sweetness level matched to the full sweetness sugar control for 6 months</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Test beverage 1 for Habitual full-calorie CSD cohort, n=28</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Reduced sweetness (moderate sugar level) for 6 months</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Test beverage 1 for Habitual low-calorie CSD cohort, n=28</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Reduced sweetness low calorie sweetener (LCS) with sweetness level matched to the moderate sugar sweetness level for 6 months</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Test beverage 2 for Habitual full-calorie CSD cohort, n=28</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Step-wise sweetness reduction over 6 months. Month 1 is the full sweetness sugar control, followed by monthly sweetness reduction. Remains at the reduced sweetness level (moderate sugar level) from months 4-6.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Test beverage 2 for Habitual low-calorie CSD cohort, n=28</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Step-wise sweetness reduction over 6 months. Month 1 is the low calorie sweetener (LCS) sweetness equivalent of the full sweetness sugar control, followed by monthly LCS sweetness reduction (reductions equivalent to the corresponding sugar reduction arm sweetness levels). Remains at the reduced sweetness level (LCS equivalent of moderate sugar sweetness level) from months 4-6.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Flavored carbonated soft drink (CSD)</intervention_name>
    <description>1-2 cans/day (330 ml per can)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control beverage for Habitual full-calorie CSD cohort, n=28</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Control beverage for Habitual low-calorie CSD cohort, n=28</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Test beverage 1 for Habitual full-calorie CSD cohort, n=28</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Test beverage 1 for Habitual low-calorie CSD cohort, n=28</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Test beverage 2 for Habitual full-calorie CSD cohort, n=28</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Test beverage 2 for Habitual low-calorie CSD cohort, n=28</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Healthy adults 25-55 years of age

          2. Habitually consume regular or diet carbonated soft drinks (CSD)

          3. Willing and able to consume at least one CSD beverage daily for a total of 6 months
             and abstain from other sweetened beverages

          4. Willing and able to complete questionnaires regarding dietary intake and sensory
             perception

          5. Has internet access via computer, phone or other device and is able to maintain
             internet access throughout the trial in order to complete daily online questionnaires.

          6. Participant is judged to be in good health on the basis of medical history and the
             general health and lifestyle questionnaire.

          7. Participant is willing to maintain his or her habitual diet, smoking habits and
             physical activity patterns, including habitual use of study approved medications
             and/or dietary supplements throughout the study period.

          8. Participant understands the study procedures and signs forms providing informed
             consent to participate in the study and authorization for release of relevant
             protected health information to the study Investigators.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Regular smoker (more than 1 cigarette per week)

          2. History or presence of clinically important endocrine (including type 1 or 2 diabetes
             mellitus), cardiovascular, pulmonary, biliary, renal, hepatic, pancreatic, or
             neurologic disorders that, in the opinion of the Clinical Investigator, could
             interfere with the interpretation of the study results.

          3. Extreme dietary habits, including but not limited to vegetarian diets and intentional
             consumption of a high fiber diet, gluten-free, low-carb, vegan, ketogenic.

          4. Extreme changes to physical activity

          5. Females who are pregnant, planning to be pregnant during the study period, lactating,
             or of childbearing potential and unwilling to commit to the use of a medically
             approved form of contraception throughout the study period.

          6. Recent history (within 12 months of screening; Visit 1) of alcohol or substance abuse.
             Alcohol abuse is defined as &gt;14 drinks per week (1 drink = 12 oz beer, 5 oz wine, or
             1½ oz distilled spirits).

          7. Individual has a condition the Clinical Investigator believes would interfere with his
             or her ability to provide informed consent, comply with the study protocol, or which
             might confound the interpretation of the study results or put the participant at undue
             risk.

          8. Dislike of study product taste

          9. Participation in another clinical trial within past 30 days and participation in a
             PepsiCo clinical trial in the past 6 months.

         10. People who have phenylketonuria (low calorie sweetened beverages contain aspartame)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>25 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>55 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Kathleen Kelley, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Biofortis Innovation Services</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>BioFortis Innovation Services</name>
      <address>
        <city>Addison</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60101</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 19, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 21, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 25, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 11, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 11, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 16, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>sweetness</keyword>
  <keyword>liking</keyword>
  <keyword>adaptation</keyword>
  <keyword>intensity</keyword>
  <keyword>low calorie sweetener</keyword>
  <keyword>full sugar</keyword>
  <keyword>carbonated soft drink</keyword>
  <keyword>sensory</keyword>
  <keyword>taste</keyword>
  <keyword>dietary compensation</keyword>
  <keyword>beverage</keyword>
  <keyword>perception</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

