<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04283604</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>0007-19-LOE</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04283604</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Effects of a Single Dose of Methylphenidate on Motor Performance</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Effects of a Single Dose of Methylphenidate on Motor Performance</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Loewenstein Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Tel Aviv University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Wingate Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Loewenstein Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>Yes</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Aim: To evaluate the effects of MPH on young adults diagnosed with ADHD on different exercise
      performance tests.

      Hypothesis: MPH will have positive effects on motor tests requiring concentration.

      Methods: 200 healthy physical education students, 100 participants diagnosed with ADHD will
      serve as the treatment group and 100 non-ADHD diagnosed will serve as a control group. The
      study will be divided into two sub studies (100 participants each), in which, two motor tests
      will be evaluated (two agility tests and two motor accuracy tests).

      All participants will arrive for two sessions, and will perform two motor tests in each
      session. In the second session, half of the participants with ADHD (25 participants) will
      undergo another session of the same motor tests with their usual treatment (treatment group)
      and another half (25 participants) without their treatment (ADHD control group). The non-ADHD
      control group (50 participants) will perform the second session without medications - to
      assess a learning effect.

      Note, we are not planning on giving the medication to the participant, rather he/she will
      consume their own prescribed MPH by them self. Control treatment for ADHD participants will
      consist of not taking their medication before the motor test.

      For evaluation of physiological responses and perception of effort we will measure heart
      rate, temperature, blood pressure and RPE before and after motor tests.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Aim of study To evaluate the effects of MPH on young adults diagnosed with ADHD on different
      exercise performance tests.

      Hypothesis: Methylphenidate (MPH) will have positive effects on motor tests requiring
      concentration.

      Methods Participants 200 healthy physical education students from the Academic college at
      Wingate, males and females, will be recruited to the study. 100 participants diagnosed with
      ADHD will serve as the treatment group and 100 non-ADHD diagnosed will serve as a control
      group.

      Procedure Recruitment procedure will consist of emails to all students in college. Volunteers
      answering the mail will be regarded as giving consent to be addressed by the research
      assistant by a phone call. A research assistant will call volunteers and will briefly explain
      the study procedures and invite them for two sessions. ADHD volunteers will kindly be asked
      to arrive to the first session before taking their medication. They will be instructed to
      take by themselves their medication, if needed, after they finished the session.

      The study will be divided into two sub studies (100 participants each), in which, two motor
      tests will be evaluated (two agility tests and two motor accuracy tests). The division was
      meant to attenuate fatigue resulted from multiple motor tests at the same session. The
      students will be recruited for the two sub -studies but may choose to participate in only one
      part. In each sub-study, the participant will attend two sessions, about sixty minutes each,
      at least one week apart between them.

      In the first session, participants will sign an informed consent form approved by the
      institutional review board (Helsinki). Next, all participants will fill a general background
      questionnaire and an ADHD self-report scale questionnaire. Then, participants will perform
      the motor tests. After the first session, half of the participants with ADHD will undergo
      another session of the same motor tests with their usual treatment (treatment group) or
      without their treatment (ADHD control group). We point out that the patient takes his own
      treatment himself when assigned to the ADHD treatment group. The assignment to the treatment
      group or to the control group will be randomly decided, and will consist of 25 participants
      in each group. The non-ADHD control group (50 participants) will perform the second session
      without medications - to assess a learning effect. The participants will be able to choose to
      participate in the next sub-studies or not.

      Treatment The treatment will include taking the patient's own medication by the patient
      himself in the treatment session 60-180 minutes before the beginning of the tests, according
      to their prescription given by their own physician. Participants must have consumed this
      medication at least 3 months before the first session as their regular treatment for ADHD.
      Note, we are not planning on giving the medication to the participant, rather he/she will
      consume their own prescribed MPH by themselves.

      Control treatment for ADHD participants will consist of not taking their medication before
      the motor test. Since there may be participant who needs to take the medication every day,
      they will be instructed to consume their medication at the end of the session. In this case,
      session meeting will be performed at morning time.

      Motor tests Sub-study 1 Agility tests Two agility tests will be performed. The best time of
      each test will be recorded. Calculation of the ratio of zigzag test without the ball and with
      the ball will be conducted on a sports hall. These two agility tests were evaluated and
      validated elsewhere.

      Zigzag test- Running agility test. Participant is required to run a course in the shortest
      possible time. A zigzag course consists of a rectangle 3 X 5 meters set out at 100º angles by
      four cones placed on the corners, with one more cone placed in the center (Fig 1). Overall
      there are 6 segments numbered from 1-6 according to their order in the test. This test
      measures rapid acceleration, deceleration and balance control. Zigzag with a ball- The same
      as the former test (fig 1), but with a ball. Participants will be instructed to run as fast
      as possible with the ball. This test measures rapid acceleration, deceleration and balance
      control as well as controlling the ball.

      Sub-study 2 Accuracy motor tests The stationary free throw shooting test (S1P)- Each
      participant will perform three series of ten free-throw shots (two throws in five different
      positions) with a 3-minute rest period between the series. Two participants will be
      positioned below the hoop and they will pass the ball to the testee. After the participant
      completes ten shots, another participant will come to the free throw line and will perform
      the same task. The average scores of the all three trials will be used for analysis.

      The dynamic 60-second free throw shooting test (S1P60)- For easier organization of the
      testing we will use volleyball court lines as illustrated in Figure 1. Each participant will
      perform five series of two free throws with sprinting between the series. Each series will be
      completed in 12 seconds. Each participant will start the test with an 18-meter sprint
      (volleyball court sideline), then will turn around a cone and run to the free throw line.
      After performing two free throws the participant will run to another cone where he will wait
      for a sound signal to start the next series. One tester will use a stopwatch to measure 12
      seconds, and to give a signal to the participant. Another tester will count the number of
      free throws made. Two other participants will pass the balls to the testee. The participants
      will perform the three S1P60 tests with a five-minute recovery time between each. The average
      score of all three trials will be used for analysis.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">March 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>The study will be divided into two sub studies (100 participants each), in which 50 ADHD and 50 non-ADHD participants will be included. In the first session, all participants will undergo motor tests, in the same conditions. In the second session, half of ADHD participants (25) will be asked to take their regular MPH treatment, before the session. All other participants (25 ADHD and 50 non-ADHD) will perform the motor tests without treatment, and serve as control groups.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Agility tests</measure>
    <time_frame>2 min</time_frame>
    <description>Two agility tests (Zigzag with and without a ball) will be performed. The best time of each test will be recorded. Calculation of the ratio of zigzag test without the ball and with the ball will be conducted</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Accuracy motor tests</measure>
    <time_frame>10 min</time_frame>
    <description>Two accuracy motor tests (the stationary free throw shooting test and the dynamic 60-second free throw shooting test) will be performed three times. The average scores of the all three trials will be used for analysis.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Blood pressure (BP)</measure>
    <time_frame>1 min X 2 times</time_frame>
    <description>BP will be measured before and after motor test by using a mercury sphygmomanometer.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Body Temperature</measure>
    <time_frame>1 min X 2 times</time_frame>
    <description>body temperature will be measured sublingually at the beginning and at the end of each motor test using an electronic thermometer</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Heart rate (HR)</measure>
    <time_frame>Continuously for 10 min</time_frame>
    <description>Heart rates will be continuously recorded throughout the test (Polar heart rate monitor S 710). HR before and after the tests will be recorded</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of Perceived exertion (RPE) scale</measure>
    <time_frame>10 sec X 2 times</time_frame>
    <description>To measure subjective sense of effort we will use the Borg rate of perceived exertion (RPE) scale (ranges from 6 to 20) at the end of each motor test.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">200</enrollment>
  <condition>ADHD</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>ADHD with MPH</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>ADHD participants, taking MPH before the second session</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>ADHD no MPH</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>ADHD participants will perform motor tests in both session, without any intervention, for evaluation of learning effect among ADHD participants.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Healthy participants</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Non-ADHD participants will serve as a control group for learning effect on motor tests</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>MPH</intervention_name>
    <description>The treatment will include taking the patient's own medication by the patient himself in the treatment session 60-180 minutes before the beginning of the tests, according to their prescription given by their own physician. Participants must have consumed this medication at least 3 months before the first session as their regular treatment for ADHD. Note, we are not planning on giving the medication to the participant, rather he/she will consume their own prescribed MPH by them self.</description>
    <arm_group_label>ADHD with MPH</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Concerta</other_name>
    <other_name>Ritalin</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Students age 18-45 years old studying at the academic college at Wingate. For the treatment
        group we will recruit students who were previously diagnosed by a neurologist or
        psychiatrist or other ADHD physician specialist as having ADHD, and are treated with a
        methylphenidate (Ritalin; Ritalin SR; Ritalin LA; Concerta) at least 3 months before the
        first session. Control group will consist of students without ADHD.

        Exclusion Criteria:

        any chronic illness other than ADHD (e.g. asthma, gastrointestinal, depression, anxiety,
        etc.), taking chronic medications apart from stimulant therapy.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>45 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Aviva Mimouni-Bloch, MD</last_name>
    <phone>7709085</phone>
    <phone_ext>972 9</phone_ext>
    <email>abloch@clalit.org.il</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <reference>
    <citation>Battle DE. Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders (DSM). Codas. 2013;25(2):191-2.</citation>
    <PMID>24413388</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Huss M, Duhan P, Gandhi P, Chen CW, Spannhuth C, Kumar V. Methylphenidate dose optimization for ADHD treatment: review of safety, efficacy, and clinical necessity. Neuropsychiatr Dis Treat. 2017 Jul 4;13:1741-1751. doi: 10.2147/NDT.S130444. eCollection 2017. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>28740389</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zimmer L. Contribution of Clinical Neuroimaging to the Understanding of the Pharmacology of Methylphenidate. Trends Pharmacol Sci. 2017 Jul;38(7):608-620. doi: 10.1016/j.tips.2017.04.001. Epub 2017 Apr 24. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>28450072</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shorer Z, Bachner Y, Guy T, Melzer I. Effect of single dose methylphenidate on walking and postural stability under single- and dual-task conditions in older adults--a double-blind randomized control trial. J Gerontol A Biol Sci Med Sci. 2013 Oct;68(10):1271-80. doi: 10.1093/gerona/glt035. Epub 2013 Apr 11.</citation>
    <PMID>23580740</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ben-Itzhak R, Giladi N, Gruendlinger L, Hausdorff JM. Can methylphenidate reduce fall risk in community-living older adults? A double-blind, single-dose cross-over study. J Am Geriatr Soc. 2008 Apr;56(4):695-700. doi: 10.1111/j.1532-5415.2007.01623.x. Epub 2008 Feb 7.</citation>
    <PMID>18266665</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cordeiro LMS, Rabelo PCR, Moraes MM, Teixeira-Coelho F, Coimbra CC, Wanner SP, Soares DD. Physical exercise-induced fatigue: the role of serotonergic and dopaminergic systems. Braz J Med Biol Res. 2017 Oct 19;50(12):e6432. doi: 10.1590/1414-431X20176432. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>29069229</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>King M, Rauch LHG, Brooks SJ, Stein DJ, Lutz K. Methylphenidate Enhances Grip Force and Alters Brain Connectivity. Med Sci Sports Exerc. 2017 Jul;49(7):1443-1451. doi: 10.1249/MSS.0000000000001252.</citation>
    <PMID>28277403</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Swart J, Lamberts RP, Lambert MI, St Clair Gibson A, Lambert EV, Skowno J, Noakes TD. Exercising with reserve: evidence that the central nervous system regulates prolonged exercise performance. Br J Sports Med. 2009 Oct;43(10):782-8. doi: 10.1136/bjsm.2008.055889. Epub 2008 Dec 3.</citation>
    <PMID>19052141</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Roelands B, Hasegawa H, Watson P, Piacentini MF, Buyse L, De Schutter G, Meeusen RR. The effects of acute dopamine reuptake inhibition on performance. Med Sci Sports Exerc. 2008 May;40(5):879-85. doi: 10.1249/MSS.0b013e3181659c4d.</citation>
    <PMID>18408610</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Marcora S. Can Doping be a Good Thing? Using Psychoactive Drugs to Facilitate Physical Activity Behaviour. Sports Med. 2016 Jan;46(1):1-5. doi: 10.1007/s40279-015-0412-x. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26497149</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Stray LL, Ellertsen B, Stray T. Motor function and methylphenidate effect in children with attention deficit hyperactivity disorder. Acta Paediatr. 2010 Aug;99(8):1199-204. doi: 10.1111/j.1651-2227.2010.01760.x. Epub 2010 Mar 12.</citation>
    <PMID>20298494</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Klass M, Roelands B, Lévénez M, Fontenelle V, Pattyn N, Meeusen R, Duchateau J. Effects of noradrenaline and dopamine on supraspinal fatigue in well-trained men. Med Sci Sports Exerc. 2012 Dec;44(12):2299-308. doi: 10.1249/MSS.0b013e318265f356.</citation>
    <PMID>22776872</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kang KD, Yun SW, Chung U, Kim TH, Park JH, Park IH, Han DH. Effects of methylphenidate on body index and physical fitness in Korean children with attention deficit hyperactivity disorder. Hum Psychopharmacol. 2016 Mar;31(2):76-82. doi: 10.1002/hup.2514. Epub 2016 Jan 12.</citation>
    <PMID>26756111</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bart O, Daniel L, Dan O, Bar-Haim Y. Influence of methylphenidate on motor performance and attention in children with developmental coordination disorder and attention deficit hyperactive disorder. Res Dev Disabil. 2013 Jun;34(6):1922-7. doi: 10.1016/j.ridd.2013.03.015. Epub 2013 Apr 10.</citation>
    <PMID>23584172</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Meckel Y, Nemet D, Eliakim A. the Effect of Methylphenidate Treatment on Exercise Performance in Children With Attention-Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder. Acta Kinesiol. Univ. Tartu 7:109-16, 2011</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>De Crescenzo F, Armando M, Mazzone L, Ciliberto M, Sciannamea M, Figueroa C, Janiri L, Quested D, Vicari S. The use of actigraphy in the monitoring of methylphenidate versus placebo in ADHD: a meta-analysis. Atten Defic Hyperact Disord. 2014 Mar;6(1):49-58. doi: 10.1007/s12402-013-0122-x. Epub 2013 Nov 28. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24287735</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Edvinsson D, Ekselius L. Long-Term Tolerability and Safety of Pharmacological Treatment of Adult Attention-Deficit/Hyperactivity Disorder: A 6-Year Prospective Naturalistic Study. J Clin Psychopharmacol. 2018 Aug;38(4):370-375. doi: 10.1097/JCP.0000000000000917.</citation>
    <PMID>29927781</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zohar AH, Konfortes H. Diagnosing ADHD in Israeli adults: the psychometric properties of the adult ADHD Self Report Scale (ASRS) in Hebrew. Isr J Psychiatry Relat Sci. 2010;47(4):308-15.</citation>
    <PMID>21270505</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mirkov D, Nedeljkovic A, Kukolj M, Ugarkovic D, Jaric S. Evaluation of the reliability of soccer-specific field tests. J Strength Cond Res. 2008 Jul;22(4):1046-50. doi: 10.1519/JSC.0b013e31816eb4af.</citation>
    <PMID>18545209</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Masuda S, Suganuma K, Kaneko C, Hoshina K, Suzuki T, Serita T, Sakakibara R. Prediction of Falls Using a 3-m Zigzag Walk Test. J Phys Ther Sci. 2013 Sep;25(9):1051-4. doi: 10.1589/jpts.25.1051. Epub 2013 Oct 20.</citation>
    <PMID>24259913</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Aquino R, Palucci Vieira LH, de Paula Oliveira L, Cruz Gonçalves LG, Pereira Santiago PR. Relationship between field tests and match running performance in high-level young Brazilian soccer players. J Sports Med Phys Fitness. 2018 Mar;58(3):256-262. doi: 10.23736/S0022-4707.17.06651-8. Epub 2017 Feb 14.</citation>
    <PMID>28198600</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Archer DT, Drysdale K, Bradley EJ. Differentiating technical skill and motor abilities in selected and non-selected 3-5 year old team-sports players. Hum Mov Sci. 2016 Jun;47:81-87. doi: 10.1016/j.humov.2016.02.001. Epub 2016 Feb 22.</citation>
    <PMID>26904973</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pojskic H, Muratovic M. The relationship between physical fitness and shooting accuracy of professional basketball players 20:1-13, 2014</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Borg GA. Perceived exertion. Exerc Sport Sci Rev. 1974;2:131-53.</citation>
    <PMID>4466663</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 22, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 22, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 25, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 22, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 22, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 25, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Loewenstein Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Aviva Mimouni-Bloch</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Head of child developmental center</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Concerta</keyword>
  <keyword>Physical Activity</keyword>
  <keyword>Motor test</keyword>
  <keyword>Exercise</keyword>
  <keyword>Ritalin</keyword>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Methylphenidate</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

