<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04286555</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IRB00232059</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04286555</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Dietary Approaches to Stop Hypertension for Diabetes</brief_title>
  <acronym>DASH4D</acronym>
  <official_title>Dietary Approaches to Stop Hypertension for Diabetes Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Johns Hopkins University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Beth Israel Deaconess Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Johns Hopkins University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The objective of the DASH4D trial is to determine the effects, alone and combined, of (a) the
      DASH4D diet (a DASH-style diet modified for people with diabetes) vs. comparison diet that is
      typical of what many Americans eat and (b) lower sodium intake vs. higher sodium intake on
      blood pressure (BP). The core design is a single-site, 4-period, crossover feeding study with
      5-week periods. Participants are fed each of four isocaloric diets, presented in random
      order. The primary contrast of interest is DASH4D diet with lower sodium vs. comparison diet
      with higher sodium.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      In persons with and without diabetes, elevated blood pressure (BP) is the leading cause of
      stroke and a major risk factor for other cardiovascular diseases, including coronary heart
      disease and heart failure. Strategies that effectively lower BP include drug therapy and
      lifestyle modification. Lifestyle modifications, particularly dietary approaches, have been
      shown to lower BP in persons without diabetes. However, there is a striking dearth of
      evidence on BP-lowering, lifestyle modifications, other than weight loss, in persons with
      diabetes. The DASH4D trial is designed to provide this evidence.

      The DASH4D trial builds upon the investigators' experience in four NIH-sponsored feeding
      studies (DASH, DASH-Sodium, OmniHeart, and OmniCarb). The trial will enroll approximately 100
      adults with Type 2 diabetes, systolic BP 120-159 mmHg, and diastolic BP &lt;100 mmHg, to
      determine the effects, alone and combined, of (a) the DASH4D diet (a DASH-style diet modified
      for people with diabetes) vs. comparison diet (typical of what many Americans eat) and (b)
      lower sodium intake vs. higher sodium intake on BP.

      The core design is a four-period, single-site, crossover feeding study with 5-week periods.
      Participants are fed each of four isocaloric diets, presented in random order:

        1. DASH4D diet with lower sodium

        2. DASH4D diet with higher sodium

        3. comparison diet with lower sodium

        4. comparison diet with higher sodium.

      The primary contrast of interest is the DASH4D diet with lower sodium vs. the comparison diet
      with higher sodium.

      The DASH4D diet is similar to the original DASH diet, but is lower in carbohydrates and
      higher in unsaturated fat than the original DASH diet, and therefore, is more consistent with
      dietary recommendations for persons with diabetes than the original DASH diet. The comparison
      diet reflects what many persons with diabetes currently consume. The lower sodium intake of
      approximately 1500 mg/day (at 2000 kcal) has been shown to lower BP in persons without
      diabetes, and has been recommended in some dietary guidelines. The higher sodium intake of
      approximately 3700 mg/day (at 2000 kcal) is based on estimated average intake in the US.

      Outcomes are measured at the end of each feeding period. The primary outcome is
      end-of-period, office-based systolic BP. Other outcomes are diastolic BP, measures of
      glycemia, plasma lipid risk factors, patient symptoms, and estimated cardiovascular disease
      risk.

      Similar to the investigators' prior feeding studies, the investigators expect that the
      results of the DASH4D trial will be immediately applicable to public health and clinical
      guidelines and will influence nutrition policy. Furthermore, the trial will provide a
      rigorous platform to assess the impact of diet and sodium intake on a diverse array of other
      outcomes in persons with Type 2 diabetes.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">September 30, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 31, 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 31, 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>The study design is a four-period crossover feeding study, in which participants will be randomly assigned to an order of four isocaloric diets for a 5-week period each.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>The investigators and the outcomes assessors will not know which order of diets the participant has been assigned. The participant will not be explicitly told which diet he or she is receiving during each period, but by the nature of higher sodium vs. lower sodium or the differences between the DASH4D and comparison diet, the participant would likely be able to guess based on the menus and taste.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Systolic blood pressure (SBP)</measure>
    <time_frame>At the end of 5-week feeding period</time_frame>
    <description>After the participant has rested quietly in the seated position for at least 5 minutes, blood pressure will be measured in triplicate, using an Omron device, with each reading separated by 30 seconds, and the average of the three readings (in mmHg) will also be recorded. Blood pressure will be measured on five separate occasions during the last 2 weeks of the feeding period, and the mean systolic blood pressure from these five blood pressures (15 total readings) will be used as the primary outcome.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Diastolic blood pressure (DBP)</measure>
    <time_frame>At the end of 5-week feeding period</time_frame>
    <description>After the participant has rested quietly in the seated position for at least 5 minutes, blood pressure will be measured in triplicate, using an Omron device, with each reading separated by 30 seconds, and the average of the three readings (in mmHg) will also be recorded. Blood pressure will be measured on five separate occasions during the last 2 weeks of the feeding period, and the mean diastolic blood pressure from these five blood pressures (15 total readings) will be used as a secondary outcome.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Glycated albumin level</measure>
    <time_frame>At the end of 5-week feeding period</time_frame>
    <description>Glycated albumin percentage (%).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Fructosamine level</measure>
    <time_frame>At the end of 5-week feeding period</time_frame>
    <description>Fructosamine level in mmol/L.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Fasting glucose level</measure>
    <time_frame>At the end of 5-week feeding period</time_frame>
    <description>Fasting glucose level in mg/dL.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hemoglobin A1c (HbA1c) level</measure>
    <time_frame>At the end of 5-week feeding period</time_frame>
    <description>HbA1c percentage (%).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cardiovascular disease (CVD) risk percentage</measure>
    <time_frame>At the end of 5-week feeding period</time_frame>
    <description>Current 10-year atherosclerotic cardiovascular disease (ASCVD) risk will be reported as a percent, using the American College of Cardiology (ACC)/American Heart Association (AHA) ASCVD risk equation.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Total cholesterol level</measure>
    <time_frame>At the end of 5-week feeding period</time_frame>
    <description>Total cholesterol level in mg/dL.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Low-density lipoprotein (LDL) cholesterol level</measure>
    <time_frame>At the end of 5-week feeding period</time_frame>
    <description>LDL cholesterol level in mg/dL.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>High-density lipoprotein (HDL) cholesterol level</measure>
    <time_frame>At the end of 5-week feeding period</time_frame>
    <description>HDL cholesterol level in mg/dL.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Triglyceride level</measure>
    <time_frame>At the end of 5-week feeding period</time_frame>
    <description>Triglyceride level in mg/dL.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Presence of orthostatic hypotension</measure>
    <time_frame>At the end of 5-week feeding period</time_frame>
    <description>Participants will lie in the supine position for 5 minutes and undergo three blood pressure measurements, separated by 30 seconds. The average of these three readings will be used as the supine blood pressure. They will stand with their arm rested on an adjacent Mayo table at 70-80 degrees from their torso, and they will then undergo another set of triplicate blood pressure measurements, separated by 30 seconds each. The average of these three readings will be used as the standing blood pressure. Presence of orthostatic hypotension will be defined as ≥ 20 mmHg drop in systolic blood pressure or a ≥ 10 mmHg drop in diastolic blood pressure upon standing.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Postural change in systolic blood pressure</measure>
    <time_frame>At the end of 5-week feeding period</time_frame>
    <description>Participants will lie in the supine position for 5 minutes and undergo three blood pressure measurements, separated by 30 seconds. The average of these three readings will be used as the supine blood pressure. They will stand with their arm rested on an adjacent Mayo table at 70-80 degrees from their torso, and they will then undergo another set of triplicate blood pressure measurements, separated by 30 seconds each. The average of these three readings will be used as the standing blood pressure. Change in systolic blood pressure (mmHg) upon standing will be calculated.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Postural change in diastolic blood pressure</measure>
    <time_frame>At the end of 5-week feeding period</time_frame>
    <description>Participants will lie in the supine position for 5 minutes and undergo three blood pressure measurements, separated by 30 seconds. The average of these three readings will be used as the supine blood pressure. They will stand with their arm rested on an adjacent Mayo table at 70-80 degrees from their torso, and they will then undergo another set of triplicate blood pressure measurements, separated by 30 seconds each. The average of these three readings will be used as the standing blood pressure. Change in diastolic blood pressure (mmHg) upon standing will be calculated.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Symptoms experienced by participants as assessed by a questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>At the end of 5-week feeding period</time_frame>
    <description>Participants will complete a questionnaire about symptoms experienced while on each diet, including symptoms related to fall risk (e.g., feeling faint), food intake and output (e.g., bloating, constipation), fluid intake and output (e.g., excessive thirst), and general symptoms (e.g., fatigue or low energy). Participants will be asked to rate each listed symptom as: did not occur, mild, moderate, or severe.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Diabetes Mellitus, Type 2</condition>
  <condition>Diabetes</condition>
  <condition>Diabetes type2</condition>
  <condition>Type2 Diabetes</condition>
  <condition>Type 2 Diabetes</condition>
  <condition>Type II Diabetes</condition>
  <condition>Hypertension</condition>
  <condition>High Blood Pressure</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>DASH4D diet with lower sodium</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>DASH-style dietary pattern, modified for people with diabetes, with sodium level of 1500 mg/day</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>DASH4D diet with higher sodium</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>DASH-style dietary pattern, modified for people with diabetes, with sodium level of 3700 mg/day</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Comparison diet with lower sodium</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Dietary pattern that is typical of what many Americans eat, with sodium level of 1500 mg/day</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Comparison diet with higher sodium</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Dietary pattern that is typical of what many Americans eat, with sodium level of 3700 mg/day</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>DASH4D diet</intervention_name>
    <description>DASH stands for &quot;Dietary Approaches to Stop Hypertension&quot;. The DASH diet is a healthy dieter that lowers blood pressure. The DASH diet emphasizes fruits, vegetables, and low-fat dairy products; includes whole grains, poultry, fish, and nuts; and is reduced in red meat, sweets, and sugar-containing beverages. The DASH4D dietary pattern is a version of the DASH diet that is lower in carbohydrate.</description>
    <arm_group_label>DASH4D diet with higher sodium</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>DASH4D diet with lower sodium</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>comparison diet</intervention_name>
    <description>The comparison dietary pattern is based on a typical American diet, with macronutrient distributions generally at the average of typical US intake, and micronutrient targets generally near the 25th percentile of usual US intake (with the exception of sodium).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Comparison diet with higher sodium</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Comparison diet with lower sodium</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>higher sodium</intervention_name>
    <description>3700 mg/day sodium</description>
    <arm_group_label>Comparison diet with higher sodium</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>DASH4D diet with higher sodium</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>lower sodium</intervention_name>
    <description>1500 mg/day sodium</description>
    <arm_group_label>Comparison diet with lower sodium</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>DASH4D diet with lower sodium</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        INCLUSION CRITERIA:

          -  Age 18 or older

          -  Diabetes Mellitus Type 2 defined by HbA1c ≥6.5% or treatment of diabetes with diabetes
             medication(s)

          -  Baseline systolic BP of 120-159 mmHg (based on average across 3 screening visits)

          -  Baseline diastolic BP &lt;100 mmHg (based on average across 3 screening visits)

          -  Willing and able to eat on site for one meal per day, 3 days per week, and eat only
             and all food provided as part of the study diets during the controlled feeding periods
             (run-in and four 5-week feeding periods)

          -  Willing and able to complete required measurement procedures

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

          -  Laboratory Exclusions

               -  Serum potassium ≥5.2 mmol/L or &lt;3.5 mmol/L

               -  Estimated glomerular filtration rate (eGFR) &lt;30 mL/min by either the Chronic
                  Kidney Disease Epidemiology Collaboration (CKD-Epi) equation or the simplified
                  Modification of Diet in Renal Disease Study (MDRD) equation

               -  HbA1c&gt;9.0%

          -  Medication Exclusions

               1. Unstable dose (i.e., change in the 2 months prior to screening) of any of the
                  following:

                    -  Anti-hypertensive medications

                    -  Sodium-glucose co-transporter 2 (SGLT2) inhibitors or glucagon-like
                       peptide-1 (GLP-1) receptor agonists

                    -  Stimulants, including oral medications for asthma or chronic obstructive
                       pulmonary disease (COPD)

                    -  Hormone replacement therapy or thyroid hormone

                    -  Weight-increasing psychotropic agents, including antipsychotic agents,
                       lithium, and mirtazapine

               2. Use of any of the following medications:

                    -  Potassium supplement, except if part of a multivitamin

                    -  Prandial or short-acting insulin

                    -  GLP-1 receptor agonist if on weight loss dose

                    -  Warfarin (Coumadin)

                    -  Chronic oral corticosteroid (intermittent use is okay)

                    -  Weight loss medications

               3. Unwillingness to keep same dose of vitamin, mineral, and botanical supplements

               4. Any medication not compatible with participation as determined by the
                  investigators

          -  Medical History Exclusions

               -  Type 1 diabetes

               -  Hypoglycemia requiring hospitalization or the assistance of another person in the
                  last 12 months

               -  Active cardiovascular disease or any event in the prior 6 months, including
                  coronary artery bypass grafting (CABG), percutaneous transluminal coronary
                  angioplasty (PTCA), myocardial infarction (MI), cerebrovascular accident (CVA),
                  or congestive heart failure (CHF) exacerbation requiring hospital admission

               -  Cancer diagnosis or treatment in the last 2 years (non-melanoma skin cancer or
                  localized breast or prostate cancer not requiring systemic therapy is acceptable)

               -  Active inflammatory bowel disease, bowel resection, malabsorptive syndrome,
                  pancreatitis (episode within past year), or history of bariatric surgery

               -  Pregnancy or lactation or planned pregnancy

               -  Any emergency department (ED) visit for asthma or chronic obstructive pulmonary
                  disease (COPD) in the last 6 months

               -  Any other serious illness or condition not compatible with participation as
                  determined by the investigators

          -  Physical Exclusions

               -  Body weight &gt;420 pounds

               -  Arm circumference ≥50cm

               -  Weight loss or gain of &gt;5.0% of body weight during prior 2 months

          -  Lifestyle and Other Exclusions

               -  Significant food allergies, preferences, intolerances, or dietary requirements
                  that would interfere with diet adherence

               -  Not able to self-monitor glucose if needed

               -  Consumption of more than 14 alcoholic drinks per week or consumption of more than
                  6 drinks on one or more occasion per week

               -  Active substance use disorder that would interfere with participation

               -  Participation in or planning to start weight loss program

               -  Current participation in another clinical trial

               -  Planning to leave area prior to end of study

               -  Investigator discretion
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Lawrence Appel, MD, MPH</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Johns Hopkins University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Hsin Chieh Yeh, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Johns Hopkins University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Nisa Maruthur, MD, MHS</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Johns Hopkins University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Lawrence J Appel, MD, MPH</last_name>
    <phone>(410) 955-4156</phone>
    <email>lappel1@jhmi.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Christine Mitchell, ScM</last_name>
    <email>ccarson4@jhmi.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Johns Hopkins ProHealth</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21207</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Letitia Thomas</last_name>
      <phone>410-281-1600</phone>
      <email>dash4d@jhmi.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 25, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 25, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 27, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 22, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 22, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 23, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>diet</keyword>
  <keyword>DASH</keyword>
  <keyword>sodium</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hypertension</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus, Type 2</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

