<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04280198</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>STUDY00004200</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04280198</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Play With Me Study</brief_title>
  <official_title>Using Positive Parent-child Interactions as an Alternative Reinforcer to Promote Healthier Eating Among Young Children</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>State University of New York at Buffalo</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>State University of New York at Buffalo</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The obesity epidemic continues to be a major public health concern, with 38% of US adults and
      17% of children obese. One factor that has been highlighted as a robust predictor of weight
      outcomes is the relative reinforcing value (RRV) of food, or how rewarding one finds eating
      compared to alternative activities. An emerging body of literature has built upon the
      observed relationship between the RRV of food and weight by hypothesizing that the promotion
      of alternative reinforcers, or rewarding activities that could take the place of eating,
      offers a novel approach to decreasing excess energy intake and combatting obesity. We aim to
      integrate distinct bodies of literature and fill a gap in the evidence by testing whether
      parenting intervention messages delivered and practiced in the context of shared activities
      can decrease the RRV of food by making parent-child interactions more rewarding. The ultimate
      goal of this research is to demonstrate that such an intervention can increase children's
      motivation to interact with their parent instead of eating a favorite food, demonstrating the
      potential for positive parent-child interactions to become an alternative source of pleasure.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The modern environment is obesity-promoting, with easy access to palatable, energy-dense
      foods and appealing sedentary activities. Despite this overarching environment, some
      individuals are able to maintain a normal weight status, suggesting that there are individual
      differences in susceptibility to obesity-promoting environments. The RRV of food captures
      individual differences in the motivation to eat by measuring how hard individuals will work
      for access to food versus other activities, and it has been shown to predict weight outcomes
      among infants, children, and adults. In a pilot study with infants, Kong, Eiden, Epstein, et
      al. demonstrated support for this hypothesis as providing infants and parents with access to
      group music classes increased infants' reinforcing values of music relative to food. Compared
      to other age groups, less research has been conducted on the RRV of food in preschool
      children. Filling this gap in the literature is important, as the preschool period is a
      period of drastic transitions, including extensive learning of food preferences and habits.
      Studies have also shown that obesity during adolescence is more likely among children who are
      already overweight by age 5, further highlighting the importance of innovative approaches to
      childhood obesity prevention prior to school entry.

      In the proposed study, we aim to bring together the literature on food reinforcement and the
      literature on parenting interventions in early childhood by promoting positive, rewarding
      parent-child interactions as a novel alternative reinforcer to decrease the RRV of food.
      Positive parenting can be defined as sensitive, responsive parenting, where parents'
      responses are appropriate for and contingent upon the child's cues and developmental level.
      This style of parenting early in life has been linked to positive cognitive and
      socio-emotional outcomes in adolescence and beyond. The focus of the present study is to
      assess the initial efficacy of the present parenting intervention, as well as its
      feasibility. This study will pave the way for future testing of this intervention's effects
      on the RRV of food and other positive developmental and health outcomes.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 26, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 31, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 30, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
    <masking_description>Membership in the &quot;intervention&quot; vs. &quot;control&quot; group will not be discussed as such, but participants will know whether they receive intervention activities early (intervention group) or after the post-test assessment (control group)</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Child's relative reinforcing value of food versus parent-child interaction</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 6 (post-test)</time_frame>
    <description>Computer-based RRV task where child can earn portions of snacks and/or time doing an activity of choice with parent</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in child's relative reinforcing value of food versus parent-child interaction</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 2 (baseline), Week 6 (post-test)</time_frame>
    <description>Computer-based RRV task where child can earn portions of snacks and/or time doing an activity of choice with parent</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Child's maximum schedule reached for food (food reinforcement)</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 6 (post-test)</time_frame>
    <description>Computer-based RRV task where child can earn portions of snacks and/or time doing an activity of choice with parent</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in child's maximum schedule reached for food (food reinforcement)</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 2 (baseline), Week 6 (post-test)</time_frame>
    <description>Computer-based RRV task where child can earn portions of snacks and/or time doing an activity of choice with parent</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Child's maximum schedule reached for parent-child interaction</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 6 (post-test)</time_frame>
    <description>Computer-based RRV task where child can earn portions of snacks and/or time doing an activity of choice with parent</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in child's maximum schedule reached for parent-child interaction</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 2 (baseline), Week 6 (post-test)</time_frame>
    <description>Computer-based RRV task where child can earn portions of snacks and/or time doing an activity of choice with parent</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Observations of warm and sensitive parenting</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 6 (post-test)</time_frame>
    <description>Coded from parent-child interaction using Iowa Family Interaction Rating Scales. The score will be a composite of the following scales, following work by Eiden and colleagues: positive reinforcement, encourages independence, sensitive child-centered, positive mood, warmth/support, prosocial, communication, listener response, relationship quality, rater response. We will also examine relationships between the scales to examine whether the composite is appropriate. Range: 1-9, 9=more warmth/sensitive parenting</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Observations of child prosocial behavior</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 6 (post-test)</time_frame>
    <description>Coded from parent-child interaction using Iowa Family Interaction Rating Scales. Scale: child prosocial behavior. Range: 1-9, 9=more prosocial behavior</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Parent-reported nurturance in parenting</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 6 (post-test)</time_frame>
    <description>Comprehensive General Parenting Questionnaire. Range: 1-5, 5=more nurturance</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Parent-reported structure in parenting</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 6 (post-test)</time_frame>
    <description>Comprehensive General Parenting Questionnaire. Range: 1-5, 5=more structure</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Parent-reported nurturance in parenting</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 10 (follow-up)</time_frame>
    <description>Comprehensive General Parenting Questionnaire. Range: 1-5, 5=more nurturance</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Parent-reported structure in parenting</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 10 (follow-up)</time_frame>
    <description>Comprehensive General Parenting Questionnaire. Range: 1-5, 5=more structure</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Parent-reported parenting efficacy</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 6 (post-test)</time_frame>
    <description>Parenting Sense of Competence Questionnaire. Range: 1-6, 6=more efficacy</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Parent-reported parenting efficacy</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 10 (follow-up)</time_frame>
    <description>Parenting Sense of Competence Questionnaire. Range: 1-6, 6=more efficacy</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Parent-reported parenting satisfaction</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 6 (post-test)</time_frame>
    <description>Parenting Sense of Competence Questionnaire. Range: 1-6, 6=more satisfaction</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Parent-reported parenting satisfaction</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 10 (follow-up)</time_frame>
    <description>Parenting Sense of Competence Questionnaire. Range: 1-6, 6=more satisfaction</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Child self-regulation</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 6 (post-test)</time_frame>
    <description>Head Toes Knees Shoulders Task</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Child total behavioral difficulties</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 6 (post-test)</time_frame>
    <description>Strengths and difficulties questionnaire. Range=0-40, 40=more difficulties</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Child overall behavioral difficulties</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 10 (follow-up)</time_frame>
    <description>Strengths and difficulties questionnaire. Range=0-40, 40=more difficulties</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Child prosocial behavior</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 6 (post-test)</time_frame>
    <description>Strengths and difficulties questionnaire. Range=0-10, 10=more prosocial behavior</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Child prosocial behavior</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 10 (follow-up)</time_frame>
    <description>Strengths and difficulties questionnaire. Range=0-10, 10=more prosocial behavior</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Child peer relationships problems</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 6 (post-test)</time_frame>
    <description>Strengths and difficulties questionnaire. Range=0-10, 10=more peer problems</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Child peer relationships problems</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 10 (follow-up)</time_frame>
    <description>Strengths and difficulties questionnaire. Range=0-10, 10=more peer problems</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Intervention compliance</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 2-5</time_frame>
    <description>Daily text messages (intervention group only)</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Intervention acceptability</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 2-5</time_frame>
    <description>Daily text messages (intervention group only)</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Intervention acceptability</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 6 (post-test)</time_frame>
    <description>Exit interview (intervention group only)</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Intervention use and acceptability</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 10 (follow-up)</time_frame>
    <description>Parent questionnaire</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>High Food Reinforcement</condition>
  <condition>Overeating</condition>
  <condition>Obesity, Childhood</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>No Intervention: Group 1 - Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will attend three laboratory visits: baseline 1, baseline 2, and post-test. At baseline 2 and post-test, the primary outcome of child RRV of food vs. parent child interaction is measured. Other measures include child height and weight, child self-regulation, and parenting in the context of a parent-child interaction task. Participants in the control group will not be assigned to complete any intervention activities during the 4-week intervention phase (which takes place between baseline 2 and post-test visits); however, they will receive contacts from a member of the lab each week in the form of electronic reminders (i.e. texts) to remind them of their upcoming post-test laboratory appointment and will receive some intervention materials after the post-test assessment.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Experimental: Group 2 - Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will attend the same three laboratory visits as the control group. The intervention group will also participate in a 4-week intervention, which consists of the parent watching brief weekly parenting videos from the online Triple P Parenting Program and completing interactive parent-child activities from activity boxes created by our laboratory (~60 min of interactive activities/week). Participants will use their activity boxes to practice specific parenting skills from the week's parenting video. Throughout the intervention phase, participants will receive regular text messages to remind them of the week's activities and ask several questions about engagement in study activities over the past 24 hours. The intervention group will also complete an exit interview about the intervention following the post-test assessment to provide insights on fidelity and acceptability.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Triple P Parenting Videos</intervention_name>
    <description>Four video clips from the online Triple P Parenting program will be used to promote specific positive parenting practices.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Experimental: Group 2 - Intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Activity Boxes</intervention_name>
    <description>There will be about 4 planned activities per week within activity boxes provided to families. The activities will be a context in which the positive parenting behaviors can be practiced. Each activity will take about 15 minutes. Families can pick each week whether they'd like their parenting practice to be embedded in reading activities, nature walks/active games, or arts and crafts. Instructions will be included with each activity, including prompts to allow the parent to apply learnings from that week's parenting video and to allow interactions to be child-led.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Experimental: Group 2 - Intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Child is 4-5 years old

          -  Parent/guardian is 18 years of age or older

          -  Child is not diagnosed with a serious physical or mental health condition that
             precludes participation

          -  At least one of the child's parents/guardians are overweight/obese based on
             self-reported height and weight. This is intended to facilitate recruitment of
             children at risk for obesity, given the overarching goals of this research.

          -  Parent and child are English speaking

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  The child is outside the age range of 4-5 years

          -  Child is diagnosed with a serious physical or mental health condition that precludes
             participation

          -  Parent/guardian &lt;18 years old

          -  None of the child's parents/legal guardians overweight/obese based on self-reported
             height and weight

          -  Parent or child not English speaking
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>4 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>5 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Stephanie Anzman-Frasca, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>State University of New York at Buffalo</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Malena Y Savell, MA</last_name>
    <phone>716-829-6269</phone>
    <email>malenasa@buffalo.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Lily A McGovern, BS</last_name>
    <phone>716-829-6691</phone>
    <email>lilymcgo@buffalo.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>State University of New York at Buffalo</name>
      <address>
        <city>Buffalo</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>14214</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Malena Y Savell, BA</last_name>
      <phone>716-829-6269</phone>
      <email>malenasa@buffalo.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Lily A McGovern, BS</last_name>
      <phone>716-829-6691</phone>
      <email>lilymcgo@buffalo.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Stephanie Anzman-Frasca, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 18, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 20, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 21, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 29, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 29, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 30, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>State University of New York at Buffalo</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Stephanie Anzman-Frasca</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>relative reinforcing value of food</keyword>
  <keyword>food reinforcement</keyword>
  <keyword>positive parenting</keyword>
  <keyword>parenting intervention</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pediatric Obesity</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hyperphagia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

