<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04289077</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MEC-2019-0816</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04289077</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Quality of Life of Patients With Desmoid-type Fibromatosis</brief_title>
  <acronym>QUALIFIED</acronym>
  <official_title>The Evaluation of Health-related Quality of Life Issues Experienced by Patients With Desmoid-type Fibromatosis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Erasmus Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Radboud University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>The Netherlands Cancer Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Erasmus Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Rationale: Desmoid-type fibromatosis (DTF) is a rare, histologically benign, soft tissue
      tumour. Although incapable of metastasizing, the clinical course is unpredictable and can be
      aggressive because of local invasive growth. Various treatments are available including;
      surgical resection, radiotherapy, hormonal therapy and chemotherapy. Nowadays there is a
      trend towards a more conservative strategy with a wait and see policy because of high
      recurrence rates after surgical resection. Health-related quality of life (HRQL) is a corner
      stone in treatment choice and can be used during the disease for monitoring the impact of the
      disease on physical, psychological and social level. Additionally, HRQL can be in important
      endpoint for future clinical trials. Today, no HRQL-tools are available which capture the
      needs of DTF patients. The hypothesis is that patients with DTF have issues on several HRQL
      domains including physical, social and emotional well-being. For this reason we developed a
      list of items based on previous research. This study aims to evaluate HRQL issues experienced
      by DTF patients.

      Purpose: Multi-centre, cross-sectional, observational study to measure HRQL of DTF patients
      and to evaluate the prevalence of the experienced problems.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Objectives: The primary objective is to evaluate HRQoL problems in adult DTF patients. The
      secondary objectives are: 1) to compare the level of HRQoL of DTF patients to the general
      population, 2) to identify patient subgroups who are at risk for developing certain HRQoL
      problems, 3) to evaluate patient preferences regarding their health care needs for DTF.

      Outline: All patients, aged above 18 years, with a histopathological proved DTF tumour and
      sufficient Dutch language skills who have received their last check-up in the hospital within
      the last five years (April 2014). Patients treated in one of the participating centres, will
      be asked to fill out a set of questionnaires (baseline questionnaire, health care
      utilization, decision making, EORTC QLQ-C30, DTF-specific questionnaire, and the EQ-5D-5L).
      Patients will only have to fill out these questionnaires once.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Enrolling by invitation</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">May 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 1, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 1, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Cross-Sectional</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>EORTC QLQ-C30 questionnaire (European Organisation for Research and Treatment of Cancer, Quality of Life Questionnaire-Core-30; version 3.0)</measure>
    <time_frame>Participants have to fill out the questionnaire once and have to complete the questionnaire within 3 months after the invitation. A reminder for participation will be send one month after the initial invitation.</time_frame>
    <description>Each question will be scored: not at all (1), a little (2), quite a bit (3), very much (4). The scores of the EORTC-QLQ30 will be calculated using a Likert scale from 1-4. The scoring manual of the EORTC will be followed. After linear transformation, all scales and single item measures range in score from 0-100. Scores for each scale will be reported as mean (SD), or as median (IQR). A higher score on the functional scales and global quality of life means better functioning and HRQoL, whereas a higher score on the symptom scales means more complaints. The EORTC QLQ-C30 summary score will be calculated using the mean scores of the function scales and the reversed mean scores of the symptom scales and represented as the mean of the combined 13 QLQ-C30 scale scores (financial impact and global health status excluded). A higher summary score represented a better outcome.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>DTF-QoL questionnaire (Desmoid-type fibromatosis Quality of Life Questionnaire)</measure>
    <time_frame>Participants have to fill out the questionnaire once and have to complete the questionnaire within 3 months after the invitation. A reminder for participation will be send one month after the initial invitation.</time_frame>
    <description>The scores for each item of the DTF-QoL will be calculated using a Likert scale from 1-4. The scores of each item will be calculated as mean ± SD, or as median (IQR). These scores (median or mean) will be reported per item.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>EQ-5D-5L questionnaire (EuroQol five-dimensional questionnaire; version 1.0)</measure>
    <time_frame>Participants have to fill out the questionnaire once and have to complete the questionnaire within 3 months after the invitation. A reminder for participation will be send one month after the initial invitation.</time_frame>
    <description>Measures health-related quality of life on five dimensions of health: mobility, self-care, usual activities, pain-discomfort, and anxiety/depression. Additionally two questions aim to rank a patients' health (scale 0-100, with 100 representing a better health). Each of the five dimensions can be divided into five levels of perceived problems: no problems (level 1), slight problems (level 2), moderate problems (level 3), severe problems (level 4) and extreme problems (level). Health states can be converted into single index values. The outcomes will be reported as frequency (proportion) of reported problems for each level and for each dimension. The Visual Analogue Scale (VAS) data will be presented as a mean value (SD). In case of skewed data, median values and IQR will be used.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>EORTC QLQ-C30 questionnaire (European Organisation for Research and Treatment of Cancer, Quality of Life Questionnaire-Core-30; version 3.0)</measure>
    <time_frame>Participants have to fill out the questionnaire once and have to complete the questionnaire within 3 months after the invitation. A reminder for participation will be send one month after the initial invitation.</time_frame>
    <description>See primary outcome 1 for a detailed description of the EORTC QLQ-C30 questionnaire.
The median or mean values for each scale of the EORTC QLQ-C30 from DTF patients will be compared to the median or mean scores per scale of the general population.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Baseline questionnaire (version 1.0)</measure>
    <time_frame>Participants have to fill out the questionnaire once and have to complete the questionnaire within 3 months after the invitation. A reminder for participation will be send one month after the initial invitation.</time_frame>
    <description>Subgroups will be created based on the information of the baseline questionnaire and will encompass: sex (male, female), age groups (categorized based by the median age and/or quartiles), primary treatment type (surgical resection, systemic treatment, radiotherapy, local treatment (e.g. cryoablation), ethnicity, educational level, relationship status, job demands, comorbidities, tumour location, and tumour recurrences.
Outcomes of this questionnaire will be descriptive and are expressed as numbers with corresponding percentages.
Mean or median scores of each scale (EORTC QLQ-C30, version 3.0), items (DTF-QoL, version 1,0) or frequency scores (EQ-5D-5L, version 1,0) will be calculated for each relevant subgroup.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Healt care utilization questionnaire (version 1.0)</measure>
    <time_frame>Participants have to fill out the questionnaire once and have to complete the questionnaire within 3 months after the invitation. A reminder for participation will be send one month after the initial invitation.</time_frame>
    <description>The health care utilization questionnaire contains the following topics: satisfaction with received care, frequency of visits to the general practitioner / specialist, satisfaction with the follow-up schedule, preferences and needs for receiving care in a DTF expert centre, receiving additional care of support from professionals (medical and non-medical). Outcomes will be descriptive and reported in numbers and corresponding frequencies per answer option.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Decision making questionnaire (version 1.0)</measure>
    <time_frame>Participants have to fill out the questionnaire once and have to complete the questionnaire within 3 months after the invitation. A reminder for participation will be send one month after the initial invitation.</time_frame>
    <description>Six questions were designed to obtain information on how patients make medical decisions, what their current role is and what their preferred role, and one question regarding their awareness of their choices, the benefits and risks of certain treatment and whether they received support an advice are designed. Two questions were designed to gain insight into the reasons for choosing an active form of treatment.
Outcomes of this questionnaire will be descriptive and expressed as numbers with corresponding percentages.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Desmoid Tumor</condition>
  <condition>Desmoid-type Fibromatosis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Patients with histopathological proven DTF</arm_group_label>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Questionnaires</intervention_name>
    <description>- Baseline questionnaire, version 1.0, October 29 2019, (Dutch) - Health care utilization, version 1.0, October 29 2019, (Dutch) - Decision-making, version 1.0, October 29 2019, (Dutch) - EORTC QLQ-C30, version 3.0, (Dutch) - DTF-QoL, version 1.0, October</description>
    <arm_group_label>Patients with histopathological proven DTF</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients, aged ≥18 years, diagnosed with a histopathological proven DTF, regardless of
        disease stage and received treatment(s) who have received their last check-up of their DTF
        in one of the participating hospitals the hospital between October 2014 and October 2019.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Aged 18 years and older

          -  Histopathological proven DTF, regardless of disease stage or treatment.

          -  Diagnosed between January 1990 and October 2019, with a visit to the hospital for
             their DTF (between October 2014 and October 2019)

          -  Sufficient Dutch language skills

          -  Competent to complete a questionnaire

          -  Written informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

        • Familial adenomatous polyposis (FAP)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>C. Verhoef, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Erasmus Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>3. Antoni van Leeuwenhoek Ziekenhuis (AVL) / The Netherlands Cancer Instituut , Amsterdam, The Netherlands</name>
      <address>
        <city>Amsterdam</city>
        <zip>1066 CX</zip>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Radboud University Medical Center (MC), Nijmegen, The Netherlands</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nijmegen</city>
        <zip>6525 GA</zip>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Erasmus MC Cancer Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rotterdam</city>
        <zip>3015 GD</zip>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Netherlands</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kasper B, Baumgarten C, Garcia J, Bonvalot S, Haas R, Haller F, Hohenberger P, Penel N, Messiou C, van der Graaf WT, Gronchi A; Desmoid Working Group. An update on the management of sporadic desmoid-type fibromatosis: a European Consensus Initiative between Sarcoma PAtients EuroNet (SPAEN) and European Organization for Research and Treatment of Cancer (EORTC)/Soft Tissue and Bone Sarcoma Group (STBSG). Ann Oncol. 2017 Oct 1;28(10):2399-2408. doi: 10.1093/annonc/mdx323. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>28961825</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Posner MC, Shiu MH, Newsome JL, Hajdu SI, Gaynor JJ, Brennan MF. The desmoid tumor. Not a benign disease. Arch Surg. 1989 Feb;124(2):191-6.</citation>
    <PMID>2916941</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Crago AM, Denton B, Salas S, Dufresne A, Mezhir JJ, Hameed M, Gonen M, Singer S, Brennan MF. A prognostic nomogram for prediction of recurrence in desmoid fibromatosis. Ann Surg. 2013 Aug;258(2):347-53. doi: 10.1097/SLA.0b013e31828c8a30.</citation>
    <PMID>23532110</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gronchi A, Colombo C, Le Péchoux C, Dei Tos AP, Le Cesne A, Marrari A, Penel N, Grignani G, Blay JY, Casali PG, Stoeckle E, Gherlinzoni F, Meeus P, Mussi C, Gouin F, Duffaud F, Fiore M, Bonvalot S; ISG and FSG. Sporadic desmoid-type fibromatosis: a stepwise approach to a non-metastasising neoplasm--a position paper from the Italian and the French Sarcoma Group. Ann Oncol. 2014 Mar;25(3):578-583. doi: 10.1093/annonc/mdt485. Epub 2013 Dec 9.</citation>
    <PMID>24325833</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gundle KR, Cizik AM, Jones RL, Davidson DJ. Quality of life measures in soft tissue sarcoma. Expert Rev Anticancer Ther. 2015 Jan;15(1):95-100. doi: 10.1586/14737140.2015.972947. Epub 2014 Nov 7. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25377073</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gounder MM, Mahoney MR, Van Tine BA, Ravi V, Attia S, Deshpande HA, Gupta AA, Milhem MM, Conry RM, Movva S, Pishvaian MJ, Riedel RF, Sabagh T, Tap WD, Horvat N, Basch E, Schwartz LH, Maki RG, Agaram NP, Lefkowitz RA, Mazaheri Y, Yamashita R, Wright JJ, Dueck AC, Schwartz GK. Sorafenib for Advanced and Refractory Desmoid Tumors. N Engl J Med. 2018 Dec 20;379(25):2417-2428. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa1805052.</citation>
    <PMID>30575484</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Husson O, Younger E, Dunlop A, Dean L, Strauss DC, Benson C, Hayes AJ, Miah A, van Houdt W, Zaidi S, Smith M, Williams J, Jones RL, van der Graaf WTA. Desmoid fibromatosis through the patients' eyes: time to change the focus and organisation of care? Support Care Cancer. 2019 Mar;27(3):965-980. doi: 10.1007/s00520-018-4386-8. Epub 2018 Aug 28.</citation>
    <PMID>30155568</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>van Broekhoven DL, Grünhagen DJ, den Bakker MA, van Dalen T, Verhoef C. Time trends in the incidence and treatment of extra-abdominal and abdominal aggressive fibromatosis: a population-based study. Ann Surg Oncol. 2015 Sep;22(9):2817-23. doi: 10.1245/s10434-015-4632-y. Epub 2015 Jun 5.</citation>
    <PMID>26045393</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bonvalot S, Ternès N, Fiore M, Bitsakou G, Colombo C, Honoré C, Marrari A, Le Cesne A, Perrone F, Dunant A, Gronchi A. Spontaneous regression of primary abdominal wall desmoid tumors: more common than previously thought. Ann Surg Oncol. 2013 Dec;20(13):4096-102. doi: 10.1245/s10434-013-3197-x. Epub 2013 Sep 20.</citation>
    <PMID>24052312</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Penel N, Le Cesne A, Bonvalot S, Giraud A, Bompas E, Rios M, Salas S, Isambert N, Boudou-Rouquette P, Honore C, Italiano A, Ray-Coquard I, Piperno-Neumann S, Gouin F, Bertucci F, Ryckewaert T, Kurtz JE, Ducimetiere F, Coindre JM, Blay JY. Surgical versus non-surgical approach in primary desmoid-type fibromatosis patients: A nationwide prospective cohort from the French Sarcoma Group. Eur J Cancer. 2017 Sep;83:125-131. doi: 10.1016/j.ejca.2017.06.017. Epub 2017 Jul 20.</citation>
    <PMID>28735069</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Timbergen MJM, van de Poll-Franse LV, Grünhagen DJ, van der Graaf WT, Sleijfer S, Verhoef C, Husson O. Identification and assessment of health-related quality of life issues in patients with sporadic desmoid-type fibromatosis: a literature review and focus group study. Qual Life Res. 2018 Dec;27(12):3097-3111. doi: 10.1007/s11136-018-1931-3. Epub 2018 Jul 16. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>30014458</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nolte S, Liegl G, Petersen MA, Aaronson NK, Costantini A, Fayers PM, Groenvold M, Holzner B, Johnson CD, Kemmler G, Tomaszewski KA, Waldmann A, Young TE, Rose M; EORTC Quality of Life Group. General population normative data for the EORTC QLQ-C30 health-related quality of life questionnaire based on 15,386 persons across 13 European countries, Canada and the Unites States. Eur J Cancer. 2019 Jan;107:153-163. doi: 10.1016/j.ejca.2018.11.024. Epub 2018 Dec 19.</citation>
    <PMID>30576971</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Giesinger JM, Kieffer JM, Fayers PM, Groenvold M, Petersen MA, Scott NW, Sprangers MA, Velikova G, Aaronson NK; EORTC Quality of Life Group. Replication and validation of higher order models demonstrated that a summary score for the EORTC QLQ-C30 is robust. J Clin Epidemiol. 2016 Jan;69:79-88. doi: 10.1016/j.jclinepi.2015.08.007. Epub 2015 Sep 28.</citation>
    <PMID>26327487</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Herdman M, Gudex C, Lloyd A, Janssen M, Kind P, Parkin D, Bonsel G, Badia X. Development and preliminary testing of the new five-level version of EQ-5D (EQ-5D-5L). Qual Life Res. 2011 Dec;20(10):1727-36. doi: 10.1007/s11136-011-9903-x. Epub 2011 Apr 9.</citation>
    <PMID>21479777</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>von Elm E, Altman DG, Egger M, Pocock SJ, Gøtzsche PC, Vandenbroucke JP; STROBE Initiative. The Strengthening the Reporting of Observational Studies in Epidemiology (STROBE) statement: guidelines for reporting observational studies. Lancet. 2007 Oct 20;370(9596):1453-7.</citation>
    <PMID>18064739</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 24, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 26, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 28, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 26, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 26, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 28, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Erasmus Medical Center</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>C. Verhoef</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Prof. dr. C. Verhoef, MD, PhD</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Health-related quality of life</keyword>
  <keyword>Quality of life</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Fibromatosis, Aggressive</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fibroma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <provided_document_section>
    <provided_document>
      <document_type>Study Protocol and Statistical Analysis Plan</document_type>
      <document_has_protocol>Yes</document_has_protocol>
      <document_has_icf>No</document_has_icf>
      <document_has_sap>Yes</document_has_sap>
      <document_date>November 26, 2019</document_date>
      <document_url>https://ClinicalTrials.gov/ProvidedDocs/77/NCT04289077/Prot_SAP_000.pdf</document_url>
    </provided_document>
  </provided_document_section>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

