<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04287543</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>R-2018-785-019</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04287543</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Melatonin on Clock Genes in Parkinson's Disease</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effect of Melatonin Administration on the PER1 and BMAL1 Clock Genes in Patients With Parkinson's Disease</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Instituto Mexicano del Seguro Social</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Instituto Mexicano del Seguro Social</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Parkinson's disease (PD) is the second most important neurodegenerative disease that affects
      about 2% of the population over 60 years of age. About 40% of the Mexican population with PD
      suffer from sleep disorders, which has been linked to a deregulation of the circadian cycle
      and therefore of the clock genes. Melatonin is a hormone produced by the pineal gland that
      regulates the sleep-wake cycle, at pharmacological doses, it is used to decrease sleep
      disorders; it is suggested that is used could also normalize the levels of the clock genes
      expression. In rats with PD, a decrease in clock genes levels has been observed, which are
      restored by administering melatonin. The aim of the study is to evaluate the effect of
      melatonin on the expression of the PER1 and BMAL1 clock genes in patients with PD during 12
      months. A controlled, double-blind, randomized clinical trial will be carried out in patients
      with a diagnosis of PD. A survey will be applied in order to know the course of the disease
      and two more tests to rule out some sleep disorder, at the beginning of the study, at the 6th
      month and at the 12th month. A blood sample (approximately 15 ml) will be taken every 3
      months for a year. By random assignment, the participant will be given Melatonin or placebo,
      which should be taken every day in the morning and evening after meals for one year.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      A controlled, double-blind, randomized clinical trial will be carried out in 58 patients with
      a diagnosis of PD. Twenty-nine patients will receive Melatonin and 29 placebo. A blood sample
      will be taken to determine the expression levels of the PER1 and BMAL1 clock genes by a
      real-time quantitative polymerase chain reaction (RT-qPCR), and as secondary variables, to
      determine the activity of the mitochondrial complex 1, the levels of malondialdehyde (MDA)
      and 4-hydroxyalkene (4-HDA) and the production of nitric oxide will be quantified by
      spectrophotometric methods. The SCOPA-Sleep and EPWORTH questionnaires will be applied to
      assess sleep. To evaluate the clinical evolution of PD in each patient, the UPDRS scale will
      be used. It will be given the assigned treatment, with the printed patient code. They will be
      supplemented with 50 mg of Melatonin at a dose of 25 mg orally every 12 hours for 12 months.
      The double-blind of the medication for this study will be maintained by the use of gels
      identical to the Melatonin supplement. The blind's break will only be authorized in case of
      emergency events that require it, and the date, time and reason for the break should be
      noted. It will be given a follow-up diary, and the patient will be explained how they should
      take the treatment and that they should record the date and time of administration, the
      description of adverse events that may occur, raising the patient's awareness that It is
      important to keep the diary and take it at each appointment to assess the attachment to
      treatment. Concerning the medications that patients ingest, before entering the protocol, it
      will be indicated to follow their usual administration. Finally, the patient will be
      instructed to schedule their appointment 3,6, 9 and 12 months later of starting treatment.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Enrolling by invitation</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">May 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2/Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Expression levels of clock genes</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline at third, sixth, ninth and twelfth month</time_frame>
    <description>Relative ratio of messenger ribonucleic acid (mRNA) expression of PER1 and BMAL1 genes corresponding to a control (GAPDH) for each sample, measured by an RT-qPCR.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>SCOPA-Sleep scale</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline at third, sixth, ninth and twelfth month</time_frame>
    <description>It is a specific instrument for the evaluation of sleep disorders in patients with PD. It is self-applicable and consists of two subscales; the first assess nighttime sleep and the second daytime sleepiness during the last month. The score greater than seven of five points respectively indicates abnormal sleepiness. Additionally, the SCOPA-Sleep scale has a question of global sleep evaluation.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Epworth scale</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline at third, sixth, ninth and twelfth month</time_frame>
    <description>Is an eight-item self-applicable instrument developed to assess the propensity to fall asleep in eight situations, mostly monotonous. A total score of less than 10 was considered normal, 10-12 as indicative of marginal drowsiness and above 12 suggestive of excessive drowsiness.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression of PD</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline at third, sixth, ninth and twelfth month</time_frame>
    <description>For the longitudinal follow-up of the PD course, the Unified Parkinson's Disease Rating Scale (UPDRS) will be applied through an interview. The scale is composed by four parts: mental, behavioral and mood; activities of daily living; motor evaluation; and motor complications. The scoring range is from 0 to 199, where &quot;199&quot; represents total disability and &quot;0&quot; without disability.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Anxiety</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline at third, sixth, ninth and twelfth month</time_frame>
    <description>To assess the severity of a person's anxiety symptoms and discriminate between anxiety and depression symptoms the Beck anxiety inventory will be use.
The rating is made through a likert scale of 0 to 3, where 0 means absence of the symptom and 3 maximum severity. The total score is obtained from the sum of the 21 reagents, 0 is the minimum and 63 is the maximum. In the Mexican population, a score of 0-5 points will be minimal anxiety, 6-15 mild anxiety, 16-30 moderate anxiety and 31-63 severe anxiety.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Depression</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline at third, sixth, ninth and twelfth month</time_frame>
    <description>To evaluate the severity of depression symptoms the Beck's depression inventory will be use. The rating is made through a likert scale of 0 to 3, where 0 means absence of the symptom and 3 maximum severity. The total score is obtained from the sum of the 21 reagents, 0 is the minimum and 63 is the maximum. In the Mexican population, a score of 0-9 points will be considered normal, 10-16 mild depression, 17-29 moderate depression, and 30-63 severe depression.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Activity of the mitochondrial complex 1</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline at third, sixth, ninth and twelfth month</time_frame>
    <description>To measure the mitochondrial complex I, a spectrophotometric assay will be used, it measures the oxidation of rotenone-sensitive nicotinamide-adenine dinucleotide (NADH) at 340 nm in mitochondria-enriched fractions</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Oxidative stress</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline at third, sixth, ninth and twelfth month</time_frame>
    <description>Products of nitric oxide metabolism and products of lipoperoxidation such as malondialdehyde and 4-hydroxyalkene by spectrophotometry will be measured</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">58</enrollment>
  <condition>Parkinson Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Melatonin group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients with PD who will receive 25 mg of melatonin gel at 12 hours a day and half an hour before sleeping for 12 months</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients with PD who will receive 25 mg of placebo gel at 12 hours a day and half an hour before sleeping for 12 months</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Melatonin</intervention_name>
    <description>25 mg of melatonin gel at noon and 25 mg of melatonin gel 30 minutes before sleeping for 12 months</description>
    <arm_group_label>Melatonin group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebos</intervention_name>
    <description>25 mg of placebo gel at noon and 25 mg of placebo gel 30 minutes before sleeping for 12 months</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with diagnosis of PD in stages 1-3 of the classification by stages of Hoehn &amp;
             Yahr

          -  Go with a companion to the appointments

          -  Patients who agree to participate in the study and sign the Informed Consent letter

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with movement disorder other than PD

          -  Prior pallidotomy, thalamotomy or deep brain stimulation

          -  Pregnant

          -  Patients who consume alcohol or coffee

          -  Patients who consume an antioxidant supplement
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>20 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Blanca M. Torres, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Instituto Mexicano del Seguro Social</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Instituto Mexicano del Seguro Social</name>
      <address>
        <city>Guadalajara</city>
        <state>Jalisco</state>
        <zip>44340</zip>
        <country>Mexico</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Mexico</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.cenetec.salud.gob.mx/descargas/gpc/CatalogoMaestro/153_GPC_PARKINSON/SSA_153_08_GRR_Parkinson.pdf</url>
    <description>Guía de practica clínica en la enfermedad de Parkinson</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://www3.inegi.org.mx/sistemas/temas/default.aspx?s=est&amp;c=17484</url>
    <description>INEGI</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>https://www.drugs.com/npp/melatonin.html</url>
    <description>Melatonin information</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Poewe W, Seppi K, Tanner CM, Halliday GM, Brundin P, Volkmann J, Schrag AE, Lang AE. Parkinson disease. Nat Rev Dis Primers. 2017 Mar 23;3:17013. doi: 10.1038/nrdp.2017.13. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>28332488</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Barzilai A, Melamed E. Molecular mechanisms of selective dopaminergic neuronal death in Parkinson's disease. Trends Mol Med. 2003 Mar;9(3):126-32. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>12657434</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shadrina MI, Slominsky PA, Limborska SA. Molecular mechanisms of pathogenesis of Parkinson's disease. Int Rev Cell Mol Biol. 2010;281:229-66. doi: 10.1016/S1937-6448(10)81006-8. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20460187</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chung S, Bohnen NI, Albin RL, Frey KA, Müller ML, Chervin RD. Insomnia and sleepiness in Parkinson disease: associations with symptoms and comorbidities. J Clin Sleep Med. 2013 Nov 15;9(11):1131-7. doi: 10.5664/jcsm.3150.</citation>
    <PMID>24235893</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Breen DP, Vuono R, Nawarathna U, Fisher K, Shneerson JM, Reddy AB, Barker RA. Sleep and circadian rhythm regulation in early Parkinson disease. JAMA Neurol. 2014 May;71(5):589-595. doi: 10.1001/jamaneurol.2014.65.</citation>
    <PMID>24687146</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cai Y, Liu S, Sothern RB, Xu S, Chan P. Expression of clock genes Per1 and Bmal1 in total leukocytes in health and Parkinson's disease. Eur J Neurol. 2010 Apr;17(4):550-4. doi: 10.1111/j.1468-1331.2009.02848.x. Epub 2009 Nov 12.</citation>
    <PMID>19912323</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Videnovic A, Willis GL. Circadian system - A novel diagnostic and therapeutic target in Parkinson's disease? Mov Disord. 2016 Mar;31(3):260-9. doi: 10.1002/mds.26509. Epub 2016 Jan 30. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26826022</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cardinali DP, Pagano ES, Scacchi Bernasconi PA, Reynoso R, Scacchi P. Melatonin and mitochondrial dysfunction in the central nervous system. Horm Behav. 2013 Feb;63(2):322-30. doi: 10.1016/j.yhbeh.2012.02.020. Epub 2012 Feb 25. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22391273</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Videnovic A, Golombek D. Circadian Dysregulation in Parkinson's Disease. Neurobiol Sleep Circadian Rhythms. 2017 Jan;2:53-58. doi: 10.1016/j.nbscr.2016.11.001. Epub 2016 Nov 12.</citation>
    <PMID>28713867</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Elbaz A, Carcaillon L, Kab S, Moisan F. Epidemiology of Parkinson's disease. Rev Neurol (Paris). 2016 Jan;172(1):14-26. doi: 10.1016/j.neurol.2015.09.012. Epub 2015 Dec 21. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26718594</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Perfeito R, Cunha-Oliveira T, Rego AC. Reprint of: revisiting oxidative stress and mitochondrial dysfunction in the pathogenesis of Parkinson disease-resemblance to the effect of amphetamine drugs of abuse. Free Radic Biol Med. 2013 Sep;62:186-201. doi: 10.1016/j.freeradbiomed.2013.05.042. Epub 2013 Jun 3. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23743292</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Abou-Sleiman PM, Muqit MM, Wood NW. Expanding insights of mitochondrial dysfunction in Parkinson's disease. Nat Rev Neurosci. 2006 Mar;7(3):207-19. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>16495942</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mattam U, Jagota A. Daily rhythms of serotonin metabolism and the expression of clock genes in suprachiasmatic nucleus of rotenone-induced Parkinson's disease male Wistar rat model and effect of melatonin administration. Biogerontology. 2015 Feb;16(1):109-23. doi: 10.1007/s10522-014-9541-0. Epub 2014 Nov 28.</citation>
    <PMID>25430725</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ortiz GG, Benítez-King GA, Rosales-Corral SA, Pacheco-Moisés FP, Velázquez-Brizuela IE. Cellular and biochemical actions of melatonin which protect against free radicals: role in neurodegenerative disorders. Curr Neuropharmacol. 2008 Sep;6(3):203-14. doi: 10.2174/157015908785777201.</citation>
    <PMID>19506721</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ortiz GG, Pacheco-Moisés FP, Gómez-Rodríguez VM, González-Renovato ED, Torres-Sánchez ED, Ramírez-Anguiano AC. Fish oil, melatonin and vitamin E attenuates midbrain cyclooxygenase-2 activity and oxidative stress after the administration of 1-methyl-4-phenyl-1,2,3,6- tetrahydropyridine. Metab Brain Dis. 2013 Dec;28(4):705-9. doi: 10.1007/s11011-013-9416-0. Epub 2013 May 24.</citation>
    <PMID>23703110</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Trotti LM, Bliwise DL. Treatment of the sleep disorders associated with Parkinson's disease. Neurotherapeutics. 2014 Jan;11(1):68-77. doi: 10.1007/s13311-013-0236-z. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24272458</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Medeiros CA, Carvalhedo de Bruin PF, Lopes LA, Magalhães MC, de Lourdes Seabra M, de Bruin VM. Effect of exogenous melatonin on sleep and motor dysfunction in Parkinson's disease. A randomized, double blind, placebo-controlled study. J Neurol. 2007 Apr;254(4):459-64. Epub 2007 Apr 3.</citation>
    <PMID>17404779</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Videnovic A, Zee PC. Consequences of Circadian Disruption on Neurologic Health. Sleep Med Clin. 2015 Dec;10(4):469-80. doi: 10.1016/j.jsmc.2015.08.004. Epub 2015 Sep 26. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26568123</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hoehn MM, Yahr MD. Parkinsonism: onset, progression and mortality. Neurology. 1967 May;17(5):427-42.</citation>
    <PMID>6067254</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jankovic J. An update on the treatment of Parkinson's disease. Mt Sinai J Med. 2006 Jul;73(4):682-9. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>16878274</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fernandez HH. Updates in the medical management of Parkinson disease. Cleve Clin J Med. 2012 Jan;79(1):28-35. doi: 10.3949/ccjm.78gr.11005. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22219231</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bolitho SJ, Naismith SL, Rajaratnam SM, Grunstein RR, Hodges JR, Terpening Z, Rogers N, Lewis SJ. Disturbances in melatonin secretion and circadian sleep-wake regulation in Parkinson disease. Sleep Med. 2014 Mar;15(3):342-7. doi: 10.1016/j.sleep.2013.10.016. Epub 2014 Jan 21.</citation>
    <PMID>24529544</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zhang Y, Chen J, Qiu J, Li Y, Wang J, Jiao J. Intakes of fish and polyunsaturated fatty acids and mild-to-severe cognitive impairment risks: a dose-response meta-analysis of 21 cohort studies. Am J Clin Nutr. 2016 Feb;103(2):330-40. doi: 10.3945/ajcn.115.124081. Epub 2015 Dec 30.</citation>
    <PMID>26718417</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Taghizadeh M, Tamtaji OR, Dadgostar E, Daneshvar Kakhaki R, Bahmani F, Abolhassani J, Aarabi MH, Kouchaki E, Memarzadeh MR, Asemi Z. The effects of omega-3 fatty acids and vitamin E co-supplementation on clinical and metabolic status in patients with Parkinson's disease: A randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled trial. Neurochem Int. 2017 Sep;108:183-189. doi: 10.1016/j.neuint.2017.03.014. Epub 2017 Mar 22.</citation>
    <PMID>28342967</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mayo JC, Sainz RM, Tan DX, Antolín I, Rodríguez C, Reiter RJ. Melatonin and Parkinson's disease. Endocrine. 2005 Jul;27(2):169-78. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>16217130</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Reiter RJ, Korkmaz A, Paredes SD, Manchester LC, Tan DX. Melatonin reduces oxidative/nitrosative stress due to drugs, toxins, metals, and herbicides. Neuro Endocrinol Lett. 2008 Oct;29(5):609-13. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18987585</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Castellani RJ, Nunomura A, Rolston RK, Moreira PI, Takeda A, Perry G, Smith MA. Sublethal RNA oxidation as a mechanism for neurodegenerative disease. Int J Mol Sci. 2008 May;9(5):789-806. doi: 10.3390/ijms9050789. Epub 2008 May 20.</citation>
    <PMID>19325784</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Reiter RJ. Oxidative damage in the central nervous system: protection by melatonin. Prog Neurobiol. 1998 Oct;56(3):359-84. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>9770244</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Korkmaz A, Reiter RJ, Topal T, Manchester LC, Oter S, Tan DX. Melatonin: an established antioxidant worthy of use in clinical trials. Mol Med. 2009 Jan-Feb;15(1-2):43-50. doi: 10.2119/molmed.2008.00117. Epub 2008 Nov 4. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19011689</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mack JM, Schamne MG, Sampaio TB, Pértile RA, Fernandes PA, Markus RP, Prediger RD. Melatoninergic System in Parkinson's Disease: From Neuroprotection to the Management of Motor and Nonmotor Symptoms. Oxid Med Cell Longev. 2016;2016:3472032. Epub 2016 Oct 18. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>27829983</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Panigel M. [Application of new methods to the anatomical study of the human and animal placenta]. Bull Assoc Anat (Nancy). 1989 Sep;73(222):47-53. Review. French.</citation>
    <PMID>2700075</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Härtter S, Nordmark A, Rose DM, Bertilsson L, Tybring G, Laine K. Effects of caffeine intake on the pharmacokinetics of melatonin, a probe drug for CYP1A2 activity. Br J Clin Pharmacol. 2003 Dec;56(6):679-82.</citation>
    <PMID>14616429</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Weishaupt JH, Bartels C, Pölking E, Dietrich J, Rohde G, Poeggeler B, Mertens N, Sperling S, Bohn M, Hüther G, Schneider A, Bach A, Sirén AL, Hardeland R, Bähr M, Nave KA, Ehrenreich H. Reduced oxidative damage in ALS by high-dose enteral melatonin treatment. J Pineal Res. 2006 Nov;41(4):313-23.</citation>
    <PMID>17014688</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Anderson G, Seo M, Berk M, Carvalho AF, Maes M. Gut Permeability and Microbiota in Parkinson's Disease: Role of Depression, Tryptophan Catabolites, Oxidative and Nitrosative Stress and Melatonergic Pathways. Curr Pharm Des. 2016;22(40):6142-6151. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>27604608</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Vural EM, van Munster BC, de Rooij SE. Optimal dosages for melatonin supplementation therapy in older adults: a systematic review of current literature. Drugs Aging. 2014 Jun;31(6):441-51. doi: 10.1007/s40266-014-0178-0. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24802882</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lewy AJ, Sack RL, Miller LS, Hoban TM. Antidepressant and circadian phase-shifting effects of light. Science. 1987 Jan 16;235(4786):352-4.</citation>
    <PMID>3798117</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Belaid H, Adrien J, Karachi C, Hirsch EC, François C. Effect of melatonin on sleep disorders in a monkey model of Parkinson's disease. Sleep Med. 2015 Oct;16(10):1245-51. doi: 10.1016/j.sleep.2015.06.018. Epub 2015 Jul 14.</citation>
    <PMID>26429753</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Innominato PF, Lim AS, Palesh O, Clemons M, Trudeau M, Eisen A, Wang C, Kiss A, Pritchard KI, Bjarnason GA. The effect of melatonin on sleep and quality of life in patients with advanced breast cancer. Support Care Cancer. 2016 Mar;24(3):1097-105. doi: 10.1007/s00520-015-2883-6. Epub 2015 Aug 11.</citation>
    <PMID>26260726</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ortiz GG, Moráles-Sánchez EW, Pacheco-Moisés FP, Jiménez-Gil FJ, Macías-Islas MA, Mireles-Ramírez MA, González-Usigli H. Effect of melatonin administration on cyclooxygenase-2 activity, serum levels of nitric oxide metabolites, lipoperoxides and glutathione peroxidase activity in patients with Parkinson’s disease. Gac Med Mex. 2017;153(Supl. 2):S72-S81. doi: 10.24875/GMM.M000008. Spanish.</citation>
    <PMID>29099102</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Morisky DE, Ang A, Krousel-Wood M, Ward HJ. Predictive validity of a medication adherence measure in an outpatient setting. J Clin Hypertens (Greenwich). 2008 May;10(5):348-54.</citation>
    <PMID>18453793</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 21, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 25, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 27, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 25, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 25, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 27, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Instituto Mexicano del Seguro Social</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Blanca Miriam de Guadalupe Torres Mendoza</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Head of aging laboratory</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>melatonin</keyword>
  <keyword>clock genes</keyword>
  <keyword>BMAL1 gene</keyword>
  <keyword>PER1 gene</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Parkinson Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Melatonin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>It is planned to inform the patient individually about their results; if the results are favorable it will be considered to apply them to the Clinical of Movement Disorders patients. All data will be published in an article.</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Statistical Analysis Plan (SAP)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Informed Consent Form (ICF)</ipd_info_type>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

