<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04280172</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CulturalCompetence</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04280172</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effectiveness of Cultural Competence Education for Nurse Mentors</brief_title>
  <official_title>Educational Intervention to Support Development of Mentors' Cultural Competence and Competence in Mentoring Culturally and Linguistically Diverse Nursing Students</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Oulu</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>The Finnish Association of Nursing Research</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Finnish Nurses Association</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Oulu</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Clinical placements are an integral part of nursing education and have significant impact on
      nursing students' professional development. According to standards set by the European Union,
      the duration of clinical placements should account for at least one half of the minimum
      duration of nursing programs. Also, students must complete training under the supervision of
      qualified nursing staff (Directive 2013/55/EU of the European Parliament and of the Council).

      Nursing staff are responsible for the mentoring of students during completion of their
      clinical placements. The role of the mentor can be challenging and several studies prove that
      providing continuing education to mentors can be effective in developing mentors' competence
      in mentoring. There is an urgent need to add issues related to the development of mentors'
      cultural competence into mentoring education. This is due to the rapid increase of cultural
      and linguistic diversity within the nursing workforce and the increase in the numbers of
      students from international backgrounds.

      This study is designed to assess the effectiveness of an educational intervention to develop
      mentors' cultural competence and their competence in mentoring nursing students from diverse
      cultural and linguistic backgrounds.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      METHODOLOGY

      Study setting:

      The study will be conducted in two hospitals, which are located in two different major cities
      in Finland.

      Study design:

      This is a nonrandomized, pre-post quasi-experimental study. Participants in this study will
      participate in cultural competence education. Participants will self-assess their level of
      competence in mentoring in general along with their cultural competence in mentoring. There
      will be three assessment time points: at baseline (before education, T0), immediately after
      the education (T1), and 6 months after the education (T2). The control group will receive
      standard mentoring education that does not contain topics specific to cultural competence or
      the mentoring of students from diverse backgrounds. The same self-assessment instrument and
      assessment time points will be used for both the intervention and control groups.

      Study size:

      A total of 60 mentors will be allocated to the intervention group and 60 mentors to the
      control group.

      Study duration:

      The educational intervention (cultural competence education) will be conducted for a duration
      of 9 months (T0, T1, T2). The education will be offered twice (fall 2020, spring 2021), thus
      the total duration of the study (from date study open for recruitment to final data
      collection) will be a total of 16 months.

      Sampling of participants

      Recruitment:

      Participants in the intervention group who attend cultural competence education and
      participants who belong to the control group will be recruited into this study via internal
      recruitment methods implemented by clinical coordinators employed at the participating
      hospitals.

      Intervention:

      Cultural competence education for participants in the intervention group comprises of
      completion of an online learning module and participation in an eight-hour training day. The
      educational content includes various topics related to cultural and linguistic diversity and
      cultural competence in mentoring.

      Control:

      Participants in the control group will not receive the educational intervention but will
      participate in standard mentoring education offered at the participating university hospital.
      This education is offered in an online learning environment and participants can complete the
      education at their own pace. The educational content focuses on general issues related to
      mentoring and does not contain topics specific to cultural competence in mentoring.

      Sample size

      A power analysis has been calculated for an effect size according to Cohen's d, two
      tail-test, significance at p&lt;0.05, power of 80% (1- Beta err prob). The estimated sample size
      was 60 participants per group after accounting for significance level of 0.05%, power of 80%
      and 50% attrition.

      INSTRUMENTS AND DATA COLLECTION

      Intervention: Cultural competence education

      Questionnaire: Mentors' competence in mentoring will be measured using the psychometrically
      validated self-assessment Mentors' Competence Instrument (MCI). A newly developed Mentors'
      Cultural Competence Instrument (MCCI) will be used to measure mentors' cultural competence.
      This instrument has been administered and pilot tested by 12 mentors prior to implementation
      of the intervention.

      Finnish language versions of the questionnaire will be administered containing the following
      sections:

        1. Sociodemographic data:

             -  Sex

             -  Age

             -  Educational background

             -  Place of work

             -  Current position

             -  Work experience

             -  Name of work organization

             -  Current work unit

             -  Time when last mentored a student

             -  Time used for reflective discussion with student

             -  Previous participation in mentoring education

             -  Experience mentoring international students

             -  How often international students are mentored

        2. Competence in mentoring using Mentors' Competence Instrument which contains 43 items
           divided into 7 sections

             -  Mentoring practices between the student and mentor

             -  Mentor's characteristics

             -  Mentor's motivation

             -  Goal-oriented mentoring

             -  Reflection during mentoring

             -  Student-centered evaluation

             -  Constructive feedback

        3. Mentors' cultural competence using Mentors' Cultural Competence Instrument which
           contains 21 items covering the following topics

             -  Cultural sensitivity and awareness

             -  Cultural knowledge

             -  Intercultural communication and interaction

             -  Cultural skills and safety

      DATA COLLECTION

      Intervention group

        1. Baseline questionnaire (T0): Paper-based questionnaires will be administered to
           participants in the intervention group on the day of study recruitment before being
           given details on how to complete the cultural competence education.

        2. Post course questionnaire (T1): Paper-based questionnaires will be administered to
           participants in the intervention group immediately following completion of the cultural
           competence education.

           a. Participants will be asked to provide their evaluation of the education in addition
           to the questionnaire described above. The evaluation contains the following questions:

             -  How satisfied were you with the mentoring education?

             -  Did the mentoring education have an impact on your ability to mentor students?

             -  Did the mentoring education have an impact on your willingness to mentor students?

             -  Open comment section for comments or concerns regarding the mentoring education

        3. 6-month follow up questionnaire (T2): Paper-based questionnaires including will be sent
           to participants via post to participants' home addresses.

      Control group

        1. Baseline questionnaire (T0): Web-based questionnaires will be administered to
           participants in the control group on the first day of standard online mentoring
           education.

        2. Post course questionnaire (T1): Web-based questionnaires will be administered to
           participants in the control group on the last day of standard online mentoring
           education.

        3. 6-month follow up questionnaire (T2): Web-based questionnaires will be sent to
           participants via email six months following completion of the standard online mentoring
           education.

      ETHICAL CONSIDERATIONS This study complies with the standards and guidelines of the
      responsible conduct of research. The necessary research permissions from the participating
      hospitals have been obtained prior to data collection and implementation of the intervention.
      In this study, formal approval from an ethics committee is not required. Participation is
      voluntary and participants will be informed of the purpose of the study and their right to
      withdraw from the study. Participants' confidentiality and anonymity will be protected and
      research data will be secured according to current standards.

      Data analysis Data will be analyzed using IBM Social Package for Social Science (SPSS,
      version 26). Data will be analyzed using descriptive statistics, a Wilcoxon Signed-Rank Test
      and a two-way ANOVA test. In this study, two-tailed testing will be used and the significance
      level will be set at a p-value &lt;0.05.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Enrolling by invitation</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Health Services Research</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in mentors' cultural competence</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre intervention, immediately after intervention and 6 months after intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Mentors' cultural competence will be measured using the newly developed Mentors' Cultural Competence Instrument. The instrument contains 21 items using a four-level Likert scale. A higher score on the likert scale indicates a higher level of competence.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in competence in mentoring</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre intervention, immediately after intervention and 6 months after intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Mentors' competence in mentoring will be measured using the psychometrically validated self-assessment Mentors' Competence Instrument (MCI), which contains 43 items divided into 7 sections using a four-level Likert scale. A higher score on the Likert scale indicates a higher level of competence.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">120</enrollment>
  <condition>Cultural Competency</condition>
  <condition>Mentoring</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cultural Competence Education</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants in the intervention group will attend cultural competence education</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Standard Mentoring Education</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants in the control group will complete standard mentoring education that does not include a cultural competence component</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cultural Competence Education</intervention_name>
    <description>Cultural competence education for participants in the intervention group comprises of completion of an online learning module and participation in an eight-hour training day. The educational content includes various topics related to cultural and linguistic diversity and cultural competence in mentoring.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cultural Competence Education</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Standard Mentoring Education</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants in the control group will not receive the educational intervention but will participate in standard mentoring education. This education is offered in an online learning environment and participants can complete the education at their own pace. The educational content focuses on general issues related to mentoring and does not contain topics specific to cultural competence in mentoring.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Standard Mentoring Education</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  be currently employed in any professional nursing role on any unit; have the skills to
             read and understand the Finnish language; and consent to participate in the study

        Exclusion Criteria:

        - be on long-term leave of absence or maternity leave; lack of skills to read and
        understand the Finnish language, decline to consent to participate in the study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Kristina Mikkonen, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>University of Oulu</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ashlee I Oikarainen, MHSc</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Oulu</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Healthcare organization in eastern Finland</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kuopio</city>
        <country>Finland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Healthcare organizations in Nordic Finland</name>
      <address>
        <city>Oulu</city>
        <country>Finland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Finland</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Oikarainen A, Mikkonen K, Tuomikoski AM, Elo S, Pitkänen S, Ruotsalainen H, Kääriäinen M. Mentors' competence in mentoring culturally and linguistically diverse nursing students during clinical placement. J Adv Nurs. 2018 Jan;74(1):148-159. doi: 10.1111/jan.13388. Epub 2017 Aug 1.</citation>
    <PMID>28702955</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Oikarainen A, Mikkonen K, Kenny A, Tomietto M, Tuomikoski AM, Meriläinen M, Miettunen J, Kääriäinen M. Educational interventions designed to develop nurses' cultural competence: A systematic review. Int J Nurs Stud. 2019 Oct;98:75-86. doi: 10.1016/j.ijnurstu.2019.06.005. Epub 2019 Jun 21.</citation>
    <PMID>31319338</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 13, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 20, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 21, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 23, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 23, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 24, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Oulu</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Ashlee Oikarainen</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Researcher</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

