<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04288206</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>SPAS Trial</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04288206</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Supracondylar Pinning Antibiotic Stewardship (SPAS) Trial</brief_title>
  <acronym>SPAS</acronym>
  <official_title>Supracondylar Pinning Antibiotic Stewardship (SPAS) Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Legacy Health System</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Legacy Health System</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Prospective, multi-center, randomized controlled trial studying infection rate with or
      without prophylactic antibiotics at the time of closed reduction and percutaneous pinning of
      pediatric supracondylar humerus fractures.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The goal of the SPAS trial will be to determine the role of prophylactic antibiotics in
      closed reduction and percutaneous fixation of pediatric supracondylar humerus fractures. The
      study will be designed as a prospective, double-blinded, two-arm, non-inferiority trial. The
      control arm will receive standard of care preoperative prophylactic antibiotics. The
      intervention group will receive a preoperative saline placebo. The primary outcome of the
      study will be the development of a surgical site infection, including all infections both
      superficial and deep. Secondary outcomes will include rate and type of post-operative
      complications in either group, to account for any drug-related adverse outcomes. The
      hypothesis is that this surgery is safe to perform without prophylactic antibiotics, and the
      investigators anticipate finding no difference in infection rates between the two groups.
      Inclusion criteria will consist of an isolated, closed, displaced supracondylar humerus
      fracture treated with closed reduction and temporary percutaneous pinning. Immunocompromised
      patients, pathological fractures, open fractures, polytrauma, skeletally mature patients, and
      those treated primarily with open reduction or those converted to open reduction will be
      excluded. Because of the low infection rate observed in this type of surgery, the sample size
      for the study is estimated at 600 patients per arm for adequate power. With a multicenter
      design, the expectation will be enrollment over the course of 1-2 years with a follow up of
      approximately 3 months post-surgical intervention per participant.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">July 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>intervention arm of intravenous cefazolin at the time of surgery (standard of care) vs placebo arm of intravenous normal saline at the time of surgery</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator)</masking>
    <masking_description>'study drug' will be prepared by a participating pharmacist and labeled with a study identification number. The drug will be otherwise not labeled with regard to the arm of the study. This will be delivered to the operating room and administered to the patient. The patient will be entered into a spreadsheet with the study identification number to be used later to evaluate the data. The enrolling/consenting surgeon, and the patient and consenting family member, will be masked to the arm of the study throughout.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>deep post operative infection</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months post intervention/surgery</time_frame>
    <description>rate of deep post operative infections at the surgical site, requiring treatment including possible hospital admission, intravenous antibiotics, or surgical intervention</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>superficial post operative infection</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months post intervention/surgery</time_frame>
    <description>rate of superficial post operative infections at the surgical site, requiring treatment limited to oral antibiotics, local wound care, pin removal, or cast change/removal</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">1200</enrollment>
  <condition>Supracondylar Humerus Fracture</condition>
  <condition>Infection</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patient will receive 'study drug' which is comprised of 300 mL of normal saline without any medication/antibiotic, which will be delivered by intravenous means at the time of surgery.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cefazolin prophylaxis</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patient will receive 'study drug' which is comprised of weight-based dose of cefazolin mixed in 300 mL of normal saline, which will be delivered by intravenous means at the time of surgery.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cefazolin</intervention_name>
    <description>intravenous cefazolin is being evaluated as a pre-operative prophylactic antibiotic measure with primary outcome being post operative infection rate among participants.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cefazolin prophylaxis</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>normal saline</intervention_name>
    <description>intravenous normal saline placebo</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo control</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Closed, isolated extension type supracondylar humerus fracture, Gartland type 2, 3, or
             4

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Inability to secure consent

          -  Open fractures

          -  Polytrauma

          -  Pathologic fractures

          -  Flexion type fracture

          -  Associated compartment syndrome

          -  Allergy to cefazolin which precludes its use

          -  Skeletally mature patients or patients greater than 18 years of age

          -  Medical comorbidities including immunocompromised state, active infection, and any
             associated bone, endocrine, or neoplastic conditions contributing to local or
             generalized abnormal bone mineralization.

          -  Inability to attain satisfactory reduction and fixation via closed manipulation,
             resulting in conversion to open reduction
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>18 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Bob Umberhandt, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Physician within Legacy Health System</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Justin N Brohard, DO</last_name>
    <phone>2177913888</phone>
    <email>justinbrohard@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Bob Umberhandt, MD</last_name>
    <phone>5034134488</phone>
    <email>rumberha@lhs.org</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <reference>
    <citation>Campbell KA, Stein S, Looze C, Bosco JA. Antibiotic stewardship in orthopaedic surgery: principles and practice. J Am Acad Orthop Surg. 2014 Dec;22(12):772-81. doi: 10.5435/JAAOS-22-12-772. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25425612</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Prokuski L. Prophylactic antibiotics in orthopaedic surgery. J Am Acad Orthop Surg. 2008 May;16(5):283-93. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18460689</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Johnson SP, Zhong L, Chung KC, Waljee JF. Perioperative Antibiotics for Clean Hand Surgery: A National Study. J Hand Surg Am. 2018 May;43(5):407-416.e1. doi: 10.1016/j.jhsa.2017.11.018. Epub 2018 Feb 3.</citation>
    <PMID>29398330</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Formaini N, Jacob P, Willis L, Kean JR. Evaluating the use of preoperative antibiotics in pediatric orthopaedic surgery. J Pediatr Orthop. 2012 Oct-Nov;32(7):737-40. doi: 10.1097/BPO.0b013e318269543b.</citation>
    <PMID>22955540</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rizvi M, Bille B, Holtom P, Schnall SB. The role of prophylactic antibiotics in elective hand surgery. J Hand Surg Am. 2008 Mar;33(3):413-20. doi: 10.1016/j.jhsa.2007.12.017. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18343301</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Berríos-Torres SI, Umscheid CA, Bratzler DW, Leas B, Stone EC, Kelz RR, Reinke CE, Morgan S, Solomkin JS, Mazuski JE, Dellinger EP, Itani KMF, Berbari EF, Segreti J, Parvizi J, Blanchard J, Allen G, Kluytmans JAJW, Donlan R, Schecter WP; Healthcare Infection Control Practices Advisory Committee. Centers for Disease Control and Prevention Guideline for the Prevention of Surgical Site Infection, 2017. JAMA Surg. 2017 Aug 1;152(8):784-791. doi: 10.1001/jamasurg.2017.0904. Erratum in: JAMA Surg. 2017 Aug 1;152(8):803.</citation>
    <PMID>28467526</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Vaquero-Picado A, González-Morán G, Moraleda L. Management of supracondylar fractures of the humerus in children. EFORT Open Rev. 2018 Oct 1;3(10):526-540. doi: 10.1302/2058-5241.3.170049. eCollection 2018 Oct.</citation>
    <PMID>30662761</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Iobst CA, Spurdle C, King WF, Lopez M. Percutaneous pinning of pediatric supracondylar humerus fractures with the semisterile technique: the Miami experience. J Pediatr Orthop. 2007 Jan-Feb;27(1):17-22. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>17195791</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schroeder NO, Seeley MA, Hariharan A, Farley FA, Caird MS, Li Y. Utility of Postoperative Antibiotics After Percutaneous Pinning of Pediatric Supracondylar Humerus Fractures. J Pediatr Orthop. 2017 Sep;37(6):363-367. doi: 10.1097/BPO.0000000000000685.</citation>
    <PMID>26558958</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bashyal RK, Chu JY, Schoenecker PL, Dobbs MB, Luhmann SJ, Gordon JE. Complications after pinning of supracondylar distal humerus fractures. J Pediatr Orthop. 2009 Oct-Nov;29(7):704-8. doi: 10.1097/BPO.0b013e3181b768ac.</citation>
    <PMID>20104149</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 24, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 26, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 28, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 26, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 26, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 28, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Legacy Health System</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Justin Brohard</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Co-Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>antibiotic stewardship</keyword>
  <keyword>post operative infection</keyword>
  <keyword>pediatric</keyword>
  <keyword>cefazolin</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Humeral Fractures</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cefazolin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>All data will be de-identified prior to sharing amongst participating researchers. Each participating site will maintain a spreadsheet of participants with their study identification numbers. This information will be de-identified prior to sharing with the PI and safety monitor at LHS. This will occur at a midterm assessment for safety, as well as at the completion of data collection when it is time to process and analyze the data.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

