<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04281043</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>QoL Robot</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04281043</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Quality of Life After Robotic Surgery for Endometrial Cancer</brief_title>
  <acronym>QoL</acronym>
  <official_title>Quality of Life After Robotic Surgery as Primary Treatment for Endometrial Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Sahlgrenska University Hospital, Sweden</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Hjalmar Svensson Foundation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Assar Gabrielsson Foundation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Göteborg Medical Society</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Sahlgrenska University Hospital, Sweden</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to investigate how robotic assisted laparoscopic surgery affects
      the quality of life of women who are treated with primary surgery for endometrial cancer. So
      far, very little has been published and basically no long-term follow-up.

      Included patients respond to questionnaires preoperatively, 2 weeks after surgery and 3
      months and 12 months after surgery.

      Each patient thus answers the questionnaires (the same) on four occasions. The questionnaires
      used are validated and used extensively internationally. The first survey has two parts,
      QLQ30 and the module for endometrial cancer EN24. In addition the study includes use PHQ -9
      and GAD 7.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Objective: In a pilot study to prospectively analyze the quality of life using QLQ-C30,
      EN-24, PHQ-9 and GAD7 in women undergoing primary surgery with robotic assisted laparoscopy
      for corpus cancer before and up to one year after surgery.

      The study aims to describe how, to what extent and when in relation to primary surgery
      women's quality of life is affected after the diagnosis of endometrial cancer. The long-term
      goal of the work is to be able to deploy any resources if needs exist, and in this case at a
      time when they are most useful, to promote the quality of life of the affected women.

      Question: How and when is the quality of life of women undergoing surgery for endometrial
      cancer affected? Is there any particular area / domain that is affected more than others and
      is this impact persistent over time? Method: The international and validated survey, QLQ-C30
      with the addition of EN24, developed by the European Organization for Research and Treatment
      of Cancer (EORTC) for quality of life measurement specifically for endometrial cancer in
      addition to PHQ-9 and GAD7 to evaluate depression and anxiety symtoms, is planned to be used
      just before primary surgery, 1-2 weeks, 3 months and 1 years postoperatively.

      Referens to the QLQ30 questionnaire below.

      Patients are included at Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology, Sahlgrenska University
      Hospital, Gothenburg, Sweden for one year.

      All patients included should give their oral and written consent. All data will be registered
      coded and analyzed without personal identification number according to the scoring manual
      from EORTC.

      Aaronson NK, Ahmedzai S, Bergman B, Bullinger M, Cull A, Duez NJ, Filiberti A, Flechtner H,
      Fleishman SB, de Haes JCJM, Kaasa S, Klee MC, Osoba D, Razavi D, Rofe PB, Schraub S, Sneeuw
      KCA, Sullivan M, Takeda F.

      The European Organisation for Research and Treatment of Cancer QLQ-C30: A quality-of-life
      instrument for use in international clinical trials in oncology. Journal of the National
      Cancer Institute 1993; 85: 365-376.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 15, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 15, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of Life at 3 months</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Quality of Life at 3 months postoperatively compared to preoperatively The QLQ-C30 is composed of both multi-item scales and single-item measures. These include five functional scales, three symptom scales, a global health status / QoL scale, and six single items. Each of the multi-item scales includes a different set of items - no item occurs in more than one scale.
Allofthescalesandsingle-itemmeasuresrangeinscorefrom0to100. Ahighscalescore represents a higher response level.
Thus a high score for a functional scale represents a high / healthy level of functioning, a high score for the global health status / QoL represents a high QoL, but a high score for a symptom scale / item represents a high level of symptomatology / problems.
The attached module EN24 has 3 functional scales and several symptom scales, which scores follows the same system.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of Life at 12 months</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Quality of Life at 12 months postoperatively compared to preoperatively The QLQ-C30 is composed of both multi-item scales and single-item measures. These include five functional scales, three symptom scales, a global health status / QoL scale, and six single items. Each of the multi-item scales includes a different set of items - no item occurs in more than one scale.
Allofthescalesandsingle-itemmeasuresrangeinscorefrom0to100. Ahighscalescore represents a higher response level.
Thus a high score for a functional scale represents a high / healthy level of functioning, a high score for the global health status / QoL represents a high QoL, but a high score for a symptom scale / item represents a high level of symptomatology / problems.
The attached module EN24 has 3 functional scales and several symptom scales, which scores follows the same system.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Anxiety scores</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Scores on GAD7 3 months postoperatively compared to preoperatively Scores 0-21, were a higher scores is associated with more symptoms.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Anxiety scores</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Scores on GAD7 12 months postoperatively compared to preoperatively</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Depression scores</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Scores on PHQ9 3 months postoperatively compared to preoperatively. Scores 0-27 were a high score is associated with more symptoms.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Depression scores</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Scores on PHQ9 12 months postoperatively compared to preoperatively. Scores 0-27 were a high score is associated with more symptoms.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Quality of Life</condition>
  <condition>Endometrial Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Surgery--Complications</condition>
  <condition>Gynecologic Cancer</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        All patients planned for primary surgery with robotic technique for endometrial cancer at
        Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology, Sahlgrenska University Hospital, Gothenburg,
        Sweden will be asked to participate.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Woman over 18 years of age

          -  scheduled for primary surgery for histologically verified endometrial cancer
             (regardless of histological type or degree),

          -  tumor clinically restricted to the uterus (presumptive FIGO stage I or II),

          -  speaks and reads Swedish,

          -  capable of completing the questionnaire independently.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Clinical or radiological cancer outside the uterus

          -  preoperative radio / chemotherapy.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Months</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Anna Lindfors</last_name>
    <phone>+46313429205</phone>
    <email>anna.m.lindfors@vgregion.se</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Pernilla Dahm Kähler, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+46313421000</phone>
    <email>pernilla.dahm-kahler@vgregion.se</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>1Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology, Sahlgrenska University Hospital, Gothenburg, Sweden</name>
      <address>
        <city>Gothenburg</city>
        <zip>41345</zip>
        <country>Sweden</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Anna Lindfors</last_name>
      <phone>+46313429205</phone>
      <email>anna.m.lindfors@vgregion.se</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Pernilla Dahm Kähler, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>+46313421000</phone>
      <email>pernilla.dahm-kahler@vgregion.se</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Sweden</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 18, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 20, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 21, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 20, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 20, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 21, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Sahlgrenska University Hospital, Sweden</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Anna Lindfors</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Medical Doctor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Endometrial Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

