<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04283851</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>992/19 S-IV</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04283851</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Dynamic Parameters in Evaluation of Fluid Responsiveness</brief_title>
  <official_title>Dynamic Parameters in Evaluation of Fluid Resposiveness in Cardiac Surgery Patients in the Early Postoperative Period</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Charles University, Czech Republic</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Charles University, Czech Republic</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Intravenous infusion of fluids in patients after surgery is a very important part of
      treatment. However, administering too much or too little fluid can lengthen the stay in the
      intensive care unit or even harm the patient. Therefore, fluid therapy should be tailored to
      the individual needs of each patient. Several methods are available to assess which patients
      will likely benefit from fluid administration. However, each of these methods is useful only
      under certain conditions. The study aims to explore some less-known, yet promising tests
      which could make adequate fluid administration more precise and easier to achieve.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Adequate fluid therapy is one of the most important variables influencing patient outcome in
      intensive care. Fluid therapy should be tailored to the individual needs of each patient.
      Static parameters of preload have proved to be of little predictive value, therefore dynamic
      parameters are preferred for prediction of fluid responsiveness. Ideally, the cardiac output
      increases by 10% after a standardised fluid challenge. There are several methods already
      available to differentiate fluid-responsive from fluid-unresponsive patients, most notably
      the passive leg-raise. However, each of these methods has its own set of indications and
      contraindications. Also, a combination of tests could guide clinician´s decision in cases
      where the results of a single test are not entirely conclusive. Therefore, it would be
      desirable to add some less-known methods for prediction of fluid responsiveness, like the
      end-expiratory and end-inspiratory occlusion tests along with the assessment of diastolic
      properties of cardiac ventricles.

      The aims of the study are:

        -  to determine the optimal increase in LVOT VTi to reliably predict fluid responsiveness

        -  to explore the accuracy of echocardiographic LVOT VTi evaluation during end-expiratory
           and end-inspiratory occlusion tests and their combination

        -  to assess the difference in echocardiographic properties of cardiac ventricles in
           fluid-responsive and fluid-unresponsive patients

        -  to compare the prediction based on echocardiography with the response to a standardised
           fluid challenge

        -  to assess the feasibility and practicality of echocardiographic monitoring in
           anesthetised cardiac surgery patients in intensive care
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 1, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 1, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Prediction of fluid responsiveness</measure>
    <time_frame>The first hour after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>fluid responsiveness is defined as a 10 % increase in cardiac output after a standardised fluid challenge; the prediction will be made based on the diastolic properties of both cardiac ventricles and the changes in LVOT VTi during end-expiratory and end-inspiratory occlusion tests</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Echocardiographic evaluation of LVOT VTi and its changes</measure>
    <time_frame>The first hour after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>TTE measurement of LVOT VTi and its changes during end-expiratory, end-inspiratory occlusion tests and after a standardised fluid challenge of a colloid</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cardiac output monitoring with Vigileo FloTrac</measure>
    <time_frame>The first hour after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>continous measurement of cardiac output with Vigileo FloTrac and its correlation with the changes of echocardiographic parameters</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Arterial pressure response</measure>
    <time_frame>The first hour after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>invasive arterial blood pressure</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Heart rate response</measure>
    <time_frame>The first hour after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>heart rate</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Oxygenation response</measure>
    <time_frame>The first hour after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>pulse oxymetry</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Central venous pressure response</measure>
    <time_frame>The first hour after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>central venous pressure</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Hypovolemia</condition>
  <condition>Hypotension</condition>
  <condition>Surgery</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>testing functional haemodynamic parameters for preload assessment</intervention_name>
    <description>dynamic testing of preload responsivity plus echocardiography</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        All patients undergoing elective CABG at the Deparment of Cardiovascular Surgery of the
        General University Hospital in Prague, who meet all the inclusion criteria and give their
        informed consent.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  patients after elective coronary artery bypass grafting

          -  hypovolemia indicated for volumotherapy by the attending physician based on clinical
             and laboratory signs (ScvO2 under 65 % with serum lactate above 2 mmol/l, increase of
             vasopressoric support with CVP under 5 mmHg)

          -  intubated and ventilated patients

          -  sedation without spontaneous breathing activity

          -  no pulmonary pathology on X-ray after surgery

          -  normal systolic and diastolic function of both ventricles (left ventricular ejection
             fraction above 50 %, TAPSE of the right ventricle above 20 mm, FAC of the right
             ventricle above 30 %)

          -  informed consent signed before surgery

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  aggresive artificial ventilation (PEEP above 10 cmH2O, Pmax above 30 cm H2O)

          -  ARDS, pneumothorax, fluidothorax

          -  hemodynamically significant valvular disease

          -  atrial fibrillation or other arrhythmia with irregular heartbeat

          -  intraabdominal hypertension with pressures above 15 mmHg

          -  open thorax

          -  bad echogenicity
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Michal Porizka, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Dept of Anest and Intensive Care, General University Hospital, Prague</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Jan Horejsek, MD</last_name>
    <phone>• +420 224 96 2733</phone>
    <email>jan.horejsek@vfn.cz</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Michal Porizka, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>• +420 224 96 2733</phone>
    <email>michal.porizka@vfn.cz</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Dept of Anaesthesia and Intensive Care, General University Hospital, 1st Medical Faculty, Charles University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Prague 2</city>
        <zip>120 00</zip>
        <country>Czechia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Martin Balik, A/Prof</last_name>
      <phone>+420224963366</phone>
      <email>martin.balik@vfn.cz</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Martin Balik, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Michal Porizka, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Miroslav Navratil, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Czechia</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Georges D, de Courson H, Lanchon R, Sesay M, Nouette-Gaulain K, Biais M. End-expiratory occlusion maneuver to predict fluid responsiveness in the intensive care unit: an echocardiographic study. Crit Care. 2018 Feb 8;22(1):32. doi: 10.1186/s13054-017-1938-0.</citation>
    <PMID>29415773</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Monnet X, Marik PE, Teboul JL. Prediction of fluid responsiveness: an update. Ann Intensive Care. 2016 Dec;6(1):111. doi: 10.1186/s13613-016-0216-7. Epub 2016 Nov 17. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>27858374</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Monnet X, Bleibtreu A, Ferré A, Dres M, Gharbi R, Richard C, Teboul JL. Passive leg-raising and end-expiratory occlusion tests perform better than pulse pressure variation in patients with low respiratory system compliance. Crit Care Med. 2012 Jan;40(1):152-7. doi: 10.1097/CCM.0b013e31822f08d7.</citation>
    <PMID>21926581</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Monnet X, Osman D, Ridel C, Lamia B, Richard C, Teboul JL. Predicting volume responsiveness by using the end-expiratory occlusion in mechanically ventilated intensive care unit patients. Crit Care Med. 2009 Mar;37(3):951-6. doi: 10.1097/CCM.0b013e3181968fe1.</citation>
    <PMID>19237902</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Marques NR, De Riese J, Yelverton BC, McQuitty C, Jupiter D, Willmann K, Salter M, Kinsky M, Johnston WE. Diastolic Function and Peripheral Venous Pressure as Indices for Fluid Responsiveness in Cardiac Surgical Patients. J Cardiothorac Vasc Anesth. 2019 Aug;33(8):2208-2215. doi: 10.1053/j.jvca.2019.01.007. Epub 2019 Jan 4.</citation>
    <PMID>30738752</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pagourelias ED, Efthimiadis GK, Parcharidou DG, Gossios TD, Kamperidis V, Karoulas T, Karvounis H, Styliadis IH. Prognostic value of right ventricular diastolic function indices in hypertrophic cardiomyopathy. Eur J Echocardiogr. 2011 Nov;12(11):809-17. doi: 10.1093/ejechocard/jer126. Epub 2011 Aug 15.</citation>
    <PMID>21846651</PMID>
  </reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Jozwiak M, Depret F, Teboul JL, Alphonsine JE, Lai C, Richard C, Monnet X. Predicting Fluid Responsiveness in Critically Ill Patients by Using Combined End-Expiratory and End-Inspiratory Occlusions With Echocardiography. Crit Care Med. 2017 Nov;45(11):e1131-e1138. doi: 10.1097/CCM.0000000000002704.</citation>
    <PMID>28857907</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>February 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 27, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 23, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 25, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 23, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 23, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 25, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Charles University, Czech Republic</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Martin Balik</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator: Jan Horejsek, General University Hospital in Prague</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>fluid responsiveness</keyword>
  <keyword>fluid administration</keyword>
  <keyword>volume expansion</keyword>
  <keyword>end-expiratory occlusion test</keyword>
  <keyword>end-inspiratory occlusion test</keyword>
  <keyword>diastolic parameters of cardiac ventricles</keyword>
  <keyword>echocardiography</keyword>
  <keyword>heart-lung interactions</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hypotension</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hypovolemia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

