<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03968718</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Istitutotumori</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03968718</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>PATIENT VOICES Integration of Systematic Assessment of Patient Reported Outcomes Within Clinical Oncology Practice</brief_title>
  <official_title>PATIENT VOICES - A Project for the Integration of Systematic Assessment of Patient Reported Outcomes Within an E-Health Program in an Italian Comprehensive Cancer Center</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Fondazione IRCCS Istituto Nazionale dei Tumori, Milano</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Fondazione IRCCS Istituto Nazionale dei Tumori, Milano</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Listening to &quot;patient voices&quot; in terms of symptoms, emotional status, satisfaction with care
      and information received, represents a major shift in medicine. It is in fact crucial in
      medical decision making and patient empowerment, especially in cancer care.

      Patient Reported Outcomes Measures (PROMs) and in particular electronically assessed PROMS
      (ePROMS), have been identified as potentially effective tools to systematically gather
      patient voices. Despite international extensive and growing interest, systematic PROM
      collection is not widely implemented in routine cancer care, due to barriers at various
      levels.

      The PATIENT VOICES is a project aimed at achieving a stepwise inclusion and integration of
      PROMs within routine clinical practice at the FONDAZIONE IRCCS ISTITUTO NAZIONALE
      TUMORI-MILANO. Phase I of the Patient Voices project (pilot and feasibility testing), will be
      the focus of the present study and its results will be the base for subsequent phases
      (implementation and impact assessment).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Study aims of this phase are:

        -  Assessing the use and attitudes toward PROMs by clinicians in a comprehensive cancer
           centre.

        -  Reviewing and compare pre-existing ePROMS assessment systems.

        -  Developing and pilot testing a flexible system for electronic collection of PROMs.

        -  Assessing feasibility of ePROM assessment of physical symptoms, psychological distress
           and patient satisfaction.

        -  Identifying barriers to and developing strategies for the final implementation and
           integration of routine ePROMs into the clinical practice.

      The project will last 2 years. Longitudinal and cross-sectional studies will be carried out
      with the aim to evaluate compliance, acceptability, and usability of a routine ePROM
      assessment system by both patients and clinicians. Participants will be enrolled among
      patients attending 3 out-patient clinics (physical symptom), 3 inpatient wards (psychological
      distress) and 5 multidisciplinary teams (patient satisfaction). The Edmonton symptom
      assessment scale, the Distress Thermometer, and a questionnaire adapted from the Bench-Can
      and EURACAN projects plus the institutional customer satisfaction survey, will be used in the
      three studies. Qualitative methods will be used identify patient and clinician related
      barriers to ePROM assessment and to pinpoint engagement strategies to promote its use in
      routine cancer care. Semi-structured interviews and focus groups will be carried out.

      Quantitative and qualitative studies will respectively enroll 600 and 40 participants.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">May 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Health Services Research</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of patient compliant with ePROM assessment</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline (one-time point only)</time_frame>
    <description>Compliant patients are defined as patients successfully completing ePROM assessment.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of clinical encounters using ePROM assessment</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline (one-time point only)</time_frame>
    <description>Clinical encounters using ePROM assessment are encounters in which the clinician gets access to symptom or psychological distress data collected by the patients through ePROM assessment</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of patient compliant with ePROM repeated assessments</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Proportion patients who succesfully complete ePROMs assessments at each follow-up visit</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of refusals</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline (one-time point only)</time_frame>
    <description>Proportion of patients refusing to use the system and reason for refusal</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">640</enrollment>
  <condition>Neoplasms</condition>
  <condition>Symptoms and Signs</condition>
  <condition>Psychological Distress</condition>
  <condition>Satisfaction, Consumer</condition>
  <condition>Quality of Life</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Systematic ePROMs Assessment</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Intervention: The intervention is constituted by a Systematic ePROMs Assessment in routine cancer care in a comprehensive cancer centre.
This will involve preliminary sensitization and training of both clinicians and patients towards the use of ePROMs.
Data filled in by patients through electronic devices will be prompt made available to the clinician during the patient examination.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Systematic ePROMs Assessment</intervention_name>
    <description>Depending on the care setting, eligible patients will be asked to fill in one of the following e-PROMs assessment:
Edmonton symptom assessment scale (ESAS-r) (outpatients)
Distress Thermometer (inpatients)
An ad hoc questionnaire adapted from the Bench-Can and EURACAN projects plus the institutional customer satisfaction survey (patients followed by multidisciplinary teams)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Systematic ePROMs Assessment</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  age 18 years or above

          -  a verified cancer diagnosis

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  inability to fill in PROMs due to cognitive impairment, psychological disturbance or
             language problems as judged by the study personnel.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Cinzia Brunelli, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Fondazione IRCCS Istituto Nazionale Tumori, Milan, Italy</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Cinzia Brunelli, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+390223903387</phone>
    <email>cinzia.brunelli@istitutotumori.mi.it</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Fondazione IRCCS Istituto Nazionale dei Tumori</name>
      <address>
        <city>Milano</city>
        <state>Milan</state>
        <zip>20133</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Cinzia Brunelli, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Claudia Borreani, PsyD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Marco Bellazzi, EngD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Augusto Caraceni, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Anna Roli, RN</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Giovanni Apolone, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Italy</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 5, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 29, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 30, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 29, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 29, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 30, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Fondazione IRCCS Istituto Nazionale dei Tumori, Milano</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Cinzia Brunelli</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Patient Reported Outcome Measures</keyword>
  <keyword>Feasibility study</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Signs and Symptoms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

