<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03966508</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HFS reliability</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03966508</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Reliability of Measuring the Area and Intensity of Secondary Hyperalgesia Induced by High Frequency Stimulation</brief_title>
  <official_title>Test-retest Reliability of Measuring the Area and Intensity of Secondary Hyperalgesia Induced by High Frequency Stimulation of Skin Nociceptors</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Université Catholique de Louvain</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Université Catholique de Louvain</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study is designed to evaluate the method of assessing the and intensity areas of
      secondary hyperalgesia induced by High Frequency Stimulation (HFS). Measures of the areas of
      secondary hyperalgesia will take place on two experimental days separated by a minimum of two
      weeks. Each experimental day, the areas of secondary hyperalgesia will be assessed three
      times, starting 30 minutes following HFS. Furthermore, the investigators will assess if
      anxiety, catastrophization, stress and demographic variables modulate the extend of
      hyperalgesia.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This prospective cohort study is designed to evaluate the method of assessing the areas and
      intensity of secondary hyperalgesia following High Frequency Stimulation (HFS), and will
      consist of two experimental days separated by a minimum of two weeks. During the two each
      session (Day1 and Day2), subjects will go through the HFS procedure on the same forearm.
      Then, after a 30 minutes break, the area and intensity of secondary hyperalgesia induced by
      HFS will be assessed three times (Time9-14), with a two-minute break between each assessment.

      Before the experiment, subjects will fill two questionnaires by email : the Spielberger Trait
      anxiety inventory and the Pain catastrophization scale.The first experimental day, the
      patients will be seated on a chair and informed consent will be gained. Subjects will provide
      demographic information to the researcher (age, gender, size) (Time1). Then, the forearm skin
      of the selected arm will be marked with a pen to improve the precision of subsequent
      measures. The subject will then observe a period of rest for 5 minutes, to provide a baseline
      measure of heart rate variability.

      Next, the patients will be asked to rate the pain induced by pin-prick stimulation in the
      area surrounding the electrode (Time2).

      Following standardized explanation of the HFS procedure, the subject will fill the
      Spielberger State anxiety inventory (Time5), and HFS will be applied on the volar forearm
      (6-10 cm distal to the cubital fossa) (Time6). To avoid any confounding effect of handedness,
      the arm onto which HFS will be applied (dominant vs nondominant) will be counterbalanced
      across participants. In summary, HFS will consist of 12 trains of 42 Hz electrical pulses
      (pulse width: 2 ms) lasting 1 s each. The time interval between each train will 10 s. The
      intensity of stimulation will be 5mA. Heart rate variability during the HFS procedure will be
      monitored.

      After a 25 minutes break the heart rate variability will be assessed a third time during 5
      minutes. During the break, subjects will be asked to stay seated, to fill the Pain
      Catastrophizing scale (short-version) and give a rating from 0-100 for the pain and stress
      experienced during the HFS procedure (Time7).

      Following this break, the area of secondary hyperalgesia will be assessed with a calibrated
      128 mN pinprick probe (The Pin Prick, MRC Systems GmbH, Heidelger, Germany) (Time9). Pokes of
      1-second duration will be provided at a frequency of 0.5 Hz, starting well outside and
      approaching the stimulation site with steps of 0,5 cm from 4 different directions towards the
      application site. Participants will be asked to keep their eyes closed during the entire
      mapping procedure. Then, participants will rate the pain induced by pin-prick stimulation in
      the area surrounding the electrode (Time10). This procedure will be conducted three times,
      with a two-minute break between each assessment (Time 11-14).

      The second experimental day (Day2), the procedure will be similar to the first, but informed
      consent and the Spielberger Trait anxiety inventory and the Pain catastrophization scale will
      not be filled.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">April 15, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">August 31, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">August 31, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The area of secondary hyperalgesia</measure>
    <time_frame>30 minutes (Time9), 35 minutes (Time11) and 40 minutes (Time13) after the application of HFS. There will be two HFS session (Day1 and Day2) separated by at least 15 days. Outcomes are taken at Day1 at Time9, 11 &amp; 13 and on Day 2 at Time9, 11 &amp; 13</time_frame>
    <description>the area of secondary hyperalgesia (cm square) will be assessed with a calibrated 128 mN pinprick probe (The Pin Prick, MRC Systems GmbH, Heidelger, Germany). Pokes of 1-second duration will be provided at a frequency of 0.5 Hz, starting well outside and approaching the stimulation site with steps of 0,5 cm from 4 different directions towards the application site. Participants will be asked to keep their eyes closed during the entire mapping procedure.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pin-prick pain in the area of secondary hyperalgesia</measure>
    <time_frame>5 minutes before (Time2), 33 minutes (Time10), 40 minutes (Time12) and 43 minutes (Time14) after the application of HFS. Outcomes are taken at Day1 at Time2, 10, 12 &amp; 14 and on Day 2 at Time2, 10, 12 &amp; 14</time_frame>
    <description>participants will rate the pain induced by pin-prick stimulation in the area surrounding the electrode on a numerical rating scale ranging from 0 (no perception) to 100 (maximal pain), with 50 representing the transition from nonpainful to painful domains of sensation</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Spielberger State Anxiety inventory (total score)</measure>
    <time_frame>Just before the application of HFS (time 5). Outcome is taken at Day 1 at Time5 and on Day 2 at Time5.</time_frame>
    <description>questionnaire assessing the state of anxiety. The score will range from 20 (low state anxiety) to 80 (high state anxiety).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Spielberger Trait Anxiety inventory (total score)</measure>
    <time_frame>On day 0, one day before the first testing session (Day 1)</time_frame>
    <description>questionnaire assessing the trait of anxiety. The score will range from 20 (low trait anxiety) to 80 (high trait anxiety). This questionnaire will be sent by email to the participant.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pain Catastrophization Scale (total score)</measure>
    <time_frame>On day 0, one day before the first testing session (Day 1)</time_frame>
    <description>questionnaire to assess thoughts and emotions in response to pain. The score will range from 0 (low catastrophization) to 52 (high catastrophization).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pain catastrophization scale modified version</measure>
    <time_frame>Just after the application of HFS (time 7). Outcome is taken at Day 1 at Time7 and on Day 2 at Time7.</time_frame>
    <description>questionnaire to assess thoughts and emotions in response to a specific painful event. The score will range from 0 (low catastrophization) to 24 (high catastrophization).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Stress assessment using a Visual Analog Stress scale</measure>
    <time_frame>Just after the application of HFS (time 7). Outcome is taken at Day 1 at Time 7 and on Day 2 at Time 7.</time_frame>
    <description>Stress on a scale from 0 (low stress) to 100 (maximal stress).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Detection threshold to a single electrical pulse (in mA)</measure>
    <time_frame>2 minutes before the application of HFS (Time3). Outcomes are taken at Day1 at Time2 on Day2 at Time2</time_frame>
    <description>Lowest intensity at which the participant feels the electrical pulse</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Age</measure>
    <time_frame>10 minutes before the application of HFS (Time1). Outcomes are taken at Day1 at Time1 on Day2 at Time1</time_frame>
    <description>Self-declared age of the subject</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Size</measure>
    <time_frame>10 minutes before the application of HFS (Time1). Outcomes are taken at Day1 at Time1 on Day2 at Time1</time_frame>
    <description>Self-declared size of the subject</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Gender</measure>
    <time_frame>10 minutes before the application of HFS (Time1). Outcomes are taken at Day1 at Time1 on Day2 at Time1</time_frame>
    <description>Self-declared gender of the subject</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Weight</measure>
    <time_frame>10 minutes before the application of HFS (Time1). Outcomes are taken at Day1 at Time1 on Day2 at Time1</time_frame>
    <description>Self-declared weight of the subject</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Heart rate variability</measure>
    <time_frame>Continuous assessment from Time1 (10 minutes before the application of HFS) to Time15 (45 minutes after the application of HFS) during each session. Outcome is taken from Time1-Time15 during each of the two testing sessions (Day1 and at Day2)</time_frame>
    <description>changes in the time interval between heart beats through the study completion.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">32</enrollment>
  <condition>Hyperalgesia, Secondary</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>hyperalgesia measurement</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>High-frequency electrical stimulation</intervention_name>
    <description>High-frequency stimulation will be applied on the volar forearm (6-10 cm distal to the cubital fossa). To avoid any confounding effect of handedness, the arm onto which HFS will be applied twice (dominant vs nondominant) will be counterbalanced across participants. HFS will consist of 12 trains of 42 Hz electrical pulses lasting 1 s each. The time interval between each train will be 10 s. The intensity of stimulation will be 5mA. Electrical pulses will be delivered to the skin using a specifically-designed electrode designed: the cathode consists of 16 blunt stainless-steel pins with a diameter of 0.2 mm protruding 1 mm from the base. The 16 pins are placed in a circle with a diameter of 10 mm. The anode consists of a surrounding stainless-steel ring having an inner diameter of 22 mm and an outer diameter of 40 mm. This procedure induces secondary pinprick hyperalgesia (an increase in pinprick sensitivity in a large area of the skin).</description>
    <arm_group_label>hyperalgesia measurement</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Male or female sex

          -  age&gt;18 years and &lt;40 years

          -  be fluent either in English or French

          -  ability to provide informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  experiencing a pre-existing pain condition

          -  self-reported medication (except contraceptives) consumption within 48 hours before
             experimental day and/or self-reported recreational drug use

          -  presenting any medical conditions, including heart, neurological, dermatological and
             psychiatric diseases

          -  participation to more than 6 hours per week of sport

          -  exhibiting sign of damage at or near the ventral forearm

          -  tattoos on the tested forearm

          -  Failure to cooperate to the tests
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>40 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UCLouvain</name>
      <address>
        <city>Brussels</city>
        <zip>1200</zip>
        <country>Belgium</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Belgium</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>April 30, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 27, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 29, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 18, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 18, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 19, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>central sensitization</keyword>
  <keyword>High-frequency electrical stimulation</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Neoplasm Metastasis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hyperalgesia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <provided_document_section>
    <provided_document>
      <document_type>Statistical Analysis Plan</document_type>
      <document_has_protocol>No</document_has_protocol>
      <document_has_icf>No</document_has_icf>
      <document_has_sap>Yes</document_has_sap>
      <document_date>May 27, 2019</document_date>
      <document_url>https://ClinicalTrials.gov/ProvidedDocs/08/NCT03966508/SAP_000.pdf</document_url>
    </provided_document>
  </provided_document_section>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

