<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03963726</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>BYSY-CKMA-LM</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03963726</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Clinical Efficacy of Stereotactic Radiotherapy and Microwave Ablation for Liver Metastases From Colorectal Cancer.</brief_title>
  <acronym>Ckvsmalm</acronym>
  <official_title>Clinical Efficacy of Stereotactic Radiotherapy and Microwave Ablation for Liver Metastases From Colorectal Cancer: a Prospective Multicenter Cohort Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Peking University Third Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>The fifth medical center of PLA general hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Tengzhou Central People's Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Guangxi Ruikang Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Hunan Aerospace Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Beijing Ditan Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Peking University Third Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>Yes</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Data of 100 colorectal cancer patients with liver metastases who received stereotactic
      radiotherapy of Cyberknife or microwave ablation in the multicenter of the research group
      from June 2019 to May 2021 were collected, as well as follow-up data.To evaluate the clinical
      efficacy of stereotactic radiotherapy and microwave ablation in liver metastases.In addition,
      the local control rate and side effects of stereotactic radiotherapy and microwave ablation
      in the treatment of liver metastases were explored, and the efficacy and safety of different
      doses of stereotactic radiotherapy were determined.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      In the study，data of 100 colorectal cancer patients with liver metastases who received
      Cyberknife stereotactic radiotherapy or microwave ablation in the multi-center of the
      research group from June 2019 to May 2021 were collected, as well as follow-up data.

        1. Radiation: Stereotactic Radiotherapy 1.1 Equipment: Accuray VSI Cyberknife stereotactic
           radiotherapy platform, simulated positioning CT machine, MR, positron emission computed
           tomography PET-CT, vacuum pad.

           1.2 Radiotherapy localization: CT, MRI and PETCT were used to simulate localization.

           1.3 Relevant Definitions of Tumor Targets CT, MRI, PET-CT fusion, combined with MRI
           location and PET-CT location image for sketching.

           To delineate target areas and organs at risk. GTV: Combining localization and fusion
           images to delineate the tumors seen PTV = GTV + 0-10mm Dangerous organs: The stomach,
           duodenum, jejunum, ileum, colon, spinal cord and esophagus were delineated on the base
           sequence of CT plain scan.

           The target area should be approved by at least one physician in charge or by a physician
           in charge.

           1.4 Target volume radiation dose: According to the volume, location, organ function and
           other factors, the dosage of radiotherapy was determined. The range of BED value of
           radiotherapy was 90-120 when the distance between the tumor and gastrointestinal tract
           was more than 5 mm (alpha/beta=10) and 70-90 when the distance between the tumor and
           gastrointestinal tract was less than 5 mm (alpha/beta=10).

           1.5 Normal Tissue Limit: Reference to TG101 Report

        2. Microwave ablation 2.1 Preoperative positioning and planning: 2.1.1 Determine the fixing
           device: generally choose vacuum pad to fix 2.1.2 Choosing the right position: The
           principle is to choose the position that is easy to operate, taking into account the
           comfort and tolerance of patients.

      2.1.3 CT scan 2.1.4 The range of tumors was determined by CT images. In principle, at the
      maximum level, the skin points corresponding to the vertical center of the tumor are the
      marker points of the locating needle. At the same time, the center of the tumor was taken as
      the origin point, and the longitudinal and transverse cross lines were drawn on the patient's
      body surface. Roughly delineate the range of tumors according to CT in body surface 2.2
      Surgery and intraoperative optimization 2.2.1 Posture reduction and fixation of patients
      2.2.2 Oxygen inhalation, ECG and blood pressure monitoring 2.2.3 Installation of 3D Printing
      Planar Coordinate Template Fixer 2.2.4 Routine disinfection, cave towel laying, local
      infiltration anesthesia, fixing 3D printing plane coordinate template according to the range
      of tumors determined by physical examination and preoperative plan, and adjusting the
      direction of plane template by protractor.

      2.2.5 Puncture locating needle and puncture assistant fixing needle in 4 directions of tumor
      margin.

      2.2.6The real-time CT 2.5mm image was imported into the navigation system, the puncture
      needle was marked, the puncture needle was simulated, and the resolution of the template was
      adjusted accurately.

      2.2.7 Enhanced CT scan to determine the position and angle of template and pin accurately
      2.2.8 Layer by layer puncture according to preoperative plan 2.2.9 After inserting the
      ablation antenna to the reserved position, scan CT again to confirm whether the puncture
      needle has reached the planned position. 2.2.10 Complete ablation of tumors as planned.

      2.3Postoperative observation 2.3.1 With the assistance of the staff in the hospital, they
      will be transported back to the ward by flat car with their families.

      2.3.2 Re-measurement of blood pressure and heart rate 2.3.3Observe whether there is bleeding
      or exudation at the puncture point after operation, and give hemostasis and pain relief if
      necessary.

      To evaluate the clinical efficacy of stereotactic radiotherapy and microwave ablation in
      liver metastases after these treatment.In addition, the local control rate and side effects
      of stereotactic radiotherapy and microwave ablation in the treatment of liver metastases were
      explored, and the efficacy and safety of different doses of stereotactic radiotherapy were
      determined.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 3, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 31, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 31, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>non-randomized trial</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Local control rate</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years after the treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Local control refers to the fact that the tumor is not enlarged on imaging, but if the tumor is not enlarged, the patients with aggravated symptoms after treatment are not included in the local control range.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Objective response rate</measure>
    <time_frame>1 years after the treatment</time_frame>
    <description>The proportion of patients whose tumors have shrunk to a certain extent and maintained for a certain period of time, including CR + PR cases</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Disease control rate</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years after the treatment</time_frame>
    <description>After treatment, the number of cases with remission and stable lesions accounted for the percentage of the total number of assessable cases</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>PFS</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years after the treatment</time_frame>
    <description>The time interval of disease progression since the date of diagnosis</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years after the treatment</time_frame>
    <description>The time from enrollment to death from any cause</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Side effects</measure>
    <time_frame>1 years after the treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Harmful reactions unrelated to the purpose of treatment occur in the course of the treatment of a disease</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of life score of tumor patients(0-60)</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years after the treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Common methods for evaluating the quality of life of patients:The full score of quality of life is 60, the worst is &lt; 20, the worse is 21-30, the average is 31-40, the better is 41-50, and the good is 51-60.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Radiotherapy</condition>
  <condition>Microwave Ablation</condition>
  <condition>Liver Metastases</condition>
  <condition>Colorectal Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Stereotactic radiotherapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>In this study, the liver metastases were treated with Cyberknife stereotactic radiotherapy.Using multimodal image fusion to outline the target area.According to the volume, location, organ function and other factors, the dosage of radiotherapy was determined. The range of BED value of radiotherapy was 90-120 when the distance between the tumor and gastrointestinal tract was more than 5 mm (alpha/beta=10) and 70-90 when the distance between the tumor and gastrointestinal tract was less than 5 mm (alpha/beta=10).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Microwave ablation therapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>In this study, 3D printing template was used to assist microwave ablation.For those whose lesions are directly smaller than 5.0cm, the ablation time is about 10 min and 15 min, and the ablation time is more than 15min in patients larger than 5.0cm.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Radiation</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>stereotactic radiotherapy</intervention_name>
    <description>The liver metastases were treated with Cyberknife stereotactic radiotherapy.Using multimodal image fusion to outline the target area.According to the volume, location, organ function and other factors, the dosage of radiotherapy was determined. The range of BED value of radiotherapy was 90-120 when the distance between the tumor and gastrointestinal tract was more than 5 mm (alpha/beta=10) and 70-90 when the distance between the tumor and gastrointestinal tract was less than 5 mm (alpha/beta=10).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Stereotactic radiotherapy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>microwave alabation</intervention_name>
    <description>The colorectal cancer patients with liver metastases will receive microwave ablation.3D printing template was used to assist microwave ablation.For those whose lesions are directly smaller than 5.0cm, the ablation time is about 10 min and 15 min, and the ablation time is more than 15min in patients larger than 5.0cm.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Microwave ablation therapy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  The age was 18 to 80 years old.

          -  It was confirmed by pathology that the liver metastasis of colorectal cancer was less
             than or equal to 3 lesions, each lesion was less than 3 cm, and there was no invasion
             of vascular tumor thrombus and adjacent organs according to the discussion of MDT.

          -  The preoperative imaging evaluation of iatrogenic or / and personal factors can
             realize microwave ablation or radiosurgery SBRT to require.

          -  The primary lesion has been treated radical and has no evidence of recurrence, and
             there is no metastasis outside the liver.

          -  The physical status score of ECOG : 0 ≥ 1 or more than 60 KPS.

          -  Predicted survival time was more than 3 months.

          -  The main organ function can tolerate stereotactic radiotherapy / microwave ablation,
             liver function child-pugh A or B, no severe hypertension, diabetes and heart disease.
             That is, within 14 days of random examination, the relevant test indexes meet the
             following requirements:

               1. blood routine examination: i. Hemoglobin was more than 90 g /L (no blood
                  transfusion); ii. Neutrophil count was more than 1.5x109/L; iii platelet count
                  was more than 100x109/ L;

               2. biochemical examination: i. total cholerythrin-1.5-ultraln (upper limit of
                  normal); ii. Blood-valley-pyruvic transaminase (ALT) or blood-glutamic-aspartate
                  aminotransferase (AST), 2.5-hulled; iii. The clearance of endophytic muscle was
                  60 ml/ min (ckroft-gault formula);

               3. cardiac Doppler ultrasound assessment: left ventricular ejection fraction (LVEF)
                  was more than 50%;

               4. blood glucose control was less than 7.2 mmol/ L, non-fasting blood glucose was
                  less than 10 mmol/L, and glycosylated hemoglobin was less than 7%.

          -  Sign informed consent form.

          -  Good compliance, family agreed to cooperate with follow-up.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients who are being treated with drugs and whose liver metastases are stable or
             relieved, and who have participated in clinical trials of other drugs within four
             weeks;

          -  There was a history of bleeding, and any serious bleeding events of 3 degrees or more
             in ctcae 5.0 occurred within 4 weeks before screening.

          -  Patients with known central nervous system metastasis or history of central nervous
             system metastasis before screening. For patients with suspected central nervous system
             metastasis, CT or MRI examination must be performed within 14 days before
             randomization to exclude central nervous system metastasis.

          -  Patients with high blood pressure and single step-down medications were not able to
             obtain good control (systolic blood pressure was more than 140 mmHg, diastolic blood
             pressure was more than 90 mmHg); patients with a history of unstable angina; a new
             diagnosis within 3 months before screening was an event of myocardial infarction
             within 6 months before or after screening; Arrhythmias (including QTCF: male,450 ms,
             female, 470ms) require long-term use of anti-arrhythmic drugs and the New York Heart
             Association rating of grade ii cardiac insufficiency;

          -  Long-term unhealed wounds or incomplete fractures,

          -  Imaging showed that the tumor had invaded the perivascular area of important vessels
             or was judged by researchers that the tumor was highly likely to invade important
             blood vessels during treatment, resulting in fatal massive bleeding.

          -  Patients with abnormal coagulation function and bleeding tendency (14 days before
             randomization must be satisfied:INR is within the normal range without anticoagulant);
             Patients treated with anticoagulant or vitamin k antagonists such as warfarin, heparin
             or its analogues; Low dose warfarin (1mg oral, once a day) or low dose aspirin (not
             exceeding 100 mg); per day) is allowed for prophylactic purposes on the premise that
             the international standardized ratio of prothrombin time (INR) was less than 1.5;

          -  Hyperarteriovenous thrombosis occurred within 6 months before screening, such as
             cerebrovascular accidents (including temporary ischemic seizures), Deep venous
             thrombosis (except where venous thrombosis caused by intravenous catheterization after
             pre-chemotherapy has been cured by researchers) and pulmonary embolism, etc.

          -  There was abnormal thyroid function in the past, and even in the case of drug
             treatment, thyroid function could not be maintained within the normal range;

          -  Having a history of psychotropic substance abuse and unable to give up or have mental
             disorders.

          -  Radiotherapy for abdominal tumors has been carried out in the past.

          -  Have a history of immunodeficiency, or suffer from other acquired, congenital
             immunodeficiency diseases, or have a history of organ transplantation.

          -  According to the researchers' judgment, there are serious diseases that endanger the
             safety of patients or affect the completion of the study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Junjie U Wang, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Peking University Third Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Fei U Xu, M Med</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Peking University Third Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Xuezhang Duan, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>The fifth medical center of PLA general hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Kaixian Zhang, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Tengzhou Central People's Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Wei Li, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Beijing Ditan Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Hui Xie, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>The fifth medical center of PLA general hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Zuping Lian, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Guangxi Ruikang Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Xian Xu, M Med</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Hunan Aerospace Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Fuxin Guo, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Peking University Third Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jing Sun, M Med</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>The fifth medical center of PLA general hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Junjie U Wang, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+8682264910</phone>
    <phone_ext>+8682264910</phone_ext>
    <email>junjiewang_edu@sina.cn</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Fei U Xu, M Med</last_name>
    <phone>+8618511866032</phone>
    <phone_ext>+8682264910</phone_ext>
    <email>xufeibysy@163.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Beijing Ditan Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Beijing</city>
        <state>Beijing</state>
        <zip>100000</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Wei Li, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Peking University Third Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Beijing</city>
        <state>Beijing</state>
        <zip>100000</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Junjie Wang, Chairman</last_name>
      <phone>+8682264910</phone>
      <email>junjiewang_edu@sina.cn</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Fei Xu</last_name>
      <phone>+8618511866032</phone>
      <email>xufeibysy@163.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Junjie Wang, Chairman</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Fei Xu</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Fuxin Guo</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The fifth medical center of PLA general hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Beijing</city>
        <state>Beijing</state>
        <zip>100000</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Xuezhang Duan, director</last_name>
      <phone>+8613621386161</phone>
      <email>13621386161@163.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Xuezhang Duan</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Hui Xie</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jing Sun</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Guangxi ruikang hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>NanNing</city>
        <state>Guangxi</state>
        <zip>530000</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>ZuPing Lian, M Med</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hunan Aerospace Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Changsha</city>
        <state>Hunan</state>
        <zip>410205</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Xian Xu, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Tengzhou Central People's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tengzhou</city>
        <state>Shandong</state>
        <zip>277599</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Kaixian Zhang, director</last_name>
      <phone>+8613563200960</phone>
      <email>kaixianzhang@aliyun.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Kaixian Zhang, director</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yuan ZY, Meng MB, Liu CL, Wang HH, Jiang C, Song YC, Zhuang HQ, Yang D, Wang JS, Wei W, Li FT, Zhao LJ, Wang P. Stereotactic body radiation therapy using the CyberKnife(®) system for patients with liver metastases. Onco Targets Ther. 2014 Jun 12;7:915-23. doi: 10.2147/OTT.S58409. eCollection 2014.</citation>
    <PMID>24959080</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mihara K, Kaihara M, Sunahori S, Yamashiro N, Nishiya S, Ito Y, Funakoshi K, Egawa T, Tsukamoto N, Nagashima A. [Stereotactic Body Radiotherapy with CyberKnife®for Liver Metastases from Colorectal Cancer]. Gan To Kagaku Ryoho. 2015 Oct;42(10):1262-4. Japanese.</citation>
    <PMID>26489566</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kress MS, Collins BT, Collins SP, Dritschilo A, Gagnon G, Unger K. Stereotactic body radiation therapy for liver metastases from colorectal cancer: analysis of safety, feasibility, and early outcomes. Front Oncol. 2012 Feb 2;2:8. doi: 10.3389/fonc.2012.00008. eCollection 2012.</citation>
    <PMID>22649775</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dewas S, Bibault JE, Mirabel X, Fumagalli I, Kramar A, Jarraya H, Lacornerie T, Dewas-Vautravers C, Lartigau E. Prognostic factors affecting local control of hepatic tumors treated by Stereotactic Body Radiation Therapy. Radiat Oncol. 2012 Oct 10;7:166. doi: 10.1186/1748-717X-7-166.</citation>
    <PMID>23050794</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Herfarth KK, Debus J, Wannenmacher M. Stereotactic radiation therapy of liver metastases: update of the initial phase-I/II trial. Front Radiat Ther Oncol. 2004;38:100-5.</citation>
    <PMID>15458194</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Méndez Romero A, Wunderink W, Hussain SM, De Pooter JA, Heijmen BJ, Nowak PC, Nuyttens JJ, Brandwijk RP, Verhoef C, Ijzermans JN, Levendag PC. Stereotactic body radiation therapy for primary and metastatic liver tumors: A single institution phase i-ii study. Acta Oncol. 2006;45(7):831-7.</citation>
    <PMID>16982547</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hoyer M, Roed H, Traberg Hansen A, Ohlhuis L, Petersen J, Nellemann H, Kiil Berthelsen A, Grau C, Aage Engelholm S, Von der Maase H. Phase II study on stereotactic body radiotherapy of colorectal metastases. Acta Oncol. 2006;45(7):823-30.</citation>
    <PMID>16982546</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lee MT, Kim JJ, Dinniwell R, Brierley J, Lockwood G, Wong R, Cummings B, Ringash J, Tse RV, Knox JJ, Dawson LA. Phase I study of individualized stereotactic body radiotherapy of liver metastases. J Clin Oncol. 2009 Apr 1;27(10):1585-91. doi: 10.1200/JCO.2008.20.0600. Epub 2009 Mar 2.</citation>
    <PMID>19255313</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lanciano R, Lamond J, Yang J, Feng J, Arrigo S, Good M, Brady L. Stereotactic body radiation therapy for patients with heavily pretreated liver metastases and liver tumors. Front Oncol. 2012 Mar 9;2:23. doi: 10.3389/fonc.2012.00023. eCollection 2012.</citation>
    <PMID>22645716</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ambrosino G, Polistina F, Costantin G, Francescon P, Guglielmi R, Zanco P, Casamassima F, Febbraro A, Gerunda G, Lumachi F. Image-guided robotic stereotactic radiosurgery for unresectable liver metastases: preliminary results. Anticancer Res. 2009 Aug;29(8):3381-4.</citation>
    <PMID>19661360</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rusthoven KE, Kavanagh BD, Cardenes H, Stieber VW, Burri SH, Feigenberg SJ, Chidel MA, Pugh TJ, Franklin W, Kane M, Gaspar LE, Schefter TE. Multi-institutional phase I/II trial of stereotactic body radiation therapy for liver metastases. J Clin Oncol. 2009 Apr 1;27(10):1572-8. doi: 10.1200/JCO.2008.19.6329. Epub 2009 Mar 2.</citation>
    <PMID>19255321</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Katz AW, Carey-Sampson M, Muhs AG, Milano MT, Schell MC, Okunieff P. Hypofractionated stereotactic body radiation therapy (SBRT) for limited hepatic metastases. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys. 2007 Mar 1;67(3):793-8. Epub 2006 Dec 29.</citation>
    <PMID>17197128</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yamashita H, Onishi H, Matsumoto Y, Murakami N, Matsuo Y, Nomiya T, Nakagawa K; Japanese Radiological Society multi-institutional SBRT study group (JRS-SBRTSG). Local effect of stereotactic body radiotherapy for primary and metastatic liver tumors in 130 Japanese patients. Radiat Oncol. 2014 May 10;9:112. doi: 10.1186/1748-717X-9-112.</citation>
    <PMID>24886477</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Benedict SH, Yenice KM, Followill D, Galvin JM, Hinson W, Kavanagh B, Keall P, Lovelock M, Meeks S, Papiez L, Purdie T, Sadagopan R, Schell MC, Salter B, Schlesinger DJ, Shiu AS, Solberg T, Song DY, Stieber V, Timmerman R, Tomé WA, Verellen D, Wang L, Yin FF. Stereotactic body radiation therapy: the report of AAPM Task Group 101. Med Phys. 2010 Aug;37(8):4078-101. Erratum in: Med Phys. 2012 Jan;39(1):563. Dosage error in article text.</citation>
    <PMID>20879569</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Groeschl RT, Pilgrim CH, Hanna EM, Simo KA, Swan RZ, Sindram D, Martinie JB, Iannitti DA, Bloomston M, Schmidt C, Khabiri H, Shirley LA, Martin RC, Tsai S, Turaga KK, Christians KK, Rilling WS, Gamblin TC. Microwave ablation for hepatic malignancies: a multiinstitutional analysis. Ann Surg. 2014 Jun;259(6):1195-200. doi: 10.1097/SLA.0000000000000234.</citation>
    <PMID>24096760</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Xu S, Hu K, Huang H, Yao Z, Wang Q, Yang P, Liu B, Yang Y, Chen G. [Effect of laparoscopic hepatectomy and microwave ablation for colorectal liver metastases]. Zhonghua Yi Xue Za Zhi. 2015 Oct;95(40):3289-92. Chinese.</citation>
    <PMID>26815350</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 21, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 23, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 28, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 18, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 18, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 19, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Radiotherapy</keyword>
  <keyword>microwave ablation</keyword>
  <keyword>Liver Metastases</keyword>
  <keyword>Colorectal Cancer</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Colorectal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasm Metastasis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms, Second Primary</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Liver Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

