<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03965143</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2014893</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03965143</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Talus Replacement Registry</brief_title>
  <acronym>3DTalar</acronym>
  <official_title>Talus Replacement Registry</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Kyle Schweser MD</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Missouri-Columbia</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Avascular necrosis of the talus is a difficult problem to manage, especially in the young and
      healthy. The only option, historically, has been a talectomy and hindfoot fusion. While this
      is a viable option, it is not without its morbidity. Arthritis of surrounding joints is
      common, occurring anywhere from 1-10 years after the procedure. This is especially true in
      younger patients, where loss of motion can be life altering both physically and mentally. The
      search for alternatives has been limited. Recently, 3D printing has become more ubiquitous
      and affordable and newer medical alternatives have arisen thanks to this technology. The 3D
      custom talus is relatively new in the orthopaedic community, but has been used at several
      centers with good success. It has been shown to re-establish the normal alignment of the
      foot, preserve motion (with some achieving almost physiologic motion), and allow for almost
      normal ambulation. However, the data is still limited and further study is necessary. Our
      facility was recently approved to perform this procedure. Our hypothesis is that custom 3D
      printed talar body replacements, either used alone or with total ankle replacements, will
      maintain physiologic motion, have no difference in complications when compared to hindfoot
      fusions with allograft, lead to good outcome scores and patient satisfaction scores. Patients
      diagnosed with avascular necrosis of the talus who have already decided to undergo a
      procedure involving a 3D custom talus as part of their standard care (talar replacement,
      total ankle/total talus, etc) will be enrolled in the study. Patients will follow standard
      post-operative protocols and return to clinic at designated time periods (2 weeks, 6 weeks, 3
      months, 6 months, 1 year). X-ray evaluation, Range of motion, return to ambulation, walking
      speed and patient reported outcomes will be evaluated at each visit. Data will then be
      compared with baseline measurements and use to determine the progression of patients over
      time after the procedure
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      After patients have undergone a standard of care 3D talar augment procedure they will return
      to clinic at designated time periods (2 weeks, 6 weeks, 3 months, 6 months, 1 year). X-rays
      performed as standard of care will be evaluated. Walking speed will be assessed after patient
      is allowed to bear weight at the same designated time periods reported above. Patients will
      also answer questions regarding pain (VAS survey), satisfaction (SSQ-8 survey), outcomes
      utilizing AAOS foot and ankle scores (survey), and self-reported return to unassisted
      ambulation. Goniometer measurements will be taken in the clinic at all post-operative visits
      to determine ROM
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 1, 2025</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 1, 2025</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational [Patient Registry]</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <target_duration>12 Months</target_duration>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change Range of motion</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Measures with a Goniometer and expressed in degrees</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in VAS pain Score</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>The visual analog scale (VAS) is a validated, subjective measure for acute and chronic pain. Scores are recorded by making a handwritten mark on a 10-cm line that represents a continuum between &quot;no pain&quot; and &quot;worst pain.&quot;</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in AAOS foot an ankle score</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>The AAOS foot and ankle questionnaire is a patient-administrated 25-item survey specifically developed for foot and ankle-related disability. The questionnaire is divided into two scales, the Foot and Ankle Core scale, comprised of 20 questions and the Shoe Comfort Scale with five questions. The questions themselves are distributed among five different categories: Pain (9 items), function (6 items), stiffness and swelling (2 items), giving way (3 items) and shoe comfort (5 items). Answers are then measured on a scale of 1 to 5 or 6, with 1 being the best outcome score.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>SSQ-8 satisfaction score</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>the SSQ-8 (Surgical Satisfaction Score) is a Patient administered 8-item survey designed to asses satisfaction after a surgical procedure. Answers are then measured on a scale of 1 to 5 or 6, with 1 being the best outcome score.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in walking speed</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Speed will be measured in seconds over a standard distance</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Avascular Necrosis of the Talus</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>3D talar group</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients that will undergo a 3D custom talar augment</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>3D talar augmentation</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients with an avascular necrosis of the body if the talar bone will undergo a 3D custom talar augmentation with or without concomitant ankle arthroplasty</description>
    <arm_group_label>3D talar group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients over 18 years of age diagnosed with avascular necrosis of the talar body and
        amenable to treatment with 3D custom augmentation
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Subjects age 18 years or above at time of screening

          2. Condition satisfies requirement for total talus replacement

          3. Able to consent and participate in the study

          4. No previous history of septic arthritis involving the hindfoot/midfoot

          5. Previous ability to ambulate

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Active infection, sepsis, osteomyelitis or history of septic arthritis involving the
             hindfoot/midfoot

          2. Unable to consent or participate in the study secondary to mental status

          3. Condition does not qualify for a total talus replacement

          4. Patients who are pregnant or imprisoned

          5. Planned relocation or unable to return for required follow-up visits
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Kyle M Schweser, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Assistant Professor Orthopaedic Trauma/Foot and Ankle</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Stacee W Clawson, RN</last_name>
    <phone>(573) 884-9017</phone>
    <email>clawsons@health.missouri.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Ennio R Esposito, MD</last_name>
    <phone>3468126445</phone>
    <email>eardvb@health.missouri.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Missouri</name>
      <address>
        <city>Columbia</city>
        <state>Missouri</state>
        <zip>65212</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ennio R Esposito</last_name>
      <phone>573-882-7615</phone>
      <email>eardvb@health.missouri.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jehan S, Shakeel M, Bing AJ, Hill SO. The success of tibiotalocalcaneal arthrodesis with intramedullary nailing--a systematic review of the literature. Acta Orthop Belg. 2011 Oct;77(5):644-51. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22187841</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ketz J, Myerson M, Sanders R. The salvage of complex hindfoot problems with use of a custom talar total ankle prosthesis. J Bone Joint Surg Am. 2012 Jul 3;94(13):1194-200. doi: 10.2106/JBJS.K.00421.</citation>
    <PMID>22760387</PMID>
  </reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Wagener J, Gross CE, Schweizer C, Lang TH, Hintermann B. Custom-made total ankle arthroplasty for the salvage of major talar bone loss. Bone Joint J. 2017 Feb;99-B(2):231-236. doi: 10.1302/0301-620X.99B2.BJJ-2016-0504.R2.</citation>
    <PMID>28148666</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Tracey J, Arora D, Gross CE, Parekh SG. Custom 3D-Printed Total Talar Prostheses Restore Normal Joint Anatomy Throughout the Hindfoot. Foot Ankle Spec. 2019 Feb;12(1):39-48. doi: 10.1177/1938640018762567. Epub 2018 Mar 14.</citation>
    <PMID>29537314</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 14, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 24, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 28, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 30, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 30, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 31, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Missouri-Columbia</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Kyle Schweser MD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor Orthopaedic Trauma/Foot and Ankle</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Necrosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>The Investigator will maintain all study records according to applicable University regulatory requirement(s). Hard copy records will be retained for at least 7 years after the last clinic follow-up visit at the Missouri Orthopaedic Institute in a locked filing cabinet. Electronic records will be retained for the same amount of time but on secured computers and servers. If the Investigator withdraws from the responsibility of keeping the study records, custody will be transferred to a person willing to accept the responsibility.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

