<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03966027</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2014997</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03966027</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Immediate Vs. Delayed Weight Bearing Postoperative Protocol in Diabetic Ankle Fractures</brief_title>
  <acronym>Diabetic Ankle</acronym>
  <official_title>Immediate Vs. Delayed Weight Bearing Postoperative Protocol in Diabetic Ankle Fractures</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Kyle Schweser MD</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Missouri-Columbia</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Operatively managed diabetic ankle fractures have significant risk for complications. The
      cause for failure is likely multifactorial, however, a component of failure has to do with an
      inability to process pain and pressure normally. This loss of protective sensation allows for
      an increase in abnormal stresses placed on the recently repaired fractures. Historically,
      diabetics have been kept non weight bearing for extended periods of time, which has its own
      functional and cardiovascular issues. The purpose of the study is to determine if a protocol
      of immediate weight bearing with a hindfoot offloading brace after surgically corrected ankle
      fracture in a diabetic patient will maintain adequate motion, have no difference in
      complications when compared to regular non-immediate weight bearing protocols, and lead to
      good outcome scores and patient satisfaction scores
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Operatively managed diabetic ankle fractures have significant risk for complications. The
      cause for failure is likely multifactorial, however, a component of failure has to do with an
      inability to process pain and pressure normally. This loss of protective sensation allows for
      an increase in abnormal stresses placed on the recently repaired fractures. Historically,
      diabetics have been kept non weight bearing for extended periods of time, which has its own
      functional and cardiovascular issues. The purpose of the study is to determine if a protocol
      of immediate weight bearing with a hindfoot offloading brace after surgically corrected ankle
      fracture in a diabetic patient will maintain adequate motion, have no difference in
      complications when compared to regular non-immediate weight bearing protocols, and lead to
      good outcome scores and patient satisfaction scores

      Patients will be recruited from the trauma and foot &amp; ankle service lines. Patients who have
      experienced an isolated ankle fracture (excluding pilon fracture) and will undergo operative
      fixation within 3 weeks of injury will be approached for consent. Patients will then be
      screened based on the inclusion and exclusion criteria. Up to 25 patients will be enrolled

      The following protocol will be applied after enrollment

        1. Pre-operatively

           a. Hemoglobin A1c will also be collected from each patient if it has not been performed
           within the last 30 days.

        2. Post-operatively a. Post-surgery i. Standard of Care:

      1. Placement into short leg, non-weight bearing splint to allow for wound healing and brace
      fabrication ii. Research Specific:

      1. Fitted for brace (will be custom made and take approximately 1-2 weeks) b. 2 week visit
      (standard of care timepoint) i. Standard of Care:

        1. Placed into compression stockings

        2. Counseling regarding skin checks and diabetic skin care

        3. Physical therapy prescription given ii. Research Specific

      1. Placement into brace so it offloads the hindfoot to 15 pounds of pressure or less 2.
      Education by prosthetist, physiatrist, and/or attending physician about proper brace wear and
      maintenance, and the importance of weight bearing only in brace.

      c. 3 Week visit (not standard of care timepoint) i. Research Specific

      1. Ankle radiographs d. 4 weeks, 6 weeks, 12 Weeks, 26 weeks, and 1 year visits (standard of
      care time points) i. Standard of Care

        1. Surveys (PROMIS, AAOS Foot and Ankle)

        2. Ankle Radiographs ii. Research Specific

      1. Counseling regarding brace wear 2. Brace adjustments as needed e. 8 week, 10 week, 14
      week, 16 week, (non-standard of care biweekly visits until healing occurs) i. Research
      Specific

        1. Ankle Radiographs (if early failure is suspected)

        2. Skin Check

      Upon study completion, patients will continue with post-operative rehab following the
      surgeon's standard of care. If a patients is removed prematurely or if the study ends
      prematurely, they will receive standard of care procedures going forward
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">April 30, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 15, 2025</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 15, 2025</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Diabetic patients with ankle fractures will be manage operatively and then randomized to be prescribed a hindfoot offloading brace 2 weeks after surgery or be randomized to follow a non-immediate weight bearing rehabilitation protocol</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse Events</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Adverse Events by type over time, severity, seriousness, and relatedness. AEs will be tabulated and summarized as counts and percentages. AEs will also be cross-tabulated according to:
Severity;
Unanticipated Adverse Device Effect (UADE)
Seriousness (Serious Adverse Event (SAE), Non-serious AE);
Device-Relatedness (Unrelated, Possibly Related, Probably Related, Definitely Related);
Procedure-Relatedness (Unrelated, Possibly Related, Probably Related, Definitely Related).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>AAOS Foot and Ankle Score</measure>
    <time_frame>12 Months</time_frame>
    <description>The AAOS foot and ankle questionnaire is a patient-administrated 25-item survey specifically developed for foot and ankle-related disability. The questionnaire is divided into two scales, the Foot and Ankle Core scale, comprised of 20 questions and the Shoe Comfort Scale with five questions. The questions themselves are distributed among five different categories: Pain (9 items), function (6 items), stiffness and swelling (2 items), giving way (3 items) and shoe comfort (5 items). Answers are then measured on a scale of 1 to 5 or 6, with 1 being the best outcome score.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PROMIS Score</measure>
    <time_frame>12 Months</time_frame>
    <description>The Patient-Reported Outcomes Measurement Information System® (PROMIS) is a flexible set of tools designed to measure self-reported physical, mental and social health and wellbeing. PROMIS instruments contain a fixed number of items from seven PROMIS domains: depression; anxiety; physical function; pain interference; fatigue; sleep disturbance; and ability to participate in social roles and activities. The questionarie assesses each of the 7 PROMIS domains with 4 questions. The questions are ranked on a 5-point Likert Scale. There is also one 11-point rating scale for pain intensity. Norm-based scores are calculated for each domain on the PROMIS measures, so that a score of 50 represents the mean or average of the reference population. A score of 60 means that the person is one standard deviation above the reference population (standard deviation = 10).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">25</enrollment>
  <condition>Ankle Fractures</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Hindfoot Offloading Braces / Immediate Weight-bearing</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Diabetic patients over 18 years of age who sustained an isolated (non-pilon) ankle fracture will undergo ORIF of the ankle fracture within 3 weeks of the event</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>No Hindfoot Offloading Braces / Delayed Weight-Bearing</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Diabetic patients over 18 years of age who sustained an isolated (non-pilon) ankle fracture will undergo ORIF of the ankle fracture within 3 weeks of the event</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Postoperative protocol (Immediate weight bearing)</intervention_name>
    <description>After ORIF of the ankle fracture, the patient will be randomized to follow an immediate weight bearing rehabilitation protocol using an offloading hindfoot brace</description>
    <arm_group_label>Hindfoot Offloading Braces / Immediate Weight-bearing</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Postoperative Protocol (Delayed Weight Bearing)</intervention_name>
    <description>After ORIF of the ankle fracture, the patient will be randomized to follow a standard delayed weight-bearing rehabilitation protocol</description>
    <arm_group_label>No Hindfoot Offloading Braces / Delayed Weight-Bearing</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Adults 18 and ove

          2. Positive for diabetes

          3. Positive monofilament test

          4. Isolated ankle fracture (non-pilon) and undergoing operative intervention within 3
             weeks of fracture

          5. Weight less than 275 (124kg)

          6. Can tolerate and comply with brace

          7. No signs of pre-existing charcot arthroplasty or ankle deformity

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Children

          2. Pregnant patients

          3. No signs of diabetes complicated by neuropathy

          4. Non-operative ankle fractures

          5. Multiple extremity injury

          6. Cannot follow post-operative protocol

          7. Chronic ankle fractures receiving surgery beyond 3 weeks of injury
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Kyle M Schweser, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Assistant Professor Orthopaedic Trauma/Foot and Ankle</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Stacee W Clawson, RN</last_name>
    <phone>(573) 884-9017</phone>
    <email>clawsons@health.missouri.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Ennio Rizzo Esposito, MD</last_name>
    <phone>3468126445</phone>
    <email>eardvb@health.missouri.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <reference>
    <citation>Raghav A, Khan ZA, Labala RK, Ahmad J, Noor S, Mishra BK. Financial burden of diabetic foot ulcers to world: a progressive topic to discuss always. Ther Adv Endocrinol Metab. 2018 Jan;9(1):29-31. doi: 10.1177/2042018817744513. Epub 2017 Dec 12. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>29344337</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jani MM, Ricci WM, Borrelli J Jr, Barrett SE, Johnson JE. A protocol for treatment of unstable ankle fractures using transarticular fixation in patients with diabetes mellitus and loss of protective sensibility. Foot Ankle Int. 2003 Nov;24(11):838-44.</citation>
    <PMID>14655888</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shehab DK, Al-Jarallah KF, Abraham M, Mojiminiyi OA, Al-Mohamedy H, Abdella NA. Back to basics: ankle reflex in the evaluation of peripheral neuropathy in type 2 diabetes mellitus. QJM. 2012 Apr;105(4):315-20. doi: 10.1093/qjmed/hcr212. Epub 2011 Nov 8.</citation>
    <PMID>22071964</PMID>
  </reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Wukich DK, Kline AJ. The management of ankle fractures in patients with diabetes. J Bone Joint Surg Am. 2008 Jul;90(7):1570-8. doi: 10.2106/JBJS.G.01673. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18594108</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Holder CG, Haskvitz EM, Weltman A. The effects of assistive devices on the oxygen cost, cardiovascular stress, and perception of nonweight-bearing ambulation. J Orthop Sports Phys Ther. 1993 Oct;18(4):537-42.</citation>
    <PMID>8220412</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 24, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 24, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 29, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 30, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 30, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 31, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Missouri-Columbia</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Kyle Schweser MD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor Orthopaedic Trauma/Foot and Ankle</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Diabetic Ankle Fractures</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Fractures, Bone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ankle Fractures</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>The Investigator will maintain all study records according to applicable University regulatory requirement(s). Hard copy records will be retained for at least 7 years after the last clinic follow-up visit at the Missouri Orthopaedic Institute in a locked filing cabinet. Electronic records will be retained for the same amount of time but on secured computers and servers. If the Investigator withdraws from the responsibility of keeping the study records, custody will be transferred to a person willing to accept the responsibility.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

