<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03962725</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2019P000260</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03962725</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Avoiding Neuromuscular Blockers to Reduce Complications</brief_title>
  <official_title>Eliminating Use of Non Depolarizing Neuromuscular Blocking Agents to Reduce Postoperative Pulmonary Complications: A Multi-center, Randomized Control Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Beth Israel Deaconess Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Beth Israel Deaconess Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The goal of this study to evaluate whether eliminating the use of non-depolarizing
      neuromuscular blocking agents (NMBA) for maintenance of general anesthesia reduces
      postoperative pulmonary complications in higher risk patients.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Pragmatic prospective randomized controlled assessor-blinded effect-size finding trial
      involving approximately 100 patients total at two academic tertiary care hospitals: Beth
      Israel Deaconess Medical Center (BIDMC) and Massachusetts General Hospital (MGH). Patients
      will be randomized into one of two study groups: standard care group which uses Rocuronium
      (NMBA) as an adjunct for maintenance of general anesthesia and non-relaxant arm that avoids
      the use of NMBA and instead uses additional inhalational anesthetics, opioids, propofol,
      dexmedetomidine, or ketamine for maintenance of general anesthesia. Assessment of
      postoperative pulmonary complications and in-hospital mortality would be achieved by close
      review of the patient's medical records during the hospital stay, for a maximum of 28 days.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Suspended</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Enrollment and other trial activities have temporarily paused due to COVID-19 and are expected
    to resume in the future; This is not a suspension of IRB approval
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date type="Actual">August 7, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants who either had postoperative pulmonary complications or died in hospital within 28 days of index procedure.</measure>
    <time_frame>28 Days</time_frame>
    <description>Composite of respiratory failure, suspected respiratory infection, aspiration pneumonia or pneumonitis, atelectasis, bronchospasm, reintubation and all cause in-hospital mortality</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Vasopressor Use Between Groups</measure>
    <time_frame>During the surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Vasopressor equivalent dose</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of Intraoperative Hypotension</measure>
    <time_frame>During the surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Mean arterial pressure &lt;55mmHg</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Surgeon's Assessment of surgical field</measure>
    <time_frame>During the surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Was the operative condition optimal for the surgeon graded qualitatively using a numerical rating scale of 1-4. A score of 1 indicates excellent operating conditions whereas 4 indicates conditions unacceptable to the surgeon.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>30-Day Readmission Rates</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days</time_frame>
    <description>How often patients had to be readmitted to the hospital within 30 days of discharge from hospital following index procedure.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Time to Post-Anesthesia Care Unit (PACU) Discharge Readiness</measure>
    <time_frame>Day after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Time is takes for patients to be ready for discharge from PACU post operatively.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Cost of Anesthetic Medication</measure>
    <time_frame>During the surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Cost of anesthetics used during surgical procedures in the study.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of Unplanned ICU Admission or Return to Operating Room</measure>
    <time_frame>24 hours</time_frame>
    <description>How often patients had either unanticipated ICU admissions or return to the operating room within 24 hours of the initial operation.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Hospital Length of Stay</measure>
    <time_frame>Upto 30 days</time_frame>
    <description>How much total time patients spent in the hospital after the operation.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Respiratory Failure</condition>
  <condition>Respiratory Infection</condition>
  <condition>Aspiration Pneumonia</condition>
  <condition>Pneumonitis</condition>
  <condition>Atelectasis</condition>
  <condition>Bronchospasm</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control Group (C)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Endotracheal intubation would be facilitated by either Rocuronium (0.6-1mg kg-1) or Succinylcholine (1-1.5mg kg-1) and further dosing of Rocuronium would be left at the discretion of the anesthesia team members. Choice and technique of induction and maintenance of anesthesia, use of vasopressors, perioperative antibiotics, analgesics/adjunct regional techniques, prophylaxis for postoperative nausea and vomiting, fluid and blood component therapy would be left at the discretion of the anesthesia team. Neuromuscular blockade would be reversed with either Sugammadex or Neostigmine (based on institutional availability) and trachea would be extubated once patient meets criteria per attending anesthesiologist.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>No Relaxant Group (NR)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Endotracheal intubation would be facilitated by Succinylcholine (1-1.5mg/kg) or Remifentanil (1-2mcg kg-1) if Succinylcholine use is contraindicated. No non-depolarizing NMBA would be administered to the patients randomized to the NR group. Choice and technique of induction and maintenance of anesthesia, use of vasopressors, perioperative antibiotics, analgesics/adjunct regional techniques, prophylaxis for postoperative nausea and vomiting, fluid and blood component therapy would be left at the discretion of the anesthesia team. Use of deeper plane of inhaled anesthetics or adjuncts (opioids, propofol, dexmedetomidine or ketamine) either as boluses or infusion would be recommended in case of sustained high peak airway pressures (&gt;35mm Hg), high intra-abdominal pressure, involuntary patient/diaphragmatic movement hindering surgical exposure and dissection. Choice and dose of adjunct/s to optimize operating conditions would be left to the discretion of the anesthesia team.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Neuromuscular Blocking Agents</intervention_name>
    <description>Use of non depolarizing neuromuscular blocking agents for maintenance of general anesthesia.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control Group (C)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Rocuronium</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Anesthetic Adjuncts</intervention_name>
    <description>Use of deeper plane of inhaled anesthetics or adjuncts (opioids, propofol, dexmedetomidine or ketamine for maintenance of general anesthesia.</description>
    <arm_group_label>No Relaxant Group (NR)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>opioids, propofol, dexmedetomidine or ketamine</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  At least 18 years of age

          -  Undergoing non-cardiac surgery under general anesthesia with an endotracheal tube

          -  those at higher risk of developing postoperative pulmonary complications (internally
             validated risk prediction score of &gt;=20)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Emergency surgery

          -  Ambulatory (outpatient) surgery

          -  Scheduled for elective postoperative ventilation

          -  Planned return to operating room within 7 days of index procedure

          -  Exposure to general anesthesia within 7 days prior to planned procedure

          -  Requirement mechanical ventilation at baseline (not including stable use of
             CPAP/BiPAP)

          -  Pregnant patients: as detected by patient self-reporting or diagnosed by preoperative
             pregnancy testing according to institutional policies at BIDMC and MGH

          -  Allergy to either non-depolarizing muscle relaxants or sugammadex

          -  Clinician refusal

          -  Prisoner
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Maximilian S Schaefer, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Beth Israel Deaconess Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Massachusetts General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02114</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Beth Israel Deaconess Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02215</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 21, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 23, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 24, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 24, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 24, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 28, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Neuromuscular Blocker Avoidance</keyword>
  <keyword>Post Operative Pulmonary Complications</keyword>
  <keyword>General Anesthesia Maintenance</keyword>
  <keyword>Inhaled Anesthetics</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Respiratory Tract Infections</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pneumonia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Respiratory Insufficiency</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pulmonary Atelectasis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Bronchial Spasm</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pneumonia, Aspiration</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Dexmedetomidine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ketamine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Propofol</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Anesthetics</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Rocuronium</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neuromuscular Blocking Agents</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

