<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03966391</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>036893</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03966391</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effectiveness of CARD for Improving School-Based Immunizations</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effectiveness of a Multi-faceted Knowledge Translation Intervention (The CARD System) for School Based Immunizations: a Cluster Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Toronto</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Alberta Health Services</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Toronto</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Vaccination is estimated to have saved more lives in Canada than any other single
      intervention and is considered one of the most important advances in the prevention of
      disease. The process of vaccination, however, is stressful for individuals. School-based
      vaccinations in particular, are associated with high levels of fear and anxiety among
      students. This randomized cluster trial will implement a multi-faceted knowledge translation
      intervention called The CARD (C-Comfort A-Ask R-Relax D-Distract) System in school-based
      vaccinations and evaluate its effects on the experience of vaccination for students and
      implementation outcomes.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The investigators developed a multi-faceted knowledge translation intervention called The
      CARD System to provide a framework for delivering vaccinations at school that integrates
      evidence-based strategies to mitigate pain, fear and fainting and promotes a student-centred
      approach to vaccination. CARD addresses 2 components of the vaccination delivery program: 1)
      pre-vaccination day preparation and 2) vaccination day activities. In a small controlled
      clinical trial in a public health unit in Niagara, Ontario, the investigators demonstrated
      benefits of CARD on student symptoms during vaccination, including fear, and
      dizziness-precursor of fainting, and satisfaction with CARD by all stakeholder groups
      (students, public health staff, school staff and parents). This study will evaluate CARD in a
      large cluster trial in Calgary, Alberta. This trial is the final phase of a 3-phase project,
      whereby the first 2 phases involve developing an implementation plan for the local context
      and evaluating feasibility of implementation.

      Eight community health centres that provide vaccination services to schools in their regions
      will be randomized in a 1:1 ratio to CARD or control (usual practices). Data will be
      collected for vaccination services carried out in grade 6 and grade 9 students in
      participating schools for the academic year 2019-2020.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Suspended</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Study suspended because of Covid-19 - there are no vaccinations in schools
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 22, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Cluster trial involving 8 community health centres. They will be randomized to CARD or control (standard care) groups in a 1:1 ratio. Eligible schools (approximately 13/community health centre) will be included.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
    <masking_description>Students will not be aware of whether they are in the intervention or control group. Care providers who are trained in the intervention are aware of the group allocation. They will not communicate with care providers not trained in the intervention. Care providers that are trained in the intervention will not deliver care to participants in the control group and care providers that are not trained in the intervention will not deliver care to participants in the intervention group</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Student fear</measure>
    <time_frame>within 5 minutes after vaccination</time_frame>
    <description>student self-reported fear during vaccination, rated on a 0-10 scale</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Student pain</measure>
    <time_frame>within 5 minutes after vaccination</time_frame>
    <description>student self-reported pain during vaccination, rated on a 0-10 scale</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Student dizziness</measure>
    <time_frame>within 5 minutes after vaccination</time_frame>
    <description>student self-reported dizziness during vaccination, rated on a 0-10 scale</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Student fainting</measure>
    <time_frame>within 1 hour after vaccination</time_frame>
    <description>student fainting during vaccination, yes/no, as assessed by immunizer</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Student post-immunization stress-related responses</measure>
    <time_frame>within 1 hour after vaccination</time_frame>
    <description>student post-immunization stress-related responses, yes/no, as assessed by immunizer using the WHO Immunization Stress Responses Criteria</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Utilization of coping strategies</measure>
    <time_frame>within 5 minutes after vaccination</time_frame>
    <description>use of individual coping strategies during vaccination (distraction, topical anesthetic, privacy, support person, deep breathing, muscle tension), yes/no, as assessed by immunizer using Documentation checklist</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Uptake of vaccination</measure>
    <time_frame>by end of school year</time_frame>
    <description>proportion of students vaccinated (overall and for each vaccine)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Implementation success of CARD</measure>
    <time_frame>within 3 months of vaccination clinics</time_frame>
    <description>perceptions of implementation success of CARD program delivery as reported by CARD implementers (primary targets) using the CARD Global Impression Checklist, individual questions (5-point likert scale, higher number represents better outcome). This information will be supplemented with information from focus groups with implementers and study notes, as well as focus groups with other stakeholder groups (secondary targets - school staff, students, parents)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cost of CARD implementation</measure>
    <time_frame>within 3 months of vaccination clinics</time_frame>
    <description>micro-costing of implementer activities - student education, vaccination clinic, planning for topical anesthetics, re-scheduling vaccinations</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Compliance with CARD</measure>
    <time_frame>within 3 months after vaccination clinics</time_frame>
    <description>percent compliance with CARD implementation as assessed by implementers using a CARD compliance checklist. This information will be supplemented with information from focus groups with implementers and study notes, as well as focus groups with other stakeholder groups (students, parents, school staff).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Knowledge of effective coping strategies</measure>
    <time_frame>within 3 months of vaccination clinics</time_frame>
    <description>knowledge of effective coping strategies, as assessed using a 10-point investigator-developed knowledge test; administered to different stakeholder groups (public health, school staff, students, parents)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Perceptions about pain and fear</measure>
    <time_frame>within 3 months of vaccination clinics</time_frame>
    <description>perceptions about pain and fear, as assessed using a 5-point likert scale (higher number represents better outcome) for different stakeholder groups (public health, school staff, students, parents)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Willingness to be vaccinated</measure>
    <time_frame>within 3 months of vaccination clinics</time_frame>
    <description>student self-reported willingness to be vaccinated, as assessed using a 5-point likert scale (higher number represents better outcome)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Fear of needles</measure>
    <time_frame>within 3 months of vaccination clinics</time_frame>
    <description>student self-reported fear of needles, rated on a 0-10 scale</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Perceptions of Vaccination Program</measure>
    <time_frame>within 3 months of vaccination clinics</time_frame>
    <description>perceptions of public health staff using the Vaccination Program Global Impression Checklist, individual questions (5-point likert scale, higher number represents better outcome).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">7800</enrollment>
  <condition>Vaccination; Complications</condition>
  <condition>Vaccine Adverse Reaction</condition>
  <condition>Fear</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>CARD (multi-faceted knowledge translation intervention)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>CARD will be integrated into the school vaccination program. This includes pre-vaccination day preparation (e.g., planning of clinic spaces, student and school staff education about CARD) and vaccination day activities (e.g., clinic set-up, processes for triaging students, implementing pain/ fear/fainting mitigation interventions from CARD during vaccination)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control (standard care)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>There are no specific procedures being undertaken to plan or execute clinics. Usual practices will be instituted (i.e., no education specific to CARD, nor clinic set-up or execution to incorporate interventions for pain, fear or fainting)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Multi-faceted knowledge translation intervention</intervention_name>
    <description>The intervention consists of education of relevant stakeholders of best practices and integration of best practices into the vaccination delivery program</description>
    <arm_group_label>CARD (multi-faceted knowledge translation intervention)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>CARD</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  grade 7 and 9 students eligible for vaccination at school

          -  public health staff in community health centre involved in the study

          -  school staff in a participating school involved in school vaccination

          -  parent of a student eligible for vaccination at school

        Exclusion Criteria:

        - unable to understand and read English
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>11 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Anna Taddio, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Toronto</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Alberta Health Services Public Health - Calgary Zone</name>
      <address>
        <city>Calgary</city>
        <state>Alberta</state>
        <zip>T2W 3N2</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://academic.oup.com/pch/issue/24/Supplement_1</url>
    <description>Description Supplement issue of Paediatrics &amp; Child Health - repository for prior research with CARD</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>June 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 25, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 25, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 29, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 10, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 10, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 12, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Toronto</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Anna Taddio</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>school vaccinations</keyword>
  <keyword>pain management</keyword>
  <keyword>knowledge translation</keyword>
  <keyword>cluster trial</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>There is no plan to share IPD</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

