<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03965468</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ETOP 14-18</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2018-003011-22</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>ESR-17-13224</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03965468</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Immunotherapy, Chemotherapy, Radiotherapy and Surgery for Synchronous Oligo-metastatic NSCLC</brief_title>
  <acronym>CHESS</acronym>
  <official_title>A Multicentre Single Arm Phase II Trial Assessing the Efficacy of Immunotherapy, Chemotherapy and Stereotactic Radiotherapy to Metastases Followed by Definitive Surgery or Radiotherapy to the Primary Tumour, in Patients With Synchronous Oligo-metastatic Non-small Cell Lung Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>European Thoracic Oncology Platform</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>AstraZeneca</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>European Thoracic Oncology Platform</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      A multicentre single arm phase II trial assessing the efficacy of immunotherapy, chemotherapy
      plus stereotactic radiotherapy to metastases followed by definitive surgery or radiotherapy
      to the locoregional primary tumour, in patients with histologically-confirmed synchronous
      oligo-metastatic non-small cell lung cancer (NSCLC).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Non-small cell lung cancer (NSCLC) continues to be the leading cause of cancer-related
      mortality worldwide. Even with adjustment for age NSCLC is responsible for almost 20% of
      cancer-related deaths. Recent years have brought tremendous progress in the understanding of
      the disease, its underlying biology and the development of effective therapies.
      Traditionally, NSCLC has been treated with surgery, platinum-based chemotherapy or
      radiotherapy alone or in combination, depending on tumour stage, tolerability of expected
      side effects and prognosis. Various strategies are currently being pursued in order to
      increase the patient population that may benefit from immunotherapy and to further improve
      the outcome of patients with NSCLC.

      The CHESS clinical trial is for patients with NSCLC that has progressed to a small number of
      other parts of the body (oligo-metastatic) and has not been previously treated, or after
      surgical resection of a single metastasis (central nervous system or adrenal). The trial aims
      to reduce the risk of systemic progression and thereby improve progression free survival.
      Participants will receive induction treatment consisting of immunotherapy combined with
      platinum-based doublet chemotherapy and stereotactic body radiotherapy (SBRT) that will be
      given to all oligo-metastatic locations. SBRT started early and concurrently with
      immunotherapy aims at enhancing a postulated immune effect and simultaneously effectively
      control the macro-metastases.

      Preclinical data have shown a strong immune-enhancing effect of radiotherapy, especially when
      delivered to small volumes, in high-single fraction doses and over a short period of time.
      Consequently, stereotactic body radiotherapy (SBRT) is currently being intensively
      investigated as a partner for systemic immunotherapy. Earlier clinical studies generated
      proof-of-principle data for the synergistic effects of combined radiotherapy and
      immunotherapy. Chemotherapy and high-dose radiotherapy are well known triggers of immunogenic
      cell death and are therefore highly promising partners for combination with immunotherapy.

      The sub-group of patients with &quot;oligometastatic&quot; disease was originally described by Hellman
      and Weichselbaum in 1995. In line with this concept, the current NCCN and ESMO guidelines
      describe that Stage IV NSCLC patients presenting with solitary metastases can be treated with
      curative intent using local surgery and/or radiotherapy. Local treatment for oligo-metastatic
      NSCLC has been adopted rapidly in the oncological community and one reason is the progress
      made in the fields of surgery and radiotherapy, both becoming less toxic (minimally invasive
      surgery) and simultaneously less toxic and more effective (precision radiotherapy),
      respectively. SBRT allows treatment of small peripheral primaries and metastases at virtually
      all anatomical locations with a favourable therapeutic ratio of local tumour control rates
      &gt;90% and low rates of toxicity. Simultaneously, minimally invasive surgery for early and
      locally advanced NSCLC today achieves excellent local tumour control with low rates of
      toxicity.

      Patients with a limited number of metastases - oligometastatic disease - are currently
      treated with combined radical local treatment for all active lesions (locoregional primary
      and metastases) and their prognosis is better as compared to patients who receive systemic
      treatment only for widespread metastatic disease. However, the majority of patients still
      develop systemic disease progression indicating the urgent clinical need for more effective
      systemic treatment to control subclinical disease.

      All CHESS trial participants will receive induction treatment with the immunotherapy drug
      durvalumab, standard platinum-chemotherapy and radiation therapy of the lung cancer
      metastases (SBRT). Durvalumab is a human monoclonal antibody carefully engineered to attach
      to immune cells to stimulate their activity against cancer cells. There are now several
      approved antibodies for the treatment of cancer or other diseases. Standard
      platinum-chemotherapy includes treatment with carboplatin and paclitaxel.

      After three months of induction treatment the status of the lung cancer will be restaged. If
      the primary lung cancer is stable or has not increased in size it will be surgically removed
      if possible or, alternatively, treated with radiation therapy. Treatment with durvalumab will
      continue until the disease relapses or for a maximum of one year from the start of induction
      treatment. If the lung cancer has increased in size at the time of the three month restaging
      all trial treatment will stop and the study doctor will discuss other treatment options that
      are available.

      The efficacy, safety and tolerability of combining immunotherapy with standard
      platinum-chemotherapy and SBRT will be evaluated in the CHESS clinical trial.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 19, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression-free survival at 12 months</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed from the date of enrolment to completion of treatment at 12 months.</time_frame>
    <description>Defined as time from date of enrollment until documented progression. Progression is defined as the development of new metastatic lesions or local progression of resected or irradiated metastases or primary tumour, assessed according to RECIST 1.1 criteria.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival</measure>
    <time_frame>Time from date of enrolment until death from any cause. Assessed for up to 30 months.</time_frame>
    <description>Defined as the time from date of enrolment until death from any cause. Censoring will occur at the last follow-up date.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pattern of disease progression</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed from the date of enrolment until progression, from enrolment up to 12 months.</time_frame>
    <description>Defined as the site of first progression. None, locoregional, distant, or both locoregional and distant.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Response to induction therapy</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed from the start of protocol treatment until the end of the induction phase (restaging at 3-month tumour assessment).</time_frame>
    <description>Defined as the best overall response [complete response (CR) or partial response (PR)] according to RECIST 1.1 criteria.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Distant progression-free survival</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed from the date of enrolment for up to 12 months.</time_frame>
    <description>Defined as the date of development of new metastases, excluding oligometastasis diagnosed at enrolment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall response</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed from the start of protocol treatment across all time points until the end of protocol treatment, for up to 12 months.</time_frame>
    <description>Defined as best overall response [complete response (CR) or partial response (PR) according to RECIST 1.1 criteria.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of response</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed from the date of enrolment for up to 12 months.</time_frame>
    <description>Defined as the interval from the date of first documentation of objective response (CR or PR), according to RECIST 1.1 criteria to the date of first documented progression or response.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Symptom-specific and global quality of life: The Lung Cancer Symptom Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed at trial entry, until 6 months after treatment start and at 12 months from enrolment.</time_frame>
    <description>The Lung Cancer Symptom Scale, a 9-item one page questionnaire will be used to assess change in total score (average of all 9 items).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Toxicity before and after surgery/radiotherapy</measure>
    <time_frame>Adverse events will be collected from the date of consent until 90 days after the completion of treatment.</time_frame>
    <description>Safety parameters will be assessed in terms of adverse events graded by CTCAE v5.0 including events leading to dose interruptions, withdrawals of protocol treatment and death; severe, serious and selected adverse events; deaths; laboratory parameters and abnormalities, and vital signs.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">47</enrollment>
  <condition>Non-small Cell Lung Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Stage IV</condition>
  <condition>Oligometastasis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Immunotherapy, chemotherapy, radiotherapy and surgery</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Durvalumab 1500 mg administered intravenously every 3 weeks for the first 4-6 cycles (during chemotherapy);
4-6 cycles of chemotherapy, carboplatin AUC5 every 3 weeks plus paclitaxel 175 mg/m2, every 3 weeks;
Stereotactic body radiotherapy (SBRT) of all oligo-metastatic lesions, in a maximum of 10 treatment fractions over 2 weeks, starting after week one of chemotherapy cycle 1 and completed within four weeks after start of durvalumab treatment;
Restaging at 3 months; if no disease progression, proceed to definitive local treatment (surgical resection of primary tumour or radiotherapy at a minimum dose of 60-66Gy to the primary tumour). Durvalumab continues at 1500 mg intravenously every 4 weeks until progression of disease or for a maximum of 1 year from start of treatment.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Durvalumab</intervention_name>
    <description>Durvalumab is a human monoclonal antibody (mAb) of the immunoglobulin G (IgG) 1 kappa subclass that inhibits binding of PD-L1. Durvalumab is expected to stimulate the patient's antitumour immune response by binding to PD L1 and shifting the balance toward an antitumour response.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Immunotherapy, chemotherapy, radiotherapy and surgery</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Imfinzi</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Carboplatin</intervention_name>
    <description>Carboplatin belongs to the group of medicines known as alkylating agents. Carboplatin interferes with the growth of cancer cells, which eventually are destroyed.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Immunotherapy, chemotherapy, radiotherapy and surgery</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Paclitaxel</intervention_name>
    <description>A compound extracted from the Pacific yew tree Taxus brevifolia with antineoplastic activity. Paclitaxel binds to tubulin and inhibits the disassembly of microtubules, thereby resulting in the inhibition of cell division. This agent also induces apoptosis by binding to and blocking the function of the apoptosis inhibitor protein Bcl-2 (B-cell Leukemia 2).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Immunotherapy, chemotherapy, radiotherapy and surgery</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Radiation</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Stereotactic body radiation therapy (SBRT)</intervention_name>
    <description>SBRT of all oligo-metastatic lesions</description>
    <arm_group_label>Immunotherapy, chemotherapy, radiotherapy and surgery</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Surgical resection - definitive local treatment.</intervention_name>
    <description>Surgical resection of primary tumour for patients with single station, non-bulky tumours.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Immunotherapy, chemotherapy, radiotherapy and surgery</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Radiation</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Radical radiotherapy - definitive local treatment.</intervention_name>
    <description>Conventional or moderately hypo-fractionated radiotherapy to the primary tumour for other tumour stages, or in case of medical inoperability.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Immunotherapy, chemotherapy, radiotherapy and surgery</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Histologically confirmed non-small cell lung cancer

          -  Synchronous oligo-metastatic stage IV disease: maximum of three distant metastases,
             one of which must be extra-cerebral for stereotactic body radiotherapy (SBRT); Initial
             mediastinal staging is recommended (except for lymph nodes &lt;1 cm on CT and
             PET-negative) preferentially by endobronchial ultrasound (EBUS); Neurosurgical
             resection of one single central nervous system (CNS) metastasis or laparoscopic
             resection of one adrenal metastasis before study inclusion is allowed (one
             extra-cerebral metastasis must be available for SBRT)

          -  Able to understand and give written informed consent and comply with study procedures

          -  Age ≥18 years

          -  ECOG Performance Status 0-1

          -  Availability of tumour tissue for translational research

          -  Adequate haematological, renal and liver function

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Prior chemotherapy, radiotherapy or therapeutic surgery for NSCLC (an exception is the
             resection of one single CNS or adrenal metastasis, as above)

          -  Activating driver mutation: epidermal growth factor receptor (EGFR), anaplastic
             lymphoma kinase (ALK), proto-oncogene receptor tyrosine kinase (ROS1)

          -  More than three distant metastases

          -  Brain metastases not amendable for radiosurgery or neurosurgery

          -  Extracranial metastatic locations such as malignant ascites, pleural or pericardial
             effusion, diffuse lymphangitiosis of skin or lung, diffuse bone marrow metastasis,
             abdominal masses/abdominal organomegaly, identified by physical exam that is not
             measurable by reproducible imaging techniques.

          -  Primary lung cancer not suitable for radical therapy (pneumonectomy excluded)

          -  History of leptomeningeal carcinomatosis

          -  Major surgery or significant traumatic injury from which the patient has not recovered
             at least 28 days before enrolment

          -  Any uncontrolled intercurrent illness, including but not limited to: ongoing or active
             infection, symptomatic congestive heart failure, uncontrolled hypertension, unstable
             angina pectoris, cardiac arrhythmia, interstitial lung disease or serious chronic
             gastrointestinal conditions associated with diarrhea, which in the investigator's
             opinion makes it undesirable for the patient to participate in the trial or which
             would jeopardise compliance with the protocol

          -  Active tuberculosis, hepatitis B, hepatitis C or human immunodeficiency virus (HIV)
             infection

          -  Active autoimmune disease requiring systemic treatment

          -  Severe or uncontrolled cardiac disease requiring treatment

          -  History of primary immunodeficiency

          -  History of allogeneic organ transplant

          -  Receipt of live attenuated vaccines within 30 days prior to enrolment

          -  Known allergies or hypersensitivity to trial drugs or to any excipient.

          -  Women who are pregnant or in the period of lactation.

          -  Sexually active men and women of childbearing potential who are not willing to use an
             effective contraceptive method during the trial and for up to 90 days after last dose
             of durvalumab.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Matthias Guckenberger, MD-PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>University Hospital, Zürich</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Isabelle Schmitt-Opitz, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>University Hospital, Zürich</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Barbara Ruepp, PharmD</last_name>
    <phone>+41315119400</phone>
    <email>barbara.ruepp@ibcsg.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Maastricht University Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Maastricht</city>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Lizza Hendriks, MD</last_name>
      <email>dirk.deruysscher@maastro.nl</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Lizza Hendriks, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Erasmus Medical Centre</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rotterdam</city>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Joachim Aerts, MD</last_name>
      <email>j.aerts@erasmusmc.nl</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Joachim Aerts, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hosp. De la Santa Creu i Sant Pau</name>
      <address>
        <city>Barcelona</city>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ivana Sullivan, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ivana Sullivan, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hosp. Uni. Virgen de las Nieves</name>
      <address>
        <city>Granada</city>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Javier Valdivia, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Javier Valdivia, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hosp. Sanchinarro- Centro Integral Oncología Clara Campal</name>
      <address>
        <city>Madrid</city>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Beatriz Jimenez Munarriz, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Beatriz Jimenez Munarriz, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hosp. Uni. Politécnico La Fe</name>
      <address>
        <city>Valencia</city>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Oscar Juan-Vidal, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Oscar Juan-Vidal, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Inselspital Bern</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bern</city>
        <country>Switzerland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Amina Scherz, MD</last_name>
      <email>amina.scherz@insel.ch</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Amina Scherz, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Geneva University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Geneva</city>
        <country>Switzerland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Alfredo Addeo, MD</last_name>
      <email>alfredo.addeo@hcuge.ch</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Alfredo Addeo, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Centre Hospitalier Universitaire Vaudois (CHUV)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lausanne</city>
        <country>Switzerland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Solage Peters</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Solange Peters, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Hospital Zurich</name>
      <address>
        <city>Zurich</city>
        <country>Switzerland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Matthias Guckenberger, MD</last_name>
      <email>Matthias.Guckenberger@usz.ch</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Matthias Guckenberger, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Netherlands</country>
    <country>Spain</country>
    <country>Switzerland</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Reck M, Rodríguez-Abreu D, Robinson AG, Hui R, Csőszi T, Fülöp A, Gottfried M, Peled N, Tafreshi A, Cuffe S, O'Brien M, Rao S, Hotta K, Leiby MA, Lubiniecki GM, Shentu Y, Rangwala R, Brahmer JR; KEYNOTE-024 Investigators. Pembrolizumab versus Chemotherapy for PD-L1-Positive Non-Small-Cell Lung Cancer. N Engl J Med. 2016 Nov 10;375(19):1823-1833. Epub 2016 Oct 8.</citation>
    <PMID>27718847</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Galluzzi L, Buqué A, Kepp O, Zitvogel L, Kroemer G. Immunogenic cell death in cancer and infectious disease. Nat Rev Immunol. 2017 Feb;17(2):97-111. doi: 10.1038/nri.2016.107. Epub 2016 Oct 17. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>27748397</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Langer CJ, Gadgeel SM, Borghaei H, Papadimitrakopoulou VA, Patnaik A, Powell SF, Gentzler RD, Martins RG, Stevenson JP, Jalal SI, Panwalkar A, Yang JC, Gubens M, Sequist LV, Awad MM, Fiore J, Ge Y, Raftopoulos H, Gandhi L; KEYNOTE-021 investigators. Carboplatin and pemetrexed with or without pembrolizumab for advanced, non-squamous non-small-cell lung cancer: a randomised, phase 2 cohort of the open-label KEYNOTE-021 study. Lancet Oncol. 2016 Nov;17(11):1497-1508. doi: 10.1016/S1470-2045(16)30498-3. Epub 2016 Oct 10.</citation>
    <PMID>27745820</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rizvi NA, Hellmann MD, Brahmer JR, Juergens RA, Borghaei H, Gettinger S, Chow LQ, Gerber DE, Laurie SA, Goldman JW, Shepherd FA, Chen AC, Shen Y, Nathan FE, Harbison CT, Antonia S. Nivolumab in Combination With Platinum-Based Doublet Chemotherapy for First-Line Treatment of Advanced Non-Small-Cell Lung Cancer. J Clin Oncol. 2016 Sep 1;34(25):2969-79. doi: 10.1200/JCO.2016.66.9861. Epub 2016 Jun 27.</citation>
    <PMID>27354481</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Twyman-Saint Victor C, Rech AJ, Maity A, Rengan R, Pauken KE, Stelekati E, Benci JL, Xu B, Dada H, Odorizzi PM, Herati RS, Mansfield KD, Patsch D, Amaravadi RK, Schuchter LM, Ishwaran H, Mick R, Pryma DA, Xu X, Feldman MD, Gangadhar TC, Hahn SM, Wherry EJ, Vonderheide RH, Minn AJ. Radiation and dual checkpoint blockade activate non-redundant immune mechanisms in cancer. Nature. 2015 Apr 16;520(7547):373-7. doi: 10.1038/nature14292. Epub 2015 Mar 9.</citation>
    <PMID>25754329</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kang J, Demaria S, Formenti S. Current clinical trials testing the combination of immunotherapy with radiotherapy. J Immunother Cancer. 2016 Sep 20;4:51. doi: 10.1186/s40425-016-0156-7. eCollection 2016.</citation>
    <PMID>27660705</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bernstein MB, Krishnan S, Hodge JW, Chang JY. Immunotherapy and stereotactic ablative radiotherapy (ISABR): a curative approach? Nat Rev Clin Oncol. 2016 Aug;13(8):516-24. doi: 10.1038/nrclinonc.2016.30. Epub 2016 Mar 8. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26951040</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Golden EB, Chhabra A, Chachoua A, Adams S, Donach M, Fenton-Kerimian M, Friedman K, Ponzo F, Babb JS, Goldberg J, Demaria S, Formenti SC. Local radiotherapy and granulocyte-macrophage colony-stimulating factor to generate abscopal responses in patients with metastatic solid tumours: a proof-of-principle trial. Lancet Oncol. 2015 Jul;16(7):795-803. doi: 10.1016/S1470-2045(15)00054-6. Epub 2015 Jun 18.</citation>
    <PMID>26095785</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hellman S, Weichselbaum RR. Oligometastases. J Clin Oncol. 1995 Jan;13(1):8-10.</citation>
    <PMID>7799047</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Weichselbaum RR, Hellman S. Oligometastases revisited. Nat Rev Clin Oncol. 2011 Jun;8(6):378-82. doi: 10.1038/nrclinonc.2011.44. Epub 2011 Mar 22. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21423255</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 24, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 28, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 29, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 20, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 20, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 21, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>NSCLC</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lung Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Non-Small-Cell Lung</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Paclitaxel</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carboplatin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Durvalumab</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

