<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03963193</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HNCH-GI-005</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03963193</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Etoposide/Cisplatin Compared With Irinotecan/Cisplatin for Advanced Gastrointestinal Neuroendocrine Tumor G3 Type</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase II Trial of Etoposide Plus Cisplatin Compared With Irinotecan Plus Cisplatin for First-line Treatment of Non-primary Pancreatic Metastatic and/or Unresectable Gastrointestinal Neuroendocrine Tumor G3 Type</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Henan Cancer Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Henan Cancer Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The aim of this study is to investigate the efficacy, safety, and survival benefit of
      etoposide plus cisplatin and irinotecan plus cisplatin in first-line therapy of non-primary
      pancreatic metastatic and/or unresectable gastrointestinal neuroendocrine tumor G3 type. In
      addition, the investigators will explore the resistance mechanisms of gastrointestinal
      neuroendocrine tumor G3, and screen out biomarkers that can predict the efficacy of
      chemotherapy.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The prognosis of gastrointestinal neuroendocrine tumor G3 type patients who cannot be
      surgically resected is poor. The median overall survival (OS) is only 6-10 months, and the
      3-year survival rate is less than 10%. Among the neuroendocrine tumors of the digestive
      system, only pancreatic neuroendocrine tumor has a standard treatment strategy, and there is
      a lack of prospective clinical research data on other gastrointestinal neuroendocrine tumors.
      According to the chemotherapy regimen of small cell lung cancer, etoposide plus cisplatin or
      irinotecan plus cisplatin is the choice of rescue therapy for advanced non-surgical or
      metastatic neuroendocrine tumor G3 type. However, prospective studies are needed to confirm
      whether there are differences in efficacy and safety between the two chemotherapy regimens.
      The aim of this study is to investigate the efficacy, safety, and survival benefit of
      etoposide plus cisplatin and irinotecan plus cisplatin in first-line therapy of non-primary
      pancreatic metastatic and/or unresectable gastrointestinal neuroendocrine tumor G3 type. In
      addition, the investigators will explore the resistance mechanisms of gastrointestinal
      neuroendocrine tumor G3, and screen out biomarkers that can predict the efficacy of
      chemotherapy.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">June 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 1, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 1, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Objective response rate (ORR)</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <description>To compare objective response rate of the two arms from date of anti-cancer therapy until progression</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression-free Survival (PFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <description>From the first day of treatment until the date of first documented progression or date of death from any cause</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival (OS)</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <description>From the first day of treatment to death or last survival confirm date</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants with Treatment-related Adverse Events</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Treatment-related adverse events will be assessed by CT CAE v4.0</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assessment of Health-related quality of life</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Quality of Life Questionnaire (QLQ-C30) will be evaluated since treatment begins. At the end of the trail, the differences between the two indicators will be compared with Mixed-effects model repeated measures (MMRM), where the baseline is scored as a covariant and the treatment group as a fixed variable. In addition, the baseline values of the two scores, the value of each visit, and the change value of the baseline will be statistically described.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">112</enrollment>
  <condition>Gastrointestinal Neuroendocrine Tumor</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Etoposide plus Cisplatin</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Etoposide 100mg/m^2 ivggt on days 1, 2, 3, Cisplatin 25mg/m^2 ivggt on days 1, 2, 3, repeated every 21 days. When the investigator believes that the participant is not suitable for continued medication or the evaluation is progressive disease (PD) according to the RECIST 1.1 standard, the medication is over.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Irinotecan plus Cisplatin</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Irinotecan 65 mg/m^2 ivggt on days 1, 8, Cisplatin 30 mg/m^2 ivggt on days 1, 8, repeated every 21 days. When the investigator believes that the participant is not suitable for continued medication or the evaluation is progressive disease (PD) according to the RECIST 1.1 standard, the medication is over.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Etoposide</intervention_name>
    <description>Etoposide 100mg/m^2 ivggt on days 1, 2, 3, Cisplatin 25mg/m^2 ivggt on days 1, 2, 3, repeated every 21 days.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Etoposide plus Cisplatin</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Cisplatin</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Irinotecan</intervention_name>
    <description>Irinotecan 65 mg/m^2 ivggt on days 1, 8, Cisplatin 30 mg/m^2 ivggt on days 1, 8, repeated every 21 days.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Irinotecan plus Cisplatin</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Cisplatin</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  1. 18-75 years old, male or female. 2. Confirmed non-primary pancreatic metastatic
             and/or unresectable gastrointestinal neuroendocrine tumor G3 type patients by
             histopathological and imaging examinations.

             3. ECOG performance status 0-1. 4. Life expectancy ≥ 12 weeks. 5. A histological
             specimen can be provided for secondary testing. 6. According to the evaluation
             criteria of solid tumor efficacy (RESIST 1.1), there should be at least one measurable
             lesion (empty organs such as esophagus and stomach cannot be taken as the measurable
             lesion), and the measurable lesion should not have received local treatment such as
             radiotherapy (the lesion located in the previous radiotherapy area is also selected as
             the target lesion if the lesion progression is confirmed).

             7. Never received system treatment before, including cytotoxic drugs. For patients who
             have received adjuvant or neoadjuvant chemotherapy appears recurrence or metastasis
             more than 6 months from accepting the last dose of chemotherapy drugs can be screened.

             8. The main organ function meets the following criteria within 7 days before
             treatment:

               1. Blood routine examination criteria (without blood transfusion within 14 days):
                  hemoglobin (HB) ≥ 90g/L, the absolute value of neutrophils (ANC) ≥ 1.5 x 10^9/L,
                  platelet (PLT) ≥ 80 x 10^9/L.

               2. Biochemical examinations must meet the following criteria: total bilirubin (TBIL)
                  ≤ 1.5 x upper limit of normal (ULN), alanine aminotransferase (ALT), aspartate
                  aminotransferase (AST) ≤ 2.5 x ULN, serum creatinine (Cr) ≤ 1.5 x ULN or
                  creatinine clearance (CCR) ≥ 60 mL/min.

               3. Doppler ultrasound assessment: left ventricular ejection fraction (LVEF) ≥ normal
                  low limit (50%).

             9. Fertile men and women must use effective contraception during the study period and
             within 6 months after the end of the study.

             10. Volunteered to participate in the study and signed an informed consent form.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  1.Patients exceeding or currently suffering from other malignant tumors within 5
             years, except for cervical cancer in site, non-melanoma skin cancer and superficial
             bladder tumors (Ta (non-invasive tumor), Tis (in situ carcinoma), and T1 (tumor
             infiltrating basement membrane)); Patients with rapid progress within 3 months.

             2. History of gastrointestinal perforation and/or fistula within 6 months prior to the
             first administration.

             3. Patients who had received radiotherapy for tumor target lesions within 4 weeks
             before enrollment.

             4. History of immunodeficiency disease, including HIV positive and other acquired or
             congenital immunodeficiency diseases.

             5. Allergic reactions and drug adverse reactions:

               1. A history of allergy to the ingredients of the study drug;

               2. Any contraindication to any study drug (etoposide, irinotecan and cis-platinum)
                  in the chemotherapy regimen.

             6. Significantly malnourished patients. Exclusion is performed if the patient is
             receiving intravenous fluids or is required to be hospitalized for continuous infusion
             therapy. Patients with good nutrition control ≥ 28 days can be enrolled before
             randomization.

             7. Any severe and/or uncontrolled disease, including:

               1. Patients with hypertension whose blood can't be well controlled by
                  antihypertensive drugs (systolic blood pressure ≥ 150 mmHg, diastolic blood
                  pressure ≥ 100 mmHg).

               2. Grade 1 or higher myocardial ischemia or myocardial infarction, arrhythmia
                  (including QTc ≥ 480 ms) or grade 2 and above congestive heart failure according
                  to New York Heart Association (MYHA) classification.

               3. Severe or uncontrolled disease or active infection (≥ CTC AE grade 2), which the
                  investigators believe may increase the risk associated with patient participation
                  and drug administration.

               4. Renal failure requiring hemodialysis or peritoneal dialysis.

               5. Patients of diabetes who have poor glycemic control (fasting blood glucose (FBG)
                  &gt; 10 mmol/L).

               6. Patients of seizures requiring treatment. 8. Patients with gastrointestinal
                  disease such as intestinal obstruction (including incomplete intestinal
                  obstruction) or those who may meet gastrointestinal bleeding, perforation
                  obstruction.

             9. Patients who underwent surgical treatment, incision biopsy or significant traumatic
             injury within 28 days prior to enrollment.

             10. Any bleeding event ≥ CTC AE grade 3 or unhealed wounds, ulcers or fractures in 4
             weeks prior to enrollment.

             11. Arterial/venous thrombosis events within 3 months, such as cerebrovascular
             accidents (including transient ischemic attacks), deep venous thrombosis and pulmonary
             embolism.

             12. Patients who prepared or accepted previously allogeneic organ or bone marrow
             transplantation, including liver transplantation.

             13. Concomitant disease that seriously harms the patient's safety or affects the
             patient's completion of the study according to the investigator's judgment.

             14. Patients cannot provide histological specimens for secondary test. 15. Patients
             who have a history of psychotropic substance abuse and are unable to quit or have a
             mental disorder.

             16. Urine routine showed urinary protein ≥ 2 + and 24-hour urine protein quantitation
             &gt; 1.0 g.

             17. Patients with brain metastases. 18. Patients who have participated in other
             anti-tumor drug clinical trials within 4 weeks.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Baoxia He</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Henan Cancer Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Ying Liu</last_name>
    <phone>13783604602</phone>
    <email>yaya7207@126.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <verification_date>May 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 20, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 23, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 24, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 23, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 23, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 24, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Neuroendocrine Tumors</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Intestinal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pancreatic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Stomach Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cisplatin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Etoposide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Irinotecan</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

