<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03963271</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NL67079.068.18</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03963271</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Noninvasive Electrocardiographic Imaging for Individuals at Risk for Apparently Idiopathic Ventricular Fibrillation.</brief_title>
  <acronym>VIGILANCE</acronym>
  <official_title>Noninvasive Electrocardiographic Imaging for Individuals at Risk for Apparently Idiopathic Ventricular Fibrillation.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Maastricht University Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Dutch Heart Foundation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Amsterdam University Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>UMC Utrecht</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Maastricht University Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study aims to evaluate the electrophysiological properties of the heart conduction
      system in patients with unexplained polymorphic ventricular tachycardia (VT) and/or
      ventricular fibrillation (VF), in patients with specific genetic mutations regarding sudden
      cardiac death or sudden cardiac arrest, in their family members and in a control cohort. The
      electrophysiological properties will be measured with the relatively new technique
      ECG-Imaging (ECGI).

      Also a National Dutch registry for patients with unexplained polymorphic VT and/or VF and
      their family members will be created.

      By combining the data from the registry and the results of ECGI, The investigators hope to
      identity risk markers for patients at higher risk for apparently idiopathic ventricular
      fibrillation, and use these for an adapted flow chart for the 'general'population of patients
      at risk for unexplained polymorphic VT and/or VF. The investigators aim to be able to
      identify patients before the first arrhythmic event, and aim for better treatment strategies
      in the future.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      ECGI combines electrical body-surface mapping with 256 electrodes placed on the thorax with a
      CT-scan obtaining the anatomy of the heart and torso, hereby able to reconstruct local
      electrograms, activation and recovery times. In recent research, ECGI provided numerous extra
      insights into normal cardiac electrophysiology, but also electrophysiological disorders and
      disease. The results strongly suggest that ECGI can play a pivotal role in further
      characterizing arrhythmia mechanisms, therefore could do so for polymorphic VT or idiopathic
      VF leading to diagnosis and treatment improvement. Moreover, ECGI seems to have the potential
      to detect arrhythmogenic substrate in individuals before their first event, offering the
      possibility to diagnose and treat patients before sudden cardiac arrest occurs.

      In the VIGILANCE study:

        1. ECGI will be used to noninvasively characterize the epicardial electrophysiological
           substrate and triggers of:

             -  Patients with unexplained polymorphic VT and VF,

             -  Index patients of family cohorts with a specific genetic mutation related to
                arrhythmogenesis, at high risk for unexplained polymorphic VT and/or VF.

             -  Family members,

             -  A control cohort. Results will be evaluated for risk stratification.

        2. All unexplained polymorphic VT and/or VF patients and their family members will be asked
           to participate in a National Dutch registry, and these date will be analysed to
           determine their prognostic value in terms of arrhythmia risk
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Enrolling by invitation</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">April 10, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 10, 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 10, 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational [Patient Registry]</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <target_duration>3 Years</target_duration>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>ECG-Imaging outcome: epicardial potentials</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>reconstructed epicardial potentials, represented in mV over time(s).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>ECG-Imaging outcome: activation and repolarization maps</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Activation and repolarization maps. These are made by measuring acivation and repolarization times from the reconstructed potentials in miliseconds. Then local activation and recovery times are plotted on a CT-derived heart mesh. The entire activation and repolarization of the epicardium of the heart can be visualized this way.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>(Possible) Prognostic risk factors for recurrent ventricular arrhythmias</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>possible risk factors, found in the registry, given as odds/hazard ratio.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Recurrence of ventricular arrhythmias</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>documentation over the period of follow-up, if studysubjects had a recurrence of ventricular arrythmia(s), presented as number of events over a time period.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>3</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">500</enrollment>
  <condition>Ventricular Fibrillation</condition>
  <condition>Ventricular Arrythmia</condition>
  <condition>Polymorphic Ventricular Tachycardia</condition>
  <condition>Sudden Cardiac Death</condition>
  <condition>Heart Arrest</condition>
  <condition>Cardiovascular Diseases</condition>
  <condition>Cardiac Arrhythmia</condition>
  <condition>Genetic Disease</condition>
  <condition>Idiopathic Ventricular Fibrillation</condition>
  <condition>Cardiac Arrest</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Patients with unexplained polymorphic VT and/or VF</arm_group_label>
    <description>Unexplained polymorphic VT and/or VF patients.
Patients with VF and the DPP6 risk haplotype, reported by the AUMC team.
The Worm population of patients with a SCN5A founder mutation and other conspiring genetic variants at MUMC+</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Family members</arm_group_label>
    <description>Family members of index patients of group(s) mentioned above</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control group</arm_group_label>
    <description>Control subjects with structurally normal hearts with an indication for a cardiac CT,</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ECG-Imaging</intervention_name>
    <description>A body surface potential mapping and a cardiac + low dose CT-scan.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Family members</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Patients with unexplained polymorphic VT and/or VF</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      DNA samples from blood, if analysed upon clinical indication
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        patients seen at the outpatient clinic at the department of cardiology or (cardio)genetics,
        patients admitted to the ward of cardiology or the intensive care unit.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        In order to be eligible to participate in this study, a subject must be ≥ 18 years old and
        meet one of the following criteria:

          -  All unexplained polymorphic VT or VF survivors in whom known structural myocardial,
             respiratory, metabolic and toxicological causes have been excluded through clinical
             evaluation&quot;, with/without a genetic mutation. NB. If results of a diagnostic tests
             show minor abnormalities but insufficient for a specific diagnosis, this is no
             exclusion criterion.

          -  Selected family members of these patients*

          -  Control subjects with structurally normal hearts with a clinical indication for a
             cardiac CT scan.

               -  All 1st and 2nd degree family members being in contact with the
                  cardiologist/treating physician as part of cascade screening will be contacted as
                  described in chapter 11.2.2.

        Family members must be in adequate health to be able to travel to the hospital for research
        purposes.

        3rd degree family members can also be contacted as described in chapter 11.2.2 if at least
        one of the following criteria is met:

          -  The family member has the same genetic mutation as index patient, or;

          -  The family member has demonstrated ventricular arrhythmias, or;

          -  The clinician has a very strong suspicion of ventricular arrhythmias in the family
             member.

        Exclusion Criteria:

        A potential subject who meets any of the following criteria will be excluded from
        participation in this study:

          -  A known strong reaction against electrode attachment or contrast agent.

          -  Any serious medical condition, which in the opinion of the investigator, may adversely
             affect the safety and/or effectiveness of the participant or the study.

          -  Pregnancy, nursing or planning to be pregnant.

          -  Subject has an estimated glomerular filtration rate (eGFR) of &lt;30mL/min/1.73m2

             , using the MDRD calculation

          -  Unability to give informed consent.

          -  Family members of patients with unexplained polymorphic VT/VF, who have severe cardiac
             abnormalities and/or disease not related to the symptoms or phenotype of the index
             patient, and which may have a negative influence on results of ECGI according to local
             investigators.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Paul Volders, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Maastricht University Medical Centre</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Maastricht Universite Medical Centre</name>
      <address>
        <city>Maastricht</city>
        <state>Nederland</state>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Amsterdam University medical Centre, location AMC</name>
      <address>
        <city>Amsterdam</city>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Medical Centre Utrecht</name>
      <address>
        <city>Utrecht</city>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Netherlands</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>August 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>April 23, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 22, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 24, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 13, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 13, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">August 15, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>idiopathic ventricular fibrillation</keyword>
  <keyword>polymorphic ventricular tachycardia</keyword>
  <keyword>body surface potential mapping</keyword>
  <keyword>ECG Imaging</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Heart Arrest</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Arrhythmias, Cardiac</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Tachycardia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Tachycardia, Ventricular</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Death, Sudden, Cardiac</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ventricular Fibrillation</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Genetic Diseases, Inborn</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Death</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cardiovascular Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

