<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03969147</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CHRMS 16-105</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03969147</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Investigation of a Novel Oropharyngeal Airway: The ManMaxAirway</brief_title>
  <official_title>Investigation of a Novel Oropharyngeal Airway: The ManMaxAirway</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Vermont</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Vermont</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Guedel pattern or oropharyngeal airways (OPA) maintain an open oral airway in unconscious or
      semi-conscious patients by preventing the tongue from covering the epiglottis, but OPA
      placement carries a risk of inducing gag reflex and vomiting. Although various sizes are
      available, the design of the OPA has undergone little change since its introduction in the
      1920s. The purpose of this study is to determine the utility of a novel airway device, the
      ManMaxAirway (MMA), as an alternative to the OPA.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Oropharyngeal airways are simple devices placed in the mouth that help to maintain an open
      oral airway in anesthetized or otherwise unconscious or semi-conscious patients and also help
      to facilitate assisted ventilation with a bag and mask. The current standard of care, the
      Guedel airway, was originally designed by Dr. Arthur Guedel in 1933 and has remained
      essentially unchanged since its inception. It is a narrow, curved plastic tube which slides
      over the tongue to lie in the back of the throat. While this device has withstood the test of
      time, proving to be largely safe and effective, it is known to have several drawbacks: 1) it
      is not held securely in place in the mouth which allows it to become easily mal-positioned or
      expelled, 2) it often triggers a gag reflex in even minimally conscious patients limiting its
      utility in emergency and prehospital settings, 3) there are case reports of serious
      complication and injury as a result of the poor fit and retention of the Guedel airway
      including aspiration and injury to the tongue, posterior pharynx, and teeth, and 4) the
      Guedel airway's narrow and rigid construction make it unsuitable for patients who may clench
      their teeth, such as in patients who are seizing.

      The purpose of this study is to obtain preliminary data to help determine the utility of the
      ManMaxAirway (MMA) for ventilation and that will aid in future study designs for the device.
      The MMA is a novel oral airway that is similar in size and shape to an athletic mouth guard,
      and which fits between and is held in place by the teeth (or gums of the edentulous patient).
      The external portion of the airway contains a flange in the front which remains anterior to
      the teeth, allowing for ventilation in a similar fashion to the Guedel airway. It also has a
      central lumen that divides posterior to the flange into two lateral passages, such that air
      passes through the U-shaped device to the posterior-lateral aspect of the tongue behind the
      back teeth. Unlike the Guedel device, it makes little contact with the tongue and does not
      protrude into the posterior pharynx. Instead, the device will - in theory - force the
      mandible to rest slightly anterior to the maxilla: this slight mandible-maxilla displacement
      (similar to that achieved via the jaw thrust technique) will theoretically allow for a better
      opening of the airway without requiring direct depression of the tongue. We hypothesize that
      the ManMaxAirway will maintain a viable airway and allow for adequate ventilation of patients
      while demonstrating the following advantages over the Guedel airway: 1) improved tolerability
      and ease of insertion with decreased gag reflex stimulation in conscious patients 2) ability
      to act as a bite block in patients actively seizing or likely to seize.

      Our proposed study will include two major aims in assessing the utility of the MMA. Our first
      aim will be to assess the mechanical effect of the device on the oropharyngeal anatomy. We
      will obtain MRI images of several healthy volunteers, with and without the MMA in place, in
      order to observe any displacement of the mandible relative to the maxilla, and any changes in
      positioning of the tongue. We will also assess the physical performance characteristics of
      the MMA vs. Guedel in terms of flow resistance in the simulation laboratory. Our second aim
      will be to determine whether there is any difference in tolerability between the Man Max
      Airway and the Guedel airway. To address the second aim we propose a crossover study using
      conscious, healthy volunteers, in which subjects will be asked to place each device in their
      mouth, one after the other. We will document the elapsed time and the number of breaths that
      subjects are able to take with each device in place (up to one minute), and will obtain
      ratings of device discomfort from each subject using a visual analog scale. We will also
      measure resistance to forced oscillatory airflow in a subset of subjects, with and without
      the airway in place, at a second visit.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Ability to place the Novel Airway Adjunct</measure>
    <time_frame>1 minute (During tolerability comparison experiment)</time_frame>
    <description>Any inability of conscious, healthy volunteers to place the device (MMA) in their mouth will be recorded.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Displacement of the mandibular condyle and the condylar fossa apex (MRI arm)</measure>
    <time_frame>2-3 weeks following MRI scans.</time_frame>
    <description>A radiologist will measure displacement (mm) between the mandibular condyle and condylar fossa apex using MRI on healthy subjects with and without the device (MMA) in place.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of respirations with airway adjunct in place (Tolerability Arm)</measure>
    <time_frame>1 minute (During tolerability comparison experiment)</time_frame>
    <description>Recorded by research staff while healthy subject has airway adjunct (either MMA or OPA) in place.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Elapsed time (up to 60 seconds) that subject is able to tolerate having the airway adjunct in place (Tolerability Arm)</measure>
    <time_frame>1 minute (During tolerability comparison experiment.)</time_frame>
    <description>Recorded by research staff while healthy subject has airway adjunct (either MMA or OPA) in place.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Visual Analog Tolerability</measure>
    <time_frame>1 minute (following tolerability comparison experiment.)</time_frame>
    <description>100 mm line that subjects will use to mark level of discomfort for each device (MMA or OPA), with 0mm correlating to complete tolerability with no discomfort and 100mm correlating to completely intolerable discomfort.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Resistance to oscillatory air flow</measure>
    <time_frame>1 minute (Assessment done following physical lab tests)</time_frame>
    <description>Airflow resistance (cmH20·s/L) of the two devices (MMA and OPA) will be compared using forced oscillations measured in a pulmonary lab.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Airway Obstruction</condition>
  <condition>Respiratory Complication</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>MRI Comparison</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>MRI images will be obtained of the airways of healthy volunteers both with the ManMaxAirway oropharyngeal airway adjunct and with no airway adjunct in place in order to observe any changes to the airway anatomy caused by placement of the airway adjunct. The order of the scans (with and without airway adjunct) will be determined by randomization software in advance.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Tolerability Comparison</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Healthy volunteers will self-place either the ManMaxAirway oropharyngeal airway adjunct or the Guedel Oropharyngeal airway adjunct, which will be left in place for an interval of one minute, while supervised by research staff. After completing a questionnaire and resting for a timed interval, they will then self-place the other airway adjunct, which will be left in place for the same length of time as the first, before completing another questionnaire. The order in which the devices are placed by each subject will be determined in advance via computer randomization.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Forced Oscillation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Volunteers from the tolerability comparison arm will also be invited as a subset of subjects to participate in a measurement of resistance to forced oscillation. The volunteers will be subject to forced oscillations in a pulmonary function lab with the ManMaxAirway oropharyngeal airway adjunct in place and with no airway adjunct in order to observe changes in resistance to oscillatory airflow</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ManMaxAirway oropharyngeal airway adjunct</intervention_name>
    <description>Healthy volunteers will self-place the ManMaxAirway.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Forced Oscillation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>MRI Comparison</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Tolerability Comparison</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Guedel Oropharyngeal airway adjunct</intervention_name>
    <description>Healthy volunteers will self-place the standard Guedel OPA.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Tolerability Comparison</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>No airway adjunct</intervention_name>
    <description>Healthy volunteers will have no airway adjunct in place.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Forced Oscillation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>MRI Comparison</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Healthy volunteers over the age of 18.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  For Tolerability arm: History of Gastroesophageal Reflux Disease, dental implants or
             dental prostheses

          -  For the MRI arm, the following were further exclusion criteria as dictated by
             institutional MRI safety protocols: claustrophobia, cerebral aneurysm clip, nerve
             stimulation device, cochlear/middle ear implant, transdermal patches, known metal in
             body (to include IUD), intraventricular shunt, implanted pumps or stents, pregnant,
             metal implants, cardiac pacemaker, Swan Ganz catheter, metal worker occupation,
             history of eye injury with metal.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Kalev Freeman, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Vermont Department of Surgery</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Zachary Miller, BA</last_name>
    <phone>8026568372</phone>
    <email>zdmiller@uvm.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Vermont College of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Burlington</city>
        <state>Vermont</state>
        <zip>05401</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Rejeanne Jalbert, BA</last_name>
      <phone>802-656-4216</phone>
      <email>rejeanne.jalbert@med.uvm.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 16, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 29, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 31, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 29, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 29, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 31, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Vermont</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Kalev Freeman</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor of Surgery</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Airway Obstruction</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

