<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03961217</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ANB_691-17</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03961217</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Return to Work Among Cancer Survivors With Treatment-induced Survivorship Syndromes</brief_title>
  <official_title>Return to Work Among Cancer Survivors With Treatment-induced Survivorship Syndromes</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Sahlgrenska University Hospital, Sweden</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Vastra Gotaland Region</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Sahlgrenska University Hospital, Sweden</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The investigators plan to investigate the consequences of late effects (radiation-induced
      survivorship syndromes) after radiotherapy in Gynecological and Prostate cancer survivors on
      return to work (Yes/No) and if RTW happened then time to RTW.

      In addition, whether general health, type of work (occupation), work environment factors,
      individual factors (lifestyle, socioeconomic status etc.), contribute to the adverse late
      effects of radiotherapy and these Gynecological cancer survivors have a higher risk for
      disability pension/long term sickness absence (NOT Return to work).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Occurrence of cancer diagnoses are rising, and both disease and treatments are aggressive.
      Due to advancement in medical technology, improved therapy and/or early detection the overall
      survival rates are also improving.

      Some of the most common cancer types, such as breast cancer, prostate cancer, cervical
      cancer, and colorectal cancer have high cure rates when detected early and treated according
      to best practices. Many of these cancer survivors are of working age and are likely to return
      to work. Women who survive cervical cancer and men who survive testicular cancer typically
      have three to four decades left in working life.

      However, return to work (RTW) among cancer survivors may not be similar to RTW among
      long-term sickness absentees due to other diagnoses. Cancer is a life threatening disease and
      cancer diagnose is a life changing event. The emotional shock after the cancer diagnosis may
      be associated with low psychological well-being even two years after prostate cancer surgery.

      The successful cancer treatment concludes with the lifelong consequences of surgery,
      irradiation, cytotoxic chemotherapy, biological anticancer substances or other drugs in the
      treatment. The ionizing radiation that eliminates malignant cells may trigger long-lasting
      pathophysiological processes in the normal tissue and affect the health of the survivors with
      lifelong treatment-induced survivorship diseases. In a recent study, Steineck et al,
      identified five radiation-induced survivorship syndromes affecting bowel health in a cohort
      of gynecological cancer; urgency syndrome (30%), leakage syndrome (26%), excessive gas
      discharge(15%), excessive mucus discharge (16%) and blood discharge (10%).

      There is a lack of knowledge about how these side effects of cancer treatment affect the
      degree of work ability and return to work. Clinical experience suggests that many cancer
      survivors have reduced work ability. There is a need for scientific studies that shed light
      on the side effects of cancer treatment and their relation to work ability.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 1991</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">October 2006</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational [Patient Registry]</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Only</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <target_duration>5 Years</target_duration>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Return to work (RTW)</measure>
    <time_frame>Five - Ten years after mapping Radiation-induced survivorship syndromes</time_frame>
    <description>Information on Sickness absence for more than 14 days was obtained from the official registries in Sweden.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to Return to work</measure>
    <time_frame>Five - Ten years after mapping Radiation-induced survivorship syndromes</time_frame>
    <description>Sickness absence (more than 14 days) until the survivor returned to work. Also obtained from the official registries in Sweden.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>3</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">2135</enrollment>
  <condition>Gynecologic Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Prostate Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Radiation Toxicity</condition>
  <condition>Malignancy</condition>
  <condition>Radiotherapy Side Effect</condition>
  <condition>Radiation Injuries</condition>
  <condition>Cancer Survivors</condition>
  <condition>Radiation Syndrome</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Gynecological Cases</arm_group_label>
    <description>Gynecological Cancer survivors with treatment induced survivorship syndroms treated pelvic radiotherapy at
Radiumhemmat, Karolinska University Hospital and
Jubileumskliniken at Sahlgrenska University Hospital in Sweden.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Prostate Cases</arm_group_label>
    <description>Prostate Cancer survivors treated with radiotherapy for localized prostate cancer at Sahlgrenska University Hospital, Gothenburg, Sweden</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Gynecological Rehab Cases</arm_group_label>
    <description>Gynecological Cancer survivors with treatment induced survivorship syndroms treated pelvic radiotherapy</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Radiation</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Radiotherapy</intervention_name>
    <description>Radiotherapy as part of cancer treatment</description>
    <arm_group_label>Gynecological Cases</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Gynecological Rehab Cases</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Prostate Cases</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Cohort of women treated with external pelvic radiotherapy for a gynaecological malignancy
        and men treated with radiotherapy for prostate cancer at two large oncology clinics in
        Sweden.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Age 25 to 60 years (working age)

          2. Employed at time of diagnosis

          3. Treated for cancer

          4. Suffering from at least one of Radiation-induced survivorship syndromes

          5. First cancer &amp; first time treatment for cancer,

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. No other chronic disease

          2. Chronic intestinal illness/surgery

          3. Stage IV cancer

          4. Recurrent cancer/Relapse
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <gender_based>Yes</gender_based>
    <gender_description>Gyaecological cancer survivors Prostate cancer survivors</gender_description>
    <minimum_age>25 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>60 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Gunnar Steineck</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Clinical Cancer Epidemiology, Sahlgrenska Academy, Gothenburg, Sweden</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Jubileumskliniken, Sahlgrenska University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Gothenburg</city>
        <zip>413 45</zip>
        <country>Sweden</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Sweden</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ejca.2009.10.023</url>
    <description>Self-reported symptoms of faecal incontinence among long-term gynaecological cancer survivors and population-based controls</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>https://dx.doi.org/10.1371%2Fjournal.pone.0171461</url>
    <description>Identifying radiation-induced survivorship syndromes affecting bowel health in a cohort of gynecological cancer survivors</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.radonc.2011.06.010</url>
    <description>Tobacco smoking and long-lasting symptoms from the bowel and the anal-sphincter region after radiotherapy for prostate cancer</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>https://www.nature.com/articles/bjc2011315</url>
    <description>Late symptoms in long-term gynaecological cancer survivors after radiation therapy: a population-based cohort study</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Steineck G, Skokic V, Sjöberg F, Bull C, Alevronta E, Dunberger G, Bergmark K, Wilderäng U, Oh JH, Deasy JO, Jörnsten R. Identifying radiation-induced survivorship syndromes affecting bowel health in a cohort of gynecological cancer survivors. PLoS One. 2017 Feb 3;12(2):e0171461. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0171461. eCollection 2017.</citation>
    <PMID>28158314</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dunberger G, Lind H, Steineck G, Waldenström AC, Nyberg T, Al-Abany M, Nyberg U, Vall-Lundqvist E. Self-reported symptoms of faecal incontinence among long-term gynaecological cancer survivors and population-based controls. Eur J Cancer. 2010 Feb;46(3):606-15. doi: 10.1016/j.ejca.2009.10.023. Epub 2009 Nov 18.</citation>
    <PMID>19926277</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Alsadius D, Hedelin M, Johansson KA, Pettersson N, Wilderäng U, Lundstedt D, Steineck G. Tobacco smoking and long-lasting symptoms from the bowel and the anal-sphincter region after radiotherapy for prostate cancer. Radiother Oncol. 2011 Dec;101(3):495-501. doi: 10.1016/j.radonc.2011.06.010. Epub 2011 Jul 5.</citation>
    <PMID>21737169</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lind H, Waldenström AC, Dunberger G, al-Abany M, Alevronta E, Johansson KA, Olsson C, Nyberg T, Wilderäng U, Steineck G, Åvall-Lundqvist E. Late symptoms in long-term gynaecological cancer survivors after radiation therapy: a population-based cohort study. Br J Cancer. 2011 Sep 6;105(6):737-45. doi: 10.1038/bjc.2011.315. Epub 2011 Aug 16.</citation>
    <PMID>21847122</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 22, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 22, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 23, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 23, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 23, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 28, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Sahlgrenska University Hospital, Sweden</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Gunnar Steineck</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor / Senior consultant</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Return to work</keyword>
  <keyword>Disability pension</keyword>
  <keyword>Sickness Absence</keyword>
  <keyword>Employability</keyword>
  <keyword>Fitness to work</keyword>
  <keyword>Wellbeing</keyword>
  <keyword>Radiotherapy Side Effect</keyword>
  <keyword>Cancer Survivors</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Radiation Injuries</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

