<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03968926</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>RECHMPL19_0049</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03968926</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Hypotension During Extracorporeal Circulatory Support Indicated for Cardiogenic Shock</brief_title>
  <acronym>RetroECMO-VP</acronym>
  <official_title>Vasoplegia During VA-ECMO for Refractory Cardiogenic Shock : Descriptive Analysis of a Retrospective Cohort</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University Hospital, Montpellier</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University Hospital, Montpellier</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The cardiogenic shock is characterized by an alteration of organs function following a
      decrease in cardiac output linked to an impairment of cardiac performance. The prognosis
      remains poor with mortality between 40 and 50%. Nowadays, Extracorporeal Life Support (ECLS
      or VA-ECMO) is the referent therapy to restore blood flow in the body when medical treatment
      is not sufficient. Despite a good blood flow provided by the ECLS, many patients develop a
      severe hypotension (so called vasoplegia) due to a loss of vascular resistance mainly
      explained by the inflammatory response to shock and extracorporeal circulation. The treatment
      of this reaction includes vasopressors (Norepinephrine in usual care) and serum surrogate
      perfusion to achieve a mean arterial pressure (MAP) above 65 mmHg.

      The purpose of this study is to describe the patients with vasoplegia among a retrospective
      cohort of patients treated with an ECLS in our university center, over the 4 last years, to
      determine major complication rate (including death, kidney failure and arrythmias) and their
      outcome. This study will provide consistent data useful for further trials about targets of
      pressure and treatments to increase blood pressure during ECLS.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Cardiogenic shock is characterized by global tissue hypoperfusion following a decrease in
      cardiac output by impairing myocardial performance in the absence of hypovolemia. This
      life-threatening hypoperfusion quickly leads to multiple organs dysfunction with a high risk
      of cardiac arrest. The main cause is ischemic. The prognosis remains poor with mortality
      between 40 and 50% and depends on the speed of care by a specialized team. Early etiologic
      treatment is essential, but initial symptomatic management is based on catecholamines, mainly
      norepinephrine and dobutamine. The intra-aortic balloon pump showed no improvement in
      survival in large randomized studies. Refractory cardiogenic shock is defined by the
      inefficiency or intolerance of catecholamines and the indication of temporary circulatory
      support should be considered as soon as possible in the absence of contraindications
      (comorbidities, advanced age, therapeutic limitation). The veno-arterial extracorporeal
      membrane oxygenation (VA-ECMO or ECLS) is the preferred circulatory assistance in this
      indication because it provides an overall circulatory support up to 100% of the theoretical
      cardiac output, with oxygenation, and is quickly implanted peripherally (surgical or
      percutaneous cannulation of the femoral vein and the femoral artery). However, this
      extracorporeal circulation also has disadvantages by opposing a major afterload to the
      failing left ventricle and reducing or even abolishing the pulmonary circulation and blood
      flow in the heart chambers. In addition, the interaction with the artificial surfaces and the
      oxygenation membrane of the extracorporeal circuit contributes to the inflammatory response
      already initiated as a result of low cardiac output, tissue hypoperfusion, mesenteric
      ischemia and possibly myocardial infarction in case of acute coronary syndrome. This systemic
      inflammatory response syndrome (SIRS) is similar to sepsis and its main clinical presentation
      is a vascular dysfunction resulting in vasoplegia and capillary leak syndrome responsible for
      relative hypovolemia and interstitial inflation.

      Since the flow provided by the centrifugal pump is continuous, the blood pressure under
      VA-ECMO presents low or no pulsatile waves and is better represented by the mean arterial
      pressure (MAP). The ideal targets of MAP under VA-ECMO are controversial but it is widely
      accepted that the MAP should not be less than 65mmHg as recommended in septic shock to
      maintain an acceptable perfusion pressure and should not exceed 95mmHg to limit afterload.
      Between these limits, the MAP must be individualized according to each situation
      (hypertensive patient for example). In France, Norepinephrine is the first-line drug to
      achieve this goal of MAP after correction of volemia, without dose limitation in the absence
      of currently validated alternative, while resistance mechanisms can be activated, and its
      efficiency may be limited in case of acidosis. Potential side effects are the occurrence of
      atrial or ventricular arrhythmias, tachycardia, pro-inflammatory cytokine release,
      immunosuppression, renal dysfunction.

      Management of MAP and vasopressors under VA-ECMO is poorly described in the literature (5),
      although Norepinephrine is widely used in routine practice. In particular, the investigators
      do not know the frequency of use and Norepinephrine doses during ECMO-VA, as well as their
      prognostic involvement. Vasoplegia during VA-ECMO is defined by a Norepinephrine dose greater
      than 0.1µg/kg/min after a 500ml fluid challenge despite overall blood flow (ECMO + native
      heart) greater than 2l/min/m2 or allowing to achieve 65% of ScvO2.

      This cohort study aims to describe the vasoplegia observed during VA-ECMO, the Norepinephrine
      treatment characteristics, complications and outcome. The primary end-point is the incidence
      of a composite criteria of major complications including death, acute kidney injury and
      arrythmias.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 30, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 30, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 1, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Retrospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Major complication composite criteria</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 7 days for acute kidney injury and arrythmia, and 30 days for death</time_frame>
    <description>Observation of acute kidney injury defined by KDIGO classification 2 or 3, or severe arrythmia (i.e. atrial fibrillation with heart rate above 150bpm or a mean arterial pressure decrease of at least 20%, sustained ventricular tachycardia, ventricular fibrillation), or death</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Initial refractory hypotension</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Norepinephrine dose maintained always above 1µg/kg/min during the first 2 hours after VA-ECMO implantation for a minimal mean arterial pressure target at 65mmHg</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Refractory vasoplegia</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 7 days</time_frame>
    <description>Norepinephrine dose above 1µg/kg/min required to maintain mean arterial pressure above 65mmHg or at the personalized mean arterial pressure target</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mortality rate</measure>
    <time_frame>Through ICU discharge, an average of 1 month, up to 7, 30 and 90 days</time_frame>
    <description>Overall mortality rate</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>VA-ECMO free days</measure>
    <time_frame>At 30 days from the VA-ECMO implantation</time_frame>
    <description>Number of days alive free of VA-ECMO at 30 days after VA-ECMO implantation</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean arterial pressure</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 7 days</time_frame>
    <description>lowest and highest mean arterial pressure (mmHg)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pulse pressure</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 7 days</time_frame>
    <description>lowest and highest pulse pressure (mmHg) defined by the difference between systolic and diastolic pressure</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Native cardiac output</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 7 days</time_frame>
    <description>lowest and highest cardiac output (L/min) measured by echocardiography (Doppler aortic Velocity Time Integration) or by a pulmonary artery catheter</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>ECMO flow</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 7 days</time_frame>
    <description>lowest and highest flow of VA-ECMO (L/min)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Lactate</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 7 days</time_frame>
    <description>Highest lactate level of the day (mmol/l)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>ScvO2</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 7 days</time_frame>
    <description>Highest and lowest central venous oxygen saturation (%)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Urine output</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 7 days</time_frame>
    <description>Total urine output of the day (ml/24H)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hydric balance</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 7 days</time_frame>
    <description>Total hydric balance calculated from day 0 to day 7 (ml)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hospital stay</measure>
    <time_frame>through study completion, an average of 3 month</time_frame>
    <description>Length (days) of hospital stay from the VA-ECMO implantation before current care ward discharge (excluding rehabilitation time)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Intensive care unit stay</measure>
    <time_frame>through study completion, an average of 3 month</time_frame>
    <description>Length (days) of intensive care unit stay from the VA-ECMO implantation</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Issue of VA-ECMO</measure>
    <time_frame>7 days after VA-ECMO withdrawal</time_frame>
    <description>Status after VA-ECMO including death, heart transplant, ventricular assist device, recovery, shock recurrence, therapy limitation</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Serious adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>Trough VA-ECMO time completion, an average of 2 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Stroke, bleeding requiring blood transfusion or surgical revision, limb ischemia, mesenteric ischemia, documented infection</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Organ failure assessment</measure>
    <time_frame>At day 0, 5 and 10 after VA-ECMO implantation</time_frame>
    <description>Sequential Organ Failure Assessment score (0 to 24), higher values represent a worse outcome</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">150</enrollment>
  <condition>Extracorporeal Life Support</condition>
  <condition>Hypotension</condition>
  <condition>Vasoplegia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Vasoplegic ECMO</arm_group_label>
    <description>All patients during VA-ECMO support for cardiogenic shock who presented, within 48 hours after implantation, a vasoplegia defined by a norepinephrine dose greater than 0.1µg/kg/min after a 500ml fluid challenge despite overall blood flow (ECMO + native heart) greater than 2l/min/m2 or allowing to achieve 65% of ScvO2</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Arterial pressure management during circulatory support by VA-ECMO</intervention_name>
    <description>Norepinephrine continuous infusion to maintain mean arterial pressure above 65 mmHg or at a higher level depending of the perfusion pressure targeted for the patient (mean arterial pressure between 65 and 85 mmHg)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Vasoplegic ECMO</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <biospec_retention>None Retained</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Plasma: preoperative, ICU admission at POD0 and POD1 samples
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients admitted in intensive care unit for cardiogenic shock at the Montpellier
        University Hospital and who required a VA-ECMO implantation
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion criteria:

          -  Refractory cardiogenic shock due to an acute coronary syndrome, a decompensation of
             chronic heart failure, a infectious or adrenergic myocarditis, or in a post-cardiotomy
             setting

          -  Admitted in our intensive care unit between January 2015 and December 2018

          -  Vasoplegia during the first 48 hours of VA-ECMO requiring more than 0.1µg/kg/min of
             Norepinephrine continuous infusion

        Exclusion criteria:

          -  Others etiologies of cardiogenic shock : heart transplant dysfunction, right
             ventricular failure after left ventricular assist device implantation, drug
             intoxication, hypothermia, pulmonary embolism

          -  Primary septic shock

          -  Cardiac arrest with a no-flow time greater than 5 min or a low-flow time greater than
             45 min

          -  Opposition to participate after reception of the information letter
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Philippe Gaudard, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University Hospital, Montpellier</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Philippe Gaudard, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+33665849543</phone>
    <email>p-gaudard@chu-montpellier.fr</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Helene David, MD</last_name>
    <phone>629834346</phone>
    <phone_ext>33</phone_ext>
    <email>h-david@chu-montpellier.fr</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Uh Montpellier</name>
      <address>
        <city>Montpellier</city>
        <zip>34295</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Philippe Gaudard, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+33665849543</phone>
      <email>p-gaudard@chu-montpellier.fr</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>van Diepen S, Katz JN, Albert NM, Henry TD, Jacobs AK, Kapur NK, Kilic A, Menon V, Ohman EM, Sweitzer NK, Thiele H, Washam JB, Cohen MG; American Heart Association Council on Clinical Cardiology; Council on Cardiovascular and Stroke Nursing; Council on Quality of Care and Outcomes Research; and Mission: Lifeline. Contemporary Management of Cardiogenic Shock: A Scientific Statement From the American Heart Association. Circulation. 2017 Oct 17;136(16):e232-e268. doi: 10.1161/CIR.0000000000000525. Epub 2017 Sep 18. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>28923988</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tanaka D, Shimada S, Mullin M, Kreitler K, Cavarocchi N, Hirose H. What Is the Optimal Blood Pressure on Veno-Arterial Extracorporeal Membrane Oxygenation? Impact of Mean Arterial Pressure on Survival. ASAIO J. 2019 May/Jun;65(4):336-341. doi: 10.1097/MAT.0000000000000824.</citation>
    <PMID>29762229</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 23, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 28, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 30, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 9, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 9, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 10, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Cardiogenic shock</keyword>
  <keyword>Temporary circulatory support</keyword>
  <keyword>Vasoplegia</keyword>
  <keyword>Inflammatory response</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hypotension</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Shock, Cardiogenic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vasoplegia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

