<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03967795</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>API/2018/93</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03967795</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Citrullinemia for the Prediction of Enteral Nutrition Tolerance Among Critically Ill Patients</brief_title>
  <acronym>PREDICT</acronym>
  <official_title>Citrullinemia for the Prediction of Enteral Nutrition Tolerance Among Critically Ill Patients</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Centre Hospitalier Universitaire de Besancon</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Centre Hospitalier Universitaire de Besancon</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The French intensive care societies (SRLF and SFAR), in agreement with the European and
      American societies for enteral and parenteral nutrition, recommend to quickly administer an
      artificial nutrition to patients admitted to ICU and for which it is expected that they will
      not be able to eat normally in the three days of admission.

      Enteral nutrition should be used in priority if the gut is functioning. However, intolerance
      to enteral nutrition, such as vomiting, regurgitation, increased residual gastric volume, or
      diarrhea, occurs in 40% of patients hospitalized in ICU receiving enteral nutrition.
      Intolerance to enteral nutrition leads to the risk of not receiving enough nutrition. Feeding
      intolerance also exposes to the risk of acute mesenteric ischemia, especially in the most
      severe patients under catecholamine for shock. Currently, it is not possible to predict
      intolerance to enteral nutrition in ICU patients. Thus, the diagnosis of intolerance is made
      a posteriori while enteral nutrition is in progress.

      Citrullinemia (normal concentration of 20 to 60 μmol / L), could be a good biomarker of the
      function of enterocytes involved in the absorption of food.

      The aim of this study is to evaluate the interest of citrullinemia to predict tolerance to
      enteral nutrition in ICU patients.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Citrulline is an amino acid mainly produced by enterocytes from glutamine.

      Citrullinemia ≤ 20μmol/L is a biomarker of enterocyte mass reduction, secondary to the
      reduction of small bowel length or secondary to villous atrophy diseases. A patient with low
      citrullinemia is probably at risk of enteral nutrition malabsorption.

      Citrulline generation test consists of measuring the course of citrullinemia after an oral or
      intravenous administration of glutamine, the main precursor of citrulline. When the small
      bowel is functional, administration of glutamine is followed by the elevation of
      citrullinemia. On the contrary, when there is enterocyte dysfunction or reduction,
      citrullinemia does not vary after glutamine administration. Peeters et al have shown the
      feasibility of carrying out the citrulline generation test in patients hospitalized in the
      ICU. In this context, intravenous administration of glutamine (20 gr of 10%
      N2-L-Alanyl-L-Glutamine, dilution in 200 ml of water for injection, IV infusion over 30
      minutes) followed by monitoring of citrullinemia (basal time and then after 90 minutes, on
      arterial sampling) is feasible and reproducible.

      There is currently no data available on the relationship between citrullinemia measured at
      ICU admission and tolerance to enteral nutrition in the days following ICU admission.
      Similarly, the value of the citrulline generation test for evaluating enteral nutrition
      tolerance is unknown.

      The investigators hypothesize that patients with low citrullinemia at ICU admission, as well
      as those with a decreased citrullinemia elevation after Dipeptiven bolus, will have less
      tolerance to enteral nutrition than patients with normal citrullinemia.

      PREDICT is the first study evaluating the interest of citrullinemia and the citrulline
      generation test to predict feeding tolerance among critically ill patients.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">June 15, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 15, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 15, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>A bolus of Dipeptiven (Glutamine-Alanine) administered intravenously over 30 minute (20 gramme of N2-L-Alanyl-L-Glutamine solution, dilution in 200 ml of water for injection, intravenous perfusion over 30 minutes).</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Feeding intolerance at day-3 and citrulline generation test</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 3</time_frame>
    <description>Feeding intolerance evaluated at day-3 of enteral nutrition Citrulline generation test: variation of citrullinemia/90 minutes</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Feeding intolerance at dat 3 and basal plasma citrulline</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 3</time_frame>
    <description>Feeding intolerance at day-3 of enteral nutrition Citrullinemia measured the first day just before initiation of enteral nutrition</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Citrullinemia and cumulative amount of enteral nutrition</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 3</time_frame>
    <description>Link between citrullinemia and cumulative amount of enteral nutrition administred during the first three days of ICU stay</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Citrullinemia and enteral nutrition complications occurrence</measure>
    <time_frame>First week</time_frame>
    <description>Link between citrullinemia levels and occurrence of acute mesenteric ischemia and inhalation pneumopathy during the first week of enteral nutrition</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">200</enrollment>
  <condition>Enteral Nutrition</condition>
  <condition>Intensive Care Unit</condition>
  <condition>Biomarkers</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>All patients</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Citrulline genration test before starting enteral nutrition
At ICU admission, a blood sample is collected (i) before and (ii) 90 minutes after N2-L-Alanyl-L-Glutamine administration</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>N2-L-Alanyl-L-Glutamine (Substance)</intervention_name>
    <description>20 gr of 10% N2-L-Alanyl-L-Glutamine, dilution in 200 ml of water for injection, intravenous perfusion over 30 minutes</description>
    <arm_group_label>All patients</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Dipeptiven</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  18 years old or older

          -  patient admited to ICU

          -  expected hospital stay of at least 3 days

          -  indication of enteral nutrition.

          -  presence of an arterial catheter

          -  signed informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  contraindication to enteral nutrition (e.g. non-functional digestive tract, mesenteric
             ischemia, occlusion, digestive fistula, active gastrointestinal bleeding)

          -  pregnancy ;

          -  chronic renal failure;

          -  chronic intestinal pathology
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Gaël PITON, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>CHU de Besancon</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Gaël PITON, MD</last_name>
    <phone>381668127</phone>
    <phone_ext>+33</phone_ext>
    <email>gpiton@chu-besancon.fr</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Lucie VETTORETTI, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+33381218378</phone>
    <email>lvettoretti@chu-besancon.fr</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <verification_date>May 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 27, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 29, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 30, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 3, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 3, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 4, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>ICU</keyword>
  <keyword>enteral nutrition</keyword>
  <keyword>tolerance</keyword>
  <keyword>prediction</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Citrullinemia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

