<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03965312</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IncuBaby-NHSRC</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03965312</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Feasibility of a Novel Neonatal Incubator for Low-resource Settings</brief_title>
  <official_title>Feasibility of a Novel Neonatal Incubator for Low-resource Settings</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>William Marsh Rice University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Malawi College of Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>William Marsh Rice University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      A team of researchers at Rice University and Queen Elizabeth Central Hospital (QECH) are
      working to develop a low-cost infant incubator called &quot;IncuBaby&quot; that consists of two
      components: a temperature sensor that can continuously monitor an infant's temperature, and a
      heated, enclosed area that can adjust internal temperature based on the feedback from the
      temperature sensor. This robust, low-cost device will allow for the individualized treatment
      of hypothermia with minimal intervention from the clinical staff. In this study, researchers
      intend to evaluate the efficacy of this incubator at QECH by comparing infants' temperatures
      before and after treatment, and calculating the proportion of time that the infants remain in
      a normothermic range after rewarming. During phase I of this study, the infants will be
      continuously monitored using the IncuBaby temperature sensor and a gold standard temperature
      monitor for up to 3 days. The accuracy of the IncuBaby temperature sensor will be determined
      by calculating the difference between the temperatures recorded by the temperature sensor and
      the commercial patient monitor at each point in time. During phase II of the study, infants
      in need of thermal care with an incubator will be treated with an IncuBaby device and their
      temperatures will be continuously monitored by both the temperature sensor of the IncuBaby
      device and a commercially available patient monitor. Care will continue at the clinician's
      discretion until the infant can be weaned from the incubator or until patients are withdrawn
      from the study and placed on the standard of care. To determine the effectiveness of the
      IncuBaby device at warming infants, the temperatures of the infants will be compared before
      and after treatment for each subject. The proportion of time the device maintains the
      subject's temperature in a normal range will also be calculated.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a two-phase, pilot prospective study to determine the effectiveness of a low-cost
      incubator in warming infants and regulating their temperatures.

      During Phase I, the following steps will be taken:

      A trained study nurse will assess the subject for clinical complications before attaching the
      temperature monitoring device.

        1. A trained study nurse or clinician will attach the temperature monitoring device to the
           infant. A trained research assistant from Rice University or from the Biomedical
           Engineering Department at Malawi Polytechnic will observe all procedures and will notify
           the nurse of any observed errors so they may be corrected. They will also be able to
           answer any technical questions from the nurse.

        2. The trained study nurse will attach the temperature probe from the commercial patient
           monitor as well as provide any other care needed.

        3. A research assistant will use a laptop to collect the electrical signals from both
           temperature monitors.

        4. Temperature monitoring will continue for up to 3 days. The research assistant may ask
           the nurse to remove and reapply the temperature monitor during this period.

      Once Phase I is complete, Phase II will begin. During Phase II, the following steps will be
      taken:

      A trained study nurse will assess the subject for clinical complications before beginning
      treatment.

        1. A trained study nurse or research technician will turn the incubator on to begin
           pre-warming.

        2. A trained study nurse or clinician will attach the temperature probe from the IncuBaby
           device to the infant and then place the infant in the incubator. A trained research
           assistant from Rice University or from the Biomedical Engineering Department at Malawi
           Polytechnic will observe all procedures and will notify the nurse of any observed errors
           so they may be corrected. They will also be able to answer any technical questions from
           the nurse.

        3. The trained study nurse will attach the temperature probe from the commercial patient
           monitor as well as provide any other care needed.

        4. A research assistant will use a laptop to collect the data from both devices.

        5. Care will be continued at the discretion of the clinician until the infant can be weaned
           from the IncuBaby device. The infant may be weaned to the standard of care or end
           thermal treatment. The infant will be transitioned to Kangaroo Mother Care (KMC) as soon
           as possible after these eligibility criteria are fulfilled:

             -  Completed other treatment (CPAP, phototherapy, IV)

             -  Mom/caregiver becomes available

             -  Weight increases &gt; 1000g

             -  Become clinically stable

             -  Body temperature is stable and not dipping below normal despite thermal support

      During both phases, a research assistant will be available during the trial to mitigate any
      complications with the device. A nurse will be available to respond to alarms from the
      continuous patient monitor. If the subject's guardian, the nurse, or the research assistant
      indicates concern during the tests, the study treatment can be discontinued and the subject
      will return to the standard of care.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 31, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 30, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 30, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>In the first phase of the study, a novel neonatal temperature monitor and a commercially available patient monitor (Philips Intellivue MP30) will be applied to the same infant; results between them will be compared.
In the second phase of the study, infants at risk for hypothermia will be placed in an infant incubator; the accuracy of the temperature sensor, time required for infant to become normothermic, and the proportion of time that the infant remains normothermic will be measured.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Temperature monitor accuracy</measure>
    <time_frame>from time of enrollment until intervention is complete; up to 28 days</time_frame>
    <description>Continuously measured temperature for temperature monitor compared against Philips Intellivue patient monitor</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Temperature of incubator</measure>
    <time_frame>from time of enrollment until intervention is complete; up to 28 days</time_frame>
    <description>Continuously measured temperature of incubator</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Temperature of infant</measure>
    <time_frame>from time of enrollment until intervention is complete; up to 28 days</time_frame>
    <description>Continuously measured temperature of infant</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time until normothermia</measure>
    <time_frame>from time of enrollment until intervention is complete; up to 28 days</time_frame>
    <description>Time until infant becomes normothermic (36.5-37.5C)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of time normothermic</measure>
    <time_frame>from time of enrollment until intervention is complete; up to 28 days</time_frame>
    <description>The proportion of treatment time that the infant is normothermic (36.5-37.5C)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Neonatal Hypothermia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Temperature monitoring (1) and incubator test (2) groups</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>In the first (1) phase of the study, the temperature probe and monitor will be attached to infants along with the Philips Intellivue patient monitor. Temperature will be monitored continuously for up to 72 hours.
In the second (2) phase of this study, infants at risk for hypothermia and not eligible for skin-to-skin care will be placed in the incubator.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Continuous temperature monitor</intervention_name>
    <description>Temperature will be measured using a novel temperature monitor continuously for up to 72 hours. Accuracy (as compared to a commercially available patient monitor) will be evaluated.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Temperature monitoring (1) and incubator test (2) groups</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>IncuBaby temperature sensor and monitor</other_name>
    <other_name>Neonatal temperature monitor</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Neonatal Incubator</intervention_name>
    <description>Infants at risk for hypothermia will be placed in a neonatal incubator. Their temperature will be monitored as they are treated. The infant will be treated until the infant is transitioned to skin-to-skin care, discharged, or no longer at risk for hypothermia.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Temperature monitoring (1) and incubator test (2) groups</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>IncuBaby</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Patient monitor</intervention_name>
    <description>Temperature will be measured using a commercially available patient monitor.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Temperature monitoring (1) and incubator test (2) groups</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Philips Intellivue patient monitor</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  The subject is currently being treated at QECH in the neonatal ward.

          -  An IncuBaby device and study monitor are available for use.

          -  The subject's caregiver has provided informed consent for their child to participate
             (consent form attached to this proposal).

          -  Phase II only: the subject is eligible for thermal care in an incubator. If the
             subject is recommended for KMC, they will not be eligible for participation in this
             study. To be considered for care with the IncuBaby, infants should be:

               -  Less than 1000 g

               -  Or &gt; 1000 g but

                    -  Receiving medical interventions such as CPAP, oxygen, phototherapy, or IV

                    -  Unstable, critically ill or surgical conditions

                    -  No mother or caregiver available for KMC

                    -  Mother too sick to provide KMC

                    -  Clinician in charge has decided against KMC as requires closer supervision
                       by nursing staff

                    -  No space in KMC

        Exclusion Criteria:

        The subject may be excluded from the study at the clinician's discretion for any reason
        including potential for skin irritation, cough or other condition that may preclude use of
        the temperature belt, or concurrent treatments that may require increased patient care.
        Only subjects eligible for care in an incubator will be enrolled in phase II.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>28 Days</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Rebecca Richards-Kortum, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>William Marsh Rice University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Queen Dube, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Malawi College of Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Rebecca Elias, MPH</last_name>
    <phone>713-348-6574</phone>
    <email>rebecca.elias@rice.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Queen Elizabeth Central Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Blantyre</city>
        <country>Malawi</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Rebecca R Richards-Kortum, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>7133483823</phone>
      <email>rkortum@rice.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Queen Dube, MD</last_name>
      <email>drdubefirst@yahoo.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Malawi</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 31, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 23, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 29, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 9, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 9, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 13, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hypothermia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <provided_document_section>
    <provided_document>
      <document_type>Informed Consent Form</document_type>
      <document_has_protocol>No</document_has_protocol>
      <document_has_icf>Yes</document_has_icf>
      <document_has_sap>No</document_has_sap>
      <document_date>June 27, 2017</document_date>
      <document_url>https://ClinicalTrials.gov/ProvidedDocs/12/NCT03965312/ICF_000.pdf</document_url>
    </provided_document>
    <provided_document>
      <document_type>Study Protocol and Statistical Analysis Plan</document_type>
      <document_has_protocol>Yes</document_has_protocol>
      <document_has_icf>No</document_has_icf>
      <document_has_sap>Yes</document_has_sap>
      <document_date>June 30, 2017</document_date>
      <document_url>https://ClinicalTrials.gov/ProvidedDocs/12/NCT03965312/Prot_SAP_001.pdf</document_url>
    </provided_document>
  </provided_document_section>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

