<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03968172</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>POWER@MS1</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03968172</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Interactive Web Platform for EmPOWERment in Early Multiple Sclerosis</brief_title>
  <acronym>POWER@MS1</acronym>
  <official_title>Development and Evaluation of a Web-based Lifestyle Intervention for EmPOWERment in Early Multiple Sclerosis (POWER@MS1) - a Randomized Controlled Trial and Mixed-methods Process Evaluation</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Universitätsklinikum Hamburg-Eppendorf</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Charite University, Berlin, Germany</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Luebeck</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University Medical Center Goettingen</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Heinrich-Heine University, Duesseldorf</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Gaia AG</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>BKK Dachverband e.V.</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Deutsche Multiple Sklerose Gesellschaft (DMSG)</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Deutsche Multiple Sklerose Gesellschaft (DMSG) Landesverband Berlin e.V.</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Universitätsklinikum Hamburg-Eppendorf</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This randomized controlled trial with an accompanying process evaluation investigates the
      hypothesis that behavioural and web-based information on immunotherapy decisions, disease
      management and lifestyle can change patient behaviour resulting in reduced inflammatory
      disease activity in multiple sclerosis.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      After a multiple sclerosis (MS) diagnosis, uncertainty and psychological stress may have a
      negative effect on the disease course, while psychological counselling may reduce
      inflammatory activity. Therefore, especially newly diagnosed patients require intensive and
      individual support to deal with the disease and to initiate lifestyle changes. This is hardly
      available in standard care. Systematic, evidence-based patient information on the value of
      lifestyle change is not available either.

      POWER@MS1 aims to encourage patients with MS to find the best way of dealing with the disease
      on the basis of evidence-based patient information (EBPI) and a complex behaviour change
      intervention. The platform will serve as a disease accompanying empowerment programme.
      Various modules will be provided to accompany patients with MS (pwMS) at an early stage of
      the disease. The multicomponent intervention will offer comprehensive support after
      diagnosis, which includes, firstly, an immunotherapy decision-support programme aligned with
      principles of shared decision-making (SDM), and, secondly, a behaviour-change intervention
      promoting disease management and lifestyle habits over a period of one year. Ideally,
      POWER@MS1 leads to a more targeted immunotherapy start, and consequently to better adherence
      and optimization of a preventive effective lifestyle.

      Primary objective:

      To determine if a web-based behavioural intervention on immunotherapy decision making,
      disease management, and lifestyle can reduce the inflammatory disease activity in MS (a
      relapse or - as a surrogate for inflammatory disease activity - new T2 lesions on MRI).

      Secondary objectives:

      The secondary objectives are to determine if the web-based intervention can

        -  strengthen patient autonomy and empowerment,

        -  promote informed decisions on immunotherapy,

        -  improve quality of life,

        -  reduce anxiety and depression,

        -  increase physical activity and a healthy diet,

        -  increase effectiveness of neurologists encounters,

        -  and save health care costs.

      In order to develop and evaluate the intervention, a multiphase mixed-methods study covering
      the first three phases of the Medical Research Council Framework for complex interventions
      will be conducted. After development, the intervention programme will be pretested and
      piloted with experts and persons with MS (pwMS). The intervention will be evaluated in a
      randomized controlled trial (RCT) with 328 patients with early MS (&lt; 12 months), who have not
      yet started immunotherapy and have at least two MS-typical lesions. Study participants will
      be recruited in 16 MS centres across Germany and randomised to an intervention group with
      access to an evidence-based information platform or to a control group with optimised
      standard care based on material of the German Multiple Sclerosis Society (DMSG). The primary
      endpoint will be reached if new T2 lesions or relapses occur. Furthermore, a mixed methods
      process evaluation and a health economic evaluation will be carried out.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>The study will be conducted as an investigator blinded trial and participating physicians as well as MS centres in general will not be provided with any information about the group assignment. Randomisation will take place only after baseline documentation. Blinding of the trial participants is pursued, but only possible to a limited extent. Furthermore, it cannot be prevented that patients discuss the intervention contents with their physician. Thus, participants and neurologist might realize their participation in the intervention group. While blinding in behavioural interventions is virtually not possible, the only strategy to increase similarity of groups is to have an active control group which we aim for with the optimized standard care group.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Occurrence of new lesions on T2-weighted images on MRI scans</measure>
    <time_frame>Change in the number of lesions on T2-weighted images from immediately after patient inclusion (month 0), to month 4, 8, 12, 18 (follow-up) and 24 (follow-up) after patient inclusion</time_frame>
    <description>As a surrogate for inflammatory disease activity, new T2 lesions will be assessed in MRI.
MRI protocol: Localizer, 3D FLAIR sagittal e.g. 3x3mmm, 3D image T1w native sagittal, 1-3mm, KM administration (0.2ml Gd /Kg body weight), PD/T2w axial 3mm, T1w after KM sagittal, protocol du-ration approx. 20 min.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to a second relapse</measure>
    <time_frame>Change in relapse status from baseline (no endpoint), to month 4, 8, 12, 18 (follow-up), and 24 (follow-up) after patient inclusion</time_frame>
    <description>Duration of complaints/impairment, relapse symptoms (worsened or newly occurred), degree of impairment due to the relapse and degree of certainty with regard to the classification of the worsening as a relapse.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Risk Knowledge (RiKno10)</measure>
    <time_frame>Month 4 after patient inclusion</time_frame>
    <description>To assess risk knowledge, RiKno 2.0 was adapted to a 10-item version (RiKno10).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Control Preference Scale (CPS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Telephone interview within two weeks after reaching the primary endpoint or immunotherapy decision</time_frame>
    <description>As a surrogate of decision quality, preferred and realized role preference based on the Control Preference Scale (CPS) will be assessed. The scores for preferred and realized roles are grouped into active, collaborative or passive.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Immunotherapy Decision Satisfaction Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>Telephone interview within two weeks after reaching the primary endpoint or immunotherapy decision</time_frame>
    <description>As a surrogate of decision quality, satisfaction with the immunotherapy decision will be assessed.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Immunotherapy Status Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline (no endpoint), month 4, 8, 12, 18 (follow-up), 24 (follow-up) after patient inclusion, as well as up to 4 weeks after the occurence of new lesions on T2-weighted images (primary endpoint) or up to 4 weeks after a relapse event (primary endpoint)</time_frame>
    <description>It will be assessed whether an immunotherapy was newly started, aborted or changed.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient Activation Measure (PAM)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and month 12 after patient inclusion</time_frame>
    <description>Assessment of patient activation development (i.e. expressed in the confidence and knowledge to take action, as well as actually taking health-related action).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Coping self-efficacy (CSE) scale</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and month 12 after patient inclusion</time_frame>
    <description>Based on the coping self-efficacy (CSE) scale, selected and adapted items will be used to measure perceived self-efficacy for emotion-focused coping behaviours. In this study, response options are ranging from 0 (completely disagree), representing a low coping self-efficacy value, to 3 (fully agree), representing a high coping self-efficacy value.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in Perceived Empowerment Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>Month 12 after patient inclusion</time_frame>
    <description>Changes in perceived empowerment will be measured based on selected and adapted items of a 3-point scale empowerment questionnaire measuring changes in patients' feelings of empowerment and/or control over their health problem.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Credibility/Expectancy Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks after patient inclusion (month 1)</time_frame>
    <description>Selected items measuring treatment expectancy and credibility.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Readiness to Change (stage assessment) based on the Health Action Process Approach (HAPA)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, month 3 and 12 after patient inclusion</time_frame>
    <description>Readiness to change will be assessed based on the Health Action Process Approach (HAPA) in order to determine the interventions impact on willingness to change lifestyle activities, such as physical activity and nutritional behaviour.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Impairment in the Expanded Disability Status Scale (EDSS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and month 12 after patient inclusion</time_frame>
    <description>MS impairment measurement with a score ranging from 0.0 (normal neurological exam) to 10.0 (death due to MS).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hamburg Quality of life in MS Scale (HAQUAMS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and month 12 after patient inclusion</time_frame>
    <description>Assessment of MS-specific quality of life based on 8 subscales (consisting of 38 individual items) and 4 additional questions. For all subscales, averaged subscores are calculated from the values of the respective items (ranging from 1 to 5), with high scores standing for low quality of life and low scores standing for high quality of life.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>EQ-5D</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and month 12 after patient inclusion</time_frame>
    <description>Assessment of health-related quality of life.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hospital anxiety and distress scale (HADS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and month 12 after patient inclusion</time_frame>
    <description>Assessment of depression and anxiety based on 14 items on 2 scales (7 on the subscale &quot;anxiety&quot; and 7 on the subscale &quot;depression&quot;), ranging from 0 (low anxiety/depression level) to 3 (high anxiety/depression level) per item, resulting in a range of 0 to 21 per scale or 0 to 42 for the total HADS value.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Godin Leisure-Time Exercise Questionnaire (GLTEQ)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and month 12 after patient inclusion</time_frame>
    <description>Amount of mild, moderate and strenuous exercise in leisure time.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Physical Activity, Exercise, and Sport Questionnaire (Bewegungs- und Sportaktivität Fragebogen (BSA-F))</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and month 12 after patient inclusion</time_frame>
    <description>Assessment of physical activity, including occupational activity, leisure time activity and sports.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>adapted Mediterranean Diet Screener (aMDS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 3-4 weeks after module 9 (~ month 4) and month 12 after patient inclusion</time_frame>
    <description>Frequency of intake of characteristic food groups (e.g. vegetables, fish, and olive oil) in the last seven days and is an indicator of the degree of adherence to an adapted Mediterranean dietary pattern.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>24-h dietary recall myfood24</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and month 12 after patient inclusion, in each case three times within two to three weeks (two weekdays and one weekend day)</time_frame>
    <description>Aggregated nutrient intake data (e.g. omega-3-fatty acids).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Health Economic Evaluation</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, month 6, 12, 18 (follow-up) and 24 (follow-up) after patient inclusion</time_frame>
    <description>Assessment of all direct costs associated with the intervention as well as costs resulting from the consumption of health-related goods and services as well as indirect costs due to productivity losses.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">328</enrollment>
  <condition>Multiple Sclerosis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Levidex</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants in the intervention group will receive access to the web-based Levidex programme, an online tool that was developed in line with principles of patient empowerment and cognitive behavioural therapy (CBT) approaches, including acceptance and mindfulness oriented techniques.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Dexilev</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants randomized to the active control group will receive access to the Dexilev information platform with optimized standard care.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Levidex</intervention_name>
    <description>Web-based behavioural lifestyle intervention that provides patients with coordinated information based on their existing health beliefs, interests, etc. In Levidex, techniques and exercises will be taught in sequentially active interactive learning units (&quot;simulated dialogues&quot;) and followed-up with email and SMS reminders in the second study year. The following topics will be focused on:
Diagnosis and disease progression
Support in disease processing
Techniques for coping with stress and depressive symptoms as well as developing positive emotions
Optimisation of dietary behaviour
Optimisation of physical activity behaviour
Sleep hygiene and methods for dealing with insomnia.
The programme will accompany each patient with information material and e-mail reminders over a period of 12 months with initial 2-3 weekly tasks, later only weekly reminders and inputs every 2 weeks. All in all, the intervention programme will consist of 16 modules.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Levidex</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Dexilev</intervention_name>
    <description>Web-based information platform with optimized standard care compiled from information material of the German Multiple Sclerosis Society (DMSG). Information will be provided in sequentially activated modules over a period of 12 months, covering the following topics:
Disease progression
Invisible symptoms of multiple sclerosis
Symptomatic therapy
Immunotherapy decision support
Coping strategies
Autonomy
Fatigue
Quality of life
Physical activity
Nutritional behaviour
In addition, a reminder system with neutral e-mail reminders will be used to promote the use of the programme.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Dexilev</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  signed informed consent

          -  suspected or confirmed MS for less than 12 months

          -  at least two MS-typical lesions on T2-weighted images in the MRI

          -  MS typical cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) finding with oligoclonal bands

          -  access to the internet and ability to use websites

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  immunotherapy already started

          -  substantial psychiatric disorder

          -  severe cognitive deficit affecting information uptake
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Christoph Heesen, Prof.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Universitätsklinikum Hamburg-Eppendorf</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Christoph Heesen, Prof.</last_name>
    <phone>+4940-7410-54076</phone>
    <email>heesen@uke.de</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Nicole Krause</last_name>
    <phone>+4940-7410-54077</phone>
    <email>n.krause@uke.de</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Universitätsklinikum Hamburg-Eppendorf</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hamburg</city>
        <zip>20246</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Christoph Heesen, Prof.</last_name>
      <phone>+4940-7410-54076</phone>
      <email>heesen@uke.de</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Nicole Krause</last_name>
      <phone>+4940-7410-54077</phone>
      <email>n.krause@uke.de</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Christoph Heesen, Prof.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Nicole Krause</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Germany</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 15, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 27, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 30, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 24, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 24, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 25, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Multiple Sclerosis</keyword>
  <keyword>Complex Intervention</keyword>
  <keyword>Lifestyle Intervention</keyword>
  <keyword>Randomized Controlled Trial</keyword>
  <keyword>Evidence-based Medicine</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Multiple Sclerosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sclerosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>An anonymized individual data set will be published in major journals in order to disseminate the study results. In addition, all trial results will be communicated at scientific conferences and meetings by the investigators and presented on the DMSG website and other relevant patient websites.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

