<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03965299</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2019-00074</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03965299</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Transcutaneous Tibial Nerve Stimulation in Acute Spinal Cord Injury</brief_title>
  <acronym>TASCI</acronym>
  <official_title>Transcutaneous Tibial Nerve Stimulation in Patients With Acute Spinal Cord Injury to Prevent Neurogenic Detrusor Overactivity: A Nationwide Randomised, Sham-controlled, Double-blind Clinical Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Zurich</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Swiss National Science Foundation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Clinique Romande de Readaptation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Rehab Basel</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Swiss Paraplegic Centre Nottwil</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Swiss Paraplegic Research</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>BioMedical Research Forschungslabor für Urologie, University of Bern</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Translational Neuro-Urology Department of Biomedicine, University of Porto</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Center for Lower Urinary Tract Research School of Medicine, University of Pittsburgh</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Zurich</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Most patients with spinal cord injury (SCI) develop neurogenic lower urinary tract
      dysfunction (NLUTD), one of the most devastating sequelae of SCI which ultimately can lead to
      renal failure. We urgently need an intervention that prevents NLUTD before irreversible
      damage occurs. Neuromodulation procedures are a promising avenue so that we investigate the
      effect of transcutaneous tibial nerve stimulation (TTNS) in patients with acute SCI.

      This nationwide randomized, sham-controlled, double-blind multicentre clinical trial includes
      all SCI centres in Switzerland (Basel, Nottwil, Sion, Zürich). Patients are randomly assigned
      to VERUM TTNS (active stimulation, n=57) and SHAM stimulation (n=57) groups in a 1:1
      allocation using computer-generated permuted block randomisation lists stratified on study
      centre and lower extremity motor score. Daily 30-minute sessions are performed five times a
      week during an intervention period of 6-9 weeks. The primary outcome of this study is the
      success of TTNS to prevent neurogenic DO jeopardizing the upper urinary tract, assessed by
      urodynamics at 1 year after SCI or any earlier time point if DO treatment is necessary (study
      end). Secondary outcome measures are bladder diary parameters, clinical symptom scores
      assessed by standardized and validated questionnaires. Furthermore, neurophysiological and
      neuroimaging outcome measures are assessed as well as, biochemical and molecular changes.
      Tertiary outcome measure is the safety of TTNS.

      Before the actual start of the TASCI RCT, start-up activities will include a piloting phase
      on groups of healthy volunteers and patients. The goal during this phase is to evaluate the
      feasibility of the experimental setup, in particular for the TTNS and SHAM intervention, but
      also to test the setup of the different pre and post assessments (e.g. neurophysiology and
      neuroimaging tests). Groups of up to 15 participants each will be enrolled in a few
      consecutive pilot studies allowing for fine tuning and small adaptations in between, if
      appropriate.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 19, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Care Provider, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>The only unmasked person involved in the trial is the operator who will be responsible for the daily application of the study intervention at the patient. The role of an operator can be occupied by a research assistant/study nurse or investigator not involved in the clinical management and assessment of clinical outcomes. Thus, patients and care providers involved with clinical assessments are blinded.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The occurrence of neurogenic DO jeopardizing the upper urinary tract</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 12 months after SCI</time_frame>
    <description>Defined as composite measure: Urodynamic assessment establishing DO amplitude ≥40 cmH2O; or else initiation of DO treatment (with antimuscarinics and/or intradetrusor onabotulinumtoxinA injections)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Volumetric changes during urodynamics and their relation to clinical outcomes</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline; 3 months after SCI; 6 months after SCI; 12 months after SCI / study end</time_frame>
    <description>Cystometric capacity [mL], volume at first DO [mL], voided volume [mL] and post void residual [mL] as assessed by urodynamic measurement</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in bladder compliance [mL/cmH2O] during urodynamics and their relation to clinical outcomes</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline; 3 months after SCI; 6 months after SCI; 12 months after SCI / study end</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pressure changes during urodynamics and their relation to clinical outcomes</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline; 3 months after SCI; 6 months after SCI; 12 months after SCI / study end</time_frame>
    <description>Maximum DO amplitude [cmH2O], detrusor leak-point pressure [cmH2O], maximum detrusor pressure [cmH2O] during storage phase, maximum detrusor pressure [cmH2O] during voiding phase, detrusor pressure at maximum flow rate [cmH2O] as assessed by urodynamic measurement</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in maximum flow rate [mL/s] as assessed by urodynamics and their relation to clinical outcomes</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline; 3 months after SCI; 6 months after SCI; 12 months after SCI / study end</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in vesicoureterorenal reflux (VUR) as assessed by videography during urodynamics and their relation to clinical outcomes</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline; 3 months after SCI; 6 months after SCI; 12 months after SCI / study end</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in pelvic floor activity as assessed by electromyography (EMG) during urodynamics and their relation to clinical outcomes</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline; 3 months after SCI; 6 months after SCI; 12 months after SCI / study end</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in bladder storage and voiding parameters and their relation to clinical outcomes</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline; once every 2 weeks during the TTNS intervention period; 3 months after SCI; 6 months after SCI; 12 months after SCI / study end</time_frame>
    <description>Assessed by a bladder diary</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in bowel diary parameters and their relation to clinical outcomes</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline; once every 2 weeks during the TTNS intervention period; 3 months after SCI; 6 months after SCI; 12 months after SCI / study end</time_frame>
    <description>Assessed by a bowel diary</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in International Prostate Symptom (IPSS) questionnaire and their relation to clinical outcomes</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline; once per week during the TTNS intervention period; 3 months after SCI; 6 months after SCI; 12 months after SCI / study end</time_frame>
    <description>The IPSS (&quot;International Prostate Symptom Questionnaire&quot;) score is based on questions concerning urinary symptoms and quality of life (QoL). It consists of 8 items covering 7 urinary symptoms related dimensions (subscales) and 1 additional item assessing quality of life. Each item is rated on a 6-point scale (0=not at all; 5=almost always). The lowest possible score in the total IPSS score is 0 (asymptomatic); the highest possible score is 35 (symptomatic). The QoL index is rated on a 7-point scale, with 0 indicating &quot;delighted&quot; and 6 &quot;terrible.&quot;</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in urinary symptoms as assessed by the Urinary Symptom Profile (USP) questionnaire and their relation to clinical outcomes</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline; once per week during the TTNS intervention period; 3 months after SCI; 6 months after SCI; 12 months after SCI / study end</time_frame>
    <description>The USP (&quot;Urinary Symptom Profile&quot;) score is based on questions concerning urinary symptoms and their severity in males and females. It consists of 13 items covering 3 dimensions (subscales) with 7 overactive bladder (OAB), 3 stress urinary incontinence (SUI), and 3 low stream (LS) related items. Each item is rated on a 4-point scale. The lowest score is 0 (asymptomatic); the highest score is 3 (symptomatic).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in Qualiveen questionnaire scores and their relation to clinical outcomes</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline; once per week during the TTNS intervention period; 3 months after SCI; 6 months after SCI; 12 months after SCI / study end</time_frame>
    <description>Qualiveen-30 assesses the Specific Impact of Urinary Problems (SIUP) on Quality of Life. It consists of 30 items covering 4 domains, namely inconvenience (9 questions), restrictions (8 questions), fears (8 questions), and impact on daily life (5 questions). Each item is rated on a 5-point ordinal scale (0=asymptomatic; 4=symptomatic). The index of the SIUP on Quality of Life is the mean of the four individual scores. The lowest possible overall score in the Qualiveen-30 is 0 (Urinary problems have no specific impact on QoL); the highest possible score is 30 (Urinary problems have a huge specific impact on QoL).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in Female Sexual Function Index (FSFI) and their relation to clinical outcomes</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline; 3 months after SCI; 6 months after SCI; 12 months after SCI / study end</time_frame>
    <description>The FSFI (&quot;Female Sexual Function Index&quot;) is based on questions concerning female sexual functions. It consists of 19 items covering 6 domains, namely sexual desire, arousal (both subjective and physiologic), lubrication, orgasm, satisfaction, and pain. The lowest possible score in the total FSFI is 2 (asymptomatic); the highest possible score is 36 (symptomatic).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in International Index of Erectile Function (IIEF) and their relation to clinical outcomes</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline; 3 months after SCI; 6 months after SCI; 12 months after SCI / study end</time_frame>
    <description>The IIEF (&quot;International Index of Erectile Function&quot;) is based on questions concerning erectile dysfunction. It consists of 15 items covering 5 domains, namely erectile functioning, orgasmic functioning, sexual desire, and intercourse satisfaction along with a fifth component which encompasses the concept of overall sexual satisfaction. While items 1-10 are rated on a 6-point Likert-type scale from 0 to 5, items 11-15 are rated on a 5-point Likert-type scale from 1 to 5. Higher scores are reflecting less dysfunction. Domain scores are computed by summing the sores for individual items in each domain.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in International Spinal Cord Society (ISCoS) Female / Male sexual function data sets and their relation to clinical outcomes</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline; 3 months after SCI; 6 months after SCI; 12 months after SCI / study end</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in Neurogenic Bowel Dysfunction (NBD) score and their relation to clinical outcomes</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline; once per week during the TTNS intervention period; 3 months after SCI; 6 months after SCI; 12 months after SCI / study end</time_frame>
    <description>The NBD (&quot;Neurogenic Bowel Dysfunction&quot;) score is based on questions concerning constipation and fecal incontinence and was developed for and validated in the spinal cord injury population. It consists of 10 items. The lowest possible score in the total NBD is 0 (asymptomatic); the highest possible score is 47 (symptomatic). The interpretation of the total NBD score is very minor NBD (0-6), minor NBD (7-9), moderate NBD (10-13), and severe NBD (≥14).The NBD score is assessed by using the international spinal cord injury (ISCoS) bowel function basic data set.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Volumetric changes during rectal sensitivity testing and barostat assessment and their relation to clinical outcomes</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline; 3 months after SCI; 6 months after SCI; 12 months after SCI / study end</time_frame>
    <description>Initial sensation [mL], volume at urge to defecate [mL], maximum tolerated volume [mL] as assessed by rectal sensitivity testing; rectal capacity [mL] assessed by barostat assessment</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pressure changes during anorectal manometry and barostat assessment and their relation to clinical outcomes</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline; 3 months after SCI; 6 months after SCI; 12 months after SCI / study end</time_frame>
    <description>Basal internal anal sphincter pressure [mmHg], squeeze external anal sphincter pressure [mmHg], relaxation internal anal sphincter pressure during defecation [%, mmHg], intraabdominal pressure during defecation [mmHg]</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in rectal compliance [mL/cmH2O] during anorectal manometry and barostat assessment and their relation to clinical outcomes</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline; 3 months after SCI; 6 months after SCI; 12 months after SCI / study end</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in defecatory disorder [Rao's classification] identified during anorectal manometry and their relation to clinical outcomes</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline; 3 months after SCI; 6 months after SCI; 12 months after SCI / study end</time_frame>
    <description>Anorectal manometry is the preferable test for defecatory disorder. Rao's classification describes the four types of manometric patterns (I-IV) that are identified through manometric assessments</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes International Standards for Neurological Classification of Spinal Cord Injury (ISNCSCI) protocol</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline; 3 months after SCI; 6 months after SCI; 12 months after SCI / study end</time_frame>
    <description>International Standards for Neurological Classification of Spinal Cord Injury (ISNCSCI) assessment to quantify the severity of the spinal cord injury</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in Lower Extremities Motor Scale (LEMS) from International Standards for Neurological Classification of Spinal Cord Injury (ISNCSCI) protocol</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline; 3 months after SCI; 6 months after SCI; 12 months after SCI / study end</time_frame>
    <description>LEMS is based on assessments of ISNCSCI and composed from the sum of muscle function grading of the five key muscles of the lower limbs. It consists of a 6-point scale (0=no; 5=normal activity) for each muscle and body site. The lowest possible score in the total LEMS score for one body site is 0 (symptomatic); the highest possible score is 50 (asymptomatic).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in Upper Extremities Motor Scale (UEMS) from International Standards for Neurological Classification of Spinal Cord Injury (ISNCSCI) protocol</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline; 3 months after SCI; 6 months after SCI; 12 months after SCI / study end</time_frame>
    <description>UEMS is based on assessments of ISNCSCI and composed from the sum of muscle function grading of the five key muscles of the upper limbs. It consists of a 6-point scale (0=no; 5=normal activity) for each muscle and body site. The lowest possible score in the total LEMS score for one body site is 0 (symptomatic); the highest possible score is 50 (asymptomatic).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in Spinal Cord Independence Measure III (SCIM-III) and their relation to clinical outcomes</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline; 3 months after SCI; 6 months after SCI; 12 months after SCI / study end</time_frame>
    <description>The SCIM-III (&quot;Spinal Cord Independence Measure III&quot;) score is based on questions concerning independence of persons with a spinal cord injured. It consists of 19 items covering 3 domains, self-care, respiration and sphincter management, and mobility. The self-care subscale ranges from 0 to 20. The respiration and sphincter management subscale ranges from 0 to 40. The mobility subscale ranges from 0 to 40. Total score ranges from 0 (symptomatic) to 100 (asymptomatic). Higher scores reflect higher levels of independence.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in spasticity in the knee and elbow flexors and extensors from the Modified Ashworth Scale (MAS) assessment and their relation to clinical outcomes</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline; 3 months after SCI; 6 months after SCI; 12 months after SCI / study end</time_frame>
    <description>The MAS is a 5-point nominal scale that uses subjective clinical assessments of muscle tone ranging from 0 - 'No increases in tone' to 4 - 'Limb rigid in flexion or extension'. A grade of (1+) indicates resistance in the movement.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in spasticity in daily life as assessed by the Spinal Cord Injury Spasticity Evaluation Tool (SCI-SET) questionnaire and their relation to clinical outcomes</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline; 3 months after SCI; 6 months after SCI; 12 months after SCI / study end</time_frame>
    <description>The SCI-SET (&quot;Spinal Cord Injury Spasticity Evaluation Tool &quot;) score is based on questions concerning the positive and negative effects of spasticity on different areas of daily life. Each of the 35 items are rated on a 7-point scale (-3=extremely problematic; 0=no effect; 3=extremely helpful). Calculations include counts and sum scores of areas of daily life where spasticity is problematic (count range: 0 to 35, sum score range: 35 to 0) or helpful (counts range: 0 to 35, sum score range: 0 to +35) as well as a mean score of all applicable items (range: -3 to +3)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in neurophysiology measurements of evoked potentials (EPs) as well as nerve conduction measurements and their relation to clinical outcomes</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline; 3 months after SCI; 6 months after SCI; 12 months after SCI / study end</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in lower urinary tract (LUT) neurophysiology: Current perception thresholds (CPTs) and LUT sensory evoked potentials (LUTSEPs) with their relation to clinical outcomes</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline; 3 months after SCI; 6 months after SCI; 12 months after SCI / study end</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in frequency power of surface electromyography (EMG) and electroencephalography (EEG) and their relation to clinical outcomes</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline; 3 months after SCI; 6 months after SCI; 12 months after SCI / study end</time_frame>
    <description>Fast Fourier Transformation analysis for delta, theta, alpha, beta, and gamma band power as assessed via EEG of the cortex and EMG of the muscle</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in EMG and EEG coherence measures and their relation to clinical outcomes</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline; 3 months after SCI; 6 months after SCI; 12 months after SCI / study end</time_frame>
    <description>Coherence for EEG and EMG signals computed as cortico-muscular, inter- and intra-muscular coherence for typical EEG/EMG frequency bands (delta, theta, alpha, beta, and gamma).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in white and gray matter area in the lumbosacral enlargement (LSE) and their relation to clinical outcomes</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline; 3 months after SCI; 6 months after SCI; 12 months after SCI / study end</time_frame>
    <description>White and gray matter areas are obtained by segmenting the T2*-weighted MRI images for white and gray matter at the level of LSE</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in white and gray matter area in upper cervical cord (at C2/C3) and their relation to clinical outcomes</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline; 3 months after SCI; 6 months after SCI; 12 months after SCI / study end</time_frame>
    <description>Obtained by segmenting the T2*-weighted MRI images for white and gray matter at the vertebral level C2/C3.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in white and gray matter volume of the conus medullaris (CM) and their relation to clinical outcomes</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline; 3 months after SCI; 6 months after SCI; 12 months after SCI / study end</time_frame>
    <description>White and gray matter volume are obtained by segmenting the T2*-weighted MRI images for white and gray matter in the CM</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in gray and white matter volume in the brain and their relation to clinical outcomes</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline; 3 months after SCI; 6 months after SCI; 12 months after SCI / study end</time_frame>
    <description>Gray and white matter volume in the brain are computed by feeding the whole-brain T1-weighted MRI images into a voxel-based morphometry algorithm. Changes in the gray and white matter volume will be evaluated in urologically relevant brain areas.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in fractional anisotropy (FA) in the brain and spinal cord and their relation to clinical outcomes</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline; 3 months after SCI; 6 months after SCI; 12 months after SCI / study end</time_frame>
    <description>FA is a common dimensionless measure used in Diffusion Tensor Imaging (DTI) studies and ranges from 0, isotropic movement of water molecules (e.g., cerebrospinal fluid), to 1, fully anisotropic movement of water molecules (e.g., fiber bundles).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in diffusivity in the brain and spinal cord and their relation to clinical outcomes</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline; 3 months after SCI; 6 months after SCI; 12 months after SCI / study end</time_frame>
    <description>Mean, axial, and radial diffusivity (MD, AD, RD) are common measures used in DTI studies providing information about the integrity of the underlying tissue.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in brain and spinal cord tissue microstructure and their relation to clinical outcomes</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline; 3 months after SCI; 6 months after SCI; 12 months after SCI / study end</time_frame>
    <description>Quantitative tissue parameters assessed using MRI Multi-Parameter Mapping.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Expression profile of microRNA (miRNA) in urine and blood as well as their relation to clinical outcomes</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline; 3 months after SCI; 6 months after SCI; 12 months after SCI / study end</time_frame>
    <description>MicroRNA (miRNA) sequencing is used to identify regulated miRNAs specific to TTNS intervention in urine and blood.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in inflammatory markers in bladder tissue, blood, and urine, as well as their relation to clinical outcomes</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline; 3 months after SCI; 6 months after SCI; 12 months after SCI / study end</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in levels of neurotransmitters (neurotrophins) in blood, and urine, as well as their relation to clinical outcomes</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline; 3 months after SCI; 6 months after SCI; 12 months after SCI / study end</time_frame>
    <description>Analysis will be performed using ELISA to detect molecules likely to be involved in the underlying molecular mechanisms of neuromodulation.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in the composition of urinary and stool microbiome and their relation to clinical outcomes</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline; 3 months after SCI; 6 months after SCI; 12 months after SCI / study end</time_frame>
    <description>Gut and bladder microbial patterns are determined from stool and urine samples</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in bladder tissue and their relation to clinical outcomes</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline; 3 months after SCI; 6 months after SCI; 12 months after SCI / study end</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of side effects as well as number and intensity/severity (mild/moderate/severe) of adverse events (AEs) and serious adverse events (SAEs) for the following categories:</measure>
    <time_frame>During complete study period, up to 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>infection - Urinary Tract Infection (UTI)
infection - other than UTI
skin irritation at the electrode site
irritation-related symptoms (e.g. dysuria, hematuria) immediately following a LUT intervention
neuro-urological deterioration
pressure ulcer
neurological deterioration
increase in pain
increase in spasticity
deep vein thrombosis / pulmonary embolism
autonomic dysreflexia
transfer/admittance to an acute care facility</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">114</enrollment>
  <condition>Spinal Cord Injury, Acute</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>VERUM transcutaneous tibial nerve stimulation (TTNS)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>SHAM transcutaneous tibial nerve stimulation (TTNS)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Sham Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>VERUM TTNS</intervention_name>
    <description>Daily 30-minute TTNS intervention is performed 5 days a week during a treatment period of 6-9 weeks, until 3-month post assessments
During a preparation phase of several minutes, sensory and motor thresholds are assessed and stimulation intensities are adjusted for the following 30-minute treatment phase</description>
    <arm_group_label>VERUM transcutaneous tibial nerve stimulation (TTNS)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>SHAM TTNS</intervention_name>
    <description>Daily 30-minute SHAM intervention is performed 5 days a week during a treatment period of 6-9 weeks, until 3-month post assessments
During a preparation phase of several minutes, sensory and motor thresholds are assessed and stimulation intensities are adjusted for the following 30-minute treatment phase</description>
    <arm_group_label>SHAM transcutaneous tibial nerve stimulation (TTNS)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age &gt;18 years

          -  Patients with acute SCI (traumatic SCI and sudden onset (&lt;7 days) non-traumatic SCI)
             within 40 days after injury

          -  Patients with acute SCI at cervical or thoracic level

          -  Willing to take part and follow the requirements of the TASCI protocol (up to one year
             after SCI)

               -  no percutaneous tibial nerve stimulation (PTNS)

               -  no functional electrical stimulation (FES)

               -  no electrical muscle stimulation (EMS)

          -  Informed Consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Contraindications to the investigational product

          -  DO with contractions greater than 40 cmH2O at a bladder filling volume of less than
             500mL at baseline visit

          -  Treatment with antimuscarinics or with mirabegron

          -  Known or suspected non-adherence, drug or alcohol abuse

          -  Inability to follow the procedures of the study, e.g. due to language problems,
             psychological disorders, dementia, etc. of the participant

          -  Participation in another study with investigational drug or product within the 30 days
             preceding and during the present study

          -  Neuromodulation treatment for urological or bowel indication in the last six months or
             ongoing

          -  Botulinum toxin injections in the detrusor and/or urethral sphincter in the last six
             months

          -  Bilaterally absent tibial nerve compound muscle action potential (cMAP, amplitude &lt;
             1mV)

          -  Women who are pregnant or breast feeding

          -  Intention to become pregnant during the course of the study

          -  Individuals especially in need of protection (according to Research with Human
             Subjects published by the Swiss Academy of Medical Sciences
             [www.samw.ch/en/News/News.html])

          -  Enrolment of the investigator, his/her family members, employees and other dependent
             persons

          -  Pre-existing or concomitant medical condition apart from SCI that might pose a safety
             issue or would interfere with interpretation of study results or study conduct (e.g.
             Parkinson's disease, neurodegenerative disorders including multiple sclerosis and
             amyotrophic lateral sclerosis, urological malignancies)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Thomas M. Kessler, Prof. Dr. med.</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>University of Zurich</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Thomas M. Kessler, Prof. Dr. med.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Balgrist University Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Armin Curt, Prof. Dr. med.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Balgrist University Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Martin Brinkhof, Dr.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Swiss Paraplegic Research</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jürgen Pannek, Prof. Dr. med.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Swiss Paraplegic Centre</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Thomas M. Kessler, Prof. Dr. med.</last_name>
    <phone>+41 44 386 39 07</phone>
    <email>thomas.kessler@balgrist.ch</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Martina D. Liechti, Dr. sc. ETH</last_name>
    <phone>+41 44 386 39 07</phone>
    <email>martina.liechti@balgrist.ch</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>REHAB Basel</name>
      <address>
        <city>Basel</city>
        <country>Switzerland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sandra Möhr, pract. med.</last_name>
      <email>s.moehr@rehab.ch</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Sandra Möhr, pract. med.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Swiss Paraplegic Centre</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nottwil</city>
        <country>Switzerland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jürgen Pannek, Prof. Dr. med.</last_name>
      <email>juergen.pannek@paraplegie.ch</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jürgen Pannek, Prof. Dr. med.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Spinal Cord Injury Department, Clinique romande de réadaption</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sion</city>
        <country>Switzerland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Xavier Jordan, Dr. med.</last_name>
      <email>xavier.jordan@crr-suva.ch</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Xavier Jordan, Dr. med.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of Neuro-Urology, Spinal Cord Injury Centre &amp; Research, Balgrist University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Zürich</city>
        <zip>8008</zip>
        <country>Switzerland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Thomas M Kessler, Prof. Dr. med.</last_name>
      <phone>+41 44 386 39 07</phone>
      <email>thomas.kessler@balgrist.ch</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Thomas M Kessler, Prof. Dr. med.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Switzerland</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://p3.snf.ch/project-179644</url>
    <description>TASCI on Swiss National Science Foundation grant database</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 26, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 23, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 29, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 2, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 2, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 5, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>randomized, sham-controlled, double-blind trial</keyword>
  <keyword>transcutaneous tibial nerve stimulation</keyword>
  <keyword>spinal cord injury</keyword>
  <keyword>neurogenic detrusor overactivity</keyword>
  <keyword>neuromodulation</keyword>
  <keyword>electrical stimulation</keyword>
  <keyword>paraplegia; tetraplegia</keyword>
  <keyword>urodynamics</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Spinal Cord Injuries</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Wounds and Injuries</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>All individual participant data (IPD) and data dictionaries that underlie results in a publication are to be uploaded to a public data registry in cases where this can be done without compromising patient privacy. Given the small size of the dataset and that spinal cord injury (SCI) is a rare condition, to ensure identity protection any publicly available dataset(s) will be modified to reduce the number of indirect identifier variables, e.g. continuous variables such as age will be grouped, categorical or binary variables with small group numbers such as study centre will not be provided. When data sets cannot be sufficiently de-identified to be made publicly available, they will be made available upon reasonable request. Data judged to be confidential to participants or the participating study centers will not be released, but efforts will be made to provide scientifically meaningful equivalent information.</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Analytic Code</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>Post-publication data packages, containing the analysis data set presented in scientific reports will be available starting 6 months after the publication date. Data that are not being prepared for publication will be available to secondary users starting 4 years after study completion or discontinuation. All data will be kept for at least 10 years after study completion or discontinuation.</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>Requests for data access will be reviewed by the TASCI steering committee, which includes the four project PIs and representatives from each of the participating study centers. The steering committee will request a project plan, including at a minimum an abstract and a list of author names and roles, from the leaders of all projects wishing to use TASCI study data. Project plans will be evaluated on the basis of scientific validity, and also on whether they include adequate measures to protect patient privacy. Secondary users will be asked to sign a data use agreement.</ipd_access_criteria>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

