<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03962686</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>SecondUNI 22.05.2019</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03962686</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Molecular Mechanisms and Carotid Atherosclerosis</brief_title>
  <official_title>Molecular Mechanisms Implied in Carotid Atherosclerosis and Atherosclerotic Plaque Progression in Patients Normoglycemics vs. Patients With Diabetes Mellitus</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Campania &quot;Luigi Vanvitelli&quot;</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Campania &quot;Luigi Vanvitelli&quot;</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The role of methylase system in the accelerated atherosclerotic progression of diabetic
      patients is unclear. Authors will evaluate methylase activity in carotid plaques of
      asymptomatic diabetic and non diabetic patients, as well as the effect of metformin in
      diabetic plaques. Plaques will be obtained from 46 type 2 diabetic and 30 non diabetic
      patients undergoing carotid endarterectomy. Diabetic patients will receive 1000 mg of
      metformin (n 23) or placebo (n 23) for 4 months before scheduled endarterectomy. Plaques will
      be analyzed for macrophages (CD68), T-cells (CD3), inflammatory cells (HLADR), methylase
      activity, nuclear factor (NF)-KB, tumor necrosis factor (TNF)-alpha, nitrotyrosine, matrix
      metalloproteinase (MMP) and collagen content (immunohistochemistry and enzyme- linked
      immunosorbent assay. Authors' study hypothesis is that methylase over-activity will be
      associated with enhanced inflammatory reaction and NF-KB expression in diabetic plaques.
      Secondly, the inhibition of methylase activity in atherosclerotic lesions of diabetic
      patients by metformin might be associated with morphological and compositional
      characteristics of a potential stable plaque phenotype, possibly by down regulating
      NF-KB-mediated inflammatory pathways.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Diabetes Mellitus (DM) leads to increased vulnerability for plaque disruption and mediates
      increased incidence and severity of clinical events. Inflammation, particularly in diabetes,
      plays a central role in the cascade of events that result in plaque erosion and fissuring.
      There is emerging evidence that the methylase system might be involved in both initial stage
      and progression of atherosclerosis. Moreover, the methylase system might be involved in
      inflammatory/oxidative stress pathway, involved for activation of nuclear factor kappa B
      (NF-KB), and other proteins linked to over inflammation/oxidative stress. Although it has
      been demonstrated that diabetes may up regulate these inflammatory/oxidative pathway, still
      no evidence exists about the potential role of methylase system in the evolution of
      atherosclerotic plaques of diabetic patients. Conversely, less data have been reported about
      the possible modulation of these pathways by hypoglycemic drugs as oral metfromin. However,
      in the present study authors hypothesized that by increasing methylase activity, diabetes may
      enhance the inflammatory potential of atherosclerotic plaques favoring instability.
      Therefore, authors designed this study to identify differences in inflammatory infiltration
      as well as methylase activity between carotid plaques of asymptomatic diabetic and non
      diabetic (normoglycemics) patients. Because experimental and pathological studies suggest
      that activation of methylase system might control inflammation/oxidative stress, the present
      study also evaluated the effect of the metformin on methylase activity in carotid plaques of
      diabetic patients.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 1, 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">January 1, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">January 1, 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Control</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>methylase status</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>to evaluate the activity (over vs. hypo activation) of methylase complex in atherosclerotic carotid plaques of normoglycemics vs. DM patients, and of DM patients vs. DM patients previous treated by metformin.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>3</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">76</enrollment>
  <condition>Diabetes Mellitus, Type 2</condition>
  <condition>Atherosclerosis of Artery</condition>
  <condition>Atherosclerotic Plaque</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>normoglycemics</arm_group_label>
    <description>In this cohort will be enrolled 30 normoglycemics patients affected by carotid artery atherosclerotic and evidence of atherosclerotic plaque causing an endolumninal stenosis &gt; 60%. These patients will receive a surgical intervention to remove the atherosclerotic plaque and to revascularize the obstructed coronary artery vessel.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>patients with diabetes mellitus (DM)</arm_group_label>
    <description>In this cohort will be enrolled 23 DM patients affected by carotid artery atherosclerotic and evidence of atherosclerotic plaque causing an endolumninal stenosis &gt; 60%. These patients will receive a surgical intervention to remove the atherosclerotic plaque and to revascularize the obstructed coronary artery vessel.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>patients with diabetes mellitus (DM) plus metformin</arm_group_label>
    <description>In this cohort will be enrolled 23 DM patients affected by carotid artery atherosclerotic and evidence of atherosclerotic plaque causing an endolumninal stenosis &gt; 60%. These patients will receive a surgical intervention to remove the atherosclerotic plaque and to revascularize the obstructed coronary artery vessel. These patients were treated before the surgical intervention by metformin 1000 mg daily.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>MetFORMIN 1000 Mg Oral Tablet</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients in the third study cohort will receive for 4 months a 1000 mg metformin oral therapy before to practice surgical intervention for carotid artery obstruction.</description>
    <arm_group_label>patients with diabetes mellitus (DM) plus metformin</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      samples of atherosclerotic plaques obtained during revascularization of carotid arteries.
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Study population will be divided in 30 normoglycemics patients vs. 46 DM patients. DM
        patients will be divided in patients without metformin therapy (23 patients) vs. DM
        patients previous treated by 1000 mg daily of metformin. All patients will be affected by
        severe obstructive carotid artery atherosclerosis.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  evidence of carotid artery atherosclerosis with endoluminal stenosis &gt; 60%;

          -  aged &gt;18 years.

          -  aged &lt;75 years

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  insulin dependent DM;

          -  absence of carotid artery atherosclerosis with endoluminal stenosis &gt; 60%;

          -  contraindication to receive a carotid artery revascularization treatment;

             --contraindication to receive metformin treatment;

          -  neoplastic diseases;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Raffaele Marfella</name>
      <address>
        <city>Naples</city>
        <zip>80138</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Italy</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 22, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 22, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 24, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 22, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 22, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 24, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Campania &quot;Luigi Vanvitelli&quot;</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Celestino Sardu</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>clinical professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Carotid Artery Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Atherosclerosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus, Type 2</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Plaque, Atherosclerotic</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Metformin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

