<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03961555</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>SYN023-004</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03961555</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Comparison of SYN023 to Human Rabies Immune Globulin in Post Exposure Prophylaxis of Rabies</brief_title>
  <acronym>ARPEP</acronym>
  <official_title>A Phase 2b Randomized Blinded Study to Evaluate SYN023 Compared to Human Rabies Immune Globulin in Post Exposure Prophylaxis of Rabies in Adults With Different Rabies Exposure Risks</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Synermore Biologics Co., Ltd.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Synermore Biologics Co., Ltd.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a Phase 2b, double blinded, randomized study of SYN023 compared to HyperRab® (a
      licensed Rabies immune globulin from human sources, HRIG) for the prevention of rabies as
      part of post-exposure prophylaxis (PEP). The trial will enroll sequentially two different
      risk substrata of WHO Category 3 rabies exposure which are Low Risk Group (LRG) and Normal
      Risk Group (NRG). The enrollment will be stepwise while subject's data will be reviewed by
      DSMB to confirm the safety and permit for next enrollment. Besides, rabies vaccine would be
      administered within 75 minutes after Study Drug in each group.

      This trial is proposed to further the licensure of SYN023 to provide an effective PEP
      alternative available to those exposed persons who need such a product. A placebo-controlled
      rabies trial is unethical thus HRIG is selected as the control group. Rabies immune globulin
      from equine and human sources (HRIG) have been evaluated in many trials and HRIG is the
      standard of care in the United States.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 3, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>geometric mean RVNA concentration (superiority)</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 and 8</time_frame>
    <description>To demonstrate that the geometric mean RVNA concentration for SYN023 recipients is superior to the geometric mean RVNA concentration for HRIG recipients on Study Day 8</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>geometric mean RVNA concentrations at D99</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 and 99</time_frame>
    <description>To demonstrate that the Study Day 99 geometric mean RVNA concentration for SYN023 recipients is not inferior to the geometric mean RVNA concentration for HRIG recipients</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>cases of probable or confirmed rabie</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1, 4, 8, 15, 29, 43, 71, 99, 127, 155, 183, 274 and 365</time_frame>
    <description>There are no cases of probable or confirmed rabies in SYN023 recipients</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>the percentage of subjects with RVNA concentration ≥0.5 IU/mL</measure>
    <time_frame>D1 and 99</time_frame>
    <description>To demonstrate that the percentage of subjects with RVNA concentration ≥0.5 IU/mL on Study Day 99 in SYN023 recipients is not inferior to the percentage of recipients with RVNA concentration ≥0.5 IU/mL for HRIG</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>geometric mean RVNA concentration on Day 4</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 and 4</time_frame>
    <description>To demonstrate that the geometric mean RVNA concentration for SYN023 is superior to the geometric mean RVNA concentration for HRIG on Study Day 4</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The ratio of the geometric mean concentrations of RVNA at each time point in geometric mean RVNA AUEC1-15</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1, 4, 8, 15, 29, 43, 71, 99, 127, 155, 183, 274 and 365</time_frame>
    <description>To demonstrate that the geometric mean RVNA AUEC1-15 for SYN023 is superior to the geometric mean RVNA AUEC1-15 for HRIG</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>geometric mean concentrations of RVNA at each time point</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1, 4, 8, 15, 29, 43, 71, 99, 127, 155, 183, 274 and 365</time_frame>
    <description>To describe the ratio of the geometric mean concentrations of RVNA at each time point in SYN023 recipients divided by the geometric mean concentrations of RVNA in HRIG recipients for LRG and NRG in the per-protocol and as-treated populations</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>the percentage of RVNA concentration ≥0.5 IU/mL at each time point</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1, 4, 8, 15, 29, 43, 71, 99, 127, 155, 183, 274 and 365</time_frame>
    <description>To describe the percentage of RVNA concentration ≥0.5 IU/mL at each time point for SYN023 and HRIG recipients for LRG and NRG in the per-protocol and as-treated populations.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PK for Vd of SYN023 using non-compartmental analysis</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1, 4, 8, 15, 99</time_frame>
    <description>To describe the pharmacokinetics of SYN023 Mab using non-compartmental analysis. Vd will be calculated when possible in the LRG and NRG protocol and as treated populations</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PK for Cmax of SYN023 using non-compartmental analysis</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1, 4, 8, 15, 99</time_frame>
    <description>To describe the pharmacokinetics of SYN023 Mab using non-compartmental analysis. Cmax will be calculated when possible in the LRG and NRG protocol and as treated populations</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PK for Tmax of SYN023 using non-compartmental analysis</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1, 4, 8, 15, 99</time_frame>
    <description>To describe the pharmacokinetics of SYN023 Mab using non-compartmental analysis. Tmax will be calculated when possible in the LRG and NRG protocol and as treated populations</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PK for AUC1-t of SYN023 using non-compartmental analysis</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1, 4, 8, 15, 99</time_frame>
    <description>To describe the pharmacokinetics of SYN023 Mab using non-compartmental analysis. AUC1-t will be calculated when possible in the LRG and NRG protocol and as treated populations</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PK for AUC1-inf of SYN023 using non-compartmental analysis</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1, 4, 8, 15, 99</time_frame>
    <description>To describe the pharmacokinetics of SYN023 Mab using non-compartmental analysis. AUC1-inf will be calculated when possible in the LRG and NRG protocol and as treated populations</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PK for t½ of SYN023 using non-compartmental analysis</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1, 4, 8, 15, 99</time_frame>
    <description>To describe the pharmacokinetics of SYN023 Mab using non-compartmental analysis. t½ will be calculated when possible in the LRG and NRG protocol and as treated populations</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PK for Cl of SYN023 using non-compartmental analysis</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1, 4, 8, 15, 99</time_frame>
    <description>To describe the pharmacokinetics of SYN023 Mab using non-compartmental analysis. Cl will be calculated when possible in the LRG and NRG protocol and as treated populations</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PK for λz of SYN023 using non-compartmental analysis</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1, 4, 8, 15, 99</time_frame>
    <description>To describe the pharmacokinetics of SYN023 Mab using non-compartmental analysis. λz will be calculated when possible in the LRG and NRG protocol and as treated populations</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The presence and effects of anti-SYN023 antibodies</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1, 15, 29, and 99 for LRG group and Day 1, 15 and 99 for NRG group</time_frame>
    <description>To evaluate presence and effects of anti-SYN023 antibodies (anti-CTB011, anti-CTB012)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>the safety (the number and percentage of adverse events) of SYN023 compared to HRIG</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1, 4, 8, 15, 29, 43, 71, 99, 127, 155, 183, 274 and 365</time_frame>
    <description>To evaluate the safety of SYN023 compared to HyperRab® S/D. The safety profile will be the number and percentage of unsolicited and solicited adverse events recorded at all available post-vaccination time points</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>effect of increasing BMI</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 4, 8, 15, 29, 43, 71, 99, 127, 155, 183, 274 and 365</time_frame>
    <description>To describe any effect of increasing BMI on SYN023 and RVNA concentrations</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">448</enrollment>
  <condition>Rabies</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>SYN023+Rabies vaccine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>SYN023:
Interventions: are administered by direct injection into the wound or by subcutaneous or intramuscular injection when this is not possible
SYN023 is an equal mass mixture of CTB011 and CTB012, two monoclonal antibodies that exhibit a wide spectrum of activity against various wild-type rabies strains in vitro.
Dosage form: 6mg/2mL, liquid,
Dosage: 0.3 mg/kg of SYN023
Frequency/duration: at Day 1
Rabies vaccine (RabAvert/Rabipur):
Interventions: should be administered in deltoid muscle
Dosage form: &gt;=2.5 IU, freeze-dried vaccine, reconstitute into 1mL before use
Dosage: 1 mL after reconstitution
Frequency/duration: at Day 1, 4, 8, 15, 29</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>HRIG+Rabies vaccine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>HRIG:
Interventions: are administered by direct injection into the wound or by subcutaneous or intramuscular injection when this is not possible
Dosage form: 150 IU/mL or 300 IU/mL, liquid,
Dosage: 20 IU/kg of HyperRab (HRIG)
Frequency/duration: at Day 1
Rabies vaccine (RabAvert/Rabipur):
Interventions: should be administered in deltoid muscle
Dosage form: &gt;=2.5 IU, freeze-dried vaccine, reconstitute into 1mL before use
Dosage: 1 mL after reconstitution
Frequency/duration: at Day 1, 4, 8, 15, 29</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>SYN023</intervention_name>
    <description>it is administered by direct injection into the wound or by subcutaneous or intramuscular injection when this is not possible</description>
    <arm_group_label>SYN023+Rabies vaccine</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>HRIG (HyperRab)</intervention_name>
    <description>it is administered by direct injection into the wound or by subcutaneous or intramuscular injection when this is not possible</description>
    <arm_group_label>HRIG+Rabies vaccine</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Rabies vaccine</intervention_name>
    <description>it should be administered in deltoid muscle</description>
    <arm_group_label>HRIG+Rabies vaccine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>SYN023+Rabies vaccine</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>RabAvert</other_name>
    <other_name>Rabipur</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria (LRG):

        Subjects must meet all of the following criteria at the time of subject ID assignment:

          1. History of dog, cat, mongoose, fox, ferret, skunk, bat or raccoon bite to trunk, leg,
             ankle or foot, or lick or scratch with, or of broken skin or mucous membrane saliva or
             neural tissue contamination, unprotected physical bat contact, scratch or saliva
             contamination of the head or neck without broken skin all ≤ 54 hours (Section 3.9.4
             and 3.9.5)

          2. Has completed the written informed consent process and signed informed consent
             document

          3. Males and females

          4. Is age equal or more than 18 years on Study Day 1

          5. Agrees to stay in contact with the study site for the duration of the study, provide
             updated contact information as necessary, and has no current plans to move from the
             study area for the duration of the study

          6. Lives within 2 hour journey by available transportation to study center

          7. For female subjects: agrees to avoid pregnancy from Study Day 1 through Study Day 121.
             Women physically capable of pregnancy (not sterilized and still menstruating or within
             1 year of the last menses if menopausal) in sexual relationships with men must use an
             acceptable method of avoiding pregnancy during this period. Acceptable methods of
             avoiding pregnancy include a sterile sexual partner, sexual abstinence (not engaging
             in sexual intercourse), hormonal contraceptives (oral, injection, transdermal patch,
             or implant), vaginal ring, intrauterine device (IUD), or the combination of a condom
             or diaphragm with spermicide

        Inclusion Criteria (NRG)

        Subjects must meet all of the following criteria at the time of subject ID assignment:

          1. History of dog, cat, mongoose, fox, ferret, skunk, bat or raccoon bite to any body
             part, lick or scratch with, or of broken skin, mucous membrane saliva or neural tissue
             contamination, or unprotected physical bat contact all ≤ 54 hours from PEP (Section
             3.9.4 and 3.9.5)

          2. Has completed the written informed consent process and signed informed consent
             document.

          3. Males and females

          4. Is age equal or more than 18 years on Study Day 1

          5. Agrees to stay in contact with the study site for the duration of the study, provide
             updated contact information as necessary, and has no current plans to move from the
             study area for the duration of the study

          6. Lives within 2 hour journey by available transportation to study center

          7. For female subjects: agrees to avoid pregnancy from agrees to avoid pregnancy from
             Study Day 1 through Study Day 121. Women physically capable of pregnancy (not
             sterilized and still menstruating or within 1 year of the last menses if menopausal)
             in sexual relationships with men must use an acceptable method of avoiding pregnancy
             during this period. Acceptable methods of avoiding pregnancy include a sterile sexual
             partner, sexual abstinence (not engaging in sexual intercourse), hormonal
             contraceptives (oral, injection, transdermal patch, or implant), vaginal ring,
             intrauterine device (IUD), or the combination of a condom or diaphragm with spermicide

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Subjects must have had none of the following at the time of subject ID assignment:

          1. Clinical evidence of rabies infection

          2. Category 3 exposure &gt; 54 hours before Study Drug receipt

          3. History or serological evidence of previous rabies vaccination

          4. Previous receipt of equine or human rabies globulin

          5. History of hypersensitivity reaction to equine or human immunoglobulin.

          6. Received immunoglobulin or blood products within 42 days before Study Day 1

          7. Received any investigational drug therapy or investigational vaccine within 60 days
             before Study Day 1

          8. Planned participation in any other investigational study during the study period.

          9. Receiving systemic immunosuppressant medication such as systemic corticosteroids but
             not limited to systemic corticosteroids

         10. History or laboratory evidence of any past, present, or possible immunodeficiency
             state including but not limited to any laboratory indication of HIV infection

         11. Previous medical history that may compromise the safety of the subject in the study
             according to the opinion of the principal investigator

         12. History or evidence on physical examination of any systemic disease or any acute or
             chronic illness that, in the opinion of the investigator, may interfere with the
             evaluation of the safety or activity of SYN023

         13. Pregnancy (results of the urine pregnancy test MUST be known before enrollment)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Lisa Huang, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+886-2-87582587</phone>
    <email>Lisa.Huang@ppdi.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Baguio General Hospital and Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baguio City</city>
        <state>Benguet</state>
        <zip>2600</zip>
        <country>Philippines</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Domingo Solimen, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>De La Salle Health Sciences Institute Independent Ethics Committee</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cavite</city>
        <state>Calabarzon</state>
        <zip>4114</zip>
        <country>Philippines</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Madeleine Grace M. Sosa, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Southern Philippines Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Davao City</city>
        <state>Davao (Region XI)</state>
        <zip>8000</zip>
        <country>Philippines</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Marie Yvette Barez, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Manila Doctors Hospital Institutional Review Board</name>
      <address>
        <city>Manila</city>
        <state>Metro Manila</state>
        <zip>1000</zip>
        <country>Philippines</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Camilo Jr. G. Te, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Asian Hospital and Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Muntinlupa</city>
        <state>National Capital Region</state>
        <zip>1780</zip>
        <country>Philippines</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Maria Rosario Capeding, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Center of Excellence in Drug Research, Evaluation and Studies, Inc.</name>
      <address>
        <city>Muntinlupa</city>
        <state>National Capital Region</state>
        <zip>1781</zip>
        <country>Philippines</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Charissa Tabora, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Institute For Tropical Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Muntinlupa</city>
        <state>National Capital Region</state>
        <zip>1781</zip>
        <country>Philippines</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Beatriz Quiambao, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Institute For Tropical Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Muntinlupa</city>
        <state>National Capital Region</state>
        <zip>1781</zip>
        <country>Philippines</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Mari Rose De Los Reyes, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Far Eastern University Hospital Nicanor Reyes Medical Foundation</name>
      <address>
        <city>Quezon City</city>
        <state>National Capital Region</state>
        <zip>1118</zip>
        <country>Philippines</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>May Emmeline Montellano, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mary Johnston Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Manila</city>
        <country>Philippines</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ronald Payumo, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Philippines</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 16, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 21, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 23, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 6, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 6, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 8, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Post-exposure prophylaxis of Rabies</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Rabies</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

