<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03962777</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>BaskentU5</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03962777</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Efficacy of Oil Pulling Therapy on Supragingival Plaque Growth</brief_title>
  <official_title>Efficacy of Oil Pulling Therapy With Coconut Oil on Four Day Supragingival Plaque Growth: a Randomized Crossover Clinical Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Baskent University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Baskent University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Oil pulling is a method based on Ayurvedic medicine which aims to obtain local and systemic
      benefits by swirling oils in the oral cavity for a period of 15 minutes, before spitting it
      out.12 Although the exact mechanism of action is not clear, there are some proposed theories.
      One proposed theory is the saponification or &quot;soap making&quot; process which occurs as a result
      of alkali hydrolysis of fat.9 Second theory speculates the inhibition of plaque formation and
      adhesion of bacteria due to the viscous nature of the oil. 13 According to the third theory,
      presence of antioxidants in oil prevent lipid peroxidation and thus help to the destruction
      of microorganisms and potentiating the action of Vitamin E in the oral cavity.14 The effect
      of oil pulling on halitosis and the use of oil pulling in addition to conventional oral
      hygiene practices was investigated in some studies13,15,16 but to the best knowledge of the
      authors, no study has evaluated the plaque-inhibiting effects of oil pulling. Therefore this
      study was conducted to evaluate the plaque-inhibiting effects of oil pulling using 4- day
      plaque regrowth study model17,18 compared to 0.2% CHX-containing mouthrinse. The tested
      hypothesis was that oil pulling would perform plaque regrowth inhibition as well as the
      CHX-containing mouthrinse.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The study was a single-center, observer masked, cross-over design with subjects randomly
      allocated to treatment sequences. During a 2-week preparatory period, participants rendered
      plaque, calculus and stain free by a thorough scaling and polishing of the teeth by both hand
      and ultrasonic instruments and were instructed in self-performed plaque control. At the end
      of the preparatory period, all subjects had clinically healthy gingiva.

      Participants were randomly allocated to two groups by closed envelop system (BM) and masked
      to the mouthrinse received. The tested products and regimens of use are shown in Table 1.
      Mouthrinses were filled in identical but coded bottles. Instructions for usage was written on
      the bottles. On day 1 (Monday) of each study periods, after disclosing the teeth with
      erythrosine all subjects received scaling and polishing to remove plaque and extrinsic stain
      and disclosing of the teeth was repeated. By this way it was confirmed that all participants
      had a plaque score of 0 at baseline. Subjects were then asked to refrain from all forms of
      tooth cleaning and to apply the rinsing regimen. The tested agents included the following: 1)
      0.2 % chlorhexidine mouthrinse ( 10 mL, twice daily for 30 seconds) 2) Coconut oil (10 Ml,
      twice daily 15-20 minute) All agents were to be used after breakfast and dinner and the
      subjects should be avoided rinsing, eating and drinking during the first hour after rinsing.
      During the 4- day period, the use of any other rinse, chewing gum or toothpaste was not
      allowed. The mouthrinses were in identical bottles but total subject blindness cannot be
      possible due to the taste, color, consistency, rinsing time differences.

      On day 5 (Friday), subjects received an oral soft tissue examination and were asked to
      complete a standardized questionnaire to evaluate their attitudes with regard to the product
      used. The patients were asked about the flavor of the mouthrinse, the alteration in the taste
      of food and drinks, the perception of the plaque reduction, the staining that the mouthrinse
      created, the feeling to create nausea. After the completion of the questionnaire, each
      subject was scored for staining using Lobene stain index.19 After that, disclosing was
      performed with erythrosine and plaque scoring was performed using the Turesky et al. 20
      modification of the Quigley and Hein index.21 Stain and plaque indices were recorded from the
      buccal and lingual surfaces of all fully erupted permanent teeth, with the exception of the
      third molars. In addition, Gingival Index (GI) and bleeding on probing (bop) were recorded
      from six sites of each teeth. All clinical examinations were performed by a single clinician
      (YS) who was masked to the study.

      After recording the clinical parameters, subjects received a polishing to remove all plaque
      and tooth stain if present and 14 days of washout periods were allowed after 4- day period.
      22 During the wash out period, the subjects returned to normal oral hygiene methods with a
      standard toothbrush* and a fluoride containing tooth paste**. These procedures were repeated
      until each participant used each of the rinses.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 9, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 15, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 9, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>plaque index</measure>
    <time_frame>day 4</time_frame>
    <description>plaque regrowth inhibition will be tested using the Turesky et al. 21 modification of the Quigley and Hein index.a score of 0 to 5 is assigned to each facial and lingual nonrestored surface of all the teeth except third molars, as follows: 0: No plaque; 1:Separate flecks of plaque at the cervical margin of the tooth; 2:A thin continuos band of plaque (up to one mm) at the cervical margin of the tooth; 3: A band of plaque wider than one mm but covering less than one-third of the crown of the tooth; 4:Plaque covering at least one-third but less than two-thirds of the crown of the tooth; 5: Plaque covering two-thirds or more of the crown of the tooth. An index for the entire mouth is determined by dividing the total score by the number surfaces ( a maximum of 2 x 2 x 14 = 56 surfaces) examined.lower values means that the agent has better plaque inhbiting effect</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Gingivitis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>oil pulling</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>patients used oil pulling therapy for 4 days</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>chlorhexidine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>patients used chlorhexidine digluconate for 4 days</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>chlorhexidine</intervention_name>
    <description>patients used chx moutrinses for four days</description>
    <arm_group_label>chlorhexidine</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>oil pulling</intervention_name>
    <description>patients used oil pulling for four days</description>
    <arm_group_label>oil pulling</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  no systemic disease

          -  having ≥ 22 natural teeth,

          -  having no removable or fixed prostheses or fixed and removable orthodontic appliances.

        Exclusion criteria:

          -  use of antibiotics and anti-inflammatory drugs in previous 6 months;

          -  allergy to any ingredient used in the study;

          -  smokers;

          -  pregnant of lactating females;

          -  history of mouthrinses, gels or chewing gums use that contains antimicrobial agents in
             the preceding 3 months

          -  having teeth with probing depth ≥4mm and signs of gingival inflammation.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>60 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>yasemin sezgin, asst prof</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>başkent university, faculty of dentistry</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Yasemin Sezgin</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ankara</city>
        <state>Please Select...</state>
        <zip>06690</zip>
        <country>Turkey</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Turkey</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 22, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 23, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 24, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 25, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 25, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 29, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Baskent University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Yasemin Sezgin</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>asistant professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>gingivitis</keyword>
  <keyword>oil pulling</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Gingivitis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Chlorhexidine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

