<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03965234</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>i 70818</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2019-02940</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>i 70818</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>P30CA016056</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03965234</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Pulmonary Suffusion in Controlling Minimal Residual Disease in Patients With Soft Tissue or Bone Sarcoma Metastatic to the Lungs</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase I/ II Study of Pulmonary Suffusion to Control Minimal Residual Disease in Resectable Sarcoma Pulmonary Metastases</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Roswell Park Cancer Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Roswell Park Cancer Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>Yes</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This phase I/II trial studies the side effects of pulmonary suffusion in controlling minimal
      residual disease in patients with soft tissue or bone sarcoma that has spread to the lungs.
      Pulmonary suffusion is a minimally invasive delivery of chemotherapeutic agents like
      cisplatin to lung tissues. Drugs used in chemotherapy, such as cisplatin, work in different
      ways to stop the growth of tumor cells, either by killing the cells, by stopping them from
      dividing, or by stopping them from spreading. Pulmonary suffusion may also be useful in
      avoiding later use of drugs by vein that demonstrate no effect on tumors when delivered
      locally.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PRIMARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To assess the safety of chemotherapy isolated to the pulmonary circulation by determining
      the maximum tolerated dose (MTD) and the recommended phase 2 dose (RP2D). (Phase I) II. To
      determine the rate of local recurrences in patients receiving pulmonary suffusion, compared
      to historical controls in patients with completely resected pulmonary metastases (unilateral
      and bilateral disease). (Phase II)

      SECONDARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To determine the local and systemic toxicities associated with pulmonary suffusion. (Phase
      I) II. To determine disease-free survival (DFS) in patients receiving pulmonary suffusion
      compared to historical controls, in patients with completely resected pulmonary metastases
      (unilateral and bilateral disease). (Phase II)

      EXPLORATORY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To evaluate the pulmonary suffusion-associated changes in local tumor microenvironment
      (TME) and potential of suffusion as an immune modulation enhancement. (Phase II) II. To
      determine overall survival (OS) in patients receiving pulmonary suffusion compared to
      historical controls, in patients with completely resected pulmonary metastases (unilateral
      and bilateral disease). (Phase II) III. To compare histology of tumor samples with previously
      resected specimens with attention to biomarkers of systemic immune recognition in patients
      eligible for repeat suffusion. (Phase II) IV. To obtain tumor and systemic immune biomarkers
      including cytokine activations for correlation with clinical responses. (Phase II) V. To
      correlate local control with biomarker for tissue effect from chemotherapy (including tissue
      levels of platinum, alkaline phosphatase [ALP]). (Phase II) VI. To correlate local disease
      control with tumor biomarker for metastasis (circulating [circ] ribonucleic acid [RNA], micro
      [mi]RNA). (Phase II)

      OUTLINE:

      Patients undergo pulmonary suffusion consisting of cisplatin via infusion. Patients then
      undergo metastasectomy. Patients found to have unresectable sarcoma may receive chemotherapy
      within 4-8 weeks of metastasectomy.

      After completion of study treatment, patients are followed up for 3 months and then every 6
      months for up to 5 years.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 16, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 25, 2030</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 25, 2029</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of local toxicities (Phase I)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Dose limiting toxicities (DLTs) will be defined based on the rate of drug-related grade 3-5 adverse events. These will be assessed using the National Cancer Institute (NCI) Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE) version (v)5.0.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Recommended phase II dose (Phase I)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 5 years</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Local recurrence (Phase II)</measure>
    <time_frame>From resection until local recurrence in the suffused lung or last clinic follow-up, assessed up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Will be treated as bivariate time-to-event data. Freedom from local recurrence will be summarized using standard Kaplan-Meier methods and the 2-year local recurrence-free rate will be estimated with a 90% confidence interval calculated using Greenwood's formula.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of local and systemic toxicities (Phase I)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Assessed using the NCI CTCAE v5.0.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Disease-free survival (Phase II)</measure>
    <time_frame>From suffusion until recurrence (local or distant), death due to or related to disease, or last follow-up, assessed up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Will be summarized using standard Kaplan-Meier methods, where estimates of the median survival and 2-year survival rates will be obtained with 90% confidence intervals.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of local and systemic toxicities (Phase II)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Assessed using the NCI CTCAE v5.0. Will be summarized by grade within each arm using frequencies and relative frequencies.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Local recurrence within the treated (suffusion) and untreated lungs for patients with bilateral disease (Phase II)</measure>
    <time_frame>At 2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Will be compared between the suffused and non-suffused lungs using McNemar?s test. A 90% confidence interval about the difference in local recurrence rates will also be obtained.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Lung injury (% reduction of spirometry and differential reduction by quantitative perfusion scan) (Phase II)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <description>The association between lung injury and response and survival outcomes will be evaluated using logistic and Cox regression models.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Immune markers (Phase II)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Will be correlated to primary endpoints. The cytokine activation, tumor, immune, and stress related biomarkers will be summarized using the appropriate descriptive statistics. The association between overall response and the biomarkers will be evaluated using logistic regression models. The association between time-to-event outcomes (freedom from recurrence and survival) and the biomarkers will be evaluated using Cox regression models. All model assumptions will be verified graphically and fit using Firth's method.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival (Phase II)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Will be compared to historical controls. Will be summarized using standard Kaplan-Meier methods, where estimates of the median survival and 2-year survival rates will be obtained with 90% confidence intervals.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Metastatic Bone Sarcoma</condition>
  <condition>Metastatic Malignant Neoplasm in the Lung</condition>
  <condition>Metastatic Soft Tissue Sarcoma</condition>
  <condition>Metastatic Unresectable Sarcoma</condition>
  <condition>Resectable Sarcoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Prevention (cisplatin, metastasectomy)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients undergo pulmonary suffusion consisting of cisplatin via infusion. Patients the undergo metastasectomy. Beginning 4-8 weeks, patients with unresectable sarcoma may receive chemotherapy.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cisplatin</intervention_name>
    <description>Given via infusion</description>
    <arm_group_label>Prevention (cisplatin, metastasectomy)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Abiplatin</other_name>
    <other_name>Blastolem</other_name>
    <other_name>Briplatin</other_name>
    <other_name>CDDP</other_name>
    <other_name>Cis-diammine-dichloroplatinum</other_name>
    <other_name>Cis-diamminedichloridoplatinum</other_name>
    <other_name>Cis-diamminedichloro Platinum (II)</other_name>
    <other_name>Cis-diamminedichloroplatinum</other_name>
    <other_name>Cis-dichloroammine Platinum (II)</other_name>
    <other_name>Cis-platinous Diamine Dichloride</other_name>
    <other_name>Cis-platinum</other_name>
    <other_name>Cis-platinum II</other_name>
    <other_name>Cis-platinum II Diamine Dichloride</other_name>
    <other_name>Cismaplat</other_name>
    <other_name>Cisplatina</other_name>
    <other_name>Cisplatinum</other_name>
    <other_name>Cisplatyl</other_name>
    <other_name>Citoplatino</other_name>
    <other_name>Citosin</other_name>
    <other_name>Cysplatyna</other_name>
    <other_name>DDP</other_name>
    <other_name>Lederplatin</other_name>
    <other_name>Metaplatin</other_name>
    <other_name>Neoplatin</other_name>
    <other_name>Peyrone's Chloride</other_name>
    <other_name>Peyrone's Salt</other_name>
    <other_name>Placis</other_name>
    <other_name>Plastistil</other_name>
    <other_name>Platamine</other_name>
    <other_name>Platiblastin</other_name>
    <other_name>Platiblastin-S</other_name>
    <other_name>Platinex</other_name>
    <other_name>Platinol</other_name>
    <other_name>Platinol- AQ</other_name>
    <other_name>Platinol-AQ</other_name>
    <other_name>Platinol-AQ VHA Plus</other_name>
    <other_name>Platinoxan</other_name>
    <other_name>Platinum</other_name>
    <other_name>Platinum Diamminodichloride</other_name>
    <other_name>Platiran</other_name>
    <other_name>Platistin</other_name>
    <other_name>Platosin</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Isolated Chemotherapeutic Lung Perfusion</intervention_name>
    <description>Undergo pulmonary suffusion</description>
    <arm_group_label>Prevention (cisplatin, metastasectomy)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>isolated lung perfusion</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Metastasectomy</intervention_name>
    <description>Undergo metastasectomy</description>
    <arm_group_label>Prevention (cisplatin, metastasectomy)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Soft tissue or bone sarcoma metastatic to the lungs

          -  Have an Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status of =&lt; 2

          -  Hemoglobin &gt; 8.0 g/L

          -  Granulocytes &gt; 1,500 uL

          -  Platelets &gt;= 100,000 uL

          -  Creatinine clearance &gt;= 30 mL/min

          -  Biopsy or cytologically proven resectable or unresectable sarcoma lung metastasis

          -  No hearing loss (normal audiology testing)

          -  Have measurable disease per Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors (RECIST) 1.1
             criteria present

          -  Forced expiratory volume in 1 second (FEV1) &gt;= 50% predicted

          -  Diffusion capacity of the lung for carbon monoxide (DLCO) &gt;= 50% predicted

          -  Vital capacity (VC) &gt;= 50% predicted

          -  Ambulatory and resting oxygen (O2) saturation &gt; 88%

          -  Six minute walk &gt;= 50 % of the expected distance

          -  Surgeon and interventional radiologist affirmation that suffusion is technically
             feasible

          -  Borg Dyspnea scale (modified) &lt; 5

          -  Control of the primary sarcoma tumor by imaging performed =&lt; 1 month prior to study
             enrollment

          -  Participants of child-bearing potential must agree to use adequate contraceptive
             methods (e.g., hormonal or barrier method of birth control; abstinence) prior to study
             entry. Should a woman become pregnant or suspect she is pregnant while she or her
             partner is participating in this study, she should inform her treating physician
             immediately

          -  Participant or legal representative must understand the investigational nature of this
             study and sign an Independent Ethics Committee/Institutional Review Board approved
             written informed consent form prior to receiving any study related procedure

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Previous lung-directed radiation therapy

          -  Use of home oxygen

          -  Participants who have had chemotherapy or radiotherapy within 4 weeks (6 weeks for
             nitrosoureas or mitomycin C) prior to entering the study or those who have not
             recovered from adverse events due to agents administered more than 4 weeks earlier

          -  Participants with known brain metastases should be excluded from this clinical trial
             because of their poor prognosis and because they often develop progressive neurologic
             dysfunction that would confound the evaluation of neurologic and other adverse events

          -  Allergy, intolerance, or other serious reaction to cisplatin

          -  Uncontrolled intercurrent illness including, but not limited to, ongoing or active
             infection, symptomatic congestive heart failure, unstable angina pectoris, unstable
             cardiac arrhythmias, or psychiatric illness/social situations that would limit
             compliance with study requirements

          -  Pregnant or nursing female participants

          -  Unwilling or unable to follow protocol requirements

          -  Any additional condition which in the Investigator?s opinion deems the participant an
             unsuitable candidate to receive study drug or the suffusion technique

          -  Received an investigational agent within 30 days prior to enrollment

          -  Hearing loss

          -  Severe peripheral neuropathy
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Todd L Demmy</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Roswell Park Cancer Institute</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Roswell Park Cancer Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Buffalo</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>14263</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Todd L. Demmy</last_name>
      <phone>716-845-8675</phone>
      <email>todd.demmy@roswellpark.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Todd L. Demmy</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 22, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 24, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 28, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 16, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 16, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 20, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Sarcoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasm, Residual</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Osteosarcoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cisplatin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

