<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03960541</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HP-00086029</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>CD24Fc-003</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>R44HL145964</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03960541</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>CD24Fc Administration to Decrease LDL and Inflammation in HIV Patients (CALIBER)</brief_title>
  <acronym>CALIBER</acronym>
  <official_title>A Phase II Randomized, Single-blinded, Placebo-controlled Clinical Trial on CD24Fc Administration to Decrease LDL and Inflammation in HIV Patients, Both as Markers of Efficacy and Cardiovascular Risk Reduction (CALIBER)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>OncoImmune, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Maryland, Baltimore</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>OncoImmune, Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a phase 2, randomized, double-blinded, placebo-controlled clinical trial. The
      intervention drug will be CD24Fc (IV infusion). A cohort of 64 patients with HIV on
      antiretroviral therapy will be randomized in a 1:1 fashion to be administered 3 doses of
      CD24Fc (240mg IV infusion) or placebo q2w during a 4-week window, followed by a 24-week
      follow-up window to assess the changes in LDL.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study is a phase 2, randomized, placebo-control, double-blinded clinical trial to assess
      the effect of CD24Fc on reduction in low-density lipoprotein (LDL) among patients with HIV.
      The effect of CD24Fc on total cholesterol and triglycerides, markers of immune activation (T
      cell activation, sCD14, and inflammatory cytokines), size of HIV reservoirs, HbA1c and
      leptin, and hepatic steatosis will be evaluated.

      It is hypothesized that therapy with CD24Fc will result in significant decreases in LDL in
      HIV patients. In addition, CD24Fc may increase leptin and reduce cholesterol, HbA1c, hepatic
      steatosis and fibrosis, and markers of inflammation in patients with chronic HIV who are
      virally suppressed on antiretroviral therapy (ART).

      In this phase 2 study, a cohort of 64 HIV patients virally suppressed on antiretroviral
      therapy will be randomized in a 1:1 fashion to receive an intravenous infusion of 240 mg of
      CD24Fc vs. placebo administered every 2 weeks during a 4-week treatment window, followed by a
      24- week follow-up period. Patients will be followed for safety and adverse events as well as
      changes in lipid metabolism and inflammatory markers during a 24-week follow-up period. This
      investigation will take place at the University of Maryland.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 30, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Randomized, double blinded, placebo controlled.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To evaluate the change in LDL during 6-week dosing period of CD24Fc.</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The percentage reduction in LDL level from the baseline (predosing) to 6 weeks (2 weeks after 3 dosings of drug).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Levels of total cholesterol, HDL, and triglycerides</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks.</time_frame>
    <description>Percent change in levels of total cholesterol, HDL, and triglycerides from baseline to Weeks 6 between placebo and intervention arms.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Markers of immune activation (CD4 and CD8 T cells, IFN, TNF, sCD14)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks.</time_frame>
    <description>Percent change in markers of immune activation (CD4 and CD8 T cells, IFN, TNF, sCD14) from baseline to Week 6 between placebo and intervention arms.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Size of HIV reservoirs</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks.</time_frame>
    <description>Change in proviral DNA from baseline to Week 6 between placebo and intervention arms.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Myocardial damage (measured by Troponin I)</measure>
    <time_frame>28 weeks.</time_frame>
    <description>Percent change from baseline to week 28 in Troponin I between placebo and intervention arms.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hepatic steatosis, as determined by transient elastography</measure>
    <time_frame>28 weeks.</time_frame>
    <description>Change in percent of hepatic steatosis (by CAP measurement) and fibrosis (by KPA) as determined by transient elastography from baseline to week 28 between placebo and intervention arms.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Level of leptin</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks.</time_frame>
    <description>Percent change in leptin from baseline to Week 6 between placebo and intervention arms.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hemoglobin A1c</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks and 28 weeks.</time_frame>
    <description>Percent change in hemoglobin A1c from baseline to Week 6 and week 28 between placebo and intervention arms.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Area under the plasma concentration versus time curve (AUC) of CD24Fc in first 6 patients.</measure>
    <time_frame>28 weeks.</time_frame>
    <description>Area under the plasma concentration versus time curve (AUC) determined by plasma concentration of CD24Fc from different time points during entire study period of 28 weeks from the first 6 patients.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The number of patients who develop Anti-drug antibody in 28 weeks of study period</measure>
    <time_frame>28 weeks.</time_frame>
    <description>To determine the number of patients who have new anti-CD24Fc antibody in 28 weeks.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>To evaluate the impact of CD24Fc on arterial inflammation measured by FDG-PET.</measure>
    <time_frame>28 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Change in baseline arterial Fluorodeoxyglucose (FDG) Uptake Assessed by FDG-PET as a measure of vascular inflammation, between baseline and week 28, for a subset of 12 patients. The 12 patients selected will have an LDL&lt;125 and will not have partook in the PK portion of the study.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">64</enrollment>
  <condition>HIV Infections</condition>
  <condition>Dyslipidemias</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>CD24Fc Treatment</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The intervention drug will be CD24Fc (IV infusion). Patients with HIV on antiretroviral therapy will be administered 3 doses of CD24Fc (240mg IV infusion) q2w during a 4-week window, followed by a 24-week follow-up window to assess safety and changes in LDL.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The intervention drug will be CD24Fc (IV infusion). Patients with HIV on antiretroviral therapy will be administered 3 doses of normal saline solution (150 ml, IV infusion) q2w during a 4-week window, followed by a 24-week follow-up window to assess safety and changes in LDL.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>CD24Fc (human CD24 extracellular domain and human IgG1 Fc fusion protein)</intervention_name>
    <description>CD24Fc will be given as IV infusion, 240 mg per infusion, q2w, total 3 doses in 4 week interval.</description>
    <arm_group_label>CD24Fc Treatment</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>CD24Fc</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Saline Solution</intervention_name>
    <description>Normal Saline Solution will be given as placebo with IV infusion, 150 ml per infusion, q2w, total 3 doses in 4 weeks.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Saline</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Provision of signed and dated informed consent form

          2. Stated willingness to comply with all study procedures and availability for the
             duration of the study

          3. At least 50 years of age or older at screening

          4. LDL-C &gt; 70 mg/dL.

          5. Has a median ACC/AHA ASCVD risk score ≥ 7.5%.

          6. Available for clinical follow-up through Week 28 after enrollment.

          7. Chronic HIV infection based on documentation from a primary care physician that the
             patient has HIV and is on antiretroviral therapy

          8. On a stable regimen of ART. The subject is expected to continue on an accepted ART
             regimen for the duration of the study (through week 36).

               1. Accepted combinations

                    -  FTC/TAF [Descovy®], FTC/TDF [Truvada®], or ABC/3TC [Epzicom®] PLUS o
                       Ritonavir (r) and darunavir (DRV), or o Raltegravir (RAL), or o Elvitegravir
                       (EVG) ± Cobicistat (c), or o Dolutegravir (DTG), or o Rilpivirine (RPV)

               2. Accepted fixed dose combinations • FTC/RPV/TAF [Odefsey®] • FTC/RPV/TDF
                  [Complera®] • EVG/c/TAF/FTC [Genvoya®] • EVG/c/TDF/FTC [Stribild®]

                    -  DTG/ABC/3TC [Triumeq®]

                    -  DTG/TAF/FTC [Biktarvy®]

               3. Alternative ART regimens will be considered on an individual basis, based on
                  available DDI data at the discretion of the principal investigator

        7. At least 2 years of maintained HIV RNA &lt; 50 copies/mL (or &lt; LLOQ if the local laboratory
        assay's LLOQ is ≥50 copies/mL) prior to Screening and HIV RNA&lt;50 at screening. 8. CD4
        count&gt;350 cells/mm3 at Screening 9. Ability to communicate effectively with the study
        investigator and other key personnel 10. Subjects must have a primary care doctor for their
        medical management 11. Willing to donate blood for sample storage to be used for future
        research 12. Female study participants with childbearing potential (defined below) and male
        study participants with female partners of childbearing potential must be willing to
        practice either:

          -  Complete abstinence from sexual intercourse with a member of the opposite sex OR

          -  At least one form of effective contraception from the list below, in addition to
             correct use of either a male or female condom throughout dosing and for a defined
             period following the last dose (30 days for women, 14 days for men) of study
             medication.: i. Intrauterine device with a failure rate of &lt;1% per year ii. Tubal
             sterilization iii. Bilateral tubal occlusion iv. Vasectomy in a male v. Female barrier
             method (diaphragm or cervical cap) vi. Hormonal methods

               1. Oral contraceptives

               2. Injectable progesterone

               3. Implants of levonorgestrel or etonorgestrel

               4. Transdermal contraceptive patch

               5. Contraceptive vaginal ring a. Definition of Childbearing Potential: For the
                  purposes of this study, a female subject is considered of childbearing potential
                  from menarche until becoming post-menopausal, unless permanently sterile or with
                  medically documented ovarian failure. Women are considered to be in a
                  post-menopausal state when they are &gt; 54 years of age with cessation of
                  previously occurring menses for &gt; 12 months without an alternative cause.
                  Permanent sterilization includes hysterectomy, bilateral oophorectomy, or
                  bilateral salpingectomy in a female subject of any age.

             13. Agreement to adhere to Lifestyle Considerations (see section 5.3) throughout study
             duration

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Current or prior history of any of the following:

               1. Clinically significant illness (other than HIV) or any other major medical
                  disorder that may, in the opinion of the investigator, interfere with the subject
                  treatment, assessment of compliance with the protocol; subjects currently under
                  evaluation for a clinically-significant illness (other than HIV) are also
                  excluded

               2. Poor venous access interfering with required study blood collection

               3. Solid organ transplantation

               4. Significant pulmonary disease, significant cardiac disease, or porphyria

               5. Uncontrolled chronic hepatitis B infection (surface antigen positive with
                  detectable HBV DNA as noted in patient's medical documentation from a treating
                  physician)

               6. Chronic hepatitis C infection

               7. Unstable psychiatric disease. (Subjects with psychiatric illness that is well-
                  controlled on a stable treatment regimen or currently not requiring medication
                  may be included.)

               8. Any malignancy or its treatment that in the opinion of the PI may cause ongoing
                  interference with host immunity; subjects under evaluation for malignancy are not
                  eligible.

          2. Abnormal hematological and biochemical parameters at screening, unless the test has
             been repeated and at least one subsequent result is within the acceptable range prior
             to study drug administration, including:

               1. Neutrophil count &lt;750 cells/mm3

               2. Hemoglobin level &lt;10 g/dL

               3. Platelet count ≤50,000 cells/mm3

               4. Estimated glomerular filtration rate, calculated by the chronic kidney disease
                  epidemiology collaboration formula: &lt;30 mL/min/1.73 m2

               5. ALT or AST level ≥5 times upper limit of normal (ULN)

               6. Total bilirubin level ≥2.0 times ULN, except in subjects with Gilbert's syndrome
                  or other clinical explanation at the discretion of the PI

               7. Albumin level &lt;3 g/dL

          3. Poorly controlled diabetes as indicated by a screening glycosylated hemoglobin (HbA1c)
             &gt;10

          4. Need for the use of the following medications from 21 days prior to the start of study
             drugs through the end of treatment:

               1. Hematologic stimulating agents, erythropoiesis stimulating agents (ESAs),
                  granulocyte colony stimulating factor (GCSF), thrombopoeitin (TPO) mimetics

               2. Chronic systemic antineoplastic or immunomodulatory treatment including
                  supraphysiologic doses of immunosuppressants such as corticosteroids (e.g.,
                  prednisone equivalent &gt;10 mg/day for &gt;2 weeks), azathioprine or monoclonal
                  antibodies (e.g., infliximab)

               3. Investigational agents or devices for any indication

          5. Hyperlipidemia (defined as an LDL≥190 mg/dL), that is not being treating with 2018
             ACC/AHA Cholesterol Clinical Practice guidelines (statins, Ezetimibe, PCSK0
             inhibitors), since these therapy would be the standard of care for these patients.,
             Patients with hyperlipidemia who are deemed ineligible to be on statin therapy by a
             treating physician will not be excluded.

          6. Known history of cardiac arrhythmia or baseline ECG with arrhythmia including but not
             limited to atrial fibrillation (with or without rapid ventricular rate),
             supraventricular tachycardia or ventricular tachycardia.

          7. Any medical, psychiatric, social condition, occupational reason or other
             responsibility that, in the judgment of the investigator, is a contraindication to
             protocol participation or impairs a volunteer's ability to give informed consent.

             Female-specific criteria:

          8. Woman who is breast-feeding or planning to become pregnant during the first 24 weeks
             after study drug administration.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>50 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Shyamasundaran Kottilil, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Institute of Human Virology, University of Maryland Baltimore</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Poonam Mathur, DO, MPH</last_name>
    <phone>(410) 706-4745</phone>
    <email>pmathur@ihv.umaryland.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Institute of Human Virology, University of Maryland Baltimore</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21201</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Poonam Mathur, DO, MPH</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tian RR, Zhang MX, Zhang LT, Zhang P, Ma JP, Liu M, Devenport M, Zheng P, Zhang XL, Lian XD, Ye M, Zheng HY, Pang W, Zhang GH, Zhang LG, Liu Y, Zheng YT. CD24 and Fc fusion protein protects SIVmac239-infected Chinese rhesus macaque against progression to AIDS. Antiviral Res. 2018 Sep;157:9-17. doi: 10.1016/j.antiviral.2018.07.004. Epub 2018 Jul 3.</citation>
    <PMID>29983395</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tian RR, Zhang MX, Liu M, Fang X, Li D, Zhang L, Zheng P, Zheng YT, Liu Y. CD24Fc protects against viral pneumonia in simian immunodeficiency virus-infected Chinese rhesus monkeys. Cell Mol Immunol. 2020 May 7. doi: 10.1038/s41423-020-0452-5. [Epub ahead of print]</citation>
    <PMID>32382131</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 15, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 20, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 23, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 26, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 26, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 28, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>HIV Dyslipidemias</keyword>
  <keyword>CD24Fc</keyword>
  <keyword>HIV Chronic Inflammation</keyword>
  <keyword>LDL Reduction</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Dyslipidemias</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Inflammation</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

