<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04217278</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>RG_17-234</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04217278</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Trial of Treatments to Assess the Effects on Outcome of Adults With AML and MDS Undergoing Allogeneic SCT</brief_title>
  <acronym>COSI</acronym>
  <official_title>An International Randomised Clinical Trial of Therapeutic Interventions With the Potential to Improve Outcome in Adults With Acute Myeloid Leukaemia and High Risk Myelodysplasia Undergoing Allogeneic Stem Cell Transplantation</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Birmingham</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Birmingham</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Treatment options for older adults with Acute Myeloid Leukaemia (AML) and Myelodysplasia
      (MDS) are limited. Although stem cell transplantation remains one of the most effective
      treatments it is associated with severe side effects which have until recently prevented its
      use in older adults. In the last decade the use of reduced intensity transplants has allowed
      the extension of the potentially curative effect of transplantation to older patients in whom
      it was previously precluded. Although a major advance such transplants are associated with a
      high risk of disease relapse particularly in patients with high risk disease.

      This study will evaluate new transplant strategies with the aim of improving the outcome of
      patients with AML and high risk MDS after stem cell transplantation. Three approaches to
      improve transplant outcome will be studied:

        1. Comparing the new pre-transplant consolidation therapy vyxeos with the standard
           consolidation therapy

        2. Comparing new conditioning therapies in patients under the age of 55 years

        3. Comparing new conditioning therapies in patients aged 55 and over

      All patients will be followed up for a minimum of 2 years.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a randomised, international, phase II/III, multicentre, clinical trial in patients
      with AML and MDS undergoing allo-SCT. Patients with AML or MDS who fulfil the eligibility
      criteria will be invited to participate in the trial across centers performing allo-SCT.

      Patients will be randomised to treatment based on a minimisation algorithm prepared at the
      Cancer Research UK Clinical Trials Unit (CRCTU).

      Randomisation 1 (R1) will compare the novel consolidation therapy vyxeos with the standard
      consolidation therapy intermediate dose cytarabine.

      Randomisation 2 (R2) will compare the novel conditioning regimen
      thiotepa/busulphan/fludarabine (TBF) with the standard conditioning therapy
      fludarabine/busulphan (FB4) in patients aged under 55 years of age.

      Randomisation 3 (R3) will compare the novel conditioning regimen mini
      thiotepa/busulphan/fludarabine (mini TBF) with the standard regimen fludarabine/busulphan
      (FB2) in patients aged 55 years of age and over.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 27, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2026</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2024</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival (all randomisations)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Defined as time from entering the relevant randomisations until death from any cause. Patients who are alive at the end of the trial will be censored at their date last seen.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in MRD status - R1 only</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed at baseline and pre-transplant</time_frame>
    <description>Change in minimal residual disease status. A patient will be categorised as either MRD status reduction (MRD positive to negative), MRD remain negative, MRD remain positive or MRD progression (MRD negative to positive) - Randomisation 1 only</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Disease-free survival</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of randomisation through to study completion, an average of 6 years</time_frame>
    <description>DFS defined as time from randomisation to the relevant question to the first of relapse or death from any cause. Patients who are alive and disease free at the end of the trial will be censored at their date known to be alive</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cumulative incidence of disease relapse</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of randomisation through to study completion, an average of 6 years</time_frame>
    <description>CIR defined as time from randomisation to the relevant question to the date of relapse. Patients who die prior to relapse will be treated as a competing risk and patients who are alive and relapse free at the end of the trial will be censored at their date last seen</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Non-relapse mortality</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of randomisation through to study completion, an average of 6 years</time_frame>
    <description>NRM defined as the time from randomisation to the relevant question to date of non-relapse death. Patients who die post-relapse will be treated as a competing risk and patients who are alive at the end of the trial will be censored at their date last seen.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of Life measured by EORTC-QLQ-C30 questionnaires, recorded at multiple timepoints - R2 and R3 only</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed at pre transplant, day 28 and months 3, 6, 9, 12, 18 and 24</time_frame>
    <description>The EORTC QLQ-C30 uses for the questions 1 to 28 a 4-point scale. The scale scores from 1 to 4 (&quot;Not at all&quot; to &quot;Very much&quot;). For the raw score, less points are considered to have a better outcome. For the questions 29 and 30 it uses a 7-points scale. The scale scores from 1 to 7 (&quot;very poor&quot; to &quot;excellent&quot;). More points are considered to have a better outcome.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of Life measured by EQ-5D questionnaires, recorded at multiple timepoints - R2 and R3 only</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed at pre transplant, day 28 and months 3, 6, 9, 12, 18 and 24</time_frame>
    <description>EQ5D is one of the most widely used health states descriptive system. EQ-5D questionnaires have 5 dimensions: &quot;Mobility&quot;, &quot;Human Autonomy,&quot; &quot;Current Activities&quot;, &quot;Pain / Discomfort&quot;, &quot;Anxiety / Depression&quot; and all dimensions are described by 3 problem levels corresponding to patient response choices. A quality of life score is obtained according to the answers to the questionnaires.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of acute and chronic Graft versus Host Disease - R2 and R3 only</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of randomisation through to study completion, an average of 6 years</time_frame>
    <description>Incidence of acute and chronic GvHD of any grade - Randomisation 2 and 3 only</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of primary graft failure - R2 and R3 only</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of randomisation through to study completion, an average of 6 years</time_frame>
    <description>Defined as loss of donor cells after transplantation - Randomisation 2 and 3 only</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Toxicity reported as per CTCAE V4.0</measure>
    <time_frame>From start of treatment until 28 days after last dose of treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Defined as the number of patients who report one or more adverse event of grade 3 or higher or a serious adverse event of any grade</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>6</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">760</enrollment>
  <condition>Acute Myeloid Leukaemia</condition>
  <condition>Myelodysplasia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>R1: Intermediate dose Cytarabine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>First Randomisation - control arm: Intermediate dose Cytarabine (1g/m^2 administered by intravenous infusion over 2 hours on days 1-5 inclusive)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>R1: Vyxeos</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>First Randomisation - experimental arm: Vyxeos (29mg/65mg/m^2 administered by intravenous infusion over 90 minutes on days 1 and 3)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>R2: FB4</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Second Randomisation - under 55 years - control arm: Fludarabine (40mg/m^2 days -7, -6, -5, and -4), Busulphan (3.2mg/kg days -7, -6, -5 and -4)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>R2: TBF</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Second Randomisation - under 55 years - experimental arm: Thiotepa (5mg/kg day -7 and -6), Busulphan (3.2mg/kg days -5, -4 and -3), Fludarabine (50mg/m^2 days -5, -4 and -3)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>R3: FB2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Third Randomisation - 55 years and over - control arm: Fludarabine (30mg/m^2 days -6, -5, -4, -3 and -2), Busulphan (3.2mg/kg days -6 and -5)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Mini-TBF</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Third Randomisation - 55 years and over - experimental arm: Thiotepa (5mg/kg day -6), Busulphan (3.2mg/kg days -5 and -4), Fludarabine (50mg/m^2 days -5, -4, and -3)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Vyxeos</intervention_name>
    <description>Vyxeos administered by intravenous infusion</description>
    <arm_group_label>R1: Vyxeos</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>CPX-351</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Fludarabine</intervention_name>
    <description>Fludarabine administered by intravenous infusion</description>
    <arm_group_label>Mini-TBF</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>R2: FB4</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>R2: TBF</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>R3: FB2</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Fludara</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Busulphan</intervention_name>
    <description>Busulphan administered by intravenous infusion</description>
    <arm_group_label>Mini-TBF</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>R2: FB4</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>R2: TBF</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>R3: FB2</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Busulfan</other_name>
    <other_name>Bulsivex</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Thiotepa</intervention_name>
    <description>Thiotepa administered by intravenous infusion</description>
    <arm_group_label>Mini-TBF</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>R2: TBF</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Tepadina</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cytarabine</intervention_name>
    <description>Cytarabine administered by intravenous infusion</description>
    <arm_group_label>R1: Intermediate dose Cytarabine</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Ara-C</other_name>
    <other_name>Cytosine arabinoside</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Eligibility Criteria for Randomisation 1 Inclusion Criteria for Randomisation 1

          1. Patients (≥ 18 years old) with a morphological documented diagnosis of AML or MDS who
             are deemed fit for allo-SCT with one of the following disease characteristics:

             AML

             o Patients in 1st complete remission (CR1) defined as &lt; 5% blasts

               -  Patients in 2nd complete remission (CR2) defined as &lt; 5% blasts

               -  Secondary AML (defined as previous history of MDS, antecedent haematological
                  disease or chemotherapy exposure) in CR1 or 2 defined as &lt; 5% blasts MDS

               -  Patients with advanced or high risk MDS with an IPSS-R of ≥3.5 (intermediate 3.5
                  or higher)

          2. Patients with an identified HLA identical sibling or suitable matched unrelated donor
             (suitable match defined as no greater than a single allele mismatch at HLA-A, -B, -C
             or DRβ1)

          3. Patients must be considered suitable/fit to undergo allo-SCT as clinically judged by
             the Local Investigator

          4. Females of and male patients of reproductive potential (i.e., not post-menopausal or
             surgically sterilised) must use appropriate, highly effective, contraception from the
             point of commencing therapy until 6 months after treatment

          5. Patients have given written informed consent

          6. Patients willing and able to comply with scheduled study visits and laboratory tests
             Exclusion Criteria for Randomisation 1

          1. Patients with contraindications to receiving allo-SCT

          2. Patients who have already received Vyxeos in their most recent treatment schedule

          3. Female patients who are pregnant or breastfeeding. All women of childbearing potential
             must have a negative pregnancy test before commencing treatment

          4. Adults of reproductive potential not willing to use appropriate, highly effective,
             contraception during the specified period

          5. Patients with renal or hepatic impairment as clinically judged by the Local
             Investigator

          6. Patients with active infection, HIV-positive or chronic active HBV or HCV.

          7. Patients with a prior malignancy, except lobular breast carcinoma in situ, fully
             resected basal cell or squamous cell carcinoma of skin or treated cervical carcinoma
             in situ. Cancer treated with curative intent ≥ 5 years previously will be allowed.
             Cancer treated with curative intent &lt; 5 years previously will not be allowed

          8. History of serious hypersensitivity reaction to cytarabine, daunorubicin, or any
             component of the Vyxeos formulation.

          9. Known history of Wilson's disease or other copper-related metabolic disorder since
             copper gluconate is a component of the Vyxeos formulation

        Eligibility Criteria for Randomisation 2 Inclusion Criteria for Randomisation 2

          1. Patients aged between 18 - 54 years with a morphological documented diagnosis of AML
             or MDS who are deemed fit for a MAC allo-SCT with one of the following disease
             characteristics: AML

               -  Patients in 1st complete remission (CR1) defined as &lt; 5% blasts

               -  Patients in 2nd complete remission (CR2) defined as &lt; 5% blasts

               -  Secondary AML (defined as previous history of MDS, antecedent haematological
                  disease or chemotherapy exposure) in CR1 or 2 defined as &lt; 5% blasts

               -  Must have received at least two courses of prior intensive chemotherapy prior to
                  transplant unless there are exceptional circumstances MDS

               -  Patients with advanced or high risk MDS (with an IPSS-R of ≥3.5 (intermediate 3.5
                  or higher) who have &lt; 10% blasts at the time of randomisation following intensive
                  chemotherapy (including R1 randomisation) or hypomethylating agents if necessary

          2. Patients with an identified HLA identical sibling or suitable matched unrelated donor
             (suitable match defined as no greater than a single allele mismatch at HLA-A, -B, -C
             or DRβ1)

          3. Patients with an ECOG performance status of 0, 1 or 2

          4. Patients considered suitable/fit to undergo a MAC allo-SCT as clinically judged by the
             Local Investigator including:

               1. Adequate hepatic and renal function as determined by full blood count and
                  biochemistry assessment

               2. Resolution of any toxic effects of prior therapy (including radiotherapy,
                  chemotherapy or surgical procedures)

               3. Performance of cardiac or pulmonary function tests (where there is a previous
                  history of cardiac or pulmonary impairment)

          5. Females of and male patients of reproductive potential (i.e., not post-menopausal or
             surgically sterilised) must use appropriate, highly effective, contraception from the
             point of commencing therapy until 12 months after treatment

          6. Patients have given written informed consent

          7. Patients willing and able to comply with scheduled study visits and laboratory tests
             Exclusion Criteria for Randomisation 2

        1. Patients with contraindications to receiving a MAC allo-SCT 2. Female patients who are
        pregnant or breastfeeding. All women of childbearing potential must have a negative
        pregnancy test before commencing treatment 3. Adults of reproductive potential not willing
        to use appropriate, effective, contraception during the specified period 4. Patients with
        renal or hepatic impairment as clinically judged by the Local Investigator 5. Patients with
        active infection, HIV-positive or chronic active HBV or HCV 6. Patients with a prior
        malignancy, except lobular breast carcinoma in situ, fully resected basal cell or squamous
        cell carcinoma of skin or treated cervical carcinoma in situ. Cancer treated with curative
        intent ≥ 5 years previously will be allowed. Cancer treated with curative intent &lt; 5 years
        previously will not be allowed.

        Eligibility Criteria for Randomisation 3 Inclusion Criteria for Randomisation 3

          1. Patients aged between 55 years or older with a morphological documented diagnosis of
             AML or MDS who are deemed fit for a RIC allo-SCT with one of the following disease
             characteristics:

             AML o Patients in 1st complete remission (CR1) defined as &lt; 5% blasts

             o Patients in 2nd complete remission (CR2) defined as &lt; 5% blasts

             o Secondary AML (defined as previous history of MDS, antecedent haematological disease
             or chemotherapy exposure) in CR1 or 2 defined as &lt; 5% blasts

             o Must have received at least two courses of prior intensive chemotherapy prior to
             transplant unless there are exceptional circumstances MDS

               -  Patients with advanced or high risk MDS (with an IPSS-R of ≥3.5 (intermediate 3.5
                  or higher) who have &lt; 10% blasts at the time of randomisation following intensive
                  chemotherapy (including R1 randomisation) or hypomethylating agents if necessary

          2. Patients with an identified HLA identical sibling or suitable matched unrelated donor
             (suitable match defined as no greater than a single allele mismatch at HLA-A, -B, -C
             or DRβ1)

          3. Patients with an ECOG performance status of 0, 1 or 2

          4. Patients considered suitable/fit to undergo a RIC allo-SCT as clinically judged by the
             Local Investigator including:

               1. Adequate hepatic and renal function as determined by full blood count and
                  biochemistry assessment

               2. Resolution of any toxic effects of prior therapy (including radiotherapy,
                  chemotherapy or surgical procedures)

               3. Performance of cardiac or pulmonary function tests (where there is a previous
                  history of cardiac or pulmonary impairment

          5. Females of and male patients of reproductive potential (i.e., not post-menopausal or
             surgically sterilised) must use appropriate, highly effective, contraception from the
             point of commencing therapy until 12 months after treatment

          6. Patients have given written informed consent

          7. Patients willing and able to comply with scheduled study visits and laboratory tests
             Exclusion Criteria for Randomisation 3

        1. Patients with contraindications to receiving a RIC allo-SCT 2. Female patients who are
        pregnant or breastfeeding. All women of childbearing potential must have a negative
        pregnancy test before commencing treatment 3. Adults of reproductive potential not willing
        to use appropriate, effective, contraception during the specified period 4. Patients with
        renal or hepatic impairment as clinically judged by the Local Investigator 5. Patients with
        active infection, HIV-positive or chronic active HBV or HCV 6. Patients with a prior
        malignancies, except lobular breast carcinoma in situ, fully resected basal cell or
        squamous cell carcinoma of skin or treated cervical carcinoma in situ. Cancer treated with
        curative intent ≥ 5 years previously will be allowed. Cancer treated with curative intent &lt;
        5 years previously will not be allowed.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Charles Craddock</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University Hospitals Birmingham NHS Foundation Trust</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Eszter Nagy</last_name>
    <phone>00442123717858</phone>
    <email>COSI@trials.bham.ac.uk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Queen Elizabeth Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Birmingham</city>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Charles Craddock</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 20, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 2, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 3, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 23, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 23, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 24, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Leukemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Myeloid</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Myeloid, Acute</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Preleukemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myelodysplastic Syndromes</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cytarabine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fludarabine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Busulfan</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Thiotepa</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

