<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04219644</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>SCH-15-048</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04219644</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluation of the &quot;Breatheasy&quot; in Pre-hospital Care</brief_title>
  <official_title>Evaluation and Validation of the &quot;Breatheasy&quot; Respiratory Rate Monitor in Pre-hospital Care</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Sheffield Children's NHS Foundation Trust</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Sheffield Children's NHS Foundation Trust</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      In the emergency department, a sick child is usually seen first by the nursing staff. Their
      job is to quickly assess how sick the child is and what immediate care is needed. The nurse
      will usually use suitable devices to check vital signs, such as body temperature, pulse rate
      and blood oxygen levels. However, normally the respiratory rate has to be manually counted
      (this is the average number of breaths taken each minute) because there is no suitable device
      which can automatically do this assessment. To overcome this problem we have produced a
      noncontact device that can automatically measure respiratory rate in children. The device has
      been designed using the latest technology and works by directly sensing the air coming from
      the nose or the mouth when held at about 20 cm from the face. It has been tested on adults
      and children and compared to the usual methods of measuring respiratory rate. We have used
      comments and Suggestions from members of the public and healthcare professionals from
      hospital, general practice and the ambulance service to help us develop the device. With this
      study, we explore the applicability and usefulness of the device in a range of difference
      clinical and nonclinical settings. Its performance will be carefully evaluated on children
      and adults in children's nurseries, schools, university, hospital emergency departments,
      general practice surgeries and ambulances. In the future, when using the device nursing staff
      will easily be able to measure each child's respiratory rate so that the most seriously ill
      children will be identified earlier and get correct treatment more quickly. This will ensure
      that the right children get admitted to intensive care units sooner and, in some cases,
      deaths will be prevented.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">September 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Respiratory rate using the prototype device</measure>
    <time_frame>5 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>In the future, when using the device nursing staff will easily be able to measure each child's respiratory rate so that the most seriously ill children will be identified earlier and get correct treatment more quickly.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">78</enrollment>
  <condition>Respiratory</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Breathing test or sleep study</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>To evaluate the usability of the device in non-clinical and clinical settings</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Breatheasy device</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Breathing test or sleep study</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        - Any adult or child within each setting, of any age with any clinical condition, as this
        will reflect clinical practice.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients deemed too unwell to consent to the procedures or requiring emergency
             treatment will not be approached.

          -  For the purposes of this feasibility study, families whose first language is not
             English will be excluded, to save translation and interpretation costs.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <verification_date>January 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 15, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 3, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 7, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 3, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 3, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 7, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

