<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04215094</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>SouthernMUC1</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04215094</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Early Diagnosis of Intracranial Infection After Craniotomy</brief_title>
  <official_title>Role of Postoperative Fever, Serum Procalcitonin, C-reactive Protein and White Blood Cell Count in the Diagnosis of Intracranial Infection After Craniotomy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Pan Jun</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Southern Medical University, China</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Intracranial infection are serious complications postoperatively in neurosurgical patients.
      Early identification of these complications is essential to minimize the mortality and
      moribidy. The aim of this study is observe the postoperative dynamic changes of body
      temperature (BT), procalcitonin (PCT), C-reactive protein (CRP), and white blood cell (WBC)
      count, and evaluate whether the use of two or more of these markers may improve the
      diagnostic accuracy of intracranial infection.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Intracranial infection is a serious complications after neurosurgical operation. Early
      identification of intracranial infection is important so that, first, optimal treatment is
      initiated which may improves outcome, second, inappropriate antibiotic treatment and
      subsequent resistance are prevented, and third, it will promote shorter hospitalization and
      less cost. In several previous studies, the values of procalcitonin (PCT) and C-reactive
      protein (CRP) in predicting intracranial infection have been evaluated in neurosurgical
      patients. However, due to the limited number of studies, the results are not convincing
      enough and more investigations seems warranted to clarify their dynamic changes in
      neurosurgical patients without intracranial infection and their role in confirming the
      suspicion of intracranial infection or excluding intracranial infection from the differential
      diagnosis.

      The aim of the investigator's study is to observe the postoperative dynamic changes of BT,
      PCT, CRP, and white blood cell (WBC) count, and evaluate whether the use of two or more of
      these markers may improve the diagnostic accuracy for rational decisions about antibiotic
      treatment.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 12, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 1, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 12, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Control</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>the diagnosis of intracranial infection after craniotomy</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 100 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Intracranial infection are serious complications postoperatively in neurosurgical patients. Early identification of these complications is essential to minimize the mortality and moribidy. The aim of this study is observe the postoperative dynamic changes of body temperature (BT), procalcitonin (PCT), C-reactive protein (CRP), and white blood cell (WBC) count, and evaluate whether the use of two or more of these markers may improve the diagnostic accuracy of intracranial infection</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">500</enrollment>
  <condition>Intracranial; Infection, Psychosis, Acute or Subacute</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>infected group</arm_group_label>
    <description>Intracranial infection were diagnosed according to the Centers for Disease Control (CDC) definitions</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>non-infected group</arm_group_label>
    <description>the postoperative recovery was uneventful with no infection</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>postoperative fever, serum procalcitonin, C-reactive protein and white blood cell coun</intervention_name>
    <description>All patients in Intracranial Infection group were cured with antibiotic treatment</description>
    <arm_group_label>infected group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>non-infected group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Postoperative intracranial infection is one of the most serious complications after
        neurosurgery. At present, there is no prospective study or recognized effective method for
        its early diagnosis. It is of great significance for a study about early diagnosis of
        postoperative intracranial infection,

        In this study, the best diagnostic points of ROC curve will be constructed based on two
        statistical principles through retrospective study, and then the diagnostic value will be
        determined through prospective multicenter randomized controlled study. In the research, we
        will establish quality control system, risk control system and dynamic design to ensure the
        safety of research subjects and the quality of research results.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. craniotomy of brain tumor;

          2. no clinical manifestations of infection before operation;

          3. no other infection such as respiratory tract infection, urinary tract infection and
             deep vein catheter infection before the definite diagnosis of intracranial infection ;

          4. the patients had informed consent to enter the study.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. blood system diseases,respiratory tract infection, urinary tract infection and deep
             vein catheter infection;

          2. malignant tumors with neuroendocrine characteristicsr;

          3. aspiration, pancreatitis, etc.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>68 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Xi'an Zhang, doctor</last_name>
    <phone>+86-020-61641815</phone>
    <email>48831443@qq.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Junxiang Peng, doctor</last_name>
    <phone>+86-020-616418006</phone>
    <email>pjxlaozong@126.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Neurosurgery department, Nanfang hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Guangzhou</city>
        <state>Guangdong</state>
        <zip>510515</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>xi'an Zhang, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <email>48831443@qq.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Junxiang Peng, MD,PHD</last_name>
      <email>pjxlaozong@126.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sughrue ME, Bonney PA, Choi L, Teo C. Early Discharge After Surgery for Intra-Axial Brain Tumors. World Neurosurg. 2015 Aug;84(2):505-10. doi: 10.1016/j.wneu.2015.04.019. Epub 2015 Apr 17.</citation>
    <PMID>25892244</PMID>
  </reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Dubey A, Sung WS, Shaya M, Patwardhan R, Willis B, Smith D, Nanda A. Complications of posterior cranial fossa surgery--an institutional experience of 500 patients. Surg Neurol. 2009 Oct;72(4):369-75. doi: 10.1016/j.surneu.2009.04.001. Epub 2009 Jul 14.</citation>
    <PMID>19604553</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Chidambaram S, Nair MN, Krishnan SS, Cai L, Gu W, Vasudevan MC. Postoperative Central Nervous System Infection After Neurosurgery in a Modernized, Resource-Limited Tertiary Neurosurgical Center in South Asia. World Neurosurg. 2015 Dec;84(6):1668-73. doi: 10.1016/j.wneu.2015.07.006. Epub 2015 Jul 11.</citation>
    <PMID>26171888</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 28, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 5, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 9, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 17, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 17, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 19, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Southern Medical University, China</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Pan Jun</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>PHD, MD</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Procalcitonin</keyword>
  <keyword>C-reactive protein</keyword>
  <keyword>white blood cell count</keyword>
  <keyword>intracranial infection</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Infection</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Communicable Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

