<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04217837</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>44-50011-000</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04217837</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Treatment of Major Depressive Disorder in the UK Using TMS Therapy</brief_title>
  <official_title>Neurostar Transcranial Magnetic Stimulation (TMS) Advanced Therapy System: Data Management, Analysis, and Reporting Format for Clinical Treatment Utilization and Outcomes in the UK</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Neuronetics</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Neuronetics</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>Yes</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The major objective of this observational study is to describe clinical outcomes of patients
      in the UK receiving treatment with the NeuroStar TMS Therapy system in routine clinical
      practice.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a single-center, naturalistic, observational study following the use of the
      NeuroStar® Advanced Therapy System and assessment of clinical outcome. The goal is to
      collect, analyze and report information as aggregated summaries on participants receiving
      treatment with the NeuroStar® Advanced Therapy System.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">March 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical Global Impression - Severity Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 6 weeks, 3, 6, 9, and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>The change from baseline to endpoint on the total score for the Clinical Global Impression - Severity scale will be reported for the 6 week 3, 6, 9, and 12 month time points. The 7-point scale requires the clinician to rate the severity of the patient's illness at the time of assessment, relative to the clinician's past experience with patients who have the same diagnosis. The scale ranges from 1-7, where a higher score means a worse outcome.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient Health Questionnaire - 9-item Self Report</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 6 weeks, 3, 6, 9, and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>The change from baseline to endpoint on the total score for the PHQ-9 will be reported for the 6 week, 3, 6, 9, and 12 month time points. The questionnaire assesses degree of depression severity. The scale ranges from total scores of 1-27, where a higher score means a worse outcome.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Inventory of Depressive Symptomatology - Self Report (IDS-SR)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 6 weeks, 3, 6, 9, and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>The change from baseline to endpoint on the total score for the Inventory of Depressive Symptomatology - Self Report will be reported for the 6 week, 3, 6, 9, and 12 month time points. It is a tool designed to screen for depression and measure changes in severity of symptoms. The scale ranges from total score ranges of 0-84, where a higher score means a worse outcome.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>EuroQol 5 Dimensions</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 6 weeks, 3, 6, 9, and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>The change from baseline to endpoint on the total score for the EuroQol 5 Dimensions will be reported for the 6 week, 3, 6, 9, and 12 month time points. The EuroQol 5 Dimensions questionnaire assesses quality of life and is presented as a health profile.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Health Resource Utilization Questionnaire (HRU)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 6 weeks, 3, 6, 9, and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>The change from baseline in health care service utilization reported on the individual questions contained in the HRU will be reported for the 6 week, 3, 6, 9, and 12 month time points. It is a socioeconomic and quality of life questionnaire. Because changes in individual questions are reported, there is no range of scores. The score ranges from 0-100, where a higher score means a better outcome.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Short Form 36-item Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 6 weeks, 3, 6, 9, and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>The change from baseline to endpoint on the Individual Factor Scores and General Medical and Mental Health Composite Scores for the SF-36 will be reported for the 6 week, 3, 6, 9, and 12 month time points. The Short Form 36-item Questionnaire evaluates quality of life outcomes.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Major Depressive Disorder</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Major Depressive Disorder</arm_group_label>
    <description>Participants who meet the DSM-5 clinical diagnostic criteria, in the opinion of the treating clinician, for primary diagnosis of unipolar, non-psychotic MDD.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Transcranial Magnetic Stimulator</intervention_name>
    <description>Transcranial magnetic stimulation (TMS) uses a targeted pulsed magnetic field, similar to what is used in an MRI (magnetic resonance imaging) machine. While the patient is awake and alert, NeuroStar TMS Therapy stimulates areas of the brain that are underactive in depression.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Major Depressive Disorder</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>TMS Therapy</other_name>
    <other_name>Neurostar</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Clinical Practice
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Men or women, age 22 - 70, out-patient

          2. Participants who meet the DSM-5 clinical diagnostic criteria, in the opinion of the
             treating clinician, for primary diagnosis of unipolar, non-psychotic MDD. The intended
             treatment plan uses the labeled treatment parameters for TMS as described in the
             NeuroStar® System

          3. Women of child bearing potential must be using a medically accepted reliable means of
             contraception (for oral contraceptive medication: must be in use for at least 3
             months)

          4. Women of childbearing potential must have a negative pregnancy test at screening using
             urine dipstick

          5. Participants must have the capacity to consent to all tests and examinations required
             by the protocol and must sign a written informed consent document to participate in
             the study.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. History of seizures or increased risk of seizure for any reason, including prior
             diagnosis of increased intracranial pressure or history of significant head trauma
             with loss of consciousness for ≥ 5 minutes

          2. Inability to locate and quantify a motor threshold as defined in the protocol

          3. Conductive, ferromagnetic, or other magnetic-sensitive metals implanted in the
             participant's head within 30 cm of the treatment coil excluding the mouth that cannot
             safely be removed. Examples include: cochlear implants; implanted
             electrodes/stimulators; aneurysm clips or coils; stents; bullet fragments; jewelry;
             and hair barrettes

          4. Any psychiatric disorder which, in the judgement of the Investigator, may hinder the
             participant from completing the procedures required by the study protocol

          5. Active or inactive implants (including device leads), including deep brain
             stimulators, and vagus nerve stimulators

          6. Cardiac pacemakers, implanted medication pumps, intracardiac lines, or acute, unstable
             cardiac disease

          7. Known or suspected pregnancy
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>22 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mohamed Abdelghani, MBBCh, MSc, MRCPsych</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>St. Pancras Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Jessica Riggleman, BS</last_name>
    <phone>4843298354</phone>
    <email>jessica.riggleman@neurostar.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Shirley Steiner</last_name>
    <phone>6109814105</phone>
    <email>ssteiner@neurostar.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>St Pancras Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>London</city>
        <zip>NW1 0PE</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Lynis Lewis</last_name>
      <phone>+020 3317 3763</phone>
      <email>lynislewis@nhs.net</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Emmanuel Rollings-Kamara</last_name>
      <phone>+020 3317 3757</phone>
      <email>emmanuelrollings-kamara@nhs.net</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Mohamed Abdelghani, MBBCh, MSc, MRCPsych</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 2, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 2, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 3, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 4, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 4, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 7, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Transcranial Magnetic Stimulation</keyword>
  <keyword>Major Depressive Disorder</keyword>
  <keyword>MDD</keyword>
  <keyword>TMS</keyword>
  <keyword>NeuroStar Advanced Therapy System</keyword>
  <keyword>Repetitive Transcranial Magnetic Stimulation</keyword>
  <keyword>rTMS</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depression</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder, Major</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

