<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04217915</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CMU1h</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04217915</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Survey of Management of Analgesia, Sedation and Delirium in ICU Patients in China</brief_title>
  <acronym>SASE</acronym>
  <official_title>A Survey of Management of Analgesia, Sedation and Delirium in ICU Patients in China</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>China Medical University, China</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>The Second Affiliated Hospital of Kunming Medical University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>The First Affiliated Hospital of Kunming Medical College</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>First Affiliated Hospital of Harbin Medical University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>The First Affiliated Hospital of Dalian Medical University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Peking University People's Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Qilu Hospital of Shandong University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>The Second Affiliated Hospital of Dalian Medical University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>The Second Affiliated Hospital of Harbin Medical University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>First Hospital of Jilin University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>General Hospital of Ningxia Medical University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>China Medical University, China</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      In 2018, the severe medicine branch of the Chinese Medical Association and the American
      Society of severe medicine successively updated the pain and sedation guidelines for severe
      patients (PADIS guidelines). In addition to the update of the original evaluation and
      management of pain and sedation and delirium, the new guidelines also increased the
      monitoring and management of early activities and sleep quality for severe patients.
      Therefore, it is necessary for us to investigate the compliance of the new guidelines for
      analgesia, sedation and delirium management among the medical staff of critical care, so as
      to find out the existing problems in the management of analgesia, sedation and delirium in
      critical care patients, and find solutions to improve the overall quality level of our
      management of critical care patients
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The first part is to master the current situation of analgesia, sedation and delirium
      management of ICU patients in China. In order to understand the compliance of Chinese ICU
      doctors and nurses with the PADIS guidelines, a questionnaire survey was conducted with the
      participation of multiple centers in China, aiming at the doctors and nurses with different
      seniority in the critical medicine department. At the same time, the total number of
      critically ill patients, pain, agitation and delirium assessment tools and critical patients
      in 2018 were investigated The incidence of pain, agitation and delirium, the implementation
      of early activities, the monitoring and evaluation of sleep quality, and related
      interventions, including real-world clinical data such as drug treatment and non drug
      treatment.The second part focuses on the management of severe delirium in ICU in China. For
      the patients with delirium in the above survey, a further in-depth and detailed survey shall
      be conducted, covering the basic diseases of the patients, the occurrence time of delirium,
      the type of delirium, relevant risk factors, the diagnosis method of delirium, the duration
      of delirium, the prevention and treatment measures (including drug treatment and non drug
      treatment measures), and the prognosis of delirium patients .
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">February 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Only</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Compliance of ICU medical staff with PADIS guidelines</measure>
    <time_frame>2020.12</time_frame>
    <description>The assessment tool is a self-designed questionnaire based on the guidelines, which is mainly used to assess the compliance of medical staff with the guidelines in their daily work</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of delirium</measure>
    <time_frame>2020.12</time_frame>
    <description>Incidence of delirium in Chinese ICU patients with analgesia and sedation during the study period</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">800</enrollment>
  <condition>Delirium on Emergence</condition>
  <condition>Analgesia</condition>
  <condition>Separation</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        The patients were randomly selected from the ICU of the A tertiary hospitals in the major
        provinces and cities of China.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age ≥ 18 years old;

          -  stay in ICU for more than 24 hours and have used analgesics and Sedatives.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Before entering the ICU, they had mental illness and dementia;

          -  coma or deep sedation could not be evaluated;

          -  brain injury, stroke sequelae, epilepsy and other brain diseases;

          -  nerious audio-visual dysfunction and unable to communicate normally.

          -  Pregnant and lactating women
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>85 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>xiaochun ma, doctor</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>China Medical University, China</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>xin li, Doctor</last_name>
    <phone>02483283182</phone>
    <email>xuanfeng7890@163.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>zhidan zhang, Doctor</last_name>
    <phone>02483283182</phone>
    <email>zhangzhidan1974@163.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Wang J, Peng ZY, Zhou WH, Hu B, Rao X, Li JG. A National Multicenter Survey on Management of Pain, Agitation, and Delirium in Intensive Care Units in China. Chin Med J (Engl). 2017 May 20;130(10):1182-1188. doi: 10.4103/0366-6999.205852.</citation>
    <PMID>28485318</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Morandi A, Piva S, Ely EW, Myatra SN, Salluh JIF, Amare D, Azoulay E, Bellelli G, Csomos A, Fan E, Fagoni N, Girard TD, Heras La Calle G, Inoue S, Lim CM, Kaps R, Kotfis K, Koh Y, Misango D, Pandharipande PP, Permpikul C, Cheng Tan C, Wang DX, Sharshar T, Shehabi Y, Skrobik Y, Singh JM, Slooter A, Smith M, Tsuruta R, Latronico N. Worldwide Survey of the &quot;Assessing Pain, Both Spontaneous Awakening and Breathing Trials, Choice of Drugs, Delirium Monitoring/Management, Early Exercise/Mobility, and Family Empowerment&quot; (ABCDEF) Bundle. Crit Care Med. 2017 Nov;45(11):e1111-e1122. doi: 10.1097/CCM.0000000000002640.</citation>
    <PMID>28787293</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>January 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>December 30, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 3, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 6, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 5, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 5, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 7, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>China Medical University, China</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Xiaochun Ma,MD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>director of ICUof first hospital of China medical university</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>analgesia</keyword>
  <keyword>sedation</keyword>
  <keyword>ICU</keyword>
  <keyword>Delirium</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Agnosia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Delirium</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Emergence Delirium</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

