<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04214457</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IGX1-MYO-CS-19-03</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04214457</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Development of a Predictive Model for Early Differential Diagnosis of Uterine Leiomyomas and Leiomyosarcomas</brief_title>
  <acronym>MYOSARC</acronym>
  <official_title>Prospective, National and Multicenter Biomedical Study of Cohorts, Aimed at Patients With Surgical Indication of Hysterectomy, Laparoscopic or Laparotomic Myomectomy Due to Diagnosis of Myometrial Tumors (Leiomyoma / Leiomyosarcoma)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Igenomix</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Igenomix</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The development of an accurate and non-invasive diagnostic method is a priority in areas such
      as gynecology and oncology, specifically to improve the health of those patients with
      surgical indication for diagnosis of myometrial tumors: leiomyomas and/or leiomyosarcomas.

      Recently, Next Generation Sequencing (NGS) technology has been successfully applied in
      different areas of knowledge, being effective not only for the detection of DNA mutations,
      but also providing through bioinformatic tools, new insights in the understanding of
      chromosomal instability. In addition, the detection of circulating tumor DNA (ctDNA) through
      this type of techniques could revolutionize the non-invasive detection and monitoring of this
      type of tumors.

      The proposed study aims to perform the differential molecular analysis of myometrial tumor
      tissue (uterine leiomyomas / leiomyosarcomas), as well as peripheral blood of a group of
      patients with surgical indication of hysterectomy, laparoscopic or laparotomic myomectomy by
      diagnosis of myometrial tumors. Thus, the obtained samples will be processed for the
      realization of techniques of massive parallel sequencing or NGS that, together with a
      specialized bioinformatic software, will facilitate the interpretation of the obtained data.

      Combination of both platforms, sequencing and bioinformatics, will offer a high potential for
      the discovery of genetic variants and genomic markers. Depending on the results of these
      analyses, differential diagnosis of leiomyoma and leiomyosarcoma could be determined, in
      addition to increasing knowledge of myometrial biology and associated pathologies in a
      clinical and therapeutic context. Moreover, the application of this technology could allow
      the development of biomarkers and targeted therapies effective in the treatment of uterine
      leiomyomas and/or leiomyosarcomas.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Leiomyomas (LM) are the most common benign gynecological tumors that affect approximately 70%
      of women of reproductive age, being responsible for 200,000 hysterectomies per year in the
      United States (USA). Despite its benign nature, LM represents a major public health problem
      due to its significant level of morbidity, which manifests as a spectrum of clinical symptoms
      such as heavy menstrual bleeding, anemia, pelvic pain, infertility and recurrent pregnancy
      loss, among others.

      Uterine leiomyosarcoma (LMS) is a rare uterine malignancy that arises from the smooth muscle
      of uterine wall. It accounts for only 1-2% of uterine malignancies and occurs mainly after
      menopause. LMS is notorious for its aggressive nature and poor prognosis.

      Although uterine LM and LMS are considered biologically unrelated tumors due to their
      cytogenetic and molecular disparity, both share morphological features that can complicate
      the diagnosis through current clinical tests or factors.

      Nowadays, long-term therapeutic options for LM are limited. Currently, laparoscopic
      morcellation is the most widely used surgical technique in the treatment of large LM.
      However, this type of surgery carries the risk of occult dissemination of malignant tumors
      such as LMS, characterized by early metastases, poor prognosis and high recurrence rates,
      with limited therapeutic efficacy. In fact, the United States Food and Drug Administration
      (FDA) has estimated that 1 in 352 of women with surgical indication of LM could have LMS, and
      treatment in this case could result in tumor spread. Given this need, Igenomix, through a
      recent pilot study with 26 samples, has identified new genetic targets that potentially
      differentiate leiomyosarcomas and leiomyomas, through integrated comparative genomic and
      transcriptomic analyses. This allowed to lay the foundations, not only to improve the
      understanding of the pathogenesis of these uterine tumors, but also provides a first step
      towards the preoperative diagnosis of leiomyomas and leiomyosarcomas by liquid biopsy.

      Based on this pilot study, a new clinical study is proposed to proceed with further
      identification of genetic markers and develop a preoperative diagnosis of LM and LMS by
      liquid biopsy. A total sample size of 1,000 patients with suspected LMS is expected to be
      recruited in this study, considering the frequency of surgeries in which obtaining a sample
      is intended, as well as the frequency of patients who will accept tissue donation for
      research. Moreover, a cut-off point with a preliminary analysis every 100 patients will be
      established, in which the laboratory data is combined with those derived from the
      Pathological Anatomy (Gold Standard), so that when a total of 40 LMS is reached the study
      will end.

      During the development of the study, after obtaining informed consent from eligible patients,
      the samples (tumor tissue and peripheral blood) will be collected at the time of surgery,
      which the patient had already planned by medical indication according to the usual clinical
      practice. Thus, the participation of the subject in this study will entail only a single
      visit coinciding with the day of the surgery. In addition, samples available from patients
      that underwent surgery before the study could be also included if, after being duly informed,
      the patient agrees to participate in the study and signs the study consent form.
      Exceptionally, samples from patients who could not consent due to major reasons (such as
      death of the subject or impossibility to be found) could also be included in the study upon
      approval of the appropriated Ethic Committee according to the local regulations for this type
      of situations. In any case, the investigators will ensure that there is no expressed
      objection from the donors in their clinical history and that samples will be codified in
      order to assure anonymity.

      Samples will be sent to histopathological diagnosis and to Igenomix, that will develop and
      optimize laboratory protocols to detect changes at the DNA (Whole Exome Sequencing) and RNA
      (RNAseq) level in order to achieve the described outcomes. This new approaches focused on
      NGS, could allow not only the detection of tumor-specific mutations but, in combination with
      bioinformatics tools, could provide new knowledge to understand chromosomal instability in
      the tumors.

      According to the histopathological diagnosis, patients will be treated by their respective
      doctors and followed up to determine their evolution. If the proposed hypothesis from NGS
      results is confirmed and the objectives are achieved, in a second phase of the project, a
      diagnostic tool will be developed to extend the non-invasive genetic diagnosis of uterine
      leiomyomas and leiomyosarcomas in peripheral blood through the free DNA analysis of
      circulating tumor cells. The possibility of being able to quantify and characterize the
      circulating tumor DNA (ctDNA) by means of this type of techniques, could revolutionize the
      non-invasive detection and the follow-up of this type of tumors.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 20, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Identification of specific genetic markers for leiomyomas and leiomyosarcomas</measure>
    <time_frame>36 months</time_frame>
    <description>Identification of genetic markers that allow the classification of myometrial tumors into leiomyomas and leiomyosarcomas by NGS.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Characterization of cell populations of uterine leiomyomas and leiomyosarcomas</measure>
    <time_frame>36 months</time_frame>
    <description>Single-cell DNA/RNAseq characterization of the uterine leiomyomas and leiomyosarcomas cell populations in order to assess the heterogeneity in these myometrial tumors.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Identification of methylation patterns characteristic of the tumorigenic process</measure>
    <time_frame>36 months</time_frame>
    <description>Study of methylation patterns that could identify tumorigenic processes</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">1000</enrollment>
  <condition>Leiomyoma</condition>
  <condition>Leiomyosarcoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Myometrial tumor with suspected leiomyosarcoma</arm_group_label>
    <description>Women between 18 and 75 years of age diagnosed with a myometrial tumor (probably leiomyoma) with suspected leiomyosarcoma</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Biopsy and peripheral blood collection</intervention_name>
    <description>After obtaining informed consent, the samples (tumor tissue and peripheral blood) will be collected at the time of surgery, which the patient had already planned by medical indication according to the usual clinical practice. Part of the sample will be sent to histopathology for gold standard diagnosis while the rest of the sample will be sent to Igenomix for molecular analysis.
If samples are available from patients who underwent surgery prior to the study, after they sign the Informed Consent, the samples will be sent to Igenomix for molecular analysis and the results obtained by histopathology will be collected from the patient's medical record.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Myometrial tumor with suspected leiomyosarcoma</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Women between 18 and 75 years of age and BMI between 18-35 kg/m2, diagnosed with a
        myometrial tumor (probably leiomyoma) with suspected leiomyosarcoma, will be evaluated at
        their reference center, verifying that they comply the inclusion / exclusion criteria to
        participate in the study
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients who voluntarily sign the informed consent approved by the research Ethics
             Committee (EC) after having been duly informed of the nature of the study, before
             carrying out any test, knowing the potential risks, benefits and discomforts arising
             from their participation. Participants should be informed that they may leave the
             study at any time, without this implying any consequences for their subsequent medical
             care.

          -  Body Mass Index (BMI) = 18-35 kg/m2

          -  Age = 18-75 years

          -  Surgical indication of hysterectomy, laparoscopic or laparotomic myomectomy by imaging
             diagnosis (ultrasound, resonance, Computerized Tomography Scan ...) of tumor mass in
             the myometrium, whether primary or recurrent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients who have participated in another biomedical study or who have received an
             experimental treatment during the last 30 days, unless approved by the sponsor.

          -  Patients who have received chemotherapy or radiotherapy 6 months before diagnosis (in
             case of recurrence).

          -  Pregnant patients before or during the development of the study.

          -  Existence of serious or uncontrolled bacterial, fungal or viral infections that, in
             the opinion of the principal investigator, may interfere with the patient's
             participation in the study or in the evaluation of the study results.

          -  Any illness or medical condition that is unstable or could endanger the patient's
             safety and compliance in the study.

          -  Psychological, family, sociological or geographical situations that do not allow
             compliance with the protocol or the signing of informed consent.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Carlos Simón, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Igenomix</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Aymara Mas, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Igenomix Foundation</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Carlos Gomez, BSc, MSc</last_name>
    <phone>+34 963905310</phone>
    <email>carlos.gomez@igenomix.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Diana Valbuena, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+34 963905310</phone>
    <email>diana.valbuena@igenomix.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Complejo Hospitalario Universitario de Cartagena</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cartagena</city>
        <state>Murcia</state>
        <zip>30202</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sebastián Ortiz-Reina</last_name>
      <phone>+34 968 12 86 00</phone>
      <email>sortizreina@yahoo.es</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Universitario Virgen de la Arrixaca</name>
      <address>
        <city>El Palmar</city>
        <state>Murcia</state>
        <zip>30120</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Anibal Nieto, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>+34968369500</phone>
      <email>anibal.nieto@um.es</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Universitario y Politécnico La Fe</name>
      <address>
        <city>Valencia</city>
        <zip>46026</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Santiago Domingo Del Pozo, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <email>santiago.domingo@ono.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Javier Monleón Sancho, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <email>monlesancho@gmail.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Spain</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>December 27, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 30, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 2, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 21, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 21, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 26, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Leiomyoma (LM)</keyword>
  <keyword>Leiomyosarcoma (LMS)</keyword>
  <keyword>Next Generation Sequencing (NGS)</keyword>
  <keyword>Circulating tumor DNA (ctDNA)</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Leiomyosarcoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leiomyoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myofibroma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

