<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04219254</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>18-BI-1206-03</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04219254</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study of BI-1206 in Combination With Pembrolizumab in Subjects With Advanced Solid Tumors (KEYNOTE-A04)</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase 1/2a Clinical Trial of BI-1206, a Monoclonal Antibody to CD32b (FcγRIIB), in Combination With Pembrolizumab in Subjects With Advanced Solid Tumors Previously Treated With Anti-PD-1 or Anti-PD-L1 Antibodies (KEYNOTE-A04)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>BioInvent International AB</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>BioInvent International AB</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Phase 1/2a Clinical Trial of BI-1206, a Monoclonal Antibody to CD32b (FcγRIIB), in
      Combination with Pembrolizumab in Subjects with Advanced Solid Tumors Previously Treated with
      Anti-PD-1 or Anti-PD-L1 Antibodies
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a Phase 1/2a, multicenter, dose-finding, consecutive-cohort, open-label trial of
      BI-1206 in combination with pembrolizumab in subjects with advanced solid tumors who have
      previously received treatment with a PD-1/PD-L1 immune checkpoint inhibitor.

      The trial will consist of 2 main parts: Phase 1 (with dose escalation cohorts and selection
      of the RP2D), and Phase 2a (with 3 expansion cohorts at the RP2D).

      Subjects in each phase will initially receive 3 planned doses of therapy with BI-1206 in
      combination with pembrolizumab.

      Subjects who show clinical benefit (CR, PR or SD) at the Week 9 Visit may continue on
      combination therapy. Starting at Week 10, these subjects will receive infusions every 3 weeks
      for up to 32 additional doses or up to 2 years from first dose of BI-1206 therapy or until
      progression.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 29, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2024</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Phase 1/2a, dose escalation, consecutive-cohort, open-label study trial of BI-1206 in combination with pembrolizumab</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
    <masking_description>open label</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Documenting AEs and SAEs and determining causality in relation to BI-1206 and/or pembrolizumab</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2 year</time_frame>
    <description>Assess the safety and tolerability profile of increasing doses of BI-1206 in combination with pembrolizumab, graded according to National Cancer Institute [NCI]-CTCAE version 4.0</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Determining the MTD of BI-1206 at the same dose level experiencing a BI-1206 or pembrolizumab-related or possibly related dose-limiting toxicity (DLT)</measure>
    <time_frame>During the 42-day treatment period on induction therapy</time_frame>
    <description>Select the RP2D dose for BI-1206 using mTPI-2 design.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluation of PK parameters for BI-1206. Maximum observed plasma concentration (Cmax)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2 year</time_frame>
    <description>Study the PK profile of BI-1206 according to a non-compartmental analysis using a validated software</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluation of PK parameters for BI-1206. Area under the plasma concentration-time curve (AUC)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2 year</time_frame>
    <description>Study the PK profile of BI-1206 according to a non-compartmental analysis using a validated software</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluation of ADA response to BI 1206</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2 year</time_frame>
    <description>Assess the immunogenicity of BI-1206. Detection and characterization of antibodies to BI-1206 will be performed using a validated method and will be evaluated for BI-1206 serum concentration to enable interpretation of the antibody data.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Measurement of CD32b receptor occupancy on B cells.</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2 year</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluate the effect of BI-1206 administered in combination with pembrolizumab on CD32b receptor occupancy on B cells in subjects with advanced solid tumors.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Assessment of best disease responses according to Immunological Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors (iRECIST).</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks after first dose BI1206 and every 9 weeks for subjects who continue on therapy</time_frame>
    <description>Initially assess possible anti-tumor activity of BI-1206 administered in combination with pembrolizumab 8 weeks after first dose of BI-1206 (i.e., the Week 9 Visit [including follow-up confirmation for progressive disease (PD)]) in subjects with advanced solid tumors. Anti-tumor activity will also be evaluated every 9 weeks for subjects whocontinue on therapy.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Measurement of progression free survival.</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2 year</time_frame>
    <description>Patients who complete a baseline and at least one post-treatment disease assessment will be evaluable.PFS will be measured from the date of administration of the first dose of BI-1206 to the first date of progression, date of death from any cause, or the last response assessment date, whichever comes first.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Measurement of duration of objective response</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2 year</time_frame>
    <description>Time-to-event estimates will be generated using the Kaplan-Meier method. In the context of this single arm study, these analyses will be only descriptive</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Measurement of objective response rate</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2 year</time_frame>
    <description>ORR is defined as the percentage of subjects who achieved a response of CR or PR. ORR and the associated 2-sided 95% exact confidence limits will be provided</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Measurement of peripheral blood B-lymphocyte depletion.</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2 year</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluate the effect of BI-1206 in combination with pembrolizumab measuring B Lymphocyutes CD19 in absolut value.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Measurement of expression levels of immunological markers such as CD32b, PD-1 in tissue biopsies.</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2 year</time_frame>
    <description>Study expression levels of immunological markers (e.g., CD32b, PD-1) in the tumor and study a potential correlation of levels of expression with clinical responses.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluate BI-1206 and pembrolizumab tumor penetrance in biopsies</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2 year</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluate BI-1206 and pembrolizumab tumor penetrance in biopsies using immunohistochemistry</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Measurement of cytokine levels</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2 year</time_frame>
    <description>Study the potential cause of infusion related reaction (IRR) by measure serum cytokine levels</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Measurement of serum cytokine levels and/or soluble CD32b.</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2 year</time_frame>
    <description>• Study the potential cause of infusion related reaction (IRR), such as cytokine release and/or soluble CD32b</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">90</enrollment>
  <condition>Solid Tumor, Adult</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>BI-1206</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>BI-1206 administrated IV with a starting dose of 1 mg/kg every third week using mTPI2 Design in escalation Phase I. RP2D to be used i Phase IIa.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pembrolizumab 25 MG/ML(MK-3475)</intervention_name>
    <description>Pembrolizumab 200mg administrated IV every third week as a fixed dose will be used in Phase I and IIa</description>
    <arm_group_label>BI-1206</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Is willing and able to provide written informed consent for the trial.

          -  Is ≥18 years of age on day of signing informed consent.

          -  Has a histologically confirmed advanced solid tumor. Subjects must have received at
             least 2 doses of an approved anti-PD-1/L1 mAb, and have documented progression on or
             within 12 weeks from the last dose of anti-PD-1/L1 mAb.

          -  Is intolerant of, refuses, or is not eligible for standard antineoplastic therapy.

          -  Has at least 1 measurable disease lesion as defined by Response Evaluation Criteria in
             Solid Tumors

          -  Is able to safely undergo a baseline tumor tissue biopsy prior to first dose of
             BI-1206

          -  Has a life expectancy of ≥12 weeks.

          -  Has an ECOG performance status of 0-1.

          -  Has adequate organ function as confirmed by laboratory values listed in the main body
             of the protocol

        Expansion Cohort-Specific Inclusion Criteria:

        In addition to the general inclusion criteria above, subjects must also meet the criteria
        for the specific cohort.

          -  Cohort 1 (Non-small cell lung cancer):

               -  For subjects whose tumor has PD-L1 ≥ 50%: Required prior therapies will include
                  anti-PD-1 therapy as monotherapy. Prior standard of care chemotherapy will be
                  allowed but not required.

               -  For tumors with unknown PD-L1 or PD-L1 &lt; 50% , required prior therapies will
                  include anti-PD 1/PD-L1 therapy and SOC chemotherapy either combined with anti
                  PD-1/PD-L1 therapy or given separately.

               -  For subjects with known anaplastic lymphoma kinase, ROS1 or epidermal growth
                  factor receptor sensitizing molecular rearrangements, one line of targeted
                  therapy will be required in addition to anti-PD-1/PD-L1 therapy.

          -  Cohort 2 (Metastatic Melanoma):

               -  Required prior therapies will include anti-PD-1 therapy either as monotherapy or
                  as part of a combination regimen.

               -  For subjects with a known BRAF V600-activating mutation combination targeted
                  therapy will be required in addition to anti-PD-1/PD-L1 therapy.

          -  Cohort 3 (Other Tumor Types):

               -  All subjects will require prior anti-PD-1/PD-L1 therapy

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Needs doses of prednisolone &gt;10 mg daily (or equipotent doses of other
             corticosteroids)

          -  Has known active central nervous system (CNS) metastases and/or carcinomatous
             meningitis.

          -  Has known or suspected hypersensitivity to pembrolizumab or BI-1206 or any of their
             excipients.

          -  Has cardiac or renal amyloid light-chain (AL) amyloidosis.

          -  Has received the following:

               -  Chemotherapy or small molecule products within 4 weeks of first dose of BI 1206.

               -  Radiotherapy within 2 weeks of first dose of BI-1206. A 1-week washout is
                  permitted for palliative radiation (≤2 weeks of radiotherapy) for non-CNS
                  disease. Subjects who have previously had radiation pneumonitis are not allowed.

               -  Immunotherapy within 4 weeks prior to the first dose of BI-1206.

          -  Has not recovered from AEs to at least Grade 1 by Common Terminology Criteria for
             Adverse Events v4.0 due to prior anti-cancer therapies.

          -  Has had Grade ≥3 autoimmune manifestations of previous immune checkpoint inhibitor
             treatments .

          -  Has a history of (non-infectious) pneumonitis that required steroids or has current
             pneumonitis.

          -  Has an active, known or suspected autoimmune disease.

          -  Is a female subject and has the ability to become pregnant (or already pregnant or
             lactating/ breastfeeding). o Intravaginal

          -  Is a male subject with partner(s) of child-bearing potential• Has had major surgery
             from which the subject has not yet recovered.

          -  Is at high medical risk because of non-malignant systemic disease including severe
             active infections on treatment with antibiotics, antifungals or antivirals.

          -  Has presence of chronic graft versus host disease.

          -  Has had an allogenic tissue/solid organ transplant.

          -  Has known human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) and / or history of hepatitis B or C
             infections, or has a positive test for HIV antibody, hepatitis B antigen / hepatitis B
             virus DNA or hepatitis C antibody or RNA.

          -  Has a history of active tuberculosis (bacillus tuberculosis).

          -  Has received a live vaccine within 30 days before the first dose of study treatment.

          -  Has uncontrolled or significant cardiovascular disease

          -  Has a known psychiatric or substance abuse disorder that would interfere with the
             subject's ability to cooperate with the requirements of the study.

          -  Has a history or current evidence of any condition, therapy, or laboratory abnormality
             that might confound the results of the study, interfere with the subject's
             participation for the full duration of the study, or is not in the best interest of
             the subject to participate, in the opinion of the treating investigator.

          -  Is participating or planning to participate in another interventional clinical trial,
             or has participated in a trial of an investigational agent or has used an
             investigational device within 4 weeks prior to first dose of study drug. Subjects who
             have entered the follow-up phase of an investigational study may participate as long
             as it has been 4 weeks after the last dose of the previous investigational agent.
             Participation in an observational trial is acceptable.

          -  Has a known additional malignancy of another type

          -  Has a diagnosis of primary or acquired immunodeficiency disorder or taking any other
             form of immunosuppressive therapy within 7 days prior the first dose of study drug.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Carneiro, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Lund University Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Susanne Gertsson</last_name>
    <phone>+46709 102 267</phone>
    <email>susanne.gertsson@bioinvent.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>McAllister, PhD</last_name>
    <email>andres.mcallister@bioinvent.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sarah Cannon Research Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Denver</city>
        <state>Colorado</state>
        <zip>80218</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Sen, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Karmanos Cancer Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Detroit</city>
        <state>Michigan</state>
        <zip>48201</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Vaishampayan, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>HealthPartners Institute - Regions Cancer Care Center,</name>
      <address>
        <city>Saint Paul</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55101</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Dudek, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Oklahoma University , Stephenson Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Oklahoma City</city>
        <state>Oklahoma</state>
        <zip>73104</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Aljumaily, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>NEXT Oncology</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Antonio</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>78229</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Karim, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sahlgrenska University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Göteborg</city>
        <country>Sweden</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ny, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Lund University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lund</city>
        <country>Sweden</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Carneiro, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Karolinska University Hospital, Solna</name>
      <address>
        <city>Stockholm</city>
        <country>Sweden</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Yachnin, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Sweden</country>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 21, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 3, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 7, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 30, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 30, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 1, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pembrolizumab</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>All information concerning the product as well as any matter concerning the operation of the Sponsor, such as clinical indications for the drug, its formula, methods of manufacture and other scientific data relating to it, that have been provided by the Sponsor and are unpublished, are confidential and must remain the sole property of the Sponsor. The Investigator will agree to use the information only for the purposes of carrying out this studytrial and for no other purpose unless prior written permission from the Sponsor is obtained.</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>Within one year from end of study</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>Paper copy of CSR</ipd_access_criteria>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

