<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04216641</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>69HCL19_0292</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04216641</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Cancer, Nutrition and Taste</brief_title>
  <acronym>CANUT-1</acronym>
  <official_title>Impact of a Food Improvement Strategy on Their Appreciation in a Population of Cancer Patients Treated With Chemotherapy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Hospices Civils de Lyon</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Hospices Civils de Lyon</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Cancer promotes weight loss; it can also lead to particular complications for patients during
      treatment. A team led by Dr Michael Sawyer, showed the deleterious impact of undernutrition
      on the benefits of chemotherapy.

      Cancer patients are at high risk of undernutrition, which is generally more pronounced for
      solid tumours (upper digestive tract, ENT, bronchial tubes…). This undernutrition leads to
      major weight loss and wasting, and may represent the first sign of a call for a diagnosis of
      cancer. Cancer-related undernutrition is multi-factorial in origin and has multiple
      consequences; it has its own prognostic value.

      Chemotherapy treatments can induce various adverse effects in patients, including sensory
      disturbances at the beginning of treatment in addition to disturbances that may already be
      present before any treatment. Altered taste and odour, observed in 86% of patients, can
      induce a change in food preferences, promote the development of aversions, and therefore,
      lead to a significant reduction in the pleasure of eating. Loss of appetite, decreased food
      intake and the development of aversions to certain foods are situations experienced by a
      large proportion of patients undergoing chemotherapy.

      The assessment of taste disorders in patients undergoing chemotherapy treatment is
      established through the use of questionnaires, interviews and taste tests.

      Changes in the perception and identification of salty, sweet, bitter and sour flavours are
      common in patients undergoing chemotherapy.

      The objective of CANUT is to study the effect of pathology and chemotherapy on gustatory and
      olfactory mechanisms and in particular on interindividual differences in the perception and
      appreciation of food.

      In this study the investigators propose to adapt foods to best respond to sensory disorders
      related to the disease and/or treatment.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Health Services Research</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>proportion of treated patients by 4 cycles of chimiotherapy that will prefere at least 1 modified version of meal.</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The main endpoint of the CANUT-1 study is the proportion of cancer patients treated with chemotherapy (after 4 cycles) who will prefer at least an adapted version of a food compared to the standard version of the same food.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Food assessment scores ( 0/4 to 4/4, 4 mean a better score)</measure>
    <time_frame>Before Cycle 1(each cycle is 28 days) of chemotherapy treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Individual food assessment scores (standard food and adapted food to taste and smell disorders) before any treatment</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Food assessment scores ( 0/4 to 4/4,4 mean a better score)</measure>
    <time_frame>after 2 cycles (each cycle is 28 days) of chemotherapy</time_frame>
    <description>: Individual food assessment scores (standard food and adapted food to taste and smell disorders) after 2 cycles of chemotherapy</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Food assessment scores ( 0/4 to 4/4, 4 mean a better score)</measure>
    <time_frame>after 4 cycles(each cycle is 28 days) of chemotherapy</time_frame>
    <description>: Individual food assessment scores (standard food and adapted food to taste and smell disorders) after 4 cycles of chemotherapy</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>European Test of Olfactory Capabilities (ETOC) (1 (mean a worse) to 9 (mean a better)</measure>
    <time_frame>Before cycle 1(each cycle is 28 days) of chemotherapy treatment</time_frame>
    <description>The results of olfactory detection and identification, familiarity, pleasantness, intensity, edibility and trigeminal perception (fresh, hot, irritant, pungent) European Test of Olfactory Capabilities (ETOC) before any treatment, after 2 and 4 cycles of chemotherapy.
The results of olfactory detection and identification, familiarity, pleasantness, intensity, edibility and trigeminal perception (fresh, hot, irritant, pungent) European Test of Olfactory Capabilities (ETOC) before any treatment</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>European Test of Olfactory Capabilities (ETOC)(1 (mean a worse) to 9 (mean a better)</measure>
    <time_frame>after 2 cycles (each cycle is 28 days) of chemotherapy</time_frame>
    <description>The results of olfactory detection and identification, familiarity, pleasantness, intensity, edibility and trigeminal perception (fresh, hot, irritant, pungent) European Test of Olfactory Capabilities (ETOC) after 2 of chemotherapy.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>European Test of Olfactory Capabilities (ETOC)(1 (mean a worse) to 9 (mean a better)</measure>
    <time_frame>after 4 cycles(each cycle is 28 days) of chemotherapy</time_frame>
    <description>The results of olfactory detection and identification, familiarity, pleasantness, intensity, edibility and trigeminal perception (fresh, hot, irritant, pungent) European Test of Olfactory Capabilities (ETOC) after and 4 cycles of chemotherapy.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Condiments consumption assessment by condiments questionnaire (0 contiment to 12 condiments)</measure>
    <time_frame>Before cycle 1(each cycle is 28 days) of treatment</time_frame>
    <description>The number of condiments added at the time of inclusion</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Condiments consumption assessment by condiments questionnaire (0 contiment to 12 condiments)</measure>
    <time_frame>after 2 cycles(each cycle is 28 days) of chemotherapy</time_frame>
    <description>The number of condiments added after 2 cycles of chemotherapy.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Condiments consumption assessment by condiments questionnaire (0 contiment to 12 condiments)</measure>
    <time_frame>after 4 cycles(each cycle is 28 days) of chemotherapy</time_frame>
    <description>The number of condiments added after 4 cycles of chemotherapy.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Food temperature</measure>
    <time_frame>Before Cycle 1(each cycle is 28 days) of chemotherapy treatment</time_frame>
    <description>The proportion of patients who prefer to consume cold foods versus those who prefer to consume hot foods at the time of inclusion</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Food temperature</measure>
    <time_frame>after 2 cycles(each cycle is 28 days) of chemotherapy</time_frame>
    <description>The proportion of patients who prefer to consume cold foods versus those who prefer to consume hot foods after 2 cycles of chemotherapy</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Food temperature</measure>
    <time_frame>after 4 cycles(each cycle is 28 days) of chemotherapy</time_frame>
    <description>The proportion of patients who prefer to consume cold foods versus those who prefer to consume hot foods at 4 cycles of chemotherapy</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Nutrition Disorders</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>At each meal: different elements will be presented to the patient (starter / main course / side dish / dessert).
For each of these elements, the patient will be offered 4 versions (a standard version and 3 adapted versions of the same food):
The standard food.
The food refers to a more elaborate texture.
The food refers to a food with a stronger smell.
The food refers to a more important flavor.
The patient will indicate the version of the food that will be preferred.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Adapted food intervention</intervention_name>
    <description>Adapted food intervention</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patient with advanced lung cancer requiring a first line of intravenous chemotherapy
             or patient with localized, histologically or cytologically proven breast cancer for
             whom intravenous chemotherapy treatment will be initiated or patient with stage III-IV
             gynecological cancer (ovarian cancer or uterine cancer) for whom intravenous
             chemotherapy treatment will be initiated.

               -  Patient with a body mass index (BMI) between 18Kg/m² and 35Kg/m².

               -  Patient whose indication for treatment with intravenous chemotherapy has been
                  selected

               -  Naive patient of previous chemotherapy.

               -  Life expectancy &gt; 3 months.

               -  Patient able to travel for 4 visits to the Paul Bocuse Institute, 1 Chemin de
                  Calabert, 69 130 ECULLY, FRANCE.

               -  Written informed consent obtained in accordance with applicable GCPs.

               -  Patients affiliated to a social security system.

               -  Patients who have the possibility of being accompanied, by the same person, to
                  the visits of the test meals at the Paul Bocuse Research Institute

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patient under 18 years of age.

          -  Patient who has had another malignant tumor in the last 3 years.

          -  Patient with symptomatic brain metastases.

          -  Patient with symptomatic mucositis.

          -  Patient suffering or having suffered from an otorhinolaryngic or oesogastrointestinal
             pathology interfering with food intake.

          -  Patients with digestive disorders before any cancer treatment.

          -  Indication for concomitant radiotherapy or immunotherapy alone treatment.

          -  Patient with a known food allergy or food intolerance.

          -  Patient with partial or total agueusia diagnosed.

          -  Patient with diagnosed partial or total anosmia.

          -  Patients who have used artificial feeding within 2 months.

          -  Patients who have lost more than 10% of their baseline weight within 2 months.

          -  Patient unable to be regularly monitored for any reason

          -  Patient deprived of liberty or placed under guardianship or curatorship

          -  Pregnant or breastfeeding patient.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>David DAYDE, manager</last_name>
    <phone>+33.4.78.86.37.74</phone>
    <phone_ext>+33</phone_ext>
    <email>david.dayde@chu-lyon.fr</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Nadjat MEDEGHRI, manager</last_name>
    <phone>+33.4.78.86.37.74</phone>
    <phone_ext>+33</phone_ext>
    <email>nadjat.medeghri@chu-lyon.fr</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <verification_date>December 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 1, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 30, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 3, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 30, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 30, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 3, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>cancer, nutrition disorder</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Nutrition Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

