<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04218890</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ASA2</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04218890</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>TF, TFPI and Plasmin as Novel Bio-markers in Early Diagnosis of Lupus Nephritis</brief_title>
  <official_title>Urinary Tissue Factor (TF), Tissue Factor Pathway Inhibitor (TFPI) and Plasmin as Bio-markers in Early Diagnosis of Lupus Nephritis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Assiut University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Assiut University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Urinary levels of plasmin ,TF , and TFPI are all elevated in active LN patients compared to
      inactive LN patients and healthy controls. All four proteins correlated with systemic disease
      activity and renal disease activity. Importantly, urine plasmin performed best among the four
      proteins in discriminating active LN from inactive disease, even better than traditional
      markers, such as anti ds DNA and complement C3. Furthermore, the combination of urine plasmin
      and TFPI showed higher specificity and negative predictive values than urine plasmin when
      compared to anti-ds DNA and complement C3
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Systemic lupus erythematosus (SLE) is a systemic autoimmune disease affects various organs,
      characterized by diverse autoantibodies production,mainly anti-DNA and anti-nuclear
      antibodies . It demonstrates variations in incidence,prevalence, disease activity and
      prognosis according to race and ethnicity . Lupus nephritis (LN) is one of the most frequent
      and severe clinical manifestations of SLE, it affects over 60% of SLE patients representing a
      leading cause of morbidity and mortality . Early diagnosis and monitoring of the disease
      flares are still challenging , although of the novel immunosuppressive drugs and biologics,
      which brought improvements in recent SLE/LN survival rates .

      The American College of Rheumatology (ACR) guidelines for the treatment of lupus nephritis ,
      recommend change in treatment if response to therapy has not been achieved after 6 months of
      induction therapy. However, response to therapy is not well defined. In addition, renal
      damage can occur within 6 months while waiting to define this response. Decision support
      tools could help define response at the start of induction therapy and have the potential to
      improve outcomes .

      Use of laboratory parameters for LN such as creatinine clearance, anti-ds DNA, proteinuria,
      urine protein-to-creatinine ratio (U-PCR),and complement levels are undesirable. These
      markers are of less sensitivity and specificity for evolve renal activity and injury in
      LN.They are not directly correlated with kidney damage, which can arise before kidney
      function affection. Outbreak of nephritis may occur in any condition in absence and new rise
      in the level of proteinuria.

      Kidney biopsy is a gold standard to assess the histological category of LN and the level of
      activity and chronicity in glomeruli. But, it is an invasive procedure and continual biopsies
      are inappropriate in the observing and follow up of LN . It may have sampling error because
      of extent number of glomeruli obtained for LN activity and chronicity. So , many studies are
      focusing on identifying non-invasive biomarkers for the early diagnosis and follow up of the
      disease and the therapy response.

      Urine is easily collected and can reflect the underlying renal affection more accurately than
      serum. Therefore, urine bio-markers represent promising candidates for the early disease
      diagnosis and monitoring .Thus, novel urinary bio-markers, which are able to distinguish
      lupus kidney activity and its extremity, anticipate kidney outbreak, and observe treatment
      reciprocation and illness breakthrough are clearly obligatory . Urinary bio-markers are more
      sensitive for lupus nephritis;they can appear in urine before functional derangement .

      Coagulation system disorders and hyper-coagulability state have been reported in lupus
      nephritis, also the frequency of thrombotic events was documented to be higher in SLE
      patients than in the general population, and these events were associated with poor outcome
      .Both thrombo-genic and thrombolytic cascades appear to be up-regulated in lupus nephritis,
      with proteins from both cascades appearing in the urine .

      Urinary levels of plasmin ,TF and TFPI are all elevated in active LN patients compared to
      inactive LN patients and healthy controls. All four proteins correlated with systemic disease
      activity and renal disease activity. Importantly, urine plasmin performed best among the four
      proteins in discriminating active LN from inactive disease, even better than traditional
      markers, such as anti dsDNA and complement C3. Furthermore, the combination of urine plasmin
      and TFPI showed higher specificity and negative predictive values than urine plasmin when
      compared to anti-dsDNA and complement C3.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">April 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 1, 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 1, 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Control</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Cross-Sectional</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The diagnostic utility of tissue factor ,, tissue factor pathway inhibitor and plasmin as biomarkers for early detection of lupus nephritis (LN)</measure>
    <time_frame>2023</time_frame>
    <description>Urinay sample of 100 subjects (80 with SLE ,40 of them with LN,and 20 are healthy persons)will be collected as a morning sample&amp; using ELISA test to detect the level of these bio-markers in the urine of these subjects</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>the correlation of these bio-markers to the clinical staging , the disease activity index and revised treatment .</measure>
    <time_frame>2023</time_frame>
    <description>correlate the level of the markers with the renal biopsy staging and activity index using (International Society of Nephrology /Renal Pathology Society classification (ISN/RPS), and disease Activity Index (SLEDAI-2K &amp; r SLEDAI)).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>3</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Lupus Nephritis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>SLE patients without lupus nephritis</arm_group_label>
    <description>40 SLE patients
40SLE patients( All SLE pt. satisfied the ACR criteria for SLE diagnosis) these patients will be without any evidences of nephritis</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>SLE patients with lupus nephritis</arm_group_label>
    <description>40SLE patients with evidences of nephritis</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>healthy control group</arm_group_label>
    <description>20 healthy subjects matched age and sex with be enrolled as healthy control group</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Urinary tissue factor (TF), tissue factor pathway inhibitor (TFPI) and plasmin</intervention_name>
    <description>urinary sample</description>
    <arm_group_label>SLE patients with lupus nephritis</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>SLE patients without lupus nephritis</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>healthy control group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Clinical data will be gathered and SLEDAI will be calculated based on chart review .SLE
        patients will then classified as having either active LN (ALN) or inactive LN (ILN). Active
        LN is defined as active urine sediment or proteinuria (rSLEDAI &gt; 0). Inactive LN is defined
        as inactive urine sediment and no proteinuria (rSLEDAI = 0).
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. age &gt;15 years

          2. SLE patients fullfiling ACR diagnostic criteria

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Renal artery stenosis, congenital renal diseases ,renal tumor,other causes of GN

          2. Pregnancy.

          3. coagulation disorders

          4. DM,HTN and the other connective tissue disease

          5. Obesity

          6. CKD
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>15 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>60 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Salwa Salah Elgendy, professor dr</last_name>
    <phone>01005766155</phone>
    <email>salwaelgendi@yahoo.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Effat Abdelhady Eltony</last_name>
    <phone>01097330309</phone>
    <email>effattony@aun.edu.eg</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <reference>
    <citation>Qin L, Stanley S, Ding H, Zhang T, Truong VTT, Celhar T, Fairhurst AM, Pedroza C, Petri M, Saxena R, Mohan C. Urinary pro-thrombotic, anti-thrombotic, and fibrinolytic molecules as biomarkers of lupus nephritis. Arthritis Res Ther. 2019 Jul 18;21(1):176. doi: 10.1186/s13075-019-1959-y. Erratum in: Arthritis Res Ther. 2019 Aug 7;21(1):185.</citation>
    <PMID>31319876</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Frijns R, Fijnheer R, Schiel A, Donders R, Sixma J, Derksen R. Persistent increase in plasma thrombomodulin in patients with a history of lupus nephritis: endothelial cell activation markers. J Rheumatol. 2001 Mar;28(3):514-9.</citation>
    <PMID>11296951</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ding H, Kharboutli M, Saxena R, Wu T. Insulin-like growth factor binding protein-2 as a novel biomarker for disease activity and renal pathology changes in lupus nephritis. Clin Exp Immunol. 2016 Apr;184(1):11-8. doi: 10.1111/cei.12743. Epub 2016 Jan 11.</citation>
    <PMID>26616478</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Petri M, Kasitanon N, Lee SS, Link K, Magder L, Bae SC, Hanly JG, Isenberg DA, Nived O, Sturfelt G, van Vollenhoven R, Wallace DJ, Alarcón GS, Adu D, Avila-Casado C, Bernatsky SR, Bruce IN, Clarke AE, Contreras G, Fine DM, Gladman DD, Gordon C, Kalunian KC, Madaio MP, Rovin BH, Sanchez-Guerrero J, Steinsson K, Aranow C, Balow JE, Buyon JP, Ginzler EM, Khamashta MA, Urowitz MB, Dooley MA, Merrill JT, Ramsey-Goldman R, Font J, Tumlin J, Stoll T, Zoma A; Systemic Lupus International Collaborating Clinics. Systemic lupus international collaborating clinics renal activity/response exercise: development of a renal activity score and renal response index. Arthritis Rheum. 2008 Jun;58(6):1784-8. doi: 10.1002/art.23456. Erratum in: Arthritis Rheum. 2008 Sep;58(9):2823.</citation>
    <PMID>18512819</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>December 28, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 2, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 6, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 3, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 3, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 7, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Assiut University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Ayat salah</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>principal investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Nephritis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lupus Nephritis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lipoprotein-associated coagulation inhibitor</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Thromboplastin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

