<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04212780</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IRB201901021</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>OCR29622</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>1UH3NS109845-01</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04212780</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Dual Lead Thalamic Deep Brain Recording (DBR)-DBS Interface for Closed Loop Control of Severe Essential Tremor</brief_title>
  <official_title>Dual Lead Thalamic DBR-DBS Interface for Closed Loop Control of Severe Essential Tremor</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Florida</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke (NINDS)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Medtronic</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Florida</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a feasibility study based on physician-initiated Investigational Device Exemption
      (IDE) including intraoperative experiments and chronic testing of implanted dual thalamic DBS
      lead systems. This study will inform protocols for optimal use of implanted next-gen DBS
      systems for primarily tremor control in refractory essential tremor.If the approach appears
      to be successful, the pilot data generated will be used to base a future pivotal trial for
      FDA approval for enhanced tremor control and adaptive DBS (aDBS) functionality of DBS
      systems.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Ventralis intermedius nucleus of the thalamus (VIM) Deep Brain Stimulation (DBS) has emerged
      as a highly effective treatment for essential tremor, which is an incurable, degenerative
      brain disorder that results in progressively debilitating tremor, afflicting an estimated 7
      million people in the US (2.2% of the population). Clinical observation shows, however, that
      disease progression results in eventual recurrence of debilitating tremor in 10 to 20% of VIM
      DBS patients. DBS revision surgery, with replacement of sub-optimally positioned VIM DBS
      leads and addition of an ipsilateral ventralis oralis (VO) DBS lead, has emerged as an
      effective rescue strategy for many such patients with delayed failure of VIM DBS therapy.

      Since essential tremors are typically not continuous, tremor suppressing DBS therapy need not
      necessarily be delivered continuously and could theoretically be effective if delivered only
      when movement intent or tremor is present.

      Our central hypothesis is that a VIM+VO DBS system capable of detecting the neurophysiologic
      markers of essential tremor (ET) associated with goal directed movements, and providing
      responsive dual lead thalamic stimulation in a targeted and personalized manner, would
      provide improved suppression of severe tremor, reduce adverse effects associated with
      continuous stimulation, and prolong the battery life of the implantable neurostimulator
      (INS), decreasing the frequency of surgical procedures necessary to replace devices with
      depleted batteries.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">August 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 30, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 30, 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Device Feasibility</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Efficacy Assessment - Tremor</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Tremor rating scale This 5-point scale rates tremor severity based on tremor amplitude, from 0 (no tremor) to 4 (severe tremor) in each part of the body, and includes assessments of specific abilities and functional disability.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">10</enrollment>
  <condition>Essential Tremor</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment Naive</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants receiving Long-term stimulation of the thalamus via dual leads for Essential Tremor</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Refractory Participants</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients with recurrent, debilitating intention tremor despite ongoing, optimized VIM DBS therapy</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Medtronic Summit Rechargable (RC)+S</intervention_name>
    <description>Dual channel closed-loop pulse generator with connection to both new DBS leads for deep stimulation of VIM vs VO</description>
    <arm_group_label>Refractory Participants</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment Naive</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ipsilateral thalamic (VIM+VO) DBS</intervention_name>
    <description>Implantation of two new ipsilateral thalamic (VIM+VO) DBS</description>
    <arm_group_label>Refractory Participants</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>standard ET DBS</intervention_name>
    <description>Single Lead VIM</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment Naive</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ipsilateral VO</intervention_name>
    <description>second lead in the ipsilateral VO</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment Naive</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patient gives an informed consent.

          -  Patient is over 21 years of age.

          -  Patient is diagnosed with a postural-intention (essential) tremor for at least 3
             years, meets diagnostic criteria for ET, has been evaluated and examined by a movement
             disorders fellowship trained neurologist, and is being treated with traditional VIM
             DBS therapy.

          -  Patient has no evidence of non-ET central nervous system disease or injury and has had
             a significantly disabling, upper extremity tremor despite ongoing VIM DBS therapy for
             at least three (3) months prior to DBS revision surgery.

          -  Patient has a postural or kinetic tremor severity score of at least 2 out of 4 in the
             extremity intended for treatment on the Fahn-Tolosa-Marin Clinical Rating Scale for
             Tremor (TRS) despite ongoing VIM DBS therapy.

          -  Patient has a TRS score of 2 or above in any one of the items 16-23 from the
             Disability subsection of the TRS: speaking, feeding other than liquids, bringing
             liquids to mouth, hygiene, dressing, writing, working and social activities despite
             ongoing VIM DBS therapy.

          -  Patient's tremor is refractory to adequate trials of at least two medications, one of
             which should be either propranolol or primidone. An adequate medication trial is
             defined as a therapeutic dose of each medication or the development of side effects as
             the medication dose is titrated.

          -  Patient is available for appropriate follow-up times for the length of the study

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Any previous neurosurgical intervention other than VIM DBS, including ablative brain
             lesions for tremor suppression.

          -  Medication related movement disorders.

          -  Any suspicion of Parkinson's disease, including presence of Parkinsonian features such
             as bradykinesia, rigidity, or postural instability.

          -  Any behaviors consistent with alcohol or substance abuse as defined by the criteria
             outlined in Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders (DSM-V).

          -  Severe medical co-morbidity including cardiovascular disorder, lung disorder, kidney
             disease, continuous neurological disease, hematological disease, or frailty that
             impact tolerability of the surgery as judged by the screening physicians.

          -  Abnormal brain MRI including hydrocephalus, stroke, structural lesions, demyelinating
             lesions, or infectious lesions. Also excluded will be subjects with severe brain
             atrophy.

          -  Any uncontrolled symptoms or signs of increased intracranial pressure (e.g., headache,
             nausea, vomiting, lethargy, papilledema).

          -  A history of seizures within the past year.

          -  A dementia rating scale score (DRS) &lt;130 signifying significant cognitive dysfunction
             and a potential for inability to cooperate with tasks involved in the study.

          -  Any attempt or intent of suicide during the previous six months.

          -  Presence or history of psychosis.

          -  Significant or active mood disorders including depression. For the purpose of this
             study, we consider a significant mood disorder to include any subject who has:

               -  Scores ≥ 20 on the Patient Health Questionnaire - 9 (PHQ-9).

               -  Currently under the care of a psychiatrist

               -  Currently participating in cognitive-behavioral therapy

               -  Been hospitalized for the treatment of a psychiatric illness within 12 months

               -  Ever received transcranial magnetic stimulation

               -  Ever received electroconvulsive therapy

          -  In addition, patients who are pregnant or plan to become pregnant will be excluded
             from this study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>21 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>99 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Karin Oweiss, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Florida</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Julie Sugura</last_name>
    <phone>352-273-5566</phone>
    <email>Julie.Segura@neurology.ufl.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Karim Oweiss, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>352-294-1898</phone>
    <email>koweiss@ufl.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Florida</name>
      <address>
        <city>Gainesville</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>32611</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>December 19, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 24, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">December 30, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 12, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 12, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 14, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Tremor</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Essential Tremor</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

