<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04218656</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NL2019-6036</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04218656</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>DUAL Pathway Inhibition to Improve Endothelial Function in Peripheral Artery Disease</brief_title>
  <acronym>DUAL-PAD</acronym>
  <official_title>DUAL Pathway Inhibition (Low-dose Rivaroxaban and Aspirin) as Compared to Aspirin Only to Improve Endothelial Function in Peripheral Artery Disease.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Radboud University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Radboud University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Peripheral artery disease (PAD) is a manifestation of systemic atherosclerosis, causing
      patients to be at high risk of major adverse cardiovascular and limb events. Therefore,
      single antiplatelet therapy is recommended when patients are symptomatic or have undergone
      revascularization. Rivaroxaban (2.5 mg twice a day) in addition to Aspirin (100 mg once a
      day) has shown to be effective in reducing morbidity and mortality from major cardiovascular
      and limb events in patients with stable peripheral or carotid artery disease compared to
      Aspirin alone. Although a higher rate of major bleeding was detected, the incidence of fatal
      or critical organ bleedings was not increased.

      Endothelial dysfunction is one of the first signs of atherosclerosis and is related to major
      cardiovascular events. The level of macro- and microvascular endothelial dysfunction can be
      measured using the carotid artery reactivity (CAR) test and noninvasive peripheral arterial
      tonometry (EndoPAT), respectively. The investigators hypothesized that a combination of
      low-dose rivaroxaban and antiplatelet therapy would improve endothelial function in PAD
      patients.

      The investigators aim to study the effectiveness of this combination therapy in improving
      macro- and microvascular endothelial function in patients with stable or symptomatic PAD.

      Therefore the investigators will study two clinical cohorts of lower extremity PAD patients
      (n=330) with intermittent claudication (group A: Fontaine stages 1-2) or critical limb
      ischemia with pain at rest and/or foot ulcers (group B: Fontaine stages 3-4) who have an
      indication for single antiplatelet therapy.

      Aspirin 100mg once a day + 2.5 mg rivaroxaban twice a day will be given during 3 months,
      preceded by a run-in period of Aspirin alone (100 mg once a day) as reference.

      The change in proportion of patients with CAR-constriction from baseline (Aspirin alone) to 3
      months after adding low dose rivaroxaban will be compared for both study groups (A and B).
      Secondary, microvascular dysfunction as quantified by finger plethysmography (EndoPAT) at
      baseline and after 3 months treatment will be compared. Innate immune function will be
      quantified by ex vivo whole blood stimulation tests at baseline.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Rationale: Peripheral artery disease (PAD) is a manifestation of systemic atherosclerosis,
      causing patients to be at high risk of major adverse cardiovascular events and major adverse
      limb events, including amputation. Therefore, clopidogrel or Aspirin depending on national
      guidelines, is recommended as single antiplatelet therapy when patients are symptomatic or
      have undergone revascularization. Anticoagulant therapies have not shown to be superior in
      PAD patients and have high rates of major bleedings. However, rivaroxaban (2.5 mg twice a
      day), an oral factor Xa inhibitor, in addition to Aspirin (100 mg once a day) has shown to be
      effective in reducing morbidity and mortality from coronary artery disease and major
      cardiovascular and limb events in patients with stable peripheral or carotid artery disease
      compared to Aspirin alone. Although a higher rate of major bleeding was detected, the
      incidence of fatal or critical organ bleedings was not increased.

      Endothelial dysfunction is one of the first signs of atherosclerosis and is present before
      clinical symptoms appear. Endothelial dysfunction contributes to the progression of
      atherosclerosis and is related to major cardiovascular events. The level of macro- and
      microvascular endothelial dysfunction can be measured using the carotid artery reactivity
      (CAR) test and noninvasive peripheral arterial tonometry (EndoPAT), respectively. The first
      test measures the CAR in response to sympathic stimulation, while the latter records digital
      pulse wave amplitude in response to a 5-minute occlusion of the forearm. These tests can also
      be used to measure endothelial dysfunction in PAD patients and how a combination of
      rivaroxaban and Aspirin affects it. The investigators hypothesized that a combination of
      low-dose rivaroxaban and antiplatelet therapy would improve endothelial function in PAD
      patients.

      Objective: To study the effectiveness of low-dose rivaroxaban with Aspirin in improving
      macrovascular endothelial function in patients with stable or symptomatic PAD.

      Study design: Two clinical cohort studies will be performed. Study population: Lower
      extremity PAD patients (n=330) with intermittent claudication (group A: Fontaine stages 1-2)
      or critical limb ischemia with pain at rest and/or foot ulcers (group B: Fontaine stages 3-4)
      who have an indication for single antiplatelet therapy are eligible for this study.

      Intervention (if applicable): Aspirin 100mg once a day + 2.5 mg rivaroxaban twice a day
      (combination therapy). The use of Aspirin alone (100 mg once a day) during the run-in period
      is used as reference.

      Main study parameters/endpoints: The primary outcome measure is the CAR after 3 months
      combination treatment. The change in proportion of patients with CAR-constriction from
      baseline (Aspirin alone) to 3 months after adding low dose rivaroxaban will be compared for
      both study groups (A and B). The secondary outcome measure is: microvascular dysfunction as
      quantified by finger plethysmography (EndoPAT) after 3 months treatment. Innate immune
      function will be quantified by ex vivo whole blood stimulation tests at baseline.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 8, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Two single clinical cohorts will be studied.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Carotid artery reactivity</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>The change in proportion of patients with carotid artery reactivity constriction from baseline (Aspirin alone) to 3 months after adding low dose rivaroxaban</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Microvascular dysfunction</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>The change in microvascular dysfunction as quantified by EndoPAT from baseline (Aspirin alone) to 3 months after adding low-dose rivaroxaban</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Innate immune function</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month</time_frame>
    <description>Baseline ex vivo innate immune cell responsiveness will be determined before revaroxaban is started by adding lipopolysaccharide to whole blood. After 24h of incubation at 37 degrees, supernatant will be stored at -80 degrees. The release of cytokines (TNF, IL-6 and IL-10) will be determined by ELISA.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">330</enrollment>
  <condition>Peripheral Artery Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>165 patients with intermittent claudication</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group B</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>165 patients with critical limb ischemia with pain at rest and/or foot ulcers</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Rivaroxaban 2.5 Mg Oral Tablet</intervention_name>
    <description>2.5 mg rivaroxaban twice a day in addition to Aspirin 100mg once a day (standard care).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Group B</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Xarelto</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Symptomatic or stable lower extremity PAD patients (Fontaine stages 2-4) with an
             indication for single antiplatelet therapy according to international (ESC) guidelines

          -  &gt;16 years old

          -  Written informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients having or at risk of major bleeding:

               -  Gastrointestinal ulceration

               -  Current malignant neoplasms

               -  Brain or spinal injury

               -  Brain, spinal or ophthalmic surgery

               -  Intracranial hemorrhage

               -  Known or suspected esophageal varices

               -  Arteriovenous malformations

               -  Major intraspinal or intracerebral vascular abnormalities

               -  Hepatic disease associated with coagulopathy and clinically relevant bleeding
                  risk, including cirrhotic patients with Child Pugh B and C

               -  Use of selective serotonin reuptake inhibitors or serotonin-norepinephrine
                  reuptake inhibitors

          -  Patients with prosthetic valves

          -  Patients with a history of asthma attacks caused by salicylates

          -  Severe renal impairment (creatinine clearance &lt;30 ml/min)

          -  Systemic treatment with strong CYP3A4 and/or P-glycoprotein inhibitors (i.e.
             azole-antimyotics, HIV protease inhibitors)

          -  Concomitant treatment with other anticoagulants

          -  Concomitant treatment with methotrexate at a weekly dosage of &gt;15 mg

          -  Pregnant or lactating

          -  Known hypersensitivity to Aspirin or rivaroxaban
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>16 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Michiel C Warlé, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Radboud University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Michel MPJ Reijnen, Professor</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Rijnstate</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Loes H Willems, MD</last_name>
    <phone>0031 24 361 5333</phone>
    <email>Loes.H.Willems@radboudumc.nl</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Rijnstate hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Arnhem</city>
        <zip>6815 AD</zip>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Michel MPJ Reijnen, Prof</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Radboudumc</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nijmegen</city>
        <zip>6525 GA</zip>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Michiel C Warlé, PhD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Netherlands</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Steg PG, Bhatt DL, Wilson PW, D'Agostino R Sr, Ohman EM, Röther J, Liau CS, Hirsch AT, Mas JL, Ikeda Y, Pencina MJ, Goto S; REACH Registry Investigators. One-year cardiovascular event rates in outpatients with atherothrombosis. JAMA. 2007 Mar 21;297(11):1197-206.</citation>
    <PMID>17374814</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bhatt DL, Eagle KA, Ohman EM, Hirsch AT, Goto S, Mahoney EM, Wilson PW, Alberts MJ, D'Agostino R, Liau CS, Mas JL, Röther J, Smith SC Jr, Salette G, Contant CF, Massaro JM, Steg PG; REACH Registry Investigators. Comparative determinants of 4-year cardiovascular event rates in stable outpatients at risk of or with atherothrombosis. JAMA. 2010 Sep 22;304(12):1350-7. doi: 10.1001/jama.2010.1322. Epub 2010 Aug 30.</citation>
    <PMID>20805624</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Brott TG, Halperin JL, Abbara S, Bacharach JM, Barr JD, Bush RL, Cates CU, Creager MA, Fowler SB, Friday G, Hertzberg VS, McIff EB, Moore WS, Panagos PD, Riles TS, Rosenwasser RH, Taylor AJ, Jacobs AK, Smith SC Jr, Anderson JL, Adams CD, Albert N, Buller CE, Creager MA, Ettinger SM, Guyton RA, Halperin JL, Hochman JS, Hunt SA, Krumholz HM, Kushner FG, Lytle BW, Nishimura RA, Ohman EM, Page RL, Riegel B, Stevenson WG, Tarkington LG, Yancy CW. 2011 ASA/ACCF/AHA/AANN/AANS/ACR/ASNR/CNS/SAIP/SCAI/SIR/SNIS/SVM/SVS guideline on the management of patients with extracranial carotid and vertebral artery disease: executive summary: a report of the American College of Cardiology Foundation/American Heart Association Task Force on Practice Guidelines, and the American Stroke Association, American Association of Neuroscience Nurses, American Association of Neurological Surgeons, American College of Radiology, American Society of Neuroradiology, Congress of Neurological Surgeons, Society of Atherosclerosis Imaging and Prevention, Society for Cardiovascular Angiography and Interventions, Society of Interventional Radiology, Society of NeuroInterventional Surgery, Society for Vascular Medicine, and Society for Vascular Surgery. Developed in collaboration with the American Academy of Neurology and Society of Cardiovascular Computed Tomography. Catheter Cardiovasc Interv. 2013 Jan 1;81(1):E76-123. doi: 10.1002/ccd.22983. Epub 2011 Feb 3. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23281092</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Writing Committee Members, Gerhard-Herman MD, Gornik HL, Barrett C, Barshes NR, Corriere MA, Drachman DE, Fleisher LA, Fowkes FGR, Hamburg NM, Kinlay S, Lookstein R, Misra S, Mureebe L, Olin JW, Patel RAG, Regensteiner JG, Schanzer A, Shishehbor MH, Stewart KJ, Treat-Jacobson D, Walsh ME; ACC/AHA Task Force Members, Halperin JL, Levine GN, Al-Khatib SM, Birtcher KK, Bozkurt B, Brindis RG, Cigarroa JE, Curtis LH, Fleisher LA, Gentile F, Gidding S, Hlatky MA, Ikonomidis J, Joglar J, Pressler SJ, Wijeysundera DN. 2016 AHA/ACC Guideline on the Management of Patients with Lower Extremity Peripheral Artery Disease: Executive Summary. Vasc Med. 2017 Jun;22(3):NP1-NP43. doi: 10.1177/1358863X17701592. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>28494710</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Aboyans V, Ricco JB, Bartelink MEL, Björck M, Brodmann M, Cohnert T, Collet JP, Czerny M, De Carlo M, Debus S, Espinola-Klein C, Kahan T, Kownator S, Mazzolai L, Naylor AR, Roffi M, Röther J, Sprynger M, Tendera M, Tepe G, Venermo M, Vlachopoulos C, Desormais I; ESC Scientific Document Group. 2017 ESC Guidelines on the Diagnosis and Treatment of Peripheral Arterial Diseases, in collaboration with the European Society for Vascular Surgery (ESVS): Document covering atherosclerotic disease of extracranial carotid and vertebral, mesenteric, renal, upper and lower extremity arteriesEndorsed by: the European Stroke Organization (ESO)The Task Force for the Diagnosis and Treatment of Peripheral Arterial Diseases of the European Society of Cardiology (ESC) and of the European Society for Vascular Surgery (ESVS). Eur Heart J. 2018 Mar 1;39(9):763-816. doi: 10.1093/eurheartj/ehx095.</citation>
    <PMID>28886620</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Warfarin Antiplatelet Vascular Evaluation Trial Investigators, Anand S, Yusuf S, Xie C, Pogue J, Eikelboom J, Budaj A, Sussex B, Liu L, Guzman R, Cina C, Crowell R, Keltai M, Gosselin G. Oral anticoagulant and antiplatelet therapy and peripheral arterial disease. N Engl J Med. 2007 Jul 19;357(3):217-27.</citation>
    <PMID>17634457</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Prins MH, Lensing AW, Brighton TA, Lyons RM, Rehm J, Trajanovic M, Davidson BL, Beyer-Westendorf J, Pap ÁF, Berkowitz SD, Cohen AT, Kovacs MJ, Wells PS, Prandoni P. Oral rivaroxaban versus enoxaparin with vitamin K antagonist for the treatment of symptomatic venous thromboembolism in patients with cancer (EINSTEIN-DVT and EINSTEIN-PE): a pooled subgroup analysis of two randomised controlled trials. Lancet Haematol. 2014 Oct;1(1):e37-46. doi: 10.1016/S2352-3026(14)70018-3. Epub 2014 Sep 28.</citation>
    <PMID>27030066</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mega JL, Braunwald E, Wiviott SD, Bassand JP, Bhatt DL, Bode C, Burton P, Cohen M, Cook-Bruns N, Fox KA, Goto S, Murphy SA, Plotnikov AN, Schneider D, Sun X, Verheugt FW, Gibson CM; ATLAS ACS 2–TIMI 51 Investigators. Rivaroxaban in patients with a recent acute coronary syndrome. N Engl J Med. 2012 Jan 5;366(1):9-19. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa1112277. Epub 2011 Nov 13.</citation>
    <PMID>22077192</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Eikelboom JW, Connolly SJ, Bosch J, Dagenais GR, Hart RG, Shestakovska O, Diaz R, Alings M, Lonn EM, Anand SS, Widimsky P, Hori M, Avezum A, Piegas LS, Branch KRH, Probstfield J, Bhatt DL, Zhu J, Liang Y, Maggioni AP, Lopez-Jaramillo P, O'Donnell M, Kakkar AK, Fox KAA, Parkhomenko AN, Ertl G, Störk S, Keltai M, Ryden L, Pogosova N, Dans AL, Lanas F, Commerford PJ, Torp-Pedersen C, Guzik TJ, Verhamme PB, Vinereanu D, Kim JH, Tonkin AM, Lewis BS, Felix C, Yusoff K, Steg PG, Metsarinne KP, Cook Bruns N, Misselwitz F, Chen E, Leong D, Yusuf S; COMPASS Investigators. Rivaroxaban with or without Aspirin in Stable Cardiovascular Disease. N Engl J Med. 2017 Oct 5;377(14):1319-1330. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa1709118. Epub 2017 Aug 27.</citation>
    <PMID>28844192</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Anand SS, Bosch J, Eikelboom JW, Connolly SJ, Diaz R, Widimsky P, Aboyans V, Alings M, Kakkar AK, Keltai K, Maggioni AP, Lewis BS, Störk S, Zhu J, Lopez-Jaramillo P, O'Donnell M, Commerford PJ, Vinereanu D, Pogosova N, Ryden L, Fox KAA, Bhatt DL, Misselwitz F, Varigos JD, Vanassche T, Avezum AA, Chen E, Branch K, Leong DP, Bangdiwala SI, Hart RG, Yusuf S; COMPASS Investigators. Rivaroxaban with or without aspirin in patients with stable peripheral or carotid artery disease: an international, randomised, double-blind, placebo-controlled trial. Lancet. 2018 Jan 20;391(10117):219-229. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(17)32409-1. Epub 2017 Nov 10.</citation>
    <PMID>29132880</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Borissoff JI, Spronk HM, ten Cate H. The hemostatic system as a modulator of atherosclerosis. N Engl J Med. 2011 May 5;364(18):1746-60. doi: 10.1056/NEJMra1011670. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21542745</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Spronk HM, de Jong AM, Crijns HJ, Schotten U, Van Gelder IC, Ten Cate H. Pleiotropic effects of factor Xa and thrombin: what to expect from novel anticoagulants. Cardiovasc Res. 2014 Mar 1;101(3):344-51. doi: 10.1093/cvr/cvt343. Epub 2014 Jan 2. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24385341</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Esmon CT. Targeting factor Xa and thrombin: impact on coagulation and beyond. Thromb Haemost. 2014 Apr 1;111(4):625-33. doi: 10.1160/TH13-09-0730. Epub 2013 Dec 12. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24336942</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Panza JA, Quyyumi AA, Brush JE Jr, Epstein SE. Abnormal endothelium-dependent vascular relaxation in patients with essential hypertension. N Engl J Med. 1990 Jul 5;323(1):22-7.</citation>
    <PMID>2355955</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mäkimattila S, Virkamäki A, Groop PH, Cockcroft J, Utriainen T, Fagerudd J, Yki-Järvinen H. Chronic hyperglycemia impairs endothelial function and insulin sensitivity via different mechanisms in insulin-dependent diabetes mellitus. Circulation. 1996 Sep 15;94(6):1276-82.</citation>
    <PMID>8822980</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Casino PR, Kilcoyne CM, Quyyumi AA, Hoeg JM, Panza JA. The role of nitric oxide in endothelium-dependent vasodilation of hypercholesterolemic patients. Circulation. 1993 Dec;88(6):2541-7.</citation>
    <PMID>8252665</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Celermajer DS, Sorensen KE, Spiegelhalter DJ, Georgakopoulos D, Robinson J, Deanfield JE. Aging is associated with endothelial dysfunction in healthy men years before the age-related decline in women. J Am Coll Cardiol. 1994 Aug;24(2):471-6.</citation>
    <PMID>8034885</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lerman A, Zeiher AM. Endothelial function: cardiac events. Circulation. 2005 Jan 25;111(3):363-8. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>15668353</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rubinshtein R, Kuvin JT, Soffler M, Lennon RJ, Lavi S, Nelson RE, Pumper GM, Lerman LO, Lerman A. Assessment of endothelial function by non-invasive peripheral arterial tonometry predicts late cardiovascular adverse events. Eur Heart J. 2010 May;31(9):1142-8. doi: 10.1093/eurheartj/ehq010. Epub 2010 Feb 24.</citation>
    <PMID>20181680</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>van Mil ACCM, Pouwels S, Wilbrink J, Warlé MC, Thijssen DHJ. Carotid Artery Reactivity Predicts Events in Peripheral Arterial Disease Patients. Ann Surg. 2019 Apr;269(4):767-773. doi: 10.1097/SLA.0000000000002558.</citation>
    <PMID>29064890</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Leentjens J, Bekkering S, Joosten LAB, Netea MG, Burgner DP, Riksen NP. Trained Innate Immunity as a Novel Mechanism Linking Infection and the Development of Atherosclerosis. Circ Res. 2018 Mar 2;122(5):664-669. doi: 10.1161/CIRCRESAHA.117.312465. Epub 2018 Jan 24. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>29367213</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>December 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>December 23, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 2, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 6, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 9, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 9, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 13, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Peripheral Arterial Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Rivaroxaban</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

