<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04211935</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>19-2794</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04211935</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Identification of Best Postoperative Analgesia Method Following a Minimally Invasive Repair of Pectus Excavatum</brief_title>
  <acronym>(MIRPE)</acronym>
  <official_title>The Use of Video-assisted Intercostal Nerve Cryoablation, Erector Spinae Block, and Thoracic Epidural for Postoperative Analgesia After Minimally Invasive Repair of Pectus Excavatum</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Colorado, Denver</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Children's Hospital Colorado</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Colorado, Denver</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Pectus excavatum is the most common chest wall deformity in children, accounting for 90% of
      all congenital chest wall deformities. It occurs in one to eight per 1000 live births. The
      severity of the pectus deformity may become more noticeable during pubertal growth spurs and
      repair is therefore usually performed in the teenage years. A common operative procedure to
      repair a pectus deformity is the minimally invasive repair of pectus excavatum (MIRPE). The
      MIRPE involves the substernal placement of a contoured metal bar secured to the lateral
      aspect of the ribs. This metal bar allows for correction of the concave deformity by applying
      constant outward pressure to the underside of the sternum. Although the cosmetic results are
      excellent, patients do report significant pain from the constant pressure exerted on the
      chest wall from the metal bar. Pain management approaches tend to differ on both the provider
      and institutional level. There is a lack of evidence regarding which postoperative analgesia
      method is best. To address this research gap, this proposal aims to conduct a randomized
      controlled trail using the three most commonly used methods; 1) patient controlled analgesia
      (PCA); 2) erector spinae blocks (ESB) with continuous infusion pumps; and 3) video-assisted
      intercostal nerve cryoablation (INC).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Pectus excavatum deformity is a common condition in a pediatric surgical practice. While
      MIRPE provides excellent cosmetic results and is associated with shorter operative time and
      lower intraoperative blood loss, the immediate correction of the concave deformity with a
      metal bar places patients in a difficult pain control situation. While multiple postoperative
      analgesia modalities have been studied, there is still a need for a large, prospective,
      randomized trial that is appropriately powered to evaluate the best pain control modality
      after MIRPE. Of the clinically appropriate interventions, ESB and INC have been shown to have
      comparable LOS after the operation, especially when employed as part of an enhanced recovery
      pathway (ERP) bundle. Comparing these newer analgesia modalities to the more established PCA
      approach may help identify the most effective postoperative pain control approach that
      maximizes the safety profile while minimizing the use of narcotic pain medications after
      MIRPE.

      The investigators propose a prospective randomized trial evaluating the effectiveness of INC,
      PCA and ESB with continuous local anesthetic infusion via a pain pump delivery system. All
      groups will follow a multimodal enhanced recovery pathway. Groups will different only in the
      use of INC, PCA, or ESB.

      Since previous studies have reported similarly short LOS for both ESB and INC, but no
      prospective, direct comparisons of these techniques have been done, we believe comparing
      these two groups to the more established PCA modality will further advance the field of post
      MIRPE pain management by providing precise estimates of length of stay (LOS), hospital
      resource utilization, and other important outcomes that have not received sufficient
      attention including pain, quality of life, resumption of activities of daily living, and a
      rigorous survey for potential adverse outcomes. The investigators specifically hypothesize
      that because of the long-term analgesia of up to 2-3 months, the INC group may experience not
      only shorter LOS but decreased narcotic use than the ESB and PCA groups, and also improved
      quality of life, with fewer encounters in the postoperative period (30 days) for pain related
      concerns.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 27, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator)</masking>
    <masking_description>Participants will be randomly assigned to one of three interventional groups. Study participants and team members will be blinded on randomized group until entering the operating room, at which point the cryoablation machine and instruments will be brought into the room for INC or the anesthesiologist will place ESB. The PCA pump will be connected to the patient's intravenous line at the end of the case.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Length of Stay</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>The investigators will measure the total length of stay following the operation until discharge from the hospital.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Total intravenous and oral opioid use</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>The investigators will quantify the total opioid usage during the hospitalization and also at home and will convert the total results to morphine equivalences for standardization.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Postoperative pain</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>The investigators will use reported pain scores to quantify this measure. Scale of 0-10 (0=no pain, 10=worst pain experienced). The investigators will also ask about chest numbness for those in the INC group and will report it on a 0-100% scale (0%=no numbness at all, 100%=completely numb or absent of any sensation).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of life after MIRPE</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>The investigators will use a questionnaire to identify if patients are back to baseline and performing their activities of daily living. The investigators will also ask about resumption of any sports related activities after the appropriate postoperative restriction timeframe has passed. This will be a multiple choice questionnaire that will record if 1) they are back to baseline, 2) they are almost back to baseline, 3) they are not back to baseline at all. The investigators will also ask in a multiple choice manner if they have resumed their activities of daily living. The possible answers will be 1) Yes, 2) Incorporating some of the preoperative activities, 3) No</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Complications</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>The investigators will ask patients about postoperative complications when they are at home. We will also refer back to the chart for any complications that occur during the initial postoperative period or those that have required a readmission after the initial operation.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">158</enrollment>
  <condition>Pectus Excavatum</condition>
  <condition>Pain, Postoperative</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Patient Controlled Analgesia</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>This technique involves connecting a patient controlled analgesia pump to the intravenous line. The patient has the ability to push a button to obtain a predetermined dose of an intravenous opioid with a set lockout time period to minimize the potential for over sedation. PCA pumps will be connected to the intravenous line of the patient at the end of the MIRPE operation. anesthesiologists with experience in regional anesthesia.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Erector Spinae Block</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>This method consists of the anesthesiologist placing two catheters on each side of the vertebrae which then delivers pain medicine continuously via pumps for 2-3 days post-surgery.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intercostal Nerve Cryoablation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The INC technique relies on multilevel freezing of the intercostal neurovascular bundle intraoperatively to block sensation and pain for approximately 2 months postoperatively. Trained pediatric surgeons will perform the INC at the time of a MIRPE procedure.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Use of PCA</intervention_name>
    <description>A commercially available PCA pump will be connected to the patient's intravenous line at the end of the MIRPE operation.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Patient Controlled Analgesia</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Use of ESB for postoperative pain control after MIRPE</intervention_name>
    <description>Pediatric anesthesiologists will place ESB at the time of the MIRPE operation if study participants are randomized into this group.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Erector Spinae Block</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Use of INC for postoperative pain control after MIRPE</intervention_name>
    <description>Pediatric surgeons will perform INC during the MIRPE operation if they are randomized to this group.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intercostal Nerve Cryoablation</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  All patients with a pectus excavatum deformity that will undergo a MIRPE procedure
             will be included in the study.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  &lt; 13 years old

          -  &gt; 18 years old

          -  chronic narcotic preoperative use

          -  previous repair of pectus excavatum deformity

          -  previous thoracic surgery

          -  pregnancy
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>13 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>18 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Jose L Diaz-Miron, MD</last_name>
    <phone>720-777-6571</phone>
    <email>jose.diaz-miron@childrenscolorado.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Children's Hospital Colorado</name>
      <address>
        <city>Aurora</city>
        <state>Colorado</state>
        <zip>80045</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jose L Diaz-Miron, MD</last_name>
      <phone>720-777-6571</phone>
      <email>jose.diaz-miron@childrenscolorado.org</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>December 23, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 24, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">December 26, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 2, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 2, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 4, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Funnel Chest</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pain, Postoperative</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

