<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04212130</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Cumhuriyet University</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04212130</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Can Environmental Cleanliness be Assessed by BCA (Bicinchoninic Acid) Method</brief_title>
  <acronym>BCA</acronym>
  <official_title>The Effect of Fluorescent Marking and BCA Methods of Patient Unit Cleaning in Intensive Care</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Cumhuriyet University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Cumhuriyet University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Effective cleaning of surfaces in the hospital environment is an absolute necessity to reduce
      pathogen transmission. Multi Drug Resistant Organisms (MDRO) in ICU are among the leading
      causes of hospital-acquired infections. Today, the growing prevalence of MDRO has made it
      more important than ever to clean contaminated surfaces with appropriate aseptic cleaning
      procedures, to protect patients and personnel. Despite the disinfection and sterilization
      methods, microorganisms that reach a sufficient concentration in the hospital environment
      survive for long periods and can cause serious transmission via contaminated hands of
      healthcare workers. In this context, surface cleaning and disinfection procedures in the
      hospital environment reduce cross-contamination of the health care units and disease-causing
      pathogens. Recently, environmental cleaning and disinfection have become important as well as
      the evaluation of cleanliness.

      The aim of this study is to evaluate the effectiveness and usability of BCA method, which is
      a new approach in evaluating the effectiveness of environmental cleanliness in intensive care
      units. fluoroscan gel marking, microbiological sampling and BCA assay methods will be
      compared to evaluate the effectiveness and usability of the BCA method. (PRO1 Micro Hygiene
      Monitoring System that System consisting of protein pen and device that analyzes with BCA
      method).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Patients admitted to the ICU are at great risk of developing nosocomial infections, partly
      because of their serious illness and partly because of exposure to life-saving invasive
      procedures. In ICU, implementation of invasive procedures, with the purpose of diagnosis and
      treatment, such as urinary catheter, central-peripheral catheter, intubation, and being
      subject to intensive antibiotic use increase the likelihood of infection. Environmental
      cleanliness is important for preventing infections.

      Effective cleaning of surfaces in the hospital environment is an absolute necessity to reduce
      pathogen transmission. Multi Drug Resistant Organisms (MDRO) in ICU are among the leading
      causes of hospital-acquired infections. Today, the growing prevalence of MDRO has made it
      more important than ever to clean contaminated surfaces with appropriate aseptic cleaning
      procedures, to protect patients and personnel. Despite the disinfection and sterilization
      methods, microorganisms that reach a sufficient concentration in the hospital environment
      survive for long periods and can cause serious transmission via contaminated hands of
      healthcare workers. In this context, surface cleaning and disinfection procedures in the
      hospital environment reduce cross-contamination of the health care units and disease-causing
      pathogens. Recently, environmental cleaning and disinfection have become important as well as
      the evaluation of cleanliness.

      Cleaning of frequently contacted environmental surfaces, monitoring and verifying the
      cleaning results are important for patient safety. The effectiveness of environmental
      cleaning can be assay by different methods. Visual evaluation, ATP (AdenosineTriphosphate)
      measurement, protein tests and fluoroscan marking methods are some of them.

      Evaluation of the patient unit cleanup in the ICU, that is carried out after the discharge of
      patients with infection or colonization that would require strict contact isolation, by
      Fluoroscan Marking, BCA and Microbiological Sampling methods, is planned with the aim of
      collecting data in order to prove the efficiency and clinical employability of the new
      cleaning assessment method, PRO1 Micro Hygiene Monitoring System (System consisting of
      protein pen and device that analyzes with BCA method).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 9, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">April 21, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 16, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To evaluate the effectiveness of cleaning</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>The absence of gel residue on the surfaces indicates that the wiping process is effective. Microbiological samples will determine the presence and amount of bacteria (colony) in the environment. It is aimed that bacteria cannot be produced in the samples taken from the environment after cleaning. The BCA protein samples will be analyzed by the researcher using the PRO 1 Micro hygiene monitoring device. PRO 1 Micro hygiene monitoring device will detect the presence of biological material on the surfaces. The presence and amount of bacteria on the surface will be determined with BCA protein. The presence and amount of bacteria can be detected by BCA protein swab, but not by bacterial species. The device is capable of detecting the biological load between 1 - 10 micrograms. Areas with values above 5 micrograms will be considered as dirty, areas with values below 5 micrograms will be considered as clean</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To evaluate the effectiveness of BCA method</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>If cleaning is not considered to be effective, cleaning will be repeated. If the results of samples taken with BCA protein pen after effective cleaning are below 5 microns, it is concluded that the area, is clean. If the BCA method (micrograms) shows clean or similar results in microbiological samples (colony), it will be concluded that the BCA method can be used to evaluate surface cleanliness.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Nosocomial Infection</condition>
  <condition>Infection Control</condition>
  <condition>Multi-antibiotic Resistance</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Evaluation of environmental cleanliness</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>In this study,
fluorescent marking,
microbiological sampling and
BCA methods will be compared in order to evaluate the effectiveness and usability of BCA method</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>BCA method for assessing environmental cleanliness</intervention_name>
    <description>Evaluating the effectiveness and usability of BCA method which is a new approach in evaluating the effectiveness of environmental cleanliness in intensive care units.
In this study, fluorecan labeling, microbiological sampling and BCA methods will be compared in order to evaluate the effectiveness and usability of BCA method</description>
    <arm_group_label>Evaluation of environmental cleanliness</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Pro 1 Micro Hygiene Monitoring Systems</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        A patient infected with resistant microorganism in the unit is in the same unit for at
        least 72 hours

        The first BCA measurement when the unit is discharged gives a result indicating the unit is
        dirty.-

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  The patient who has been infected with the resistant microorganism in the unit has
             been hospitalized for less than 72 hours

          -  The first BCA measurement when the unit is empty does not give a result indicating
             that the unit is dirty.

          -  Impaired blindness for any reason included in the study

          -  In case the patient is included in the study but new patient admission to the unit
             before the cleaning stages are completed

          -  In the event that other employees who are included in the work but do not complete the
             cleaning stages enter and leave the unit, the work will be terminated.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cumhuriyet University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sivas</city>
        <country>Turkey</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Turkey</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>December 19, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 24, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">December 26, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 21, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 21, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 22, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Cumhuriyet University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Zuhal Gülsoy</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Lead researcher</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Intensive care unit</keyword>
  <keyword>Infection Control</keyword>
  <keyword>Microbiological Monitoring</keyword>
  <keyword>High-touch surfaces</keyword>
  <keyword>Fluorescent marker</keyword>
  <keyword>Hospital environment</keyword>
  <keyword>Cleanliness assessment</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Infection</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Communicable Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cross Infection</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

