<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04215445</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>FF-2019-386</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04215445</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effect of SGLT2 Inhibition on OCT-A Parameters in Diabetic CKD</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effect of Sodium Glucose co Transporter 2 (SGLT2) Inhibition on Optical Coherence Tomography Angiography (OCT-A) Parameters in Diabetic Chronic Kidney Disease (CKD)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National University of Malaysia</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National University of Malaysia</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>Yes</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Diabetes mellitus is a major and growing problem worldwide with many known micro and
      macrovascular complications. According to International Diabetes Federation, there were 285
      million adults diagnosed with diabetes in 2010 and expected to increase to 439 million adult
      in 2030. It is a leading cause of chronic kidney disease (CKD) followed by hypertension,
      glomerulonephritis, and cystic kidney disease. Renal impairment patients metabolize and
      excrete drugs differently from patients with normal renal function and hence only limited
      number of oral hypoglycemic agent (OHA) available for them. One of the choices is sodium
      glucose co-transporter-2 inhibitor (SGLT2i) which is now widely used. Apart from its
      nephroprotective advantage, it also has additional benefit on cardiovascular and renal
      function based on EMPA-REG OUTCOME trial. One of the examples of SGLT2i is Empagliflozin
      (JARDIANCE) tablet, which has FDA U.S. Approval in 2014. It acts by reduces renal
      reabsorption of filtered glucose and lowers the renal threshold for glucose, thus increases
      urinary glucose excretion. It can cause osmotic diuresis, which may lead to intravascular
      volume contraction. Apart from its additional cardiovascular and nephroprotective effect,
      SGLT2 inhibitor might have additional protective effect to the eye. Nowadays, optical
      coherence tomography angiography (OCT-A) has emerged as one of a non-invasive methods to
      study the microvasculature of the retina and choroid. Many studies had discussed
      regarding-pre clinical changes present on OCT-A in patients without clinical diabetic
      retinopathy. These pre-clinical changes includes capillary dropout, microaneurysm,
      neovascularization, venous beading and enlargement of fovea avascular zone. However, there
      are minimal data and publications on different type of diabetic CKD with OCT-A parameters in
      diabetic patients. The purpose of this study is to determine the effect of short term SGLT2
      inhibition on OCT-A parameters (fovea avascular zone (FAZ) size, vessel density and perfusion
      density) in diabetic CKD.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a prospective, single-centred, open-labeled, randomized clinical trial conducted in
      ,University Kebangsaan Malaysia Medical Centre (UKMMC). This is also a Quasi-experimental
      study and all patients from Endocrine, Nephrology and Ophthalmology Clinic in UKM Medical
      Centre from November 2019 till November 2021 will be involved in this study. Patients who
      fulfill the inclusion criteria will be included in this study. All eligible subjects will be
      asked to sign an informed consent.

      Participants will be randomized into two groups, diabetic patient with proteinuria and
      diabetic patient without proteinuria. Participants will be interviewed on demographic data
      (age, gender, race, blood pressure, Body Mass Index) will be taken. Urine sample and
      peripheral blood (2-3ml) is collected from patients in sterile container (EDTA tube) and will
      be sent for urine albumin creatinine ratio (ACR) and HbA1c test. The eye with best fundal and
      signal view on OCT-A will be chosen or if both eyes similar, right eye will be chosen.
      Pre-treatment tests fundus photo and OCT-A measurement will be taken at eye clinic after
      dilating the pupils with 1% tropicamide and 2.5% phenylephrine hydrochloride. Fundus
      examination is taken using a digital mydriatic retinal camera (Topcon Retinal Camera TRC-50DX
      (type 1A), Tokyo Japan. OCT-A measurement is taken by using Cirrus HD-OCT, 2016 Carl Zeiss
      Meditec.

      Then Tab.empagliflozin 25mg once daily for 28 days will be given to both group of patients
      proteinuric and non proteinuric diabetic CKD. After 28 days, post-treatment tests of fundus
      examination and OCT-A measurement will be taken at eye clinic.

      The statistical data analysis will be performed using statistical package for Social Science,
      version 22.0 (SPSS, Inc. Chicago III USA) for IOS. The OCT-A parameters studied (FAZ size,
      vessel density and perfusion density) will be used as main response variables. All variables
      will be defined by method of descriptive statistics. The analysis of quantitative variables
      includes a calculation of mean and standard deviation. T test will be performed to test the
      significant between the 2 groups. Correlation will be measured with Pearson correlation
      coefficient. A p &lt;0.05 will be considered as statistically significant.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">December 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Comparison of change in fovea avascular zone within retina of proteinuric and non-proteinuric chronic kidney disease patients treated with SGLT2-inhibitor</measure>
    <time_frame>After 28 days of treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Change in fovea vascular zone (FAZ) size (um2) from Baseline using Optical Coherence Tomography Angiography (OCT-A) post-SGLT-2 treatment</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Comparison of change in retinal and choroidal vessel density in proteinuric and non-proteinuric chronic kidney disease patients treated with SGLT2-inhibitor</measure>
    <time_frame>After 28 days of treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Change in vessel density (mm-1) from Baseline using Optical Coherence Tomography Angiography (OCT-A) post-SGLT-2 treatment</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Comparison of change in retinal and choroidal vascular perfusion density in proteinuric and non-proteinuric chronic kidney disease patients treated with SGLT2-inhibitor</measure>
    <time_frame>After 28 days of treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Change in perfusion density from Baseline using Optical Coherence Tomography Angiography (OCT-A) post-SGLT-2 treatment</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">90</enrollment>
  <condition>Diabetic Retinopathy</condition>
  <condition>Chronic Kidney Diseases</condition>
  <condition>Diabetes Mellitus</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Proteinuric diabetic CKD</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Tab.empagliflozin 25mg once daily for 28 days</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Non-Proteinuric diabetic CKD</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Tab.empagliflozin 25mg once daily for 28 days</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Empagliflozin 25 MG</intervention_name>
    <description>Tab.empagliflozin 25mg once daily for 28 days</description>
    <arm_group_label>Non-Proteinuric diabetic CKD</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Proteinuric diabetic CKD</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Jardiance</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>OCT-A</intervention_name>
    <description>Optical coherence tomography angiography (OCT-A) is a non-invasive method to study the microvasculature of the retina and choroid.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Non-Proteinuric diabetic CKD</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Proteinuric diabetic CKD</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Cirrus HD-OCT</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients diagnosed with Type 2 DM with CKD (eGFR 45 - 60 ml/min/1.7m2)

          -  Age between 35 and 65 year old

          -  Patients able to give informed consent to participate in the study.

          -  Patients previously not on tablet Empagliflozin

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Heart or respiratory failure, recent MI, shock, hypotension

          -  Pregnancy or lactation.

          -  Known case of CKD due to other causes such as hypertension, renal calculi, analgesic
             nephropathy

          -  Patients with multiple diuretic use.

          -  Hypersensitivity reactions to SGLT2 group of agents

          -  Patient underwent previous ocular intervention (surgery, laser or intraocular
             injection) within 3 months

          -  Dense cataract which could obscured the fundal view and signal strength on OCT-A

          -  HbA1c more than 10%

          -  Systolic blood pressure more than 180mmHg
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>35 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Wan Haslina Wan Abdul Halim, M.D</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Department of Ophthalmology, UKM Medical Centre</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Wan Haslina Wan Abdul Halim, M.D</last_name>
    <phone>+6019-6679633</phone>
    <email>afifiyad@yahoo.co.uk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UKM Medical Centre</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kuala Lumpur</city>
        <state>Wilayah Persekutuan</state>
        <zip>56000</zip>
        <country>Malaysia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Wan Haslina Wan Abdul Halim, M.D</last_name>
      <phone>+6019-6679633</phone>
      <email>afifiyad@yahoo.co.uk</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Wan Haslina Wan Abdul Halim, M.D</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Yong Meng Hsien, M.D</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Norasyikin A. Wahab, M.D</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Rozita Mohd, M.D</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ruslinda Mustafar, M.D</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Siti Husna Hussein, M.D</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Malaysia</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cho NH, Shaw JE, Karuranga S, Huang Y, da Rocha Fernandes JD, Ohlrogge AW, Malanda B. IDF Diabetes Atlas: Global estimates of diabetes prevalence for 2017 and projections for 2045. Diabetes Res Clin Pract. 2018 Apr;138:271-281. doi: 10.1016/j.diabres.2018.02.023. Epub 2018 Feb 26.</citation>
    <PMID>29496507</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>American Diabetes Association. 10. Microvascular Complications and Foot Care: Standards of Medical Care in Diabetes-2018. Diabetes Care. 2018 Jan;41(Suppl 1):S105-S118. doi: 10.2337/dc18-S010. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>29222381</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>National Renal Registry Malaysia. 20th report of the Malaysian Dialysis &amp; Transplant Registry 2013. Minist Heal Malaysia. 2013. Doi: 10.1143/JJAP.35.L657</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Port J Nephrol Hypert 2017; 31(2): 122-131 • Advance Access publication 29 May 2017. Diabetic Nephropathy and its two phenotypes: the proteinuric and non-proteinuric Regina Silva, Catarina Meng, Luís Coentrão</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bolignano D, Zoccali C. Non-proteinuric rather than proteinuric renal diseases are the leading cause of end-stage kidney disease. Nephrol Dial Transplant. 2017 Apr 1;32(suppl_2):ii194-ii199. doi: 10.1093/ndt/gfw440.</citation>
    <PMID>28340010</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Perez-Monteoliva, N. R., Robles et al. Non-proteinuric diabetic nephropathy is the main cause of chronic kidney disease. Journal of Hypertension: June 2018 - Volume 36 - Issue - p e11. doi: 10.1097/01.hjh.0000538992.55964.f1</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Garg AX, Kiberd BA, Clark WF, Haynes RB, Clase CM. Albuminuria and renal insufficiency prevalence guides population screening: results from the NHANES III. Kidney Int. 2002 Jun;61(6):2165-75.</citation>
    <PMID>12028457</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rodriguez-Poncelas A, Garre-Olmo J, Franch-Nadal J, Diez-Espino J, Mundet-Tuduri X, Barrot-De la Puente J, Coll-de Tuero G; RedGDPS Study Group. Prevalence of chronic kidney disease in patients with type 2 diabetes in Spain: PERCEDIME2 study. BMC Nephrol. 2013 Feb 22;14:46. doi: 10.1186/1471-2369-14-46.</citation>
    <PMID>23433046</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Penno G, Solini A, Bonora E, Fondelli C, Orsi E, Zerbini G, Trevisan R, Vedovato M, Gruden G, Cavalot F, Cignarelli M, Laviola L, Morano S, Nicolucci A, Pugliese G; Renal Insufficiency And Cardiovascular Events (RIACE) Study Group. Clinical significance of nonalbuminuric renal impairment in type 2 diabetes. J Hypertens. 2011 Sep;29(9):1802-9. doi: 10.1097/HJH.0b013e3283495cd6.</citation>
    <PMID>21738053</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Retnakaran R, Cull CA, Thorne KI, Adler AI, Holman RR; UKPDS Study Group. Risk factors for renal dysfunction in type 2 diabetes: U.K. Prospective Diabetes Study 74. Diabetes. 2006 Jun;55(6):1832-9.</citation>
    <PMID>16731850</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zinman B, Wanner C, Lachin JM, Fitchett D, Bluhmki E, Hantel S, Mattheus M, Devins T, Johansen OE, Woerle HJ, Broedl UC, Inzucchi SE; EMPA-REG OUTCOME Investigators. Empagliflozin, Cardiovascular Outcomes, and Mortality in Type 2 Diabetes. N Engl J Med. 2015 Nov 26;373(22):2117-28. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa1504720. Epub 2015 Sep 17.</citation>
    <PMID>26378978</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Škrtić M, Cherney DZ. Sodium-glucose cotransporter-2 inhibition and the potential for renal protection in diabetic nephropathy. Curr Opin Nephrol Hypertens. 2015 Jan;24(1):96-103. doi: 10.1097/MNH.0000000000000084. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25470017</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Komala MG, Panchapakesan U, Pollock C, Mather A. Sodium glucose cotransporter 2 and the diabetic kidney. Curr Opin Nephrol Hypertens. 2013 Jan;22(1):113-9. doi: 10.1097/MNH.0b013e32835a17ae. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23042029</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>JARDIANCE current prescribing information and medication guide, www.jardiance.com. Boerhringer Ingelheim International GambH.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Vasilakou D, Karagiannis T, Athanasiadou E, Mainou M, Liakos A, Bekiari E, Sarigianni M, Matthews DR, Tsapas A. Sodium-glucose cotransporter 2 inhibitors for type 2 diabetes: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Ann Intern Med. 2013 Aug 20;159(4):262-74. doi: 10.7326/0003-4819-159-4-201308200-00007. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24026259</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nishimura R, Tanaka Y, Koiwai K, Inoue K, Hach T, Salsali A, Lund SS, Broedl UC. Effect of empagliflozin monotherapy on postprandial glucose and 24-hour glucose variability in Japanese patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus: a randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled, 4-week study. Cardiovasc Diabetol. 2015 Jan 30;14:11. doi: 10.1186/s12933-014-0169-9.</citation>
    <PMID>25633683</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yoshizumi H, Ejima T, Nagao T, Wakisaka M. Recovery from Diabetic Macular Edema in a Diabetic Patient After Minimal Dose of a Sodium Glucose Co-Transporter 2 Inhibitor. Am J Case Rep. 2018 Apr 19;19:462-466.</citation>
    <PMID>29670074</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mieno H, Yoneda K, Yamazaki M, Sakai R, Sotozono C, Fukui M. The Efficacy of Sodium-Glucose Cotransporter 2 (SGLT2) inhibitors for the treatment of chronic diabetic macular oedema in vitrectomised eyes: a retrospective study. BMJ Open Ophthalmol. 2018 Jul 23;3(1):e000130. doi: 10.1136/bmjophth-2017-000130. eCollection 2018.</citation>
    <PMID>30123844</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>SGLT2- inhibition with Empaglifozin Reduces Progression of Diabetic Retinopathy in Patients With High Risk of Diabetic Macular Edema (The SUPER-Trial)</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Thompson IA, Durrani AK, Patel S. Optical coherence tomography angiography characteristics in diabetic patients without clinical diabetic retinopathy. Eye (Lond). 2019 Apr;33(4):648-652. doi: 10.1038/s41433-018-0286-x. Epub 2018 Dec 3.</citation>
    <PMID>30510234</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Goudot MM, Sikorav A, Semoun O, Miere A, Jung C, Courbebaisse B, Srour M, Freiha JG, Souied EH. Parafoveal OCT Angiography Features in Diabetic Patients without Clinical Diabetic Retinopathy: A Qualitative and Quantitative Analysis. J Ophthalmol. 2017;2017:8676091. doi: 10.1155/2017/8676091. Epub 2017 Jun 29.</citation>
    <PMID>28761762</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sandhu HS, Eladawi N, Elmogy M, Keynton R, Helmy O, Schaal S, El-Baz A. Automated diabetic retinopathy detection using optical coherence tomography angiography: a pilot study. Br J Ophthalmol. 2018 Nov;102(11):1564-1569. doi: 10.1136/bjophthalmol-2017-311489. Epub 2018 Jan 23.</citation>
    <PMID>29363532</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ashraf M, Nesper PL, Jampol LM, Yu F, Fawzi AA. Statistical Model of Optical Coherence Tomography Angiography Parameters That Correlate With Severity of Diabetic Retinopathy. Invest Ophthalmol Vis Sci. 2018 Aug 1;59(10):4292-4298. doi: 10.1167/iovs.18-24142.</citation>
    <PMID>30167660</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lee DH, Yi HC, Bae SH, Cho JH, Choi SW, Kim H. Risk factors for retinal microvascular impairment in type 2 diabetic patients without diabetic retinopathy. PLoS One. 2018 Aug 9;13(8):e0202103. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0202103. eCollection 2018.</citation>
    <PMID>30092018</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ting DSW, Tan GSW, Agrawal R, Yanagi Y, Sie NM, Wong CW, San Yeo IY, Lee SY, Cheung CMG, Wong TY. Optical Coherence Tomographic Angiography in Type 2 Diabetes and Diabetic Retinopathy. JAMA Ophthalmol. 2017 Apr 1;135(4):306-312. doi: 10.1001/jamaophthalmol.2016.5877.</citation>
    <PMID>28208170</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cheung CY, Tang F, Ng DS, Wong R, Lok J, Sun Z, Tso T, Lam A, Brelén M, Chong KK, Luk AO, Chan JC, Wong TY, Tham CC. The Relationship of Quantitative Retinal Capillary Network to Kidney Function in Type 2 Diabetes. Am J Kidney Dis. 2018 Jun;71(6):916-918. doi: 10.1053/j.ajkd.2017.12.010. Epub 2018 Feb 28.</citation>
    <PMID>29501263</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>CIRRUS HD-OCT User Manual- Models 500, 5000 ©2016 Carl Zeiss Meditec, Inc</citation>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>December 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>December 25, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 29, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 2, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 29, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 29, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 2, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>National University of Malaysia</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Wan Haslina Wan Abdul Halim</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Consultant Ophthalmologist-Cornea And Anterior Segment</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Diabetic Retinopathy</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Kidney Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Renal Insufficiency, Chronic</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Empagliflozin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

