<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04210375</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>JK07.1.01</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04210375</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study of JK07 in Subjects With Heart Failure With Reduced Ejection Fraction (HFrEF)</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized, Double-Blind, Placebo-controlled, Single-ascending Dose Study to Assess the Safety, Tolerability, and Pharmacokinetics of JK07 in Subjects With Heart Failure With Reduced Ejection Fraction (HFrEF)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Salubris Biotherapeutics Inc</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Salubris Biotherapeutics Inc</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a Phase 1, randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled, single-ascending dose study
      to assess the safety, tolerability, immunogenicity, PK, and exploratory efficacy of JK07 in
      subjects 18 to 80 years of age with HFrEF ≤40%.

      Initially 5 cohorts are planned with the option to expand the study to a total of 7 cohorts.
      The size of the cohorts will range from 5 to 9 subjects. Each cohort will include one single
      active unblinded sentinel subject receiving a single IV dose of JK07 prior to randomized
      single dose administration of JK07 or placebo [3:1] in the remainder of the cohort.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a Phase 1, randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled, single-ascending dose study
      to assess the safety, tolerability, immunogenicity, PK, and exploratory efficacy of JK07 in
      HF subjects 18 to 80 years of age with LVEF ≤40%. Subjects must have been maintained on an
      optimal HF medical regimen for at least 3 months prior to enrollment and remain on the same
      treatment regimen throughout the course of the study, per the 2017 ACC/AHA/HFSA) treatment
      guidelines.

      At screening, eligible subjects will undergo a physical examination, 2-dimensional
      transthoracic echocardiography (2D-TTE), ECG assessment, blood sampling for laboratory
      parameters, and urine testing. Safety assessments at screening will include hematology,
      biochemistry, coagulation, liver, and thyroid function.

      Subjects will be observed in the hospital on continuous telemetry from the time of hospital
      admission until shortly before discharge approximately 48 hours later. During this time, they
      will additionally have safety labs, vital signs, PK and biomarker samples collected, and ECGs
      and 2D-TTEs performed.

      Only a single dose of the investigational product will be administered and only a single
      hospital admission is planned per subject during the study. Subjects will complete follow-up
      visits through 180 days after administration of the investigational product.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">July 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 15, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 15, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Double-blind, placebo-controlled, single-ascending dose with single active sentinel subject per cohort</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence and severity of treatment-emergent adverse events [safety and tolerability]</measure>
    <time_frame>Screening to 30 days</time_frame>
    <description>All safety information will be collected and evaluated</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetics (area under the concentration versus time curve) of JK07</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to 60 days</time_frame>
    <description>Blood samples will be taken on Days 1-4, and Days 7, 11, 15, 22, 30, and 60</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Left ventricular and systemic vascular resistance assessment</measure>
    <time_frame>Screening to 180 days</time_frame>
    <description>2D-transthoracic echocardiography</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Biomarkers</measure>
    <time_frame>Screening to 180 days</time_frame>
    <description>Assessment of potential predictive biomarkers</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Concentration-QT correlation</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to Day 3</time_frame>
    <description>Assess the possible relationship between JK07 plasma concentrations and any observed change in QT intervals</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">63</enrollment>
  <condition>Heart Failure With Reduced Ejection Fraction</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>JK07</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Single dose of JK07 administered by intravenous infusion over 60 minutes</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Matching Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Single dose of placebo administered by intravenous infusion over 60 minutes</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>JK07</intervention_name>
    <description>Recombinant fusion protein consisting of a fully human immunoglobulin G1 monoclonal antibody and an active polypeptide fragment of the human growth factor NRG-1</description>
    <arm_group_label>JK07</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Matching Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Vehicle control</description>
    <arm_group_label>Matching Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Adults 18 and 80 years with stable NYHA Class II or III HF diagnosis (ischemic or
             non-ischemic confirmed by medical history) at least 6 months prior to enrollment as
             confirmed by medical history.

          2. Stable HF defined as no hospitalizations for cardiac-related issues within the
             previous 3 months prior to the screening visit or between screening and randomization,
             other than for routine device generator changes.

          3. Subjects with clearly interpretable echocardiographic images and with a screening LVEF
             ≤ 40% in the absence of ≥ Grade 3 valvular disease on 2D-TTE.

          4. Subjects must be taking clinician-directed appropriate pharmacological therapy for HF
             as per the 2017 ACC/AHA/HFSA treatment guidelines at stable doses (except for
             diuretics) for at least 3 months prior to screening. Subjects with implantable
             cardioverter-defibrillators (ICDs), if the devices are not &quot;pacing&quot;, are eligible.

          5. Body mass index ≥18 kg/m2 and ≤40 kg/m2.

          6. Screening hemoglobin ≥9.0 g/dL, platelets ≥100 K/mL, ANC ≥1500/mL.

          7. Able and willing to use adequate contraception until the end of the study.

          8. Capable of providing informed consent and to comply with the protocol.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Participating in any other study, have received any other investigational drug within
             30 days prior to screening or 5-half-lives or any other investigational implanted
             device within 30 days prior to screening, or are taking part in a nonmedication study
             which, in the opinion of the Investigator, would interfere with study compliance or
             outcome assessments.

          2. Any past participation in a study that has investigated the NRG-1 pathway (e.g.,
             Neucardin, Cimaglermin).

          3. Heart failure due to hypertrophic cardiomyopathy, restrictive cardiomyopathy,
             arrhythmogenic right ventricula dysplasia (ARVD), stress-induced (&quot;Takotsubo&quot;)
             cardiomyopathy, chemotherapy-induced cardiomyopathy, peripartum cardiomyopathy,
             infiltrative or inflammatory cardiomyopathies, and primary valvular disease.

          4. Acute coronary syndrome within 3 months of screening or acute MI within 6 months of
             screening.

          5. Cardiac surgery, coronary artery revascularization, percutaneous coronary
             intervention, or valvuloplasty within 3 months prior to screening.

          6. Any subject who has received an indication for coronary revascularization within 3
             months prior to screening.

          7. Any major surgical procedure within 1 month prior to screening or planned surgical
             procedure during the study period.

          8. Sustained systolic blood pressure &lt;100 mm Hg and/or diastolic blood pressure &lt;50 mm
             Hg.

          9. Sustained resting heart rate &gt;100 beats per minute.

         10. Cerebrovascular accident or hospitalizations for CV (cardiovascular) causes other than
             routine device generator changes, including HF, chest pain, stroke, transient ischemic
             attack, or arrhythmias within 3 months prior to randomization.

         11. At screening have an abnormal or clinically significant 12-lead ECG abnormality, ei.;
             (QRS &gt;120 msec, PR &gt;210 msec, heart rate (HR) &lt;45 bpm, sustained HR &gt;100 bpm) that, in
             the opinion of the Investigator, would affect efficacy or safety evaluation or place
             the subject at risk.

         12. History or evidence of clinically significant arrhythmia uncontrolled by drug therapy
             or use of an implantable defibrillator, long QT syndrome, or evidence of QT
             prolongation with QTcF &gt;450 ms for males or QTcF &gt;470 ms for females prior to
             randomization.

         13. Clinically significant renal dysfunction as measured by the estimated GFR &lt;45
             mL/min/1.73m2 at screening, or a clinically significant change in renal function
             between screening and baseline.

         14. Clinically significant liver dysfunction as measured by: ALT &gt;2.0 × ULN, alkaline
             phosphatase &gt; 2.0 × ULN, AST &gt;2.0 × the ULN, or GGT &gt;2.0 × the ULN or serum bilirubin
             ≥ 1.2 × the ULN at screening, or a clinically significant change in liver function
             between screening and baseline.

         15. Subjects with alteration of the coagulation panel (INR) and/or PT ≥ 1.5 × the ULN;
             aPTT ≥ 1.5 × ULN, or serum albumin ≤ 3 gm/dL. For subjects on warfarin or other
             anticoagulants, an INR (or PT/PTT) considered by the Principal Investigator as
             therapeutically appropriate will be allowed.

         16. Subjects with values of CPK and/or CK-MB &gt;2.5 times normal institutional limits at
             screening.

         17. Any subject who by Investigator's judgement, has a significant hematuria or
             proteinuria at screening.

         18. Concurrent treatment with Class I or III antiarrhythmic drugs (unless the medication
             was discontinued more than 3 months before proposed enrollment).

         19. Positive screening for HIV antibodies, hepatitis B surface antigen, or hepatitis C
             virus antibodies.

         20. Known history of or active alcohol abuse (no more than 14 units/week for males or 7
             units/week for females) or use of illicit drugs within 1 year prior to randomization
             other than recreational use of marijuana or cannabis-based products.

         21. Other medical or psychiatric condition that, in the opinion of the Investigator, would
             preclude obtaining voluntary consent/assent or would confound the secondary objectives
             of study.

         22. A history of malignancy of any type or any pre-malignant condition (e.g. ductal
             carcinoma in situ, colonic polyp, or cervical atypia). All subjects are to undergo
             cancer screening following study enrollment in accordance with American Cancer Society
             Guidelines.

         23. Pregnant or lactating female subjects at screening.

         24. Subjects with clinically significant or poorly controlled disease including, but not
             limited to, endocrine (including diabetes and thyroid) disease, neurological or
             psychiatric (even mild), GI, hematological, urological, immunological, or ophthalmic
             diseases as determined by the Investigator.

         25. Subjects who are not non-smokers or light smokers (no more than 5 cigarettes per day)
             and who cannot abstain from smoking from 2 weeks prior to the administration of IP
             through the end of the study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Wilson Tang, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>The Cleveland Clinic</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Sam Murphy, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>617-584-3853</phone>
    <email>sam.murphy@salubrisbio.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>John Li, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>301-828-8579</phone>
    <email>john.li@salubrisbio.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Arizona College of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tucson</city>
        <state>Arizona</state>
        <zip>85724-5039</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Nancy Sweitzer, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>520-626-2000</phone>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Lizzette Cruz</last_name>
      <phone>(520) 626-2471</phone>
      <email>marquez@shc.arizona.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Stanford University Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Stanford</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94305</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Matthew Wheeler, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>650-723-5468</phone>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Jennifer Kim</last_name>
      <phone>(650) 725-6911</phone>
      <email>jennckim@stanford.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Harvard Medical School/ Massachusetts General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02114-2696</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Nasrien E Ibrahim, MD</last_name>
      <phone>617-726-9554</phone>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Lizzie Suschana</last_name>
      <phone>(617) 726-2488</phone>
      <email>ESUSCHANA@mgh.harvard.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cleveland Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cleveland</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>44195</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Wilson Tang, MD</last_name>
      <phone>216-444-6697</phone>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Teresa Fonk</last_name>
      <phone>(216) 445-1766</phone>
      <email>fonkt@ccf.org</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Oregon Health Science University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Portland</city>
        <state>Oregon</state>
        <zip>97239</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Johannes Steiner, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>John Halvorson</last_name>
      <phone>(503) 418-1679</phone>
      <email>halvorsj@ohsu.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital of the University of Pennsylvania</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19104</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Joyce W Wald, DO</last_name>
      <phone>215-615-0719</phone>
      <email>joyce.wald@uphs.upenn.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Nicole Escobar</last_name>
      <phone>(609) 519-8366</phone>
      <email>Nicole.Escobar@Pennmedicine.upenn.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>December 17, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 23, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">December 24, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 29, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 29, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 2, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>heart failure</keyword>
  <keyword>HFrEF</keyword>
  <keyword>neuregulin 1</keyword>
  <keyword>NRG-1</keyword>
  <keyword>heregulin</keyword>
  <keyword>HER3</keyword>
  <keyword>HER4</keyword>
  <keyword>ErbB3</keyword>
  <keyword>ErbB4</keyword>
  <keyword>reduced ejection fraction</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Heart Failure</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

