<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04211181</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HAVEN-VTE</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04211181</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>HAVEN-VTE Study in Hospitalized Patients to Prevent Hospital-Acquired Venous Thromboembolism</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effects of the System-wide Multifaceted Intervention for Implementing on Venous Thromboembolism Prophylaxis Among Hospitalized Patients in China: A Cluster-Randomized Clinical Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>China-Japan Friendship Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>China-Japan Friendship Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Although pharmacologic and mechanical methods to prevent VTE are safe, effective,
      cost-effective, and advocated by authoritative guidelines,many studies continue to
      demonstrate that these preventive methods are significantly underutilized, especially in
      China.A number of quality improvements (QI) program have been established in several
      countries or hospitals.However,no exit effective protocol has been demonstrated well enough
      or adequate to drive breakthrough levels of improvement. A reliable and practical QI that can
      support hospitals or physicians in China is warranted.To evaluate the multifaceted quality
      improvement intervention effect in clinical setting, we will conduct a cluster-randomized
      clinical trial among China PUlmonary Thromboembolism REgistry Study (CURES) group, aiming to
      test whether it's applicable to real-world practice in China.

      A multicenter, two-arms, open-label clinical trial has been designed to determine whether the
      system-wide multifaceted intervention could increase the rate of at-risk participants who
      received prophylaxis (RP) and decrease the incidence of any hospital-associated VTE in 90
      days during and after hospital admission. .Selected hospital will be regarded as a cluster
      and randomized into interventional or control group.In interventional group, eligible
      hospitalized patients will receive a variety of the multifaceted quality improvement(QI)
      interventions since admitted in hospital.In control group, patients will receive no more than
      common recommended care or an existing policy.The primary outcomes are the proportion of
      appropriate prophylaxis in hospitalized patients and the incidence of HA-VTE in 90 days after
      hospital admission.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Hospitals nationwide which have willingness to participate this study in CURES group will be
      selected. Each selected hospital will be regarded as a cluster and randomized into
      interventional or control group.

      During the study period, eligible patients enrolled in hospitals assigned to interventional
      group will receive a variety of the multifaceted quality improvement(QI) interventions,
      including mandatory risk assessment, a computer alert(computer-based clinical decision
      support system and computerized reminders), strengthened education, and audit. Patients in
      hospitals assigned to control group will receive common recommended care only, or an existing
      policy.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">February 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 30, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 30, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of appropriate prophylaxis rate during hospitalization</measure>
    <time_frame>90 days after hospital admission</time_frame>
    <description>The proportion of appropriate prophylaxis is defined as the number of appropriate prophylaxis among the patients at risk of VTE and without corresponding contraindications.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The proportion of participants who developed the VTE(all, symptomatic, asymptomatic VTE)</measure>
    <time_frame>90 days after hospital admission</time_frame>
    <description>The incidence of HA-VTE is defined as the proportion of participants who developed the VTE(all, symptomatic, asymptomatic VTE)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>All-cause mortality</measure>
    <time_frame>90 days after hospital admission</time_frame>
    <description>Proportion of participants who was dead(all-cause mortality)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of complications related to the intervention</measure>
    <time_frame>90 days after hospital admission</time_frame>
    <description>complications(i.e. major bleeding,minor bleeding, thrombocytopenia) related to the intervention</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">4800</enrollment>
  <condition>Venous Thromboembolic Disease</condition>
  <condition>Pulmonary Embolism</condition>
  <condition>Venous Thromboembolism</condition>
  <condition>Deep Venous Thrombosis</condition>
  <condition>Quality Improvement</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>The multifaceted QI interventions</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Hospitals randomized into experimental group will implement follow interventions including：the distribution of the guideline and pathway, a computer alert(computer-based clinical decision support system and computerized reminders),audit and feedback.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Routine VTE prophylaxis in local clinical practice</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients in the routine VTE prophylaxis(control) group will receive routine VTE prophylaxis according to current guidelines and clinical practices.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>The multifaceted interventions</intervention_name>
    <description>An evidence-based clinical guideline and pathway in hospital.
A series Written care protocols for the implementation of performance measures.
A computer-based clinical decision support system(CDSSs) and a computerized reminder, which was referred to as a key element to enhance VTE assessment and prophylaxis. A well-designed computer program will be integrated into the Electronic Medical Record(EMR) of intervention group and By processing, analyzing, summarizing and representing crucial information, physicians can be altered.
A full-time quality coordinator
A trained physician or nurse in each intervention cluster will be acted as a quality coordinator. The responsibility of the quality coordinator includes:</description>
    <arm_group_label>The multifaceted QI interventions</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Routine VTE prophylaxis</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients randomized to the Routine VTE prophylaxis (Control) group will receive routine VTE prophylaxis according to current guidelines and clinical practices</description>
    <arm_group_label>Routine VTE prophylaxis in local clinical practice</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Aged ≥14 years

          2. Have an expected hospital stay ≥72 hours for medical and/or surgical treatment

          3. Written informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Inability to be followed-up at until 3 months after randomization

          2. Have participated in similar trials or are undergoing other clinical trials

          3. Refuse or are unable to give informed consent

          4. VTE identified on CTPA or lower extremity vein ultrasound at or any time before
             enrollment

          5. Requiring a full dose of anticoagulant treatment (e.g., recent VTE, atrial
             fibrillation).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>14 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Zhenguo Zhai, Doctor</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>China-Japan Friendship Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Zhenguo Zhai, Doctor</last_name>
    <phone>86-10-84206265</phone>
    <email>zhaizhenguo2011@126.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <reference>
    <citation>Piazza G, Rosenbaum EJ, Pendergast W, Jacobson JO, Pendleton RC, McLaren GD, Elliott CG, Stevens SM, Patton WF, Dabbagh O, Paterno MD, Catapane E, Li Z, Goldhaber SZ. Physician alerts to prevent symptomatic venous thromboembolism in hospitalized patients. Circulation. 2009 Apr 28;119(16):2196-201. doi: 10.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.108.841197. Epub 2009 Apr 13. Erratum in: Circulation. 2010 Jul 6;122(1):e4.</citation>
    <PMID>19364975</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pai M, Lloyd NS, Cheng J, Thabane L, Spencer FA, Cook DJ, Haynes RB, Schünemann HJ, Douketis JD. Strategies to enhance venous thromboprophylaxis in hospitalized medical patients (SENTRY): a pilot cluster randomized trial. Implement Sci. 2013 Jan 2;8:1. doi: 10.1186/1748-5908-8-1.</citation>
    <PMID>23279972</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kucher N, Koo S, Quiroz R, Cooper JM, Paterno MD, Soukonnikov B, Goldhaber SZ. Electronic alerts to prevent venous thromboembolism among hospitalized patients. N Engl J Med. 2005 Mar 10;352(10):969-77.</citation>
    <PMID>15758007</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Writing Group for the CHECKLIST-ICU Investigators and the Brazilian Research in Intensive Care Network (BRICNet), Cavalcanti AB, Bozza FA, Machado FR, Salluh JI, Campagnucci VP, Vendramim P, Guimaraes HP, Normilio-Silva K, Damiani LP, Romano E, Carrara F, Lubarino Diniz de Souza J, Silva AR, Ramos GV, Teixeira C, Brandão da Silva N, Chang CC, Angus DC, Berwanger O. Effect of a Quality Improvement Intervention With Daily Round Checklists, Goal Setting, and Clinician Prompting on Mortality of Critically Ill Patients: A Randomized Clinical Trial. JAMA. 2016 Apr 12;315(14):1480-90. doi: 10.1001/jama.2016.3463.</citation>
    <PMID>27115264</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Garcia DA, Highfill J, Finnerty K, Varoz E, McConkey S, Hutchinson K, Libby E. A prospective, controlled trial of a pharmacy-driven alert system to increase thromboprophylaxis rates in medical inpatients. Blood Coagul Fibrinolysis. 2009 Oct;20(7):541-5. doi: 10.1097/MBC.0b013e32832d6cfc.</citation>
    <PMID>19584716</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fontaine A, Mahé I, Bergmann JF, Fiessinger JN, Dhote R, Cohen P, Vinceneux P. Effectiveness of written guidelines on the appropriateness of thromboprophylaxis prescriptions for medical patients: a prospective randomized study. J Intern Med. 2006 Oct;260(4):369-76.</citation>
    <PMID>16961674</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>December 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>December 8, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 24, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">December 26, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 24, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 24, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">December 26, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>China-Japan Friendship Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Zhenguo Zhai,MD,PhD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Quality improvement</keyword>
  <keyword>Venous Thromboembolism</keyword>
  <keyword>Hospital Associated-VTE</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pulmonary Embolism</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Thrombosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Thromboembolism</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Embolism</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Venous Thromboembolism</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Venous Thrombosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

