<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04218279</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>STUDY19080090</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>DTNH2215R00029</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04218279</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The EMS Sleep Health Study: A Randomized Controlled Trial</brief_title>
  <official_title>The EMS Sleep Health and Fatigue Study: A Randomized Controlled Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Pittsburgh</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Highway Traffic Safety Administration (NHTSA)</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Association of State EMS Officials (NASEMSO)</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Pittsburgh</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The experiment seeks to determine the impact of a sleep health and fatigue education and
      training program on diverse indicators of sleep and fatigue among Emergency Medical Services
      (EMS) personnel. The overarching goals of this research study are to [1] enhance our
      understanding of the relationships between shift work, sleep, and fatigue in EMS operations;
      and [2] determine whether or not providing education and training to EMS personnel on the
      importance of sleep health and dangers of fatigue impact indicators of sleep and fatigue. The
      investigators will accomplish these goals by using a cluster-randomized trial study design
      with a wait-list control group.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The overarching goals of this research study are to:

        1. enhance our understanding of the relationships between shift work, sleep, and fatigue in
           EMS operations; and

        2. determine whether or not providing education and training to EMS personnel on the
           importance of sleep health and dangers of fatigue impact indicators of sleep and
           fatigue.

      The investigators will recruit EMS nationwide for EMS agencies to participate in this study
      and focus on moderately sized EMS agencies with between 50 and 300 employees (yet we will not
      outright exclude smaller or larger organizations). Agencies that run dual ground-based and
      air-medical EMS services are eligible. Maximum enrollment at the agency-level is n=30 EMS
      agencies. Agencies will be randomized upon enrollment to one of two arms: [1] Intervention
      group; or [2] the Wait-List control group. The intervention group will receive immediate
      access to the intervention materials (the 10 brief Sleep Health Education Modules). The
      wait-list control group will receive access to intervention materials at 3 months post
      enrollment/baseline.

      Within each agency, the investigators will recruit individual EMS clinicians to participate.
      Goal enrollment within each agency is a minimum of 30 and a maximum of 50 EMS clinicians.

      All individual EMS clinician participants will undergo informed consent, answer a baseline
      survey, and be queried via mobile phone text message at regular intervals which will begin
      upon enrollment. These mobile phone text message queries will assess indicators of sleep and
      fatigue. All participants will be asked to answer two follow up surveys at 3 months and 6
      months. The total duration of study participation is 6 months. The primary outcome of
      interest is sleep quality as measured by the Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index (PSQI). The
      secondary outcome of interest is fatigue as measured by the Chalder Fatigue Questionnaire
      (CFQ).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 24, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 31, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 31, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
    <masking_description>Unblinded</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in Sleep Quality at 3 months</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline to 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Sleep quality will be measured with the Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index (PSQI) tool. Scores range from 0-21 with scores greater than or equal to 6 classified as poor sleep quality.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in Sleep Quality at 6 months</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline to 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Sleep quality will be measured with the Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index (PSQI) tool. Scores range from 0-21 with scores greater than or equal to 6 classified as poor sleep quality.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in Fatigue at 3 months</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline to 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Fatigue will be measured with the Chalder Fatigue Questionnaire (CFQ). The CFQ is a brief 11-item survey tool that measures mental and physical fatigue with scores ranging from 0-11. Scores 4 or greater indicate severe fatigue.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in Fatigue at 6 months</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline to 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Fatigue will be measured with the Chalder Fatigue Questionnaire (CFQ). The CFQ is a brief 11-item survey tool that measures mental and physical fatigue with scores ranging from 0-11. Scores 4 or greater indicate severe fatigue.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">1500</enrollment>
  <condition>Sleep Quality</condition>
  <condition>Fatigue</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sleep Health Education</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>At baseline, the experimental group will have immediate access to 10 brief education modules focused on diverse elements of sleep health and fatigue.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Wait List Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>At 3 months after baseline, the wait-list control group will be provided access to the 10 education modules focused on diverse elements of sleep health and fatigue..</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sleep Health Education</intervention_name>
    <description>Intervention materials include 10 brief education modules that the target population will review/view on a secure study-specific website.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Sleep Health Education</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Wait List Control</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  EMS Personnel:

               1. 18 years of age or older

               2. Currently working as an EMS clinician

               3. Working a minimum of one shift a week

               4. Working &amp; residing in the United States

               5. Working at one of the EMS organizations that agreed to participate in this study

               6. Have a cellular, mobile, or smart phone that can send and receive text messages

               7. Willing to answer online surveys and respond to text-message queries for seven
                  days in a row every third week of the month for a total of 24 weeks/6 months

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  EMS Personnel:

               1. Individuals &lt;18 years of age

               2. Not currently working as an EMS clinician

               3. Does not work a minimum of one shift a week

               4. Does not work and/reside in the United States

               5. Does not work at one of the EMS organizations that agreed to participate in this
                  study

               6. Does not have a cellular, mobile, or smart phone that can send and receive text
                  messages

               7. Is not willing to answer online surveys and respond to text-message queries for
                  seven days in a row every third week of the month for a total of 24 weeks/6
                  months.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>100 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Daniel Patterson</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Pittsburgh</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Daniel Patterson</last_name>
    <phone>412-864-3830</phone>
    <email>pdp3@pitt.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Beth Wesoloski</last_name>
    <phone>412-647-0517</phone>
    <email>wesoloskiba@upmc.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Pittsburgh</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pittsburgh</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>15261</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Daniel Patterson</last_name>
      <phone>412-843-3830</phone>
      <email>pdp3@pitt.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Beth Wesoloski</last_name>
      <phone>412-647-0517</phone>
      <email>wesoloskiba@upmc.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 2, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 2, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 6, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 25, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 25, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 26, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Pittsburgh</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Daniel Patterson, PhD, NRP</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Fatigue</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>All of the individual de-identified participant data collected during the trial will be shared with the funding organization (the National Highway Traffic Safety Administration (NHTSA)) and with researchers who provide a methodologically sound proposal and have been approved by the funding organization and by the University of Pittsburgh.</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Statistical Analysis Plan (SAP)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Informed Consent Form (ICF)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>The de-identified data will be made available immediately following publication and upon approval from the funding organization. No end date.</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>Access will be provided to researchers who provide a methodologically sound proposal and have been approved by the funding organization and by the University of Pittsburgh.</ipd_access_criteria>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

