<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04215081</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>EA22019SCI</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04215081</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>ExoAtlet II For SCI Patients</brief_title>
  <acronym>EXOATLET2SCI</acronym>
  <official_title>ExoAtlet II Lower Extremity Exoskeleton Safety and Efficacy Use With Spinal Cord Injured Individuals</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>ExoAtlet</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>ExoAtlet</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will evaluate the ExoAtlet II exoskeleton for safety and effectiveness of
      providing persons with a spinal cord injury (SCI) who are non-ambulatory or have limited
      ambulatory function, to stand up and ambulate under a variety of conditions.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The study will introduce the ExoAtlet II exoskeleton to SCI patients with lower extremity
      paralysis (partial or complete) and provide rehabilitative standing and walking intervention.
      The study will be conducted with a trained clinician that will fit each patient into the
      adjustable exoskeleton system and provide customized programming to meet each user's specific
      needs. The training program will be initiated based upon each patient's comfort in the
      exoskeleton and ability to stand with assistance. Each patient will be closely monitored to
      assess ongoing health as well as their individual standing and walking ability. All
      exoskeleton sessions will be performed with a trained medical professional controlling the
      exoskeleton. Patient safety is the primary concern and all adverse events will be documented
      and addressed. This study will evaluate the ExoAtlet 2.0 exoskeleton for safety and
      effectiveness of providing persons with a spinal cord injury (SCI) who are non-ambulatory or
      have limited ambulatory function, the ability to stand up and walk in a clinical facility.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 18, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">January 4, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">January 4, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>SCI Level T4-L5 or, C7-T3 with ASIA D</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>0-8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Document and track any adverse events, both minor and major, during exoskeleton sessions.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Skin integrity</measure>
    <time_frame>0-8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>A visual inspection of the participant's skin, at all areas of contact with the exoskeleton, will be conducted at the beginning and end of each session.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>10 Meter Walk Test</measure>
    <time_frame>1 Day</time_frame>
    <description>Assesses walking speed, in the exoskeleton, in meters per second over a distance of 10 meters</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>6 Minute Walk Test</measure>
    <time_frame>1 Day</time_frame>
    <description>Record the distance covered during a 6 minute walk test utilizing the exoskeleton, to evaluate users endurance</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Transfer in and out</measure>
    <time_frame>2 Days</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of patients able to successfully transfer in and out of the exoskeleton with or without assistance</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Perform Sit to Stand to Sit</measure>
    <time_frame>2 Days</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of patients that successfully completed both sit to stand and stand to sit in the exoskeleton</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Spinal Cord Injuries</condition>
  <condition>Paraplegia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>ExoAtlet II Safety and Efficacy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>20 participants with paraplegia from SCI will participate in gait training using ExoAtlet II powered exoskeleton.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Gait training using ExoAtlet exoskeleton</intervention_name>
    <description>Subjects will learn to use the ExoAtlet II exoskeleton, with the assistance of a trained medical professional, to perform functional activities (including stand-up, sit-down, stepping forward, and walking).</description>
    <arm_group_label>ExoAtlet II Safety and Efficacy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. 18 Years of age or older in general good health

          2. Weight, no more than 220lbs (100kg)

          3. Skin must be healthy where it touches the ExoAtlet 2.0

          4. Able to stand using a device such as a standing frame

          5. Have enough strength in your hands and shoulders to support yourself standing and
             walking using crutches or a walker

          6. Have good control of upper body

          7. Determined to have enough bone health to walk full weight bearing without risk of
             fracture. Meeting of this condition is at the discretion of your personal MD

          8. Passive range of motion (PROM) at shoulders, trunk, upper extremities and lower
             extremities within functional limits for safe gait and use of appropriate assistive
             device/stability aid

          9. Hip width no greater than 18&quot; (46 cm) measured when sitting.

         10. Femur length between 37 cm and 49 cm measured between mid patellar tendon and the
             floor.

         11. In general, good health and able to tolerate moderate levels of activity.

         12. Blood pressure and heart rate within established guidelines for locomotive training:
             At rest; Systolic 150 or less Diastolic 90 or less and Heart rate 100 or less
             Exercise; Systolic 180 or less, Diastolic 105 or less and Heart Rate 145 or less

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Spinal cord injury level higher than T4 or C7 ASIA D

          2. Severe muscle stiffness/tightness

          3. Significant spasticity (Modified Ashworth Scale score of 3 or above)

          4. Trunk or lower extremity pressure ulcer

          5. Open Wounds/tissue hypersensitivity

          6. Unstable spine, un-healed limbs, or fractures

          7. Severe sensitivity to touch

          8. Presence of bone in soft tissue where bone normally does not exist (heterotopic
             ossification), limiting range of motion in the hip or knee joints

          9. Joint instability, dislocation, moderate to severe hip dysplasia

         10. Significant scoliosis (&gt;40 degrees)

         11. Hardware, implant, or any external device impeding with safe fitting or use of
             ExoAtlet 2.0

         12. Femoral or tibial rotation deformity (&gt;15 degrees)

         13. Significant flexion contractures limited to 35ยบ at the hip and 20ยบ at the knee

         14. Uncontrolled seizures, musculoskeletal injury, fracture or lower-limb surgery in past
             year.

         15. Known history of pulmonary disease limiting exercise tolerance or history of cardiac
             disease

         16. Psychopathology, or other condition that the physician or investigator, in his or her
             clinical judgment, considers to be exclusionary to safely use an exoskeleton.

         17. Severe concurrent medical diseases, illness, systemic or peripheral infection

         18. Dizziness or headache with standing

         19. History of autonomic dysreflexia

         20. Orthostatic Hypotension: Decrease in Systolic BP &gt; 20, Diastolic BP &gt; 10 upon standing
             from a seated position.

         21. Pregnant or lactating females
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Sergey Kotov, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Moscow Regional Research and Clinical Institute Moniki n.a. M.F. Vladimirskiy</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Moscow Regional Research Clinical Institute. M.F. Vladimirsky</name>
      <address>
        <city>Moscow</city>
        <zip>129110</zip>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Russian Federation</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gagnon DH, Cunha JD, Boyer-Delestre M, Bosquet L, Duclos C. How does wearable robotic exoskeleton affect overground walking performance measured with the 10-m and six-minute walk tests after a basic locomotor training in healthy individuals? Gait Posture. 2017 Oct;58:340-345. doi: 10.1016/j.gaitpost.2017.08.027. Epub 2017 Aug 26.</citation>
    <PMID>28865396</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Miller LE, Zimmermann AK, Herbert WG. Clinical effectiveness and safety of powered exoskeleton-assisted walking in patients with spinal cord injury: systematic review with meta-analysis. Med Devices (Auckl). 2016 Mar 22;9:455-66. doi: 10.2147/MDER.S103102. eCollection 2016. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>27042146</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tefertiller C, Hays K, Jones J, Jayaraman A, Hartigan C, Bushnik T, Forrest GF. Initial Outcomes from a Multicenter Study Utilizing the Indego Powered Exoskeleton in Spinal Cord Injury. Top Spinal Cord Inj Rehabil. 2018 Winter;24(1):78-85. doi: 10.1310/sci17-00014. Epub 2017 Nov 20.</citation>
    <PMID>29434463</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hartigan C, Kandilakis C, Dalley S, Clausen M, Wilson E, Morrison S, Etheridge S, Farris R. Mobility Outcomes Following Five Training Sessions with a Powered Exoskeleton. Top Spinal Cord Inj Rehabil. 2015 Spring;21(2):93-9. doi: 10.1310/sci2102-93. Epub 2015 Apr 12.</citation>
    <PMID>26364278</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kozlowski AJ, Bryce TN, Dijkers MP. Time and Effort Required by Persons with Spinal Cord Injury to Learn to Use a Powered Exoskeleton for Assisted Walking. Top Spinal Cord Inj Rehabil. 2015 Spring;21(2):110-21. doi: 10.1310/sci2102-110. Epub 2015 Apr 12.</citation>
    <PMID>26364280</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>McIntosh K, Charbonneau R, Bensaada Y, Bhatiya U, Ho C. The Safety and Feasibility of Exoskeletal-Assisted Walking in Acute Rehabilitation After Spinal Cord Injury. Arch Phys Med Rehabil. 2020 Jan;101(1):113-120. doi: 10.1016/j.apmr.2019.09.005. Epub 2019 Sep 27.</citation>
    <PMID>31568761</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>December 20, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 28, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 2, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 22, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 22, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 23, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Spinal Cord Injuries</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Paraplegia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

