<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04210011</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Parental Resilience</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04210011</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Enhancing the Resilience of Parents by Understanding Their Perceptions, Behaviour, Attitudes, and Experiences Related to Cancer and Its Treatment of Their Child</brief_title>
  <official_title>Enhancing the Resilience of Parents by Understanding Their Perceptions, Behaviour, Attitudes, and Experiences Related to Cancer and Its Treatment of Their Child</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>The University of Hong Kong</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>The University of Hong Kong</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study is to describe the psychosocial well-being and quality of life of Hong Kong
      Chinese parents of children with cancer with the aim at understanding the needs and concerns
      of parents, including their perceptions, behaviour, attitudes, and experiences related to
      cancer and its treatment of their child.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Advances in diagnostic techniques and cancer treatments have yielded remarkable increases in
      the overall survival rates of children with cancer. Inevitably, however, cancer and its
      treatments may also have long-term effects on the physical and psychological well-being of
      children with cancer,

      Previous studies revealed that parents play a pivotal role in encouraging their child with
      cancer to engage in healthy behaviours. It was shown that Chinese parental psychological
      behaviour and control may influence the psychological well-being of their children.
      Therefore, a thorough understanding the needs and concerns of Chinese parents, including
      their perceptions, behaviour, attitudes, and experiences related to the illness of their
      child is essential to facilitate them to empower their child to fight at every step of the
      long and difficult cancer journey.

      On the other hand, the diagnosis of cancer not only undermines children themselves in
      physical and psychological, but also it brings overwhelming psychological distress for these
      children's parents. An increasing number of studies have examined patients' resilience in
      adaptation to cancer. Assessing resilience in parents of children with cancer is crucial for
      a thorough understanding of their responses to stress and adversity, which is an essential
      prerequisite for the design of an appropriate psychological intervention to enhance their
      resilience and foster the development of their coping mechanisms and positive psychological
      well-being. Nevertheless, the resilience levels and its influencing factors among parents of
      children with cancer in Hong Kong have never been studied.. Further qualitative and
      quantitative analyses are necessary to thoroughly explore the relationships between
      resilience and its influencing factors from a culturally specific perspective, with the goal
      of developing interventions to promote resilience that are applicable to the Hong Kong
      Chinese population.

      A sequential mixed methods design will be used with a quantitative study (Phase I) will be
      first conducted and followed by a qualitative study (Phase II). The reason for that the
      quantitative findings will provide a general understanding of the psychosocial well-being and
      quality of life of Hong Kong Chinese parents of children with cancer. The qualitative
      findings and the analysis will help to explain the quantitative findings by exploring the
      perceptions, behaviour, attitudes, and experiences related to cancer and its treatment of
      their child.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 2, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 30, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 30, 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Only</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Cross-Sectional</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Connor-Davidson resilience scale</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Connor-Davidson resilience scale (CD-RISC) will be used to measure the resilience level of parents having children with cancer. It contains a total of 25 items, which can be divided into 3 subcategories: (1) tenacity, (2) strength, and (3) optimism.The total possible scores of the scale range from 0 to 100, with a higher score indicating greater resilience.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The EuroQoL 5-Dimension 5-level</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline</time_frame>
    <description>The EuroQoL 5-Dimension 5-level (EQ-5D-5L) will be used to measure parents' quality of life.Each health state can potentially be assigned a summary index score based on societal preference weights for the health state. Health state index scores generally range from less than 0 (where 0 is the value of a health state equivalent to dead; negative values representing values as worse than dead) to 1 (the value of full health), with higher scores indicating higher health utility. The second part of the questionnaire consists of a visual analogue scale (VAS) on which the patient rates his/her perceived health from 0 (the worst imaginable health) to 100 (the best imaginable health).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The Center for Epidemiologic Studies Depression Scale (CES-D)</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline</time_frame>
    <description>The Center for Epidemiologic Studies Depression Scale (CES-D) consists of 20 items, which was originally designed to measure depressive symptoms in general population surveys.Subjects are asked to rate the frequency of each symptom during the past week on a four-point Likert scale representing 'rarely (less than 1 day)', 'some (1-2 days)', 'occasionally (3-4 days)' and 'most (5-7 days)', which are scored from 0 to 3, with total possible scores ranging from 0 to 60. Higher scores indicate a greater risk of depression.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The Chinese version of the State Anxiety Scale for Adults (C-SAS-A)</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline</time_frame>
    <description>The state anxiety level of parents will be measured by using the The Chinese version of the State Anxiety Scale for Adults (C-SAS-A). The scale consists of 20 items, which are scored from 1 to 4, with possible scores ranging from 20 to 80.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The Multidimensional Scale of Perceived Social Support (MSPSS)</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline</time_frame>
    <description>The Multidimensional Scale of Perceived Social Support (MSPSS) is a 12-item scale with a seven-point scale (from 1=strongly disagree to 7=strongly agree) measuring three sources of support, namely, Family, Friends, and Significant Other.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Parents' perceptions, behaviour, attitudes, and experiences related to the cancer and its treatment of their child</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Parents will be asked their perceptions, behaviour, attitudes, and experiences related to the cancer and its treatment of their child in the semi-structured interview.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">114</enrollment>
  <condition>Parents of Children With Cancer</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Hong Kong Chinese parents of children with cancer admitted to Hong Kong Children's Hospital
        are eligible. Study inclusion criteria for parents are as follows: (1) the primary
        caregiver, either father or mother, (2) ability to speak Cantonese and read
        Chinese-language materials, (3) having a child aged 0-16 years and diagnosed with cancer at
        some time in the previous month and currently undergoing active treatment. Parents with
        chronic illness and cognitive or learning disorders will be excluded.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  the primary caregiver, either father or mother,

          -  ability to speak Cantonese and read Chinese-language materials,

          -  having a child aged 0-16 years and diagnosed with cancer at some time in the previous
             month and currently undergoing active treatment

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Parents with chronic illness and cognitive or learning disorders
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ho Cheung William Li, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>The University of Hong Kong</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Ho Cheung William Li, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>39176634</phone>
    <email>william3@hku.hk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The University of Hong Kong</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hong Kong</city>
        <country>Hong Kong</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ho Cheung William Li, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>39176634</phone>
      <email>william3@hku.hk</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ho Cheung William Li, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Hong Kong</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>December 20, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 20, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">December 24, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 23, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 23, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 25, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Pediatric oncology</keyword>
  <keyword>Parental resilience</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

