<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01719562</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IRB00020968</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2012-01613</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>P30CA012197</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>CCCWFU 99112</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>R01CA167821</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>R21CA226960</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01719562</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>MRI in Detecting Heart Damage in Patients With Cancer Receiving Chemotherapy With Exercise Capacity Addendum</brief_title>
  <official_title>Improving Exercise Capacity With a Tailored Physical Activity Intervention in Lymphoma and Breast Cancer Patients Undergoing Treatment - An Addendum to NIH R01CA167821 &quot;Early Imaging Detection of Cardiovascular Injury After Cancer&quot;</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Wake Forest University Health Sciences</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Wake Forest University Health Sciences</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This trial studies how well magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) works in detecting heart damage
      in patients with cancer receiving chemotherapy. Diagnostic procedures, such as MRI, may help
      doctors predict whether patients will have heart damage caused by chemotherapy in patients
      with cancer receiving chemotherapy.

      Exercise Capacity Addendum Brief Summary: This study is designed to demonstrate feasibility
      of performing the physical activity intervention and the primary outcome measures before,
      during and six months after initiating Anth-bC for treatment of non- or Hodgkin lymphoma.
      This study will test the potential for a novel (lifestyle) intervention designed to improve
      exercise capacity, health-related quality of life and cardiac and cognitive dysfunction. This
      data will inform the development of the R33 phase of the clinical trial to determine if the
      physical activity intervention can reduce exercise intolerance in this high-risk population.
      In addition, cardiac MRI data from individuals within this pilot will be compared to cardiac
      MRI data from individuals in the parent study that did not undergo either of the two
      interventional arms of this study.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PRIMARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To design an automated MRI hardware/software platform for measuring and reporting left
      ventricular (LV) function (volumes, strain, and ejection fraction [EF]), T1 myocardial
      signal, and aortic pulse wave velocity (PWV).

      II. To determine if pre- to 3 month post-anthracycline-based chemotherapy (Anth-bC) changes
      in our MRI platform generated measures of LV volumes, EF, strain, myocardial T1, and aortic
      PWV predict pre- to 24 month post-Anth-bC differences in these same parameters.

      OUTLINE:

      Patients undergo MRI scans for LV function, T1 myocardial signal, and aortic PWV at baseline,
      3 months, and 24 months.

      Exercise Capacity Addendum Objectives:

      Primary Objective:

        -  To provide critical participant enrollment data necessary to accomplish the R01
           submission, including:

        -  Feasibility of screening, enrolling, and randomizing 21 Non or Hodgkin lymphoma and
           stage I-III breast cancer patients including the reasons for failed randomization,

        -  Identification of barriers for participating in, or adhering to the Patient ES-AI and
           the Healthy Living Control Group.

      Secondary Objective:

      • In these 21 patients, at study initiation then 3 and 6 months after initiating Anth-bC or
      other potentially cardiotoxic cancer therapies, to assess the ability to ascertain: peak
      exercise cardiac output, calculated arteriovenous oxygen difference (A-V O2) and VO2 (maximum
      rate of oxygen), and pre-exercise measures of left ventricular and cognitive function,
      health-related quality of life, six-minute walk distance (6min WD) and fatigue. Ascertainment
      of the left ventricular function and health-related rate quality of life will be attempted in
      a manner similar to ascertainment of these variables from 47 individuals with lymphoma in the
      parent study.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 31, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 31, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>For the exercise capacity portion of this trial, participants will be randomized to 1 of 2 arms.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Parent Study - To correlate results of an automated MRI hardware/software platform for measuring left ventricular (LV) function with manual results.</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 24 months</time_frame>
    <description>For the automation to be considered useful it should correlate highly with the manual results, exhibit a similar mean value and overall variability. 95% confidence intervals (CIs) of the difference between measures will be constructed and the upper and lower bounds of these intervals will be examined. The final diagnostic we will perform is to run F-tests to determine whether the variability from each measure is the same or different. 95% CIs will be examined for the ratio of the variance.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Parent Study - To test the ability of the pre- to post-anthracycline-based chemotherapy (Anth-bC) changes in our MRI platform generated measures of LV function to predict pre- to 24 month post-Anth-bC differences in LV function.</measure>
    <time_frame>From baseline to 24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Each patient is individually categorized as either having a persistent CV worsening or not depending on whether they exhibit a 20% worsening of their outcome by 3 months and that level of worsening persists to 24 months. We will examine paired t-tests for each time point for each measure to test whether measures are significantly worse at each time point. We will fit longitudinal models that examine all three time points (baseline, 3 and 24 months) simultaneously to determine whether there is a linear (or some other) function that can describe the decline in these subclinical CV MRI measures.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants Completing the Trial (Exercise Capacity Addendum)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months after treatment initiation</time_frame>
    <description>Participants that are able to complete the intervention while documenting barriers to participation.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants Able to Complete Assessments (Exercise Capacity Addendum)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months after treatment initiation</time_frame>
    <description>For both active and control groups, investigators will determine participants that are able to complete baseline and follow-up assessments of measures of interest (cardiovascular imaging, exercise measures (peak VO2 and six-minute walk distance)). A 95% confidence interval using the Clopper-Pearson method will be used to compute these measurements.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Peak Exercise Cardiac Output (Exercise Capacity Addendum)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months after treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Investigators will calculate descriptive statistics in order to get some preliminary data concerning the mean values and variability of these measures using a 95% exact confidence interval (Clopper-Pearson method). To be taken at initial visits, 3 and 6 months after initiating treatment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Arteriovenous Oxygen Difference (A-V O2) (Exercise Capacity Addendum)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months after treatment initiation</time_frame>
    <description>Investigators will calculate descriptive statistics in order to get some preliminary data concerning the mean values and variability of these measures using a 95% exact confidence interval (Clopper-Pearson method). To be taken at initial visits, 3 and 6 months after initiating treatment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum Rate of Oxygen Consumption (VO2) (Exercise Capacity Addendum)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months after treatment initiation</time_frame>
    <description>For this measure (peak VO2) investigators will calculate descriptive statistics in order to get some preliminary data concerning the mean values and variability of these measures using a 95% exact confidence interval (Clopper-Pearson method). To be taken at initial visits, 3 and 6 months after initiating treatment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Variability of Left Ventricular Function (Exercise Capacity Addendum)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months after treatment initiation</time_frame>
    <description>Investigators will calculate descriptive statistics in order to get some preliminary data concerning the mean values and variability of these measures using a 95% exact confidence interval (Clopper-Pearson method). To be taken at initial visits, 3 and 6 months after initiating treatment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Variability of Cognitive Function (Exercise Capacity Addendum)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months after treatment initiation</time_frame>
    <description>Investigators will calculate descriptive statistics in order to get some preliminary data concerning the mean values and variability of these measures using a 95% exact confidence interval (Clopper-Pearson method). To be taken at initial visits, 3 and 6 months after initiating treatment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Health-Related Quality of Life (Exercise Capacity Addendum)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months after treatment initiation</time_frame>
    <description>Functional Assessment of Cancer Treatment-Lymphoma (FACT-Lym) - A self-administered 42-item scale to assess disease-specific health-related quality of life in four primary domains: physical, social, emotional well-being with an additional sub-scale that measures participant concerns related to lymphoma. The MOS 36-item short form health survey will also be used as a measure of health status including vitality and physical function. Scale range is 0-4, 0 = not at all; 4 = very much. The higher the score shows the impact on the participant's quality of life.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>6-minute Walk Distance (Exercise Capacity Addendum)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months after treatment initiation</time_frame>
    <description>Investigators will calculate descriptive statistics in order to get some preliminary data concerning the mean values and variability of these measures using a 95% exact confidence interval (Clopper-Pearson method). To be taken at initial visits, 3 and 6 months after initiating treatment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Functional Assessment of Cancer Therapy - (FACT-Fatigue) (Exercise Capacity Addendum)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months after treatment initiation</time_frame>
    <description>A self-administered 13-item scale to assess fatigue in participants. Score scale - Scale range is 0-4, 0 = not at all; 4 = very much. The higher the score the greater level of fatigue.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">130</enrollment>
  <condition>Cardiac Toxicity</condition>
  <condition>Malignant Neoplasm</condition>
  <condition>Breast Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>ADDENDUM: Physical Activity Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will be offered one to two training sessions per week at onsite rehab facilities and 1-2 sessions per week at home consisting of slow 15 minute aerobic warm-up followed by 20 minutes of strength training, 15 minutes of progressive intensity aerobic exercise and 10 minute cool down.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>ADDENDUM: Healthy Living Instruction Group (Control Arm)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Organized various health workshops lasting for 60 minutes to match the number of visits to the rehab centers for participants in Arm 1 with 2 sessions offered per month onsite and remaining sessions offered over the phone for 6 months. .</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>MRI (Diagnostic)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients undergo MRI scans for LV function, T1 myocardial signal, and aortic PWV at baseline, 3 months, and 24 months.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Magnetic resonance imaging</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients undergo MRI scans for left ventricular function, T1 myocardial signal, and aortic PWV at baseline, 3 months, and 24 months.</description>
    <arm_group_label>ADDENDUM: Healthy Living Instruction Group (Control Arm)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>ADDENDUM: Physical Activity Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>MRI (Diagnostic)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>MRI</other_name>
    <other_name>NMR imaging</other_name>
    <other_name>NMRI</other_name>
    <other_name>nuclear magnetic resonance imaging</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Physical Activity</intervention_name>
    <description>Tailored aerobic exercise program onsite and at home.</description>
    <arm_group_label>ADDENDUM: Physical Activity Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>MRI (Diagnostic)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Healthy Living</intervention_name>
    <description>Healthy living presentations at a centralized meeting place and over the phone.</description>
    <arm_group_label>ADDENDUM: Healthy Living Instruction Group (Control Arm)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>MRI (Diagnostic)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cardiopulmonary Exercise Testing (CPET)</intervention_name>
    <description>Performed on the treadmill using the Bruce or Modified Bruce protocol based on current fitness level.</description>
    <arm_group_label>ADDENDUM: Healthy Living Instruction Group (Control Arm)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>ADDENDUM: Physical Activity Intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Questionnaire Administration</intervention_name>
    <description>A self-administered 13-item scale to assess fatigue in participants</description>
    <arm_group_label>ADDENDUM: Healthy Living Instruction Group (Control Arm)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>ADDENDUM: Physical Activity Intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        PARENT STUDY:

        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Receiving &gt;= 350 mg/m^2 of Anth-bC therapy, or a combination of Anth-bC (&gt;= 250
             mg/m^2) and subsequent paclitaxel or Herceptin

          -  Ability to understand and the willingness to sign a written informed consent document

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Intracranial metal, pacemakers, defibrillators, functioning neurostimulator devices,
             or other implanted electronic devices

          -  Ferromagnetic cerebral aneurysm clips, or other intraorbital/intracranial metal

          -  Allergy to gadolinium or other severe drug allergies

          -  Unstable angina

          -  Significant ventricular arrhythmias (&gt; 20 premature ventricular contractions
             [PVCs]/minute due to gating difficulty)

          -  Acute myocardial infarction within 28 days

          -  Atrial fibrillation with uncontrolled ventricular response

          -  Moderate or severe aortic stenosis

          -  Claustrophobia

          -  Congestive heart failure (New York Heart Association [NYHA] class III or IV)

          -  Significant valvular disease, or significant pulmonary disease requiring supplemental
             oxygen therapy

          -  Participants unwilling to complete the protocol (24 month duration)

          -  Women who are pregnant

          -  Patients unable or unwilling to provide informed consent

        EXERCISE CAPACITY ADDENDUM:

        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Men and women aged 18-85 with non- or Hodgkin lymphoma or I-III stage breast cancer
             patients that expect to receive an anthracycline based chemotherapeutic regimen or
             other potentially cardiotoxic cancer therapies (e.g. chemotherapy regimens
             [anthracyclines, trastuzumab]), immuno-therapies (immune checkpoint inhibitors
             [ICI's]) or radiation (within 8 weeks of completion).

          -  Potential enrollees will need the capacity to walk at least two (2) city blocks on a
             flat surface.

          -  English speaking participants only will be enrolled.

        Exclusion Criteria: The following are relative contraindications and can be considered by
        the medical director of the study:

          -  Uncontrolled hypertension (systolic blood pressure &gt;190 mm Hg or diastolic blood
             pressure &gt;100 mm Hg)

          -  A recent history of alcohol or drug abuse.

          -  Inflammatory conditions such as lupus or inflammatory bowel disease, or another
             medical condition that might compromise safety or successful completion.

          -  Other exclusions include those with contraindications to MRI such as ferromagnetic
             cerebral aneurysm clips or other intracranial metal, pacemakers, defibrillators,
             functioning neurostimulator devices or other implanted electronic devices.

          -  Unstable angina.

          -  Inability to exercise on a treadmill or stationary cycle.

          -  Significant ventricular arrhythmias (&gt;20 PVCs/min due to gating difficulty).

          -  Atrial fibrillation with uncontrolled ventricular response.

          -  Acute myocardial infarction within 28 days.

          -  Moving within 12 months of enrollment.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>85 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>William Hundley</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Wake Forest University Health Sciences</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Comprehensive Cancer Center of Wake Forest University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Winston-Salem</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27157</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>William G. Hundley</last_name>
      <email>ghundley@wakehealth.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>William G. Hundley</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Virginia Commonwealth University Health Sciences</name>
      <address>
        <city>Richmond</city>
        <state>Virginia</state>
        <zip>23284</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Alexander Lucas</last_name>
      <email>alexander.lucas@vcuhealth.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Alexander Lucas</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 11, 2012</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 30, 2012</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 1, 2012</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 1, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 1, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 2, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cardiotoxicity</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

