<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03873909</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Sapote2017</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03873909</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Bioavailability of Carotenoids Present in Mamey Sapote (Pouteria Sapota (Jacq.) H. E. Moore &amp; Stearn) Fruit</brief_title>
  <official_title>Bioavailability of Carotenoids Present in Mamey Sapote (Pouteria Sapota (Jacq.) H. E. Moore &amp; Stearn) Fruit</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Hohenheim</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Universidad de Costa Rica</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Hohenheim</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The goal of the study is to determine if mamey sapote fruit, rich in rare potentially
      provitamin A keto-carotenoids, is a good source of vitamin A in humans. Furthermore, it will
      help to compare the absorption of carotenoids between the fruit versus a &quot;matrix-free&quot;
      formulation.

      The objective will be accomplished by quantitation of the immediate post-prandial plasma
      concentrations of parent carotenoids and vitamin A metabolites from participants consuming a
      meal consisting of a mamey sapote fruit smoothie or a shake containing mamey sapote
      encapsulated carotenoids.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The present study seeks to obtain a better understanding of the bioavailability and
      metabolism of the exceptional keto-carotenoids, sapotexanthin and cryptocapsin from mamey
      sapote fruit in humans. For this purpose, the absorption of such carotenoids after the
      consumption of fresh mamey sapote fruit and a &quot;matrix-free&quot; water-dispersible formulation
      containing isolated mamey sapote carotenoids will be compared.

      The participants of the study will be healthy, non-pregnant, non-smoking adults aged 18-65.
      Prior to the study, the people who wants to participate in the study will have an education
      session where the coordinator explains the study in detail and discusses which foods and
      supplements need to be avoided during the study. They will give their consent to participate
      in the study, will be screened for body height/weight (BMI) and will complete a health
      questionnaire. Afterward, if they fit the necessary health criteria for the study, they will
      be enrolled as a participant and an appointment will be made for their post-prandial visit to
      the School of Medicine (University of Costa Rica).

      The participants will refrain from consuming products containing high levels of carotenoids
      (β-carotene, β-cryptoxanthin, lutein, and zeaxanthin) for 10 days prior to the first day of
      treatment until the end of the study (&quot;washout&quot;). They will receive a list of foods and
      supplements to avoid. They will record their actual daily consumption of
      carotenoid-containing foods on the list of foods to avoid. The record will allow determining
      whether participants are remaining compliant and avoiding carotenoid-containing foods.

      For the post-prandial visit, a blood sample will be taken at hour 0 (baseline sample) and
      then the corresponding test meal (fruit smoothie or matrix-free shake) will be administered
      to the participants. Subsequent blood sampling will be carried out at 2,4,5,6,8 and 9.5 h
      after the meal is consumed. A carotenoid-free lunch will be provided at 4.5 hours. Afterward,
      the triglyceride-rich fraction (TRL) will be isolated from the plasma samples and the
      concentration of carotenoids and retinyl esters determined. The values obtained will be used
      to determine the mean value of the Area Under the Curve (AUC) through time to compare the
      absorption between the two meals provided.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 1, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 13, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">November 13, 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>randomized 2-way cross-over</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in carotenoid concentration in blood plasma over 9.5 h after meal consumption</measure>
    <time_frame>7 post-prandial blood samples over 9.5 hours including baseline</time_frame>
    <description>An area under the curve for concentration of carotenoids (from triglyceride-rich lipoprotein (TRL) fraction of plasma) will be obtained by using carotenoid concentrations from hours 0, 2, 4, 5, 6, 8 and 9.5 over time to quantify absorption after subjects consume a meal consisting of a mamey sapote fruit smoothie or a &quot;matrix-free&quot; carotenoid-rich shake.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in retinyl esters concentration in blood plasma over 9.5 h after meal consumption</measure>
    <time_frame>7 post-prandial blood samples over 9.5 hours including baseline</time_frame>
    <description>An area under the curve for concentration of retinyl esters (from triglyceride-rich lipoprotein (TRL) fraction of plasma) will be obtained by using retinyl esters concentrations from hours 0, 2, 4, 5, 6, 8 and 9.5 over time to quantify conversion of carotenoids to retinyl esters after subjects consume a meal consisting of a mamey sapote fruit smoothie or a &quot;matrix-free&quot; carotenoid-rich shake.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">13</enrollment>
  <condition>Biological Availability</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Fruit Smoothie</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Post-prandial study feeding 155-200 g mamey sapote mesocarp, 6 g of soybean oil , crushed ice and 150-200 g of water to reach a total volume of 450 mL. (845 µg sapotexanthin, 1.21-1.51 mg cryptocapsin).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Matrix-Free Shake</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Post-prandial study feeding 2 g of carotenoid powder formula (845 µg sapotexanthin, 1.21-1.51 mg cryptocapsin), 37.5 g of sugar, 75 µg of citric acid, 6 g of soybean oil emulsified into 300 g of water using 3 g of soy lecithin as well as ca. 100 g of crushed ice, yielding a shake volume of 450 mL.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Fruit Smoothie</intervention_name>
    <description>Fruit Smoothie with 150-200 g mamey sapote fruit</description>
    <arm_group_label>Fruit Smoothie</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Matrix-Free Shake</intervention_name>
    <description>Shake containing mamey sapote extracted carotenoids (2 g, 845 µg sapotexanthin and 1.21-1.51 mg cryptocapsin</description>
    <arm_group_label>Matrix-Free Shake</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Healthy adult men and women with a BMI 17 to 30

          -  Aged 18-65 years.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  lactating, pregnant, or planned to be pregnant

          -  smokers/those who use tobacco products

          -  metabolic or malabsorption disorders

          -  with history of cancer

          -  with history of liver insufficiency or other gastro-intestinal diseases

          -  with history of chronic diseases related to lipid metabolism

          -  obesity
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Patricia Esquivel, Ph.D</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Universidad de Costa Rica</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Silvia Quesada</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Universidad de Costa Rica</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Costa Rica</name>
      <address>
        <city>San José</city>
        <state>San Pedro De Montes De Oca</state>
        <country>Costa Rica</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Hohenheim</name>
      <address>
        <city>Stuttgart</city>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Costa Rica</country>
    <country>Germany</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 25, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 12, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 14, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 12, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 12, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 14, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Ketocarotenoids</keyword>
  <keyword>Mamey sapote</keyword>
  <keyword>Sapotexanthin</keyword>
  <keyword>Cryptocapsin</keyword>
  <keyword>Vitamin A</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

