<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03877614</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>A-ER-107-149</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03877614</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Artificial Intelligence With Deep Learning and Genes on Cardiovascular Disease</brief_title>
  <official_title>Application of Artificial Intelligence Deep Learning to the Correlation Between Cardiovascular Disease and Individualized Differences</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Cheng-Kung University Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Cheng-Kung University Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      An association study with large database from electronic medical record system, images,
      outcome analysis and genetic single nucleotide polymorphism variations by machine learning
      and artificial intelligence methods in a Taiwanese and Chinese medical center based
      population
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      In recent years, the analysis of big data database combined with computer deep learning has
      gradually played an important role in biomedical technology. For a large number of medical
      record data analysis, image analysis, single nucleotide polymorphism difference analysis,
      etc., all relevant research on the development and application of artificial intelligence can
      be observed extensively. For clinical indication, patients may receive a variety of
      cardiovascular routine examination and treatments, such as: cardiac ultrasound, multi-path
      ECG, cardiovascular and peripheral angiography, intravascular ultrasound and optical
      coherence tomography, electrical physiology, etc... The current study is for the
      investigative cardiovascular team to take the advantage that in addition to the examination
      and treatment the participants should appropriately receive, the investigators can also
      analyze the individual differences and using the &quot;deep learning methodology&quot; to analyze the
      difference in physical fitness, therapeutic effectiveness and the consideration in the safety
      of the treatment. The additional goal of this study is to improve the quality of health care,
      the realization of cardiovascular &quot;precise medicine&quot; especially with personal difference on
      genetic variation.

      This study will analyze the differences in the individualization of cardiovascular disease
      between diseases and other subjects to further improve the quality of care for clinical
      patients. By using artificial intelligence deep learning system, the investigators hope to
      not only improve the diagnostic rate and also gain more accurately predict the patient's
      recovery, improve medical quality in the near future.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">August 28, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Major cardiovascular events</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <description>The rate of myocardial infarction, stroke, death, cardiovascular death, heart failure with hospitalization</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Heart function changes</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <description>parameters and function changes from echocardiography</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Lipid profiles</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <description>The percentage changes and response of lipid profile with regular lipid lowering agents</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Arrhythmia events</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <description>The rate of arrhythmia associated complications and clinical events, stokes</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Recurrent acute coronary events</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <description>The rate of recurrent acute coronary events with hospitalization needed or re-intervention procedures for coronary artery needed</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">5000</enrollment>
  <condition>Cardiovascular Diseases</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cardiovascular high-risk (disease) group</arm_group_label>
    <description>A. Coronary artery disease B. Congestive heart failure with reduced ejection fraction C. Hypertrophic cardiomyopathy D. Atrial fibrillation E. Pulmonary hypertension F. Fabry's disease</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cardiovascular Low-risk (control) group</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patient with only risk factors with ASCVD score&lt;10% will be recognized as the comparison group</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ASCVD risk score</intervention_name>
    <description>ASCVD score&lt; 10% will be in the control or low-risk group</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cardiovascular Low-risk (control) group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cardiovascular high-risk (disease) group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Salivary DNA with genetic polymorphism chips comparative analysis
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Pipeline for case enrollment:

          1. We will enroll investigating subjects from the clinics of near 10 physicians screened
             by our assistant or physicians themselves, with nearly 100-120 cases/month. According
             to our initial experience during our previous hospital-based grant in 2018 showed
             feasible case number to be enrolled, nearly 1000 case within 3 months enrollment. In
             total, we plan to recruit 5000 subjects with cardiovascular disease or with risk
             factors within 3 years. (IRB approval A-ER-107-149)

          2. Our study subjects will be evaluated whether they fulfill the cases criteria by an
             independent physician every month.

          3. In comparison with disease, the risk factor only group (500 cases) will be the
             matching group on genetic background and outcome comparison.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients' selection criteria and enrollment plan:

        We will enroll subjects from either cardiovascular clinics or inpatients from the National
        Cheng Kung University Hospital from 2018 to 2021 after the signature of inform consent from
        patients and their families. The major enrollment criteria include one of the flowing
        diseases or conditions:

        A. Coronary artery disease:

          1. History of myocardial infarction

          2. Coronary artery disease with computer tomography angiography image study with at least
             one vessel luminal stenosis &gt;70%

          3. Coronary artery stents implantation by hospital-based image database

          4. Thallium-201 scan positive/treadmill test positive with additional 2 risk factors,
             including

               1. Diabetes mellitus

               2. Hypertension

               3. Dyslipidemia

               4. Family history of sudden death, coronary bypass surgery, cerebral vascular
                  attacks (CVA), premature myocardial infarction

               5. Smoking behaviors

        B. Congestive heart failure with reduced ejection fraction

        1. Echocardiography left ventricular ejection fraction &lt;40%

        C. Hypertrophic cardiomyopathy:

          1. Left ventricle interventricular septum（IVS) &gt;15 mm

          2. Left ventricle mass index&gt; 200gm

          3. Apical hypertrophy noted on the report with 4 chamber view

        D. Atrial fibrillation

          1. Recorded by Holter continuous EKG

          2. Recorded by standard 12 leads complete EKG

        E. Pulmonary hypertension

          1. Echo with systolic pulmonary pressure (sysPAP)&gt; 40 mmHg

          2. Diagnosis of idiopathic pulmonary hypertension

          3. Under pulmonary hypertension medication

        F. Fabry's disease

          1. α-Galactosidase (a-GAL) enzyme deficiency

          2. Genetic disorder

        G. Patient with only risk factors (&lt;3 risk factors), recognized as the comparison group
        (&gt;500 cases)

          1. Diabetes mellitus

          2. Hypertension

          3. Dyslipidemia

          4. Family history of sudden death, coronary bypass surgery, cerebral vascular attacks,
             premature myocardial infarction

          5. Smoking behavior

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients unwilling to be enrolled

          -  Concentration of DNA collection was inadequate after 3 times of collection
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of Internal Medicine, National Cheng Kung University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tainan</city>
        <zip>704</zip>
        <country>Taiwan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ping-Yen Liu, MD, PhD.</last_name>
      <phone>+88662353535</phone>
      <phone_ext>4602</phone_ext>
      <email>larry@mail.ncku.edu.tw</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Pei-Tiang Hsu</last_name>
      <phone>+88662353535</phone>
      <phone_ext>2389</phone_ext>
      <email>sz2137@yahoo.com.tw</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Taiwan</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 8, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 13, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 15, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 13, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 13, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 15, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>National Cheng-Kung University Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Ping-Yen Liu</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Director of Cardiology, Internal Medicine and Professor of Institute of Clinical Medicine</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cardiovascular Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

