<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03879057</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CGOG-3006/2018-012-00CH2</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03879057</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Trial of Surufatinib Combined With JS001 in the Treatment of Advanced Solid Tumors</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase I Trial Evaluating the Safety, Tolerability, Pharmacokinetics, and Efficacy of Surufatinib Combined With JS001 in Patients With Advanced Solid Tumors</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Peking University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Peking University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is an open-label, phase I study evaluating safety, tolerability, pharmacokinetics and
      efficacy of Surufatinib combined with the humanized anti-PD-1 antibody JS001 in patients with
      solid tumors.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">December 21, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 20, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 20, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Safety of participants followed for the duration of hospital stay, an expected average of 1 week</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum tolerated dose</measure>
    <time_frame>4 week</time_frame>
    <description>tolerability during the treatment of first cycle</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Objective response rate</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of first dose until the date of first documented progression or date of death from any cause, whichever came first, assessed up to 24 months</time_frame>
    <description>The number of cases in which tumor size is reduced to PR or CR / the total number of evaluable cases (%). In the event of PR or CR, the subjects should confirm it no less than 4 weeks after the first evaluation. CT/MRI will be performed every 2 cycles of treatment by RECIST 1.1(each cycle is 21 days))</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>time to treatment failure(TTF)</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month</time_frame>
    <description>From date of enrollment until the date of tumor progression</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum Plasma Concentration (Cmax)</measure>
    <time_frame>8 days</time_frame>
    <description>Pharmacokinetic profile in terms of observed maximum plasma concentration</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Area Under the Curve From Time Zero Extrapolated to Infinity (AUC(0-inf))</measure>
    <time_frame>8 days</time_frame>
    <description>Pharmacokinetic profile in terms of plasma concentration-time curve from time zero extrapolated to infinity, AUC(0-inf)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">24</enrollment>
  <condition>Solid Tumor</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Surufatinib 200mg/JS001 240mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Surufatinib at a dose of 200mg Qd, with humanized anti-PD-1 monoclonal antibody（JS001） injected intravenously 240mg per 3 weeks until disease progresses or unacceptable tolerability occurs.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Surufatinib 300mg/JS001 240mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Surufatinib at a dose of 300mg Qd, with humanized anti-PD-1 monoclonal antibody（JS001) injected intravenously 240mg per 3 weeks until disease progresses or unacceptable tolerability occurs.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Surufatinib/humanized anti-PD-1 monoclonal antibody</intervention_name>
    <description>humanized anti-PD-1 monoclonal antibody(JS001) is a programmed death-1 (PD-1) immune checkpoint inhibitor antibody, which selectively interferes with th combination of PD-1 with its ligands, PD-L1 and PD-L2, resulting in the activitation of lymphocytes and elimination of malignancy theoretically.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Surufatinib 200mg/JS001 240mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Surufatinib 300mg/JS001 240mg</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Surufatinib/JS001</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Must have read, understood, and provided written informed consent voluntarily. Willing
             to adhere to the study visit schedule and the prohibitions and restrictions specified
             in this protocol.

          2. Male and Female aged between 18 and 75 years are eligible;

          3. Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status score of 0 or 1;

          4. Histologic diagnosis of locally advanced or metastatic unresectable solid tumors
             (neuroendocrine tumors, liver carcinoma, gastric carcinomas considered with priority);

          5. Failed after standard treatment (disease progression or intolerable for toxic side
             effects) or no effective to treatment;

          6. For liver carcinoma with Child-Pugh of grade A and grade B (≤ 7 points);

          7. Radiographic evidence of disease rogression by RECIST criteria on or after last
             anti-cancer therapy within 6 months; If the single lesion previously received
             radiation, ablation, there must be an imaging identification for disease progression;

          8. Predicted survival &gt;=3 months;

          9. At least 1 measurable lesion (only 1 measurable lymph node lesion is excluded)
             (routine CT scan &gt;=20mm, spiral CT scan &gt;=10mm, no prior radiation to measurable
             lesions);

         10. Screening laboratory values must meet the following criteria (within past 14 days):
             hemoglobin ≥ 9.0 g/dL; neutrophils ≥ 1500 cells/ μL; platelets ≥ 100 x 10^3/ μL; total
             bilirubin ≤ 1.5 x upper limit of normal (ULN); aspartic transaminase (AST) and alanine
             transaminase (ALT) ≤ 2.5 x ULN without, and ≤ 5 x ULN with hepatic metastasis; serum
             creatinine ≤1╳ULN, creatinine clearance &gt;50ml/min (CockcroftGault equation) PT/INR,
             aPTT≤1.5 x ULN;

         11. Males or female of childbearing potential must: agree to use using a reliable form of
             contraception (eg, oral contraceptives, intrauterine device, control sex desire,
             double barrier method of condom and spermicidal) during the treatment period and for
             at least 12 months after the last dose of study drug.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. The toxicity associated with previous anti-tumor treatment has not recovered to
             ≤CTCAE1, except for peripheral neurotoxicity and alopecia ≤CTCAE2 caused by
             oxaliplatin;

          2. Had other malignant tumors in the past 5 years (except for basal cell carcinoma or
             squamous cell carcinoma, cervical carcinoma in situ that have been effectively
             controlled);

          3. Evidence with active CNS disease;

          4. Prior treatment with chemotherapy, biological immunotherapy, targeted therapy, Chinese
             herbal medicine within 2 weeks.

          5. Prior treatment with radical radiation within 4 weeks

          6. Prior treatment with antiPD1/PDL1/PDL2/CTLA-4 antibody or Sulfatinib;

          7. Prior treatment with corticosteroids (dose &gt; 10 mg/day prednisone or other hormones)
             or other immunosuppressive agents within 2 weeks, nasal or inhalation in allowed (dose
             &gt; 10 mg/day prednisone or other hormones).

          8. Patients with any active autoimmune disease or a documented history of autoimmune
             disease, or history of syndrome that required systemic steroids or immunosuppressive
             medications, such as hypophysitis, pneumonia, colitis, hepatitis, nephritis,
             hyperthyroidism or hypothyroidism;

          9. Prior live vaccine therapy within past 4 weeks;

         10. Prior major surgery within past 4 weeks (diagnostic surgery excluded);

         11. Uncontrolled malignant pleural effusion, ascites or pericardial effusion;

         12. Hypertension that is not controlled by the drug, and is defined as: SBP≥140 mmHg
             and/or DBP≥90 mmHg;

         13. The patient currently has disease or condition that affects the absorption of the
             drug, or the patient cannot be administered orally;

         14. Received a potent inducer or inhibitor of CYP3A4 within 2 weeks, or continue receiving
             these drugs during the study;

         15. Digestive tract disease such as gastric and duodenal active ulcer, ulcerative colitis
             or unresected tumor, or other conditions determined by the investigator that may cause
             gastrointestinal bleeding and perforation;

         16. Evidence of bleeding tendency or history within 2 months, or thromboembolic event
             (including a stroke event and/or a transient ischemic attack) occurred within 12
             month;

         17. Severe, uncontrolled medical condition that would affect patients' compliance or
             obscure the interpretation of toxicity determination or adverse events, including
             active severe infection, uncontrolled diabetes, angiocardiopathy (heart failure &gt;
             class II NYHA, LVEF &lt;50%, myocardial infarction, unstable arrhythmia or unstable
             angina within past 6 months, cerebral infarction within past 3 months) or pulmonary
             disease ( interstitial pneumonia, obstructive pulmonary disease or symptomatic
             bronchospasm);

         18. Clinically significant severe electrolyte abnormality judged by investigator ;

         19. Active infection or unexplained fever during the screening period (temperature &gt;38.5C)

         20. History with tuberculosis who are receiving or have received anti-TB treatment within
             1 year.

         21. Pulmonary fibrosis, interstitial pneumonia, pneumoconiosis, radiation pneumonitis,
             drug-associated pneumonia, severe impaired lung function, etc; Radiation pneumonitis
             in the radiotherapy area is allowed;

         22. Positive tests for HIV, HCV, HBsAg or HBcAb with positive test for HBV DNA
             (&gt;2000IU/ml);

         23. Prior antitumor therapy (including corticosteroids and immunotherapy) or participation
             in other clinical trials within past 4 weeks, or have not recovered from toxicities
             since the last treatment;

         24. Pregnant or nursing;

         25. Hypersensitivity to Sulfatinib or recombinant humanized antiPD1 monoclonal Ab;

         26. Underlying medical condition that, in the Investigator's opinion, would increase the
             risks of study drug administration or obscure the interpretation of toxicity
             determination or adverse events.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Lin Shen, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Peking University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Lin Shen</last_name>
    <phone>86-10-88196561</phone>
    <email>linshenpku@163.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Beijing Cancer Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Beijing</city>
        <state>Beijing</state>
        <zip>100142</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Lin Shen</last_name>
      <phone>86-10-88196561</phone>
      <email>linshenpku@163.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>December 28, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 15, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 18, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 27, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 27, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 1, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Peking University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Shen Lin</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>MD, Professor, Chief of Department of GI Oncology, Peking University Cancer Hospital</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Antibodies</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Antibodies, Monoclonal</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

