<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03879122</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CA209-9HX</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03879122</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Trial of Immunotherapy Strategies in Metastatic Hormone-sensitive Prostate Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Multi-arm, Multi-stage, Randomized Phase II/III Trial of Immunotherapy Strategies in Metastatic Hormone-sensitive Prostate Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Spanish Oncology Genito-Urinary Group</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Syntax for Science, S.L</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Bristol-Myers Squibb</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Spanish Oncology Genito-Urinary Group</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Metastatic prostate cancer is an incurable disease that typically spreads beyond the
      prostate. The standard of care is to systemically treat the disease with androgen deprivation
      therapy (ADT). However, the disease progresses in virtually all patients to the state of
      castration resistant prostate cancer (CRPC), with a median time to progression of 24 months.
      Patients with high volume disease (with either visceral metastasis and/or bone metastasis)
      exhibit a worse prognosis, with a median clinical progression of 14 months.

      Recently, the CHAARTED and STAMPEDE studies demonstrated that the combination of Docetaxel
      (chemotherapy) and ADT delayed the clinical progression and improved the survival a median of
      14 months (17 for high volume patients). Nevertheless, the prognosis of patients with high
      volume metastatic disease continues to be poor.

      Meanwhile the immunotherapy, the use of antibodies that recognize tumoral cells and promote
      the immune system activity against the cancer, has emerged as a very useful option in many
      cancers. Among others, the antibodies Nivolumab and Ipilimumab have been approved for the
      treatment of multiple types of cancer.

      In this context, SOGUG (Spanish Oncology Genitourinary Group) has designed this new study
      &quot;PROSTRATEGY&quot; with the objective of evaluating whether the addition of immunotherapy to
      chemotherapy and ADT improves the prognosis and survival of patients with high volume
      metastatic hormone-sensitive prostate cancer.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 11, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 31, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2/Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Multi-arm multi-stage (MAMS), multi-centre randomised controlled trial with 3 arms (2 experimental arms and a control arm) and 4 stages (three intermediate and a final stage). In all 3 intermediate stages of the trial, each experimental arm is compared in a pairwise manner with the control arm using an &quot;intermediate&quot; outcome measure. Experimental arms that do not reach a predefined critical value are discontinued. In the final stage, the remaining(s) arm(s) will be compared with the control arm in terms of overall survival (definitive outcome). The 3 arms included in this trial are the Control arm (ARM 1): ADT plus 6 cycles of DOCETAXEL and 2 experimental arms: ADT plus DOCETAXEL plus NIVOLUMAB (ARM 2) and ADT plus IPILIMUMAB alternating with DOCETAXEL and with NIVOLUMAB (ARM 3). Other experimental arms could be included later.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall Survival</measure>
    <time_frame>through study completion, an average of 2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Overall Survival</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PSA response</measure>
    <time_frame>through study completion, an average of 2 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PSA progression-free survival (PSA-PFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>through study completion, an average of 2 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Radiological progression-free survival (rPFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>through study completion, an average of 2 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical progression-free survival (cPFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>through study completion, an average of 2 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to castration resistant prostate cancer (TCRPC)</measure>
    <time_frame>through study completion, an average of 2 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Immune radiological progression-free survival (irPFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>through study completion, an average of 2 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Immune clinical progression-free survival (icPFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>through study completion, an average of 2 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to immune castration resistant prostate cancer (TiCRPC)</measure>
    <time_frame>through study completion, an average of 2 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Symptomatic skeletal-related event free survival (SSREFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>through study completion, an average of 2 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Toxicity of each of the treatment arms by assessing Adverse Events</measure>
    <time_frame>through study completion, an average of 2 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of life (QOL)</measure>
    <time_frame>through study completion, an average of 2 years</time_frame>
    <description>EQ-5D Questionnaire</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of life (QOL)</measure>
    <time_frame>through study completion, an average of 2 years</time_frame>
    <description>FACT-P Questionnaire</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of life (QOL)</measure>
    <time_frame>through study completion, an average of 2 years</time_frame>
    <description>BPI Questionnaire</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">135</enrollment>
  <condition>Metastatic Hormone-sensitive Prostate Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>ADT + Docetaxel</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>ADT (androgen deprivation therapy) plus 6 cycles of DOCETAXEL</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>ADT + Docetaxel + Nivolumab</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>ADT (androgen deprivation therapy) plus DOCETAXEL plus NIVOLUMAB</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>ADT + Ipilimumab / Docetaxel + Nivolumab</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>ADT (androgen deprivation therapy) plus IPILIMUMAB alternating with DOCETAXEL and followed by NIVOLUMAB</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ipilimumab 5 MG/ML</intervention_name>
    <description>Ipilimumab will be administered on day 1 of each cycle every 3 weeks. In arm 3, ipilimumab should be started at least 2 weeks but no later than 120 days after surgical castration or the first dose of LHRH analogue. Patients should receive 2 doses of ipilimumab (6 weeks). It will be followed, 3 weeks later, by 3 cycles of docetaxel and by 2 additional doses of ipilimumab and 3 more cycles of docetaxel. Four weeks later, Nivolumab will be administered on day 1 every 2 weeks until a maximum of 24 doses (48 weeks)</description>
    <arm_group_label>ADT + Ipilimumab / Docetaxel + Nivolumab</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>YERVOY</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Nivolumab 10 MG/ML</intervention_name>
    <description>Nivolumab will be administered every 2 weeks, until clinical progression or a maximum of 24 doses. Nivolumab should be started 4 weeks after the last dose of docetaxel, providing all the adverse effects have recovered, as if a new cycle of docetaxel were to be administered</description>
    <arm_group_label>ADT + Docetaxel + Nivolumab</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>ADT + Ipilimumab / Docetaxel + Nivolumab</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Opdivo</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Docetaxel</intervention_name>
    <description>Docetaxel should be given on day 1 every 21 days, for up to 6 cycles (1 cycle = 21 days). Docetaxel should be started within 7 working days from the date of randomization in the arm 1 and 2.
In arm 3, docetaxel will be given 3 weeks after the last dose of the previous treatment, providing all the side effects are grade ≤1.</description>
    <arm_group_label>ADT + Docetaxel</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>ADT + Docetaxel + Nivolumab</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>ADT + Ipilimumab / Docetaxel + Nivolumab</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ADT (androgen deprivation therapy)</intervention_name>
    <description>Androgen deprivation therapy per the standard of care</description>
    <arm_group_label>ADT + Docetaxel</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>ADT + Docetaxel + Nivolumab</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>ADT + Ipilimumab / Docetaxel + Nivolumab</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients must be at least 18 years of age

          2. Signed and dated written informed consent, obtained before the performance of any
             protocol-related procedure.

          3. Histological or cytological diagnosis of prostate cancer with an elevated PSA level
             and radiologic evidence of metastatic disease.

          4. ECOG performance-status score of 0, 1, or 2. Patients with a score of 2 are eligible
             if the decrement in functioning was due to prostate cancer.

          5. Metastatic disease that has spread beyond the prostate or relapsed after local
             therapy, documented by body CT scan and/or bone scan, according to PCWG 3 criteria,
             with high volume according to criteria used in the CHAARTED study.

          6. Radiological and scintigraphic studies to identify initial evaluable disease should be
             done as follows:

               -  If ADT has not been initiated, CT scans and bone scan must be obtained within 6
                  weeks prior to the start of ADT.

               -  If all required imaging had not been completed prior to starting ADT, any
                  additional scan must be obtained after starting androgen deprivation but prior to
                  randomization and the initiation of docetaxel (It is assumed that the scans of
                  patients with high volume disease would not normalize in less than 120 days to
                  the point that a patient would go from &quot;high volume&quot; to &quot;low volume&quot;).

          7. Measurable or evaluable disease according to the PWGC 3.

          8. Patients who started ADT for metastatic disease are eligible if ADT commenced within
             120 days before randomization, they have not started docetaxel chemotherapy yet, and
             there was no evidence of clinical, radiological or biochemical progression after ADT.

          9. Patients receiving ADT in the adjuvant and/or neoadjuvant setting for less than 30
             months of therapy, AND the effect of the last depot injection had expired at least 12
             months prior to documentation of metastatic disease, AND

               -  They had no evidence of disease (PSA &lt; 0.2 ng/dL) after prostatectomy plus
                  hormonal therapy, or

               -  PSA was &lt; 0.5 ng/dL after completing radiation therapy plus adjuvant or
                  neoadjuvant hormonal therapy, and had not doubled above nadir in at least 12
                  months.

         10. Patients must have adequate organ function within 4 weeks prior to randomization and
             evidenced by:

               -  Absolute Neutrophil Count &gt; 1500/mm 3

               -  Platelet count &gt; 100,000/mm 3

               -  Creatinine clearance (CrCl)&gt; 30 mL/min calculated at screening using the
                  Cockcroft- Gault formula: Creatinine clearance for mule (mL/min) = (140- age in
                  years)(body weight in kg)/[72x(serum creatinine in mg/dl).

               -  Total bilirubin &lt; 1.5 ULN (&lt; 3.0 mg/dl in patients with Gilbert´s Syndrome).

               -  Prothrombin time or INR and PTT &lt; 1.5 x ULN, except if on therapeutic anti-
                  coagulation in which case the patient can be enrolled if stable and
                  anti-coagulation levels are appropriate for their condition per good clinical
                  practice.

               -  ALT and AST &lt; or = 3 x ULN (or &lt; or = 5 if liver metastases)

         11. At least 4 weeks should have passed after major surgery prior to randomization, and
             the patient should be recovered from all side effects and complications.

         12. Men who are sexually active with WOCBP must agree to follow instructions for methods
             of contraception for the duration of treatment with study drug plus 5 half-lives of
             study drug plus 90 days (duration of sperm turnover) for a total of 31 weeks
             post-treatment completion.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients are not eligible if the PSA has risen from its lowest point, between the
             beginning of androgen deprivation therapy and the date of randomization, and met
             criteria for progression as defined in the protocol.

          2. Prior treatment with an anti-PD-1, anti-PD-L1, anti-PD-L2, anti-CTLA-4 antibody,
             PROSTVAC, Sipuleucel-T or any previous immunotherapy or vaccines for cancer.

          3. Prior chemotherapy in the adjuvant or neoadjuvant setting.

          4. Unable to receive docetaxel at full doses at investigator criteria.

          5. Peripheral neuropathy grade &gt; 1.

          6. All toxicities attributed to prior anti-cancer therapy other than neuropathy, alopecia
             or fatigue must have resolved to Grade 1 (NCI CTCAE version 4) or baseline before
             administration of study drug. Subjects with toxicities attributed to prior surgery or
             radiotherapy, which are not expected to resolve and result in long-term lasting
             sequelae, are permitted to enrol.

          7. History of hypersensitivity reaction to Docetaxel®, other drugs formulated with
             polysorbate 80, or monoclonal antibodies.

          8. Prior hormone therapy or immunotherapy in the metastatic setting.

          9. Prior palliative radiation therapy within 30 days of starting docetaxel.

         10. Known acute or chronic HIV, Hepatitis B, or Hepatitis C. Past Hepatitis B infection
             with no signs of activity later, are allowed

         11. Active brain metastases or leptomeningeal metastases, except if they have been treated
             and there is a magnetic resonance imaging (or CT scan if MRI were contraindicated)
             showing no evidence of progression for at least 4 weeks after the treatment

         12. Subjects with a condition requiring systemic treatment with either corticosteroids (&gt;
             10 mg daily prednisone equivalents) or other immunosuppressive medications within 14
             days previous to randomization. Inhaled or topical steroids and adrenal replacement
             doses &gt; 10 mg daily prednisone equivalents are permitted in the absence of active
             autoimmune disease.

         13. Subjects with active, known or suspected autoimmune disease. Subjects with vitiligo,
             type I diabetes mellitus, residual hypothyroidism due to autoimmune condition only
             requiring hormone replacement, psoriasis not requiring systemic treatment, or
             conditions not expected to recur in the absence of an external trigger are allowed.

         14. Active cardiac disease defined as active angina, symptomatic congestive heart failure,
             or myocardial infarction within the previous six months

         15. History of malignancy in the past 5 years except for basal cell and squamous cell
             carcinoma of the skin and non-muscle-invasive bladder cancer. Other more malignancies
             considered to have a low potential to progress may be enrolled if approved by study
             chair.

         16. Any serious or uncontrolled medical disorder that, in the opinion of the investigator,
             may increase the risk associated with study participation or study drug
             administration, impair the ability of the subject to receive protocol therapy, or
             interfere with the interpretation of study results.

         17. Participation in another clinical trial within 30 days prior to randomization.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <gender_based>Yes</gender_based>
    <gender_description>Condition is exclusive of males</gender_description>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jose Ángel Arranz Arija, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Physician - Investigator</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Jose Ángel Arranz Arija, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+34 610287201</phone>
    <email>secretaria@sogug.es</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Universitario Central de Asturias</name>
      <address>
        <city>Oviedo</city>
        <state>Asturias</state>
        <zip>33011</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Carlos Álvarez Fernández, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Carlos Álvarez Fernández</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hestia Duran I Reynals</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hospitalet de Llobregat</city>
        <state>Barcelona</state>
        <zip>08908</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Josep Maria Piulats, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Josep Maria Piulats</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Sant Joan de Deu (Althaia Manresa)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Manresa</city>
        <state>Barcelona</state>
        <zip>08242</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Montserrat Domènech, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Montserrat Domènech</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital de Sabadell</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sabadell</city>
        <state>Barcelona</state>
        <zip>08208</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Enrique Gallardo, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Enrique Gallardo</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital General, Materno E Infantil Reina</name>
      <address>
        <city>Córdoba</city>
        <state>Cordoba</state>
        <zip>14004</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>María José Méndez Vidal, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>María José Méndez Vidal</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Son Llatzer</name>
      <address>
        <city>Palma De Mallorca</city>
        <state>Islas Baleares</state>
        <zip>07198</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>María Belén González, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Maria Belén González</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Universitario Puerta de Hierro Majadahonda</name>
      <address>
        <city>Majadahonda</city>
        <state>Madrid</state>
        <zip>28222</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Constanza Maximiliano, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Constanza Maximiliano</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Universitario Infanta Sofía</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Sebastián De Los Reyes</city>
        <state>Madrid</state>
        <zip>28072</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Francisco Zambrana, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Francisco Zambrana</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Complejo Hospitalario de Navarra</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pamplona</city>
        <state>Navarra</state>
        <zip>31008</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Nuria Lainez, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Nuria Lainez</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Arnau de Vilanova</name>
      <address>
        <city>Valencia</city>
        <state>Valenci</state>
        <zip>46015</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>José García Sánchez, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>José García Sánchez</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital de Basurto</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bilbao</city>
        <state>Vizcaya</state>
        <zip>48013</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Teresa Abad, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Teresa Abada</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Del Mar</name>
      <address>
        <city>Barcelona</city>
        <zip>08003</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Alejo Rodríguez Vida, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Alejo Rodriguez Vida</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Universitari Vall D'Hebron</name>
      <address>
        <city>Barcelona</city>
        <zip>08035</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Joan Carles Galcerán, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Joan Carles Galcerán</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Clínic de Barcelona</name>
      <address>
        <city>Barcelona</city>
        <zip>08036</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Nuria González, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Nuria González</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Universitario de Burgos</name>
      <address>
        <city>Burgos</city>
        <zip>09006</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Guillermo Crespo Herrero, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Guillermo Crespo Herrero</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital General de Ciudad Real</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ciudad Real</city>
        <zip>13005</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jose Carlos Villa Guzmán</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jose Carlos Villa Guzmán</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital San Pedro de Alcántara</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cáceres</city>
        <zip>10003</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ricardo Collado Martín, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ricardo Collado Martín</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Universitari de Girona Dr. Josep Trueta</name>
      <address>
        <city>Girona</city>
        <zip>17007</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Nuria Sala, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Nuria Sala</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Universitario Lucus Augusti</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lugo</city>
        <zip>27003</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sergio Vázquez Estévez, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Sergio Vázquez Estévez</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital General Universitario Gregorio Marañón</name>
      <address>
        <city>Madrid</city>
        <zip>28007</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jose Angel Arranz Ariza, MD, PhD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jose Angel Arraza Ariza</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Ramón Y Cajal</name>
      <address>
        <city>Madrid</city>
        <zip>28013</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Teresa Alonso, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Teres Alonso</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Clínico San Carlos</name>
      <address>
        <city>Madrid</city>
        <zip>28040</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Javier Puente, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Javier Puente</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Universitario 12 de Octubre</name>
      <address>
        <city>Madrid</city>
        <zip>28041</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Juan Sepúlveda, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Juan Sepúlveda</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Virgen Del Rocío</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sevilla</city>
        <zip>41013</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Begoña Pérez Valderrama, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Begoña Pérez Valderrama</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Nuestra Señora de Valme</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sevilla</city>
        <zip>41014</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Eva María Fernández Parra, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Eva María Fernández Parra</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Virgen Macarena</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sevilla</city>
        <zip>41071</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Juan Antonio Virizuela, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Juan Antonio Virizuela</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Virgen de La Salud</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toledo</city>
        <zip>45004</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Iciar García Carbonero, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Iciar García Carbonero</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Fundación Instituto Valenciano de Oncología</name>
      <address>
        <city>Valencia</city>
        <zip>46009</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Miguel Ángel Climent, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Miguel Ángel Climent</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Consorcio Hospital General Universitario de Valencia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Valencia</city>
        <zip>46014</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Cristina Cabarllero, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Cristina Caballero</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Universitario Alvaro Cunqueiro</name>
      <address>
        <city>Vigo</city>
        <zip>36312</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Martín Lázaro Quintela, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Martín Lázaro Quintela</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Spain</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 13, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 15, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 18, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 16, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 16, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 17, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>prostate cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>immunotherapy</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Prostatic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hypersensitivity</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Docetaxel</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Nivolumab</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ipilimumab</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Androgens</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

