<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03876717</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>SJ-641</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03876717</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effect of the Sequestrant Colesevelam in Bile Acid Diarrhoea</brief_title>
  <acronym>SINBAD</acronym>
  <official_title>Treatment Effect of Colesevelam for Bile Acid Diarrhoea - a Randomised Placebo-controlled Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Lars Kristian Munck</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Pierre and Marie Curie University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Zealand University Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Bile acid diarrhoea is a chronic disease that impairs quality of life. One in 100 has the
      condition and many suffer from the disease without knowing. The current test is called SeHCAT
      and is expensive and time-consuming and is unavailable in many places, including the US. The
      disease is often misdiagnosed as irritable bowel syndrome and estimated one third of patients
      with irritable bowel syndrome of the mixed type and the diarrhoea predominant type suffer
      from bile acid diarrhoea without knowing.

      A blood test called 7α-hydroxy-4-cholestene-3-one (C4) could make it much easier to diagnose
      bile acid diarrhoea.

      To establish the new test, the results of both C4 and SeHCAT are compared with the treatment
      effect of the drug called colesevelam.

      We invite patients who are referred for the SeHCAT test to participate in the trial. The
      SeHCAT test takes two days that are one week apart. The study patients register stool habits
      with a diary in the week between the SeHCAT visits. Based on the diary results, we screen for
      eligibility; e.g. a certain degree/severity of diarrhoea is required for participation. We
      treat eligible study patients (i.e those with diarrhoea) with either colesevelam or placebo
      (medicine without effect) that is randomly assigned. 140 study patients need to complete the
      treatment.

      We aim to validate (ie. compare) both the C4-test and the SeHCAT test with the colesevelam
      treatment response as the reference.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      ISSUE Bile Acid Diarrhoea (BAD) affects 1% of the general population and many people live
      with the disease and the impaired quality of life it causes without knowing it. The current
      scintigraphic seleno-homo-taurocholic acid retention test (SeHCAT) is time-consuming,
      expensive and causes a diagnostic bottleneck. the SeHCAT test is unavailable in many
      countries including the US. The biomarker 7α-hydroxy-4-cholesten-3-one (C4) could provide a
      cheap and available diagnostic option to surmount the issue of the many undiagnosed patients.
      The pivotal step for this is validation of the C4-test with the placebo-controlled treatment
      effect.

      PURPOSE

        1. To determine the efficacy and safety of colesevelam for treating Bile Acid Diarrhoea

           and

        2. To correlate the new C4 test (and secondarily the current SeHCAT test) with the
           placebo-controlled treatment effect

      BACKGROUND Chronic diarrhoea affects 4-5% of the Western adult population and often results
      in specialist referral and endoscopies. Availability of the diagnostic SeHCAT test for BAD is
      limited, and BAD is often mistaken for the Irritable Bowel Syndrome (IBS). 32% of patients
      with two of the three IBS subtypes have BAD and the prevalence of BAD in the general
      population is thus approximately 1%.

      DIAGNOSIS of Bile Acid Diarrhoea The current diagnostic test for BAD is the SeHCAT
      scintigraphic retention test using 75Selenium labelled Homo-tauro-cholic acid. The γ-emission
      is measured on day 1 and again on day 8. Seven-day SeHCAT retention rates of &lt;5% represent
      severe BAD, &lt;10% moderate BAD, and &lt;15% mild BAD. Although not properly validated, in
      observational studies 70-80% of patients with SeHCAT &lt;10% report a good response to
      cholestyramine. SeHCAT is unavailable in many countries including the the US, and clinicians
      instead rely on the patient's response to a therapeutic trial. However, the non-specific
      action and multiple side effects of the first line treatment with cholestyramine gives rise
      to multiple diagnostic pitfalls.

      BIOMARKERS of Bile Acid Diarrhoea The recent increased insight into bile acid homeostasis and
      regulation has identified two biomarkers of BAD that may replace SeHCAT.
      7α-hydroxy-4-cholestene-3-one (C4) is a bile acid precursor that correlates with bile acids
      synthesis rate. C4 is increased in BAD and has a sensitivity of 87% and specificity of 86%
      for diagnosing BAD defined by SeHCAT &lt;10%. However, analysis of C4 is technically difficult
      and is thus primarily used at centres with special interest and no access to SeHCAT.

      Another biomarker Fibroblast Growth Factor 19 (FGF19) is released to the portal circulation
      from the terminal ileum in response to bile acid absorption. In the liver, FGF19 inhibits
      bile acid synthesis enticing a negative feedback loop. Fasting values of FGF19 correlate
      inversely with C4 and with SeHCAT, but the sensitivity of 67% and specificity of 77% for
      detecting even severe BAD is clinically insufficient.

      Performance of the biomarkers in a modern Danish population The investigators studied C4 and
      FGF19 in two pilot studies in selected populations and further established a Danish national
      collaboration with four university hospitals and prospectively recruited 71 subjects. The
      positive test cut-off C4 ≥ 15.4 ng/mL had 76% sensitivity and 80% specificity for detecting
      BAD defined by SeHCAT ≤ 10%.

      The analysis of these results and the literature suggest that taking account of liver
      cirrhosis, hyperbilirubinemia, and use of alcohol and statins may increase the diagnostic
      yield of C4.

      TREATMENT OF BILE ACID DIARRHOEA Sequestrants bind bile acids in the intestinal lumen and
      thus alleviate the diarrhoea symptoms. The first line therapy is cholestyramine, but this
      powder-formulation is distasteful with a low patient acceptability. Colesevelam tablets are
      much better tolerated, and therefore placebo-controlled studies of colesevelam for BAD are
      warranted.

      A systematic review found cholestyramine to be effective in 70% of BAD patients. A
      placebo-controlled trial of colesevelam in patients with suspected type 1 BAD. Diarrhoea
      intention-to-treat remission rates were 67% for colesevelam and 27% for placebo (p=0.057),
      but extreme selection criteria slowed recruitment and the study ended prematurely. Of note,
      only one of 19 dropped out due to side effects to colesevelam. In summary, colesevelam and
      cholestyramine have similar response rates of 70%. For a clinical trial, colesevelam is
      superior due to effective blinding and a much lower dropout rate.

      METHODS Effect parameters in chronic diarrhoea Symptoms reported by diary The Bristol stool
      form scale (BSFS) classifies stool from 1 (hard lumps) to 7 (completely watery). Clinical
      trials often use a seven-day diary. Patients with an organic cause of diarrhoea more often
      have ≥3 stools per day or a consistently watery stool consistency (BSF≥6) than those who have
      a functional cause of the diarrhoea.

      Criteria for activity and remission of diarrhoea (Hjortswang's criteria) Hjortswang
      correlated chronic diarrhoea symptoms with impact on quality of life for patients with
      microscopic colitis, and validated the definition of clinical activity as ≥ 3 stools per day
      or ≥ 1 watery stool (BSF 6-7) and remission as &lt;3 stools per day and &lt; 1 watery stool as a
      mean of the seven-day diary.

      MEDICINE Colesevelam The hospital pharmacy of the Capital Region over-encapsulates
      colesevelam tablets with Capsugel® DBcaps®

      Placebo Matrix placebo tablets, over-encapsulated as the colesevelam tablets. No side effects
      are expected.

      Dose: One, two or three capsules of 625mg twice daily. The dose is titrated by a central
      blinded study nurse without contact to the investigators.

      POWER CALCULATION Assumed

        -  remission rate of 63% for colesevelam and 27% for placebo.

        -  two-sided α = 0.05 and β = 0.20 (ie. 80% power).

        -  1:1 allocation. This gives 29 subjects with BAD in each arm (G.Power 3.1: z-test of two
           independent proportions). 45.7% of subjects in our prospective pilot study that would be
           eligible for the SINBAD study had SeHCAT &lt;10%. Thus, (2 x 29 / 45.7%) * 110% = 140
           subjects.

      BIOCHEMISTRY C4 and bile acid species are analysed with liquid chromatography - tandem mass
      spectrometry. FGF19 is analysed with ELISA (R&amp;D Systems, MN, USA).

      The hospital laboratories of the participating centres perform the routine biochemical
      analyses.

      STUDY PLAN Pre-screening

        1. We send a written invitation to eligible patients who already are referred for SeHCAT

        2. At the first SeHCAT visit, further information is provided and voluntary informed
           consent is obtained.

      Study visit 1 - Day 1: start of baseline registration The investigator creates an electronic
      Case Record Form (EasyTrial) including medical and surgical history, medication, and physical
      status. Baseline blood analyses include ALT, ALP, bilirubin, amylase; and on indication HCG.

      The investigator notifies the referring doctor.

      The participants start Study Diary 1 (screening+baseline).

      Study visit 2 - Day 8: Screening results - randomisation This is concurrent with the second
      SeHCAT visit. All subjects meet in the fasting for blood sampling. All subjects answer the
      baseline questionnaires (SHS, GSRS, SF36v2).

      The screening diary is assessed:

      Subjects without diarrhoea: cannot continue to randomisation.

        1. SeHCAT results are registered once available

        2. Result of the diagnostic work-up is registered at a six-month telephone follow-up.

      Subjects with diarrhoea: continue to randomisation. The subject

        -  is given a uniquely numbered treatment package

        -  starts Study Diary 2

        -  is telephoned by the central study nurse for the planning of dose titration

      Telephone consultation - Day 9 (treatment day 2):

      The study nurse takes a history of adverse events and titres the dose

      Telephone consultation - day 13 (± 1 day): End of Run-in-period As on day 9.

      Ad hoc telephone consultations Any change in dose mandates a follow-up telephone consult
      after 2-3 days.

      Study visit 3 - Day 21 (+ 1-3 days) Intervention-End The intervention has ended on day 20.

      The investigator:

        -  Collects Study Diary 2

        -  Takes a history of AEs

        -  Collects surplus medication to assess compliance

        -  Distributes questionnaires

        -  Orders follow-up blood analysis

        -  Schedules study-end telephone consultation

      Telephone consultation - Study day 26 (± 2 day): Clinical Study end AE registration continues
      three days after the end of treatment.

      The investigator:

        -  Assess biochemical AEs

           o Informs of results

        -  Takes a history of AEs

        -  Takes action if needed

      Six-month follow-up The questionnaires are redistributed. The patient's Medical file is
      checked and a telephone interview is done to note any conclusive diagnosis on the patients
      diarrhoea and (if any) anti-diarrhoea medication
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 1, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 30, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Parallel arms, randomized 1:1 allocation.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>Study subjects and all investigators are blinded. As effect and side effects of the active drug may demask the blinding, a central study nurse is the primary contact for the subjects during the intervention periode regarding everything except suspected/possible serious events.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Intention-to-treat diarrhoea remission rate defined by the Hjortswang criteria for colesevelam in patients with BAD defined by C4 ≥ 15.4 ng/mL</measure>
    <time_frame>Intervention days 6 through 12 (last seven intervention days)</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Per protocol diarrhoea remission rate defined by the Hjortswang criteria for colesevelam in patients with BAD defined by C4 ≥ 15.4 ng/mL</measure>
    <time_frame>Intervention days 6 through 12 (last seven intervention days)</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Intention-to-treat diarrhoea remission rate defined by the Hjortswang criteria for colesevelam in patients with BAD defined by SeHCAT &lt;= 10%</measure>
    <time_frame>Intervention days 6 through 12 (last seven intervention days)</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Per protocol diarrhoea remission rate defined by the Hjortswang criteria for colesevelam in patients with BAD defined by SeHCAT &lt;= 10%</measure>
    <time_frame>Intervention days 6 through 12 (last seven intervention days)</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>placebo-controlled effect of colesevelam in patients with bile acid diarrhoea defined by C4 on the absolute number of stools as mean per day over 6 or 7 days</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline period compared with Intervention days 6 through 12 (last seven intervention days)</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>placebo-controlled effect of colesevelam in patients with bile acid diarrhoea defined by C4 on the total number of Bristol type 6 and 7 stools as a mean over 6 or 7 days</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline period compared with Intervention days 6 through 12 (last seven intervention days)</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Intention-to-treat diarrhoea remission rate defined by the Hjortswang criteria for colesevelam in patients with BAD defined by FGF19 &lt;= 85 pg/mL</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline period compared with Intervention days 6 through 12 (last seven intervention days)</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference in change in Health related quality of life (HRQoL) in the primary endpoint population by the Short Form 36 version 2 (SF36v2) Physical component score (colesevelam vs. placebo)</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline period compared with Intervention days 6 through 12 (last seven intervention days)</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference in change in Health related quality of life (HRQoL) in the primary endpoint population by the Short Form 36 version 2 (SF36v2) Mental component score (colesevelam vs. placebo)</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline period compared with Intervention days 6 through 12 (last seven intervention days)</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Placebo-controlled subject assessed &quot;good response&quot; ITT rate in the primary endpoint population</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline period compared with Intervention days 6 through 12 (last seven intervention days)</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Placebo-controlled ITT diarrhoea remission rate defined by the Hjortswang criteria for colesevelam in patients with non-BAD, ie. defined by C4 &lt; 15.4 ng/mL</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline period compared with Intervention days 6 through 12 (last seven intervention days)</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Placebo-controlled remission rates (ITT+ PP) for colesevelam defined by the Hjortswang criteria in patients with BAD defined by SeHCAT &lt;=5%</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline period compared with Intervention days 6 through 12 (last seven intervention days)</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Placebo-controlled remission rates (ITT+ PP) for colesevelam defined by the Hjortswang criteria in patients with BAD defined by SeHCAT &lt;=15%</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline period compared with Intervention days 6 through 12 (last seven intervention days)</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Intention-to-treat and per-protocol diarrhoea remission rate defined by the Hjortswang criteria for colesevelam in non-BAD</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline period compared with Intervention days 6 through 12 (last seven intervention days)</time_frame>
    <description>Separately for non-BAD defined by 1) C4 &lt; 15.4 ng/mL and by 2) SeHCAT &gt; 10%</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>The placebo-controlled effect of colesevelam in non BAD-patients on the absolute number of stools</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline period compared with Intervention days 6 through 12 (last seven intervention days)</time_frame>
    <description>Separately for non-BAD defined by 1) C4 &lt; 15.4 ng/mL and by 2) SeHCAT &gt; 10%</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>ROC analysis (dichotomous positive/negative) of C4, SeHCAT, FGF19, subject assessed &quot;good response&quot;, with response by Hjortswang criteria as gold standard.</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline period compared with Intervention days 6 through 12 (last seven intervention days)</time_frame>
    <description>Positive tests: for C4 ≥ 15.4ng/mL, for SeHCAT ≤ 10%, for FGF19 ≤ 85pg/mL.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Validation of C4 cut-off ≥ 15.4ng/mL with SeHCAT ≤ 10% for diagnosing BAD</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline period compared with Intervention days 6 through 12 (last seven intervention days)</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Test-retest variability of baseline C4 assessed with a Bland-Altman plot</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline day 1 vs day 8 (before treatment start)</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Test-retest variability of baseline FGF19 assessed with a Bland-Altman plot</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline day 1 vs day 8 (before treatment start)</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Exploratory assessment of the effect on C4 test-retest variability assessed with a Bland-Altman plot comparing C4 measured on baseline day 1 possibly affected by different factors compared with 'gold standard' C4 measured on day 8.</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline day 1 versus day 8</time_frame>
    <description>Possible day 1 factors: 1) late sampling time, 2) statin use, and 3) alcohol intake.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Health-related quality of life Short Form 36 v.2 item 'Physical Component Score (range 0-100)' correlated with diarrhoea symptoms</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, last seven treatment days and six-month follow-up.</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Health-related quality of life Short Form 36 v.2 item 'Mental Component Score (range 0-100)' correlated with diarrhoea symptoms</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, last seven treatment days and six-month follow-up.</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">140</enrollment>
  <condition>Bile Acid Malabsorption</condition>
  <condition>Chronic Diarrhea</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Colesevelam, active arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Colesevelam hydrochloride, 625mg tablets. Overencapsulated with DB caps AAA for blinding.
Oral use. Dose: 1, 2, or 3 capsules twice daily. Starting dose 2 capsules twice daily. Dose titration by specific criteria by a central study nurse Treatment duration 12 days</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Inactive placebo tablets. Overencapsulated with DB caps AAA for blinding. Oral use. Dosage and treatment duration as specified for colesevelam</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Colesevelam Hydrochloride</intervention_name>
    <description>Colesevelam is a sequestrant that binds bile acids in the intestinal lumen, the bile acids are then excreted with the feces. Colesevelam is registered for treating hypercholesterolemia but it is as other sequestrants (e.g. cholestyramine and colestipol) effective against bile acid diarrhoea.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Colesevelam, active arm</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Cholestagel</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo oral capsule</intervention_name>
    <description>Inactive placebo tablets over-encapsulated with DB caps AAA</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Inactive placebo</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patient referred to Clinical Physiological/Nuclear Medicine departments for SeHCAT

          -  Suspected Bile acid diarrhoea

          -  Age &gt; 18 years and under 80 years

          -  women of fertile age must use safe contraception during the treatment part of the
             study

          -  Ability to give informed consent after written and oral information in Danish language

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Inflammatory bowel disease, including microscopic colitis

          -  Investigator assessed debilitating chronic disease e.g. World Health Organisation
             performance score 3-5

          -  Prior treatment with colesevelam

          -  Treatment with laxatives or anti-diarrhoeal drugs during the study

               -  Except for stable dose the last four weeks of psyllium husk and opioids for pain

          -  Breastfeeding women

          -  Crucial medication that cannot be separated appropriately from colesevelam

               -  i.e. taken one hour before or 4 hours after colesevelam

          -  Oral anticoagulation, both warfarin, and new oral anticoagulation

          -  Treatment with cyclosporine within two months

          -  Bowel obstruction (subileus or ileus)

          -  Biliary obstruction

          -  Short bowel syndrome

          -  Bowel ostomy

          -  Allergy to colesevelam or its constituents

          -  Allergy to placebo constituents (excluding lactose)

          -  Investigator assessed high risk of non-compliance

          -  If on statin/fibrate medication, unwilling to pause medication between study visits 1
             and 2
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Lars K Munck, DMSci</last_name>
    <phone>+45 47322400</phone>
    <email>lkmu@regionsjaelland.dk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Christian Borup, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+45 23328035</phone>
    <email>chrbo@regionsjaelland.dk</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Aalborg University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Aalborg</city>
        <zip>9000</zip>
        <country>Denmark</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Enrolling by invitation</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Aarhus University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Aarhus</city>
        <zip>8200</zip>
        <country>Denmark</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Enrolling by invitation</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hvidovre University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hvidovre</city>
        <zip>2650</zip>
        <country>Denmark</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Christian Borup, MD</last_name>
      <email>chrbo@regionsjaelland.dk</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Zealand University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Køge</city>
        <zip>4600</zip>
        <country>Denmark</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Christian Borup, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+45 23328035</phone>
      <email>chrbo@regionsjaelland.dk</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Christian Borup, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Denmark</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 9, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 12, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 15, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 12, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 12, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 15, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Zealand University Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Lars Kristian Munck</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Senior Physician, Clinical Associate Professor, Sponsor-Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Malabsorption Syndromes</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diarrhea</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Colesevelam Hydrochloride</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>An electronic Data Management Plan has been created on dmponline.dcc.ac.uk with details on management of raw data, refined data, metadata, organising, storing, backup, sharing, and curation of the data The biological material is saved anonymously and destroyed 15 years after study end.
Positive and negative results will be published in an international peer-reviewed journal. We regard the study protocol, consent form, questionnaires, statistical analysis plan, raw data, refined data, statistical code, and metadata as long-term valuable data to be shared after de-identification in the repository of the Danish National Archives to be available after the primary article is published. Data access is unrestricted and indefinite and with investigator assistance for the first 36 months.</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Statistical Analysis Plan (SAP)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Clinical Study Report (CSR)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Analytic Code</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>De-identified data will be made available without restrictions after articles from the study have been published</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>Data access is unrestricted and indefinite and with investigator assistance for the first 36 months. Publications need proper citing.</ipd_access_criteria>
    <ipd_url>https://dmponline.dcc.ac.uk/</ipd_url>
  </patient_data>
  <provided_document_section>
    <provided_document>
      <document_type>Study Protocol and Statistical Analysis Plan</document_type>
      <document_has_protocol>Yes</document_has_protocol>
      <document_has_icf>No</document_has_icf>
      <document_has_sap>Yes</document_has_sap>
      <document_date>January 4, 2019</document_date>
      <document_url>https://ClinicalTrials.gov/ProvidedDocs/17/NCT03876717/Prot_SAP_000.pdf</document_url>
    </provided_document>
  </provided_document_section>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

