<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03879967</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Allo_3_OCS_zmkUnibe</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03879967</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Lateral Ridge Augmentation Using Allograft Blocks and GBR for Implant Sites</brief_title>
  <official_title>Lateral Ridge Augmentation Using Allograft Blocks and Guided Bone Regeneration for Implant Sites</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Bern</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Bern</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Clinicians are increasingly faced with the challenge of reconstructing the alveolar ridge as
      more patients desire fixed implant-supported restorations. Reconstruction of large horizontal
      alveolar defects still remains a challenge in implantology. Although autogenous blocks from
      intraoral sites are proven effective for such defects, donor site morbidity and limited graft
      availability are major limitations. Allogenic bone blocks have been proposed to overcome
      these limitations, however, the outcomes reported in the literature are inconclusive. In this
      case series, the efficacy of allogenic blocks for lateral augmentation of atrophic ridges was
      evaluated, over a three-year period.

      In nineteen edentulous sites from ten patients, cortico-cancellous allogenic blocks (PHOENIX,
      TBF, France) were shaped to the defect and screw-fixated. A double-layer of autogenous chips
      and demineralized bovine bone (Bio-Oss, Geistlich Pharma AG, Switzerland) was used to fill
      the voids. The augmented site was covered by non-cross-linked collagen membrane (Bio-Gide,
      Geistlich Pharma AG, Switzerland). After a healing period of 9 months, implants were placed
      and CBCT analysis was performed post-implantation. Following a period of 34 months of
      function (range 22 to 44 months), patients were clinically and radiographically re-examined.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The present study design is a mono-center three-year follow-up case series study to examined
      the safety and effectiveness of allograft bone blocks combined with guided bone regeneration
      (GBR). The study was in accordance to the principles of the Declaration of Helsinki and was
      approved by the standing ethical committee of the state of Bern, Switzerland.

      The preoperative analysis included a complete medical history, clinical examination of the
      dentition and a thorough analysis of the implant recipient using 3D cone beam computed
      tomography (3D Accuitomo 170, Morita, Kyoto, Japan).

      Surgical Procedure:

      The surgical procedures were done in two stages. In the first stage surgery, a full-thickness
      mucoperiosteal flap was raised on both the facial and palatal aspects. Ridge augmentation was
      done using a mineralized, cortico-cancellous, delipidized, lyophilized allogenic block (ALB ;
      PHOENIX allograft, TBF Mions, France). Following hydration of the ALB, the cortico-cancellous
      part of the block was shaped to fit the recipient site and fixated by two fixation screws
      (Medartis, Modus, Medartis Holding AG, Basel, Switzerland). Voids around the ALB were filled
      with autogenous bone chips (AGB) harvested locally from the recipient site. The augmented
      site was covered by a first layer of deproteinized bovine bone mineral mixed (DBBM; Bio- Oss,
      Geistlich Pharma, Wolhusen, Switzerland and a non-crosslinked collagen membrane (BG; Bio-
      Gide, Geistlich AG, Wolhusen, Switzerland) as described previously (Chappuis et al DOI
      10.1111/cid.12438). A periosteal-releasing incision was used to provide tension-free flap
      closure. The wound margins were approximated using non-resorbable poly- amide suture
      (Seralon, Serag-Wiessner GmbH, Naila, Germany) to obtain primary wound closure. All patients
      were prescribed an antibiotic regimen with 2g of amoxicillin with clavulanic acid 1 hour
      preoperatively to be continued as 1g twice daily for 3 days post-surgery. Patients were also
      prescribed analgesics and chlorhexidine digluconate (0.2%) for chemical plaque control. In
      patients with post-surgical complications the antibiotic regimen was prolonged. Sutures were
      removed around 14 days postoperatively. Removable provisionals were adapted, but patients
      were instructed to not to wear them unless unavoidable during the initial healing phase.

      The second stage surgery was performed after a minimal healing period of six months (range 6
      to 13months for me this would belong to the results). A paracrestal incision was given to
      elevate a full thickness mucoperiosteal. The fixation screws from the previous surgery were
      removed and the implant bed was prepared based on the specific requirements of the site. All
      implants placed had chemically modified, sandblasted, and acid-etched surface and had either,
      a tissue level implant (TL) or a bone level implant (BL) design (SLActive, Straumann AG,
      Basel, Switzerland). Simultaneous re-grafting was performed as required using autogenous bone
      chips, DBBM and a non-cross linked collagen membrane. A tension-free wound closure was
      obtained by non-resorbable sutures. The antibiotic and analgesic regimen and post-surgical
      care as the same as in the first-stage surgery. Sutures were removed after 14 days. Patients
      were instructed to wear the provisional with caution. After the healing period of 4-6 months
      the healing abutments were placed for the future prosthetics. The implants were restored with
      either single-unit crowns (SC), crowns with extensions (SC-E), bridges (B), bridges with
      extensions (B-E) or ball abutments (BA). All restorations were screw-retained. Patient were
      given oral hygiene instructions and directed to enroll onto a supportive periodontal therapy
      to monitor oral health.

      Clinical and radiographic follow-up examination after 3 years:

      Clinical parameters - Updates on medical conditions, smoking, oral hygiene and enrollment in
      a maintenance care program were collected from the patients. Clinical examinations were taken
      by the same examiner (VC) throughout the three-year follow-up period. The clinical parameters
      were assessed as previously described (Chappuis et al DOI 10.1111/cid.12438): peri-implant
      suppuration, modified plaque index (mPLI), modified sulcus bleeding index (mBLI), probing
      depth, DIM (distance from the implant shoulder to the mucosal margin), width of the KM,
      mobility and full mouth plaque scores.

      Radiographic analysis using 2D radiographs and 3D CBCT - The peri-implant bone loss was
      measured on periapical 2D radiographs analysing the proximal DIB values as the vertical
      distance from the implant shoulder to the first bone-to-implant contact as described earlier
      (DIB; mm) (Weber HP et al 1992). The mean DIB value per implant considered was the average of
      the mesial and distal values.

      The horizontal bone gain of the atrophic sites was assessed by with the smallest field of
      view (3D Accuitomo 170, Morita, Kyoto, Japan). The image analysis was performed by a
      high-resolution screen, using a specialised software (i-Dixel, Morita, Kyoto, Japan). The 3D
      analysis included a preoperative analysis of the proposed implant site. A standard reference
      point, 4mm crestal to the shoulder of the future implant was used for all measurements
      (Chappuis 2017). CBCT measurements were repeated prior to implant placement, using the same
      reference point and repeated again at the 2-3year follow-up appointment. The radiographic
      measurements were done by one examiner (OE).

      Assessment of biological, technical complications and patient reported outcome measures
      (PROMS) - All events of complications, intra-operative and post-operative at each surgical
      phase (graft surgery and implant surgery), prior to prosthetic treatment and post prosthetic
      rehabilitation both operator-assessed and self-reported were recorded.

      Patient reported outcome measures were assessed by the Oral Health Impact Profile (OHIP)
      scores and patient satisfaction scores based on a visual analog scale (VAS) were recorded for
      each patient after the entire treatment was completed and the patients received the
      prosthetic replacements.

      Statistical Analysis:

      All data sets were first analysed descriptively and were expressed as mean values with
      standard deviation. A repeated measures design was chosen and a linear mixed model was fitted
      for each single factor to assess its impact on the final outcome and co-relations were
      evaluated. Throughout, p-values less than 0.05 were considered as statistically significant.
      p-values were not corrected for multiple testing due to the explorative nature of this study.
      The statistical analysis was performed with the software package R (Version 3.5.1, R
      Foundation for Statistical Computing, Vienna, Austria).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 11, 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 14, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 7, 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>A group of thirteen patients were selected for lateral ridge augmentation using cortico-cancellous allogenic block with guided bone regeneration. After the first surgery a healing phase was given and then a second surgery for implant placement in these augmented sites was carried out. Post healing, the implants were prosthetically restored and followed up upto three years.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in ridge thickness with use of the allograft block</measure>
    <time_frame>The measurements were done at approximately 9 months after ridge augmentation surgery and prior to implant placement.</time_frame>
    <description>The change in ridge thickness was measured in mm at a specific reference point 4mm apical to the shoulder of the implant. The measurements were done from a CBCT image in the coronal/sagittal plane.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in ridge thickness with use of the allograft block after implant placement</measure>
    <time_frame>The measurements were done at the follow-up appointment approximately 3years after implant placement.</time_frame>
    <description>The change in ridge thickness was measured in mm at a specific reference point 4mm apical to the shoulder of the implant. The measurements were done from a CBCT image in the coronal/sagittal plane.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Peri-implant suppuration</measure>
    <time_frame>Recorded at the 3years follow-up time point</time_frame>
    <description>Measured by palpation and probing</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Modified plaque index by Mombelli</measure>
    <time_frame>Recorded at the 3years follow-up time point</time_frame>
    <description>Measured visually and with a periodontal probe. Assessed at four aspects around the implants mesial, distal, buccal and lingual.
score 0, no detection of plaque; score 1, plaque only recognized by running a probe across the smooth marginal surface of the implant; score 2, plaque can be seen by the naked eye; and score 3, abundance of soft matter. The average of the four scores, gives the Modified plaque index for the implant</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Modified sulcus bleeding index by Mombelli</measure>
    <time_frame>Recorded at the 3years follow-up time point</time_frame>
    <description>Measured visually and with a periodontal probe.Measured visually and with a periodontal probe. Assessed at four aspects around the implants mesial, distal, buccal and lingual.
score 0: no bleeding when a periodontal probe is passed along the gingival margin adjacent to the implant; score 1: isolated bleeding spot visible; score 2: blood forms a confluent red line on margin; score 3: heavy or profuse bleeding. The average of the four scores gives the Modified sulcus bleeding index for the implant</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Probing depth</measure>
    <time_frame>Recorded at the 3years follow-up time point</time_frame>
    <description>Measured with a periodontal probe in mm. Normal probing depth is between 1-3mm.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Distance from the implant shoulder to the mucosal margin</measure>
    <time_frame>Recorded at the 3years follow-up time point</time_frame>
    <description>Measured in mm from a 2D radiograph on mesial and distal aspects of the implant</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Width of the keratinized mucosa</measure>
    <time_frame>Recorded at the 3years follow-up time point</time_frame>
    <description>Measured with a probe in mm on the buccal surface</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mobility</measure>
    <time_frame>Recorded at the 3years follow-up time point</time_frame>
    <description>Measured by palpation and resonance frequency analysis. Resonance frequency value les than 60 shows low stability and over 70 shows high stability.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Full mouth plaque scores</measure>
    <time_frame>Recorded at the 3years follow-up time point</time_frame>
    <description>Full mouth plaque score expressed as a percentage</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with intraoperative complications at graft surgery</measure>
    <time_frame>During graft surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Presence or absence of intraoperative complications as assessed by operator. Score 1 : no complications score 2: bleeding The patient is allotted one of the two scores</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with intraoperative complications at implant surgery</measure>
    <time_frame>During the implant placement surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Presence or absence of intraoperative complications as assessed by operator. Score 1 : no complications score 2: bleeding The patient is allotted one of the two scores</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with post graft surgery complications</measure>
    <time_frame>One day after to 6 months post graft surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Presence or absence of post surgical complications as assessed by operator or reported by patient score 1: no complication score 2: hematoma score 3: post operative bleeding score 4: infection score 5: sequestrum The implant is allotted one of the above scores</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with post implant surgery complications</measure>
    <time_frame>One day after to 6 months post implant surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Presence or absence of post surgical complications as assessed by operator or reported by patient score 1: no complication score 2: hematoma score 3: post operative bleeding score 4: infection score 5: sequestrum The implant is allotted one of the above scores</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of patients with technical complications</measure>
    <time_frame>One day after to 3 months post prosthetic rehabilitation</time_frame>
    <description>Presence of absence of technical complications with prosthesis as assessed by operator or reported by patient.
score 1: no complication score 2: chipping score 3: framework fracture score 4:loosening score 5: abutment fracture score 6: new crown to be fabricated The implant is allotted one of the above scores</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Visual Analog Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years afer implant placement</time_frame>
    <description>As assessed by the patient to rate the experience with the prosthesis on a scale of 1 to 100 with 1 being the lowest and 100 being the highest score</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Oral Health Impact Profile 14</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years after implant placement</time_frame>
    <description>As assessed by the patient to rate the overall treatment. The patient has to answer 14 questions related to the treatment and each question is scored from a score of 0 to 4.
score 0: never, score l: hardly ever score 2: occasionally score 3: fairly often, score 4: very often The scores for all questions are added to obtain a score for the patient</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">13</enrollment>
  <condition>Alveolar Ridge Augmentation</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Allograft block graft</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>For lateral alveolar ridge augmentation, all patients will be treated with allograft block with guided bone regeneration. After a minimal healing phase of six months, implants would be placed in the augmented site. After a healing phase of about 4months, the implants would be loaded and then followed until the control appointment approximately 3 years later.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Allograft block graft</intervention_name>
    <description>The graft used is a mineralized, cortico-cancellous, delipidized, lyophilized allogenic block.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Allograft block graft</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Atrophy of the alveolar ridge in the horizontal plane (&lt;4 mm in posterior sites and &lt;5
             mm in anterior sites), or a crest width 5 mm in esthetic sites.

          2. Patients who agree to sign an informed consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients who had adequate horizontal ridge thickness and did not require ridge
             augmentation

          2. Patients with deficient vertical height of the ridge requiring vertical augmentation

          3. Patients who were not ready for implant supported prosthesis
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Daniel A Buser Prof, DDS,DMD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Department of Oral Surgery and Stomatology, ZMK, University of Bern</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Vivianne Chappuis Prof, PD, DMD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Department of Oral Surgery and Stomatology, ZMK, University of Bern</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Odette Engel, Dr med dent</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Department of Oral Surgery and Stomatology, ZMK, University of Bern</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Supriya Ebenezer, BDS, MDS</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Department of Oral Surgery and Stomatology, ZMK, University of Bern</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of Oral Surgery and Stomatology, ZMK, University of Bern</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bern</city>
        <zip>3010</zip>
        <country>Switzerland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Switzerland</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chappuis V, Cavusoglu Y, Buser D, von Arx T. Lateral Ridge Augmentation Using Autogenous Block Grafts and Guided Bone Regeneration: A 10-Year Prospective Case Series Study. Clin Implant Dent Relat Res. 2017 Feb;19(1):85-96. doi: 10.1111/cid.12438. Epub 2016 Jul 31.</citation>
    <PMID>27476677</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 8, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 15, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 19, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 15, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 15, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 19, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Allograft block</keyword>
  <keyword>guided bone regeneration</keyword>
  <keyword>implants</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <provided_document_section>
    <provided_document>
      <document_type>Study Protocol</document_type>
      <document_has_protocol>Yes</document_has_protocol>
      <document_has_icf>No</document_has_icf>
      <document_has_sap>No</document_has_sap>
      <document_date>December 8, 2018</document_date>
      <document_url>https://ClinicalTrials.gov/ProvidedDocs/67/NCT03879967/Prot_000.pdf</document_url>
    </provided_document>
  </provided_document_section>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

