<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03875885</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IRB00056635</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>5KL2TR001421-04</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>WFBCCC 99519</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03875885</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>CONNECTing Head and Neck Caregivers to Supportive Care Resources</brief_title>
  <acronym>CONNECT-HNC</acronym>
  <official_title>CONNECTing Caregivers to Supportive Services (CONNECT): A Technology-Based Intervention to Connect Cancer Caregivers With Supportive Care Resources</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Wake Forest University Health Sciences</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Center for Advancing Translational Science (NCATS)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Wake Forest University Health Sciences</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this research is to determine feasibility and acceptability of randomized
      pilot trial to evaluate a technology-based intervention (CONNECT) to empower and educate
      caregivers about the benefits of supportive care resources, identify their unmet needs, and
      connect them with resources.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The registration is for Objective two and three that refers to the clinical trial. The
      investigators will determine their ability to recruit caregivers of patients with head and
      neck cancer being treated at Wake Forest Baptist Comprehensive Cancer Center to a study that
      uses a technology-based intervention, CONNECT, which may increase head and neck cancer
      caregivers' knowledge about the benefits of supportive care resources, identify their unmet
      needs, and connect them with supportive care resources. In this study the investigators also
      want to look at their ability to recruit a control group of caregivers, that is, caregivers
      of patients with head and neck cancer being treated at Wake Forest Baptist Comprehensive
      Cancer Center that will receive a list of supportive care resources. Control groups are used
      in research to see if the intervention being studied really does have an effect. In addition,
      the investigators will determine whether or not the intervention has led to improvements in
      caregivers' use of supportive care resources, quality of care, and overall quality of life.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">August 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Health Services Research</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of Caregivers Who Agree to Participate</measure>
    <time_frame>9 months</time_frame>
    <description>Number of caregivers who agreed to participate divided by the number of months of recruitment</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of Eligible Participants</measure>
    <time_frame>9 months</time_frame>
    <description>Proportion of eligible participants who agreed to participate</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Retention of Participants</measure>
    <time_frame>9 months</time_frame>
    <description>Number of participants who completed the T2 assessment divided by the number who agreed to participate</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Acceptability</measure>
    <time_frame>9 months</time_frame>
    <description>Survey developed for study to assess how much caregivers liked different aspects of CONNECT; and a ~30min (approximately) qualitative interview to further explore acceptability. (Appendices H, I, and J)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Supportive Care Utilization</measure>
    <time_frame>Over 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Adapted version of the 28-item Consumer-Based Cancer Care Value Index- Services and Resources instrument assessing use of services to meet multidimensional supportive needs. Intervention caregivers will also self-report service use by completing an auto-generated REDCap survey to query about utilization of the specific resources that each caregiver expressed interest in accessing.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>FAMCARE Questionnaire (Caregiver)</measure>
    <time_frame>Over 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>A 20-item instrument with 4 subscales to assess family caregiver satisfaction with information giving, availability of care, physical patient care, and symptom control. Participants will answer questions to indicate how satisfied they are with care family member has received. (Subscales = (S) satisfied, (U) undecided, (D) dissatisfied or (VD) very dissatisfied</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Caregiver Reaction Assessment</measure>
    <time_frame>Over 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Caregiver Reaction Assessment - 24-item instrument assessing positive and negative aspects of caregiving (esteem, lack of family support, finances, schedule, and health). The CRA has been tested in cancer caregivers; demonstrated validity and reliability. Each item is rated on a 1 to 4 scale. 1 (not at all) 2 (somewhat) 3 (quite a bit) 4 (completely)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PROMIS Emotional Distress-Anxiety-Short Form 8a</measure>
    <time_frame>Over 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>An 8-item instrument that assesses fear, anxious misery, hyperarousal, and somatic symptoms related to arousal; widely used in oncology populations. Each item on the measure is rated on a 5-point scale (1=never; 2=rarely; 3=sometimes; 4=often; and 5=always) with a range in score from 8 to 40 with higher scores indicating greater severity of anxiety.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PROMIS Emotional Distress- Depression-Short Form 8a</measure>
    <time_frame>Over 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>An 8-item instrument that assesses sadness, guilt, self-criticism, worthlessness, loneliness, interpersonal alienation, as well as loss of interest, meaning, and purpose. Each item on the measure is rated on a 5-point scale (1=never; 2=rarely; 3=sometimes; 4=often; and 5=always) with a range in score from 8 to 40 with higher scores indicating greater severity of depression.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Caregiver Quality of Life Index-Cancer (CqoL-Canc)</measure>
    <time_frame>Over 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>35-item instrument assessing dimensions of caregiver quality of life (burden, disruptiveness, positive adaptation, financial concerns). Scoring scale is 0 = not at all to 4 = very much). Maximum score of 140. Higher scores indicate better quality of life.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Caregiver Risk Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>Over 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>A 7-item measure to assess caregiver behaviors for managing self-care. Questions are answered Yes or No and is a summation of the number of risks. Score range of 0-7, the higher the number, the greater the risk.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Caregiving Self-Efficacy Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>Over 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>21-item instrument assessing caregivers' perceived self-efficacy for coping with cancer (managing medical information, caring for care recipient, caring for oneself, managing difficult interactions/emotions). Uses a likert scale from 1 (not at all confident) to 9 (totally confident). Higher scores indicate higher self-efficacy for coping with cancer.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Barriers to Supportive Care Use Survey</measure>
    <time_frame>Over 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>A 16-item survey with an additional &quot;other&quot; category for a caregiver to report additional barriers not noted on the survey. Response options range from never (0) to always (4). Higher scores indicate a greater number of barriers.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Caregiver Adherence to Referral Survey</measure>
    <time_frame>Over 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Survey responses will be coded as &quot;adhered&quot; or &quot;did not adhere&quot; for agency- and caregiver- reported service utilization. The score reporting is a dichotomous outcome of an adhered or not adhered.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>SF-12 Patient Measures - Physical/Emotional Well-being</measure>
    <time_frame>Over 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>A 12-item instrument measuring physical and mental well-being, though our analyses will focus on physical well-being; widely used in oncology populations. Physical and Mental Health Composite Scores (PCS &amp; MCS) are computed using the scores of twelve questions and range from 0 to 100, where a zero score indicates the lowest level of health measured by the scales and 100 indicates the highest level of health.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Unplanned Healthcare Utilization Survey</measure>
    <time_frame>Over 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Unplanned healthcare utilization survey will be calculated using a one item continuous score. The survey will capture patient self-reported unplanned healthcare utilization (number of unplanned visits to the emergency room, urgent care, or healthcare provider) from time points of baseline to end of treatment.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>FAMCARE Questionnaire (Patient)</measure>
    <time_frame>Over 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>A 20-item instrument with 4 subscales to assess family caregiver satisfaction with information giving, availability of care, physical patient care, and symptom control. Participants will answer questions to indicate how satisfied they are with care family member has received. (Subscales = (S) satisfied, (U) undecided, (D) dissatisfied or (VD) very dissatisfied</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>PROMIS Emotional Distress-Anxiety-Short Form 8a for Patients</measure>
    <time_frame>Over 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>An 8-item instrument that assesses fear, anxious misery, hyperarousal, and somatic symptoms related to arousal; widely used in oncology populations</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>PROMIS Emotional Distress- Depression-Short Form 8a for Patients</measure>
    <time_frame>Over 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>An 8-item instrument that assesses sadness, guilt, self-criticism, worthlessness, loneliness, interpersonal alienation, as well as loss of interest, meaning, and purpose.Each item on the measure is rated on a 5-point scale (1=never; 2=rarely; 3=sometimes; 4=often; and 5=always) with a range in score from 8 to 40 with higher scores indicating greater severity of depression. Each item on the measure is rated on a 5-point scale (1=never; 2=rarely; 3=sometimes; 4=often; and 5=always) with a range in score from 8 to 40 with higher scores indicating greater severity of anxiety.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Patient - Quality of Life Functional Assessment of Cancer Therapy - Head and Neck (FACT-H&amp;N)</measure>
    <time_frame>Over 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>A 39-item instrument that measures physical, social, emotional, and functional well-being, as well as additional head and neck-related concerns. Scoring scale is 0 = not at all to 4 = very much). Maximum score of 156. Higher scores indicate a better quality of life.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">90</enrollment>
  <condition>Head and Neck Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>CONNECT Intervention Group - Group A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>A web-based intervention (CONNECT) to empower and connect caregivers of newly diagnosed cancer patients to supportive care resources A randomized pilot study will be conducted to assess feasibility and acceptability and obtain data on caregiver and patient outcomes. CONNECT e-tool, re-education and optional referral (2 weeks post CONNECT e-tool). Baseline, one month post randomization data collection, three months post randomization data collection, quantitative and qualitative measures.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>CONNECT Comparison Group - Group B</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Baseline, one month post randomization data collection, three months post randomization data collection, quantitative and qualitative measures.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>CONNECT</intervention_name>
    <description>A novel web-based intervention with input from an advisory panel of cancer caregivers, oncology providers, and psychosocial oncology professionals empowering caregivers with needs to seek services by providing education about the benefits of supportive care resources, systematically identifying their unmet needs, and connecting them with tailored supportive care resources.</description>
    <arm_group_label>CONNECT Intervention Group - Group A</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>CONTROL</intervention_name>
    <description>This group will receive a generic resource list. The generic resource list will be printed for participants and emailed to them, if participants have an email address.</description>
    <arm_group_label>CONNECT Comparison Group - Group B</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Eligible caregivers include those who are:

          -  Caregivers must be providing some capacity of informal (unpaid) care for a patient
             meeting patient eligibility criteria. If a patient unexpectedly becomes deceased
             during the study period, caregivers will be allowed to continue participation in the
             assigned study arm and complete study assessments if they wish to.

          -  Greater than or equal to 18 years of age.

          -  Ability to access study materials by internet or complete study activities in person
             as institutional and government policies allow.

        Eligible patients include those who:

          -  Have new or recurrent American Joint Committee on Cancer (AJCC) stage I-IV head and
             neck cancer.

          -  Are receiving cancer treatment or awaiting planned treatment initiation, excluding
             those receiving neoadjuvant surgery or surgery only.

          -  Patients must be ambulatory and up more than 50% of waking hours, as measured by an
             ECOG Performance Status rating of level 0, 1, or 2.

          -  Greater than or equal to 18 years of age.

          -  Ability to access study materials by internet or complete study activities in person
             as institutional and government policies allow.

          -  Patients must be receiving some capacity of informal care from a caregiver meeting the
             above criteria. If the caregiver unexpectedly becomes deceased during the study
             period, the patient will be un-enrolled from this study as we are evaluating a
             caregiver-only delivered intervention.

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Caregivers will be excluded if:

        • Cannot read/communicate in English

        Patients will be excluded if they:

        • Cannot read/communicate in English

        Eligibility to participate in the study is conditional on participation of both the
        caregiver and patient.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Chandylen Nightingale, PhD, MPH</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Wake Forest University Health Sciences</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Chandylen Nightingale, PhD, MPH</last_name>
    <phone>336-713-5440</phone>
    <email>cnightin@wakehealth.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 4, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 12, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 15, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 1, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 1, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 7, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Head and Neck Cancer Caregivers</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Head and Neck Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

