<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03875430</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ARI-ME-18-01</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03875430</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study to Investigate the Effectiveness of a Food Supplement Made of Hop in the Improvement of Menopausal Symptoms</brief_title>
  <acronym>OLSEM</acronym>
  <official_title>Multicenter Prospective Observational Study to Investigate the Effectiveness of a Food Supplement Made of Hop in the Improvement of Menopausal Symptoms</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Aristo Pharma Iberia</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Analysis and Research Network, S.L</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Aristo Pharma Iberia</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This observational study will assess the effects of a dietary supplement based on Humulus
      Lupulus L. to relieve the symptoms of menopause in perimenopausal and postmenopausal women,
      by doing a follow up of the Cervantes scale and the Anxiety and depression Goldberg Scale in
      a period of 6 months. Participants will be allocated to dietary supplement being the
      difference between groups if they are perimenopausal or postmenopausal, and will attend to 3
      visits (baseline, 3 months and 6 months).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">April 15, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 30, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 30, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in quality of life (QoL) - Measured with Score on the Cervantes Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline, to 3 months and 6 months visit</time_frame>
    <description>Score on the Cervantes Scale on quality of life.
The scale is composed of 31 questions divided in 4 domains. Each question is punctuated from 0 to 5. And total scale result ranges from 0 to 155, where 0 corresponds to the maximun QoL value and 155 worst value.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in quality of life (QoL) - Measured with Score on the Cervantes Scale, domain: Menopause and Health.</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline, to 3 months and 6 months visit</time_frame>
    <description>This domain of the Cervantes Scale is composed of 15 items, punctuated from 0 to 5. This domain ranges from 0 to 75, where 0 corresponds to abscence of physical symptoms, and 75 to the maximum level of physical problems.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in quality of life (QoL) - Measured with Score on the Cervantes Scale, domain: Sexuality.</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline, to 3 months and 6 months visit</time_frame>
    <description>This domain of the Cervantes Scale is composed of 4 items, punctuated from 0 to 5. This domain ranges from 0 to 20, where 0 corresponds to abscence of sexual problems, and 20 to the maximum level of sexual problems.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in quality of life (QoL) - Measured with Score on the Cervantes Scale, domain: Psychic.</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline, to 3 months and 6 months visit</time_frame>
    <description>This domain of the Cervantes Scale is composed of 9 items, punctuated from 0 to 5. This domain ranges from 0 to 45, where 0 corresponds to abscence of anxiety and depression problems, and 45 to the maximum level of anxiety and depression problems.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in quality of life (QoL) - Measured with Score on the Cervantes Scale, domain: Couple relationship.</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline, to 3 months and 6 months visit</time_frame>
    <description>This domain of the Cervantes Scale is composed of 3 items, punctuated from 0 to 5. This domain ranges from 0 to 15, where 0 corresponds to abscence of relationship problems, and 15 to the maximum level of relationship problems.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Cervantes personality scale.</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured at Baseline visit</time_frame>
    <description>The scale is composed of 20 questions divided in 3 domains. Each question is punctuated from 0 to 5.
First domain is introversion, it is comprised of 7 Items. This domain is punctuated from 0 to 10, where 0 represents a more extroverted personality and 10 more introverted.
Second domain is emotional instability, it is comprised of 7 Items. This domain is punctuated from 0 to 35, where 0 represents more emotional stability and 35 more emotional instability.
Third domain is sincerity, it is comprised of 6 Items. This domain is punctuated from 0 to 30, where 0 represents less sincere and 30 more most sincere.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in anxiety and depression - Measured with Score on the Anxiety and Depression Goldberg Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline, to 3 months and 6 months visit</time_frame>
    <description>The scale is composed of 18 items. Each item is punctuated from 0 to 5. And total scale result ranges from 0 to 90, where 0 corresponds to depression unlikely and more than 54 to severe depression.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>Through the study, an average of 9 months.</time_frame>
    <description>Number of adverse events (recorded in the investigator's CRF) to assess the tolerability/safety of the product</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Compliance with treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Recount of product returned at the 3 months visit and at the 6 months visit of study.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Treatment satisfaction</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured at the 6 months visit</time_frame>
    <description>Treatment satisfaction is measured in three questions valued from 0 to 10, where 0 is considered worst and 10 better. The three questions are about:
Patient satisfaction with the capsules.
Patient satisfaction with the results of the treatment.
Investigator satisfaction with the results of the treatment.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">443</enrollment>
  <condition>Menopause</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Perimenopausal</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients in this group will take one capsule of a dietary supplement containing Humulus lupulus L.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Postmenopausal</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients in this group will take one capsule of a dietary supplement containing Humulus lupulus L.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Humulus lupulus L</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients with this intervention will receive a dietary supplement to relieve the symptoms of menopause</description>
    <arm_group_label>Perimenopausal</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Postmenopausal</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Women between 40 and 60 years old that attend ginecological consultation in Spain.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Perimenopausal according to the Stages of Reproductive Aging Workshop (STRAW) or
             postmenopausal women between the ages of 40 and 60.

          -  Having moderate or severe hot flushes.

          -  Accepting and signing the Informed consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Women unable to answer the questionnaires.

          -  Women being treated with sulfonamides, methotrexate, triamterene, sulfasalazine,
             estrogens, phenytoin, anxiolytics, antidepressants, daily multivitamins, hormonal
             therapy, use of oral contraceptives in the last 3 months, herbal products to reduce
             vasomotor symptoms in the last months.

          -  Women in treatment and control for psychiatric pathology.

          -  Women with any comorbidity that could be the cause of a symptomatology coinciding but
             not bound to peri or post-menopause.

          -  Women diagnosed or with Clinical suspicion of breast cancer, endometrium or other
             hormone-dependent tumors, genital tract bleeding, actives thromboembolic disorders,
             active gall bladder illness or being lactose intolerant.

          -  Women being treated with antithyroid medications and other drugs like letrozole,
             raloxifene, bazedoxifene, bethanechol, desmopressin and calcitonin or other drugs that
             at investigators judgement could interfere in the study's result.

          -  Use of dietary supplements that include phytoestrogens (drinks or desserts based in
             soya) in the last month.

          -  Women with coronary diseases, strokes or chronic renal diseases, type 2 diabetes, deep
             vein thrombosis or pulmonary embolism.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>40 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>60 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <verification_date>March 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 11, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 12, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 14, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 12, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 12, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 14, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

