<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03874858</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CAMN107AIT15</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2018-002898-21</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03874858</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study of Full Treatment-free Remission in Patients With Chronic Myeloid Leukemia Treated With Nilotinib</brief_title>
  <acronym>DANTE</acronym>
  <official_title>A Phase II, Single-arm, Multicenter Study of Full Treatment-free Remission in Patients With Chronic Myeloid Leukemia in Chronic Phase Treated With Nilotinib in First-line Therapy Who Have Achieved a Sustained, Deep Molecular Response for at Least 1 Year</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Novartis Pharmaceuticals</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Novartis</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a prospective, single arm, phase II study to assess the effect of nilotinib reduced
      to half the standard dose for 12 months on treatment-free remission in patients with Chronic
      Myeloid Leukemia - Chronic Phase (CML-CP) treated with first-line nilotinib who reached a
      sustained deep molecular response before entering the study.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of the present study is to evaluate the rate of full treatment-free molecular
      remission in a selected population of CML-CP patients treated with nilotinib at half the
      standard dose during a consolidation period of 12 months, followed by complete therapy
      cessation.

      The study is made up of 4 phases:

        -  Screening (week -4 - week 0)

        -  Nilotinib consolidation (week 0 - week 48)

        -  Nilotinib treatment-free remission (TFR) phase (week 48 - week 144)

        -  Follow up phase Patients fulfilling this protocol-specific definition of sustained deep
           molecular response (DMR) and all other inclusion/exclusion criteria will start the
           consolidation phase of the study.

      During Nilotinib consolidation (week 0 - week 48) period, patients will be treated with
      nilotinib 300 mg QD. At the end or during the consolidation period, patients will proceed as
      follows:

        -  Patients with sustained DMR at the end of the consolidation phase will enter the
           tretament-free remission (TFR) phase and nilotinib will be discontinued.

        -  Patients with loss of major molecular response (MMR) at any time during the
           consolidation phase will enter the follow-up phase and will return to the standard
           nilotinib administration regimen (nilotinib 300 mg BID) until the end of the trial (week
           144). Loss of MMR is defined as breakpoint cluster region--c-abl oncogene 1 (BCR-ABL)
           &gt;0.1% international scale assessed in a single blood sample and will mandate
           reinitiation of nilotinib treatment at 300 mg BID within 5 weeks after the collection of
           the blood sample demonstrating loss of MMR.

        -  Patients with more than MMR, but without meeting the definition of sustained DMR, will
           remain in the consolidation phase and will be treated with nilotinib 300 mg QD until the
           end of the trial (week 144).

      During the TFR phase, BCR-ABL levels will be monitored every month for the first year at
      weeks 52, 56, 60, 64, 68, 72, 76, 80, 84, 88, 92, 96 and then every three months until the
      end of the study at weeks 108, 120, 132 and 144 (end of study) or whenever clinically
      indicated at the discretion of the investigator. The primary objective will be evaluated at
      week 96. During the TFR phase, loss of MMR will cause reinitiation of nilotinib treatment at
      300 mg BID.

      Follow up phase for patients who were discontinued from the trial, starting from the date of
      trial discontinuation up to the end of the trial (144 week), and for patients with loss of
      MMR at any time during the study.

      Patients discontinued from the treatment for any reason will be followed for survival
      information every 3 months until week 144.

      All patients still on study treatment at the end of the study will be transitioned to
      prescription nilotinib.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">April 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 30, 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 31, 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of patients in full treatment-free remission 96 weeks after the start of the consolidation phase.</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline of consolidation phase up to 96 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Full Treatment-Free Remission (FTFR) is defined as patients with Major Molecular Response (MMR) or better, including those who have totally discontinued treatment during the Treatment-Free Remission (TFR) phase and those who are treated with half the standard dosage.
Percentage of patients in full treatment-free remission 96 weeks after the start of the consolidation phase is calculated by dividing the number of patients with no loss of MMR-Major Molecular Response (BCR-ABL ≤ 0.1% (IS) after 96 weeks by the number of patients who entered the consolidation phase.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of patients who remain in sustained Deep Molecular Response (DMR) at the end of the consolidation phase (week 48).</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline of consolidation phase up to 48 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The percentage of patients in sustained DMR at the end of the consolidation phase (week 48). Sustained DMR: ≥ MR 4.0 (BCR-ABL level ≤0.01% IS) in all of the last 4 BCR-ABL RQ-PCR assessments. The proportion of patients in sustained DMR at the end of the consolidation phase (week 48) is calculated by dividing the number of patients in sustained DMR at week 48 by the number of patients who entered the consolidation phase.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of patients who remain in DMR at the end of the consolidation phase (week 48), at 96 weeks and at 144 weeks after the start of the consolidation phase.</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline of consolidation phase, week 48, 96 and 144</time_frame>
    <description>The percentage of patients in deep molecular response is calculated by dividing the number of patients in DMR (≥ MR 4.0 (BCR-ABL level ≤0.01% IS in all of the last 4 BCR-ABL RQ-PCR assessments) 48, 96 and 144 weeks after the start of the consolidation phase by the number of patients who entered the consolidation phase.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of patients in full treatment-free remission 144 weeks after the start of the consolidation phase.</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline of consolidation phase, week 144</time_frame>
    <description>The percentage of patients in full treatment-free remission at week 144 is calculated by dividing the number of patients with no loss of MMR (BCR-ABL ≤ 0.1% (IS)) 144 weeks after the start of the consolidation phase by the number of patients who entered the consolidation phase.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of patients with MMR or better at 48, 96, 144 weeks after starting the consolidation phase</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline of consolidation phase, week 48, 96 and 144</time_frame>
    <description>The percentage of patients with MMR at week 48, 96 and 144 is calculated by dividing the number of patients with MMR at week 48, 96 and 144, regardless of whether they required re-initiation of treatment after the start the study, by the number of patients who entered the consolidation phase.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Polymerase Chain Reaction (PCR) of BCR-ABL transcript after re-start of nilotinib therapy in patients who failed Treatment Free Remission Phase.</measure>
    <time_frame>Restart of nilotinib therapy up to approximately 144 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Descriptive statistics of BCR-ABL levels (International scale), measured by quantitative Polymerase Chain Reaction (PCR), over time after re-start of nilotinib therapy up to 144 weeks in patient who failed Treatment Free Remission Phase.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Polymerase Chain Reaction (PCR) of BCR-ABL transcript after discontinuation of nilotinib therapy in Treatment Free Remission Phase.</measure>
    <time_frame>Discontinuation of nilotinib therapy in patients in TFR phase up to approximately 144 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Descriptive statistics of BCR-ABL levels (IS), measured by quantitative PCR, over time after discontinuation of nilotinib therapy in Treatment Free Remission Phase up to 144 weeks.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Polymerase Chain Reaction (PCR) of BCR-ABL transcript during the consolidation period.</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline of consolidation phase up to 48 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Descriptive statistics of BCR-ABL levels (IS), measured by quantitative PCR, over time during the consolidation period to 48 weeks.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Full Treatment-Free Survival (FTFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline of consolidation phase up to 144 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>FTFS: time from the start of the consolidation phase to the earliest occurrence of any of the following events: loss of MMR, reinitiation of treatment due to any cause, progression to accelerated phase (AP)/blast crisis (BC), or death due to any cause.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of patients among those who entered the TFR phase with no loss of MMR and no reinitiation of nilotinib after drug discontinuation</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline of consolidation up to 96 and 144 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of patients in TFR at weeks 96 and week 144 is calculated by dividing the number of patients with no loss of MMR and no reinitiation of nilotinib after drug discontinuation at weeks 96 and week 144 by the number of patients who entered the TFR phase.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Treatment-free survival (TFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>From the start of the TFR phase up to Week 144.</time_frame>
    <description>TFS: time from the start of the TFR phase to the earliest occurrence of any of the following events: loss of MMR, reinitiation of treatment due to any cause, progression to AP/BC or death due to any cause.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression-free survival (PFS) after the start of consolidation phase</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline of consolidation phase up to 144 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>PFS: time from the start of the consolidation phase to progression to AP/BC or death due to any cause, whichever occurs first.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression Free Survival (PFS) after the start of TFR phase</measure>
    <time_frame>From the start of the TFR phase up to week 144.</time_frame>
    <description>PFS: time from the start of the TFR phase to progression to AP/BC or death due to any cause, whichever occurs first.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall Survival (OS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline of consolidation phase up to 144 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>OS: time from start of the study to death due to any cause.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The number of patients with Adverse Events as measure of safety and tolerability</measure>
    <time_frame>From screening up to approximately week 144</time_frame>
    <description>To assess safety during the nilotinib treatment consolidation phase, TFR phase and during reinitiation of treatment with nilotinib.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Correlation between clinical and laboratory factors and clinical outcome</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline of consolidation phase up to 96 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Statistical correlation between clinical and laboratory correlates at diagnosis (e.g. Sokal Risk scale, demography, type of BCR-ABL transcript) or during previous treatment (e.g. Early Molecular Response=BCR-ABL transcript measured by quantitative PCR &lt;10% after 3 months of first-line treatment with nilotinib at the dose of 300 mg BID) and the achievement of Full Treatment Free Remission and Treatment Free Remission at 96 weeks</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">103</enrollment>
  <condition>Chronic Myeloid Leukemia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Nilotinib</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Oral 300 mg hard capsules taken once a day</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Nilotinib</intervention_name>
    <description>Nilotinib oral 300 mg QD hard capsules</description>
    <arm_group_label>Nilotinib</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>AMN107</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Male and female patients 18 years or older.

          2. Diagnosis of CML-CP according to the World Health Organization.

          3. Patients with CML-CP under first-line treatment with nilotinib at the approved daily
             dose of 300 mg BID mg for at least 3 calendar years. Note: At study entry, an ongoing
             treatment at a dose ≥400 mg per day is allowed.

          4. Sustained DMR defined as ≥ MR 4.0 (BCR-ABL level ≤0.01% IS) in all of the last 4
             BCR-ABL RQ-PCR assessments with a minimum interval between each assessment of 3 months
             and a maximum interval of 6 months.

          5. Patient must meet the following laboratory values at the screening visit:

               -  Absolute Neutrophil Count ≥1.0 x 109/L

               -  Platelets ≥75 x 109/L

               -  Hemoglobin (Hgb) ≥ 9 g/dL

               -  Serum creatinine &lt; 1.5 mg/dL

               -  Aspartate transaminase (AST) ≤ 3.0 x Upper Limit of Normal (ULN)

               -  Alanine transaminase (ALT) ≤ 3.0 x ULN

               -  Serum lipase ≤ 2 x ULN

          6. Patient has an Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status 0-2.

          7. Study subjects must be able to comply with study procedures and follow-up
             examinations.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients with known atypical transcript.

          2. CML treatment resistant mutation(s) (T315I, E255K/V, Y253H, F359C/V) detected if
             testing was done in the past (there is no requirement to perform mutation testing at
             study entry if it was not done in the past).

          3. Dose reductions/interruptions due to neutropenia or thrombocytopenia in the past 6
             months.

          4. Patient ever attempted to permanently discontinue nilotinib treatment.

          5. Known impaired cardiac function including any one of the following:

               -  Inability to determine QT interval on ECG

               -  Complete left bundle branch block

               -  Long QT syndrome or a known family history of long QT syndrome

               -  History of or presence of clinically significant ventricular or atrial
                  tachyarrhythmias

               -  Clinically significant resting bradycardia

               -  QTcF &gt; 480 msec

               -  History or clinical signs of myocardial infarction within 1 year prior to study
                  entry

               -  History of unstable angina within 1 year prior to study entry

               -  Other clinically significant heart disease (e.g. uncontrolled congestive heart
                  failure or uncontrolled hypertension)

          6. Severe and/or uncontrolled concurrent medical disease that in the opinion of the
             investigator could cause unacceptable safety risks or compromise compliance with the
             protocol.

          7. History of acute pancreatitis within 1 year prior to study entry or past medical
             history of chronic pancreatitis.

          8. Known presence of a significant congenital or acquired bleeding disorder unrelated to
             cancer.

          9. History of other active malignancy within 5 years prior to study entry except for
             previous or concomitant basal cell skin cancer, previous cervical carcinoma in situ
             treated curatively.

         10. Patients who have not recovered from prior surgery.

         11. Treatment with other investigational agents (defined as not used in accordance with
             the approved indication) within 4 weeks of Day 1.

         12. Impairment of gastrointestinal (GI) function or GI disease that may significantly
             alter the absorption of study drug (e.g. ulcerative disease, uncontrolled nausea,
             vomiting, diarrhea, malabsorption syndrome, small bowel resection, or gastric bypass
             surgery).

         13. Patients actively receiving therapy with strong CYP3A4 inhibitors and/or inducers, and
             the treatment cannot be either discontinued or switched to a different medication
             prior to study entry.

         14. Patients actively receiving therapy with herbal medicines that are strong CYP3A4
             inhibitors and/or inducers, and the treatment cannot be either discontinued or
             switched to a different medication prior to study entry. These herbal medicines may
             include Echinacea, (including E. purpurea, E. angustifolia and E. pallida), Piperine,
             Artemisinin, St. John's Wort, and Ginkgo.

         15. Pregnant or nursing (lactating) women.

         16. Women of childbearing potential, defined as all women physiologically capable of
             becoming pregnant, unless they are using highly effective methods of contraception
             during dosing and for at least 14 days after stopping medication. There is a limited
             amount of data on pregnancies in patients while attempting treatment-free remission
             (TFR). If pregnancy is planned during the TFR phase, the patient must be informed of a
             potential need to re-initiate treatment with nilotinib during pregnancy

        Highly effective contraception methods include:

          -  Total abstinence (when this is in line with the preferred and usual lifestyle of the
             subject. Periodic abstinence (e.g., calendar, ovulation, symptothermal, post-ovulation
             methods) and withdrawal are not acceptable methods of contraception.

          -  Female sterilization (have had surgical bilateral oophorectomy with or without
             hysterectomy), total hysterectomy, or tubal ligation at least six weeks before taking
             study treatment. In case of oophorectomy alone, only when the reproductive status of
             the woman has been confirmed by follow up hormone level assessment.

          -  Male sterilization (at least 6 months prior to screening). The vasectomized male
             partner should be the sole partner for that subject.

          -  Use of oral, injected or implanted hormonal methods of contraception or placement of
             an intrauterine device (IUD) or intrauterine system (IUS), or other forms of hormonal
             contraception that have comparable efficacy (failure rate &lt;1%), for example hormone
             vaginal ring or transdermal hormone contraception.

        In case of use of oral contraception, women should have been stable on the same pill for a
        minimum of 3 months before starting the study.

        Women are considered post-menopausal and not of childbearing potential if they have had 12
        months of natural (spontaneous) amenorrhea with an appropriate clinical profile (i.e. age
        appropriate, history of vasomotor symptoms) or have had surgical bilateral oophorectomy
        (with or without hysterectomy), total hysterectomy, or tubal ligation at least six weeks
        ago. In the case of oophorectomy alone, only when the reproductive status of the woman has
        been confirmed by follow up hormone level assessment is she considered not of childbearing
        potential.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Novartis Pharmaceuticals</last_name>
    <phone>+41613241111</phone>
    <email>novartis.email@novartis.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Novartis Pharmaceuticals</last_name>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bari</city>
        <state>BA</state>
        <zip>70124</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bologna</city>
        <state>BO</state>
        <zip>40138</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cagliari</city>
        <state>CA</state>
        <zip>09126</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Catania</city>
        <state>CT</state>
        <zip>95123</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Catanzaro</city>
        <state>CZ</state>
        <zip>88100</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Firenze</city>
        <state>FI</state>
        <zip>50134</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Genova</city>
        <state>GE</state>
        <zip>16132</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Milano</city>
        <state>MI</state>
        <zip>20122</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Milano</city>
        <state>MI</state>
        <zip>20162</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Palermo</city>
        <state>PA</state>
        <zip>90127</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Palermo</city>
        <state>PA</state>
        <zip>90146</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pescara</city>
        <state>PE</state>
        <zip>65124</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Perugia</city>
        <state>PG</state>
        <zip>06100</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ravenna</city>
        <state>RA</state>
        <zip>48100</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Roma</city>
        <state>RM</state>
        <zip>00144</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Roma</city>
        <state>RM</state>
        <zip>00161</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Roma</city>
        <state>RM</state>
        <zip>00168</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Salerno</city>
        <state>SA</state>
        <zip>84131</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Orbassano</city>
        <state>TO</state>
        <zip>10043</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Torino</city>
        <state>TO</state>
        <zip>10126</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Torino</city>
        <state>TO</state>
        <zip>10128</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Udine</city>
        <state>UD</state>
        <zip>33100</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Napoli</city>
        <zip>80131</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Napoli</city>
        <zip>80132</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Novara</city>
        <zip>28100</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Italy</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 5, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 12, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 14, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 8, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 8, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 11, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>CML</keyword>
  <keyword>CML-CP</keyword>
  <keyword>TFR</keyword>
  <keyword>nilotinib</keyword>
  <keyword>AMN107</keyword>
  <keyword>Tasigna</keyword>
  <keyword>DMR</keyword>
  <keyword>sustained deep molecular response</keyword>
  <keyword>full treatment-free remission</keyword>
  <keyword>TKI</keyword>
  <keyword>qPCR</keyword>
  <keyword>adult</keyword>
  <keyword>ddPCR</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Leukemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Myeloid</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Myelogenous, Chronic, BCR-ABL Positive</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Novartis is committed to sharing with qualified external researchers, access to patient-level data and supporting clinical documents from eligible studies. These requests are reviewed and approved by an independent review panel on the basis of scientific merit. All data provided is anonymized to respect the privacy of patients who have participated in the trial in line with applicable laws and regulations.
This trial data availability is according to the criteria and process described on www.clinicalstudydatarequest.com</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

