<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03874468</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>coronal femoral Bowing</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03874468</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Prevalence of Coronal Femoral Bowing in the Egyptian Arthritic Knee</brief_title>
  <official_title>Prevalence of Coronal Femoral Bowing in the Egyptian Arthritic Knee</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Kerolos Naiem Shehata Rofael</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Assiut University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To Detect the Prevalence Of Coronal Femoral Bowing in Egyptian arthritic knee. The
      restoration of normal coronal alignment of the lower extremity is very important to surgeons
      who perform reconstructive surgery of the knee, such as total knee arthroplasty (TKA). The
      importance of achieving normal coronal alignment of the lower extremity after TKA is widely
      recognized . TKAs with coronal malalignment tend to fail earlier than those with neutral
      alignment. 8 Coronal alignment is considered key to the function and longevity of a TKA.
      However, most studies do not consider femoral and tibial anatomical features such as coronal
      femoral bowing and the effects of these features and subsequent alignment on function after
      TKA are unclear investigators therefore determined the prevalence of coronal femoral bowing,
      femoral condylar orientation (mLDFA ) , and tibia plateau inclination (mMPTA ) in
      osteoarthritic Egyptian population
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Radiological methods :

      1) standing anteroposterior radiographs of the full-length lower limb with patients in the
      standing position. ( HKA Long Film Radiographs ).

      Measurements :

        1. mechanical hip-knee-ankle axis (HKA) angle: the angle formed by the mechanical axes of
           the femur and tibia

        2. anatomical hip-knee-ankle axis (HKA) angle: the angle formed by the anatomical axes of
           the femur and tibia

        3. For condylar orientation : the mechanical lateral distal femoral angle (mLDFA) was
           defined as an angle formed by the mechanical axis of the femur and the line connecting
           the distal ends of the medial and lateral femoral condyles of the femur.

        4. For tibia plateau inclination : the mechanical lateral proximal tibial angle (mLPTA) was
           defined as an angle formed by the mechanical axis of the tibia and the articular surface
           of the proximal tibia .

        5. Coronal femoral bowing Using the method of Yau et al. : the femoral diaphysis was
           divided into four equal parts, . Because Yau et al. didn't exactly describe the femoral
           diaphysis, we had defined the femoral diaphysis from the lower border of the lesser
           trochanter to upper border of the distal femoral segment which is defined by a square
           whose sides have the same length as the widest part of the femoral condyle so called
           rule of square (from the lowest level of the lesser trochanter to 5 cm above the lowest
           level of the lateral femoral condyle), and the midpoint of the endosteal intramedullary
           canal was depicted in each quarter. The angulation between midlines drawn in the
           proximal and distal quarters of the femoral diaphysis will be measured
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">May 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 1, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 1, 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Cross-Sectional</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To asses the Prevalence Of Coronal Femoral Bowing in Egyptian arthritic knee</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Coronal Femoral Bowing in Egyptian arthritic knee may be prevalent and its effect on TKR will be measured and reported</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">400</enrollment>
  <condition>Arthritis Knee</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>X-ray</intervention_name>
    <description>standing anteroposterior radiographs of the full-length lower limb with patients in the standing position. ( HKA Long Film Radiographs ).</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        any Egyptian patient who suffer from advanced osteoarthritis schedual for TKR at any age
        ,any sex
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        -Any advanced Osteoarthritic patient schedual for TKA

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  History of femoral or tibial fracture or osteotomy around the knee .

          -  Presence of a congenital anomaly in the femur or tibia .

          -  History of prior knee or hip arthroplasty .

          -  Diagnosis other than primary osteoarthritis (RA-inflmmatory arthritis..etc) .

          -  Position in radiographs preventing complete evaluation of radiographic variables .
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>20 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>110 Years</maximum_age>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>kerolos naiem shehata, resident</last_name>
    <phone>01202803982</phone>
    <email>kerolosnaiem@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kobayashi H, Akamatsu Y, Kumagai K, Kusayama Y, Aratake M, Saito T. Influence of coronal bowing on the lower alignment and the positioning of component in navigation and conventional total knee arthroplasty. Orthop Traumatol Surg Res. 2017 Apr;103(2):251-256. doi: 10.1016/j.otsr.2016.11.017. Epub 2017 Jan 11.</citation>
    <PMID>28087396</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nakano N, Matsumoto T, Hashimura M, Takayama K, Ishida K, Araki D, Matsushita T, Kuroda R, Kurosaka M. Coronal lower limb alignment in normal knees--A radiographic analysis of 797 normal knee subjects. Knee. 2016 Mar;23(2):209-13. doi: 10.1016/j.knee.2015.12.004. Epub 2016 Jan 7.</citation>
    <PMID>26775257</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 12, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 12, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 14, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 13, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 13, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 15, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Assiut University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Kerolos Naiem Shehata Rofael</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principle investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Arthritis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

