<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03871894</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ILBS-ICLC01</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03871894</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Indirect Calorimeter Based Study in Patients With Liver Cirrhosis</brief_title>
  <acronym>ICLC</acronym>
  <official_title>Metabolic and Clinical Effects of Enteral Nutrition Therapy: Measured Versus Estimated Energy and Substrate Requirements in Critically Ill Cirrhotics-A Randomized Controlled Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Institute of Liver and Biliary Sciences, India</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Institute of Liver and Biliary Sciences, India</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Part I- Observational study In the first part , investigator would investigate and compare
      the energy requirements and substrate utilization in healthy subjects and in patients with
      liver cirrhosis of various etiologies across the disease severity state viz compensated,
      stable decompensated, critically ill cirrhotics. The investigator would also enroll patients
      with chronic kidney disease, critically ill patients of acute liver failure or acute on
      chronic liver failure as disease controls.

      Part II- Randomized Controlled Study All the eligible, critically ill cirrhotic patients on
      mechanical ventilator support would be randomized to a control group (receiving the
      nutritional therapy as per the standard enteral nutritional practice in a critical care
      setting) or the intervention group (receiving enteral nutrition based on proposed measured
      requirements by Indirect calorimetry (IC) given till the patient is in ICU(Intensive care
      unit). The IC would be done thrice a week in both groups.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">May 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To study and compare the resting energy expenditure(REE) measured by Indirect Calorimetry between all the groups</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To study and compare the substrate utilization(Respiratory quotient- RQ) at fasting state measured by Indirect Calorimetry between all the groups.</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The effect of nutritional therapy as per standard versus measured protocol during ICU stay on duration of mechanical ventilation in critically ill ventilated patients with cirrhosis</measure>
    <time_frame>28 days</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The effect of nutritional therapy as per standard versus measured protocol during ICU (Intensive Care Unit) stay on mortality in critically ill ventilated patients with cirrhosis</measure>
    <time_frame>28 days</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The effect of nutritional therapy as per standard versus measured protocol during ICU stay on the changes non esterified fatty acid levels (NEFA) in critically ill ventilated patients with cirrhosis</measure>
    <time_frame>28 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The effect of nutritional therapy as per standard versus measured protocol during ICU stay on the levels of interleukin 6 (IL6) in critically ill ventilated patients with cirrhosis</measure>
    <time_frame>28 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The effect of nutritional therapy as per standard versus measured protocol during ICU stay on the Fraction of Inspired oxygen (FiO2) in critically ill ventilated patients with cirrhosis</measure>
    <time_frame>28 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The effect of nutritional therapy as per standard versus measured protocol during ICU stay on the incidence of new onset infection in critically ill ventilated patients with cirrhosis</measure>
    <time_frame>28 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The effect of nutritional therapy as per standard versus measured protocol during ICU stay on NUTRIC (The Nutrition Risk in Critically ill score) score range (0-9 ) in critically ill ventilated patients with cirrhosis.</measure>
    <time_frame>28 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Liver Cirrhoses</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>This is the group of critically ill cirrhotic patients on mechanical ventilator support who would receive the nutritional therapy as per the standard enteral nutritional practice in a critical care setting in cirrhotics till the period admitted in ICU(Intensive care unit) 35-40 Kcal/Kg IBW/day; 1.5-2g protein per kg per day.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>This is the group of critically ill cirrhotic patients on mechanical ventilator support who would receive the nutritional therapy based on indirect calorimetry measurements till the period admitted in ICU(Intensive care unit)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Indirect calorimetry based nutritional intervention till patient in ICU(Intensive care unit)</intervention_name>
    <description>Nutrition therapy based on indirect calorimetry (IC) measurements(measured resting energy expenditure and/or substrate utilization) and to be adjusted according to the variations shown by IC.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Standard and fixed nutritional intervention till patient in ICU</intervention_name>
    <description>Fixed standard nutritional therapy 40 Kcal/Kg IBW/day and 1.5 to 2 g protein /Kg IBW/Day throughout the period of ICU stay</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Disease groups:

        • Patients with liver cirrhosis (diagnosis established based on routine clinical,
        biochemical and at least radiological, endoscopic or histological parameters.) admitted in
        Liver coma Intensive care unit and those admitted in ward.

        Disease controls:

          -  Patients with Acute liver failure (diagnosis established based on routine clinical,
             biochemical and at least radiological parameters) admitted in Liver coma Intensive
             care unit

          -  Patients with severe acute pancreatitis (diagnosis established based on routine
             clinical, biochemical and at least radiological parameters) admitted in Liver coma
             Intensive care unit

        Healthy Controls:

          -  Healthy subjects- Relatives of patients with no known chronic diseases (Chronic
             obstructive pulmonary disease, Coronary artery disease, Type 2 diabetes, Hypertension,
             Hypothyroidism, Koch's disease) or not on any long term medications.

          -  Patients with liver cirrhosis (diagnosis established based on routine clinical,
             biochemical and at least radiological, endoscopic or histological parameters.)
             admitted in Liver coma Intensive care unit who require mechanical ventilation

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Age&lt;18 years

          -  Active upper gastrointestinal bleeding

          -  If there are conditions which precluded IC, such as an FiO2 &gt;60 %, failure to
             cooperate, agitation, seizure activity, spasticity, or positive end-expiratory
             pressure (PEEP) &gt;10 mmHg.

          -  Pregnant women

          -  Refused to consent/ inability to obtain informed consent.

          -  Known long standing diabetic

          -  If there is any evidence of medical/surgical instability

          -  Hepatocellular carcinoma Extrahepatic malignancies

          -  With persistent gastrointestinal dysfunction and ileus

          -  Patients who would be readmitted to the ICU

          -  Known long standing diabetic

          -  Terminally ill patients on high inotropic support

          -  Acute liver failure

          -  If there is any evidence of medical/surgical instability

          -  If patients are taking any portion of nutrition by mouth.

          -  Pregnant women

          -  Refused to consent/ inability to obtain informed consent.

          -  Patient on CRRT- continuous renal replacement therapy

          -  Severe co morbidities such as Chronic kidney disease requiring maintenance dialysis,
             COPD and Cardiac pathologies (Acute myocardial infarction, heart failure, ).

          -  Hepatocellular carcinoma Extrahepatic malignancies

          -  Moribund patient with likely survival &lt;24 hours

          -  Patients enrolled in other drug trials.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Jaya Joy Benjamin, Msc,PhD</last_name>
    <phone>011-46300000</phone>
    <email>jayabenjaminilbs@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>ILBS</name>
      <address>
        <city>New Delhi</city>
        <state>Delhi</state>
        <zip>110070</zip>
        <country>India</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Varsha Shasthry, MBBS,PDCC</last_name>
      <phone>011-46300000</phone>
      <email>varsha.bhat@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>India</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 26, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 9, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 12, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 9, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 9, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 12, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Indirect calorimeter</keyword>
  <keyword>Resting energy expenditure</keyword>
  <keyword>substrate utilization</keyword>
  <keyword>nitrogen balance</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Liver Cirrhosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fibrosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

