<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03870685</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>18-701</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03870685</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Surgical Site Infiltration of Exparel vs TAP Block With Exparel in Patients Undergoing Laparotomy Via Midline Incision</brief_title>
  <official_title>Surgical Site Infiltration of Liposomal Bupivacaine Versus Transversus Plane Block With Liposomal Bupivacaine in Patients With Suspected or Known Gynecologic Cancer Undergoing Laparotomy Via Midline Incision</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Danbury Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Danbury Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a randomized-controlled prospective study to be conducted at Danbury Hospital and
      Norwalk Hospital to compare postoperative opioid consumption and pain scores of patients with
      suspected or known gynecologic malignancies undergoing midline laparotomy who received TAP
      block with liposomal bupivacaine versus surgical site infiltration of liposomal bupivacaine.

      Primary outcome: Total postoperative opioid consumption as measured by morphine equivalents
      over 48 hour period.

      Secondary outcomes include: Pain scores (based on visual analog scale 1-10) at 2 hours, 6
      hours, 12 hours, 24 hours and 48 hours postoperatively at rest and upon exertion (Valsalva
      maneuver), Severity of nausea, Episodes of vomiting, Total antiemetics consumption over 48
      hour period.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Recent studies suggest surgical site infiltration of local anesthetic into the preperitoneal,
      subfascial and/or subcutaneous planes as an alternative approach. The literature suggests
      this offers superior pain relief and significantly reduced morphine consumption. This
      procedure has been shown to provide excellent analgesia in open inguinal hernia repair and
      colorectal procedures up to 72 hours after a single injection. However, there is limited
      published data comparing TAP block with liposomal bupivacaine and surgical site infiltration
      of liposomal bupivacaine in open hysterectomy patients.

      The investigators propose to prospectively study the efficacy of surgical site infiltration
      of liposomal bupivacaine versus TAP block with liposomal bupivacaine in patients with
      suspected or known gynecologic malignancies undergoing midline laparotomy. The investigators
      hypothesize that surgical site infiltration of liposomal bupivacaine is more effective than
      TAP block with liposomal bupivacaine in this patient population. The investigators primary
      outcome will be postoperative total 48 hour opioid consumption.

      Secondary outcomes will include visual analog scale (VAS) pain scores at rest and upon
      exertion (Valsalva maneuver) at 2 hours, 6 hours, 12 hours, 24 hours and 48 hours
      postoperatively, severity of nausea, episodes of vomiting and total antiemetics consumption
      postoperatively. Pain scores and severity of nausea scores will be collected in person or
      over the phone.

      The investigators expect the results of this study to demonstrate that surgical site
      infiltration of liposomal bupivacaine in patients with suspected or known gynecologic
      malignancies undergoing midline laparotomy may help shorten the recovery period and reduce
      the need for postoperative opioid medications. Furthermore, generally patients undergoing
      procedures such as tumor debulking and lymph node dissection would have an extended
      hospitalization. If surgical site infiltration of liposomal bupivacaine administration is
      found to decrease the length of hospitalization (versus TAP Block with liposomal
      bupivacaine), it will significantly decrease the health care costs.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 5, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 5, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 5, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Patients randomized to TAP block with liposomal bupivacaine OR surgical site infiltration of liposomal bupivacaine for postoperative analgesia after undergoing midline laparotomy</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Total postoperative opioid consumption over 48 hours</measure>
    <time_frame>over 48 hour period after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Total postoperative opioid consumption as measured by morphine milligram equivalents (MME)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pain scores at rest and upon exertion</measure>
    <time_frame>2 hours, 6 hours, 12 hours, 24 hours and 48 hours postoperatively</time_frame>
    <description>Pain scores based on Wong-baker FACES Pain Rating Scale (Visual analog scale (VAS)) at rest and upon exertion (Valsalva maneuver) will be collected in person or over the phone. 0 - no hurt, 2 - hurts little bit, 4 - hurts little more, 6 - hurts even more, 8 - hurts whole lot, 10 - hurts worst.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Severity of nausea</measure>
    <time_frame>2, 6, 12, 24, &amp; 48 hours postoperatively</time_frame>
    <description>Severity of nausea will be collected in person or over the phone. Severity of Nausea Scale:- 0 = none, 1 = mild, 2 = moderate, 3 = severe</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Episodes of vomiting</measure>
    <time_frame>48 hours postoperatively</time_frame>
    <description>Total number of vomiting episodes will be collected from medical record.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Total antiemetics consumption</measure>
    <time_frame>48 hour postoperatively</time_frame>
    <description>Total antiemetics consumption (type of antiemetic, mode of administration, dose, time of administration) will be collected from medical record.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Postoperative Pain</condition>
  <condition>Postoperative Nausea and Vomiting</condition>
  <condition>Opioid Use</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>TAP block with Exparel</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients will receive immediate postoperative bilateral 2-quadrant TAP block with Exparel (liposomal bupivacaine) admixed with bupivacaine HCl and saline by the anesthesia team.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Surgical Site Infiltration of Exparel</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients will receive surgical site infiltration of Exparel (liposomal bupivacaine) admixed with bupivacaine HCl and saline by surgeon.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>TAP Block</intervention_name>
    <description>Transversus Plane block</description>
    <arm_group_label>TAP block with Exparel</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Surgical Site Infiltration</intervention_name>
    <description>Surgical Site Infiltration</description>
    <arm_group_label>Surgical Site Infiltration of Exparel</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Exparel</intervention_name>
    <description>liposomal bupivacaine</description>
    <arm_group_label>Surgical Site Infiltration of Exparel</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>TAP block with Exparel</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Any woman age 18 or over with known or suspected gynecologic malignancy who is
             scheduled for laparotomy via vertical midline incision at Danbury Hospital or Norwalk
             Hospital

          -  American Society of Anesthesiologists physical status I to IV (a normal healthy
             patient to a patient with severe systemic disease that may be constant threat to life)

          -  English or Spanish speaking

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Pregnancy

          -  Unable to obtain consent

          -  Severe allergies and/or anaphylaxis to bupivacaine or other anesthetics of the same
             class, to hydromorphone or morphine equivalents

          -  Patients taking fospropofol, hyaluronidase, propofol, propranolol, St John's Wort and
             verapamil at the time of screening

          -  Significant psychiatric disturbance as recorded in the medical record

          -  Current or history of alcohol or drug addiction

          -  Have current acute or chronic pain disorders as indicated in medical record

          -  Current or history of opioid dependence

          -  Contraindications to acetaminophen (significant hepatic dysfunction or disease),
             ketorolac and ibuprofen (significant renal dysfunction or reactive airway disease)

          -  ≥2 previous midline laparotomies

          -  BMI &gt;45
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <gender_based>Yes</gender_based>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Linus Chuang, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Danbury Hospital, Nuvance Health</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Joann Petrini, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>203-739-6882</phone>
    <email>Joann.petrini@wchn.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Rakhee Agarwal, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>203-739-4932</phone>
    <email>Rakhee.agarwal@wchn.org</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Danbury Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Danbury</city>
        <state>Connecticut</state>
        <zip>06810</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Joann Petrini, PhD, MPH</last_name>
      <phone>203-739-6882</phone>
      <email>joann.petrini@wchn.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Vaagn Andikyan, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Atim A, Bilgin F, Kilickaya O, Purtuloglu T, Alanbay I, Orhan ME, Kurt E. The efficacy of ultrasound-guided transversus abdominis plane block in patients undergoing hysterectomy. Anaesth Intensive Care. 2011 Jul;39(4):630-4.</citation>
    <PMID>21823381</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Carney J, McDonnell JG, Ochana A, Bhinder R, Laffey JG. The transversus abdominis plane block provides effective postoperative analgesia in patients undergoing total abdominal hysterectomy. Anesth Analg. 2008 Dec;107(6):2056-60. doi: 10.1213/ane.0b013e3181871313.</citation>
    <PMID>19020158</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Abdallah FW, Halpern SH, Margarido CB. Transversus abdominis plane block for postoperative analgesia after Caesarean delivery performed under spinal anaesthesia? A systematic review and meta-analysis. Br J Anaesth. 2012 Nov;109(5):679-87. doi: 10.1093/bja/aes279. Epub 2012 Aug 19. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22907337</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Brogi E, Kazan R, Cyr S, Giunta F, Hemmerling TM. Transversus abdominal plane block for postoperative analgesia: a systematic review and meta-analysis of randomized-controlled trials. Can J Anaesth. 2016 Oct;63(10):1184-96. doi: 10.1007/s12630-016-0679-x. Epub 2016 Jun 15. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>27307177</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Joshi GP, Rawal N, Kehlet H; PROSPECT collaboration, Bonnet F, Camu F, Fischer HB, Neugebauer EA, Schug SA, Simanski CJ. Evidence-based management of postoperative pain in adults undergoing open inguinal hernia surgery. Br J Surg. 2012 Feb;99(2):168-85. doi: 10.1002/bjs.7660. Epub 2011 Sep 16. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21928388</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>McDonnell JG, O'Donnell B, Curley G, Heffernan A, Power C, Laffey JG. The analgesic efficacy of transversus abdominis plane block after abdominal surgery: a prospective randomized controlled trial. Anesth Analg. 2007 Jan;104(1):193-7. Erratum in: Anesth Analg. 2007 May;104(5):1108.</citation>
    <PMID>17179269</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chahar P, Cummings KC 3rd. Liposomal bupivacaine: a review of a new bupivacaine formulation. J Pain Res. 2012;5:257-64. doi: 10.2147/JPR.S27894. Epub 2012 Aug 14.</citation>
    <PMID>23049275</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hotta K, Inoue S, Taira K, Sata N, Tamai K, Takeuchi M. Comparison of the analgesic effect between continuous wound infiltration and single-injection transversus abdominis plane block after gynecologic laparotomy. J Anesth. 2016 Feb;30(1):31-8. doi: 10.1007/s00540-015-2083-z. Epub 2015 Oct 14.</citation>
    <PMID>26467038</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gasanova I, Alexander J, Ogunnaike B, Hamid C, Rogers D, Minhajuddin A, Joshi GP. Transversus Abdominis Plane Block Versus Surgical Site Infiltration for Pain Management After Open Total Abdominal Hysterectomy. Anesth Analg. 2015 Nov;121(5):1383-8. doi: 10.1213/ANE.0000000000000909.</citation>
    <PMID>26252171</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 8, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 11, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 12, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 3, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 3, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 5, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Danbury Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Linus Chuang</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Network Chairman OB/GYN</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Vomiting</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Postoperative Nausea and Vomiting</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

