<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03874754</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>J1886</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>P30NR018093-01</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>IRB00175781</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03874754</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Tailored Home-Based Exercise Program for Multiple Chronic Conditions</brief_title>
  <acronym>iHBE</acronym>
  <official_title>Assessment of a Tailored Home-Based Exercise Program on Symptoms, Well-Being, and Resilience Among Cancer Survivors With Multiple Chronic Conditions</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Sidney Kimmel Comprehensive Cancer Center at Johns Hopkins</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Nursing Research (NINR)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Sidney Kimmel Comprehensive Cancer Center at Johns Hopkins</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      A home-based, tailored, technology-enhanced home-based exercise program (iHBE) using a
      combination of the integrated mobile technologies (wearable device and phone application) and
      tailored home-based exercise will be pilot tested. Participants will choose one of the four
      home-based exercise options [National Institute of Aging (NIA) Go4Life (an exercise and
      physical activity campaign from the NIA), Iyengar-style yoga, walking, and modified Otago
      exercise] based on participants' preference and goals. The integrated mobile technologies
      system will allow the investigators to extract heart rate data directly from the wearable
      device to the research server. This data will be used to provide appropriate and personalized
      feedback on physical performance. The survey and notification to the participants on the
      smartphone.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The benefits of physical activity on managing chronic illnesses and multiple symptoms are
      well established. However, increasing the physical activity of persons living with Multiple
      Chronic Conditions (MCC), especially low -income cancer survivors with MCC, is challenging.
      Home-based exercise improves physical activity and symptoms among persons with the single
      chronic disease. One major challenge of the home-based exercise is the motivation and
      adherence. The mobile technologies (e.g., wearable device and smartphone application) have
      been used to improve motivation and monitor a person physical activity. Guided by the society
      to cells framework and previous preliminary findings, the investigators developed a
      technology-enhanced home-based exercise program using a combination of the integrated mobile
      technologies (wearable device and phone application) and tailored home-based exercise.
      Participants will choose one of the four home-based exercise options [National Institute of
      Aging (NIA) Go4Life, Iyengar-style yoga, walking, and modified Otago exercise] based on
      participants' preference and goals. The integrated mobile technologies system will allow the
      investigators to extract heart rate data directly from the wearable device to the research
      server. This data will be used to provide appropriate and personalized feedback on physical
      performance and trigger algorithms to send the survey and notification to the participants in
      real time. This pilot project will examine the feasibility of this technology-enhanced home
      exercise tailored to participants' goals and preferences. The intervention will leverage the
      cancer survivorship phase (post-treatment) to motivate self-care by combining tailored
      existing evidence-based physical activity programs and mobile technology for participants to
      engage in the resilience-enhancing physical activity. Identification of BDNF's role as one of
      the exercise outcomes provide a novel target for an intervention and increase the
      investigators' understanding of the underlying mechanism of symptoms and resilience. This
      study aims to examine the feasibility and acceptability of the iHBE program among low-income
      cancer survivors living with co-morbid conditions. Eight participants who have completed
      treatment for a solid tumor cancer with at least one comorbidity (e.g., diabetes and/or
      hypertension) will be assigned to an open-label trial of the idea. The investigators will
      gather feedback on goal setting, problem-solving strategies, exercise choices, and tracking
      mechanisms, program feasibility, and acceptability and modify the intervention as needed.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">August 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 31, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 31, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>The data collectors are blinded to the group allocation</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Fatigue as assessed by self-reported fatigue questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre- and post-intervention, up to 4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>6-items; self-reported fatigue (frequency, duration, intensity) and the impact on physical, mental, and social activities, has five response options (1 or never to 5 or always). The overall score range from 6 (no fatigue) to 30 (extreme fatigue)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Resilience as assessed by Connor-Davidson Resilience scale</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre- and post-intervention, up to 4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Connor-Davidson Resilience scale: 10 item self-report rating scale 0 (not true at all) to 4 (true nearly all the time). The overall score range from 0 (no resilience) to 40 (High Resilience).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Physical well being</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre- and post-intervention, up to 4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Physical well being as assessed by 36 item self-report instrument. The overall score derived from the physical functioning, role limitation-physical, and bodily pain domains. The overall score range from 0-400, with a score 400 reflecting the highest rating of physical health.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Mental well being</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre- and post-intervention, up to 4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Mental well being is measured by the 36 item self-report instrument. The overall score derived from the mental health, role limitation-emotional domains. The total score range from 0 to 200, with the score of 200 indicated high mental well being</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Physical activity</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The physical activity will be measured in a form of average step count/day and average active minutes/day measured by a wrist-worn wearable device.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Brain Derived Neurotrophic Factor level (in serum)</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre- and post-intervention, up to 4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The level of Brain Derived Neurotrophic Factor in serum measured by ELISA. The level will be measured in nanograms/milliliter.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Brain Derived Neurotrophic Factor level (in sweat)</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre- and post-intervention, up to 4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Brain Derived Neurotrophic Factor level in sweat collected through the sweat pad. The level will be measured in nanograms/milliliter.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">58</enrollment>
  <condition>Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Hypertension</condition>
  <condition>Diabetes</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>The iHBE program group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>an intervention group</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Usual Care (Control group)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>A control group</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Tailored Technology-Enhance Home-based exercise program (iHBE)</intervention_name>
    <description>The tailored technology enhanced home-based exercise (iHBE) program is a 4-week program with 1 assessment home visit session, 4 home visits during exercise. The detail activities are presented in table 1. The technologies, a wearable device, and a smartphone application, will be used as a tool to monitor physical performance (heart rate [HR], step count), provide immediate feedback, send daily reminding message through Mobile Ecological Momentary Assessment (mEMA). The coded raw data without personal identification information from the wearable device will be sent to the servers where the investigators can store it in the database alongside the mEMA data and create custom reports showing Heart Rate (HR) 30 minute before each Ecological Momentary Assessment (EMA) survey, showing HR and previous self-report responses before/ after each automatically triggered EMA.</description>
    <arm_group_label>The iHBE program group</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>iHBE</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  participants diagnosed with solid tumor cancer who have completed cancer treatment at
             least 6 months;

          -  diagnosed with diabetes and/or hypertension for at least a year;

          -  aged 21 years or older,

          -  have an annual household incomes of below $30,000 for families of three,

          -  the average fatigue level within the past 7 days at the level of 3 or more on the 0
             (no fatigue) to 10 (worse fatigue) Likert scale

          -  give informed consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  currently undergoing treatment for cancer;

          -  have an active infection (e.g., fever, localized redness, swelling, sinus congestion);

          -  diagnosed with a psychological disorder (e.g., suicidal or homicidal tendencies,
             extreme anxiety or depression)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>21 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Nada Lukkahatai, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Johns Hopkins School of Nursing</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Nada Lukkahatai, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>410-614-5297</phone>
    <email>nada.lukkahatai@jhu.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The Sidney Kimmel Comprehensive Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21205</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Nada Lukkahatai, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>240-750-9867</phone>
      <email>nada.lukkahatai@jhu.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 12, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 12, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 14, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 2, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 2, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">December 4, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Multiple chronic conditions</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Multiple Chronic Conditions</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>The individual participant data (IPD) will not be shared with other researchers</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

