<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03874312</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>371-072017</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03874312</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Ultrasound-assessed Internal Jugular Vein Distensibility in Advanced Chronic Heart Failure (US-IJVD in CHF)</brief_title>
  <acronym>US-IJVD-CHF</acronym>
  <official_title>Ultrasound-assessed Internal Jugular Vein Distensibility to Predict Right Atrial Pressure and Other Hemodynamic Parameters in Patients With Advanced Chronic Heart Failure</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Niguarda Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Niguarda Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Prospective validation of the ultrasound-assessed internal jugular vein distensibility (JVD)
      ratio to identify patients with systolic chronic heart failure and right atrial pressure
      (RAP) of 7 or less mmHg measured by the right heart catheterization. In a calibration cohort,
      a threshold ratio will be identified, above which the RAP is normal with the highest
      accuracy. This diagnostic tool with a defined threshold of the JVD ratio will be assessed in
      a second prospective validation cohort.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Peripheral congestion is caused by an excess of fluid in tissues and vessels. Fluid overload
      is associated with poor outcome in heart failure (HF)(1). Several clinical signs can suggest
      peripheral congestion, such as peripheral edema or neck vein distention. In particular, the
      clinical sign of the neck jugular vein distention is used to estimate right atrial pressure
      (RHC) and is associated with fluid overload and congestion. Nevertheless, clinical assessment
      is somewhat subjective depending on the anatomy of the patient's neck and on the expertise of
      the physician (2). It has been reported that the detection of elevated RAP can be measured
      using a bedside ultrasound (US)(3). In this study, the Authors compared the jugular vein
      distensibility (IVD) ratio assessed with US with the invasive measure of the RAP reporting a
      good accuracy in detecting normal RAP. They showed a good performance of this diagnostic
      test, nevertheless, they evaluated this diagnostic test in a mix population including only 27
      patients with congestive HF. More recent studies showed the prognostic value of the IVD ratio
      in patients with HF (4). Nevertheless, a specific threshold of the internal JVD ratio to
      identify patients with normal RAP in the setting of patients with systolic chronic HF (CHF)
      has never been described. Furthermore, in patients with CHF clinical signs of congestion
      cannot always be evident at clinical examination, making the decision to modify diuretic
      dosage or to introduce vasodilator drugs uneasy. Thus, a convenient, accurate, and
      reproducible non-invasive tool to identify patients with normal RAP (normal mean RAP is 7 or
      less mmHg) patients with systolic CHF would be desirable to tailor therapy, in particular in
      outpatient clinics.

      The main hypothesis of this study is that US-assessment of the internal JVD could be an
      accurate diagnostic tool to identify patients with normal RAP in this challenging set of
      patients.

      The primary aim of the study prospectively validates an US-assessed internal JVD ratio to
      identify patients with systolic CHF and RAP of 7 or less mmHg measured by RHC. In a
      calibration cohort, a threshold of the JVD ratio above which the RAP is normal with the
      highest accuracy will be identified and then this diagnostic tool with a defined JVD ratio
      will be validated in a second prospective validation cohort.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 18, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 31, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Identification of patients with normal RAP (=&lt;7 mmHg) with US-IJVD based on the JVD ratio obtained from the calibration cohort.</measure>
    <time_frame>From July 2017 to June 2019</time_frame>
    <description>Positive predictive value (PPV) of the JVD ratio to identify patients with normal (RAP=&lt;7 mmHg) measured by RHC in the validation group. In particular a higher JVD ratio indicated lower RAP.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical major cardiac events among patients included in the calibration group divided on the basis of the JVD ratio</measure>
    <time_frame>From July 2017 to June 2019</time_frame>
    <description>Clinical events include cardiac death, unknown death, cardiac hospitalization, urgent heart transplant, left ventricular assist device implantation. In particular it is expected that patients with JVD ratio above the identified threshold in the calibration group have a better outcome.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Relationship between JVD ratio and other hemodynamic parameters obtained by RHC</measure>
    <time_frame>From July 2017 to June 2019</time_frame>
    <description>The hemodynamic parameters will include pulmonary artery pressures and pulmonary capillary wedge pressure</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">200</enrollment>
  <condition>Systolic Chronic Heart Failure</condition>
  <condition>Congestion, Venous</condition>
  <condition>Advanced Heart Failure</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Calibration group</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients with systolic chronic heart failure who undergo right heart catheterization (RHC) for heart transplant/left ventricular assist device workup.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Validation group</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients with systolic chronic heart failure who undergo RHC for heart transplant/left ventricular assist device workup.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Linear ultrasound (US) assessment of the internal jugular vein</intervention_name>
    <description>Evaluation of jugular vein distensibility at rest and after Valsalva maneuver by US at the time of the RHC. US-guided IJV is routinely performed at the time of vein cannulation.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Calibration group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Validation group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients with systolic chronic heart failure defined by a left ventricular ejection
        fraction (LVEF) &lt;50% on echocardiogram that, undergo elective RHC in the heart
        transplant/left ventricular assist device work-up.

        All procedure, RHC, ultrasound assessment of the IJV, echocardiogram, laboratory test exams
        are routine exams in the heart transplant/left ventricular assist device work-up or in the
        staging of patients with advanced HF. No adjunctive procedures have been performed for this
        specific study.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  All patients with systolic chronic heart failure defined by a left ventricular
             ejection fraction (LVEF) &lt;50% on echocardiogram that, undergo elective RHC in the
             heart transplant/left ventricular assist device work-up.

          -  In case of occlusion of the left internal jugular vein (IJV), the RHC is performed
             from to contralateral IJV, and US-assessed JVD ratio will be measured on the right
             IJV.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients supported by a left ventricular assist device.

          -  Patients with acute heart failure that undergo RHC as an urgent procedure in
             hemodynamically unstable patients.

          -  Patients unable/unwilling to sign a written informed consent.

          -  Patients in which an RHC is not feasible from an internal jugular vein.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Enrico Ammirati, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Niguarda Hospital, Milano, Italy</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Fabrizio Oliva, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Niguarda Hospital, Milano, Italy</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Davide Marchetti, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Università Statale di Milano, Italy</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Andrea Garascia, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Niguarda Hospital, Milano, italy</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Giada Colombo</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Università Statale di Milano, Italy</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Loredana Lupica, MD</last_name>
    <phone>00390264444688</phone>
    <email>loredana.lupica@ospedaleniguarda.it</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Enrico Ammirati, MD</last_name>
    <phone>00390264447791</phone>
    <email>enrico.ammirati@ospdalenigua.it</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>De Gasperis Cardio Center, Niguarda Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Milano</city>
        <state>Lombardy</state>
        <zip>20162</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Enrico Ammirati, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>00390264447791</phone>
      <email>enrico.ammirati@ospedaleniguarda.it</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Fabrizio Oliva, MD</last_name>
      <phone>00390264447791</phone>
      <email>fabrizio.oliva@ospedaleniguarda.it</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Italy</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Caldentey G, Khairy P, Roy D, Leduc H, Talajic M, Racine N, White M, O'Meara E, Guertin MC, Rouleau JL, Ducharme A. Prognostic value of the physical examination in patients with heart failure and atrial fibrillation: insights from the AF-CHF trial (atrial fibrillation and chronic heart failure). JACC Heart Fail. 2014 Feb;2(1):15-23. doi: 10.1016/j.jchf.2013.10.004. Epub 2014 Jan 8.</citation>
    <PMID>24622114</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>McGee SR. Physical examination of venous pressure: a critical review. Am Heart J. 1998 Jul;136(1):10-8. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>9665212</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Simon MA, Kliner DE, Girod JP, Moguillansky D, Villanueva FS, Pacella JJ. Detection of elevated right atrial pressure using a simple bedside ultrasound measure. Am Heart J. 2010 Mar;159(3):421-7. doi: 10.1016/j.ahj.2010.01.004.</citation>
    <PMID>20211304</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pellicori P, Kallvikbacka-Bennett A, Dierckx R, Zhang J, Putzu P, Cuthbert J, Boyalla V, Shoaib A, Clark AL, Cleland JG. Prognostic significance of ultrasound-assessed jugular vein distensibility in heart failure. Heart. 2015 Jul;101(14):1149-58. doi: 10.1136/heartjnl-2015-307558. Epub 2015 May 25.</citation>
    <PMID>26006717</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 12, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 12, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 14, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 13, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 13, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 15, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>right heart catheterization</keyword>
  <keyword>Peripheral congestion</keyword>
  <keyword>Right atrial pressure</keyword>
  <keyword>Internal jugular vein distention ratio</keyword>
  <keyword>ultrasound of jugular vein</keyword>
  <keyword>chronic heart failure</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Heart Failure</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hyperemia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>The informed consent does not include to make public the individual participant data</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

